<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Thu" Date="2" Month="Jul" Year="1959" Vol="176" No="4" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 2 Iúil 1959" DateEnglish="Thursday, 2 July 1959" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="469" />Do chuaigh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 10,30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="The Taoiseach Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take business on the Order Paper in the following order: Nos. 1, 9 (Votes 49 to 56) and No. 8.  If not already reached, it is proposed to interrupt business at 1.30 p.m. to take No. 8 and, when completed, to resume the order. Questions will be taken at 3 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee of" RHead="Selection">
    <Title>Committee of Selection.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonnchadhOBriain" hpid="Rúnaí Parlaiminte an Taoisigh (Donnchadh Ó Briain) Rúnaí Parlaiminte an Taoisigh (Donnchadh Ó Briain)">
      <NameTxt>Rúnaí Parlaiminte an Taoisigh (Donnchadh Ó Briain)</NameTxt>
      <P>Tairgim:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Go scaoilfear an Teachta Pádraig Ó hIrighile ón gCoiste Roghnóireachta agus go gceapfar an Teachta Seán Ó Dochartaigh ina ionad.</P>
      <P>That Deputy Patrick J. Hillery be discharged from the Committee of Selection and that Deputy Seán Doherty be appointed in substitution for him.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Estimates for Public" RHead="Services, 1959-60">
    <Title>Estimates for Public Services, 1959-60.</Title>
    <P>The Dáil, according to order, went into Committee on Finance and resumed consideration of Estimates for Public Services for the year ending 31st March, 1960.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Vote" RHead="49&mdash;Agriculture (Resumed)">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Vote 49&mdash;Agriculture (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;That the Estimate be referred back for reconsideration&rdquo;.</P>
    <Col N="470" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Smith) Patrick Smith">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Smith)</NameTxt>
      <P>I never like to start at this early hour&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>Nobody does.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;but I suppose it cannot be helped.  Last night I was dealing with land reclamation and, while I did not complete the observations I had hoped to make, I do not propose to return to it now.  A few other points arose in the course of the discussion that are, in some way, associated with that subject.  As I said at the outset, I do not like the sort of childishness resorted to in this House of laying claim to what a particular Minister did or did not do.  One of my predecessors spoke on the subjects of lime, fertilisers, grassland and grassland improvement and the attitude to those subjects over the years.  After all, the use of lime is not anything new in this country.  Our great grandfathers used lime, and on the hillsides in the county in which I was born and reared one can see traces of the old means by which they burned lime in those days.</P>
      <P>That went on, as I say, all down the years and indeed in 1934, a very short time after we came into office, the first subsidy on lime was introduced by one of my predecessors and it was continued up to 1950.  I was amazed to hear some of the claims made by Deputy Dillon on this whole matter of his contribution to the production of ground limestone.  The strange thing about it is that any evidence that I could find went to show that Deputy Dillon was very reluctant to devote the moneys made available at the time, to ground limestone.  He had other ideas&mdash;maybe ideas with which I would not disagree myself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I mention that merely to show that so far as this Party and this Government are concerned, we have, in fact, been paying this subsidy on lime from 1934 to 1950 and we introduced a subsidy on superphosphates in 1938 and continued and increased it in the early years of the war until the raw material was no longer easily available.  I refer to those matters briefly to show that when a claim is made or an allegation advanced that there has been a change of policy so far as the Government are concerned, there is no justification <Col N="471" /> whatever for that claim or that charge. After all, with whatever arable land we have in the country, 10,000,000 11,000,000 or 12,000,000 acres, even during the war years we never succeeded in reaching a stage when we could induce our farmers one way or the other to till 25 per cent. of the land to produce wheat as well as feeding stuffs for animals.  If, during the war years, we could not succeed to that extent, surely in time of peace we could not hope to do better.</P>
    <P>What, then, are we going to do&mdash; whatever Party is in office, whatever Government are in office or whatever Minister is in charge of Agriculture&mdash; with the other 75 per cent. of the land of the country except use it for grazing and the production of animal feeding stuffs, be it hay, silage, or anything else?  Naturally, the more profitable that occupation becomes, the more one is inclined to devote attention and energy to it and to expend on it whatever moneys or resources can be made available for the improvement of our grasslands.  It is nonsense then to say that there has been a change of attitude or a change of policy.  Away back, pre-war, as a result of Government subsidy I was able to purchase ground phosphate and have it delivered at my place at £2 9s. per ton.  That was a low price, perhaps, but it must be remembered that money was scarce at that time and it was just as difficult, if not more difficult, to come by £2 10s. as it is to find ten guineas or £11, or whatever the price of phosphate is now.</P>
    <P>References were made to the possibility of a scheme being introduced for the disposal of this year's barley crop.  Discussions have been taking place with all the interests concerned, with the officials of my Department and myself, for many months past on this matter.  A scheme will be announced shortly.  I do not want to refer to it in detail now except to say to those who have shown some interest in this matter that there are three important factors that I shall try to safeguard and there are three important interests I shall try to protect.</P>
    <P>First, a Government guarantee has <Col N="472" /> been given to the people who grow barley.  It is naturally the responsibility of the Government to see that that guarantee is honoured to the extent that marketable barley will be produced by the growers.  If that is secured, then the growers will have no cause, I hope, for complaint.  Secondly, the scheme will provide that foodstuffs will be available to those who feed animals, livestock of all kinds and poultry, at the cheapest possible rate. That is a very desirable objective and one which, I am sure, will be accepted by everybody.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FlorenceWycherley" hpid="Mr. Wycherley Mr. Wycherley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wycherley</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very desirable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>The third factor is one about which I have shown concern and it is also one I shall endeavour to safeguard.  I agree with the growing of barley here.  I do not belong to a barley growing district but my mind is not so small, and never was so small, as to fail to grasp the importance of barley growing both to those who engage in it and to those who use barley.  I am aware of the prejudice that existed for many years in favour of maize meal.</P>
      <P>In any scheme that is devised it would be undesirable that such a scheme could be used for the purpose of shipping out barley without any qualification and allowing maize freely &mdash;I say &ldquo;freely&rdquo;&mdash;to come in and take its place here.  Habits, customs and practices are difficult to cultivate. Everybody knows that.  Many people have now become accustomed to using barley and, as far as I am concerned, I shall try to ensure that, in the scheme devised, reasonable protection will be given to those who continue to engage in the production of barley.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As far as I possibly could, I have tried to get all the interested parties to talk to my officials, and on a number of occasions to myself, because I like to meet people who are interested, even if they are prejudiced and even if their interests are selfish ones.  I like to hear the worst because, knowing both sides, enables one to judge and to strike a fair balance.  We have subjected this proposal to scrutiny, examination and discussion.  More will be heard about it.  For the moment I merely want to tell the House and the <Col N="473" /> country that, in devising a scheme, I am trying to provide for and against the three important factors or interests that I have mentioned.  I believe the scheme will meet the case, for and against.</P>
    <P>With regard to wheat and the wheat levy, I shall not say anything more on that.  I dealt with it in my opening remarks and what I said then has been stated over and over again. Reference was made to growing wheat on contract.  Members will recall that when the levy was introduced and the Grain Board set up I stated quite clearly here at the time that the idea was not mine.  The representatives of the growers knew the problem that was there and knew the problem that had to be met.  They had discussed it with my late predecessor and, following on his death, they came to see me.  I showed no enthusiasm at all for the scheme and they appeared to feel at one stage, in fact, that I would not accept it.  I was taking the line of showing all the weaknesses, as I would like those who would come to see me in relation to the barley scheme to do, provided they were doing it genuinely. Finally, I informed the Government that the growers' representatives wanted a scheme along those lines and I gave it to them.</P>
    <P>In this House and outside it, in my own Party and other Parties, in county committees of agriculture and all the rest, I was asked, &ldquo;Why do you not grow wheat on the contract basis?  See how Guinness can have barley grown on the contract basis and the Sugar Company can have beet grown on that basis, and so on.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>It is only the privileged ones who get the contracts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not defending this. I am merely saying what was said to me.  I know every weakness in all these things, just as the Deputy does. I am merely telling the House that when this scheme, which was admitted by the representatives of the growers to be necessary, was introduced, it was their scheme.  They did not regard it as ideal but they said, &ldquo;This is the scheme we want&rdquo; and they got it.  I was thinking of the contract system <Col N="474" /> and my officials had examined it.  Now, we have had some experience of the working of the scheme that is in existence and it has been demonstrated this year that it has one weakness that I do not like.  I do not think we should try to grow more wheat than we want for national purposes.  I think it would be foolish to do that.  It is wise to rise to that level.  With the system at present in operation, we had last year, in spite of the proposed levy, a substantial increase in acreage and would have had a very substantial increase in yield, were it not for the bad weather that was experienced.</P>
      <P>As a result of that bad year and the decrease in acreage this year, of which there is evidence, it appears as if we will not have a yield sufficient to meet the national requirements.  Instead of growing wheat, people have gone over to barley and oats and perhaps some other crops.  I do not know to what extent that is the case.  I am not objecting to their going over to barley, provided they give us the wheat acreage that will meet the national requirement.</P>
      <P>I see one advantage in the contract system.  While it has, as Deputy Crotty reminds me, all the weaknesses that we know, the favouritism and all the rest, it would at least ensure an acreage each year that would be likely to yield our requirements.  That may be 300,000 tons or, if the percentage of Irish wheat were increased, the acreage could also be increased. Through the contract system, the requirements could be gauged much better than is possible through any other system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>County committees, through their central body, the National Committee, and the millers and others have told me that they propose to examine the possibility of introducing a contract system.  They are doing that on their own.  Any and every assistance in the way of information that is available to my Department will be given to them in order to enable them to carry out that work.  It is their responsibility. I know that, in the circumstances, it is not possible to get an ideal scheme.  There is a scheme in operation. It is not ideal.  The contract system <Col N="475" /> may not be ideal.  It is a matter of getting the best of the two or three schemes available to us.  I look with favour upon the activities of any body or group of people such as I have indicated. I wish them every luck in their efforts and I and the Department will give them every assistance possible. Officially, we cannot take any part in this, but, having regard to our knowledge of the difficulties, we are entitled to make that assistance available to them.</P>
    <P>Now I come to the butter levy.  There has been a great deal of discussion and publicity and a great deal has been written on this subject.  I do not blame the I.C.M.S.A. for its activities.  I shall not charge the I.C.M.S.A. with being a political body associated with Fianna Fáil, Fine Gael or any other Party.  I know that in the I.C.M.S.A., as in the case of other organisations, there are people of all political persuasions, because the matter with which they are dealing is one in which they are vitally interested.  They could, in fact, be regarded as a trade union.  Whatever they may think or say about me or the Government of which I am a member, I really do not mind.  I have heard it charged against us in this House that when, on another occasion, we went out of office, we encouraged the activities of these people.  As far as I am concerned, I can, with a clear and open conscience, entirely repudiate that suggestion.  In fact, I can go so far as to say publicly that when that organisation was being founded, after we had gone out of office, in 1948-49, I had been the Minister for Agriculture in the outgoing Government and I received an invitation to take part in that organisation from a very decent man who is now very high in the ranks of the I.C.M.S.A.</P>
    <P>I wrote to that gentleman telling him that I was a politician, a public man, that I had been Minister for Agriculture, that I had a special interest in milk production and milk producers and people engaged in that branch of agriculture, and had tried to show it while I was Minister for 12 months, and did show it, but that I would not join any such organisation because, I <Col N="476" /> said, I might be Minister tomorrow or in two years or 10 years; that if I am not, it does not matter, but, if I am, by joining the organisation now I would be leading them up the garden and making them believe that as long as I was with them, if ever I became Minister again, they would be all right. Therefore, in a very wholehearted way, I can repudiate the suggestion that we ever sold ourselves to that sort of activity.</P>
    <P>I am prepared to admit that in all these organisations that are made up of people of every political persuasion, there may be a section that would try to take advantage of a political situation.  I cannot be sure of that.  If it is happening against me now, I shall not complain about it because I do not deny the right of the milk producers to organise themselves and to make the best case they can and take the best stand they can, within reason.  They are free to thump me around the ring in any way they like but, in thumping me around the ring, I would ask them to remember&mdash;I do not want to make any boastful claim about it; I think I have said it before&mdash;that I happen to be the fortunate one who came in in 1947, when things were beginning to settle down after the war and the shortages and the controls, and, as Minister for Agriculture, was able to get my colleagues to give the dairying industry fairly reasonable conditions as far as the price of milk was concerned at that time.</P>
    <P>I do not want to claim that it was a wonderful achievement of mine, or anything like that, but if you look at the figures of the cow population since 1947-48 and note the solid growth in the number of cows supplying milk to creameries and the number of farmers attached to creameries as suppliers you will see that the very first real benefits they got after the war years were secured as a result of the luck that fell to me to come in at a time when I was able to help them substantially.  I have not lost my interest in them now.  I do not blame them for their activities.  I do not blame them for resenting that we were obliged to collect this levy.  If I were outside, not associated with this House, and were one of these suppliers, <Col N="477" /> the chances are that I, too, would stand up for my rights and try to get all that was going, just the same, possibly, as members of any other trade union might.</P>
    <P>A short time ago, three Deputies called to my office in this House and presented me with a resolution passed by their own committee of management of the local creamery.  The resolution was to the effect that they called upon their Deputies and Senators to interview the Minister for Agriculture with a view to securing that he would abandon the levy collected the previous year on butter manufactured, and so on.  I read the resolution half aloud and half to myself.  I looked at the three or four Deputies and Senators and I said, in effect: &ldquo;Ladies and Gentlemen, that is a resolution with which, if I were a supplier down in that area, I would find myself in thorough agreement.  I am not a supplier in that area.  I am a supplier of milk to a creamery but I am Minister for Agriculture. I take a realistic view, with my colleagues, of the problems that confront us in this regard.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>With the present Taoiseach, I found myself in London in 1958 discussing the whole question of butter.  You all remember the reason.  In that year we had a surplus of butter.  It cost somewhere in the neighbourhood of £3,000,000 to sell it, as butter prices were very low on the British market at that time.  Even then, I was dreadfully anxious, because of our general policy and our general aims, not only to maintain milk production at the level at which it then was, even though it gave us a surplus towards which we had to contribute largely from the Exchequer in order to dispose of it, but to increase milk production because of the other advantages that would obviously flow to the producers themselves and to the community as a whole.</P>
    <P>Having regard to the steady increase in the number of cows that in 1947-48 were supplying milk to creameries, and the number of suppliers, it was desirable to foster the idea that that tendency would continue and develop. If it were, do you think, in our circumstances, it would be reasonable to expect the taxpayers to meet <Col N="478" /> it all?  Do you think it would be reasonable to expect them to give a home-supported price at a level about which we have had complaints from Deputies and then come along and, from the Exchequer, subsidise the sale of whatever surplus we had?</P>
    <P>While conceding all the rights I have conceded to the organised producers to agitate for themselves, I am now defending myself as Minister and asking myself and my colleagues &mdash;and my colleagues ask me: &ldquo;Is it reasonable that you should go out to increase and expand, even if you turn the increased milk into cheese, chocolate crumb, milk powder, and so on?  Is it reasonable still to keep pressing in the direction of an increase?  Is it reasonable to ask the taxpayer to do these two things, to maintain a home-supported price at the present level and carry the whole burden of the export subsidy?&rdquo; I am not afraid to say here, with the shelter that this House affords me, that I am completely and absolutely in my conscience justified in standing over that decision.  Not only will I say it in the quietude of this place but I shall go into any area and claim that that is not an unjust and unfair decision in the circumstances in which we find ourselves and which could at any time arise.</P>
    <P>The case that is made is that in 1958, contrary to expectations, butter production decreased.  It did.  However, at this time in 1958, all the evidence went to show that, as far as supplies were concerned, we would have an increase on 1957.  Nobody was more disappointed than I was.  Just as in the case of the crops, the Almighty intervened.  The remaining months of the year turned the increase into a deficit.  Anyhow, we had a considerable amount of butter to export. In fact, the levy we collected was barely sufficient to meet one-third of the cost of selling the reduced quantity of butter available for export.</P>
    <P>Then this year came along.  All last summer, the season was bad.  Cows suffered because of it.  The winter was hard.  The early part of the grass season was not very good.  I was being pressed to abandon this levy by people who were making prophecies as to the <Col N="479" /> outcome of the season.  I claimed and I still claim, even though we are half way through it, that, even yet, nobody knows for certain how this season will turn out.  Undoubtedly, up to the present there has been a reduction of about 15 per cent. in deliveries to creameries as compared with last year. The second part of the season could make a wonderful change in that position. I am prepared to state, even before those who are justifiably selfishly interested in the matter, that there is no real benefit in a policy if you switch and change from one foot to the other every six or twelve months.</P>
    <P>I have given to this House and to the suppliers outside the assurance that any money collected from them by way of this levy&mdash;although it was stated to the contrary by people in this House who well knew they were not presenting the case fairly&mdash;will stay in that fund and belong to the suppliers. Every £ that comes out of that fund for the purpose of disposing of any surplus butter we may have means that £2 must come from the Exchequer.  I can assure you of this.  The more £2 we have to part with, the more I will like it, either this year or next year or any other year, because I know, in the general line of things, this is a very important industry.  We should be prepared to give reasonable assistance and the industry should be appreciative of the difficulties that are there. While they should naturally complain, they should be a little bit reasonable in such matters.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>This levy looks like becoming a permanent tax on the farmers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot prevent the Deputy arriving at all the reasonable conclusions at which I know he is capable of arriving on questions of this nature, and I do not propose to dispute vigorously the method he adopts in order to arrive at whatever conclusions he wishes to arrive at.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>What does the Minister mean when he says the money will belong to the suppliers?  It will not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="480" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>It will never be touched as far as we are concerned until such time as it is necessary to serve the purpose for which it is designed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>They will not have any control over it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what the Deputy means by that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister said the money, even if it is not expended by way of subsidy on exports this year, will belong to the suppliers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>So it will.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>It will not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I could have money deposited in the bank in my name but the money could belong to you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>I would take good care I had control over it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be a personal transaction and I would not blame the Deputy for being cautious there.  He may take it that what I have said in this respect is completely in order.  The money was never collected and will not be used for a purpose other than that to which I have referred.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>Levies that were previously imposed to right the balance of payments were switched to permanent taxation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>That is another subject. You could be tossing that over in your mind for the next three or four years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FlorenceWycherley" hpid="Mr. Wycherley Mr. Wycherley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wycherley</NameTxt>
      <P>When the supplier is paying one-third are you paying two-thirds all the time into this fund?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>We are paying two-thirds on every pound of butter that is exported at a loss.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FlorenceWycherley" hpid="Mr. Wycherley Mr. Wycherley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wycherley</NameTxt>
      <P>But that fund is being built up when there is no butter exported.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be foolish. That money will be there when it is required.  I do not know what form the <Col N="481" /> fund takes in that regard.  What difference does it make?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FlorenceWycherley" hpid="Mr. Wycherley Mr. Wycherley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wycherley</NameTxt>
      <P>It makes a bit of a difference.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>Not a bit in the world, unless you thought you would not be solvent when the payment would have to be made.  That will not happen as far as this Government are concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FlorenceWycherley" hpid="Mr. Wycherley Mr. Wycherley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wycherley</NameTxt>
      <P>The same could happen to the farmers.  We are expecting the farmers to be solvent all the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I am talking about insolvency.  Some criticism has been levelled against us on the grounds that in the Government's proposal for economic expansion there is a recommendation and a hope expressed that the cow population would be increased and some of the critics of the Department of Agriculture and of myself have expressed themselves as very doubtful as to the wisdom of the paragraph advising farmers in certain parts to produce more calves on the basis of their using the milk of the cow and the heifer.  The whole aim of the policy as outlined in that document is to increase the cow population one way or another irrespective of what course the individual farmer pursues in helping towards the realisation of that aim.  The cow population has been almost static for many years.  Although it has increased since the price of milk was fixed away back in 1947/48 at the level which was then determined, the number of cows has been fairly static over a very long period and the aim of the Government, as indicated in that document, is that we should bring cow numbers in 1964 to 1,500,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>No matter what policy is pursued by the individual farmer we cannot do that without increasing the volume of milk that is bound to come into the creameries and go into the production of butter, chocolate crumb, cheese, milk powder, and so on.  We do not feel in any way distressed about that paragraph.  That paragraph was carefully vetted and referred largely to areas that were not at all accustomed to milk production in any form.  We did hope that in those areas there <Col N="482" /> would be the development in relation to heifers and the rearing of calves that is taking place in other counties, a development which has taken place in these parts of the State and, we hope, will continue.  Side by side with that we could see that if the aim was to be achieved which was set out in the document to which I have referred we must also have an increase of cows in the milk areas and that as a result of that increase we would have a gradual increase in the supply of milk.  It would be our responsibility, as the Government acting on behalf of the taxpayer, and the responsibility of the farmers to combine as best we could to see that that is disposed of in the most profitable way and diverted to the most profitable purposes possible.</P>
    <P>There was no question whatever in relation to that paragraph, as I gave the assurance before, of our turning our back on the milk suppliers, the milk producers, or a failure on our part to recognise the vital importance of these people to our whole economy and the vital contribution they will have to make if we are to be successful in the aims that have been set out.</P>
    <P>I intended to give numbers and percentages from 1947-48 to 1957-58 of the general trend to which I have been referring.  I do not like to give these numbers because if you take, for example, the numbers of cows that are now supplying milk to creameries as against the numbers for 1947-48, we know there have been changes. Farmers' butter for many years has not been as saleable as it was.  There had to be a spreading of the travelling creamery and the collection and conversion of milk through the creamery organisation that was formerly disposed of in the old fashioned way. That resulted in bringing into the creamery network a large number of herd owners and a great number of cows.</P>
    <P>It would be unfair of me then to say there was not some other factor as well as improved prices contributing towards that end.  However, even allowing for that, those who claim that there is a desertion of the business on the part of creamery milk suppliers, a business in which they and their <Col N="483" /> fathers before them have been engaged, have no evidence to show for it.  There is no evidence of a desertion and there is not likely to be any such evidence.  The total increase in the cow population in those years is roughly 127,000.  That is not nearly enough.  I would hope that, as a result of their activities, the number would steadily increase to the number mentioned in the target during the next four or five years.</P>
    <P>The matter of pig production and the grading of pigs in factories is not a new subject to any of us who have any association at all with this business. The reduction in the number of pigs has been checked very substantially in recent months.  As far as we can find out through the C.A.O.s and through other checks which we carry out, there is a very welcome tendency to show an increase and in the months ahead we have no doubt that that increase will be felt at the fairs and in the factories all over the country.</P>
    <P>There are at least two reasons which I know of for that reduction. There was the swine fever and, again, there was the unfortunate year we had from the point of view of feeding stuffs. There was a shortage of potatoes, oats and all the rest of it.  For that reason, of course, the tendency towards increasing the production of pigs was bound to come to an end.  In fact, you might almost be sure that a decline was on the way.  That, as I say, took place for the two reasons given.  It is now corrected and we are on the upward trend again, which is a very welcome thing.</P>
    <P>With regard to grading, I do not see what you can do on this subject.  I think I spoke about it last year on the Estimate for the Department of Agriculture. I am well aware of all the criticism which is sometimes levelled at the grading system and at the alleged injustice of it.  Still I contend that the percentage of pigs taken in on a grade A basis is proof that the system must be reasonably fair.  I do not know how you can devise any other scheme that would be more likely to give a greater degree of satisfaction than the present one.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="484" /> The weights at which pigs are being exposed for sale has quite a lot to do with the improvement in the grading of pigs.  People are becoming fairly knowledgeable with regard to the live weight of a pig which is likely to grade best.  People who have gone in for pig production in a big way maintain that that has a lot to do with it, apart from breeding and feeding.  Nobody whom I have met has been able to devise any other scheme that would be likely to give satisfaction to the producer as far as grading is concerned.</P>
    <P>I am always very anxious to meet anybody with new ideas on that matter.  We have plenty of discussion on the subject in the Department with outside representatives of producers and county committees and, while they are prepared to be critical, none of them really has any worthwhile suggestion to make as to the way in which this matter might be dealt with.</P>
    <P>I referred to the question of the bovine T.B. eradication in my opening speech.  I will not go into any great detail now except to say that I was not present here when a Deputy of my own Party apparently made some suggestion that we have been discourteous to a particular county committee because of our failure to reply to a scheme which a sub-committee of that committee designed to help us in this task.</P>
    <P>Nothing could be further from the truth.  In fact, we had no complaints direct from the committee itself because in the Department of Agriculture we get many schemes and suggestions from every conceivable kind of source.  They are all taken seriously as far as we are concerned.</P>
    <P>Our approach to this task is changing from day to day and will change but we cannot, simply because a Deputy in this House or a county committee of agriculture has certain ideas as to the way we should approach the matter, adopt the proposals until we have these suggestions examined by every conceivable interest in the whole trade.  We have often had our own minds clear on a course we would hope to take in the future and when we brought in some of the interests vitally concerned they said <Col N="485" /> they agreed it would have to be done ultimately, but not to do it just then.  I say then that if the allegation is made that we were discourteous in any way to a county committee of agriculture or to any individual interested in a matter of such tremendous importance as this, it certainly was not intended.  We will always welcome every criticism of that nature, either in writing or verbally, as far as this work is concerned.</P>
    <P>We have a tremendous knowledge of it in the Department at the present time.  We have a tremendous idea of the difficulties of it.  We have, I think, a staff of very keen-minded active men. I sometimes think that if we could only get half the co-operation to which we are entitled from the public and the stockbreeders, I would not be the least bit doubtful that we could achieve this task within the time set for it.  Unfortunately, it has to be brought home very clearly to some people before you can get them to give the sort of co-operation that is necessary.  The house has to be really falling on their heads.</P>
    <P>The reasonable concession which we secured from the British as to the importation by them of once tested cattle is satisfactory from our point of view but only in a limited way and in a very limited way as far as the farmers are concerned too.  They wanted tested stock.  This is only just a make-shift arrangement.  It has weaknesses both from our point of view and from theirs.  We are glad to have this arrangement and we are glad to take advantage of it because we could not just carry on without it.  But while we are very thankful for it, we feel the effects its shortcomings have on us. We want, therefore, to get to the point where we will be approaching the end. As I have already said, I have not the slightest fear or doubt in my mind but that we can accomplish this task if we can get a reasonable degree of co-operation.</P>
    <P>We are getting a fair degree of co-operation but there has to be vim and enthusiasm on the part of all the veterinary people who are working in the country.  They have their own private practices but I would ask them <Col N="486" /> to try to press this work forward and ask the farmers and people calling upon them to try to co-operate and not be so indifferent as to who is there to meet the vet. and indifferent as to the amount of time the man is going to lose there.  There are so many ways in which the farmers can show by a small contribution of that kind their enthusiasm for the work.  If they do that we shall be able to make progress.</P>
    <P>The Department will be making some further announcements of changes in the scheme very shortly. These will not be the last either, the House may take it, and I merely mention this to let the House know that in so far as we may not have replied fully to the Cork County Committee and their scheme, it is because whatever proposals they make have to be examined in conjunction with half a dozen other proposals from other sources and the ideas that we have ourselves.  When all these are blended together and discussions have taken place between the interested parties, we have to arrive at any amendments which we conclude are desirable.  I ask the co-operation of all Deputies in all Parties to do what they can by word and deed to encourage all those with whom they come in contact to get and to keep this work moving.</P>
    <P>Deputy Dillon reminded me of our alleged failure to deal with the condemnation of some pure bred cattle that were recently exported to America.  The Deputy must have missed the statement which was released from my Department a short time ago.  It was a public release dealing with this whole matter.  When this took place we sent one of our most experienced veterinary people to the United States and he investigated the whole question very fully.  He sifted all the facts and circumstances and following his return the statement which I hold in my hand was issued to the Press dealing with that situation, so that it is not necessary for me to read it.  The date of the issue was the 12th June, 1959.</P>
    <P>Deputy Russell referred to the London talks.  Yesterday the Taoiseach dealt with this matter in the course of a reply to a Parliamentary Question <Col N="487" /> and to some Supplementary Questions which followed.  I have nothing to add to that.  The official statement which was issued following the talks which we had with Mr. Maudling and Mr. Hare indicated clearly that these talks were of a continuing nature and I do not think that it would be reasonable to expect that statements would be made here as to what exactly took place.  The Deputy can be assured that the official statement and what it contained is genuine in the sense that we are anxious to maintain and strengthen our trading relations with Britain and that it is a mistake for Deputies, as they sometimes do in this House, to emphasise overmuch the importance of the British market to us.  We are conscious of it and the British are also conscious of our importance to them. It is on that basis that discussions here should be conducted.</P>
    <P>After all, the British do not have to be reminded of these things.  They know them well.  If we have any remarks to make we should direct them to the two sides.  There are advantages on both sides but I certainly agree with some of the speakers who expressed themselves as being disappointed with our ability to find a market for such commodities as, say, eggs, and who have expressed themselves as being depressed, as I am indeed, with the condition of the poultry industry.</P>
    <P>I remember in 1947 when the then Taoiseach, the present Taoiseach, the Minister for Finance and I went to Britain for the first trade discussions which took place after the war.  We discussed the question of developing our poultry industry and I was tremendously interested in that because apart altogether from my national interest in it I knew it was a business that was of great importance to smallholders everywhere and had been all down the years.  I was anxious to get some arrangement that would prove attractive and bring the business to real life.</P>
    <P>I remember saying to the British Minister with whom I had that discussion:&mdash;&ldquo;For goodness sake, if we are to set out on a development programme, <Col N="488" /> let us set out on that programme and on that policy with a reasonable prospect of continuity, a continuity of opportunity&rdquo;.  We had the feeling that that would be so.  In 1948 the permanent agreement was made and anybody who looks at the discussions that took place in this House will see that many of the hopes which we had as to the availability of all kinds of markets have not materialised.  Any Deputy will see what the British should be able to see, that our present trade relations are based on the 1938 and 1948 Agreements and the whole pattern has changed so much since then as a result of Britain's policy in favour of their own producers.</P>
    <P>We cannot complain or protest about their rights in that regard but we can at least point out the result which has followed the policy that they have pursued at home.  Nothing would please me better, or any Minister for Agriculture, or any Government which knew the circumstances here, or be better for the country, than to get a reasonable output for these vital products, these traditional products such as butter and milk products and bacon, eggs and poultry.  Nothing would give a Government more satisfaction than to get reasonable prices and a reasonable continuity of availability of markets for these products because they are traditional to us and if at times we have been forced to come to their rescue it is because of their traditional character and because of their importance in the lives of our people.  If we could raise them up to a higher plane it would mean more security for those who are living, and whom we hope will continue to live in the country.  That is our aim.  I can assure the House that is an objective that so far as I am concerned I will keep firmly in my mind in any discussions in which I may be called upon to participate.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister say if it is proposed to give further information to the House on the trade talks in London?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it would be reasonable to do that at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="489" />
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that when discussions are going on it is not always advisable to disclose their course until a later stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>It is really never advisable and it is never done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree.  Not giving information can often cause disquietude and there is a genuine desire, not only among the agricultural community but in general, to know what will be the position of this country if the seven-nation arrangement goes through.  We know that the Taoiseach has stated that it will not preclude bilateral agreements between this country and Great Britain but nevertheless the general picture created by newspapers&mdash;which may not always be accurate&mdash;is that we are going to be on the outside looking in and that our position may be worsened.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Deputy can get anything more than the assurance I have given.  I have tried to give to the House and the country an outline of the general ideas in my mind and in the minds of the members of the Government.  These are the ideas that we will pursue in the course of any discussions that will take place, or may take place in future, in regard to these trade matters.  I take it that the Deputy does not disagree with the general expression of opinion and policy which I have just given and after that, if you approve of that general line, you will have to trust us to try to do the best we can. After we have done that you will have your chance to give your views on whether we achieved the success we wished to achieve.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Will it be possible to conclude these discussions at some stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>In every case where you enter on discussions, you always hope for a conclusion.  This will be one of those occasions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I know, but the Free Trade Area discussions have been protracted.  Is it expected that the discussions <Col N="490" /> with Great Britain will be concluded?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I certainly hope they will be.</P>
      <P>Question: &ldquo;That the Estimate be referred back for reconsideration&rdquo; put and declared lost.</P>
      <P>Vote put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Vote" RHead="59&mdash;External Affairs">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Vote 59&mdash;External Affairs.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Aire Gnothaí Eachtracha (Proinsias Mac Aogáin) Aire Gnothaí Eachtracha (Proinsias Mac Aogáin)">
      <NameTxt>Aire Gnothaí Eachtracha (Proinsias Mac Aogáin)</NameTxt>
      <P>Tairgim:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Go ndeonfar suim nach mo ná £284,840 chun slánaithe na suime is gá chun íoctha an mhuirir a thiocfadh chun bheith iníoctha i rith na bliana dar críoch an 31ú lá de Mhárta, 1960, chun Tuarastal agus Costas Oifig an Aire Gnóthaí Eachtracha agus Seirbhísí áirithe atá faoi riaradh na hOifige sin (Uimh. 16 de 1924), lena n-áirítear Deontas-i-gCabhair.</P>
      <P>Le cead an Cheann Comhairie, tá fúm an Meastachán le haghaidh Gnóthaí Eachtracha agus an Meastachán le haghaidh Comhar Idirnáisiúnta a thógaint le chéile mar a rinneadh blianta eile.</P>
      <P>I gcás na nGnothái Eachtracha, is é atá sa Mheastachán £427,240.  Sin méadú glan de £13,390 ar mheastachán na bliana anuraidh.  Is le haghaidh na nithe seo a leanas a mheastar an bhreis a bheith riachtanach: (1) tuarastail, pá agus liúntais do na hoifigigh atá ag fónamh sa cheancheathrú; (2) teileagraim, teileafóin agus postas sa cheanncheathrú; (3) costais taistil ár n-ionadaithe thar lear; agus (4) comhar cultúir le tíortha eile (deontas-i-gcabhair). Mar neodrú go pointe áirithe ar an gcostas breise seo tá le háireamh gur mó de £3,049 an tsuim a luaitear faoin fho-mhírcheann leithris i gcabhair; go bhfuil laghduithe beaga déanta ar na suimeanna a thugann an tír seo mar ranníoc do chomhluchtaí dlíthiúla Idir-Rialtais, agus ar an gcaiteachas i ndáil tuarastal, pá agus liúntas dár gcuid oifigeach thar lear agus i ndáil postais, páigéireachais, teileagram agus teileafón ár n-ionadaithe thar lear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="491" /> Tá breis agus ceithre mhile punt de mhéadú sa mheastachán le haghaidh tuarastal, pá agus liúntas sa cheann-cheathrú.  Is é is cuis leis sin an méadú tuarastail a tugadh don Státseirbhís anuraidh agus an gnáth-bhreisiú i dtuarastal bliantúil na n-oifigeach bunaithe.</P>
    <P>Is deacair an caiteachas ar theileagraim, teileafón agus postas sa cheann-cheathrú a mheas go cruinn mar ní ionann i gcónaí an glaoch ar na seirbhísí seo.  Tá méadaithe ar an meastachán i mbliana, ach tá sin bunaithe ar an ráta caiteachais a bhí ann dáiríre anuraidh.</P>
    <P>Tá méadú cuíosach mór&mdash;méadú £7,000&mdash;sa mheastachán le haghaidh costas taistil ár n-ionadaithe thar lear. Is é is bun leis sin gur dócha gur mó a bheidh oifigigh á n-aistriú agus á gcur in ath-ionad agus ag teacht abhaile ar saoire ná mar a bhí anuraidh.</P>
    <P>£7,000 an deontas-i-gcabhair le haghaidh Comhar Cultúir i mbliana. Méadú é sin a thugann sásamh mór dom féin, agus a thabharfaidh sásamh do na Teachtaí freisin, tá mé cinnte.  Ar feadh a bhfad de bhlianta £10,000 a bhíodh sa deontas-i-gcabhair seo ach de dheasca an crua-chás airgeadais a tharla ann trí bhliain ó shin laghdaíodh é go dtí £2,000 nó beagán thairis.  Chuir sin srian linn sna himeachtaí a bhféadfaimís aghaidh a thabhairt orthu agus chros sé ar fad orainn imeachtaí eile a mb'fhéadfadh toradh maith a bheith orthu.  Tig linn bheith bródúil as go leor dá bhfuil déanta san iomad gné dár saol cultúrtha, agus ar mhaithe lenár ndeachlú thar lear ba chóir a chur in iúl i dtíortha eile go bhfuil an dul-ar-aghaidh sin déanta.  Mar sin is maith ann an méadú faoin fhomhírcheann seo i mbliana.  Máidir leis an gcaoi a gcaitear an deontas-i-gcabhair, tá comhairle an Choiste um Chomhar Cultúrtha ar fáil dom agus sin cúnamh ó dhaoine a bhfuil aitheantas bainte amach acu ina raon saothair féin.  Is maith liom an deis a bheith agam anois chun buíochas a ghabháil le chuile duine a d'oibrigh chomb fiúntach sin ar an gCoiste blianta eile agus aithním freisin go bhfuil Coiste an lae <Col N="492" /> inniu chomb fial céanna ag tabhairt toradh a gcuid ama agus eolais don Stát.</P>
    <P>Is é an cúiteamh is mó atá le lua i gcoinne na breise sa mheastachán ná an t-airgead breise sa leithreas-i-gcabhair. Is é is bun leis sin gur cheadaigh an tAire Airgeadais le déannaí fáltais bheaga éagsula a áirití go n-úige seo mar Fháltais Bhreise Státchiste a áireamh feasta mar chuid den leithreas-i-gcabhair.</P>
    <P>Máidir leis an Meastachán le haghaidh Comhar Idirnáisiúnta (Vóta 60), ta an méid, £63,670, le haghaidh ranníocaí do Chomhairle na hEorpa, don Eagras um Chomhar Eacnamaíochta san Eoraip agus do na Náisiúin Aontaithe; agus le haghaidh costa eile a bhaineann leis sin.  Is é an Meastachán iomlán £95,470.  Sin laghdú glan de £2,500 ón mbliain anuraidh.</P>
    <P>Tá laghdú de £1,500 déanta ar rannioc na tire seo le haghaidh costas Chomhairle na hEorpa i leith na bliana seo ach is airde na costais taistil, de £1,200.  Rinneadh diluacháil ar an fhranc Francach mi Nollag seo caite.  Tagann as sin gur fearr dúinne an ráta iomlaoide atá i bhfeidhm anois agus is lúide an rannioc atáimid a dhéanamh.  Is de réir céatadáin seasta nó cuiosach seasta de Cháinaisnéis na Comhairle a riomhtar amach an rannioc sin.  Maidir leis an mbreisiú sa mheastachán le haghaidh costas taistil, is rud riachtanach é mar gheall ar chruinnithe breise ag Coisti den Chomhairle Chomhairlitheach agus méadú ar na rátai liúntais chothabhála.</P>
    <P>Fé mar a tharla laghdú sa rannioc le haghaidh Comhairle na hEorpa is lú freisin an rannioc don Eagras um Chomhar Eacnamaiochta san Eoraip. Is é meid an laghdaithe sin dhá mhile is céad punt agus is é is cuis leis gur fábharai dúinn anois an ráta iomlaoide i leith frainc na Fraince.</P>
    <P>Tá méadú áfach ar na figiúirí i leith taistil agus mion-chostas faoin mircheann seo.  £1,150 an bhreis i leith taistil.  £280 an bhreis i leith mion-chostas. Ar an airgead a iocfar faoi na fo-mhircheanna seo áiritear caiteachas i leith na n-oifigeach as gach Roinn a dhéanann freastal ar chruinnithe <Col N="493" /> an Eagrais um Chomhar Eacnamiochta san Eoraip agus tá an meastachán bunaithe ar an méid a cheaptar a theastóidh ó na Ranna sin go léir i mbliana.</P>
    <P>Maidir leis na hiocaiochtai i leith na Náisiún Aontaithe tá laghdú £2,000 ar an rannioc do Eagras na Náisiún Aontaithe i gcompráid leis an mbliain seo caite.  Is é a caitheadh anuraidh £28,650.  An tsuim atá luaite an turas seo, chítear dúinn gur gaire i dáirire don rannioc a bheidh le déanamh i mbliana.  Tá na mireanna a bhaineann le taisteal agus mionchostais méadaithe de £3,000 agus £150 faoi seach.  Tá an meastachán sin bunaithe ar ráta caiteachais na bliana anuraidh móide foráil le haghaidh siosón speisialta den Ard-thionól a fhéadfadh a bheith ann. Ní dhearnadh aon fhoráil mar sin cheana.  Tá laghdú de £1,150 sa ranníoc le haghaidh Coiste Leanaí na Náisiún Aontaithe ach ina choinne sin tugadh £1,670 do chiste na dTeitheadh, rud nar tugadh cheana.  Sin fo-mhircheann C.7.  D'fhonn cabhrú le hArd Choimisinéir na dTeitheach chun deireadh a chur leis na campaí san Eoraip, mar atá beartaithe aige, gheallamar cúig míle punt don chiste sin, agus é a íoc i dtráthchodanna comhionanna i rith trí bhliain.</P>
    <P>Iarradh orainn tuilleadh airgid a thabhairt le haghaidh Beartas Chúnaimh Teicniúil na Náisiún Aontaithe agus shocraíomar go méadófaíann ranníoc go dtí £5,000, an tsuim a íoctaí cheana.  Laghdaíodh de £5,500 an ranníoc le haghaidh Fórsa Éigeandála na Náisiún Aontaithe, ach bhí sé sin de réir laghdú a bheartaigh na Naisiúin Aontaithe féin sa chaiteachas ar an bhfórsa sin.  Ar deireadh ansin tá mír nua de £1,000, curtha leis an Meastachán le haghaidh ranníoc do Ghníomhaireacht Faoisimh agus Oibreacha na Náisiún Aontaithe.  Cuid de ghnó na Gníomhaireachta seo cabhrú leis an lucht teithe sa Neas-Oirthear agus iad a athbhunú más féidir.  Sin ceann de na fadhbanna is déine atá le réiteach agus ba faoiseamh agus laghdú achrainn don chuid sin den domhan é dá bhféadfaí e réiteach lenár linn.</P>
    <P>The events of the past twelve months have done little to relieve anxiety <Col N="494" /> about the present international situation. They have indeed repeated the now familiar pattern of successive crises which only stop short of provoking wide-spread armed conflict, with all its attendant dangers for mankind.</P>
    <P>During 1958 we saw, in particular, the development of extremely dangerous situations in the Middle East and in the Far East.  Our part in regard to such world problems was to make the best contribution we could to consideration of the issues involved as they arose at the United Nations. In some cases we put forward suggestions of our own aimed at relaxation of international tension, which is the first condition of progress towards a just and stable peace.</P>
    <P>As Deputies are aware, the Middle East crisis of last summer, which culminated in American and British landings in Lebanon and Jordan, led to a Special Emergency Session of the United Nations General Assembly in August.  The course of events is so recent in our memories that I need hardly recall them now.  I should comment, however, that the outcome of the Session was very much more successful than appeared possible when it was summoned.  The General Assembly agreed unanimously on a solution, which was supported and indeed suggested by all the Arab countries including those whose differences in regard to the basic issues at stake had been fundamental to the crisis.  It was encouraging to see the countries of the area concerned coming together in this fashion to devise a solution for local problems.  It was also very encouraging to see the growing realisation by the Great Powers, as demonstrated by the evolution of these events, of the wisdom of restraint in dealing with the affairs of smaller nations.</P>
    <P>In my address to the Assembly last August I endeavoured to stress this aspect of the general Middle Eastern situation, urging that establishment of the principle of neutrality for the whole region would be a contribution to peace in the area and in the world generally and that it would create a psychological atmosphere favourable to negotiations for peace in other critical <Col N="495" /> areas.  The theme of my remarks was that the Assembly should work to establish the outline of a general settlement in the Middle East, including a reduction of the Arab-Israeli antagonism. I supported the imaginative proposal of President Eisenhower who took the exceptional course of addressing the session for the establishment of a Middle East Economic Agency on the lines of the O.E.E.C.  And I suggested in particular that the Arab refugees problem was the greatest single obstacle to lasting peace in the area and that the United Nations should be ready to make extraordinary efforts to break the deadlock on this issue.</P>
    <P>It seemed to me that the greatest hope of a solution lay in guaranteeing full compensation to the refugees by the United Nations.  The refugees, I said, were entitled to look for compensation to the organisation which some years earlier had taken decisions so vitally affecting them, not as charity but as a matter of justice. The Irish delegate on the Assembly's Special Political Committee developed this suggestion during the debate on the Palestine Refugees question in the Assembly's Thirteenth regular Session which commenced in September last. While the idea has not yet won the necessary measure of support, I believe that it has made some impression on the general thinking on the problem. We must hope that through this or other means arrangements will be evolved to ensure the peaceful and prosperous development of the Middle Eastern area which is still menaced by very serious tensions.</P>
    <P>In the context of these Middle Eastern troubles, it is fitting that I should pay a tribute to the part played by the Irish officers who served in the United Nations Observation Group in Lebanon.  Their work was a credit to their country and a fine example of the contribution which a small nation can make to the preservation of peace. In the words of Mr. Hammarskjold, the Irish officers &ldquo;served well the cause of the United Nations.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>A wide range of world problems <Col N="496" /> was dealt with by the Assembly's Thirteenth Session.  The Irish delegates took their due part in the deliberations of the various Committees.  The printed records of the Session are deposited in the Library as they become available and the interventions made by Irish delegates in the various debates were reported in the newspapers of the time.  I do not think it necessary therefore to enter into an exhaustive review of the Session's activities.</P>
    <P>I should, however, refer to the election of our Permanent Representative at the United Nations to the Chairmanship of the important Trusteeship Committee.  This was a significant mark of Ireland's standing in the organisation and, above all, a striking recognition of the personal qualities of the official concerned.  It was particularly fitting, I think, that the guidance of the Trusteeship Committee's proceedings should have been entrusted to a representative of Ireland.  The Committee's work during the Session concerned in a very direct way the problems attending the evolution towards independence of former colonies and dependencies, the problems, principally, of the great African continent emerging from a long period under European rule and beginning to assert its considerable potential in world affairs.  The Committee's Chairman was indeed to say at the end of the Session that the labours of the Committee had been important enough to justify the Session's being known as the &ldquo;African Assembly.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I should like also to mention briefly the Assembly Resolution calling for the institution of a World Refugee Year.  Deputies will be aware that perhaps the greatest humanitarian problem confronting the world to-day is that of the several million people who, through no fault of their own, are refugees from their native countries, driven from their homes, not only by the last great war, but by continuing local conflicts.</P>
    <P>It is to meet this problem that the United Nations decided to launch this particular appeal.  It is, humanly speaking, of vital importance that the <Col N="497" /> final resettlement and rehabilitation of these people, so long delayed, should now be accomplished as soon as possible, if they are to be saved from apathy and despair.  It is the purpose of the World Refugee Year, to call on all citizens, each according to his means, to remember these unfortunate homeless, and to offer all the help they can, so that by the end of 1960 this immense work of Christian charity may be successfully achieved.</P>
    <P>As I have already informed the House, the Government have promised £6,000 to the United Nations effort and have further requested the Irish Red Cross to undertake the organisation of Ireland's private contribution to the Year.  We know that the Irish Red Cross, with its magnificent tradition of service to humanity, is particularly suited to this task, and we are confident that the Irish people will respond worthily, and that all our charitable bodies and institutions will co-operate with the Society in this effort to the fullest extent.</P>
    <P>I now come to what was, from the point of view of the Irish Delegation, the principal feature of the 1958 Session of the United Nations.  Our main effort was concentrated upon drawing attention to the dangers involved for peace in the wider dissemination of nuclear weapons.  This was the central theme of my address in the Assembly's General Debate and we took steps to develop it further during the First Committee's disarmament debate.</P>
    <P>Our initiative on the matter in the United Nations was two-fold, consisting, firstly, of a statement of the problem as we saw it and a concrete suggestion as to a solution and, secondly, of the tabling of a draft resolution designed as a first step towards that solution.</P>
    <P>I suggested that the conclusion of an international agreement, by which the present nuclear Powers would remain the sole possessors of such weapons, was an urgent necessity for world peace.  I expressed the view that the nuclear stalemate now preserving world peace would cease to apply once nuclear weapons began to come <Col N="498" /> into the possession of smaller countries.  A general war could, I argued, result from the use of these weapons by a small State or revolutionary group.</P>
    <P>The solution I put forward was that there should be general agreement that no State outside the present Nuclear Club should manufacture or otherwise obtain nuclear weapons. The two elements in this agreement would be an undertaking by the nuclear Powers not to supply such weapons to any other country, and a renunciation of the weapons by all other countries.</P>
    <P>My discussions with other delegates showed that there was considerable support for the proposal.  In the First Committee, therefore&mdash;and this was the second aspect of our initiative in the matter&mdash;I tabled a draft resolution asking for recognition of the dangers involved in wider dissemination of the weapons and proposing the establishment of an Ad Hoc Committee to study the matter.</P>
    <P>At the conclusion of the debate, the paragraph recognising the dangers involved in the spread of nuclear weapons was voted on separately at our request and was adopted by 37 votes to none, with 44 abstentions.  The favourable votes spanned many of the voting blocs in the Assembly.  They were a measure of the anxiety felt by a considerable number of countries on this issue and it was particularly gratifying that no country voted against the principle propounded.  As I did not wish to press the particular method suggested for dealing with the acknowledged danger, that is, the establishment of an Ad Hoc Committee, I then withdrew the resolution as a whole.  It had by that stage of the debate become clear that the Disarmament Commission was about to be reconstituted and I suggested that it should deal with the nuclear restriction question as one of its first items.</P>
    <P>We learnt subsequently&mdash;and the Australian and Norwegian delegates explained their votes in this sense in the Committee&mdash;that many of the delegations that had abstained in the vote on the paragraph in question, did so <Col N="499" /> only because they did not favour the idea of setting up the Ad Hoc Committee. I felt, too, that many Governments had not had time to study the matter and instruct their delegations in the interval between our tabling the resolution and its consideration in the First Committee.</P>
    <P>For reasons quite unconnected with our proposals, the Disarmament Commission has not met since the conclusion of the Session.  However, the necessity of restricting the spread of nuclear weapons throughout the world has been receiving some attention in the Press and elsewhere.  I have been considering how best to pursue the matter at the approaching Fourteenth Session of the General Assembly and I recently requested that the item be entered on the agenda of that Session. Copies of the memorandum which accompanied the request, in accordance with the usual practice in such cases, will be found in the Library.</P>
    <P>There is, of course, another current international problem, that of the discontinuance of tests of nuclear weapons, which has a direct bearing on the question of restricting the spread of those weapons.  The three-power Conference on nuclear weapons tests has been meeting in Geneva since last October and we must hope that the progress it has already made will not finally be nullified by unresolved disagreement on the points still at issue.  Let us hope and pray that the series of conferences being held in Geneva may crack the ice of the cold war and open the way to true peace based on law and justice and the rights of all nations great and small.</P>
    <P>I do not propose in these introductory remarks to enter further into a review of the events of the past year although I shall naturally be happy to try to answer any questions Deputies may raise.  It would not be fitting, however, that I conclude this statement without a brief reference to the visit which the former President made in March to the U.S.A.  It was a high honour for this country that our President should have been invited by the President of the United States to be his official guest.  I, who had the privilege of accompanying the President <Col N="500" /> on this historic visit, can testify to the warmth of the reception accorded to him everywhere he went and by everyone he met from President Eisenhower down.  And I can also endorse at first hand all that has been written and said about the superb manner in which President Ó Ceallaigh represented our country and the overwhelming success of the visit.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the Estimate be referred back for reconsideration.</P>
      <P>I have always held the view that cooperation is essential among nations if we are to bring about a world order in which freedom and justice will be the basis of international relations.  It is therefore important that our policy and attitude should be guided by our own traditions, our history and our culture, which reflect a strong Christian outlook.  It is important, too, not to minimise the influence of this country and equally vital not to exaggerate it.</P>
      <P>Any action we take should strengthen the power and influence of the free world because any action which weakens that situation is bad and detrimental to the welfare of humanity as a whole.  We have laid it down as part of our policy that we would observe the terms of the Charter and that, as well as observing the terms of the Charter ourselves, we would pursue the aims of securing acceptance of the terms of the Charter, however difficult that might be at times, because we recognised that adopting a constructive and independent rôle would reflect not only our traditions and outlook but that, as a result, we would gain in prestige and influence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like, therefore, to join in expressing appreciation of the work which the Irish officers did as part of the special United Nations' Force in the Lebanon.  They brought credit on themselves and credit on this country. If, as I say, we adopt this position of independence, we shall gain respect and serve our own interests as well as the welfare of the world as a whole. Difficult questions will inevitably arise, questions on which this country may have to express an opinion or be <Col N="501" /> obliged to vote should a specific matter be put before the Assembly. It is obvious that when such questions occur this country may have to take a decision one way or the other.  Some of these decisions might indeed involve us in conflict with some who have been old friends.  If such happens, it would indeed be regrettable but it might be unavoidable.</P>
    <P>These circumstances are, however, different from what would occur if we took action ourselves and which would result in disquiet in a country or countries which have traditional ties of friendship with Ireland.  That is why I believe our attitude on the admission of Red China was a mistake. This country should not take the initiative in a matter which involves us in avoidable conflict with friendly nations and in adopting an attitude alien to our traditions.  If the matter came before the Assembly because of its insertion on the agenda we could not prevent its being discussed, but taking a lead on the question is quite a different approach.</P>
    <P>It has been said that because national Parliaments discuss questions which at times may be embarrassing to the Government of the day, the same rule should apply at the United Nations.  There is, however, a vital difference between the United Nations and the deliberations of our Parliament or, for that matter, of the Parliament of any other Member State or country.  The spotlight of world-wide publicity is on the deliberations of the United Nations and the mere expression of an opinion may be interpreted as the foreign policy of the country concerned.  The same cannot be said of a debate in the Dáil where the repercussions are unlikely to secure the same publicity, and in any event such a debate could not be interpreted in the same way as an opinion expressed in the United Nations.</P>
    <P>The election of the permanent representative of this country to the Chairmanship of the Trustee Committee was a tribute to the qualities which we on all sides in this country know he possesses.  The efficient manner in which the deliberations of <Col N="502" /> that committee were carried out under his chairmanship is, in itself, a testimony to his capacity in guiding their deliberations during the last session.  I understand on other occasions the committee overran their allotted time-span, and on this occasion for the first time their deliberations were concluded a day or two earlier than was anticipated.  The fact that it was possible to achieve that result must, in itself, reflect credit on the manner in which our representative performed his duties.</P>
    <P>The part which small countries can play and the role which this country is peculiarly fitted to play have been referred to on many occasions.  Quite recently, when the former Premier of Iran spoke here reference was made to the unique opportunity which Ireland has of playing a role which not only reflects our own traditions but also enables us to act as a leading influence in guiding some other countries who have lately secured freedom. Many of those countries have secured liberty more recently than we have.  Quite a number of countries in Asia have in the past drawn inspiration from our struggle for freedom. They regard this country as being uncommitted and as being a country devoted to the ideals of peace based on justice, and a country which, because of our long struggle for religious and political freedom, is peculiarly fitted to play a constructive and a useful role in the United Nations.  We, therefore, have a responsibility to see not merely that our attitudes and policies reflect our own traditions, but that we measure up to the high standards which these countries expect from us and that we measure up to our responsibilities as I believe we can, as in our own domestic affairs, we have shown our capacity to work a democratic system.</P>
    <P>In considering this Estimate, it is essential, I believe, that we should dwell on the importance of having an agreed national policy for the reunification of the country.  On many occasions in the past, differences of opinion on this vital matter have prevented progress from being made, or have impeded efforts which were <Col N="503" /> being made to secure advances on the national front.  I have always held the view that the policy to be adopted on this question must be decided by the Government, who are responsible to the Dáil, and through the Dáil to the people.  While people may express impatience or dissatisfaction with what has been accomplished, the responsibility for deciding national policy can only be given to the Government and Parliament.</P>
    <P>It is vital, therefore, that all public opinion should be harnessed towards securing agreement on the national objective of reuniting the country.  The fact that up to the present progress has not been sufficiently fast, or that at times it would appear as though no progress at all were being made, is no justification for the attitude of those who say that the Government and Parliament are doing nothing about securing the unification of the country or that they are doing nothing to promote that objective.  Anything which promotes better understanding and brings a clearer appreciation to bear on the problems common to both parts of the country, and of the importance, from the point of view of the country as a whole, of having a single Parliament responsible to all sections of the people and promotes, however slowly and however imperceptibly, the reunification of the country, is to be commended.</P>
    <P>The measures which have been taken by various Governments since the establishment of the State give no justification for the attitude adopted by people who refuse to recognise the authority and the sovereign character of the Dáil and of the Parliament established here.  What we can do to hasten the end of Partition is a matter for decision by the majority of the people.  We must calmly and carefully analyse the problems and difficulties and we must apply ourselves to the task of thinking out clearly how they can be removed or minimised.  It is, therefore, vital from the national point of view that a great deal of the loose thinking on this matter and a great deal of the talk and the catchcries which in the past may have been emotionally satisfying, should now be <Col N="504" /> shown to be without any real foundation. The problem, however large or however difficult it may be, is to secure from all sections in this part of the country the recognition that responsibility for achieving unity must be tackled on a national basis and that that national responsibility for guiding policy devolves on whatever Government are in office, the Government, in turn, looking for support from the Dáil and the various other organs of the State.</P>
    <P>I should like to get from the Minister some idea as to what is happening in the Free Trade Area negotiations. As I understand it, the attitude of the Government is that we are endeavouring to secure an arrangement which will be acceptable to 17 member nations of the O.E.E.C. and that we are not greatly interested in the particular attitude which may be adopted by any of the smaller groupings. To that end, we have endeavoured to direct our energies towards securing the acceptance by the member States of an agreement on as wide a basis as possible.  There will be no objection, I think, to that attitude. While it is the ultimate objective, however, very energetic efforts by different groupings&mdash;both the six and the seven &mdash;are being made.  What we fear may occur is that, in our desire to secure an acceptable arrangement on as wide a basis as possible, we may lose sight of the importance of making a satisfactory bilateral trade arrangement with Britain.</P>
    <P>I do not want to stress unduly the importance of this matter, but there is now general recognition of the traditional policy of this Party that our trading with Britain is vital to our economy and that it is, therefore, essential to improve these trading arrangements whenever possible.  There is a danger that, because of the preoccupation with a European Free Trade Area and the lengthy discussions in regard to it, we may be lulled into a state where, because of our efforts to achieve agreement on as wide a basis as possible, we may neglect to safeguard our own vital interests by not improving our existing trading arrangements with Britain.  The fact <Col N="505" /> that a country from which we have had keen competition in the past&mdash; Denmark&mdash;has recently concluded an agreement on its own is important from our point of view and is a pointer indicating that we should bend all our energies towards endeavouring to improve our existing trade arrangements with Britain and, if necessary, to conclude a fresh agreement.</P>
    <P>In connection with our trading agreements with Continental countries, I have expressed the view before that most of these agreements have been in existence now for a number of years. Some of them were made by the present Government.  Others were entered into by the previous Government. A number have been renewed or re-negotiated as occasion warranted. In almost every case, we have a heavy adverse balance with these countries. It is time, therefore, to scrutinise these agreements carefully and exhaustively to see what changes are desirable and to consider what action can be taken to improve, if possible, trading balances with these countries.</P>
    <P>On many occasions our traders, exporting abroad, find that administrative and other difficulties are placed in their way.  While representations may secure the elimination of these discriminatory practices, or may modify the attitude adopted, we must remember that most of our exporters are small individual business concerns. The trader concerned has not available to him an elaborate organisation. If he is faced with administrative difficulties, or obstacles of some other nature, he may lose heart and may not pursue the matter further.  It is important from our point of view that we should examine carefully the entire situation.  These agreements have been in operation now for anything from ten years down.  We have had adequate time and experience in which to observe their working in practice and to see what difficulties exist.</P>
    <P>The Minister referred to the increased sum made available this year for cultural relations.  I should be glad if he would tell us, when he comes to reply, who are the present members of the Cultural Relations Committee and when they were appointed.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="506" /> I understand we have now no permanent delegate at Strasbourg.  I was urged on many occasions to appoint a permanent delegate there. On one occasion the somewhat impracticable suggestion was made that our delegate there could represent us in a number of European countries. I understand the present position is that we send out a delegate when occasion warrants.  We have ceased to have a permanent delegate there for some time.  I should be glad to know why the person appointed is no longer there permanently.  I should also be glad to know what change, if any, has taken place in the form of the work being done by the Council of Europe.</P>
    <P>Before concluding, I should like to express the satisfaction we all feel at the appointment of the new Nuncio to this country, Archbishop Ribieri.  He was here many years ago.  He has many friends in the country who recognise his great personal qualities as well as his devotion to, and interest in, the welfare of Ireland and the Irish people.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AnthonyCEsmonde" hpid="Sir Anthony Esmonde Sir Anthony Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Sir Anthony Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>This is becoming one of our most important Estimates.  Events which take place in the world, no matter where, must now have significance for Ireland, even though as a nation we represent a small section of the European community, as a whole, and of the world at large.  I welcome the fact that the Minister saw fit this year to give us a statement&mdash;a somewhat limited one admittedly&mdash;on foreign affairs as a whole.  I regret that he made no reference to the free trade negotiations which are taking place.  Perhaps he refrained out of deference to his Leader.  Perhaps his Leader will make an extensive statement to this House in the course of this debate.  I sincerely hope he will.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In his statement on international relations, the Minister confined his remarks principally to the Near East and to the suggestions he had made at the United Nations in reference to nuclear warfare.  I do not think anybody would take exception to any suggestions he has made with reference to the support he gave to President Eisenhower in the Near East or, <Col N="507" /> possibly, in his own resolution that he introduced at the United Nations in reference to nuclear warfare.</P>
    <P>The Minister said that by 37 votes to none his resolution went through the United Nations, but that there were 44 abstentions.  I should like to know from the Minister, when he is replying, if the 37 who were in agreement with his resolution comprised members of the so-called Iron Curtain group and, if they did, and if they were supporting his resolution by word or implication or in any way, if they gave any sort of guarantee that they would live up to the letter and law of the resolution, because I think the world is getting rather tired of empty statements made by this dictatorial and Communist group to the effect that they will support peace plans and anything that will restrict nuclear armament or rearmament as a whole.</P>
    <P>I should like the Minister to tell us also who the major abstentionists were and who the major group were who voted for his resolution.  It is probably true to say that nuclear armament would be confined to the bigger nations, that is, the nations who are actively concerned with it at the moment.  Its extension to smaller countries is restricted in that such nations have not the financial resources to do anything in that line.</P>
    <P>The Near East raises the problem that European colonialism as we knew it in the past is moving along.  It will no longer be the force that it was or remain as it has existed heretofore.  It seems to me that the line of argument we should take is that those countries that are under-developed and that are achieving their own national Governments, such as we achieved, and that are being allowed from now on to conduct their own affairs, are in an extremely fluid position.  They constitute what one might call the third force existing in the world to-day. There are the giants of the free world, and thank God for their existence. Thank God, that they are there to preserve for us the freedom that we cherish so much.</P>
    <P>There is the group on the other side <Col N="508" /> of the Iron Curtain who, in spite of their mealy-mouthed platitudes, have but one aim in life, that is, to enslave and victimise the world and to root out the foundations that we hold sacred, the Christian foundations on which our civilisation is based.  Then there is this third force that is becoming a new group in the world, a force that have not much for which to thank Europe except as far as Europe gave them the foundation of some form of culture.  In so far as we can influence the councils of other nations, our attitude should be that the free world should as far as possible give all the energy, resources, know-how, technical skill and financial aid at their disposal to enable these countries to build themselves up.  That is the only way by which we shall win back these countries to our side, to enable us to maintain our freedom against the unpleasant force that exists in the world to-day.  In its contributions, Ireland should stress that idea with all the force she can command.</P>
    <P>In my travels abroad I have noticed that, although we are not a powerful nation and do not seek to conquer anyone or to force our opinions on anyone, our advice is often accepted because we are regarded as a nation with an old tradition in its fight for freedom.  We are regarded as being fundamentally the most Christian nation in the world.  We are regarded as being on the perimeter of other nations so that we look at things detachedly and, therefore, have a clearer vision than would be the case of a country which might be directly concerned.  For that reason the office of Minister for External Affairs is one of the most important in the State at the present time.</P>
    <P>Before I leave that question, I should like to say that I do think that the attitude the Minister adopted some time ago in reference to the vote on Red China was unfortunate.  I like to be fair to the Minister.  I believe that what he actually voted for was misconstrued. I should like to put this point of view to the Minister, for his direction in future.  The communist persecution of the Christian Faith has changed in the last couple of years.  It <Col N="509" /> was found that direct persecution of Christianity and the prevention of religious services created resistance to the atheistic movement.  A far more sinister attitude was then adopted.  An effort was made to create confusion within the ranks of the Christian churches and to establish a communist-inspired national church.</P>
    <P>The greatest effort has been made in China.  Priests and bishops were cut off from their authority.  Confusion and discord were created.  It was impossible for people in jail and under house arrest to know what was going on. Therefore, I would suggest to the Minister that he should be careful in his utterances in future.  He may be sure that whatever he said in support of the case of Red China was allowed to filter through to those people who were fighting a lone battle, cut off from their authority, and that it was represented to them that Ireland, the country that, perhaps, has given more blood, tears and sacrifices to uphold our principles, was in some way sympathetic towards Red China.  That may not be true.</P>
    <P>As I said at the beginning, I want to be fair to the Minister but I want to put that point of view to him.  If he speaks on behalf of Ireland and if he gives any inch at all to that band of thugs&mdash;I can call them nothing else&mdash; they will misconstrue what he says and he will bring sorrow into the hearts of our faithful missionaries who are bringing Christianity to many parts of the world.  I shall pass from that now.</P>
    <P>The Minister for External Affairs is the Minister who makes our trade agreements.  Many of us who live in maritime counties and constituencies are considerably concerned with regard to our territorial limits.  I have endeavoured by Parliamentary Question and by speeches on other Estimates, on which I have been ruled out of order, to convey to the Government that conditions in regard to our territorial waters are in an extremely unsatisfactory state&mdash;as far as we are concerned, anyway, on the South-East coast of Ireland and I believe it to be the same in other parts of the country as well.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="510" /> I have tried to stress the point that I feel that unless we take action to extend our territorial waters we shall ruin the industry dependent on them. That state of affairs has become far more acute in the last couple of years than heretofore.  The Minister states he is introducing legislation to amend the base lines.  I should like to put it to the Minister that that does not really affect the issue one way or the other. It only means that the marauding trawlers or foreign trawlers will be pushed out a matter of a quarter of a mile, in the majority of instances.</P>
    <P>We have these rich influxes of fish off the Wexford and Waterford coasts. all down there.  We have had the greatest armada hanging about there, fattening on this return, in the past two seasons.  I understand that the United Nations are having a conference next February or March to discuss further the question of territorial waters.  They have already had two conferences.  My information, such as it is&mdash;which I believe to be correct&mdash;is that one group are pressing for a 12-mile territorial limit, another group are satisfied with six miles and that no agreement has been reached on that subject.  In the meantime, Ireland has a 3-mile territorial limit. Our waters are being fished and overfished and our spawning grounds are in serious danger.  I want to put it to the Minister that another fishing season will have come and gone before any further conference has taken place in regard to this vital matter.</P>
    <P>I want to ask the Minister if he can see his way to make a bilateral agreement. That is a topical subject nowadays. The Danes have made a bilateral agreement with the British with regard to their territorial waters.  The Danes are in the process of making a bilateral agreement with the British in regard to agricultural produce.  Why can we not try to make a bilateral agreement, even if it is only a temporary one, even if it will only tide us over the next season?  I should like the Minister to tell us if he thinks that is possible and, if it is, I urge him to act with all the expedition he can command.  Many people in this country are vitally concerned with the preservation <Col N="511" /> of their rights to obtain a livelihood.</P>
    <P>I have asked several Parliamentary Questions with regard to a trade agreement, but I have not yet succeeded in getting the information from the Minister concerned.  We have a trade agreement with Britain the duration of which is six months.  As I understand it, the agreement is terminable on notice by one side or the other.  Our trade is vitally concerned with Britain.  Let us have no illusions on the subject.  They stand to gain just as much from trade with us as we do from them.  <i>Per capita</i>, we are their best client in Europe and probably the world.  We are about to spend £10,000,000 on the eradication of bovine T.B.  If we spend that sum, what guarantee have we, after all the expense and all the labour, of a perpetuation of our trade agreement? True enough, it is complementary to both countries.</P>
    <P>I fail to see why we cannot have a long-term trade agreement.  The whole trouble in Ireland at the moment is the question of increasing production. If you increase production you must have a guarantee that you will be able to sell the produce.  To put it perfectly frankly, I do not trust the British as far as trade is concerned.  We have every reason to doubt their integrity in their trade relations with us over the past few years.  At the end of 1956 or early in 1957 there was a catastrophic fall in our livestock prices for the reason that the British were importing meat wholesale from the Argentine.  As a result, our farmers went to the markets and came home again unable to sell.  At the time, I suggested we might do something about it.  Perhaps it was not an opportune time to do that but now things seem to be different.</P>
    <P>At present, all the nations of Europe are negotiating with regard to a free trade agreement.  It is absolutely certain, come what may, that some form of free trade agreement will emerge in Europe.  The original common market, now known as the European Economic Association of the six nations concerned in it, was more or less scoffed <Col N="512" /> at by Britain, to start with.  The United Kingdom turned its back on Europe and took no interest.  We were behind them, on the other side, here, and we did nothing either.</P>
    <P>What happened then?  The economic community&mdash;Germany, France, Italy, the Benelux countries&mdash;came into being as a separate economic <i>bloc</i> in Europe. The United Kingdom was the only major power outside this <i>bloc.</i>  Then the British changed their tactics, largely due to heavy pressure which was brought to bear on them by the younger Conservative group within the present Party in power in the British House of Commons.  They became whole-hearted adherents of the free trade idea.  As the House knows, and as the Minister knows, these negotiations went on.  The present Taoiseach attended many conferences there on behalf of Ireland under the Maudling Committee, which came to nothing.</P>
    <P>The next move was that we had the Stockholm group coming together.  I confess I cannot understand the attitude of this Government.  Several nations are now negotiating to start another <i>bloc.</i>  The Taoiseach came into this House and in reply, I think, to a Parliamentary Question said that this did not really interest us, that we were dealing only with industry, that we had nothing to get out of it.  Surely it interests us?  If seven nations, one of them our principal rival in agriculture in Europe, are coming together to negotiate, and if Britain is one of the negotiating media, one of the prime movers in these negotiations, surely we have some interest in these negotiations?</P>
    <P>Even if we are not taking part in those negotiations is it beyond our power to send an observer there so that we might know what is going on? That was put very forcibly to the Government by several Deputies from the other side of the House and they did nothing about it.  However, the other day the Minister for Agriculture and the Minister for External Affairs hastened to London for what they called exploratory talks.  In other words they are beginning to see that we may be right, that something was going on there behind their backs, and <Col N="513" /> they went over to find out what it was. So far no statement has been made to Dáil Éireann on the subject.  We are no wiser than we were before.</P>
    <P>I should like to ask the Minister for External Affairs if he is endeavouring to make a new trade agreement with Britain?  Is he endeavouring to safeguard our interests and to see that any bilateral agreement that the United Kingdom makes does not in any way affect our trade which is vital not only to them but to us as well?  The Minister should give us some information on that subject.</P>
    <P>It does seem strange that in making a statement on foreign affairs the Minister did not refer to Partition. Probably there is not very much he can say on Partition but, occupying the important position he does, he should, when making an annual statement on foreign policy, refer to that question and make it clear to the House what his policy is on this all-important matter.</P>
    <P>That again brings us back to the Free Trade Area.  I myself cannot envisage any sort of free trade group coming into being in Europe&mdash;as I believe it ultimately will; I do not think anybody can gainsay that; we cannot like the ostrich stick our heads in the sand&mdash;without its being necessary for every nation that is complementary to that group to be economically powerful.  For that reason I believe that the European reaction as a whole to Partition will be that a small country like Ireland cannot afford two Governments.  The Minister should allow his mind to dwell on that because there is a ray of hope that out of the unification of Europe, which is vital for the preservation of the free world, may come the unification of Ireland.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFlanagan" hpid="Mr. S. Flanagan Mr. S. Flanagan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Flanagan</NameTxt>
      <P>Unfortunately I was not present when the Minister for External Affairs introduced this Estimate but I gather from the speeches already made that no reference was made to the negotiations at present going on about the formation of an Outer Seven.  I think it wise on the part of the Minister not to make any statement to the House at this stage <Col N="514" /> and I agree with the attitude taken by him that we should not be directly represented at the conference table in connection with this proposal.</P>
      <P>So long as the Free Trade Area negotiations were going on under the chairmanship of the British Minister we certainly had to be directly represented. Our interests were vitally involved, the more so because we are an undeveloped country.  It is a matter of regret that negotiations never materialised in anything workable. One can only deplore the emergence of smaller groups because they will lead towards division rather than unification in Europe and thus we shall be moving in a direction opposite to that envisaged when the Council of Europe was set up over ten years ago. It will be quite some time before these negotiations conclude and I feel the Minister should not make any very extensive statement on the matter at this delicate stage of the negotiations.</P>
      <P>In the course of his speech Deputy Sir Anthony Esmonde again referred to what the Minister for External Affairs said on the question of the admission of Red China to the United Nations.  I am not surprised that Deputy Esmonde did so but I very much regret it, and regret also the attitude taken by the Opposition both on this matter and on the matter of the attendance, for instance, of the Minister at receptions to members from countries which happened to be represented at the international conferences. In adopting that attitude I think that Fine Gael are doing a great disservice to the country.  It is most important that our people should be educated out of the insular attitude to which they are prone and into an understanding of the changed pattern of the world and the part that Ireland can, and ought, to play in it.  By their attitude following the Minister's first speech at the United Nations, Fine Gael did a disservice to the people by giving them a peg on which to hang a completely irrelevant and wrong attitude to what the Minister had said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy Esmonde, who made a very good speech, referred to the formation of what he called a national church in <Col N="515" /> China.  It is true that the Communists are attempting to set up a rival so-called Catholic Church organisation and that they have gone so far as to be able to get so-called bishops to officiate.  That is something fearful to think about just as the &ldquo;human ant&rdquo; movement which the Communists tried last year was something fearful to think about from another point of view. But surely it is primarily a matter for the Church to deal with this question and for us, as members of the Church, to take whatever kind of steps we can to deal with it, but I suggest that the steps we can and ought to take have nothing to do with our Parliamentary duty and nothing to do with the attitude the State should take in the United Nations on a political problem involving the free world.  Surely our attitude, as shown by the Minister, in the United Nations, if properly understood and explained and not misrepresented by mixing up religious with political issues in a false fashion, was a correct one.</P>
    <P>The Minister was at pains to point out that the people of Ireland are more opposed by nature and by conviction to Communism than, perhaps, any other country in the world and that no other country had a greater innate detestation of the Communist ideology than we had, but he then went on to deal with the political question and to give what he thought, as the representative of Ireland, was the right answer to the political issue involved.</P>
    <P>It would have been a great thing for the people of Ireland had the Opposition supported the Minister on that occasion.  Instead of doing so, they put down a motion of no confidence in the House and drummed up a lot of propaganda about the insults that we offered to the Catholic missionaries, including our own in China and elsewhere throughout the world.</P>
    <P>It was a heaven-sent opportunity for misrepresentation and it is a matter of great regret to me that the Opposition were so small-minded as to take it and were not big enough to support the Government because, had they done so, I think the rather unseemly debate that ensued in the papers here or, for <Col N="516" /> that matter, in newspapers as far away as America, would never have occurred and the Irish people would have been led along the right path, which is to think in terms of the peace of the world and of Ireland playing her full part in trying to ensure the peace of the world.</P>
    <P>It sounds very well to speak in indignant terms about the torture of the missionaries but it is irrelevant and it is unfair.  It is also doing a disservice to the people as a whole. I suppose it is too late now for the Opposition to change their attitude but I appeal to them to do so and to recognise that political problems should be dealt with on the evidence, always, of course, keeping in mind that we are firmly on one side in the ideological battle that is going on. Surely that does not have to be said. It should always be understood.</P>
    <P>There are a few smaller matters in respect of which I should like to get from the Minister an indication of developments.  Over the past few years, there has been considerable simplification of formalities for taking cars throughout the Continent.  The triptyque has been abolished in most of the countries on the mainland of Europe.  I think I have already pointed out that there was an enormous increase in the number of cars which went into Austria, which, I believe, was the first country to abolish the triptyque and the result of that was a rather dramatic increase in the number of tourist cars entering Austria.</P>
    <P>Although I think the position has been under review, I do not think that any final decision has been given regarding the attitude of this country to that question.  There are other considerations that apply to an island country which would have to be thought about.  I think the correct attitude would be for us to fall in line with the countries on the Continent of Europe and substitute for the car triptyque a simple form of identification such as has been in use in Austria and the other countries which followed Austria in this matter.</P>
    <P>As the Minister knows, the Council of Europe recently adopted a resolution regarding maintenance allowances <Col N="517" /> for children.  At the present time they are putting through a corollary to that. As the Minister also knows, this matter is of very considerable importance to this country because of the number of people who pass between this country and England and of the very great difficulties of enforcing an order obtained in one country against a person in another country.  The result is that great hardship is caused to the children involved.  Indeed, this problem is possibly of more importance in this country than in the other countries on the mainland of Europe. I hope the Minister will pursue this matter until such time as the necessary protection is available for these children and orders obtained in one country can be readily enforced in another so as to provide maintenance for children who are abandoned by their fathers.</P>
    <P>The broadcasts that have already been made from Radio Éireann in connection with the World Refugee Year have been very good.  I am sure the Minister was partly responsible for the fact that they were given.  We, as a country, should give every support we can towards providing funds in connection with these activities.  I believe that a film is to be made available as well.  If that is so and if it is available I hope arrangements will be made to have it shown in the various cinemas throughout the country because I believe it would have a greater impact than the broadcasts which have already taken place.</P>
    <P>One suggestion made was that a week should be set aside during which school children would be asked to contribute a penny a day and that the country could be organised on county lines.  These pennies, which many are willing to give, would be collected and the amount of money involved at the end of the week would be quite substantial. It is only one of various other suggestions put forward but I think that if we could put any idea into operation, it would help us to play our part in the activities of the World Refugee Year.</P>
    <P>Deputy Cosgrave mentioned that Ireland's permanent representative to Strasbourg is not at present living in Strasbourg but is commuting between <Col N="518" /> Dublin and Strasbourg.  I understand this was tried as an experiment because it was felt that the representative did not have enough duties in Strasbourg and could be better employed during off periods in the Department at his ordinary work.  I do not know what view the Minister takes about how that experiment has worked out; my own feeling is that the representative should be living in Strasbourg, if at all possible.  I should be glad if the Minister would let us know whether it is proposed to continue the present arrangement or to revert to the previous arrangement of having the representative actually living in Strasbourg.</P>
    <P>Another matter concerns the &ldquo;Aiken Nuclear Club&rdquo; proposal at U.N.O. which I understand now has the support of the Socialist Party in Britain.  I would be very doubtful as to whether the Minister can depend on the continued support of the British Labour Party on this proposal and I think I had better content myself by saying only that.  However, he and his colleagues deserve every congratulation for having put this proposal forward and indeed I do not think I should lose this opportunity of saying that Ireland, during the past couple of years, has played a notable part in the United Nations.  As Deputy Esmonde said, we have come to be recognised as an uncommitted country, neutral and fairminded, and have earned a great deal of respect from the parties in opposing camps because of that fact.</P>
    <P>To revert to what I said at the beginning, I think Deputy Esmonde and others of his Party should follow that line to its logical conclusion, particularly with regard to what the Minister said on the admission of Red China.  If we are to continue to be regarded as a neutral and fairminded country, it is essential that we should continue to make our proposals on a political basis because it is for that that the United Nations Organisation was founded, with the aim of world peace as its ultimate objective. We would be doing a great disservice if in any way we mixed up that aim with other aims, private or religious, <Col N="519" /> which we may have in life.  I would therefore appeal to Deputy Esmonde&mdash; whom I regard as a fairminded man&mdash; not to continue these speeches which I believe do harm rather than good and divide people on matters upon which they should be united; they mislead them in matters which they should understand and on which they are looking for guidance.  They can only look to us for guidance on the political level.  I do not think that we can say the Irish people are lacking in instruction from their religious leaders and we can safely leave it to those entrusted with the task of giving religious advice to guide the people on religious issues and I have no doubt they will do so.</P>
    <P>One recalls the hubbub created about the purchase of the Embassy in Paris and I am sure the Opposition will be glad to know that the premises then purchased is worth two or three times more than what it was at the time it was bought and represents a very excellent investment indeed.  The Irish representatives abroad have, during the past 12 months, done very well and I might safely conclude by expressing what I believe will be the feelings of everybody here, that is, that the best ambassador we had during that period was the former President, Mr. Seán T. O'Kelly, who did such a wonderful job when he toured the United States a few months ago.  I believe he deserves the best thanks of the people for his wonderful performance during that time.</P>
    <P>I congratulate the Minister again on the work he has done during the past 12 months and feel sure that he will continue on the lines he has taken so far with, I hope, greater co-operation from the people on the other side in the months ahead.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankSherwin" hpid="Mr. Sherwin Mr. Sherwin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherwin</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Esmonde mentioned that the Minister for External Affairs has nothing to say about Partition.  When the Italians were trying to unite their country, the man mainly responsible was Count Cavour. He stated that while he did not agree with force, nevertheless he turned a blind eye towards it because it maintained the passion for freedom.  He <Col N="520" /> was referring to Garibaldi and others. Likewise, even if we do not advocate such things as force, at least we should agree that we should shout loudly about it for the same purpose of maintaining that passion for freedom.  The Minister for External Affairs, however, cares to say nothing.</P>
      <P>In my opinion, it is the duty of the Minister for External Affairs to seek protection and security and power for his country and that is his main task. His job is largely a political one.  If he makes trade agreements, he does so merely on the instructions of others, such as the Minister for Industry and Commerce, and other matters are dealt with by junior officials.  His main job is political&mdash;the protection of his country and its advancement and if we have any political claims, his job is to try to get support for them so as to attain our objective.  The only objective, politically, that we have is the independence of our country.  I am not aware that we seek colonies or have any other political objective.  Our prime objective is to bring about the unity of our country.</P>
      <P>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Finance Bill," RHead="1959&mdash;Committee Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Finance Bill, 1959&mdash;Committee Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on amendment No. 9:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Before section 78 to insert the following new section:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Section 6 (1) of the Finance Act, 1946, is hereby amended by the addition after the word &ldquo;minerals&rdquo; where it first occurs, of the words &ldquo;or an open pit or open cast excavation made for the purpose of getting any of the minerals specified in the Schedule to the Finance (Profits of Certain Mines) (Temporary Relief from Taxation) Act, 1956&rdquo;.&mdash;(Gerard Sweetman.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>The four amendments in my name are all about minerals so I have no objection to discussing them together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Finance (Dr. Ryan) James Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>We might as well discuss them all together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="521" />
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we deal with the Bill itself I want to express my appreciation of the manner in which the Minister, at short notice, changed the time at which we were to take the Finance Bill in order to suit my convenience. It is evidence that when we do have a reasonable discussion on Bills we can get co-operation on both sides.</P>
      <P>Last night I had started dealing with the first amendment which I put down and, as we are going to take all four together, just for the record I might confirm that all deal with mining though, in fact, they cover separate points.  The Finance Act of 1946, in Section 6, provided methods by which the development costs of a mine&mdash;what might arise in the early years&mdash;could be spread over and set against the profits of the mine over later periods.  I think we are all agreed, on both sides of the House, that the provisions of Section 6 should be utilised to the fullest to make certain that as much as possible of our minerals are as fully developed as possible.</P>
      <P>When the Finance Act of 1946 was being enacted it was clear that what was visualised then&mdash;and I do not deny this in any way&mdash;was an underground mine, a mine by reason of a shaft being driven into the ground.  I do not think that here in Ireland at that time we had become as fully aware as we did later of the possibilities of open-cast mining which was carried on in England, particularly in the years immediately after the war and, indeed, during the war itself.  We were not at all as <i>au fait</i> with the possibilities of open-cast mining at that time as we became subsequently, and as we are now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Therefore, the effect of the definition in the Finance Act of 1946 of the word &ldquo;mine&rdquo;, as being an underground excavation made for the purpose of getting minerals, means that the benefits of the spread-over provided by that section are confined solely to the case in which you make a hole in the side of a mountain and then proceed to disembowel the mountain.  On the other hand, as the Finance Act of 1946 is now enacted and as it now governs the position, if you make a hole in <Col N="522" /> the top of the mountain and go downwards, excavating as you go, you are not covered by the spread-over provisions of the 1946 Act.  Equally, if you work into the side of a mountain, and remove your over-burden as you go, you are not entitled to the mine development allowance.</P>
    <P>I agree that underground excavation is a dearer type of excavation for our minerals than open-cast, open-pit mining, but that only effects the actual mining itself.  The amount of development work may be even far more heavy in open-cast mining.  One could visualise, for example, that if it were decided to get at the minerals in a particular mountain from the bottom and you drove a shaft right in, you would not have anything like the development work necessary on roads that you would have if you decided that the best way of getting the minerals was to go up to the top of the mountain, proceed to clear off the whole top, and work down from there. Quite apart from the development that there would be in road-building, it is quite inevitable that in such work there would be mountain river bridges to be erected and you would want, for that sort of work, heavier expenditure on plant and equipment than you would need for the actual underground excavation as such.</P>
    <P>There is also the question in open-cast mining that you have to pay compensation to surface owners for damage to the surface of their land. As the law now stands none of the ependiture on road building, on bridge building, on the additional plant and equipment that would be necessary, and the compensation to surface owners, can be allowed as a write-off against future production, and this is all treated entirely as a capital expenditure.</P>
    <P>Frankly, in the circumstances, I think that is not right and, even apart from the question of whether it is right or not, it certainly operates as a disincentive towards getting the minerals that are required.  I know the Revenue Commissioners as the statutory body have very strong views in relation to capital expenditure and the removal of over-burdenment.  I am <Col N="523" /> glad to say that recently in my professional capacity I had a small part in succeeding in persuading the Supreme Court to hold against them, but I know that decision is not in any way going to prejudice their statutory mind.  I do feel, however, that there is a very clear distinction between the type of sand and gravel quarrying, with which they are rather inclined to allow themselves to be influenced too much in relation to the general problems of mining, and that, therefore, it seems to me we should make an entirely different approach when we have minerals defined, in the way that they have been defined by the Oireachtas in the Finance (Profits of Certain Mines) (Temporary Relief from Taxation) Act, 1956.</P>
    <P>In the Schedule to that Act there are certain minerals that are described as scheduled minerals.  They are barytes, felspar, serpentinous marble, quartz rock, soapstone, ores of copper, ores of gold&mdash;if there are any&mdash;ores of iron, ores of lead, ores of manganese, of molybdenum, of silver, of sulphur and of zinc.  We are not therefore considering the question of minerals entirely <i>in vacuo</i> as to what are minerals, apart from dictionary definitions, as we were when the Act was being passed in 1946.  The Minister and the House will see that I quite deliberately restricted the benefit that I wished to give to open-pit or open-cast mines to the minerals that were defined in the 1956 Act, the list of which I have now read.</P>
    <P>It could well be that the effect of amendment 9 in my name would be materially to assist production and searching for minerals on the edge of the area Deputy Loughman represents, Silvermines, and in Wicklow and Avoca.  I do not know about other specific places personally but I believe that in Allihies in Cork the situation would similarly arise.  I have heard a suggestion that there are other areas in the country but the Silvermines company, of which I think Deputy Russell is chairman, and the Avoca one are two of the cases where the work of getting minerals is more <Col N="524" /> publicised and it is only because of that that I mention those two cases.</P>
    <P>I do not know whether there is, in fact, a clear case in relation to them or not.  I seem to remember something in the Government papers that I saw in relation to the development of Avoca that suggested there might be some reason to believe that there are minerals at the top of the mountain as well as at the bottom of it according to the Reports of Mianraí Teoranta.  I have not got those, and I am not quoting them as such.</P>
    <P>So much, therefore, for the first amendment that I have proposed. There is, I understand&mdash;but I do not know where it is&mdash;one specific case in the country.  The Minister may have the details of it.  I have not, because it was dealt with professionally and the details could not be disclosed to me, nor could I disclose them if I had them, which I have not.  I believe, however, there is one place where the winning of ore&mdash;if you like&mdash;has been abandoned because the mining development cost could not be covered by production.  So far as the actual cost of production was concerned, it would be a practical proposition to produce ore from that mine.  I do not even know which type of ore it is but I am told it is one of the ores specified in the Schedule of the 1956 Act.  The job of winning the ore would be possible and would show a profit but the job of mining development at the beginning&mdash;if it could not be set up as a production cost in the manner permitted by the 1956 Act&mdash;would not be economically possible.  We have not yet got sufficient figures in this House&mdash; the Minister may have them&mdash;to show the contribution mineral exploitation is making in 1959 to our balance of payments.  I have no doubt that by the end of the year the contribution made in that way will be quite substantial.</P>
    <P>I have already said I do not think there will be any difference between us in the House in our anxiety to ensure that our balance of payments problem should be relieved as far as possible by the winning of such minerals as are possessed by the State.  I should like to make it clear also that the spread that is provided <Col N="525" /> by the 1946 Act is one calculated to assist the best possible type of mining development.  If a person has to spend a great deal of money on underground or open-cast development, as I am now suggesting, and has to rely on getting that back from future production and on profits on a long term spread over basis, we shall then get in relation to that mining the maximum employment content and the maximum value to the national economy.  In such cases, you cannot have the quick in-and-out profit, the quick profit of development which might be otherwise visualised with open-cast mining.  It is not the facility in relation to open-cast mining as such that I am advocating but the spread-over or the permissibility to spread over initial cost.  It is that permissibility to spread cost that will mean that mines will be developed over a long-term period rather than a short-term one.</P>
    <P>The second amendment with which I am concerned is also in relation to the same section of the 1946 Act. Section 6 provides that any reference to certain things shall be excluded. Paragraph (c) excludes reference to any expenditure on the acquisition of the site of the mine or the site of any such works or of rights in or over any such site.  Clause (d), in the same way, excludes any spread over benefit being given to any expenditure on the acquisition of, or rights over, the deposits.</P>
    <P>The effect of that unduly restricts the spread over particularly because a lot of the work is often done before the actual trading concern comes into operation.  We must therefore consider the picture as it is not merely in relation to the company doing the actual mineral development but also in relation to how it started to find its deposits and to get its knowledge. We could not go on to consider that position without the deletion of these two clauses I have read out and amendment 10 is to that extent more or less necessary, consequential on amendments 11 and 12.</P>
    <P>I am concerned in relation to amendments 11 and 12, to make certain that changes in ownership as such will not mean that the <Col N="526" /> right to spread over the development costs will be lost.  There is a modern mining tendency and in this connection the Minister will pardon my saying that, when the negotiations for Avoca were under way, I had the necessity of looking pretty extensively into modern mining development tendencies everywhere.  Modern tendencies are towards the work of exploration and development being done not by the concern which finally does the trading.  It is only in an area where there are already proven minerals that it is likely that the trading concern as such will deal with the development work also.</P>
    <P>The effect of amendments 11 and 12 is not to provide that any additional expenditure will be allowed, that any new expenditure will be brought into the spread over allowance; but purely that the expenditure which has in fact been expended will be allowed as a spread over against production profits, notwithstanding by whom such expenditure had been incurred.  The capital development expenditure can be spread, under the Act of 1946, if it has all been incurred by the original trading company and provided that the original trading company was actually carrying on a trade at the time that the expenditure was incurred.  It is clear, however, that in relation to much of this development work, there would, in fact, be no trade then carried on.  What would be happening would be developing exploration and, in fact, there is not then a trade at all. If the effect of that was that the allowances could not later be spread over when the trade was commenced and established, it seems to me that it would be extremely unfair.</P>
    <P>Let us take a case in point, a completely abstract, theoretical case, but one which I think illustrates the position.  An exploration company is formed which goes into an area and explores all over that area and decides or discovers eventually that there is a certain amount of mineral wealth in relation to one of the minerals in the 1956 Act.  Having ascertained that it is there, it then exposes the face of the ore body.  Having done that valuable and essential work, the exploration company fades into the background <Col N="527" /> and a new company&mdash;a public company, perhaps&mdash;is then floated and formed for the purpose of carrying out the trade of working the mine.  The first company sells its rights to the second company, which I call the operating company.  It might sell them for a capital sum or for a rent.  I do not suggest for a moment that whatever profit that exploration company should make in its sale price should be allowed as a deduction in relation to the operating company's profits; but I do think that the money which had been actually expended by the exploration company on the ascertainment, development, exposing the face of the ore, etc., should be allowed to the new trading company.  If we are not going to do that, then I am afraid we will not succeed in having any prospecting carried out here.  Certainly, the prospecting which will be carried out will be limited to a very narrow degree.</P>
    <P>The exploration company sometimes may be precluded by its very nature from carrying on the trade of working the mine.  The fact that it is so excluded has also the effect of excluding the operating company from the benefit of the spread-over provisions of the Finance Act of 1946.  I would ask the Minister to look at this position from the broad view, that what we want to do is to get the maximum amount of minerals that we can extract from the ground, both as raw materials for our own industrial purposes and as a valuable form of exports.</P>
    <P>Finally, I might say that in relation to amendment 13, it seems to me that to do this, to make the amendments I have suggested, in the middle of what I might term the post-war mineral searching boom, would be injudicious and unwise.  Therefore, I think that we might fairly take the Finance Act of 1946 as being the commencement of that period and that we should cover&mdash; in so far as future years of assessment only are concerned and not, of course, anything about going back by way of repayment on existing assessments&mdash;in this amendment whatever has been done or is at the moment being done <Col N="528" /> while we are considering the Bill in the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>First of all, to go back to Section 6 of the Act of 1946, allowances on capital expenditure were provided in the section for the development of mines.  Development, I think, covered searching for or testing deposits, or winning access to them or constructing mines and mining works. These allowances were to be spread over a maximum of 20 years.  That section did not, as the Deputy pointed out, extend to expenditure on acquisition of the site or on rights over mineral deposits.</P>
      <P>The Deputy said there was a case that he was aware of&mdash;I must say I have not heard of it&mdash;where some work had been done on a mine in the way of development and where it had to be abandoned because no allowance could be made.  If that was recently, as the Deputy is aware, it would come under the 1956 Act and therefore the provisions of that Act would apply, that is, no tax for four years and only half tax for another four years.  At any rate, I did not hear of that case and I shall make inquiries to see if there is such a case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>In fact, looking at the note given to me, I now see that the word is &ldquo;cases&rdquo;&mdash;in the plural.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>This section is designed to secure that the allowances will over the years equal the relevant capital expenditure, less the amount represented by the residue, that is, the site and so on.  Having got that far in pointing out what the 1946 Act laid down, we come to amendment No. 9.  In this the Deputy urges that open-cast mining should be included in the case of non-bedded deposits.  At present open-cast mining is excluded, as far as they are concerned.  The 1956 Act applies to all mines and gives a relief of the full tax due for the first four years and of 50 per cent. for the next four years.  The Deputy's amendment covers only non-bedded minerals.  When I first looked at it, I thought no case could be made for excluding bedded minerals.  However, the Deputy has made such a case and I do not want to delay on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="529" /> Going back to the debate on the 1946 Act, I was rather impressed by the arguments put up, because this question of open-cast mining was raised.  The then Minister made what appeared to me to be a fairly good case against including open-cast mining. His case was that there was a very much bigger risk involved in making borings.  You were not sure whether or not you would strike a good bed of minerals, whether or not you would strike a substantial amount or whether or not they were easy to work.  In open-cast mining you did not take the same risk.  For that reason, the 1946 Act excluded open-cast mining.</P>
    <P>I should like to say a few words about all the amendments.  Amendment 10 is to delete paragraphs (c) and (d) of sub-section 1 of section 6. As the Deputy pointed out, these paragraphs exclude from relief expenditure on the acquisition of the site of the mine or the rights of that site and also the acquisition of rights over the deposits.  The Deputy thinks that these exclusions should now be deleted and that relief should be given for any expenditure on the site and on the rights over the deposits.</P>
    <P>The Act was designed to cover development expenditure and deliberately excludes the question of site and deposits.  The question is whether we should now consider removing these exclusions or not.  I believe it has been a very controversial subject in other countries.  In England, for instance, I understand the Deputy's suggestion was recommended by a Royal Commission but it was not adopted by Parliament.  The British case is not a good parallel to ours. In Britain, no other relief of any kind is given and in that event they were not in a position to consider it on the same basis as we would here.</P>
    <P>A case can be made for it, as the Deputy has done, but I think arguments can be advanced against it. Arguments such as we had here yesterday on another matter would apply to some extent.  For instance, if this concession were given, the owner of the mine would look for a better price from the buyer.  In that <Col N="530" /> case, the owner or vendor would reap an advantage in no way due to his own initiative, and there is no reason why the Dáil should confer that benefit on him.  If the amendment were to be adopted by the Dáil and if I, in turn, were to say: &ldquo;Let us take the tax off the vendor&rdquo;, that might not be welcome to the Dáil, either.  If it happened that by our action the value of the mine was increased, the purchaser might come to the conclusion that it would have been better if the Dáil had not dealt with the matter at all.</P>
    <P>Another point that arose yesterday was this.  If we relieve the purchaser of a certain tax and do not put a corresponding tax on the vendor, there is always a danger of collusion between the two which would lead to tax evasion.  That, as we agreed yesterday, could be avoided in some other way.  Under the existing law, if the owner of a property in which there are deposits leases the property to a person for a rent or a royalty, the person who takes the lease pays on his profits from the mine, if there are any, and of course deducts tax from his rent or royalty when paying that over. If the change is made and if he pays a lump sum, while he will be still liable to pay tax to the Revenue Commissioners, he will not have the opportunity of deducting tax from the person who leases either the rent or royalty to him.  It is a controversial subject and one that would require a great deal of thought before it could be agreed to.</P>
    <P>Section 6 deals with the case of a mine changing hands.  It is dealt with in very much the same way as we have dealt in this Bill with the changing ownership of a factory building&mdash;that the writing off of the factory building would still go on.  But, as the Deputy rightly pointed out, the section did not cover the case of a man who had spent a certain amount of money developing a mine but had not actually entered into production.  At least, it is doubtful if the section covered that.  In amendments 11 and 12 the Deputy seeks to cover that contingency by making it a continuous process, as it were, and the first man would now count as expenditure when the second man purchased the mine.  I think <Col N="531" /> these two amendments are right and should be implemented.  The Commissioners do not know of any such case where this has occurred.  I am not saying it should not be done; but for that reason, it is not urgent.</P>
    <P>Amendment 13 brings in cases in which operations may have started before this part of the Finance Bill was passed.  Having, as it were, given my views on this matter, I would put it this way to the Deputy, that I agree Nos. 11 and 12 must be done.  It is not urgent and it will be time enough to do them in the next Finance Bill because if a case should occur during the coming year, it could be worked into the provisions of the next Finance Bill.  It gives us time to review the whole thing and see, first of all, if these amendments which are consequential amendments are necessary and if there are any other odds and ends, they can be cleared up at the same time.</P>
    <P>As regards Nos. 9 and 10, I have no very strong views for or against them. If I were forced by a decision to vote, I would vote against them because I think there is not sufficient information to express an opinion in their favour. Therefore, in conclusion, I agree that Nos. 11, 12 and 13 should be dealt with in the next Finance Bill.  As regards Nos. 9 and 10, I shall give them further consideration and while, at the moment, I am not convinced that they are correct, I certainly have an open mind, and I am prepared to consider any arguments that may be put forward before the next Finance Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say that the Minister has met me very fairly but I understand there is some urgency about Nos. 11, 12 and 13.  I suggest they could easily be dealt with by leaving over the matter until Report Stage so that I could ascertain if there is any urgency.  So far as No. 10 is concerned, it was not an amendment that I was putting forward on its own legs but because I felt that if I did not introduce it as it was, the other amendments would be entirely inoperative.  It is more consequential.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="532" /> I know that when the Finance (Profits of Certain Mines) (Temporary Relief from Taxation) Act, 1956, was going through we had some discussions about this and frankly, I do not mind admitting I have learned a great deal more about mining in those discussions and in discussions I have had since that time.  I would ask the Minister to see if he can ascertain whether these cases have arisen where it is alleged that people were going to go into production and into the work of exploring and searching for and producing minerals but discovered because it was not possible to writeoff production costs or original costings, the whole venture was useless and was abandoned.  If there are such cases, and if I can get them brought by the persons concerned to the attention of the Minister, he might view the situation in a different way.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.  The Revenue Commissioners have no knowledge of such cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think they can have knowledge until it becomes a crystallised case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy will have to help me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall have to ask the persons who told me about it to help me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>On amendment No. 9 which Deputy Sweetman introduced, I should like to refer to the question of extending the tax benefits to open-cast or open-pit mining.  There is the other point that before you actually mine, you have to explore.  That is generally done by diamond drilling and it is only after that that you can decide what method you will adopt to extricate the ore from the deposit.  It is quite possible that a mining company might decide to adopt both methods; in other words, to open-cast up to a certain stage and then to mine in depth.  If that is so, they would be entitled to relief on one type of mining and not on the other.  Is that correct?  Does not that strengthen the case for this amendment, of applying that exemption to both the open-cast and the mining in depth.  They <Col N="533" /> can be, and very frequently are, a continuing process and, as Deputy Sweetman says, if you want to encourage mining, it would be a good thing if that were done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall give it full consideration anyway.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment 10 not moved?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it be possible for me to move these amendments and then to withdraw them so that they will appear on the records?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The position is that only one amendment has been before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>May I move the others <i>seriatim</i> and then withdraw them because I want them on the records?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy may, if it is agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 10:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before section 78 to insert the following new section:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Section 6 (1) of the Finance Act, 1946, is hereby amended by the deletion in the paragraph relating to references to capital expenditure incurred in connection with a mine of clauses (c) and (d) thereof.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 11:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before section 78 to insert the following new section:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Section 6 (12) (a) of the Finance Act, 1946, is hereby amended by the addition after the word &lsquo;mine&rsquo; where it thirdly occurs, of the words &lsquo;or would have been so granted had the original trader carried on the trade of working the mine&rsquo;.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 12:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="534" /> Before section 78 to insert the following new section:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Section 6 (12) (b) of the Finance Act, 1946, is hereby deleted and the following substituted therefor:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&lsquo;another person (in this subsection referred to as the successor) succeeds to the original trade or would have so succeeded had the person incurring the said capital expenditure been carrying on a trade&rsquo;.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 13:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before section 78 to insert the following new section:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Section 6 (12) (a) and (b) of the Finance Act, 1946, shall apply to expenditure incurred before as well as after the passing of this Act.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I wanted to move the amendments because otherwise they would not appear on the records.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments 14 and 16 are largely drafting amendments.  I can explain the changes on the Schedule.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what I was about to ask.  Wait until we come to the Schedule.  We shall deal with No. 14 now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 14:</P>
      <P>In subsection (2), page 52, to delete &ldquo;enactment&rdquo; in line 9 and substitute &ldquo;enactments&rdquo; and in lines 10 and 11 to delete &ldquo;have effect as on and from the 16th day of April&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;come into operation on the 1st day of August&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 78, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 79.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 79 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Was it on Section 79 or the Third Schedule that we decided to discuss the levies again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="535" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it was on the Schedule.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Just as the Minister prefers.  I thought that under the section which puts them in the care of the Revenue Commissioners, it might be more in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Very well.  I think this is rather complicated so I shall send the Deputy a copy in writing afterwards. Up to 16th April, certain articles of iron and steel were liable to an ordinary protective customs duty.  This duty had attached to it the ordinary licensing provision that applies to all protective duties.  Similar articles made of aluminium or aluminium alloy were not liable to any protective duty but were liable to a special import levy. The levies have attached to them only a limited licensing provision, operative only in the case of goods required for use in manufacture, as apart from consumer use.  There is a distinction there in that, in regard to goods subject to protective duty, a case could be made that even they should be imported free for consumers.  That could be done, but in the case of the levy they could be imported free of levy only for manufacturing purposes.</P>
      <P>The Department of Industry and Commerce had projects in train because some aluminium manufacturing businesses asked to have the aluminium levy transferred to a protective duty.  It was transferred over at the same rate&mdash;I mean, at the same rate of duty&mdash;and it was decided at the same time to re-enact the already existing duty on iron and steel goods and to extend its scope to the aluminium goods.</P>
      <P>Reference No. 3 gives effect to this. So far as iron and steel goods are concerned, the Reference reproduces the ordinary licensing provision that had always attached to these goods but, in the case of aluminium goods, there is provided only the limited licensing provision that had applied to them under the levy.  It is really perhaps an extension.  As I say, this is somewhat complicated and I shall send the Deputy a copy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Minister <Col N="536" /> will remember, when we were discussing this the other day I sent him over my marked copy of the neostyled Order.  Yesterday, I asked for it back. I got another marked copy back and it explains the situation perfectly. The Minister need not, therefore, bother to send me the Order.  Had I got my own copy back I should not have understood it.  I got that from somebody else marked with the cross in the right place.  I had put it in the wrong place.  It is quite clear now that the emphasis arises because it says that on all other articles these special manufacturing licensing provisions are not applicable.</P>
      <P>I should like to raise some other points in relation to the question of levy.  I shall not go into the general position in regard to levies or what part of the proceeds from them are being paid to capital account or balance of payments at all.  I have made my views on that known to the Minister.  I shall not repeat them now but I want to make it quite clear that, though I am not repeating them, I am not withdrawing them.  Rather, I hold them even more strongly as day follows day.</P>
      <P>One of the things at present chargeable under special import levies is sensitised photographic film.  In my view that is one of the first things that should have been discharged when there was to be relaxation of levies.  If I am correct&mdash;I use &ldquo;if&rdquo; deliberately &mdash;that photographic film for hospitals or for microfilming work in relation to libraries and so forth is excluded, and if I am correct in thinking that the type of photographic film material needed for photostat work for industrial business purposes still has to bear a levy, it seems to me to be quite wrong that such film should be subjected to levy. This film is not made here and there is no point whatever in keeping it still subject to levy.  The ordinary wide X-ray plate film is no longer subject to levy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not understand why electro-thermic and electro-mechanical appliances are still subject to levy when there is no element of protective duty involved.  In relation to electro-thermic appliances, thermostatic and regulative <Col N="537" /> control is involved.  If thermostats are not installed there will be excessive use of electricity.  That will not be of any great assistance to the national economy.</P>
    <P>I do not know whether or not the Minister is in a position, if I put down a question, to give me the amount of duty collected under each separate heading in relation to special import levy last year in so far as that levy is retained this year.  I am wondering whether or not we can get a breakdown of figures to see what the current special import levy list produced last year.  I do not expect the Minister to give me an estimate of what each reference number would produce this year.  If we can get what it produced last year, on the basis on which it is now in force, that will enable us to make an adequate comparison.  If it is possible to get that information, I shall put down a question to the Minister. That may shorten some of the discussion we might otherwise have, perhaps, on the Report Stage in relation to one of the sections.  Section 19, already discussed.  The general position in relation to levies is one we can discuss again.  I shall not waste the Minister's time discussing it now.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not give detailed information to the Deputy with regard to what the licensing provisions would be in relation to films.  Generally speaking, where films are used for X-ray and that sort of thing, they are free.  I should be very glad to give the Deputy the information he seeks.  I shall send it to him or, if he likes, he can ask a question.</P>
      <P>I am not sure whether the reference numbers are the same, but, when we were considering the list and trying to make some gesture by reducing levies, one of the considerations was that we would cut out those which were hardly worth collecting, those which only brought in an income of £500 or £1,000.  In that way we did get an estimate of the yield under each of the items and I can give the Deputy the information if he asks for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The original reason for bringing in electric appliances, and so forth, was <Col N="538" /> in order to bring the balance of payments position under control.  As I pointed out in my Budget speech, it is still necessary to keep some of the import levies in order to maintain a satisfactory balance of payments position. That is the only defence we can make for keeping the levies on certain articles not made here.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Thermostats should be excluded because they act as a regulator of consumption rather a boost to consumption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That can be considered.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 80.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 15:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To add to the section the following subsection:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(8) Any reference in this Act to any other enactment shall, except so far as the context otherwise requires, be construed as a reference to that enactment as amended by or under any other enactment, including this Act.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I think this is the amendment that covers the point I raised in relation to the 1920 Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is correct.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 80, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">FIRST SCHEDULE.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the First Schedule be the First Schedule to the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to the First Schedule, is this the amount that is added in respect of interest for the dealer in securities, who is not exempted?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  Section 7 deals with the dealer.  That is the first point. Sections 8 and 9 deal with charities, exempted companies and ordinary companies.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="539" /> SECOND SCHEDULE.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Second Schedule be the Second Schedule to the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>This deals with the agreement to prevent stripping on one side of the Irish Sea or the other.  The Second Schedule is to prevent dividend stripping being done across the Irish sea, either way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  Where our Act protects us against stripping, the British Act prevents them.  It is doubtful if the agreement is not over and above that and that, therefore, they could get around it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>The art or device of dividend stripping was not conceived at the time of the original agreement between the two countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">THIRD SCHEDULE.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Third Schedule be the Third Schedule to the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister prepared to state how much of the deficit on the quarter's accounts up to the 30th June, which he published the other day, is due to this change in the collection of duty on tobacco?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be nearly £2 million, I believe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>So that, if it is £1 million down, his revenue is £1 million up?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It more than makes up the deficit.  I mean, if we had collected the tobacco tax the same as last year, we would have a better revenue this year.  I do not know exactly the amount.  It is almost £2 million, I think.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the new system of importing crude oil to the refinery and collecting the revenue as excise, had any effect on the customs revenue?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Very little.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="540" /> FOURTH SCHEDULE.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 16:</P>
      <P>To delete Part I and substitute the following Part:</P>
      <P Just="Center">&ldquo;PART I.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="12*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="23*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Number and Year.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Short Title.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Extent of Repeal.</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 11 of 1928.</entry>
            <entry>Finance Act, 1928.</entry>
            <entry>Section 26.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 20 of 1932.</entry>
            <entry>Finance Act, 1932.</entry>
            <entry>Paragraph (b) of subsection (3) of section 25.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 15 of 1933.</entry>
            <entry>Finance Act, 1933.</entry>
            <entry>Section 19.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 31 of 1934.</entry>
            <entry>Finance Act, 1934.</entry>
            <entry>Section 20.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 28 of 1935.</entry>
            <entry>Finance Act, 1935.</entry>
            <entry>Section 25.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 31 of 1936.</entry>
            <entry>Finance Act, 1936.</entry>
            <entry>Section 12.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 25 of 1938.</entry>
            <entry>Finance Act, 1938.</entry>
            <entry>Paragraphs (a), (b) and (c) of subsection (1) and subsection (2) of section 22.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 18 of 1939.</entry>
            <entry>Finance Act, 1939.</entry>
            <entry>Section 17.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 18 of 1950.</entry>
            <entry>Finance Act, 1950.</entry>
            <entry>Section 7.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 21 of 1953.</entry>
            <entry>Finance Act, 1953.</entry>
            <entry>Section 5.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 22 of 1956.</entry>
            <entry>Finance Act, 1956.</entry>
            <entry>Section 18.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>I promised to give some details here, a Leas-Cheann Comhairle.  I shall take them in order as given here: Finance Act, 1928, Section 26&mdash; exemption for horse racing; Finance Act, 1932&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Why is that being deleted?  What does it mean?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>All sports are now gone, so it is no longer necessary to have this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="541" />
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>These are all entertainments duty, are they?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, they are all entertainments duty.  I resume the list: Finance Act, 1932&mdash;exemption for outdoor sports promoted by G.A.A. or N.A.C.A.; Finance Act, 1933, Section 19&mdash;repayment concession for greyhound racing in rural areas and exemptions for amateur boxing, badminton, international lawn tennis, swimming and rowing; Finance Act, 1934, Section 20&mdash;general exemption for outdoor sports; Finance Act, 1935, Section 25 &mdash;amendment of Section 19, Finance Act, 1933, which is being repealed; Finance Act, 1936, Section 12&mdash;exemptions for fencing and table tennis; Finance Act, 1938&mdash;exemptions for billiards, chess and squash rackets; and then there was an amendment of Section 20 of the Finance Act, 1934, which is being repealed: Finance Act, 1939, Section 17&mdash;exemption for bridge; Finance Act, 1950, Section 7 &mdash;amateur wrestling was removed at that time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Only amateur, though.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Only amateur.  Finance Act, 1953, Section 5&mdash;exemptions for basketball and cycle roller racing and Finance Act, 1957, Section 18&mdash;amendment of Section 19, Finance Act, 1933, which is being repealed.</P>
      <P>Deputies will see that the thing was being done piecemeal over the years and there was practically nothing left at this stage, so the general relief on all outdoor sports and indoor sports was brought in to finish the job.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: That the Fourth Schedule, as amended, be the Fourth Schedule to the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I understand, the amendment only covered Part I of the Fourth Schedule.  Is not that so?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  The rest remain as they were.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister <Col N="542" /> tell us, for the record, what the purpose of each repeal is in Parts II and III?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>In Part II, the first&mdash; the Stamp Act&mdash;arises out of the change in marine insurance.  They are all purely consequential.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>They are an purely consequential?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>That is all right. In Part III are they purely consequential?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, consequential on the provisions of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported with amendments.</P>
      <P>Report Stage ordered for Wednesday, 8th July, 1959.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Estimates" RHead="for Public Services, 1959-60">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Estimates for Public Services, 1959-60.</Title>
    <P>The Dáil, according to order, went into Committee on Finance and resumed consideration of Estimates for Public Services for the year ending 31st March, 1960.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Vote" RHead="59&mdash;External Affairs (Resumed)">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Vote 59&mdash;External Affairs (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;That the Estimate be referred back for reconsideration.&rdquo;&mdash;(Deputy Cosgrave).</P>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Sherwin was in possession.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Will you let Deputy Sherwin in, if he comes in later on?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>No; it is not customary, when the Deputy is not in his seat on resumption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>He only drew breath and convenienced the Minister.  However, he can argue that out with you when he comes in, I suppose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is a welcome development that the Minister has at least made some <Col N="543" /> gesture, however limited, to indicate his views on foreign policy, for the first time in three years, but there are certain matters relative to foreign policy in general which I should like to bring before the House.  I do not think I am wrong in believing that the fundamental purpose of diplomacy is to serve the vital interests of Ireland, in so far as our Minister for External Affairs carries on diplomatic activities at the United Nations or anywhere else.  If we lose sight of that fundamental fact, our diplomacy is liable to lose itself in a maze of good intentions, oblivious of the fact that good intentions constitute the pavement to hell. There is only one sound sheet anchor for the Minister to cling to in his diplomatic activities and that is, does this answer the vital interest of Ireland? It is important to realise that the language of diplomacy is founded on the universal assumption that the Foreign Ministers of countries attend international gatherings or represent their countries abroad for the purpose of defending the vital interests of their own countries and that the language employed by them in the course of that work is interpreted in the light of that assumption by other diplomats or other Foreign Ministers with whom they are engaged in controversy or discussion. I cannot help feeling that the activities of our Minister for External Affairs, especially at the United Nations, seem to be wholly divorced from that fundamental assumption.</P>
    <P>It is not always what you say that matters.  It is the way you say it.  It is when you say it and it is to whom you say it that may be very important.  I think that what has been said by our Minister for External Affairs at the United Nations (1) in respect of the question of the admission of Communist China to the United Nations being placed upon the agenda; (2) his quasi-Rapacki plan for disengagement in Middle Europe and (3) his current proposal in regard to what he describes as the &ldquo;Atomic Club&rdquo; are all resulting in discomfiture for our friends and gratification for our natural enemies.</P>
    <P>It is no use for the Minister to say <Col N="544" /> in effect: &ldquo;All I meant was that we would put the question of the admission of Red China on the Agenda and when it was there, God knows what I would say but those of you who know me can pretty fairly guess what I was likely to say on such an occasion.&rdquo; The fact is that the Minister found himself aligned with all those opposed to democracy and freedom and in opposition to all those who believe in the things in which we believe.</P>
    <P>The Minister gave bitter offence to the American people who ordinarily have been our traditional friends and, as Deputy Esmonde stated here today, he apparently entirely overlooked the fact that in respect of a very large part of the world's surface, there is no means of communication for the dissemination of news except the Communist-controlled radio.  Throughout a whole vast area where persecution was rampant in China, there was disseminated the news that the representative of Ireland had aligned himself at the United Nations, as they may have tendentiously put it, on the side of giving consideration to the admission of Red China to the United Nations.</P>
    <P>What vital interest of Ireland is served by voting for the inclusion of that item on the Agenda of the United Nations?  When Deputy Cosgrave was Minister for External Affairs, that matter came up.  I think he said, with perfect propriety, on that occasion that at some date this matter might come on the Agenda but certainly Ireland would not take the initiative in precipitating that event.  On the occasion on which Deputy Cosgrave was speaking as the Irish Minister for External Affairs, he adverted to the fact that the United States of America and others were not prepared to include this matter on the Agenda at the present time and that so far as he was concerned he was not prepared to go against them, though he was quite conscious of the fact that the march of events might result in this item turning up at some future date, in which event he would be prepared to deal with it, if he were so charged.</P>
    <P>Deputy Cosgrave's successor, the <Col N="545" /> Minister for External Affairs, Deputy Aiken, rushes into the affray and says he feels he has a high duty to insist that this item forthwith be placed on the Agenda.  What vital interest of Ireland was served by that?  It exasperated and enraged our friends and provided our traditional enemy with material with which they were able to discomfit and dismay millions of people suffering persecution who had no source of information other than the possible distortion which was made possible, in my judgment, by the indiscretion of our Minister who should have foreseen the capacity of international Communism to use his position for any misrepresentation which they thought would serve their basic purpose of discomfiting and discouraging those who are holding out against that particular form of tyranny that Communism is concerned to impose on the countries they conquer.</P>
    <P>To me, the greatest element of error in our Minister's decision on that occasion was gratuitously to do something which was in no way necessary for the vital interests of this country and which caused consternation, dismay and humiliation amongst a vast section of the best friends we have in the United States of America.  I have never yet heard from the Minister any genuine justification for that, except the implication on one occasion that he wanted to establish the fact that he was following an independent line at the United Nations and was not subject to dictation or direction from anybody. That is a deplorable occupation for our Minister for External Affairs to be engaged in.</P>
    <P>I do not think it was ever necessary for Deputy Cosgrave when he was representing this country at the United Nations to swagger up and down the corridors announcing that he was an independent man.  I do not think he ever had to go to the rostrum there and declare that he was not a paid hireling.  He was received there as a representative of an independent State charged faithfully to carry out the instructions of the Government he represented.  He was quite prepared and well-equipped to speak on behalf of this country.  He was never put upon his proof that he was anything <Col N="546" /> but the independent representative of a sovereign Government, a co-equal member of the United Nations.  It is that cracked obsession of our Minister that he has perennially to give a demonstration of his independence at the United Nations Headquarters at New York that betrays him into some of the foolish activities in which he is engaged.</P>
    <P>If I am correct and I think I am&mdash;I do not think I am being unduly harsh &mdash;we begin by carrying consternation and dismay into the hearts of our friends in America.  Our next stage is the quasi-Rapacki Plan.  Here we are on the fringe of Europe and the Atlantic Ocean.  We have never taken any part in any European conflict&mdash; we have declared our firm intention not to&mdash;but we take the initiative to propose a plan to require the troops representative of N.A.T.O. to undertake substantial withdrawals from vital parts of Europe.  We know or we ought to know that the Administration of Chancellor Adenauer in Bonn is passionately opposed to that course.</P>
    <P>It will be appreciated that, in so far as this country has any Continental relations, they should be cordial with those of the Government of Bonn but it appears to me that for no other reason than to show off the strategic equipment of our Minister for External Affairs we start throwing our weight about in regard to the disposition of N.A.T.O. troops in Europe which causes a Government which I believe is well disposed for various reasons to this country and to which we certainly ought to be well disposed, the utmost possible annoyance, confusion and dismay.</P>
    <P>Is there rhyme or reason in doing a thing like that?  I cannot understand it.  It may be just as embarrassing to the Minister for External Affairs as it is to me that the substance of this plan is associated in the minds of most people who are interested in this matter with the Rapacki Plan and the Rapacki Plan was conceived in Warsaw and is greatly beloved of Mr. Khrushchev who thinks it is just wonderful and who thinks that Adenauer is a cranky old rascal that he will not fall in with it, that <Col N="547" /> Adenauer does not want peace and that Mr. Khrushchev has come to the conclusion that he is the nigger in the woodpile and wants to keep the cold war going.  In fact we discover that the Rapacki Plan is a powerful propaganda instrument in the hands of Mr. Khrushchev for the purpose of misrepresenting the Christian Democratic Government of the Federal Republic of Western Germany.</P>
    <P>Nobody is in the least interested in the Aiken Plan but inasmuch as it corresponds pretty closely to the Rapacki Plan, it is represented that if this issue ever comes to be determined at the United Nations our Minister for External Affairs is closer to Rapacki than he is to Adenauer. What vital interest of Ireland is served by representing this country as being in much closer understanding with Mr. Rapacki than it is with Mr. Adenauer?  I certainly do not feel nearer the mind of Mr. Rapacki than I do to the mind of Chancellor Adenauer.  I doubt if any Deputy here does and I doubt if anybody would wish to be so represented in the world.  What vital interest of Ireland is served by getting embroiled in this way on the wrong side?</P>
    <P>The only vital interest that confronts this country in that sphere is that there are 200,000,000 Russians and 600,000,000 Chinese and, if some control is not kept on that horde, Christian civilization as we understand it will be overrun and trampled underfoot.  That is the only vital interest we have in European politics at the present time and that there should be maintained between us and that horde, which is disciplined, orgainsed and resolved to wipe out Christian civilization, an effective screen which would preserve us and our other neighbours who survive in freedom with the prospect of continuing in the enjoyment of the freedom we now have.</P>
    <P>If that is a correct assessment of the fundamental, vital interest of Ireland in European politics, how are these interests served by our Minister for External Affairs appearing to say 12 months ago that he is in favour of restricting <Col N="548" /> control of atomic weapons to the United States, Great Britain, Russia and France and of now announcing that he intends to introduce a resolution into the United Nations the effect of which appears to me to be to exclude France from that control and to restrict control of atomic weapons to Great Britain, the United States and Russia as being the only nations at present in control of such armaments?</P>
    <P>I am not prepared to argue and I am not equipped to argue the rights and the wrongs of whether France should be recognised as eligible for similar atomic status with the United States, Russia and Great Britain, but France has always tried to show us consideration, respect and friendship. At this most crucial moment when we have every reason to believe that the Government of France attaches supreme importance to the recognition of its right to be on atomic equality with the other three Great Powers, why should Ireland take the initiative in proclaiming we think she is not?  What do we know about it?  Why should we take the initiative&mdash;I do not think I use too strong a phrase&mdash;in slapping General de Gaulle across the face?</P>
    <P>It may be that if the United States or if Britain or Russia brought the question before the United Nations as to whether steps should be taken to prevent France having the atomic bomb, we would have to consider our position in regard to that.  I would be prepared to argue that strongly, but I do not think it falls to be argued here.  All I am asking is: what vital interest of Ireland is served by our appearing to take an initiative which cannot but be offensive to the Government of France?  That continued childish meddling in order to show what busy bees we are in the United Nations is causing this country very serious loss, loss of a much more significant kind than anything that can be measured in terms of pounds, shillings and pence.  We are manoeuvring ourselves into the postion of being looked upon as that kind of a friend on whom nobody can depend.</P>
    <P>Progress reported: Committee to sit again.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions." RHead="Oral Answers. - Dublin Arrests">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Dublin Arrests.</Title>
    <Col N="549" />
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Justice if he will state (1) the number of persons taken into custody by the Gardaí and brought to College Street Garda Station on the night of 15th June, 1959; and (2) what charges are being brought by the Gardaí against these persons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Traynor) Oscar Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Traynor)</NameTxt>
      <P>The number of persons brought in custody to the Garda station was fourteen.  Only two have been charged, one with assault and obstruction of a member of the Garda Síochána, the other with obstruction of a member of the Garda Síochána and conduct calculated to lead to a breach of the peace.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that some of these people were provoked by the Guards by pushing these people against other Guards and that these Guards treated the civilians as if they had attacked the Guards? Was that made known to the Minister?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no foundation whatever for the statement the Deputy has made.  This was an organised group of people&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order. May I suggest that if people are on charge it is not appropriate for the Minister for Justice&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>They have been tried. One person has been found guilty.  In the other the individual was remanded by the District Justice to see how he would conduct himself for the time being.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister allow me?  If people are on charge, matters in connection with which they are charged should not be raised here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBoland" hpid="Mr. G. Boland Mr. G. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>Why put it on the Order Paper so, Sir?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Are these people on charge?  If there are people on charge&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="550" />
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>This has nothing to do with the charges, Sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It surely has something to do with the charges.  If there are people on charge this question should not be pursued.  Anything that would prejudice the hearing of the case should not be raised here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>What I am going to ask will not prejudice the hearing of the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Are they on charge? What does the Minister say?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I tried to give an explanation which was ruled out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Are they on charge?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I have made a statement. When questioned by the Chair, I cannot proceed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The only thing the Chair questioned was whether the people are on charge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>The position as I know it is that one of these persons was charged and found guilty.  The other was remanded by the District Justice for the purpose merely of seeing how he would conduct himself in the interval.  Whether he is technically still on charge is a matter of debate. Can I proceed any further on that? My only interest naturally was in the charge the Deputy made against the Gardaí.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The matter should be left for the courts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>What I wanted to say to the Minister now would not have anything to do with the people who are charged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely if it has not anything to do with the people who are charged it is not relevant?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be relevant. I want to ask&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Nothing should be said here, under the protection of the House, which would be likely to interfere with the course of justice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="551" />
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>What I have to say, Sir, will not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>What you said so far had a lot to do with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>If a Guard interfered to establish order at a Fine Gael meeting would he be sent to a bog station? The Minister for Defence would know where to send him.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers. -" RHead="Cork Bovine Tuberculosis Eradication Scheme">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Cork Bovine Tuberculosis Eradication Scheme.</Title>
    <P>2.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJohnCorry" hpid="Mr. Corry Mr. Corry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corry</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he has received proposals from the Cork County Bovine Tuberculosis Eradication Committee for the speeding up of the eradication scheme in the county; and what decision he made in the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Minister for Local Government (Mr. Blaney) (for the Minister for Agriculture) Neil T. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government (Mr. Blaney) (for the Minister for Agriculture)</NameTxt>
      <P>I recently received proposals from this Committee and they are at present being considered.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Rise in Price of Leather">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Rise in Price of Leather.</Title>
    <P>3.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he will state the reason for the recent substantial rise in the price of leather to shoe makers and boot repairers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. J. Lynch) Jack Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. J. Lynch)</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the increased price of leather is attributable to an increased demand for hides in world markets and a consequential increase in the price of hides.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister not take steps to endeavour to control the price of leather in view of the fact that people who buy leather for the purpose of repairing boots and shoes are usually men in a small way of business and that the people who usually send their boots and shoes for repair to them are poor people?  This is another addition to the cost of living. I think the Minister should take steps to control the price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not a question.  It is a statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Drainage of Roscommon River">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Drainage of Roscommon River.</Title>
    <Col N="552" />
    <P>4.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government whether in connection with his statement of the 10th June regarding the clearing off of works carried out under the Local Authorities (Works) Act, 1949, he will consider making funds available for the completion of the drainage of the Crannagh river, County Roscommon, in order that the flooding caused by its present partly drained condition may be overcome.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>The reference in question related to a token provision to enable outstanding accounts arising from works undertaken in previous years to be cleared off.  It does not provide for grants for further drainage schemes.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Ballycotton (Cork) Housing Scheme">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Ballycotton (Cork) Housing Scheme.</Title>
    <P>5.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJohnCorry" hpid="Mr. Corry Mr. Corry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corry</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if he will state the reason for the delay in sanctioning the Ballycotton housing scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>Approval issued to the acceptance by Cork County Council of a tender for the erection of four serviced cottages at Ballycotton within six weeks after receipt of the proposal. There was no avoidable delay in dealing with the proposal which, I am glad to say, shows a considerable reduction in normal house construction costs.  Special features of construction and finish were provided for, in the contract for these houses, on the lines adopted in the case of the recently completed houses at Ringaskiddy.  A final inspection of the latter scheme was carried out before the Ballycotton tender was approved.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - New Road to Whitegate (Cork)">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - New Road to Whitegate (Cork).</Title>
    <P>6.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJohnCorry" hpid="Mr. Corry Mr. Corry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corry</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if he has received plans for a suggested new road to Whitegate which would by-pass Midleton; and if in view of the alarm caused in Midleton by such suggested by-passing, a copy of the proposed plans will be sent to Midleton Urban Council before any decision is come to in this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="553" />
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>I have received no such plans.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Collins Commemoration Ceremony">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Collins Commemoration Ceremony.</Title>
    <P>7.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Mr. O'Sullivan Mr. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will permit the National Army to pay honour to the founder and first Commander-in-Chief of the Army, General Michael Collins, at the annual commemoration ceremony at Béal-na-Bláth on 23rd August, 1959.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. K. Boland) Kevin Boland">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. K. Boland)</NameTxt>
      <P>As I stated in An Dáil on 30th October, 1957, in order to avoid the difficulties involved in selecting individual anniversaries in commemorating which the State might participate, a special day, Easter Sunday, has been set apart on which the State celebrates the securing of independence and honours all who took part in the struggle to achieve it.  This is, of course, apart from the annual State commemoration at Arbour Hill for those who died in 1916.</P>
      <P>I am still of opinion that that arrangement is the appropriate one and accordingly it is not proposed that the Army should officially participate in the ceremony referred to in the Deputy's question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister state whether the Army takes any part in the Wolfe Tone ceremonies?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is another matter surely.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not think so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>The Army takes part in a special celebration at the Wolfe Tone grave.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The commemoration at Béal-na-Bláth would not be considered to be in the same line, I suppose, as the one at Bodenstown?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>Obviously it is completely different.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Put that on record. They will unite the people of Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Appropriation Accounts, 1957-58. -" RHead="Report of Committee of Public Accounts">
    <Title>Appropriation Accounts, 1957-58. - Report of Committee of Public Accounts.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="554" /> That the Report do lie upon the Table; and that the Report, with the Proceedings, Minutes of Evidence and Appendices in connection therewith, be printed.</P>
    <P>Agreed and ordered accordingly.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Appropriation Accounts, 1957-58. -" RHead="Estimates for Public Services, 1959-60">
    <Title>Appropriation Accounts, 1957-58. - Estimates for Public Services, 1959-60.</Title>
    <P>The Dáil, according to order, went into Committee on Finance and resumed consideration of Estimates for Public Services for the year ending 31st March, 1960.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Vote" RHead="59&mdash;External Affairs (Resumed)">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Vote 59&mdash;External Affairs (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;That the Estimate be referred back for reconsideration.&rdquo;&mdash;(Deputy Cosgrave.)</P>
    <P>
      <i>Deputy Dillon rose.</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankSherwin" hpid="Mr. Sherwin Mr. Sherwin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherwin</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order. I was speaking when the debate adjourned.  I waited for an hour.  I have come back now but will I be allowed to speak again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>When all the other Deputies who wish to speak on External Affairs have spoken.  The Deputy did not wait over to take his turn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankSherwin" hpid="Mr. Sherwin Mr. Sherwin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherwin</NameTxt>
      <P>I waited a long time, Sir.  Am I out now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is not out. I think it should be put on record that we waited and dallied for Deputy Sherwin but we got a qualified undertaking that he would be let in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankSherwin" hpid="Mr. Sherwin Mr. Sherwin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherwin</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we adjourned I expressed apprehension lest our general course of conduct in the United Nations would earn for us the reputation of being a friend on whom no one could depend.  No one is more detestable in human relations than the person who describes himself <Col N="555" /> as your frank friend because he is the person who, when you do not want him, bores you with his continued attention, but when the time of difficulty arises, he is the first to bring the stiletto stealing down his sleeve to stab you in the back.  It is reasonable in international relations to recognise our friends and to expect this much at least of them&mdash;that where no vital interest of a friend is involved, that friend can be depended upon to lend one a hand where one's own vital interest is involved, on the clear understanding that if any situation arises in which the vital interests of oneself and those of one's friends clash, there will be a full and fair understanding and agreement that in those circumstances there must be a temporary parting and that there is no misunderstanding and no ill will.</P>
      <P>It is straining friendship beyond the limits which we can reasonably rest upon if we claim, whenever the vital interests of one of our friends is involved, that even though it is a matter of relative indifference to this country, our friends may find us aligned against them for no better reason than that we want to demonstrate to the world that we are not the bond slaves of our friends.  I am afraid that is what is happening in our foreign relations.  I have pointed out on more than one occasion, and do so again, that in the very limited sphere where I attended on behalf of the Irish Government, and on occasions had instructions to act on behalf of our Government in opposition to the Government of the United States, so complete was the understanding of enduring friendship between ourselves and them, I had no difficulty whatever in explaining our position to the representatives of the United States and finding in them a full understanding and a ready recognition of our right and duty to part with them in the special circumstances, on the clear understanding that once that issue was determined our cordial relations and mutual confidence would continue to obtain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is quite illusory and quite false to imply, as I am afraid I must charge <Col N="556" /> the Minister and the ex-Taoiseach with implying in this House, that unless you throw your weight about perennially, you are bound to accept the position of a satellite of one of the Great Powers which is inconsistent with the position of Ireland.  That is not true. If we were associated with Russia or China, that would be true, but it has never been the case, certainly in my limited experience and I believe in the experience of my colleagues, that cooperation with the great democracies has involved any such relationship whatever.  It does involve and should involve obligations.  There should be a reciprocal obligation and where the vital interest of one of us is not involved and the vital interest of the other is, that other country is entitled to expect to find you on its side.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LionelBooth" hpid="Mr. Booth Mr. Booth">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Booth</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the vital interest of America that is at stake?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Once America made it a matter of substance that she strenuously objected at that stage to the inclusion on the Agenda of the United Nations of the question of the admission of Red China to the United Nations and once she had taken up that position, then her vital interest was at stake because she was involved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LionelBooth" hpid="Mr. Booth Mr. Booth">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Booth</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the position now.  That is the difficulty we are in, and that is the attitude which we should try to correct.  We think it a desirable thing and an admirable thing in those circumstances to say to Mr. Dulles&mdash;the Lord have mercy on him&mdash;&ldquo;You think your interests are involved but you are quite mistaken. Take that box on the ear and go away and remember that Mr. Aiken, our Minister for External Affairs, really knows what your vital interests are and he will put you right.  Now, when your face is red after that blow, you will be wiser next time.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think that is wrong.  In the event of Mr. Dulles' stand on that or any other issue conflicting with the vital interests of Ireland we could, without any trouble, go to the American Secretary of State, whoever he might be, and say: &ldquo;Look, we understand <Col N="557" /> your interest in this.  We appreciate it but we think you will understand our interests and it is just as fundamental to us as it is to you.  We should like to be on your side, as we are on most other things but, in the special circumstances, we must differ on this occasion.&rdquo;  I think the American Secretary of State, or indeed the British Foreign Secretary, would fully understand our position.  What is resented, and legitimately resented, is that where the American Secretary of State says: &ldquo;This is a vital interest to us,&rdquo; we take it upon ourselves to say &ldquo;Oh, no, you are quite mistaken. Go away, you are annoying us.  We think you are being obscurantist and silly and mulish; we take the view that Bulgaria is right.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The American Secretary of State may well say: &ldquo;You are too stupid to see that this is a sinister move on behalf of a satellite of the Kremlin to deal a serious and injurious blow at our prestige, at a time when it is vital that that should be maintained in regard to some vital interest we might have in the Far East or far away from where you might be interested.&rdquo; However, in Deputy Booth's view it is quite legitimate for us to say: &ldquo;You are quite mistaken, my dear Mr. Dulles; we understand the position much better than you do.  It is not&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="LionelBooth" hpid="Mr. Booth Mr. Booth">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Booth</NameTxt>
      <P>Was our position not understood?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It was repudiated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the trouble.  The position we took up caused consternation and dismay and horror.  The Deputy was not here when Deputy Esmonde was speaking.  He pointed out another facet which I think people have overlooked.  Not only did it cause consternation and dismay among our friends in America but it was used on the Communist Radio and disseminated all through Christian China where our missionaries had been operating and where there was no other means of communication.  They said that Ireland was aligned on the side of China.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="558" />
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Esmonde did not say that that was done, that Fine Gael propaganda was circulated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>No, he did not say that because it would not be true, but he said that the stupidity of the Irish Minister for External Affairs was used for the purposes of Red propaganda on mediums of communication in areas where there was no other means of communication.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>It is bad enough to misrepresent me but do not misrepresent Deputy Esmonde.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>As you see, the Minister is very angry about it.  It is the very combination of stupidity and vanity on our man's part.  I want to stop that.  I think he is inept, vain and stupid, and this thing is becoming a gross abuse.  It is bad enough to slap America in the face and proceed to slap Federal Germany in the face, but then he goes on to slap France in the face.  I am asking who is going to be left whose face we have not slapped?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LionelBooth" hpid="Mr. Booth Mr. Booth">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Booth</NameTxt>
      <P>Which Governments have objected?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>If we only had to deal with Governments it would not matter so much but I am afraid we are getting to the point when we will have to deal with people, and we are acquiring the reputation that we shall be an unreliable friend, the kind of friend without whom you would be much safer and much better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LionelBooth" hpid="Mr. Booth Mr. Booth">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Booth</NameTxt>
      <P>Which Government&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be better to allow Deputy Dillon make his statement without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very helpful to me to learn of Deputy Booth's difficulties so that I can resolve them for him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not in accordance with order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very helpful to have some Fianna Fáil Deputy say something.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="559" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The vital interest of Ireland in international affairs at the present time is to multiply her friends, the number of her friends.  If that is our primary, vital interest&mdash;and I think it is&mdash;I suggest the policy and the proceedings of our Minister for External Affairs are, in fact, in grave conflict with the only real vital interest that Ireland has, and we are multiplying the number of persons who take grave offence at what may be the well-intended folly of our Minister for External Affairs.</P>
      <P>I do not know how Deputies in this House feel but it gives me no small measure of embarrassment that the French Government, in the course of the past two or three months, sends to this country out of sheer good will an officer of the highest standing in the French Army to present to the Minister for External Affairs, and to the Minister for Defence in our Government, the flags of the regiments of the Irish Brigade and that, within a month of that gesture, we announce that we are going to move in the United Nations that the existing controllers of atomic weapons will be the only persons allowed to have them, at a time when the Government of France have made it manifest that they are prepared to equip themselves, and regard it as an absolutely vital interest of theirs that they should be recognised as a proper custodian of such armament.</P>
      <P>Let me crystalise what I have to say. The question I want to ask our Minister for External Affairs is this: why need we always take the initiative in affronting our friends?  Would we not be wiser to avoid that to the limit of our ability and accept the necessity of doing it, if such necessity should ever arise, as a most distasteful duty to be fully explained in advance to those of our friends upon whose sensibilities such action, if it be necessary, may impinge?  Now, I should like to say that I think it is very important to remember&mdash;and there are a lot of people inclined to forget it&mdash;that there are worse things than being blown up by a bomb, whether it is a trinitrotoluol bomb or an atomic bomb.  It can be worse to live in servitude than to die a free man.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="560" /> It might be well for people who are naturally inclined to think more with their hearts than with their heads to recall that there are 800,000,000 people deployed under Communist direction and consecrated by their slave masters to the task of wiping out Christian civilisation to which we belong and that, by the end of this century, it is calculated that that 800,000,000 will have grown, probably to 1,300,000,000 or 1,400,000,000 without any corresponding increase in the population of that part of Europe to which we belong and which remains faithful to Christian civilisation.  Between us and that inevitable avalanche there stands nothing but the equality of armament which is now in existence, on the one side in the hands of the United States and Great Britain, and on the other side in the hands of Russia.</P>
    <P>If, in a moment of aberration soft hearts ever prevail on soft heads to abandon these armaments, and to leave ourselves naked before the avalanche that threatens from the East, we may discover too late that we have purchased immunity from explosion at the price of perpetual servitude and, in that servitude, we may discover that we no longer have the licence to die so that, when we talk glibly of abolishing all armaments, or certain categories of armaments, let us ask ourselves first what protection can be taken to ensure that in the event of such armaments being effectively removed, 800,000,000 Communists will not prevail over the relatively few Christian free men who inhabit the remainder of the Continent of Europe, of which we constitute a part?</P>
    <P>If I may turn from these complex matters to matters more mundane, Deputy Cosgrave or Deputy Esmonde referred to the French and German trade agreements that had been negotiated in the past and had not been re-negotiated for some time.  He commented on the fact&mdash;I think it was Deputy Cosgrave&mdash;that in respect of many of these trade arrangements there was a very great deal in favour of the Continental countries in that they exported to us a great deal more than we exported to them.  Am I right in believing it has proved impossible to <Col N="561" /> re-negotiate the German and French trade agreements?  Have we any trade agreements with those two countries?</P>
    <P>I saw a short statement in the papers which led me to believe that negotiations designed to continue these agreements had broken down and that no basis of agreement had been found. I should be glad if the Minister would tell us specifically what is the position with regard to trade relations with France and Western Germany at the present time.  Am I right in believing that, in fact, trade agreements with both of these countries are temporarily at least abrogated and that we have no specific trade agreements with them? What, in his opinion, does the future hold in regard to trade relations with these countries?</P>
    <P>I remember very well certain well-intentioned people telling me when I was Minister for Agriculture that I ought to make the French and the Germans sign agreements and make them take our goods or we would not take theirs.  I was obliged to tell these well-intentioned people that they did not know what they were talking about, and that the only effect of my persuading my colleagues in the Government to restrict severely German imports would be to throw a large number of persons out of employment. The number of motor cars that the Germans would be deterred from sending here they would be in a position to sell 10 times over in the United States.  Our position in negotiating with Continental countries is not nearly as strong as our position in negotiating with Great Britain whose second best customer in Europe we are.</P>
    <P>There is no other country in Europe which attaches very serious importance to the volume of trade that we are in a position to put in their way.  While in office we succeeded in maintaining moderately satisfactory trade with France, Germany, Holland, Spain and, I think, even with Sweden, but they were not easy to negotiate with.  Since we left office it appears that it has become impossible to negotiate to a satisfactory conclusion either with Germany or with France.  However, now that <Col N="562" /> I see our good friend, Herr Lubke, who was himself a Minister for Agriculture, has been elected President of Western Germany, I think we may expect a sympathetic hearing in that case.  I suggest our Minister for External Affairs might well return to the arena of negotiation in the knowledge that there is an understanding President in the West German Federal Republic at the present time.  I say so, because I remember with affection and esteem meeting him as my colleague, as Federal Germany's Minister of Agriculture, at meetings of the O.E.E.C. in Paris.</P>
    <P>That brings me to the question which I think was mentioned by Deputy Esmonde&mdash;how long are we going to &ldquo;sit on our sash&rdquo; here while the &ldquo;Seven&rdquo; negotiate in Stockholm and while Denmark negotiates in London for the purpose of securing for themselves access to a market which is utterly vital to us? I have suggested now on more than one occasion that we should approach the British Government forthwith and point out to them that we expressed our readiness to be associated with them in the Maudling Plan for the Free Trade Area with the other 15 nations of O.E.E.C., but that Plan is temporarily suspended&mdash;the discussions are going on in Stockholm&mdash;but that <i>ad interim</i> would the British not enter into relations with us analogous to those designed for the Free Trade Area and let us operate a free trade area here between ourselves and Great Britain and Northern Ireland into which others could enter if and when they wanted to?</P>
    <P>Personally, I believe that the very fact that the Free Trade Area negotiations have broken down may provide us with a singularly advantageous opportunity at this stage to go to Great Britain for a bilateral agreement on terms which would, in fact, be more advantageous to us than we could have hoped to get either through the Common Market or the Free Trade Area.  I directed the attention of the Minister for Industry and Commerce, now the Taoiseach, during the discussion of his Estimate to the Gamage plan which was published in the <Col N="563" /><i>Financial Times</i> and to which I gave the reference then, where it is clearly recognised that anything which contributes to a higher standard of living and to a more generally-diffused prosperity in a customer or potential customer of Great Britain redounds ultimately to the advantage of Great Britain herself.</P>
    <P>We are Britain's second best customer in Europe and there is a great potential for expansion of consumption here in a country which is prepared to pay for all she purchases from Britain in goods of a character without which Britain cannot survive.  I say that quite deliberately&mdash;not only goods of a character Britain is willing to buy but goods of a character without which she cannot survive.  I think we must be the only European country, except perhaps Denmark, that is in a position to say that, with this great distinction, that owing to our geographical propinquity to England, Scotland and Wales, the seas that separate these two islands can be controlled in a way that the North Sea can never be.</P>
    <P>There are a great many commodities which we are in a position to sell to Britain which are equally available in Denmark but with this immense distinction, that at the time when these commestibles might be vital to the survival of Britain they might not be available from Denmark, but nobody can make them unavailable from here. We have something very material and substantial to offer Great Britain in expanding quantities and they know that the ordinary course of trade will result in expanding purchasing power in this country redounding, as to 90 per cent., to the advantage of industrial expansion in Britain.</P>
    <P>Surely the time has come to go to Britain and say to her: &ldquo;If you will associate our agricultural industry with your own and determine that, in respect of certain commodities, our farmers will be put on a basis of equality with your farmers as you have already done under the 1948 Trade Agreement in respect of cattle; if you will extend that concession, say, to pigs, bacon, sheep, mutton and possibly butter, we on our side will extend to you all <Col N="564" /> the advantages contemplated under the Free Trade Area agreements that were under discussion in Paris and from such an agreement great mutual advantage could derive&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Quite frankly, I am afraid that with the present Minister for External Affairs, the present Minister for Industry and Commerce and the present Taoiseach that great opportunity may be let slip because I think the Taoiseach is more interested in manufacturing nails or studs or gewgaws in any factory in any city than he is in the welfare of the 12,000,000 acres of arable land and the 500,000 farmers who live on it.  I think that fundamentally the reason energetic measures are not being taken on the lines suggested by me is that, in his heart of hearts, the Taoiseach believes that the agricultural industry of this country is resting on a feather-bed. He believes that the solution of all our problems is that farmers should work harder for longer hours and take less so that they can provide a reservoir of purchasing power in which the industrialist could get a fair return on capital investment and the industrial worker a 45 or 44 hour week and a guaranteed wage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy should leave that field.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that is the reason why we are not negotiating with the British at the present time.  I do not think we are prepared to make an agreement now which would secure for us the kind of advantages without which the people of this country can make up their minds that sooner or later they will find thrust upon them a lower standard of living.  Mind you, time is running out.  Europe is now dividing into the six nations of the Rome Treaty, the Outer Seven of the Scandinavian agreement and we are with the descaminados&mdash;Iceland, Turkey, Greece and Ireland, the shirt-less ones of Europe.  We have elected to take our place with them.  It was at our request that we were enumerated in that company, the ones who had nothing to offer anyone except outstretched hands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We do not belong in that company. <Col N="565" /> We are the second greatest customer Britain has in Europe.  It is our own Government, in the person of the Taoiseach, at Paris, who elected to place us in that company.  I know and sympathise with the special difficulties of Greece, Turkey and Iceland, but they are not our difficulties and we should never have been in that company and it does not serve our vital interests that we should stay there. The great danger is that we are going to be completely isolated.  We ought to get our agreement made before we find ourselves alone.</P>
    <P>Now, it would be much better if these things could be done without such aspects of the situation being too energetically canvassed here.  But how long is an Opposition to sit, watching the situation deteriorate, without saying a word?  This Government have been in office for nearly three years&mdash; two and a half years&mdash;and nothing has been done.  Nothing has been done for nine months now, but thumping the tub and tearing passion to tatters over proportional representation.  During the whole of that period, Sweden, Denmark and Norway were concocting a new free trade area of their own, and Denmark has been in London negotiating day and night.  Do you know what Denmark is looking for? Denmark is looking for and yearning for what we got in 1948 and still hold. While we are threshing the air, painting the roads and storming the country on the question of P.R., all our competitors are gnawing away at the doors of our market, to get our place in that market.  Mind you, I think they will get away with it.  Now that all that diversionary brouhaha is over, will the Government act; or am I right in believing that the industrialist bent of the Taoiseach's mind prohibits action?  If that is the case, it is time Deputies asked themselves: &ldquo;Where do we go from here?&rdquo;</P>
    <P>We have all experienced what it is like to feel what I believe to be, in our existing circumstances, a quite temporary oscillation in the demand and the price level of cattle.  Suppose that becomes permanent.  Suppose it is accompanied by a serious contraction of the available market for bacon <Col N="566" /> and a disappearance of our market for butter, in respect of both of which commodities we at present enjoy a considerable preference over all our competitors in the British market.  I think the Danes are negotiating those preferences away and we are going to feel the draught.  The Government will not say a word about it.  Surely it is our duty to say something and to warn Deputies as to where we are drifting. Nine weary months have gone by in futile disputation in this country.  Two and a half years of this Government's life have gone by.  Every nation in Europe has done something to improve its international trading position, except Ireland.  Are we not entitled to ask the Government now: &ldquo;What are you going to do about it, and when?&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankSherwin" hpid="Mr. Sherwin Mr. Sherwin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherwin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry for not being here when the debate was adjourned, but it was like this&mdash;one would starve if one did not go out&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy should not be called until all the other Deputies have spoken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I conclude after Deputy Sherwin?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be the ordinary way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>I rose to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankSherwin" hpid="Mr. Sherwin Mr. Sherwin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherwin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Ceann Comhairle has since called me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I did, because I did not want to call two Deputies from the same benches one after the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Could you not let Deputy Sherwin say what he has to say?  No precedent is created, but Deputy Sherwin gets in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankSherwin" hpid="Mr. Sherwin Mr. Sherwin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherwin</NameTxt>
      <P>As I said, we have to earn a few shillings because if one were to depend on what one gets here, one would starve.  I earned a few bob since I left.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I was saying before the debate was adjourned, the Minister's primary duty is to look after the security of the State.  His function is largely a political <Col N="567" /> one and while there are other responsibilities there are other people there to look after them.  As Partition is one of the problems for the Minister, I am surprised that he did not refer to it in his opening speech.  I know that the subject is like cancer, something that is ugly and that we should not talk about.  People may get hurt when you talk about it, but it is there and you have to face it; you have to speak about it and you have to solve it.  It is the Minister's responsibility to do that.  Even though we admit that it is a tough problem about which he cannot do much&mdash;nor anyone else&mdash; unfortunately it it his baby and how and when it is to be solved is something which is his job, and he ought to refer to it.</P>
    <P>I should like to refer to statements in the Press.  It appeared in one of the English newspapers that a treaty was about to be concluded between Britain and Ireland which would enable persons to be taken from this part of Ireland to the Six Counties for trial; in other words, an extradition treaty.  I do not know what truth there is in that, but if such a treaty is ever concluded it will be the finish for the Government responsible.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no truth in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankSherwin" hpid="Mr. Sherwin Mr. Sherwin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherwin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to hear the Minister say that.  There is also the question of the several hundred Irishmen who are interned without trial in Northern Ireland.  It is the Minister's duty to make some protest.  At one time, if one Englishman was insulted, a gunboat was sent; but here we have several hundred men in jail without trial, some of them for four or five years.  I can understand a person being charged and imprisoned because of some offence, but where you have several hundred interned without trial, it is the Minister's duty to make some protest.  It is his job to protect Irishmen abroad, especially those in the hands of those we should term the enemy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I know it is a delicate subject.  I think that in my own little way I know just as much about it as the <Col N="568" /> Minister.  I know the problem inside out, not like some Deputies fond of talking about it.  To me, the people up there are Englishmen and Scotsmen, but they are not like Englishmen and Scotsmen absorbed by the rest of the community.  They remain the same as the day they landed here. That is the bugbear.  While I do not like mentioning religion, that is responsible for their remaining Englishmen and Scotsmen and not being absorbed.</P>
    <P>I know the problem seems insoluble but in any event it is the Minister's duty to protest.  In my opinion, there is not much the Government or the Opposition can do about it.  I do not think we could ever improve so much economically that we could entice in Northern Ireland.  If we prosper, it will be because of England prospering, and for the same reason, so will Northern Ireland.  According to my little study of the problem, our population is diminishing and we have less employment, whereas the population in Northern Ireland is increasing and there is more employment, even if there is unemployment.  They have their social benefits.  Then there is this snag of Irish, which will make this problem insoluble.  If we all speak Irish only and they speak English, and if to get jobs they have to speak Irish, they will come to the conclusion there is no room for them in a united Ireland.  I realise all these things and I sympathise with the Minister.  A protest might incite them.  One of the main arguments we have for '16 and '98 was they awakened the people from a long sleep.  Let us continue protesting, even if we can do no more.  Perhaps some day in some world conflict it will end. That is the only way I believe it will end.  I accept the toughness of the problem and all I ask is that the Minister should continue to protest.</P>
    <P>I am not so much concerned about the Minister's activities in the United Nations.  I am inclined to keep to matters which concern us here.  Why should we concern ourselves about rows in Europe when we have a row at home?  We should always think in terms of what benefits this country and leave moralising to others.  We <Col N="569" /> should not offend those who benefit us. I agree with Deputy Dillon in that.  I do not expect that China or Russia will ever be of any advantage to us. If there was trouble in Europe, they would be an the other side of the fence and we would have to look for assistance to those we are inclined to let down.  We should be realistic. According to Machiavelli an honest diplomat would be a fool.  Diplomacy consists in kidding the other fellow and obtaining your ends.  I have studied diplomacy from Richelieu to Metter-nich and all the rest.  I know their minds, even if I have not the Minister's experience of U.N.O.  Thank you, a Cheann Comhairle, for allowing me in.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>In these eight pages, there are two matters, not really very small matters, in which I can join with the Minister as a matter of congratulation&mdash;not for him indeed but for the two groups mentioned.  One is his tribute to the officers of our Army by reason of their superb conduct in the course of their sojourn in the Lebanon as members of the International Force. That conduct was only what we would expect it to be, in the best traditions of our Army.  The second matter on which I agree with the Minister is the manner in which the former President, Mr. O'Kelly, conducted his tour of the United States at the invitation of the United States Government.  That is not a matter of congratulation for the Minister for External Affairs; that is a tribute, well deserved, by reason of the excellent personal and diplomatic qualities of the former President.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As to the rest of the Minister's speech, it appears to me to be an <i>apologia</i>, but in the mildest possible terms, for his conduct in the United Nations in the course of the past year or so.  In dealing with the conduct of the Minister in relation to the sessions of the United Nations which he attended, and at which he made contributions, I do not seek, as some people in high places outside this House have sought, to distinguish between the conduct of the Minister and the conduct of his officials.  Quite the contrary.  Their actions cannot be distinguished or divorced from the actions of the Minister and they are, in the last <Col N="570" /> analysis, the actions of the Government themselves.</P>
    <P>It is for that reason that I deplore the recent utterances outside this House condemning the officials of the Department of External Affairs for the manner in which they participated in the affairs of the United Nations, while those who sought to condemn them said nothing of the Minister who was their leader and to whom they were responsible.  When I say that, I do not for one moment suggest that the conduct or utterances of any permanent official of the Department is in any way blameworthy <i>per se.</i></P>
    <P>Deputy Seán Flanagan rebuked the Opposition here today for attempting to question the conduct of the Irish delegation to the United Nations in relation to the question of the admissibility of Red China into that body and the debate on that subject.  I straight away accept the quibble that it was not a vote to include Red China but a vote to enable the Assembly to debate the question as to whether or not Red China should be admitted.  The Irish delegation preparatory to the giving of that vote considered the merits in the case of Red China and they offered it as an excuse that the merits and demerits had to be discussed before they could give their final vote and they advocate at the same time that that is the action of free men of a free nation.</P>
    <P>I remember at Easter of 1956 at a meeting of the Council of the Inter-Parliamentary Union in Dubrovnik in Yugoslavia, I attended as a member of that Council with the Taoiseach who was then a member of the Opposition. I want the House to know that when the Inter-Parliamentary Union takes decisions, they are not in any way binding and have purely a recommending effect generally.  In November, 1955, the Executive Committee of the Inter-Parliamentary Union, through the casting vote of the then President, Lord Stansgate, at New Delhi, admitted Red China to membership of the Union.  That decision of the Executive Committee had to be ratified by the Council of the Union.</P>
    <P>As I say, I was present at Easter, 1956, at Dubrovnik with the Taoiseach. I remember the very intense lobbying <Col N="571" /> that went on, even in a non-mandatory body such as the Inter-Parliamentary Union, in order to have the decision of the Executive Committee at New Delhi nullified and the admission of Red China to membership of the Inter-Parliamentary Union rejected.  For at least three years it could not come up again.  The Americans were led by Senator Reed at the time and there was a very old Senator, whose name I do not recall, who died shortly after his return to America after that session, whose last speech I shall always remember. He said his membership of the Inter-Parliamentary Union went back over many years and that he had made the journey at his great age in order to see that the principles of freedom would survive in the union of world parliaments.</P>
    <P>The curious thing is that while we watched everybody else taking their stand, neither the Taoiseach nor I discussed between ourselves what we would do.  I had my mind made up, and I am quite sure that so had he. We very probably would have had a discussion but for the fact that I was suddenly called upon to act as teller with a delegate from Hungary while the counting of the votes was taking place and we took our places beside the President while the votes were being collected.</P>
    <P>I should like to think that the Taoiseach, who was then in Opposition, voted in the same way as I did and, in fact, from an analysis of the votes afterwards, I am inclined to think he did.  If he did not, somebody from Hungary or Yugoslavia must have voted anti-Russia, which is extremely unlikely.  I remember how American prestige, even at that small gathering, was puffed up and how everybody in the Western world seemed extraordinarily happy.  Even the abstentionists from the Scandinavian countries were not too secretly overjoyed by the fact that Russia received that rebuff that morning.</P>
    <P>I am telling this to the House because I think our action at the Inter-Parliamentary Union, which is admittedly a non-mandatory body, appears to have been so quietly taken and was so different from the vast publicity <Col N="572" /> attached to the subsequent action at the United Nations of the Government of which Deputy Lemass was then Tánaiste.  It must have been known to the Irish delegation what the set-up in Red China was.  It must have been known also to our friends in America that the whole bloc of that portion of free Europe was opposed, not only to the admission of Red China, but to any discussion as to the merits or demerits of the admission of Red China.  I do not think one need apologise for the assertion that once we knew about China, having regard to our very long spiritual association with that country and the work of our missionaries there, we should have recognised where our duty lay in relation to giving the particular regime in China at the moment a pat on the back or in relation to doing anything foolish, well-intentioned though it might be, that might appear to be a pat on the back.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrancisLoughman" hpid="Mr. Loughman Mr. Loughman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Loughman</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Deputy think that admitting Russia to the United Nations was giving a pat on the back to China?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>Admitting Red China was giving Russia a pat on the back.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrancisLoughman" hpid="Mr. Loughman Mr. Loughman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Loughman</NameTxt>
      <P>Considering we are agreeable to be in the United Nations with Russia, is that not the same thing as patting China on the back?  Would the Deputy exclude Russia?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Would Deputy Loughman admit China?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not exclude Russia.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrancisLoughman" hpid="Mr. Loughman Mr. Loughman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Loughman</NameTxt>
      <P>The reason I ask is I want to know what is the difference between admitting China&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>All the difference in the world.  There is a mighty difference between those who were in at the beginning and the admission of undesirables at a subsequent date. Whatever we might think of Russia being a founder member, it would nevertheless be our duty ideologically to see that Russia is kept in her place in the United Nations and to join at all times with those other groups which have to face up to this ideological clash that exists in the world. <Col N="573" /> Even if the action of the Minister for External Affairs could be justified on technical grounds, I do not think advantage should be taken of a technicality which might have disastrous factual results.</P>
      <P>There is no gainsaying, apart altogether from what Deputy Seán Flanagan is inclined to call Fine Gael propaganda&mdash;I shall deal with that in a moment&mdash;that there was a clamour in the Press of the United States of America and in newspapers all over the world as a result of what might be described, at its very mildest, as the strange action of the Irish delegation. When men of the eminence of Dr. Cuthbert O'Hara take a strong line in this matter, having regard to his association and that of his brethren with China, that is something we cannot overlook.  The Minister for External Affairs particularly, and the Government generally, would do well to try even at this late stage to rectify the harm that was done and the wrong that was done and to change or alter in some way, at least in part, the wrong impression created throughout the world as a result of this foolish action on the part of the Minister, however well intentioned it might have been by reason of a technicality or a quibble.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When one is desirous of championing freedom or showing that one is a free man, there is no need for one to kick somebody else in the face in the process.  That was done to the Americans at that time.  It was later done to the Germans.  Now it is sought, through the medium of this proposal about nuclear weapons, to exclude France.  Anybody conversant with recent history must accept that France must be kept strong.  Nobody wants a repetition of the collapse of France in 1940, in the event of another world conflagration.  To that collapse could be attributed, I suppose, three years of war.  The war might well have ended three years earlier if France had not collapsed.  Now, by limiting the possession of nuclear weapons to America, Great Britain and Russia, we are seeking to keep France in the same weak position. Even as late as yesterday, an American <Col N="574" /> spokesman in Paris reiterated the American resolution to back France to the limit in their Algerian stand.  I see no reason why we should take the initiative in trying to create a position in which that situation might be put in jeopardy.</P>
    <P>So much for the United Nations. I shall conclude my references to that body by reiterating my belief and my faith in the permanent officials of the Department of External Affairs.  I deplore the attack that was made on them outside when, in fact, it was the Minister who should have been attacked.</P>
    <P>This Department is the Department ultimately responsible for the concluding of trade agreements.  In the course of the Minister's speech, there was not one reference to trade agreements, and that at a time when the whole of Western Europe is seething with activity of that kind.  Either multilateral agreements or bilateral agreements are being sought, such as the &ldquo;Seven,&rdquo; on the one hand, and the Anglo-Danish, on the other.</P>
    <P>For the purposes of our tourist trade, there could be a substantial relaxation not alone in the matter of triptyques for motor cars and vehicles generally but also in the matter of passports of short duration. Recently in Great Britain the system of day trips to France without passports has been adopted.  I think it was the late Ernest Bevin, British Foreign Secretary at the time, who said he would like to see the day when men and money could pass freely through every country in the world. If there were less preoccupation with the passport, the <i>carnet</i>, the police document, the embarkation and disembarkation card, and all the other trammels which go to make travel so difficult, people would get to know one another better and nationalities would grow closer.  The cause of peace might be promoted better in that way than in any other.</P>
    <P>The Minister has dealt with the problem of refugees to some extent. The problem is a big one and one of which, as he says, we must take serious heed, not alone in charity but in justice.  We must make some contribution <Col N="575" /> to the solution of that problem, officially and unofficially.  We did our bit in the case of Hungary.  It was not altogether easy.  The refugee problem is by no means an easy one to handle. Very often the country which takes in refugees gets less thanks perhaps than it deserves.</P>
    <P>On the question of disarmament, I agree wholeheartedly with Deputy Dillon when he says he would rather be blown up by any kind of bomb than live in the kind of servitude which we know exists in one of those countries at least where a particular bomb has a very special position at the present. There is a great deal to be said for the old way of putting it, the description of &ldquo;the equaliser&rdquo;.  If you cannot maintain peace by the adoption of the simple principles of the Sermon on the Mount, you must take other means that are open to you within the Christian code in order to maintain it. I do not see any reason in the world why Britain, the United States of America or other countries should be asked to disarm when Russia and her satellites deny to the United Nations observers the right of supervision.  If you are unable to supervise the arsenals of other countries, you simply do not know what they have got, and, not knowing what they have got makes you feel that you had better have as much as possible in order to deal with any situation.</P>
    <P>Has anybody ever talked for a considerable time with the pacifist, the person interested in disarmament?  He will talk all day, all night, all week and all month about the virtues of disarmament but does not seem to have any solution unless it is world disarmament.  We had experiences of that several times in the world's history and we know the disastrous results that flowed from it.  Some of the older philosophers had a saying which has a great deal to commend it, namely, if you wish for peace, prepare for war.  I do not see why we should go out of our way to ask people to disarm when we do not say to all of them, first, &ldquo;Will you do it?&rdquo; and then &ldquo;Do it&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>On page 1, the Minister said:</P>
    <P>In some cases we put forward <Col N="576" /> suggestions of our own aimed at relaxation of international tension which is the first condition of progress towards a just and stable peace.</P>
    <P>If we could get rid of international tension, or at least achieve some relaxation of it, we would be on the way towards a just and stable peace, but have the suggestions put forward by the Irish delegation to the United Nations, while they are allegedly aimed at relaxation of international tension, made any contribution towards such relaxation?  If they had achieved anything in that regard, we might be prepared to forgive them for the other tension which has been created in the process.</P>
    <P>It is all very well to talk about pursuing a middle of the road policy and not taking sides with one or the other, but, as I said some time ago, in this ideological clash, as we see it in the world today, men can no longer, any more than countries, stay on the fence.  That does not mean that the policy of neutrality in relation to warfare cannot be maintained. I am simply referring to the undesirability and absolute unfeasibility of a neutrality of the mind.  Such cannot exist.  The more one tries to neutralise one's mind, the more insular it inevitably becomes and, naturally, from such insularity must come a lesser and lesser contribution to the councils at home or the councils of the nations.</P>
    <P>In the speech of the Minister, there is no reference whatsoever to the question of Partition.  As I pointed out here on the occasion of the nomination of the Taoiseach, I would prefer that references to problems were omitted unless they were sincere and practical.  I do not know, nor does anybody know, until such time as the Minister replies, why he omitted any reference to the question of the Partition of our country.  Is it due to the fact that he and his Government recognise it, from their point of view at least, as an insoluble problem? Would it be due to the fact that they might recognise that perennial speeches in this regard are of very little use when they cannot be <Col N="577" /> followed up by practical steps throughout the year between the speeches?</P>
    <P>In that regard, I want to put on record how pleased I was this year by what I would call an advance in thinking in relation to Partition, namely, that the annual Easter meeting at Trafalgar Square in London was not proceeded with on this occasion.  Anybody who ever attended there could not but have a feeling of utter futility.</P>
    <P>The solution of Partition involves very many facets and very many problems, not alone those that are apparent when one sets out to solve it but those that crop up in the course of the solution.</P>
    <P>It was extremely pleasant on Thursday last, at the inauguration of the President, to meet the Nationalist Members of the Stormont Parliament and members of the Six County Senate. It was a symbol of unity in Dublin Castle.</P>
    <P>Let us be realists about all this. Deputy Sherwin has made the point that, economically, it will always be difficult to solve Partition.  I do not agree.  Once the part of the country over which this Parliament has jurisdiction reached the stage of having a higher standard of living, more productivity in machine shop and farm, a retention, if not an increase, of its population, we would begin to show ourselves to the people of the Six Counties as hard workers and people who are ready to work hard to achieve high standards.  Remember, too, that it is an attribute of the people of Northern Ireland to be hard workers and to know which side their bread is buttered on.</P>
    <P>I should like to pose this question on the occasion of this Vote not to the Minister for External Affairs but, through him, to our brethren in Northern Ireland.  When I say &ldquo;our brethren in Northern Ireland&rdquo;, I mean the whole lot of them in Northern Ireland. I do not accept them as Scottish or British, as Deputy Sherwin does.  I want to ask those of them who vote for Nationalist candidates at elections if their votes can be described merely as votes recorded by Catholics negativing <Col N="578" /> the votes of their brother Protestants, or if they mean something more.</P>
    <P>When somebody goes into a polling booth on an election day and records his vote for a Nationalist candidate, does he say to himself: &ldquo;I am voting for the Nationalist candidate, not because I want him to go to Stormont but because I want him to do everything in his power to restore national unity and national sovereignty&rdquo;?  They are different things when we examine them.  Is it a simple anti-Protestant vote or is it a vote that carries with it all the aspirations of somebody genuinely interested in trying to solve Partition?  That is something in relation to which I should like a plain and unequivocal answer from the people of Northern Ireland.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Notice taken that 20 Members were not present; House counted and 20 Members being present.</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJBurke" hpid="Mr. P.J. Burke Mr. P.J. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to make the point that only two Fine Gael Deputies are present.  Deputy McGilligan called for a House.  We have not seen him here in the past six months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I gather that is meant to be friendly?  I gather it is a welcome?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course it is.  Deputy P.J. Burke never means to be anything other than friendly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall meet him in Portrane.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJBurke" hpid="Mr. P.J. Burke Mr. P.J. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>It is nice to see Deputy McGilligan after six months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>I was dealing with the possible implications of a vote recorded in the Six Counties at an election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I fail to see how the Minister's responsibilities arise on this matter.  We are discussing the Estimate for the Department of External Affairs.  Only what the Minister is responsible for is relevant. How the votes are recorded in the Six Counties is certainly not a matter for the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely the Department of External Affairs is responsible for foreign policy and, as such, would be <Col N="579" /> interested in what goes on in portions of the country outside the jurisdiction?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister may be very interested but he has no responsibility for the matters referred to by the Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>As I see the situation in the Republic of Ireland <i>vis-a-vis</i> the Six Counties economically, they are on a basis of security from which it would virtually be impossible to lure them at the moment.  Their social services and benefits generally rank much higher and are more generous than they are here.  I should be extremely interested in the implications that might be gathered from a possible plebiscite in this connection.</P>
      <P>I should like the Minister to tell us why he did not mention this.  I should like to think it is from the sincere conviction that perennial references do not admit of any further advance towards the solution of the problem. His speech today was not sufficiently comprehensive and did not deal with the great number of problems that come up for review in his Department. In this regard, I deplore the lack of detail.</P>
      <P>As I said at the outset, the Minister's opening speech was an <i>apologia</i>, mildly put, for his performance at the United Nations.  I suppose it is the correct thing or at least the one, in a situation such as that in which the Minister now finds himself, most likely to be advantageous&mdash;in other words, that the least said at this stage, the soonest mended.  I cannot say that we could accept this account of the doings of his Department, having regard to world conditions, world movements and world upheavels, as at all adequate in the circumstances obtaining here. Perhaps in his reply he will develop at least some of the points that have been raised by all the speakers in this debate and in that way maybe dispel our doubts and relieve our anxiety in this regard, a regard which cannot be overlooked in respect of last year as well as this year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have a feeling in common with many other Deputies that the Minister for External Affairs comes in here, <Col N="580" /> reads his speech with the utmost contempt for everyone occupying all of the benches in the house as much as to say: &ldquo;I am here because it is a feature of our Parliamentary life that an Estimate must be brought into the House.  The Minister must make his speech and the less I say the less bored I shall be.&rdquo;  I hope we shall be forgiven for not allowing too short a time, even if it bores him, to put forward the points in which we are interested. Never at any time shall we allow a situation in which members of the House can be treated with the utmost contempt, due either to failure by the Minister to have anything worthy to record or to an utter disregard for the people who are in the final analysis very interested, the members of this House and the people of the country.</P>
    <P>This speech when published tomorrow can mean little or nothing to the average Irishman.  If we had more interest and more of the detail appertaining to foreign affairs percolating to our people they would have a better understanding not alone of themselves but of the people of other countries.  They certainly can learn nothing from this.  They could not even know what it is all about except perhaps the figure of £6,000 which the Minister says we are going to give to the United Nations towards assisting refugees.  Having regard to the mighty problem of the refugees this paltry contribution must be rated as very low towards such a worthy cause when the Government can find vast sums running into millions of pounds for the airports of the country for the upkeep of what they call their prestige, whereas they should recognise that the greatest prestige of all comes from the full exercise of the virtue of charity.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I almost got a shock.  I thought one of the Government Party was about to take part in the proceedings of this House at last.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJBurke" hpid="Mr. P.J. Burke Mr. P.J. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>We would not like to interrupt the Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>It is about time that somebody from the Government side would defend the Minister for External Affairs but I do not expect <Col N="581" /> they will defend the Minister for External Affairs in this discussion when they were not able to support the election of the Taoiseach last week.</P>
      <P>Last year the Minister read a short brief in Irish when he was introducing his Estimate.  He treated the House with contempt and then when he came to reply on his Estimate he did not even have the courtesy to answer any of the questions or even to make a statement as to what is the policy of this Republic of Ireland on external affairs.  It would be hard for the Minister to have an unbiassed policy because it is well known that his notorious hatred of Great Britain makes him regret that Great Britain was not destroyed and defeated in the last war by Nazi Germany, and he could not look at the United States with anything but bias because they entered the war as allies of Great Britain.</P>
      <P>It is these prejudices which cloud the Minister's judgment when he goes to the United Nations.  He wants to go to the United Nations, strut up and down the hall there and say: &ldquo;I have an independent mind.  We are an independent State.&rdquo;  It is a good thing that we can be independent but it should not cloud the judgment of the Minister and therefore subject the country to a good deal of shame. Almost every Irishman and woman has either a friend or a close relative in an honourable calling in the United States.  When the United States was only a young country, when the people there had great difficulties for themselves and the appalling famine came to this country, almost wiping out our people, many of them fled to the United States.  It was from the United States that food ships were sent to try to keep alive those who remained at home.  We find ourselves through the representation of the Minister for External Affairs going to the United Nations and taking our place amongst the nations of the earth.  How can we as Irishmen take our place amongst the nations of the earth when we are not prepared to stand with our friends?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We had older friends than the Americans.  We had the French, and, <Col N="582" /> as Deputy Dillon said here today, the French Government sent an officer here with the replicas of the flags of the Irish Brigades that were in the service of France to be presented to the Minister for External Affairs, honouring the people of Ireland, honouring the men who joined those Brigades. What do we get?  We start getting into the atomic bomb business.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGeoghegan" hpid="Mr. Geoghegan Mr. Geoghegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Geoghegan</NameTxt>
      <P>What does the Deputy know about it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I know more about it than the Minister and that is very little.  These are the speeches we get from this great Party of 78 men&mdash;a little bit of an interjection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGeoghegan" hpid="Mr. Geoghegan Mr. Geoghegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Geoghegan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is trying to keep the House going.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>This Deputy does not have to try to keep the House going. When he speaks he has something worthwhile to say.  I hope the Minister in his closing speech on this Estimate will tell us what is his policy and what is the foreign policy of this country. We had a contribution from a young Deputy here today, Deputy Seán Flanagan, the only man in the Fianna Fáil benches who has spoken in defence of the Minister.  The loyalty of a man like Deputy Seán Flanagan is wonderful.  Deputy Seán Flanagan was a Government nominee to the O.E.E.C.  He was sent to Strasbourg where he acquitted himself with some distinction, if I might say so.  He came back but I notice that he was dropped from the Irish delegation to the O.E.E.C.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that cannot be discussed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>This has something to do with External Affairs, Sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has no responsibility for these appointments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnchadhOBriain" hpid="Donnchadh Ó Briain Donnchadh Ó Briain">
      <NameTxt>Donnchadh Ó Briain</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy does not know what he is talking about.  Deputy Seán Flanagan had nothing to do with O.E.E.C.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister in his speech said:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I supported the imaginative proposal <Col N="583" /> of President Eisenhower who took the exceptional course of addressing the session for the establishment of a Middle East Economic Agency on the lines of O.E.E.C.  And I suggested in particular that the Arab refugees problem was the greatest single obstacle to lasting peace in the area and that the United Nations should be ready to make extraordinary efforts to break the deadlock on this issue.</P>
    <P>May I say that that has something to do with External Affairs?</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonnchadhOBriain" hpid="Donnchadh Ó Briain Donnchadh Ó Briain">
      <NameTxt>Donnchadh Ó Briain</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Seán Flanagan had nothing whatever to do with O.E.E.C.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>We might possibly get Deputy Seán Flanagan in, if there was a count of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>He was a delegate&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnchadhOBriain" hpid="Donnchadh Ó Briain Donnchadh Ó Briain">
      <NameTxt>Donnchadh Ó Briain</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not relevant either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Was there a House called?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a House present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not call for a House.  If you want to go on with your trained dog act, go somewhere else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Lynch will not refer to the act of any Deputy in this House as a trained dog act.  It is not in order. Deputy Lynch might be allowed to make his speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Now I am very grateful to you, Sir.  One of the cloaks put on this is the cry that can go up from the Government benches and the tied Government organ <i>Pravda</i> that we are trying, by implication, to brand the Minister for External Affairs as a Communist.  We are doing no such thing.  That is what you are all trying to say.  We are not saying anything like that but you are trying to imply we are saying it.  It was a pity that I was not allowed to go on about Strasbourg.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="584" /> In the matter of the Continent of Europe, it is the Minister's function to make trade agreements.  I do not think we have any trade agreement with anybody on the Continent of Europe now. Both the Germans and the French have thrown us over.  Of course, we would not make a trade agreement with the British.  The Minister and his colleague, the Minister for Agriculture, had to go in great haste about seven or eight days ago to England in great secrecy.  When they returned, no statement was made as to what happened.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCarty" hpid="Mr. Carty Mr. Carty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carty</NameTxt>
      <P>No secret agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish he had some kind of an agreement, secret or otherwise. No secret agreement was made between the Danes and Great Britain this week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NicholasEgan" hpid="Mr. N. Egan Mr. N. Egan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Egan</NameTxt>
      <P>A damned good bargain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>A damned good bargain. No statement was made about it.  The Minister for External Affairs should have said that they were in England last week, that they had intended to make a trade agreement, that they had made a trade agreement or not, or that he was prepared to start another economic war but he should give us notice.  I note that has been received in noticeable silence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCarty" hpid="Mr. Carty Mr. Carty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carty</NameTxt>
      <P>Give him five minutes more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Agriculture had to have the Minister for External Affairs attending him going over.  I always notice that the Minister for Agriculture is never allowed to go to Great Britain or anywhere else on his own.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The House is not discussing the Minister for Agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>We are discussing the Minister for External Affairs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGeoghegan" hpid="Mr. Geoghegan Mr. Geoghegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Geoghegan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has nothing else to say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a wonder the Deputy would not say something.  He has been long enough in the House to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="585" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnGeoghegan" hpid="Mr. Geoghegan Mr. Geoghegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Geoghegan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy wants to say something because he has some visitors in the House.  That is it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>In his speech, the Minister said:&mdash;</P>
      <P>I now come to what was from the point of view of the Irish Delegation the principal feature of the 1958 Session of the United Nations. Our main effort was concentrated upon drawing attention to the dangers involved for peace in wider dissemination of nuclear weapons. This was the central theme of my address in the Assembly's General Debate and we took steps to develop it further during the First Committee's disarmament debate.</P>
      <P>Our intitiative on the matter in the United Nations was two-fold ...</P>
      <P>Why should we have the initiative in this?  Why should we have to be tied on to every kind of clap-trap like this?  This is not a matter for us at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="586" />
      <i>Notice taken that 20 Members were not present; House counted and 20 Members being present</i>,</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJBurke" hpid="Mr. P.J. Burke Mr. P.J. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Two minutes to go!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCarty" hpid="Mr. Carty Mr. Carty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carty</NameTxt>
      <P>Saved by the bell!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Let Deputy Burke not be put out about this.  It is no trouble to me whether there are two minutes or two hours to go.  That is no drawback to me at all.  There was a matter I was dealing with when we asked for a House to come in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>These atom bombs.</P>
      <P>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 5 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Tuesday, 7th July, 1959.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>