<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Thu" Date="29" Month="Oct" Year="1959" Vol="177" No="4" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 29 Deireadh Fómhair 1959" DateEnglish="Thursday, 29 October 1959" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="487" /> Do chuaigh an Leas-Cheann Comhairle i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="The Taoiseach Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed that business, as set out on the Order Paper, be taken in the following order: Nos. 1, 8, 9, 10, 11 and 12.  Questions will be taken at 3 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Taoiseach when he has in mind to take the Intoxicating Liquor Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="The Taoiseach Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is ordered for the 11th November.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that Wednesday week?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="The Taoiseach Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  I think it is safe to presume that it will be taken on that date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it if we are anxious to have it postponed, the matter may be discussed by the Whips.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="The Taoiseach Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I have already made it clear that there is no intention of trying to rush the passage of that Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee of" RHead="Selection&mdash;Ninth Report">
    <Title>Committee of Selection&mdash;Ninth Report.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonnchadhOBriain" hpid="Rúnaí Parlaiminte an Taoisigh (Donnchadh Ó Briain) Rúnaí Parlaiminte an Taoisigh (Donnchadh Ó Briain)">
      <NameTxt>Rúnaí Parlaiminte an Taoisigh (Donnchadh Ó Briain):-</NameTxt>
      <P>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Tuairiscíonn an Coiste Roghnóireachta go bhfuil sé tar éis an Teachta Seosamh Ó Braonáin, Rúnaí Parlaiminte an Aire Airgeadais, agus an Teachta Séamas Díolún d'urscaoileadh ón gCoiste um Chuntais Phoiblí ar na Cuntais Leithreasa i gcóir na bliana <Col N="488" /> dár chríoch 31 Márta, 1959 agus an Teachta Séamas Ó Tuathail agus an Teachta Liam Mac Cosgair a cheapadh ina n-ionad.</P>
    <P>The Committee of Selection reports that it has discharged Deputies Joseph Brennan, Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance, and James M. Dillon from the Committee of Public Accounts on the Appropriation Accounts for the year ended 31st March, 1959, and has appointed Deputies James O'Toole and Liam Cosgrave in substitution for them.</P>
    <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
    <P>That the Report do lie upon the Table.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Electoral (Amendment) Bill," RHead="1959&mdash;Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Electoral (Amendment) Bill, 1959&mdash;Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Before moving the adjournment of the debate last night I commented on the fact that the time was ripe for a completely fresh examination of the duties of Deputies, both in this House and outside it.  An opportunity for such a discussion occurs once every 12 years and surely the time available should be used for a reasoned discussion, so that, in the period ahead, the maximum amount of useful legislation will be enacted and, at the same time, the electorate generally will not suffer from lack of representation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Other Deputies have already spoken on the question of the size of the membership of the House.  There are various views on this matter and it would appear that complaints at the moment are due to a conflict in the minds of various people as to what the real duties of public representatives, or members of this House, should be. Listening to the Taoiseach yesterday evening, I felt that his idea of public representation was that a Deputy was elected mainly for the purpose of listening to grievances throughout the length and breadth of rural constituencies, or in the limited confines of a Dublin constituency, depending <Col N="489" /> on which part of the country he is elected to represent.  That was his main function.  Consequently, if the people were to get proper attention in this matter of having their grievances listened to, it would be necessary to have very large representation.</P>
    <P>That was one part of the case which was made.  If it is accepted as one of the ideals of public representation, then there is no doubt it is essential that we should have at least 150 Deputies, if not more, to deal with those grievances.  As a matter of fact, judging by the number of letters and grievances I receive&mdash;and I feel I am overworked in the amount of correspondence I have to deal with&mdash;if that is the experience of other Deputies, we should be asking for another 50 members to ease our work.</P>
    <P>I feel that approach is wrong.  I believe the more time spent by a Deputy in examining grievances, 50 per cent. of which are not real grievances, the less time he can devote to the consideration of legislation and the study of Bills.  Consequently, the work of this House is neglected through a lack of attention on the part of the majority of Deputies or&mdash; should I put it this way?&mdash;the consideration of Bills and legislation is left in the hands of a limited few.  If, as I say, that is the outlook so far as a Deputy is concerned, if his duties are considered to be mainly those of a grievance officer, why do we not do as they do in Sweden and appoint a grievance officer in every constituency, if necessary, or take from the Civil Service a liaison officer who will be quite independent, who will listen to the grievances of people in connection with old age pensions and other such matters, and iron out the difficulties between those people and the various Departments.  That is the work Deputies are doing at the moment.</P>
    <P>In the various constituencies where there are three, four or five Deputies, we have, in many cases, the same constituent trying out the three, four or five Deputies.  That may keep these Deputies on their feet but my experience is that, of the 3, 4 or 5, the brunt of the work will in the long run <Col N="490" /> lie on the shoulders of one or two. Some Deputies may say: &ldquo;There is a strong case for a single-seat constituency.&rdquo; The pinning of responsibility on each Deputy may be a strong case for a single-seat constituency or for the transferable vote but we are not discussing the transferable vote or single-seat constituency.</P>
    <P>My line of approach is this.  I shall take County Galway as an example.  I believe that in a county like Galway six or seven Deputies will do as much work, and do it as efficiently as the present number of nine allotted to that county.  The basis on which we are getting nine in that county is that, according to the Taoiseach, we want to give a rural bias on the one hand, and, on the other hand, that parts of Galway, for instance, are so poor and the topographical position is such that it is a great hardship on Deputies to travel to the extreme ends of the county.  Will the same situation not arise if you have ten or twelve Deputies in it?  Would it not be more logical to give representation on the population basis and, where the constituencies are large, perhaps to give an allowance to the Deputies in those large constituencies to travel to various centres, if necessary, to meet their constituents? That would be a far more practical way of dealing with it.</P>
    <P>The sad comment on all this is that in various areas in the West over the past 30 to 35 years the population has been going down year by year.  It is a poor comment that now, while the population is going down and emigration is at a high rate, the one thing Fianna Fáil can promise is that they will not reduce the number of Deputies: &ldquo;Whatever about the people going out of the depressed areas, we shall make sure there will be enough Fianna Fáil Deputies to look after the few who are left.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Again, I want to show how unrealistic this measure is as far as the western areas are concerned.  The constituency I have the honour to represent, that is, Roscommon, is about to lose a seat under this Bill.  I am satisfied with that arrangement.  Let nobody be under the illusion that I am arguing on a personal basis in this matter. <Col N="491" /> The Taoiseach and the Minister have said they are anxious for representation in rural Ireland and particularly in the West.  I want to show how hollow these statements are and how they are trying to cod the public.</P>
    <P>Roscommon is a rural area and a western constituency.  It ranks for treatment under the Undeveloped Areas Act just the same as Galway and elsewhere.  In addition, the topographical features are such that it is 75-80 miles long.  It is a long, narrow county and it is a difficult one to travel, in many ways, as far as the area is concerned.  It has many of the characteristics of the counties which have received special consideration from the Government.  I admit that it did receive special consideration but not of the type that Galway and Donegal got.  If the same yardstick, as far as population is concerned, were applied in Galway as has been applied in Roscommon then Galway would now be receiving a representation of seven Deputies instead of nine.</P>
    <P>Roscommon has lost one seat and, on the basis of the statistics and figures of population, Galway should have seven Deputies.  Why is it suggested that Galway should, under the circumstances, be looked upon as a rural area?  According to the Taoiseach, he is looking for a rural bias.  Is there anything less rural about Roscommon than there is about Galway?  The figures I have given for Roscommon apply to Cavan and the situation I have outlined in Galway applies also in Donegal.  Now can we see what has happened?  The anxiety displayed by the Taoiseach for rural Ireland comes about because he feels that, in the areas mentioned, Donegal and Galway, if the reduction which should take place were made, Fianna Fáil would be sufferers to the extent of at least three seats.  They cannot afford that&mdash;big and all as their majority may be now.</P>
    <P>In order to put it across to the public that this is a measure designed to give a rural bias and to show how keen the present Taoiseach is on reviving rural Ireland and expanding it, <Col N="492" /> he had the temerity to come into this House and suggest that the measure is for the protection of rural Ireland when, in fact, it was really for the protection of a number of Fianna Fáil Deputies.  It is also a significant fact in relation to the area mentioned, that is, particularly West Galway and Donegal&mdash;places on the West coast&mdash; that the more depressed the area, the stronger the Fianna Fáil representation has been in the past ten or 12 years.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FintanCoogan" hpid="Mr. Coogan Mr. Coogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I weakened it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to put it to the Minister that the people in these areas and in the West generally are more anxious for help in so far as agricultural expansion, fishing, and the setting-up of industries based on agriculture are concerned.  They are far more anxious that practical steps be taken in these respects to absorb those who are emigrating and those who are unemployed rather than to have themselves over-represented, as far as rural Deputies are concerned.  I do not think that if another 5,6,8,9 or 10 Deputies were offered in the West of Ireland it would be the solution for the problems that exist there.  It would appear that, so far, at any rate, it is the only solution that is being offered.  I am afraid the offer is being made for the purpose of protecting political Parties and their back-benchers rather than for the benefit of the community.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am not one of those who believe under any circumstances that a Deputy's duty is the same as that of a county councillor.  I do not want to go into that aspect in any detail. However, it would appear that that is the mentality that is being displayed at the moment.  That is the parish pump mentality, as far as a Deputy's functions are concerned&mdash;that he should go around practically from townland to townland with his hand behind his ear listening to every kind of grievance that can be put to him. That is the view that is expressed from the Fianna Fáil benches.  Of course, it may be suitable for the clique that control the Party to have their back-benchers' time absorbed by this kind of work.  It certainly gives more scope to <Col N="493" /> those who run the Party to carry out their plans.  They will not be troubled by Deputies kicking up rows about the adoption of certain lines of policy, because those Deputies are up to their eyes in constituency work which should not be put on their shoulders at all.</P>
    <P>I shall not delay the House on this any longer.  I do not suppose at this stage we can do much to have a general review of the position as far as representation is concerned and to have a clear discussion on non-Party lines as to what the real functions of Deputies are and what their duties should be as regards this House and as regards the general public.  The Bill as it is will not get my blessing but I am sure that will not cause the Government any concern wathever.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Constitution requires us to have some Electoral Amendment Bill at this time and accordingly this Bill, in some form, must pass.  There are, however, certain considerations in relation to it to which I think it may be well to refer, especially in the light of the Taoiseach's observations last night.</P>
      <P>I want to deprecate here in Parliament, as I have deprecated down the country, what I believe to be the widely held view that the number of Deputies is grossly excessive.  That is an entirely illusory belief.  Parliament is a very precious institution to our people.  On its effective functioning ultimately depends the individual liberty of the humblest as well as the most powerful citizen of this State.  On its effective functioning depends what I think is most precious in a free democracy, the certainty that there is no individual, however obscure, on whose person injustice can be wrought without, in the last analysis, his representative having the right to raise his case here in an assembly truly representative of the Irish people and without his having the fair certainty that if gross injustice is threatened the weight of feeling in this House will effectively put matters to right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is not a Dáil of professional politicians.  A strong argument can be made for establishing a Dáil on that basis and it is no harm to remind ourselves <Col N="494" /> and to remind our neighbours that that is the practice in the United States of America where every member of Congress receives an annual allowance of $22,500 and very extensive amenities by way of clerical assistance and otherwise in order to facilitate the performance of his duty as a representative of the people.  That is their system.</P>
    <P>In Great Britain, Parliament is moving more and more to the view that Members of Parliament should receive salaries which render them independent of any other occupation while they continue to be Members of the House.  I can remember when Members of Parliament in the British House of Commons got nothing, no allowance at all and no travelling expenses.  I can remember when distinguished Irishmen represented this country in the British House of Commons without compensation of any kind and, because they were poor, lived in single tenement rooms in London while they discharged their duty as representatives of our people in that deliberative assembly.  Now I believe Members of the British House of Commons receive something like £1,750 a year and travelling allowances.</P>
    <P>Every Deputy in this House who is not a member of the Government has to earn his living as best he may while he is attending this House and doing work for his constituency.  Most Deputies by bitter experience know that if they come from rural Ireland they have to meet lodging expenses and expenses of meals while they are in the city of Dublin attending to their Parliamentary duties, and if they look after their constituents as is their duty they have not much left out of the annual allowance of £600 a year they receive at present as Deputies of Dáil Éireann.</P>
    <P>All of us who are not members of the Government are part-time employees. All of us must retain a sufficiency of free time to earn our living while we continue as representatives here.  I want to say quite deliberately that, in my judgment, the number of Deputies is barely adequate effectively to carry on the day-to-day business <Col N="495" /> transacted in this Chamber and the business carried on in the various committees of this House in which Deputies are obliged to participate if required to do so by the Dáil.  There are the Committee of Public Accounts, the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, the Committee of Selection and a variety of other committees continually operating.</P>
    <P>I do not agree with Deputy McQuillan that it is a bad thing that Deputies should be kept in constant touch by their constituents with their personal problems and difficulties.  I think one of the most useful functions a public representative can discharge is to look after the problems of his constituents and help them wherever he can.  That burden could be lightened if there was, as I suggested on another occasion, a complaints officer similar to the public official that exists in Sweden, Norway and Denmark.  However, even if such a public officer existed I still believe there would be a large volume of work which would properly devolve upon a Deputy.  That is a good thing because it brings constantly present to the minds of our people the fact that Parliament is the citadel of their liberty, that it is not something remote and distant from simple people, that the simplest man or woman in Ireland is entitled to have his rights defended from the front bench or the back bench of any Party in this House. Any Minister from the Taoiseach down to the most junior member of the Government can be called to the front Government benches to account to this House for any alleged injustice by the Executive against the humblest citizen of this State.</P>
    <P>That is a link between the people and the Parliament which is infinitely precious and which can be maintained by nobody but the Deputy representing his constituents.  Therefore, I believe if Parliament is to function properly Deputies must be here in sufficient numbers to enable them to represent the people on that basis. They must be here in sufficient numbers to permit of their getting their work done and, included in that work, <Col N="496" /> a constant readiness to represent individual constituents where they believe some fundamental right is challenged. I agree with Deputy McQuillan that all of us have experience of people asking Deputies sometimes to do outlandish things.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Sometimes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, I think Deputy McQuillan will agree with me that, on balance, although you sometimes do get outlandish requests if you take the trouble to write to the person and explain that what he is seeking is quite impossible and outlandish, in 99 per cent. of the cases the person will be satisfied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWMoher" hpid="Mr. Moher Mr. Moher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moher</NameTxt>
      <P>He will try the other fellow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, is not that a good thing, that our people have never felt themselves, and should never be made to feel themselves, the bond-slaves of any Deputy?  If I should fail a constituent in Monaghan, is it not a good thing that he should test my performance by going to another Deputy from Monaghan and finding out whether I failed because I had not bothered or whether I failed because it was not possible to have his request met?  I rejoice that that is so.  Of course, we know of people going sometimes to a Fianna Fáil Deputy and then to a Fine Gael Deputy and subsequently to a Labour Deputy and not infrequently protesting that it never occurred to them to go to anybody else but to each one after the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I never realised that fully until I became a Minister and frequently opened files to find four letters addressed to four different groups, each letter protesting that the writer was the undying and unswerving supporter of the particular Party.  I am obliged to say that while I may not admire the veracity of the writer I rejoice that he felt he had that right. I particularly rejoice that here were three or four Deputies all of whom had taken the trouble to tackle the Minister and see if relief could be obtained.  It must have been discouraging <Col N="497" /> for the original correspondent to get the same letter from the same Minister in each of the four cases.  He must have sat down at the end and said that at least the first man was an honest man, that he had tried and had failed.  Far from disparaging that, as Deputy McQuillan appeared to do&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I did not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, I may have misunderstood the Deputy.  I think that very feeling on the part of the writer of that letter, and his neighbours and friends, made him realise that this Parliament was his Parliament and that his claim had to be heard by the responsible Minister of the Executive when he invoked his parliamentary representative.  It would be a tragic thing if from an obscurantist desire for false economy, we so reduced the number of Deputies in this House as to make that continuous process impossible. Parliament, I feel, would have lost a great part of its value as an instrument of individual liberty. That after all in the last analysis is its principal justification.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>In the cases that the Deputy referred to would he not agree that it would be more desirable to have a grievance officer to deal with those matters rather than have the time of Deputies taken up replying to letters of that nature?  I do not want to deprive any individual of his right to appeal but if a grievance officer were appointed such matters could be directed to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that a great many such matters could be directed to him.  I think there is a certain merit, however, in the fact that if some poor person approaches Deputy McQuillan and he wants to press that person's point, very frequently he will go himself to the Department to have the matter settled.  Supposing he does not get satisfaction and I am the Minister for Agriculture.  He comes to my private secretary and asks for an interview and presents the case to me.  If the request cannot be met he will say: &ldquo;Well, if this cannot be <Col N="498" /> done I should be most obliged if you would write me a letter explaining why it cannot be done.&rdquo;  In the last analysis it is a good thing that Deputy McQuillan can say: &ldquo;I forced this matter up to the level of the Minister and that is his letter.  If that does not please you I shall put down a Parliamentary Question and have it answered in public.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I agree that many current matters could be attended to on the lines of the Scandinavian grievance officer but there is a lot to be said for our system which, in the last analysis, enables the humblest person to bring the Taoiseach or any Minister to the Front Bench to answer what he believes to be a legitimate complaint.</P>
      <P>That deals with the general question of the number of Deputies in Dáil Éireann which was mentioned by the Taoiseach yesterday.  That general question is governed by the Constitutional provision fixing one Deputy for every 20,000 to 30,000 citizens of the State.  In the drafting of this Bill I think it is true that when the Taoiseach speaks of the Government's solicitude for maintaining a rural bias&mdash;which I endorse and approve&mdash;it is a striking thing that the rural bias has turned up so dramatically in Galway.</P>
      <P>In Roscommon and Cavan, and even in Cork, the same passionate solicitude has not been made manifest. When we recall that Fianna Fáil have one seat out of four in Roscommon and never had more, and can never hope for more, than two out of four in Cavan then the rural character has assumed, in the eyes of Fianna Fáil, a somewhat autumnal shade.  In Galway the shades have been more happy and we are in the full blast of spring.  Recently I met a Deputy&mdash;a representative of Galway&mdash;bounding down the steps of Leinster House when the Electoral Bill was first published saying: &ldquo;My God, is it not wonderful news?  They are not taking a single seat from Galway?&rdquo;  I have great sympathy with the Deputy in question but it spoke eloquently to me of the quality of Fianna Fáil's rural bias.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>What about Wexford?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="499" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not believe that anybody in the House believes that the Minister for Local Government and his colleagues sat down and engaged on this work with the detachment and objectivity of an archangel.  I am quite prepared to say they genuinely desired to preserve rural bias in some measure to off-set the world phenomenon, as it is manifest in Ireland, of the flight from the land to urban centres, but I think it is noteworthy that this rural bias turned up so dramatically in Donegal, Galway, and Kerry and that there was no corresponding reaction in Roscommon or Cavan, which I can certify to the House, from personal experience, are fully rural constituencies.</P>
      <P>There have emerged from the discussion so far two net problems, one, in relation to the representation of Dublin where there appear to be two Deputies less than the population would justify, and another problem in connection with mid-Cork, where two reasonably manageable constituencies have been converted into one constituency, which is as bad as any constituency in Ireland from the point of view of attempting effectively to represent or campaign in it.  I do not think I greatly exaggerate when I say you can travel nearly 100 miles from one end of mid-Cork to the other.  It is manifest that that situation creates a problem.</P>
      <P>It has been suggested that we investigate the possibility of arriving at some more rational arrangement in connection with these specific problems. We might have some discussions through the usual channels, through the Whips, and I understand that proposal meets with the approval of the Taoiseach and the Minister for Local Government.  If it does, we shall be very glad to join in the discussions to see if we can find a generally acceptable solution for those apparent flaws in these proposals.  I think it will be a useful thing to do.  If we cannot, then we shall have to agree to differ and let the matter be finally settled by the arbitrament of a Dáil decision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think it is a good thing, where at all possible, that the work of this House should be done by agreement <Col N="500" /> always provided that if we do not agree, we can agree to differ without growing to hate one another.  I think it is a desirable thing that we should seek, by consultation, to remove the flaws which appear to this House to disfigure these electoral proposals, with special reference to the situation in Cork and Dublin.  I understand the suggestion has been made that we should have discussions some day next week and, if they produce a degree of agreement, on the next Stage of this Bill, we can communicate that to the House and it will be for the House to determine for itself whether it agrees or not.  If we do not agree, on the next Stage of the Bill, every Deputy who is in a Party or who is not in a Party can present his proposals for the improvement of this Bill, and they can be debated and determined by the ordinary processes of Dáil Éireann.</P>
    <P>In the meantime, I want to reaffirm the sentiments with which I opened my observations, that this Dáil is a citadel of the individual liberty of the humblest citizen of this State.  The day it ceases effectively to function, the one who will suffer most is the most defenceless person in the country. It cannot function without an adequate number of Deputies to carry on all its work.  I believe that our present numbers represent pretty near the minimum with which it is possible effectively to do that, and I do not think this House should ever yield to suggestions, from any source, that we should reduce the number of representatives in this House to a level that would turn this Parliament into a fraudulent facade.  Accordingly, I suggest that after a full debate of the measure, and by consultation, at a later stage any flaws that may be in it may be removed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrowne" hpid="Mr. S. Browne Mr. S. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to delay the Minister's reply very much. I shall be very brief.  I should first like to congratulate him on this measure, with the exception of one or two matters.  I think one of the primary objectives the Minister had in mind was to confirm the existing representation of rural Ireland in Dáil Éireann, so far as it was possible to <Col N="501" /> do so.  He has assured us, and I think the Taoiseach also did so in his statement yesterday evening, that he is prepared to take full advantage of the provisions of the Constitution to do so.  To my mind, that is a very wise and very proper decision.</P>
      <P>It came somewhat as a surprise to me to find some of the leading lights in the Fine Gael Party strongly opposing this measure on the ground that it gives an unfair representation to rural Ireland at the expense of Dublin city.  In recent years, I have listened to some of those Deputies claim that this Party here is city-minded, and that this Government of ours are a city-minded Government.  It is very hard to reconcile such statements with their present claims for more city representation at the expense of rural Ireland.</P>
      <P>I claim that it is a much more difficult task to represent a rural constituency than a city one.  Let me say straight away that a city Deputy, who has just as large a volume of work to get through as the majority of rural Deputies, has not the same difficulties of travel and distance to contend with in his work.  It has been said by Deputy Donnellan, I think, that a threepenny bus ride will take a Dublin Deputy from one end of his constituency to another.  I for one doubt if C.I.E. is so generous, but, at any rate, I think a 6d. bus ride would take a Dublin Deputy from one end of his constituency to another.  On the other hand, let us examine the situation in any rural constituency.  Take my own rural constituency of Wexford.  Deputy Alien and Deputy Esmonde in the north of that county would travel approximately a round journey of 150 miles to meet their constituents in the South.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think the Minister would be very wise to keep the membership of this House at the highest possible level, and he has given us an assurance to that effect.  There are those who write flowery, well-paid articles in some of our local and daily papers claiming that a much lesser number of Deputies would suffice to represent the people. I claim that they know little of a Deputy's duties and the volume of <Col N="502" /> work a Deputy has to do.</P>
    <P>Deputy McQuillan referred, I think, to some of these duties.  Whether he likes it or not, a Deputy must perform these duties&mdash;they are the duties of a member of the House and have grown up with the House.  A Deputy in many ways must be a glorified Social Welfare officer and an expert on many things.  He must be a bit of a county manager, a legal adviser, an expert on health matters and most other things. Taking them by and large, I would say emphatically that Deputies provide the people of this country with one of its best and certainly with one of its cheapest services.</P>
    <P>That brings me to the point I want to deal with specifically, the case of Wexford constituency.  The Minister claimed in his opening speech that he erred on the side of leniency in dealing with our rural constituencies.  He certainly deserves full marks for that, and indeed a bonus mark, as far as I am concerned.  Wexford is one of the counties where the Minister did not err on the side of leniency.  It cannot be alleged that he is reducing the representation of Wexford county in Dáil Éireann for political motives.  I think that is the last thing that can be alleged in this case.</P>
    <P>Deputy Corish yesterday made a very good case for the retention of the five seats in Wexford.  I do not wish to follow Deputy Corish on some of the lines which he took in making that case.  For instance, he suggested that we might again take in part of Carlow. I have no territorial ambitions that way.  We had portion of the Carlow area attached to Wexford for Dáil election purposes some years back and the Wexford representatives were very proud to represent that portion of Carlow.  The Carlow people are a very fine people&mdash;there is no doubt about that&mdash;and if they were willing or wished to come in with Wexford again, I am sure the present Dáil representatives of Wexford would be equally proud and happy to represent them. But we do not wish to take in any territory.  I do not think it is wise to do so unless the people are willing and unless their own representatives in Dáil Éireann wish to have this done.</P>
    <P>In Wexford, I think we have a very <Col N="503" /> good case for retaining the five Deputies without seeking any outside territory or assistance.  We have practically the required number.  In the last election our quota was one of the highest in Ireland and at the present time our number of Dáil electors per seat under the new proposals would be one of the highest in Ireland and would be bracketed with the Dublin figures. Under the new proposal of 21,815 of the population per seat, it would mean that there would be five constituencies in Ireland with less, two with the same and seven on a par with that, seven slightly greater.  We would be on a par with 15, roughly speaking.</P>
    <P>Taking our present figures without any change there would be four with less, five with the same and four with a slightly greater number, putting Wexford County on a par with 14 of the new constituencies in accordance with the proposals in this measure.</P>
    <P>We have a great case in Wexford for the retention of five seats, the five seats we had since this Parliament was set up.  It is a large county with circumstances somewhat similar to those of other counties with which the Minister has dealt leniently, counties like Donegal, Galway and Kerry.  I make a strong appeal to the Minister to reconsider this matter and allow Wexford its present representation in Dáil Éireann.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FintanCoogan" hpid="Mr. Coogan Mr. Coogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not propose to delay the Bill, but, as I see it, this Bill is so framed because the people refused to abolish proportional representation. That is my view but I may be wrong.  I think it is the view held throughout the country also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not hold with Deputy McQuillan that we should have a complaints officer.  Every Deputy elected to this House knew why he was elected&mdash;to represent the people and make representations on their behalf.  No Deputy was forced into this House against his will and he knew why he was coming in.  Why then delegate his duties or the duties he accepted by appointing a complaints officer?  I think we have 39 constituencies and I know it would <Col N="504" /> be nice to have 39 complaints officers, one for each constituency.  I think that would be a case for getting rid of T.D.s</P>
    <P>I live in Galway City.  I am at the border of three constituencies; all roads lead to Galway as far as I am concerned from the other constituencies. I must listen to the complaints from one end of the county to the other.  I am not complaining myself about it but I am just putting the case that I knew before I came here on the last occasion that I would have to do this, even though my own constituency goes from Boffin Island to Oranmore and from there to the Aran Islands.  It is a 24 hour job to do what is required.  I am not complaining. I have listened with interest to other Deputies talking about cutting the representation of county Galway.  I am not saying it could not be done; in fact, I am not afraid of it if it is done; but I know the reason it is not being done and every member of the House knows why it is not being done.  It is not being done because if you were to cut the representation of county Galway, you would cut seats from Fianna Fáil.  That is the only reason.</P>
    <P>Mark you, they could afford to lose a seat in part of Galway.  If all the Deputies, or even half of them, did as much as I do, Galway would be very well represented and could, I think, afford to lose a seat on those grounds. That is why I say this Bill was framed so as not to injure Party interests.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceEDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall not delay the Minister very long but I feel I must support the various members who have spoken on the question of over-all representation in this House.  The Taoiseach mentioned it and Deputy Dillon and other members have referred to it.  It is very important that our people should realise that if representation here falls below a certain figure&mdash;and already with the number of Deputies we have at the moment, it is, in my opinion, too low&mdash;we would not be able adequately to carry out the functions of a Government or an Opposition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If it went any lower, we would not <Col N="505" /> be able adequately to carry out the functions of a Government and an Opposition.  The difficulty which the selection of a Deputy entails is not generally realised.  If you cut down your numbers, you will not adequately be able to appoint sufficient Ministers or Parliamentary Secretaries.  Exactly the same will apply on the Opposition side of the House with regard to a shadow Cabinet for the manning of various committees which are essential to the adequate running of the House.</P>
    <P>There is a point on the general question of representation which I do not think has been dealt with very much on this Bill.  We have 22 three-member constituencies.  Those three-member constituencies in most places constitute marginal constituencies. That is to say, the Fianna Fáil Party instituted those constituencies in the hope at the time they would almost certainly be the gainers, but the position in regard to them is very much altered in recent years.  What is not altered is the fact that, under proportional representation when you have three-member constituencies, you do not get proportional representation working properly.  You are, in effect, disfranchising a large number of your constituents.  They are not getting adequate representation and so I feel that, at this time, at least one voice must say that the way in which our constituencies are carved up into three-member constituencies is not giving complete justice to our people and is not giving representation in the way in which the system under which we work intended them to be given.</P>
    <P>I think that we must view this matter from the widest possible point of view and not as Deputy James Dillon said from the point of view of archangels.  Nevertheless, we must approach this from the population basis and on that basis Dublin is slightly under-represented and the west is slightly over-represented.  I consider that Dublin could be given more representation and possibly it could be knocked off somewhere in the West.  I would suggest that if there are any alterations to be made <Col N="506" /> it should be borne very much in mind that three-member constituencies, wherever possible, should be amalgamated and larger areas should be made.  I know that sometimes it has been said in the case of Cork that there are geographical difficulties but that does not apply to some of the constituencies here in Dublin and the areas surrounding Dublin.  There could well be amalgamation and greater representation given to the citizens in those areas.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Minister for Local Government (Mr. Blaney) Neil T. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government (Mr. Blaney)</NameTxt>
      <P>Certain arguments run through many of the speeches on this Bill.  One of them is that the sole intention of the Government and myself in framing this Bill, was to try, as some Deputy put it, to rob the people of Dublin of their representation and in some way or another pass over that representation to the country but only to selected areas of the country from which we, as a Party in Fianna Fáil, would hope to gain the greatest advantage.  In following that line of argument, it has also been suggested that one of the prime reasons motivating our actions in this alleged way is that we have been beaten at various elections in Dublin in the recent past.</P>
      <P>I could possibly make an argument as to the truth of whether or not we were beaten in Dublin on the votes that were trotted out here as examples by these people but I want to say at the outset that we are not robbing Dublin.  It has not been our intention to rob Dublin of representation.  It should be clearly understood that Dublin is, in fact, despite all the talk, getting and retaining as many seats next year, the year after and possibly for the next 12 years, as the people of Dublin have had during the past 12 years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is suggested that we are, in fact, giving over-representation to particular parts of the country.  Notably Galway and Donegal are chosen for the brunt of the attack.  We are not giving anything new to Galway, Donegal, Mayo, Clare, Kerry or West Cork. We are merely retaining what they had and the reason we are retaining what they had in the past, is that <Col N="507" /> these counties have one thing in common above all others.  From West Cork to North Donegal, along the entire western seaboard, there is a similar type of terrain and geographical layout&mdash;indented coasts and difficulty of travel over mountainous country.  We have our population scattered here, there and everywhere, in almost inaccessible places, in small groups and in isolated houses with long journeys to be covered to get to the point, as in my own constituency which, as the crow flies or across the sea, is only 12 miles, yet it takes a journey of 88 miles to get from one point to the other, namely from Fanad Head to Malin Head.</P>
    <P>I come from Fanad Peninsula myself.  I represent Fanad in the East Donegal constituency.  If and when I want to go to Fanad Head or if anybody from there wants to come and see me, the return journey is 176 miles and yet we hear people talk here as if this question of mileage and geography meant nothing whatever when it comes to sitting down to try to work out, within the framework of the Constitution, a fair and equitable distribution of seats and a fair and equitable representation for our people.</P>
    <P>If our people cannot get to their representatives and if the representatives have grave difficulty in getting to all of their people now and again, it cannot be said that those people are fairly or equitably represented for the very good reason that a Deputy placed in such a position cannot have the knowledge he requires, as to the wants and needs of his various constituents and cannot do justice to them in this House.</P>
    <P>It is on that theme and on that note that I, as Minister for Local Government and with the Government's full knowledge, have had to tackle this problem with the officials of my Department, to try to give fair and equitable representation to all our people, no matter where they may live, in the Twenty-Six Counties.</P>
    <P>Galway and Donegal have been mentioned very specifically.  They have been taken as the examples where <Col N="508" /> Fianna Fáil support has been consistent and sound over a long number of years and that very support which has been in evidence there for so many years is now being given to this House as the reason, and the only real reason, why we have left Donegal untouched. I have not had time to find out; I have looked around a bit, but let me say particularly to those who talked of Donegal and of misrepresentation in East Donegal that I do not know of any other constituency in this country with four seats or three seats that entails journeys as long as that of which I have given an example here today and included in my speech here last night and that is only one example of the long journeys that are necessary to get from one point to another in East Donegal.</P>
    <P>Some people seemed to think that East Donegal is the flat, fertile part of our county.  Nothing could be further from the truth.  It is true that there is the flat, fertile valley in the east of the county in that constituency but there is also the whole Inishowen peninsula which is as awkward to get around as are many entire constituencies in the middle of the country. There are also the peninsulas running right along the Fanad, Rosguill and back to the Dunfanaghy area and, to complicate matters still further, there is the mountain range which practically divides the northern part of the county from the southern half.</P>
    <P>If we were to reduce the representation in Donegal, we would merely reduce East Donegal by a seat.  We might theoretically give part of the now known East Donegal constituency to West Donegal.  In theory, that would be the case, but, in practice, what is north of that mountain range, if represented at all, would have to be represented by the East Donegal Deputies and not by the West Donegal Deputies, for the good reason that these people are really cut across; they are cut off from the west and it would be trying to lift something from one side of the mountains over to the other side, and I do not think that would be satisfactory to the people or to the representatives in West Donegal and I do not think it would be fair <Col N="509" /> to the new, reduced number in East Donegal that three of them should in future have to represent the number of people that are in a four seat constituency and should have to do it in a county and a constituency which, as far as travel is concerned, is one of the most difficult in Ireland.</P>
    <P>We come now to Mayo.  There has been no outcry whatever against Mayo.  Why, I do not know.  When we get down to Galway, we find a lot of allegations being made as to why Galway is left alone.  Kerry is mentioned also, but not so violently as are Galway and Donegal.  No mention whatever is made of the fact that we have left West Cork as it is and nobody can suggest that in leaving West Cork as it is, we are doing something to the benefit of our own narrow political Party view.  Nobody can suggest that.  We are being consistent from West Cork to North Donegal in dealing with similar counties and similar types of terrain and people living in a similar manner, generally speaking.  We have been consistent in dealing with the counties that are favourable to Fianna Fáil and those that are not favourable to Fianna Fáil and no better instance in that regard can be quoted than, on existing figures, West Cork.</P>
    <P>There is also South Kerry.  We have nothing to gain there as the figures now indicate.  In regard to North Kerry, it cannot be said that we hope to get three out of the four seats there in future.  Clare has been left as it is, and what is wrong with leaving Galway, Mayo and Donegal as they are?  From a political point of view, the argument that has been used here is not only without foundation but, taken in conjunction with the other counties of the western seaboard that have been similarly treated in this Bill, is fully exploded and there cannot be any suggestion that this Bill was framed with the one idea in mind, namely, perpetuating where possible and bolstering up the Fianna Fáil support.</P>
    <P>Neither is it true to say that we are taking something from Dublin and giving it to the western seaboard for the motives that have been alleged&mdash;Party <Col N="510" /> motives.  It cannot be alleged that we are taking something from Dublin and giving it to the western seaboard for these base motives that have been suggested. We are leaving Dublin as it is and I am sure that the people of Dublin would be the first to agree that, with representation as we have outlined it and propose in this Bill, they are in a better position to get better service more conveniently from the number of Deputies we are still leaving in Dublin city than any resident in any constituency from North Donegal right down to Cork.</P>
    <P>There can be no suggestion that, because there is an average of 23,000 or 24,000 electors in any of the Dublin city constituencies per Deputy, any elector cannot be properly represented by his Deputy or will be less well represented than his counterpart in Donegal, Galway, Kerry or West Cork where the average per Deputy may be as low as 16,000, 17,000 or 18,000.  Any reasonable person outside this House, in Dublin, will readily agree that 30 Deputies for the county and city of Dublin leave no cause for complaint of their being under-represented in this House.  It is all too easy to juggle with figures, to come along here, state the average numbers in this constituency or that, and, on the figures alone, to produce a picture that seems to bolster up some of the allegations made here.</P>
    <P>My introductory speech has been misquoted.  I should like to reiterate one sentence I used which was misrepresented by the very first speaker who got up.  I said &ldquo;It is for these reasons&rdquo;&mdash;the reasons about which I have just been talking&mdash;&ldquo;that the proposals in the Bill may appear, if viewed in a purely statistical light, to err on the side of leniency as far as rural representation is concerned.&rdquo; Regardless of what has been said by any other speaker here, I maintain that the figures merely give an appearance of erring on the side of leniency as far as the rural areas are concerned.  If we were not circumscribed by the provisions we have to fulfil in this matter and if I personally had the doing of this without any let or hindrance, there would be quite a few more Deputies from rural Ireland. <Col N="511" /> They would not be brought in to back up any political Party but purely because of the fact that the people of rural Ireland are entitled to have sufficient Deputies to represent them and to have the opportunity of meeting those Deputies conveniently without too much expense, travel or waste of time.</P>
    <P>That is not possible at the moment. The distances some of our people have to travel to meet their representatives and, in turn, the distances the representatives have to travel to meet their people are beyond reason.  It is not possible for many Deputies in these scattered and difficult constituencies to give sufficient representation to their people or to meet them sufficiently often.  A Deputy may be at home for only two or three nights, particularly when the House is in session.  He may also be on some local bodies and may not be available during the weekdays.  People who want to see him urgently may have to travel 90 miles to do so.  They have to try to make a fixed appointment with him; they may have to travel 80 or 90 miles to meet him or he may have to travel that distance to have an interview with them in regard to some individual case.  Any Deputy from rural Ireland knows how difficult it is to find suitable times to interview constituents and to travel the journeys required, and then the Deputy has to see to all the grievances he hears as he goes around.  That brings me to the several speakers who suggested we had too many Deputies in this House.  Possibly we have, but, for the reasons I have stated, I do not think so.  I think rural Ireland is under-represented&mdash;not directly represented because we have not sufficient Deputies and in existing circumstances we cannot very well have more without doing what has been said here we have already done: robbing Dublin and giving seats to the country.</P>
    <P>We have not done that.  If we were to give rural Ireland adequate, equal and fair representation as compared with the cities and the urbans, then we would be forced to rob the cities, if you like, in order to bolster <Col N="512" /> up the representation in the country. We are not doing that; we have not done it; and we do not intend to do it.</P>
    <P>It has been suggested here that one of the proofs that we have too many Deputies is the fact that Deputies spend far too much of their time as messenger boys and grievance officers of their people.  That system has grown up in this country and it is still growing.  The fact is that, with very rare exceptions, any Deputy who does not like that system and refuses to be that sort of Deputy, will not be a Deputy for very long.  You can take it or leave it; that is the position.  Like it or not, every Deputy knows that is the pattern of the life of a Deputy in this country today.</P>
    <P>I would go further and say that the further west you go, the more has that pattern developed.  I think that is due to the special circumstances of the people of the western seaboard where a greater variety of social benefit and other special Government schemes have been in operation over the years. Every new scheme brings more work to the door of the Deputy in that part of the country.  So we have the pattern well and truly laid of the Deputies being the grievance officers as well as the representatives of their people here.</P>
    <P>As I say, that pattern has developed along the western seaboard more than it has in the east and the midlands, and it is one of the reasons why the western seaboard has been given special treatment in that we have not reduced the representation enjoyed there.  In those areas, the people have more occasion to have recourse to their Deputies and to enlist their aid than the people in other parts of the country.  That, added to the geographical difficulties and the montainous terrain of the western seaboard with its indented coastline, makes it imperative that the representation in that part of the country should not be further reduced.  If there appears to be some disparity in our approach to the western seaboard as against some other rural counties, such as Roscommon, Wexford, Longford, Westmeath and Cavan&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Col N="513" />
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Mr. O'Sullivan Mr. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>Or Cork.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is true to say that, if we had sufficient seats to go round in all those counties, and if the situation were such that we could have more seats to satisfy all these rural constituencies, then we would not find ourselves in this House today being attacked by anybody from any of these constituencies because of a reduction. It is all very well to get up and make a case for Wexford.  A very good case can be made for Wexford and, if I were a Wexford Deputy, it is the case I should make.  But I could make an equally good case for Roscommon.  I could make an equally good case for Longford-Westmeath. I could make an equally good case for Cavan.  If I were a Cork Deputy, I could make a good case why Cork should get their twelfth seat in the county, or their 17 seats over the whole county and city.  But the position is not on all-fours with the cases made by the Deputies who have spoken here so far.</P>
      <P>In our Bill, we have distributed 142 seats.  Under the Constitution, we could have 144 seats.  We have, as it were, two seats and the question arises as to where those two seats should be allotted, how many claimants there are for them and how many good cases can be made for them.  It is not just a case of one good case, or two good cases.  At least five good cases can be made for these two seats, excluding the case that has been made for Dublin city so ably last night by its representatives here.  Five good cases can be made in rural Ireland for these two seats, two seats over and above those we have already distributed.  It is not quite true to say that we have two seats to spare or to ask why we do not give one of those to Roscommon. It is not quite fair to ask why we do not reduce Roscommon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The question is: why did we reduce Roscommon?  If we had not reduced Roscommon, could we have reduced Cavan?  Could we have reduced Longford-Westmeath?  Could we have reduced Wexford?  Could we <Col N="514" /> have reduced Cork?  If we had not made any reduction in such cases, we would have had to reduce somewhere else.  From the general tone of the debate, it would appear that we would have had to reduce Dublin by three, four or five seats.  We were not prepared to do that.  That is the situation. It is completely unrealistic to argue that we have these two seats to spare and that they should be allotted to this, that or the other constituency, when five good cases could be made in rural Ireland alone for the retention of seats.  But five will not go into two.</P>
    <P>Remember, that that does not take cognisance of the case made by Dublin for more seats than it now has.  If there seems to be a disparity or an apparent difference in our approach to various parts of rural Ireland, as instanced by the case of Wexford, Longford-Westmeath, Cavan and Roscommon, it is for the very good reason that if we were to treat all these as we have treated the western seaboard, we would have had to take seats from other areas, and the only areas from which we could have taken seats are the cities.  Cork city and Dublin city would have had to bear reductions in order that these counties might be left as they are.</P>
    <P>Despite the fact that Roscommon is west of the Shannon, it cannot be argued here by any reasonable man that, if one compares it and the necessity for its retaining a fourth seat with my own constituency, for instance, and the necessity for its retaining its fourth seat, the choice could have been other than it is.  Any reasonable person who travels over the two constituencies and who appreciates the implications of the difficulties of travel and the inaccessibility generally in my constituency would not for a moment hesitate as between the two.  He would not for a moment hesitate as to which of the two should have four seats and which should have three.</P>
    <P>Choice had to be made.  That choice has been made in the Bill now before the House, not only in regard to Roscommon and Donegal, but in regard to the other western counties <Col N="515" /><i>versus</i> the midland and other counties. In my opinion, they need the representation they have.  Indeed, I think they should, if possible, have more representation. But we cannot give more representation because we are not entitled to do so under our Constitution, unless we take seats from some other area.</P>
    <P>From the outset, it has been our avowed intention in our approach to this whole matter not to reduce representation in any area, if we could possibly avoid it.  I have painted the picture for the House.  I hope Deputies appreciate the difficulties.  I trust that my explanation will clear their minds of any idea that these things are done purely from the point of view of Party political advantage.  We have faced the facts of the situation to the best of our ability.</P>
    <P>It was suggested by the Taoiseach yesterday and by the Leader of the Opposition, Deputy Dillon, this morning that between now and the Committee Stage, there might be some possibility of agreed solutions in regard to the changes.  Naturally, I, as Minister for Local Government, will be very happy if some satisfactory agreement can be reached in regard to these two floating seats, if one may so describe them.  I have grave doubts of finding an agreeable solution, a solution agreeable to all Parties, when one remembers that there are at least five claimants with five good cases and that to those must be added the claims of Dublin city, the case for which was made so forcibly here last night.  Those who try to find an agreed solution in regard to these two seats will, I believe, find themselves eventually with a much clearer mind on the matter and a much clearer appreciation of the difficulties with which the Government, I and the officers of my Department found ourselves faced in recent weeks in our efforts to solve the problem and bring into the House a Bill which would meet with general agreement.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankSherwin" hpid="Mr. Sherwin Mr. Sherwin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherwin</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask a question? The Minister stressed the problem of rural Deputies having to travel long distances.  He did not answer my point <Col N="516" /> that there should be single-seat constituencies under P.R.  That would solve the problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaSnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot have them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankSherwin" hpid="Mr. Sherwin Mr. Sherwin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherwin</NameTxt>
      <P>We can.  The idea obviously is to keep the small man out. P.R. keeps him in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>In reply to Deputy Sherwin, under the Constitution we may not have constituencies of less than three seats.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankSherwin" hpid="Mr. Sherwin Mr. Sherwin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherwin</NameTxt>
      <P>We can change it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>That would need another Referendum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankSherwin" hpid="Mr. Sherwin Mr. Sherwin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherwin</NameTxt>
      <P>The idea is to keep the small man out.  The big shots and big business do not care.  It is the small man who does all the work.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Sheldon) Acting Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the Committee Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to order it for next Wednesday.  If, however, that does not give sufficient time for the talks to which reference was made, we need not take the Bill on Wednesday. I think we should at least try to conform to constitutional requirements and get the Bill through by 26th November, if possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Mr. O'Sullivan Mr. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>We can order the Bill for Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJohnCorry" hpid="Mr. Corry Mr. Corry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corry</NameTxt>
      <P>That is too soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>We do not necessarily have to take it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps it will not be taken.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 4th November, 1959.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Funds of Suitors Bill," RHead="1959&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Funds of Suitors Bill, 1959&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="517" /> SECTION 2.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before subsection (3) to insert the following new subsection:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(3)  (a) No sum intended to be applied for or towards the rebuilding of the Abbey Theatre, Dublin, shall be paid out of the Capital Fund until:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(i)  the National Theatre Society Limited shall make such alterations in its Memorandum and Articles of Association and take such other steps as may be recommended by a Committee which shall be appointed by the Minister consisting of the Director of An Chomhairle Ealaíon and eleven other persons; or</P>
      <P>(ii)  such alterations are made in the ownership and management of the Abbey Theatre, Dublin, as may be recommended by a Committee which shall be appointed by the Minister consisting of the Director of An Comhairle Ealaíon and eleven other persons.</P>
      <P>(b)  Of the ordinary members of the Committee three shall be authors of plays, three shall be actors, three shall be persons whom the Minister considers to be representative of Irish cultural interests and two shall be persons experienced in the management of theatres.</P>
      <P>My colleague Deputy Ryan and I put down this amendment.  On Second Reading, I attempted to discuss the policy of the Abbey Theatre and I was told to wait for this Stage.  I insisted anyway and I succeeded in putting on the record part of what I wanted to say.  I want to ascertain from the Minister the position as regards the Abbey Theatre.  If this Theatre is built with public money to the amount of £250,000, will it be vested in the directors or the shareholders and directors of the old Abbey Theatre?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFlanagan" hpid="Mr. S. Flanagan Mr. S. Flanagan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Flanagan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this amendment relevant?  Has it been ruled relevant?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>It has not been ruled irrelevant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="518" />
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Traynor) Oscar Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Traynor)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not certain.  I cannot answer the question on the spur of the moment. I should require notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a very important question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the intention?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>It deals with £250,000 of public money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I said in opening that it will be put into the Capital Fund and it will be withdrawn from that, on, I presume, the request of the Minister for Finance, but I cannot answer the question straight away as to whether that complete sum will be handed over to the Abbey directors. It will be handed over only for the definite purpose of the building of the new Abbey Theatre and cannot be used for any other purpose.  I think that is what the Deputy has in mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Not exactly.  I want to make it quite clear that I have no objection to the rebuilding of the Abbey Theatre as soon as possible but I want to know when the £250,000 is handed over to the Abbey Theatre for rebuilding, who will own the Abbey Theatre?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>The present ownership will be carried on.  It will not change, in any respect, the ownership of the Abbey Theatre.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>May I take it then that we are actually giving a present of £250,000 to the present directors of the Abbey?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>We are making a grant of the money to the Abbey. Theatre for the purpose of rebuilding on the old site.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you not giving something worth a quarter of a million pounds?  This new property will be an asset to the national theatre and an asset to the present shareholders. Admittedly, under the Memorandum and Articles of Association, they are not entitled to make a profit&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we to have a sort of spasmodic discussion?  If the <Col N="519" /> amendment is moved, I can perhaps reply at a greater length.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I have moved the amendment as set out on the Order Paper.  I would say that the policy of the management of the Abbey Theatre has not commended itself to people who are interested in the theatre in Ireland and it has not recommended itself to the people who work in the theatre in Ireland.  The Minister said of course that we could look back on the old Abbey and mention names like Lady Gregory, Synge and O'Casey.  They are no longer there. O'Casey is still alive but he left the Abbey Theatre.  There was a great tradition, but the policy that has been carried on for some years past has not done anything to revive that tradition. As a matter of fact, it has stifled it and exasperated many people so that they left the Abbey.  Groups of Abbey actors left and set up in other theatres in Dublin.</P>
      <P>The reason my attention was drawn to this is that I have some interest in the theatre.  The Wexford Theatre Royal was closed&mdash;I mentioned this on Second Reading&mdash;and it was necessary to try to revive that theatre.  A group of people got together and did me the honour of asking me to be chairman.  We opened the theatre and we did not come here to look for money.  If that theatre were burned down, I am sure the Dáil would not build a new one&mdash;nor could we expect it to do so&mdash;and hand it over to me.</P>
      <P>I admit all the time that the Abbey Theatre is a great institution so far as its name is concerned.  I am not jealous of the fact that we are putting up £250,000 of public money which is to be taken from the funds of suitors, but I think that as a public representative the Minister should take steps or precautions to see that the Abbey Theatre is properly run as a national theatre.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I might as well say what my idea of a national theatre is and I should like the Minister to take special note of this.  The Abbey Theatre began in the 1920s after getting a subsidy from the Government.  Touring companies were sent down the <Col N="520" /> country and at that time they did a great deal of good for the Irish theatre.  There is a great amateur theatrical movement all over the country.  As I say, they sent touring companies around the country.  There was always a certain amount of amateur theatricals in the country but the standard was very low.  I admit that the fact that professionals went to the smaller towns and smaller centres in Ireland gave the amateur theatrical movement the polish it has had in rural areas.  I have been present at their performances.  I have seen people drive long distances to come to see them.  I have heard their comments on them&mdash;of how they put it over, how their entrances, exits and technique were accomplished.</P>
    <P>All that no longer exists.  The Abbey Theatre Company now say they are tied to the &ldquo;Queens.&rdquo;  I have a letter here which they sent when we asked them to come to Waterford.  I have quoted this letter before.  They said they would not be able to come down to go on tour.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;... if we had two plays each of which could be performed by seven or eight people and each of which could be well cast from our company without leaving the other short of suitable talent.  In that case we could send whichever of the two plays seemed most suitable to Waterford and keep the other in the Queens.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>It looks as if they are undermanned and understaffed.  If they are, and if they are not getting money and if they are not able to make it pay, I must say I never heard of this House refusing to increase their subsidy if they wanted it.</P>
    <P>That letter gives me the impression that the Abbey Theatre is on crutches and would not be able to stagger down the country.  It looks to me as if it would be in danger of falling asunder before getting to Waterford or Wexford or any other place.  It would be a wonderful thing, now that there are so many smaller theatres down the country, if the Abbey Theatre could send its company on tour and give the people down the country the chance <Col N="521" /> of comparing their performances with those of the Abbey Theatre company. It has been said to me that the reason the Abbey do not now go on tour is that they would be afraid to have their performances seen by the people down the country.</P>
    <P>Do you think the policy of the Abbey Theatre is a good policy, the policy that has turned away three Irish plays that have made the international stage within the past 12 months?  There is no courage in their policy.  I do not expect the Abbey Theatre to put on success after success.  I would rather see them stage a play on a Monday and have to take it off on a Thursday night, and do that a good few times, because, by that method of trial and error, they would eventually find a success.  They have become so cagey that they will put on practically nothing that is new. Plays are being sent to them and are constantly rejected.</P>
    <P>Deputy Moloney praised the Abbey to the skies when speaking here the other day.  He claimed he comes from the constituency that has made a great mark in the amateur theatre.  I suppose he was referring to <i>Sive.</i>  He must know something about the theatre&mdash;he is coming into the House now&mdash;or it must be his claim that because <i>Sive</i> was produced in Kerry, it is rather wonderful.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon) Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)">
      <NameTxt>Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)</NameTxt>
      <P>I dislike interrupting the Deputy but he seems to be speaking in very general terms.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I shall have to ask the Chair to bear with me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon) Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)">
      <NameTxt>Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>When I wanted to speak like this on the Second Reading, I was told to wait for the Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy was ruled out of order.  I gather the amendment is in order?  Is the amendment in order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon) Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)">
      <NameTxt>Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I know, it is, but I am not discussing the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="522" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The matter discussed on the amendment was ruled out of order on the Second Stage.  It seems funny that it is now in order. However, I am sure it is in order, on the ruling.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFlanagan" hpid="Mr. S. Flanagan Mr. S. Flanagan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Flanagan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is creating a very dangerous precedent to rule this amendment in order.  This is a very narrow Bill.  The question of the policy of the directors of the Abbey Theatre is not relevant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Mr. O'Sullivan Mr. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely when the Chair has ruled, it is no longer within the province of the House to express an opinion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFlanagan" hpid="Mr. S. Flanagan Mr. S. Flanagan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Flanagan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am accepting the ruling but I submit it is creating a dangerous precedent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon) Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)">
      <NameTxt>Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the difference between an amendment being in or out of order and a discussion on it.  I am waiting to hear the discussion on the amendment on the Order Paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielJMoloney" hpid="Mr. Moloney Mr. Moloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moloney</NameTxt>
      <P>I think and I respectfully say that the amendment that has been submitted here is entirely out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, well!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielJMoloney" hpid="Mr. Moloney Mr. Moloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moloney</NameTxt>
      <P>I am entitled to say so.  Am I correct in my assumption?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>How often does the Acting-Chairman have to say it is in order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielJMoloney" hpid="Mr. Moloney Mr. Moloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moloney</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Acting-Chairman says it is in order, I accept his ruling but I still submit it is going very wide.  This is in respect of the provision of moneys to erect a building. We are attacking the personnel of a committee of management of an institution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is making a speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not attacking any personnel.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment is in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="523" />
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad there is only one man in the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon) Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)">
      <NameTxt>Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am waiting to hear a discussion on the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The last time, I had to put up with three or four chairmen, too.  As I was saying, I thought it was strange that a Deputy coming from the constituency that produced a play such as <i>Sive</i> would not be on the same side as I am.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielJMoloney" hpid="Mr. Moloney Mr. Moloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moloney</NameTxt>
      <P>That is why I wanted to indicate my point of view. The difference is that I come from the county which has produced <i>Sive</i> and that I know what I am talking about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy must have produced it or written it or been responsible for it.  I wanted to say that I thought the Deputy would resent the fact that the Abbey had thrown <i>Sive</i> out into the road.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielJMoloney" hpid="Mr. Moloney Mr. Moloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moloney</NameTxt>
      <P>That is incorrect. They never threw it out.  The Deputy should be made withdraw that allegation because it is incorrect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon) Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)">
      <NameTxt>Acting-Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)</NameTxt>
      <P>If Deputy Lynch would keep to the amendment and not go into so much detail&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I am keeping to the amendment.  I am not making an attack.  I am saying that the Abbey Theatre has not been run properly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielJMoloney" hpid="Mr. Moloney Mr. Moloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moloney</NameTxt>
      <P>Tell us why, and tell us how.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>We are giving away £250,000.  If this £250,000 were being split up and given to Cork, Wexford, Waterford and Kerry there would be some strings tied on to it.  Why are there no strings tied on to it now?  Do Deputies think so little of £250,000 that they can just dismiss it and turn it over to a board that has proved over the years that they are not running the Abbey Theatre as it should be run?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am sorry that the discussion on this amendment has taken the turn it did.  It was through no fault of mine. In the interests of the Abbey Theatre&mdash;<Col N="524" /> I say the Abbey Theatre, not the National Theatre Society of Ireland which they call themselves, because they are no longer the National Theatre &mdash;and in order to revive the great spirit of the old Abbey Theatre, I appeal to the Minister to see to it that when this building for which we are to give £250,000 is erected, this dead hand policy which has been carried on for years now by the Abbey Theatre will come to an end.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanielJMoloney" hpid="Mr. Moloney Mr. Moloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moloney</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Minister not to accept this amendment because there is no purpose in it.  I was hoping the mover of the amendment would give us some good reasons as to why the Abbey Theatre management should be reorganised.  The amendment asks that the funds which it is proposed to provide be not made available until:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(i)  the National Theatre Society Limited shall make such alterations in its Memorandum and Articles of Association and take such other steps as may be recommended by a Committee which shall be appointed by the Minister consisting of the Director of An Chomhairle Ealaíon and eleven other persons; or</P>
      <P>(ii)  such alterations are made in the ownership and management of the Abbey Theatre, Dublin, as may be recommended by a Committee which shall be appointed by the Minister consisting of the Director of An Comhairle Ealaíon and eleven other persons.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>One would naturally assume that the present management of the Abbey Theatre was a body subject to a great deal of public criticism and was not functioning in accordance with the general requirements and wishes of the people.  I expected the Deputy to make a case on those lines.  I was agreeably surprised to find that he made no general allegations against the efficiency of the management of the Abbey or the National Theatre Society, Limited, as it is known.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We find critics in all walks of life. In relation to the programmes presented by Radio Éireann people, well informed people indeed, will occasionally make wild criticisms.  In most <Col N="525" /> cases of that kind you will find the critics fail to supply the specific reasons why they criticise a programme or a particular dramatic performance.  The same applies in respect of the Abbey Theatre.  I hear many people in dramatic circles particularly, say the Abbey Theatre are not fulfilling the functions which have been assigned to them.  Those people as a rule have no idea of the general policy which obtains by virtue of experience over the years.</P>
    <P>As regards the personnel of the Abbey Theatre management, they are men of outstanding integrity and ability with a first-class national background. They have come from different parts of the country and have rendered in their own time outstanding service to the nation in many spheres.  They have gone among the people and they have various means of feeling the pulse of the people in relation to drama of which they have been appointed to take charge.  I understand the directors are men who are co-opted from time to time with the exception of one director who represents the Government because of the fact that the Abbey has been given a State subsidy over the past 30 or 35 years.</P>
    <P>I do not wish to go into the personalities of these directors as such, but I am sure most Deputies know their background as well as I do.  They may not be performing the duties assigned to them to the satisfaction of everybody. That would be too much to expect but there is at least an obligation on anybody who attempts to make that charge against their policy to specify even in some general way where they are failing in their duty.</P>
    <P>The play &ldquo;Sive&rdquo; has been mentioned as having been rejected by the Abbey Theatre.  It has been said that many people were annoyed because of that decision by the Abbey.  I happen to represent the constituency where &ldquo;Sive&rdquo; was first produced and I can tell the House that there is no truth in the suggestion that the management of the Abbey refused to put &ldquo;Sive&rdquo; on their programme.  Evidently at one stage a free-lance critic in the reading Committee of the Abbey happened to get a copy&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Col N="526" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWPalmer" hpid="Acting-Chairman (Mr. Palmer) Acting-Chairman (Mr. Palmer)">
      <NameTxt>Acting-Chairman (Mr. Palmer)</NameTxt>
      <P>There can be no discussion on plays or such matters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielJMoloney" hpid="Mr. Moloney Mr. Moloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moloney</NameTxt>
      <P>I must accept your ruling but it is a statement of fact that the management of the Abbey Theatre did not reject &ldquo;Sive.&rdquo;  In fact they accepted the play and had it performed here in Dublin with the Listowel cast as they had done in the case of a Gaelic play from Donegal some years previously.</P>
      <P>I am not inclined to take up the attitude that the Abbey is perfect.  No human organisation is and I am quite sure the management of the Abbey would be quite happy to have suggestions made to them, on matters in connection with which they do not seem to please a small section of the people, by those interested in drama and other types of culture which the Abbey is supposed to foster.</P>
      <P>I suggest we should be helpful in this matter and I feel that perhaps Deputy Lynch may be trying to be helpful.  He appears to be a man who knows more about drama than I or most other Deputies do.  I think he could be very helpful if he gave specific instances of where the Abbey directorate appeared to be lacking in matters of policy.  I am sure the Abbey would be glad to consider any worthwhile suggestions in that regard.  They are doing a very difficult job and, when it comes to criticising them, the criticism should be specific.  I appeal to Deputy Lynch and also to Deputy Ryan to try and direct their criticism on those lines.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FintanCoogan" hpid="Mr. Coogan Mr. Coogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like the Minister to attach one string to this expenditure of £250,000 of public money. People all over the country, north, south, east and west, have to contribute to the Abbey and therefore I should like that string to be attached to let the Abbey know that they must give greater encouragement to the amateur stage throughout the country. Where are they to draw from but from the amateur stage?  The Abbey has now become a clearing station for the films and rightly so.  They have produced some of the finest film actors in the world and I am proud to say that <Col N="527" /> at least two of them came from my own town.  I refer to Mr. Seán McGlory and Miss Siobhán McKenna.  They came from the Taidhbhairc in Galway and worked their way up from the amateur stage.</P>
      <P>There are areas throughout the country in which there are good amateur character actors.  In fact, we have them in this House but they do not pull the curtains often enough here; that is the trouble.  I should like to see the rest of the country getting a fair crack of the whip by the encouragement of the amateur stage. They have not been given that encouragement up to the present and I should like that string to be attached.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask the House not to suggest to Deputy Lynch, myself or anybody else to launch an attack on the Abbey directors.  I do not think it desirable that this House should put itself in the position of dramatic critic. But looking back over the last ten, 20 or 30 years of the Abbey, surely Deputies will agree with me that there has been widespread criticism of the existing management of the Abbey. Whether the criticism is right or wrong is not a matter which this House is qualified to determine but we would not be doing our duty were we to ignore completely all the criticism, much of which has come from people as well qualified, if not better qualified than the directors of the Abbey to say what has happened.  I think it a most undesirable development for this House to give £250,000 to a small group which has been criticised right, left and centre for many years past. That is the whole purpose of the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What have the directors of the Abbey to fear?  What have any lovers of the Abbey to fear?  Might I say in passing, lest anybody question my motives, that there was hardly a play produced in the Abbey over the past ten years that I have not seen.  I suppose I shall continue to go there despite all the mediocrity.  The fact is that they have nothing to fear if things are run as they should be run. Is it that some people, including the <Col N="528" /> directors of the Abbey, believe that criticism might be forthcoming from the body consisting of three dramatists, three actors, three persons representative of Irish cultural interests and two persons experienced in the management of theatre?</P>
    <P>I know that I speak for Deputy Lynch when I say that we who put down this amendment have no objection whatsoever if a committee is constituted in some other way, or if the members of this committee are drawn from a different type of people.  I believe that when Dáil Eireann is giving £250,000 to a private company, that should not be done until public uneasiness has been allayed.  I ask the House to consider for a moment what the position would be if there never had been an Abbey and a Minister came in here asking us to vote £250,000 for the establishment of a National Theatre.  Would the House not ask how the theatre was to be run?  Would there not be a suggestion that it might be run in some one way better than another?  That is the objective of this amendment to ensure that the best possible scheme of ownership and management is utilised.</P>
    <P>The amendment refers to the Memorandum and Articles of Association which, as Deputies know, are the constitution which governs any limited company.  Amongst some of the undesirable things in the Articles of Association, which were inserted because of criticism, is one providing that a majority of directors can get rid of any other director without stating their reasons.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanielJMoloney" hpid="Mr. Moloney Mr. Moloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moloney</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that not in the Articles of Association of every company?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No, allow me to differ. The reason some directors were got rid of was that they dared to criticise those who, for the time being, were holding the managing positions. That is most undesirable.  We should not hand over £250,000 to a very small group.  At the moment I believe there are only three directors and they are to have the sole say as to what should <Col N="529" /> be put on in the national theatre.  In addition, there is a proviso which would not be tolerated anywhere else. That is that no shareholder shall inspect the books and accounts of the company without the specific permission of the directors.  The reason for that is that two of the largest shareholders are directors who were dismissed. They were not even allowed to examine the accounts of the company in which they were shareholders.</P>
      <P>There is another provision in the Articles under which when some directors in the past protested again and again, and then as a means of making further protest absented themselves from meetings, because they did not get the prior permission of the other directors, they got the order of the boot.</P>
      <P>The question is: should we hand over a quarter of a million pounds until these disputes are resolved and until public uneasiness is allayed? That is the whole motive behind the putting down of this amendment and if we felt sure some steps would be taken&mdash;if not of this kind, of some similar kind&mdash;to allay public uneasiness, then the amendment might be withdrawn.  I think it is very necessary and desirable that we should get some assurance from the Government that this money will not be handed over until there is a complete and impartial investigation of things as they stand.</P>
      <P>As I say, I am not going into criticisms of managements because I think it is undesirable.  That is a matter for a committee of specialists such as has been suggested in the amendment, but might I just say, in passing, that the founders of the Abbey Theatre said it was being founded because of: &ldquo;Our desire to bring upon the stage the deeper thoughts and emotions of Ireland.  We will show that Ireland is not the home of buffoonery and of easy sentiment ... but the home of an ancient idealism.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I, and many other members of the House who have gone to the Abbey Theatre in recent years, have seen very little more than buffoonery and easy sentiment.  The Abbey has departed <Col N="530" /> completely from the idealism of its early years.  The reason may be that the Directors wanted to make the Abbey a paying proposition, but, if we are to have a national theatre worthy of the ancient idealism of which Yeats and Lady Gregory spoke, then we must ensure that it is run in a manner befitting the dignity of the ideals which it is supposed to live up to at all times.</P>
    <P>On that account, I would ask the House to accept the amendment in the atmosphere in which it is put forward. It is put forward in order that the Abbey may achieve the ideals for which it was founded, and in order that public uneasiness in regard to the existing Abbey directorship may be allayed.  If, on investigation, it is allayed, then they are completely right in what they are doing and surely it would be a desirable thing that that should be said by such a committee as is proposed?  Let us trust that when the Abbey is reconstructed, the great words of Yeats will be fulfilled.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GusHealy" hpid="Mr. Healy Mr. Healy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Healy</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to me that those who put down this amendment have now got the House discussing the reconstruction of the personnel of the Abbey Theatre board of directors rather than the reconstruction of the physical Abbey Theatre building.  Personally, I regret to see that happen because those of us who are completely outside the knowledge, shared by the last speaker, of the difficulties between members of the board are anxious to see the Abbey Theatre, the physical structure, rebuilt, and that as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have heard certain statements made today and it would seem as if controversy and criticism are now being aimed against the Abbey Theatre for the first time.  I make bold to say that since it was founded, the Abbey Theatre never escaped criticism and controversy from a very voluble section of the people.  From my experience, though it be only a brushing one with artists, actors and theatricals, it would seem that they find it much more difficult to compromise with each other's opinions and compose their differences than even politicians.  Therefore, I cannot see anything diametrically wrong in <Col N="531" /> having differences of opinion between those of artistic bent.</P>
    <P>I know that the Abbey Theatre has refused plays which were afterwards performed successfully in other places.  The directors may not have taken everything they should have taken, but we have only to read today's papers to see that a commercial theatre in Dublin had to take the unprecedented step of taking off a play that was put on only this week.</P>
    <P>As a Parliament, we would be well advised to do everything possible to see that the physical Abbey Theatre building is put up as soon as possible.  If we have criticisms to offer afterwards, we shall have an opportunity when we are dealing with the Vote on Account.  If the directors are holding something from the shareholders, then we have a Government director and they cannot hide anything from him.  We can find out anything we are entitled to know through him.  I believe that those who put down the amendment did so in good fath, but I think they are doing something which is diverting from the purposes of the Bill.</P>
    <P>I come from a provincial constituency and I am not at all satisfied with the policy of the Abbey Theatre in not sending plays and the company on tour.  Like Deputy Lynch, I should be anxious that they should do that. I say this not from any desire to hinder the management of the theatre here in Dublin, but I do not subscribe to the criticism that they do not send their players to the provincial towns because they are afraid they may meet more than their match, and that the people would not think they were up to standard.  I think the standard of acting has not deteriorated.  The plays may have, but the acting has not.  It is a national asset, at home and abroad.</P>
    <P>The sooner we put up the physical structure the better, and then we shall have an opportunity to see that the theatre is run on lines&mdash;not those we would suggest ourselves because, as somebody said, we are not competent to direct theatre policy, but on the lines of those who are competent to <Col N="532" /> make suggestions.  In that sense, I would ask the movers of the amendment to withdraw it so that it would seem there was no haggling about the erection of the physical structure of the Abbey Theatre.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not endeavouring to halt the building of the Abbey Theatre.  We are anxious to have it rebuilt but we are most anxious also to have it competently run.  I should explain to Deputy Healy that the reason we are doing this to-day is that for some time I have been endeavouring to break up this facade that surrounds the Abbey, and which has made it into a kind of sacred cow about which no one dare say anything.</P>
      <P>Long ago I was ruled out of order when I put down a question to the Minister for Finance regarding the subsidy to the Abbey Theatre.  I was told that I could raise the matter when this Bill was introduced.  Then when I did raise it, on the introduction of the Bill, I was ruled out of order by the Leas-Cheann Comhairle.  Now, before any Government are committed, we should have an opportunity to say something and I for one should like to get a little more information.</P>
      <P>I should like to ask the Minister in whom is the new Abbey Theatre to be vested, and I should also like to know who represents the Government on the Abbey Theatre board of directors?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Whether this amendment is in order or not does not greatly concern me.  What I am concerned about at the moment is what is in the Bill and only what is in the Bill.  I do not therefore propose, as a matter of principle, to lend myself to a discussion on the proposals contained in the amendment or to discuss now the questions of policy or the management of the Abbey Theatre regarding which there is no proposal in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Successive Governments have indicated their agreement that funds should be provided for a new building and we are trying to implement that view.  I know that there has been criticism of the Abbey.  Hardly any section of the community running the <Col N="533" /> business of amusements or catering for the public as the Abbey does, escapes every form of criticism.  The Abbey must expect to come under criticism simply because it has to reject so many plays that are submitted to the board. In my opinion, there can be only one deciding factor as to whether a play is suitable to go on the Abbey stage or not and it stands to reason that when plays are rejected, the people will be annoyed.  The plays of many persons who have since become successful producers of plays at the Abbey have been rejected.  I understand that at least one play by Yeats was rejected. I understand that plays of Lennox Robinson were rejected.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The play of W.B. Yeats was rejected when it was submitted anonymously.  When he submitted it under his own name, it was put on the boards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I am trying to disabuse the minds of people who have spoken here of the idea that there is anything that can be regarded as free from criticism.  The Deputies, the Government and the Opposition are not free from criticism.  We must all accept criticism, whether or not it is justified.</P>
      <P>As I said earlier, I am not concerned with whether this amendment is in order or not.  I am opposing it, of course.  All I am concerned with is the passing of this Bill as quickly as possible in order to be able to provide the opportunity to have the Abbey Theatre rebuilt.  If we can get on with the task, we are fulfilling a number of useful purposes.  We are creating employment and providing something that has been delayed now for, I think, seven years.  To accept the amendment would be to delay it for probably another year or two.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Why?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no reason whatever why this amendment should be accepted.  I am opposing it on the grounds I have stated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked the Minister if he could tell me who represents <Col N="534" /> the Government on the present Abbey Theatre Board?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is Mr. Wilmot.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no objection to Mr. Wilmot; I just wanted to know who it was.  I have something here that says there are only three directors &mdash;a letter dated 24th August, 1959.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I think Mr. Wilmot was nominated to replace Mr. O'Connor who was a former director.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Mr. Frank O'Connor was not a Government nominee.  He was a shareholder in his own right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>At any rate, Mr. Wilmot is the Government representative. That is the answer to the question the Deputy asked.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall give you the Bill&mdash;we do not want to delay this. We did not come in here to cast any mud at the Abbey directors.  We do not want to have this cloak of criticism thrown over this business.  I would appeal to the Minister to have a conversation with the Abbey Theatre directors of the present time and, as the Minister who is to hand over this £250,000, to see to it that there will be some safeguard.</P>
      <P>It has been said that the Abbey has always been subject to criticism.  We are always subject to criticism but when the criticism becomes a storm, even the Government must listen and the criticism that has been storming around the Abbey for the past ten years should be listened to.  It is not just a case of criticism from people who had plays rejected.  Great artists had to leave the Abbey; great people of the theatre had to leave.  They were pushed out of the directorate.  There is an intolerance in the Abbey that is not good for it.  I would remind the Minister of what my colleague Deputy Ryan said, that if there were no Abbey and we were to build a national theatre we would appoint a board and if somebody&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="535" />
    <Speaker pid="GusHealy" hpid="Mr. Healy Mr. Healy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Healy</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall never do it; we would never build such a theatre, if it was never there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy's people are going to build one in Cork.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GusHealy" hpid="Mr. Healy Mr. Healy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Healy</NameTxt>
      <P>A civic theatre, not a national theatre.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>There are many people who have great spirit.  The people of Dublin wanted to build the national theatre, the Abbey Theatre, after it had been burned, but the directors spurned them.</P>
      <P>We are not coming here just to put up criticism against individuals.  I have never met any of these gentlemen. I want the Minister and the Deputies to look upon this national theatre as the treasure that we all cherish.  I want them to look at it from the business point of view that we are putting up £250,000.  After that, if the Abbey Theatre is run and is losing money, I shall be one of the first to come in here and support a Vote that will raise the subsidy.</P>
      <P>I would not have the Abbey Theatre cutting itself down at all; but we must judge by results.  Surely we must look at the results of the past 20 years and ask were they good results?  No rockets were sent up as had been sent up in the years when it was storming. A dead hand seems to be there for the past 20 years.  That is the only reason I and my colleague have taken this action.  I had an enormous post about this.  An enormous number of people approached me about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One thing about which I am disappointed is that Deputies did not consider it worth their while to speak on this or even to say that they wanted to see the policy changed or that they were prepared to stand over the policy here today.  I am surprised also that the Deputies are so lightly voting £250,000 without coming in to ask some questions.  We shall not delay the Minister.  The Minister can have his Bill&mdash;all Stages&mdash;as was agreed here when we took the Second Reading.  Again, I would say to him, even at this late stage, to accept the amendment although he says he will not accept it.  That is all right but <Col N="536" /> I say that he should take this matter up with the present Abbey directors and with his colleagues at Cabinet level.  I think his colleagues might direct him to say we are entitled to have a greater representation on the Board of the Abbey than we have to-day.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I mention a possible solution?  We are as anxious as the Minister to see the new Abbey built with all possible speed.  Is there anything to prevent the Abbey being built but not handed over to the National Theatre Company until a satisfactory reconstruction of directors takes place?  I think that would be the anxiety.  It would help to allay the fears of people that the theatre might be handed over to the wrong people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not give any such undertaking.  Arising out of the matter to which Deputy Lynch referred, I want to make it clear&mdash;I am sure it is clear&mdash;that the £250,000 granted in this Bill is for the specific purpose of building a theatre and for no other purpose.  It cannot be used for any other purpose.  I want to make clear also the other point about which the Deputy seemed to be concerned. With regard to the directors, I was correct in saying that Séamus Wilmot was the representative of the Government. Then there is Mr. Ernest Blythe, Mr. Gabriel Fallon and Mr. Roibeárd Ó Fearacháin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the third name?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>The names are: Séamus Wilmot, the Government representative; Mr. Ernest Blythe; Mr. Gabriel Fallon and Mr. Roibeárd Ó Fearacháin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>How long has Mr. Fallon been a director?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GusHealy" hpid="Mr. Healy Mr. Healy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Healy</NameTxt>
      <P>Twelve months I suppose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I have just given a letter to the usher which I got from the Abbey.  It mentions Mr. Ernest <Col N="537" /> Blythe, Mr. Wilmot and Mr. Ó Fearacháin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that Mr. Gabriel Fallon was the latest appointee. I think that was only a matter of months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FintanCoogan" hpid="Mr. Coogan Mr. Coogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister convey to the Abbey the views expressed here to-day that they should develop latent talent with a view to giving it a show?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no doubt that the Abbey directors will be sufficiently concerned about this debate to read up what has been said.  From that point of view, I think it is the best posible way in which they could be informed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>You would not move them with gunpowder.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>On Second Reading, I asked the Minister a question. As I understand it, this money will be paid into the Capital Fund established by the Central Fund Act, 1956.  Then the Minister is to apply the moneys from time to time.  The Minister is not the Minister for Justice but the Minister for Finance, as I understand it. Secondly, I drew the attention of the Minister for Justice to the fact that once it fits into the Central Fund Act, 1956, there surely has to be each year an account of the payments into the Capital Fund and the payments out and that such an account has to be prepared by the Minister for Finance and given to the Comptroller and Auditor General for his report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is further provided by the Central Fund Act that the report of the Comptroller and Auditor General must be brought before the Houses of the Oireachtas.  I cannot believe that the £250,000 will be paid over all at one go.  The payments will be made in such a way that they will go into two financial years at least.  That means that there will be two reports from the Comptroller and Auditor General which will give the House another <Col N="538" /> opportunity of discussion.  I think that is the situation but I should like to have it confirmed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>In answer to the Deputy's question, the requirements of the law will be carried out.  The Deputy asked on Second Reading&mdash;I had not the figures then&mdash;how the amounts accumulated in the Dormant Fund.  As a matter of interest, I asked the Department to look these figures up.  For September, 1949, they amounted in the aggregate to some £610,500.  In September, 1954, they increased to £721,800 and in September, 1959, they amounted to £860,000, the figure we were discussing.  The average increase would appear to have been about £25,000.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 3 and 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining stages to-day.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Courts of Justice Bill," RHead="1959&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Courts of Justice Bill, 1959&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Traynor) Oscar Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Traynor)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Bill be now read a Second Time.  It is a short measure, the sole object of which is to provide for an increase in the salaries of all members of the Judiciary.</P>
      <P>The question of making a further adjustment in the salaries of members of the Judiciary has been under consideration by the Government on a number of occasions since 1957, when the Judges and Justices submitted requests for pay increases.  As Deputies are aware, Judges' salaries are fixed on a long term basis and are not revised, to cover changes in the cost of living, with the same frequency as occurs in the case of persons engaged in other branches of the public service or in outside employment generally.  In fact, since the salaries of the majority of Judges were first fixed in 1924, adjustments have been made on only two occasions&mdash;in 1947 and in 1953.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Since 1953, the cost of living has <Col N="539" /> increased by about 15 per cent. and, generally speaking, persons in the public service and in outside employment have received pay increases on two occasions.  As I mentioned already, the Government have since 1957 given careful consideration to the question whether Judges' salaries should be increased, and if so, what should be the pattern of the increase.  As a result of a full examination of all aspects of the question, the Government are satisfied that the increase proposed in the Bill, that is, a flat increase of 10 per cent. on all judicial salaries, is fair and reasonable, and I submit this proposal for the approval of the House.</P>
    <P>It will be noted that the proposed salary increases are to be paid with effect from 1st January last.  That is being done to meet the unusually long delay that has elapsed between the request for the increase, which was submitted in 1957, and the Government's decision on that request.  My view is that it would be unfair to the Judiciary that they should receive no compensation for the exceptional delay, and I am satisfied that in all the circumstances the modest degree of retrospection now proposed is fully justified.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the amendment standing in my name and that of Deputy Dr. Browne:</P>
      <P>To delete &ldquo;now&rdquo; and to add at the end of the motion &ldquo;this day twelve months.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I move the amendment, Sir, not because of any actual criticism of what a judge or justice or any member of the Judiciary is entitled to.  I want to get that quite clear.  But, there are a number of points which the Government should consider in connection with this proposal and our aim in moving the amendment is to give sufficient time for our proposal to be examined and, if considered desirable, to be adopted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is admitted that in recent years the principle of conciliation and arbitration has been accepted throughout this part of Ireland.  The trade unions, when they demand an increase in wages and salaries, have to put a case <Col N="540" /> and, in many cases, have to go before the Labour Court.  The Civil Service, State bodies, semi-State bodies have arbitration or conciliation boards, as the case may be.  So, it is accepted that when a case is being put forward for an increase in salaries, there is some group charged with the responsibility of examining in detail the application for the increase.</P>
    <P>It must be accepted that that principle of arbitration is in operation even in relation to the Garda Síochána and, to my mind, it would appear that some form of arbitration or examination of claims in relation to the Judiciary was in operation in 1953 because, although the Minister, and rightly so, has pointed out that the categories to which he has referred have received only two increases in salaries since 1924, it is necessary to emphasise that prior to their obtaining their last increase, in 1953, the Government of the day set up a Select Committee to examine the question of judicial salaries, expense allowances and pensions.  That meant that in 1953 a Select Committee of this House, consisting of members of both the Government and the Opposition, considered a memorandum submitted by Judges of the Supreme Court, the High Court and Circuit Court and submissions by the district justices on their claims for an increase in salary.  As a result of the recommendation of that Select Committee, the Government decided, and rightly so, in 1953, to increase substantially the salaries of all members of the Judiciary by amounts ranging from £250 to £450 in the case of justices and circuit court judges. That was in 1953.  I cannot understand, and many other Deputies cannot understand, why a similar move was not made in 1957 or 1958 when, apparently, members of the Judiciary made a further request for an increase in their salaries.</P>
    <P>Under the Constitution, all the people in this State are equal.  Of course, nobody for a moment suggests that the request of the Judiciary should be neglected or that their claims should not be listened to, but I submit that at least the same rules should be applied to their claims for <Col N="541" /> an increase as are applied to the higher ranks of the Civil Service and other State bodies.</P>
    <P>I am not the only one who is making a comparison between members of the Judiciary and the Civil Service.  The judges of the Supreme Court and the High Court, in 1953, in support of their claims for an increase in salaries, made a comparison between their position and the position of Secretaries of Departments and other higher civil servants and servants of State and semi-State bodies and based their argument for an increase in their salaries on the position that obtained in the Civil Service.  Therefore, I cannot see any objection now to having another Select Committee of the House to consider the claims put forward in the same manner as the claims put forward in 1953 were considered.</P>
    <P>I would also point out to the Minister that in the memorandum submitted by the Judges of the Supreme Court and the High Court in 1953, they stated as follows:</P>
    <P>We wish to make it plain that we do not claim any right to have our salaries increased from time to time on account of any temporary increase in the cost of living, whether reckoned by reference to the index figure or otherwise.</P>
    <P>That statement was made in the memorandum submitted by these very learned and responsible gentlemen. Surely, when they made such a statement in support of their claims in 1953, it is not unreasonable to suggest that this House, through a Select Committee, be given the reasons for the arguments these same members of the Supreme Court have evidently put forward to the Government?  A great case can be made for the setting up of another Select Committee to examine those proposals.</P>
    <P>When I make the comparison with trade unions and point out that even the lowest paid members of local authority staffs have to go before the Labour Court, that does not mean that I want to put the members of the Judiciary into exactly the same category. <Col N="542" /> I merely wish to see the same attitude adopted as was adopted in 1953.  It would appear that special privilege attaches to members of the Judiciary as far as remuneration is concerned, despite the fact that the judges themselves, in page 20 of their report, make it clear that they do not claim to have their salaries increased from time to time on account of any increase in the cost of living.  In spite of that statement in 1953, we have a claim in 1957.  Is that claim on the basis of a temporary increase in the cost of living, or is the case being made that there is a permanent increase in the cost of living?  On what basis is the claim being made?  If this House and the public were entitled to know in 1953 the reasons put forward by the Judiciary in their claim for an increase, surely the House and the country are now entitled to know the reasons advanced in 1957?</P>
    <P>When those reasons were put forward in 1953, the case was threshed out publicly in this House.  A Select Committee sat and the remainder of the House abided by their recommendations. Would it not be a better proposition for the Government to accept what was recommended in 1953 rather than have the whole question reopened, as it must be if the Government do not agree?  Nobody is more anxious than the members of the Judiciary to ensure that their position in the State is kept above suspicion.</P>
    <P>In 1957, an increase in travelling expenses and subsistence allowances was given to certain categories of the Judiciary.  This House heard no word of that increase and no Government Order was made on it.  I know I can be told that no Government Order was necessary, but those increases, made in November, 1957, were backdated to June, 1956.  That information did not come before the House. It was extracted through the medium of Parliamentary Question.  When I sought to find out what the position generally was and how expenses and allowances were arrived at, I found no records were available in the form of Government or Ministerial Orders in the Library.</P>
    <P>Let me be quite clear about the <Col N="543" /> comparison I am making.  In November, 1957, the officers of the Garda Síochána received an increase in travelling expenses and subsistence allowances&mdash;on the same date, in fact, as the members of the Judiciary received almost similar allowances.  A Ministerial Order was made and published&mdash;it is available in the Library or at any stationery office&mdash;giving full details of what the officers of the Garda Síochána received, but no Order was made concerning, nor did any member of this House know of, the fact that the members of the Judiciary received a similar increase at the same time. Was there not a question of privilege there?</P>
    <P>I do not suggest that the increase the members of the Judiciary received was a large one, but I am suggesting there was an air of secrecy attached to it which is entirely undesirable and which the members of the Judiciary would be the first to suggest should be removed.  Following that increase in allowances, we are now told there was a claim for an increase in salaries and that the Government have decided, having examined it, to back-date it to the beginning of this year.</P>
    <P>I shall not talk much further on that aspect except to say it is accepted throughout the country that the principle of conciliation and arbitration is the proper method of dealing with any question of an increase in salaries or allowances to any section of our people.  I do not think an exception should be made in this case, especially when, in 1953, a precedent was established. Otherwise, the public will be dissatisfied and the standing of the Judiciary will not be improved.</P>
    <P>That is the first reason I advance as to why we believe that a lapse of 12 months would be desirable so that the Government may re-examine the position.  In the meantime, it will not cause any great hardship to the members of the Judiciary.  The second point I wish to make is this.  Within that period, the Government will have an opportunity of examining the other privilege which seems to be in operation as far as the Judiciary are concerned, <Col N="544" /> that is, the method of their appointment.</P>
    <P>In regard to higher civil servants, in regard to local authority appointments, in regard to any appointment made in the State, there is an examination and interview and the Local Appointments Commission is brought into operation to ensure, not only that the best possible candidate is appointed but that there shall not be the slightest trace of influence.  That is the general position, but in regard to the Judiciary, the position is that the only qualifications necessary for appointment to the Bench are, first of all, the initial law examination, and, after that, tie yourself on to some political Party until you climb so high in their graces that the day will come when you will sit on the Bench.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The question of the qualifications of the Judiciary is not before the House.  The only matter before the House is their remuneration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>The matter before the House is to postpone for 12 months a decision on this motion.  Reasons must be given as to why that postponement is necessary.  The reasons are, (1) to examine the question of conciliation and, (2), to examine the methods of appointment.  Consequently, 12 months is desirable for such a committee to work.  I want to put the members of the Judiciary above suspicion.  The House and the country would like that, and nobody more so than the members of the Judiciary themselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There used to be an old adage to the effect that there was one law for the rich and another for the poor.  We know how untrue that is, but there is to-day another aphorism creeping into the Republic; that is, that there is one law for those with influence and another for those who have no influence.  Is it not only natural that that feeling should be there when people remember that appointments to the Judiciary are made because of association with and affiliation to a political Party?  Admittedly, the appointee may be a very well qualified man, but he is inevitably in a weaker <Col N="545" /> position than he would be if he were appointed by some neutral body specifically set up for that purpose.  I do not propose to say anything about the composition of such a board. There are people here who are as anxious as I am to keep the Judiciary above reproach, and who are better qualified than I am to suggest a suitable type of board for the purpose of appointing members of the Judiciary on qualifications alone and without reference to political affiliations.</P>
    <P>In Britain, political affiliations enter into the question.  The system that operates there is similar to the system which operates here.  But the fact that it operates in Britain, and appears to do so successfully, is no justification for putting the same system into operation here.  For one thing, we have not the same number as they have in Britain from which to make a choice and, therefore, there is far graver need here, because of the limited number available, for careful screening and selection in the filling of these posts.</P>
    <P>I am not casting any aspersions on any members of the Judiciary and I have no intention of doing so.  I merely ask that this Bill be postponed for twelve months, or less, if in the meantime the Government adopt the proposal to examine into the position regarding the appointment of members of the Judiciary in general with a view to the elimination of any suggestion of political bias in such appointments; and, secondly, that in that twelve-month period a Select Committee on lines similar to that which sat in 1953 be set up to examine into the two suggestions made here.  I do not think that is an unreasonable proposal. I know for a fact that it will meet with the approval of many members of the Judiciary itself.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume it will not be necessary to discuss this amendment and the Second Reading of the Bill in different speeches.  I presume the whole matter can be covered in the one speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="546" />
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment and the Bill can be discussed together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like, first of all, to speak briefly on the suggestion that the Bill should be postponed for 12 months and on the statements made in support of the proposals outlined. The amendment has been based on two arguments.  One is that this country has got into a kind of mood in which increases in salaries are invariably discussed by some kind of arbitration board under some method of conciliation and arbitration; and, secondly, there has been a selection procedure adopted in regard to Judges on a former occasion and the Deputy supporting the amendment thinks the same procedure should be followed now.  Another view put forward is that the Government should have time in which to think over the situation and eventually introduce some proposals with regard to appointments generally to the Judiciary.  To my mind, that is a wholly different matter and one which the Deputy can raise by way of motion, leaving it open to discussion as an entirely separate issue.</P>
      <P>The Deputy's first argument rests on two fallacies.  It is not the case that everybody has to go before an arbitration board, a labour court, or some similar body, in order to get an increase in salary.  The Deputy made a comparison with the higher officers of the Civil Service.  There are certain non-arbitrable classes in the Civil Service.  Yet, the fact is that Governments have, after arbitration in connection with State personnel subject to arbitration, given to those in the non-arbitrable classes increases corresponding to those given to personnel in the arbitrable classes.  There is no reason, therefore, why Judges should be made undergo any procedure of arbitration or conciliation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The second argument was founded upon the fact that some years ago a special committee was set up for a specific purpose.  To my mind, that argument also fails.  The Minister's case in presenting this piece of legislation is that, since the last increase in judicial salaries, the cost of living <Col N="547" /> has risen by 15 per cent. and it is proposed to give the Judiciary now an increase of ten per cent. to compensate for that 15 per cent. increase in the cost of living.  There can be no denying the fact that the cost of living has risen.</P>
    <P>When the special committee was set up, it was set up for a specific purpose. It did a good deal more than merely examining whether the salaries of the Judiciary had, through the depreciation of money, lost a particular purchasing value and ought therefore to be increased.  There was an examination of the position of Judges <i>inter se.</i>  That matter was under discussion and required lengthy deliberation by the committee which eventually reported to this House.</P>
    <P>The simple question that arises here is: do the members of the Judiciary require any increase in salaries in the light of an increase in the cost of living of 15 per cent.?  It is proposed in this Bill to give the Judiciary an increase of ten per cent.  On that, I have a very distinct view.  I am clearly of the opinion that a case can be made for improving judicial salaries, and a ten per cent. increase does not meet the increase in the cost of living and, therefore, does not compensate these people as a group for what they have suffered because of the decreased purchasing value of money.</P>
    <P>I speak with a certain amount of assurance in this because when I was Minister for Finance I had made up my mind quite definitely that the Judiciary should have some increase in their emoluments.  I was looking at the salaries, not in relation to individuals but in relation to the positions which they occupy.  Because of the very high positions these people occupy it was the view of myself and my colleagues in Government at the time that an improvement in their situation was required.  The atmosphere in those days, of course, was entirely different because we had deliberately embarked on a policy of trying to level up salaries.  Salaries had been pegged under Standstill Order, and by means of other devices, and held at a particular point.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="548" /> There was no doubt that salaried classes, particularly those who were made eventually the subject of arbitration in the Civil Service, and those in industrial and other forms of employment outside, had suffered acutely because money had not kept its 1939 purchasing value.  By degrees, between 1948 and 1951, the salaries of various groups were successively improved. First of all, the really badly-off were attended to&mdash;the old age pensioners and those who depend on the justice of the State, though it sometimes fails in charity.  Having dealt with those and encouraged those outside to go to the Labour Court, arbitration was introduced and the Government encouraged State personnel to look for an improvement in their financial status.  That, too, was dealt with in successive stages.</P>
    <P>The last group which needed attention then was that composed of the members of the Judiciary and certain others whom it was my intention to put on equality with all the others. Because of the defeat of the Government in 1951, that was impossible, but in those days it certainly was the intention to recast judicial salaries. That would have been done in 1951 if Fate had provided us with the power to do it.</P>
    <P>The atmosphere has changed considerably since then but I think a case can be made&mdash;a good case&mdash;for increasing judicial salaries.  While personally I should have no hesitation in increasing them at the present time, there is a definite mood in the country that this is not the time to give an increase anywhere.  I remember in 1956 a statement was made here about certain improvements made in the old age pensions and in certain of the State services which were described as chunks of inflationary expenditure being brought before the House and that our attitude towards certain State personnel had sparked off a demand for further increases and that was regarded as a bad thing.  I regard it as a very good thing.  The argument made by the Government when in Opposition was that we were adding to and increasing the claims that were made in order to have a better adjustment made to equate whatever moneys <Col N="549" /> that were then being paid to the cost of living.</P>
    <P>I believe there is a case to be made&mdash; a good case&mdash;and there is no necessity for a Select Committee at the moment because the simple case in any reconsideration of the salaries of the Judiciary is <i>inter se</i> and not a question of whether certain people should be raised from a low level to a higher one or that the cost of living has gone up by so much that we should increase the salaries.</P>
    <P>Deputy McQuillan quoted from the statement of the Judiciary to the effect that they would not look for day by day or year by year increases on account of any temporary increase in the cost of living.  That statement has to be understood as it was made.  I take it to mean that their salaries should not be harnessed to a cost of living figure and go up automatically as it rose.  They were applying for a radical examination of their salary position and they got that from the Select Committee.  That is an entirely different matter.  The cost of living figure has gone up and we are asked to raise the salaries of the Judiciary accordingly.</P>
    <P>I should like to say that to raise the judicial salaries is a matter of greater importance and of far greater moment than raising the salaries of other people.  Deputy McQuillan wants to know if this increase is being given because of a temporary increase in the cost of living figure.  If I had any faith, any belief, that the cost of living figure would change and go downwards instead of up, I would say that there is a good deal to be said for giving this matter further consideration because we are not giving the Judiciary a bonus.  We are giving them an addition to their salaries and once they get an addition to their salaries, under the Constitution, those salaries cannot be lowered while each individual judge is in office, so it is an important step.  However, in the belief that there is no possibility of the cost of living coming down, I take it we have just got to face it now as year succeeds year that the fact is that the value of money has declined and that there is a downward trend.</P>
    <P>If and when this measure is further discussed, I should like to make a <Col N="550" /> suggestion to the Minister.  We have over the years in connection with salaried people&mdash;State personnel rather than salaried classes&mdash;developed two lines of approach.  The Civil Service many years ago asked for and eventually in 1956 got a Superannuation Act in which power is given to any civil servant&mdash;actually it is in the Local Authorities (Superannuation) Act of the same year&mdash;who is about to retire and who is entitled to a pension on retirement, to come to an agreement by which he surrenders part of his pension.  His pension in part is then given over to his widow, if the lady survives him.</P>
    <P>There is also legislation which allows a dependent child to have part of the real value of the pension given over for his benefit.  There is no cost to the State in that because the value of the pension substituted for the pension earned has to be actuarial and equivalent to whatever he surrenders. Therefore, there is no cost to the State.  That principle is already accepted with regard to civil servants and servants of local authorities and, as it involves no cost to the State, I think it should be included in whatever legislation there is with regard to the Judiciary to enable them, if they like&mdash;giving each individual his choice&mdash;to surrender part of their pensions and to get a lesser pension to which they would be entitled during the joint lives of themselves and their wives.</P>
    <P>There is another provision that is not made with regard to the Judiciary, and which has been made with regard to the Civil Service personnel, namely, that if they die in harness before they retire, they are entitled to a gratuity which is measured in different ways.  I suggest both these matters should be considered in relation to the Judiciary as well as to other classes of the community.</P>
    <P>I was rather astonished to hear the Minister say that the retrospective dating of this to 1st January is due to the considerations of delay.  That delay was caused by the Government themselves. Requests for an increase in salary which were made in 1957 are only brought in here in 1959 and it is thought proper and reasonable to <Col N="551" /> back-date them to the beginning of this year.  That is acceptable from one angle but it has not always been the mood.  I remember a time when the civil servants made a claim which was afterwards seconded by the Arbitration Court.  There were months of controversy in this House as to whether it should be retrospective to the date on which the claim was advanced or retrospective to the date of arbitration.  I am glad at least that this has been accepted now because it will be a principle which will bind hereafter with regard to other grades.</P>
    <P>I do not want to have this 12 months' delay.  The matter should be decided here and now and the legislation should go through in the next two or three weeks, or it should not go through.  The 12 months' delay is asked for, for the purpose of setting up a Select Committee.  I regard that as unnecessary.  It is also asked for, for the purpose of having an examination into the system of the appointment of judges.  That is an entirely different matter which is causing a good deal of anxiety throughout the country.  It may eventually be debated here by way of motion but as regards the 12 months' delay, I would not be in agreement with that at all.</P>
    <P>My view is that there is a good case to be made for giving the judges this or some other increase.  Whether or not it is the proper time, the House will have to decide.  Up and down the country, there are repercussions of a type out of all proportion to the value of the money involved.  I think £13,000 or £14,000 would meet all the increases, but notwithstanding that small amount the view, which Deputy McQuillan expressed, will get an impetus if these moneys are voted at this time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>It appears to me that so far as the Government are concerned, the sky is the limit.  My view simply is that it is ridiculous that people who earn or have a salary of nearly £5,000 should get an increase in that salary.  I think that is madness. I understand the Minister said it was in 1957 that this application was made.  I wonder what delayed <Col N="552" /> them?  Why not be honest about it? They were ashamed to come to this House or ashamed or afraid of public opinion on this matter.  They realised what would be thought of their proposal to give an increase to people who are already earning up to £5,000 a year.</P>
      <P>I am sure no Deputy from his heart would vote for a Bill of that nature. Yesterday I put down a question to the Minister in connection with those salaries.  What has happened?  In one case there is an increase of £485 per annum, to date back, by Jove, to 1st January last.  As Deputy McGilligan pointed out, it is a new principle, anyhow.  It is strange that a present, you might say of twelve months back money, is to be given to people already drawing huge salaries.  I know it is very hard to mention it here and people may say that one is being personal, but that is not the case.</P>
      <P>I put it straight to the Minister and to the House that it is ridiculous, in the case of large salaries such as £4,850, to give an increase of £485, bringing that salary up to £5,335 per year.  That is his salary and that has been his salary.  If it ever happens that the cost of living should come down, which I am afraid will never happen, that salary cannot be touched.</P>
      <P>Does the Minister not realise that a salary such as that which I have mentioned is a ridiculous salary and that there is no need for an increase of £485 per annum?  In the other cases, the salaries mentioned and the proposed increases are as follows: A salary of £3,700 is to be increased by £370 per annum and a salary of £3,550 is to be increased by £325 per annum.  The salaries of the Judiciary alone in this country cost £158,768:10:0.  That is an enormous amount of money.  It is not difficult to imagine the public reaction to this proposal.  Just ask yourself what these increases mean&mdash; £485, £370, £370, £325, £325, £257:10, £201.  There are many people in this country who are in severe need of money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister may make the case that the cost of living has gone up by <Col N="553" /> 15 per cent.  Has it not gone up for every other section of the community? What is the reason for the special consideration for the Judiciary?  Why is there not some similar consideration for the old age pensioners and the unemployed who also must live and make their pitiful way as best they can?  There is no word about the cost of living as far as they are concerned but there is word about the cost of living for the man drawing £5,000 per annum.  Surely these salaried people mentioned in this Bill should be able to live in much more than modest comfort on their already very high salaries indeed, to put it mildly?  In my opinion, they can well live on them.  The man who cannot live on £5,000 a year should die immediately.  Gone are the days when £1,000 a year was too much for any man.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Who was it said that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>The name of the person who made that statement is so well known that I shall not mention it.  I wonder if some Deputies listening to me remember those days? I wonder if they ever thought the day would come when a Minister for Justice in a Fianna Fáil Government would introduce a Bill to increase salaries that are already £5,000 a year?  I never dreamed that it would happen and I think it is ridiculous. I do not think it is the Taoiseach's wish, the Minister's wish or the wish of this Government.  The Minister and the Government should withdraw this Bill which is absolutely ridiculous in the present condition of our country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>These salary increases must be paid for by the producer.  Does the Taoiseach or the Minister realise the present position of the agricultural community, especially in the west of Ireland?  Consider the sheep or lamb trade at the moment.  The agricultural community, farmers and workers, will have to bear the brunt of the proposed increases.  What is their position? Does the Taoiseach realise the position of the cattle trade at the moment?  Furthermore, sheep are not saleable at all in the West of <Col N="554" /> Ireland.  The position as regards cattle is that people who bought them last May and 12 months ago have to sell them to-day at prices lower than those they paid for them 12 months ago.  Yet they are the people who will have to bear this proposed increase in salary for people who in some cases are already getting £4,850 per annum and who are now to get an increase of £485, bringing that salary to roughly £5,335, the increase to date back to 1st January last.</P>
    <P>I do not think the Minister, the Taoiseach, the Government, or any Minister or any Taoiseach or any Government, could make a case for an increase in a salary of £5,000 at the present time in this country.  It is ridiculous and I shall oppose it in every way I can, both in this House and in the country.  When I look across at the Fianna Fáil Deputies, I know they do not want this Bill.  I know they were never consulted about it.  I know it is not their wish.  I know that if they go into the Lobby to vote for this Bill, they will do so against their will.  They are well aware that the electorate in general will take a very poor view of their action.  I would say that 99 out of every 100 voters would counsel them: &ldquo;Do not vote for the increases.  These people with £4,000 to £5,000 per annum are damned well off as it is and better off than any other section of the community.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Every member of the House recognises the importance of the Judiciary and recognises how important it is that its members should be remunerated in accordance with the office which they hold.  I believe that has already been achieved and that we are honouring our obligations to this section of the community in providing them with that reasonable remuneration in accordance with the resources of our State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Few people enjoy the remuneration enjoyed by the members of the Judiciary. The Taoiseach, with the many onerous duties and major responsibilities imposed on him, does not enjoy the remuneration of several of the people whose salaries we are asked to increase. <Col N="555" /> The office of Taoiseach is a much more important and onerous one, so far as the welfare of the country is concerned, than, say, that of Chief Justice.  How does their scale of remuneration compare? The Taoiseach with all the burdens and responsibilities imposed on him, has a salary of £3,000 per year, a salary to which I believe he is entitled.  If the Government had brought in a motion to the effect that that salary was inadequate, I would not oppose it, recognising, as I do, the importance of that office.  The burden of the office of Chief Justice does not compare with that of the office of Taoiseach; yet the salary is some 63 per cent. or 64 per cent. greater than that enjoyed by the head of the Government. That should not be the case and that is one of the reasons why I oppose this measure.</P>
    <P>The Chief Justice, if we may mention some of the persons in receipt of the highest salaries in the Judiciary, is in receipt of something like £100 per week, plus all additional expenses incidental to office.  I am asking the Taoiseach and the Minister for Justice, who are present, do they consider that fair and adequate remuneration, having regard to the resources of the country? Do they feel that a person enjoying almost £100 per week for his duties to the State is not sufficiently remunerated? If that is their opinion, I should like to know what is their opinion so far as the ordinary workers are concerned, so far as the ordinary labourers in my constituency of West Cork are concerned, where they cannot get a wage greater than £5. 11. 0. per week and where they are very lucky if they secure the work to provide that wage for them.</P>
    <P>Similarly, a reasonable percentage of the other members of the Judiciary are remunerated to the extent of £3,700 per year, plus all incidental expenses.  A salary of £3,700 per year, as is enjoyed by the Judges of the High Court and the President of the Circuit Court, is adequate to meet their needs.  The same can be said of the Circuit Court Judges and the District Justices.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="556" /> If the Taoiseach and the Government have some money available from public funds to increase the incomes of certain public employees, they will have little difficulty, if they look around, in finding other sections of the community who need that increase much more than the judges of the Supreme Court, the High Court and the Circuit Court and the justices of the District Court.</P>
    <P>It is not my intention to take from the status of the Judiciary but, having regard to our economic resources and the position of our people&mdash;and if I may say so, many of the people I represent in West Cork are fleeing daily from the land to seek a livelihood elsewhere&mdash;no Government have a mandate to come into this House to vote an increase to people who, as far as salaries go, are in a very favoured position.</P>
    <P>I am opposing this measure as forcefully and as vehemently as I possibly can.  While we in the Labour Party always address ourselves sympathetically to the question of increases in the income of workers, irrespective of whether they are professional workers, manual workers, self-employed or other workers, having examined this question closely and diligently, we cannot say that the people who are the subject matter of this Bill are in need of an increase.  We cannot say that and we do not propose to say it by our votes here.</P>
    <P>It may be said there is little more to mention in regard to this Bill, but I know that other members in the course of their contributions have adversely commented on the system of appointing these people and I should not like to let this opportunity pass without adding my voice to that condemnation. We all know that if you wish to obtain office as a Justice of any court, it is necessary that you apprentice yourself to a political Party.  That fact cannot be denied and if I were to review, as I think I am entitled to do on such a measure as this in order to support my argument that these people are sufficiently well paid, the activities of a number of these persons before they secured office as judges, what would <Col N="557" /> we find?  We would find that most of them were very active politicians.  A number of them are ex-members of this House; another number of them sought to become members but unfortunately for them, or maybe fortunately, they could not get the confidence of the people so that they could be elected.</P>
    <P>As I had occasion to mention in my own constituency of West Cork in connection with the recent Presidential Election and the Referendum, I had to contend in public speaking against potential judges.  I remember a man from the city of Dublin, or from an area contiguous to it, telling the people of West Cork that they should support the nomination of the present President and warning them of the pitfalls that were before the Irish people if they did not back the Government's decision to introduce the straight vote.</P>
    <P>Where would you look for some of these people to-day?  They have obtained promotion.  I had occasion to say to my constituents when addressing them publicly: &ldquo;It is unlikely that you will have this speaker with you here again.  He is here for the purpose of promoting his nomination as a member of the Judiciary.&rdquo;  And indeed he has been so promoted.</P>
    <P>Deputy Corry or anybody else in the Fianna Fáil Party will not deny that.  He went out to West Cork trying to belittle the Opposition Party in West Cork and he got his reward. That is very fine.  The Taoiseach or the Minister for Justice may say it is very fine, but I am asked, as a representative of the people of West Cork, to come here and impose a burden on these people in order to give him an increase in salary.  I have no intention of doing so and if this matter were left to a free vote of the House, I do not think my friends on the Fianna Fáil side would do so, either.</P>
    <P>I regret very much having to make such remarks because we all recognise the importance of law and order in the country.  We all recognise the importance of the independence of those who administer that law and order.  There is an obligation on <Col N="558" /> every one of us to look up to these men and to acklowledge that they are appointed by the State, the Government of the day, and that they have certain functions and duties and we as citizens have certain obligations to them.  I am asking the Taoiseach that in so far as future appointments to the Bench are concerned he as a new man in the office of Taoiseach, as a new head of the State, should put a few hours aside to look into this subject. I can tell him that as a result of these political appointments to the Bench in the various courts, we are losing, amongst the general public, a certain respect which they should have for the administrators of law and order.</P>
    <P>Let us examine the position.  If I were to go to West Cork and inform the people in the various districts that the man who was recently speaking to them has now been appointed a judge and appointed, possibly, as a result of going to West Cork and advising them to vote for Mr. de Valera's nomination and to vote &ldquo;yes&rdquo; in the referendum, that these are the main qualifications he enjoyed over and above his colleagues on the Bench for that office, naturally it would be bound to bring about a certain disrespect for the law which none of us would like.</P>
    <P>No matter from what angle we look at this Bill, there is no justification for it.  Look at it from the point of view of the professional worker or in comparison with other professional workers who may be endowed with similar academic qualifications.  Comparatively speaking, the Judiciary are more favoured.  Not only have they large salaries but there is no need on the part of the members of the Judiciary to look forward to the rainy day.  Thanks to the goodness of the State, they are well looked after and as soon as a member of the Judiciary leaves the Bench on his retirement not only does he enjoy a substantial gratuity but a substantial pension which many of our people would not earn in the course of their lifetime, even if they lived to be 80 years of age.</P>
    <P>Look at it from the point of view of the wage earner.  At the present time, a big proportion of our people <Col N="559" /> are in receipt of a remuneration varying between £3 and £8 a week. Unfortunately in my constituency many of them would be very glad if they were assured of an income even of £3 a week and many of them have family commitments.  Are they likely to be favourably disposed towards the Government's proposal to increase by almost £500&mdash;or, to be exact, £485&mdash; the remuneration of the Chief Justice who, as I said already, enjoys the formidable salary of almost £100 a week?  I doubt if they would be and I doubt if the Taoiseach, with all his ability as an orator, would be able to convince the people that this increase is justified.  If we look at it from the point of view of the business man, let him be big or small, we find that, if anything, there is more of a recession in trade than anything else and that the income of business people is more on the decline than on the upward trend.  That has been pointed out by the previous speaker.</P>
    <P>If we look at it from the point of view of the people in the main industry in this country, the agricultural community what do we find?  We find that during the past months the agricultural community had to bear a big decrease in income, due to the reduction of cattle and sheep prices.  Now we are asking these people, the different sections&mdash;the wage&mdash;earning sections, the business sections, and I would include the professional sections, and the farming sections&mdash;to vote a ten per cent. increase, retrospective to 1st January, to people already in receipt of high remuneration.</P>
    <P>I wish to oppose this Bill on behalf of the Labour Party.  We feel, as I have already stated, that any moneys which are available in Government funds for increases for public officials could be channelled towards the lower income groups and I am speaking of the many public servants, such as road workers and others, who have to live, whether they like it or not, on the uncertain remuneration of £5 to £6 a week.  Consequently, I am asking this House to reject this uncalled for Bill in no uncertain manner.  It is designed to increase the remuneration of people <Col N="560" /> who got a marked increase in 1953 and who, in my opinion, have no case whatever for an increase in 1959.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="The Taoiseach Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government were well aware, when we decided to bring this measure to the Dáil, that it was likely to meet with an amount of criticism here, criticism from some, perhaps, who were concerned about the principles of public policy involved in it, and from others who were concerned to exploit the political difficulties which the introduction of a measure of this kind necessarily involves for a Government in office.  If we allowed any thought of possible political penalties to ourselves, or any other improper consideration, to deter us from doing what we believed to be right in respect of the salaries paid to the members of the Judiciary, to induce us to fail to meet what seems to us to be a necessary obligation&mdash;to adjust these salaries in accordance with the changes in money values which have taken place since the scales were fixed &mdash;then it would be a very serious dereliction of duty on our part and, in my view, would demonstrate our unfitness to hold office as members of the Government.</P>
      <P>Deputy McGilligan said rightly enough, that in presenting this Bill to the Dáil, the Government are not asking members to settle the principles which should determine the remuneration of judges but merely to make adjustments in existing scales considered necessary by reason of changes in money values since they were last fixed.  If we were considering the basic principles which should determine the remuneration of judges, we would have to take into account a great deal more than the amounts they would require to enable them to live in comfort.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The question of what constitutes proper and adequate remuneration for judges has been considered in all democratic countries over many years, and principles have emerged from that consideration which have been applied almost universally.  I am sure that all members of the House accept that the independence of the Judiciary is something which we should try to preserve. <Col N="561" /> It is certainly something that all democratic Governments strive to uphold, and they try to express that aim in the levels of the remuneration fixed for judges.</P>
    <P>In any democratic society, judges occupy, and should be seen clearly by the public to occupy, positions of high authority, of independence and detachment. Independence in the sense that we use that term in relation to judges means something more than freedom from improper Government influence. It means putting them into a position in which they will be, as far as possible, immune from improper influence of any kind, and it is no exaggeration to say, in my view, that an adequate and, indeed, a generous basis of remuneration for judges is the basis of their independence.  It has always been so regarded here.  It is, indeed, so regarded everywhere.</P>
    <P>We have been very fortunate in this State in that from its beginning a very high standard of integrity has characterised our Judiciary.  There is, I think, a widespread public realisation that we have in our judges people who are immune from improper influences of any kind, people on whose integrity the public can rely.  That fact, and the recognition of that fact by the public, is the source of a great feeling of security to our people, and is an important contribution to the stability of our political institutions.  It is clearly desirable that we here in Dáil Éireann should take no action which might prejudice it, or which might be thought by the public to place it in jeopardy.</P>
    <P>The known integrity, independence and detachment of our judges is an important national asset which we must, in all circumstances, endeavour to preserve.  I know it may be said that you cannot buy integrity but we, and perhaps even more important the people, must have absolute confidence that the judges cannot be subjected to improper influences of any kind.</P>
    <P>Deputy Murphy and, I think, Deputy McQuillan, referred to the method of appointment.  I want to place my position on that beyond all doubt.  The appointment of members of the Judiciary is an important function of Government and to my last <Col N="562" /> breath I shall oppose any proposition to transfer that function to some bureaucratic institution or committee. The independence of the individual judge in the exercise of his judicial functions is very important, but that the Government elected by the people are superior in status and function to any other branch of the administration is a principle we must assert&mdash;a principle always asserted by those who understand the real functioning of democratic institutions.</P>
    <P>We must never be unfair to the judges, as we could well be tempted to, by the fact that they are completely within our power in respect to the adjustment of their salaries. The judges cannot, by reason of the character of their office, present their case to the Dáil or to the bar of public opinion.  Nevertheless, they have a case and, indeed, one which would take consideration of their position considerably further than the proposals embodied in this Bill, if we were to attempt to deal with it fully. Why should judges be singled out in this matter?  Why should they be subjected to definite objections to adjusting their salaries when there has been no opposition, as far as I know, to much greater increases given to other highly paid public servants?</P>
    <P>The case made by the judges is based upon the fact that their remuneration has not increased in the same proportion as the remuneration paid to other public servants, the salaries of whom were originally in closer relation to that of the judges than they are now.  In this Bill we are not in fact, proposing to give to members of the Judiciary increases comparable to that which senior officials of Government Departments and other public functionaries have obtained.</P>
    <P>There are also some facts in this regard which I think should be emphasised.  We here in this country, now and always, have paid our judges a great deal less than judges receive in other countries, a great deal less than judges are paid in the Six Counties or in Great Britain.  I am not going to suggest that we should adopt British standards in this regard but, if we were to attempt to relate <Col N="563" /> the salaries paid to our judges to the salaries paid in the Six Counties or Great Britain, or even to increase the salaries to the same degree as salaries of judges in these other countries have been increased, we would be giving them a great deal more than we are now giving them, or propose to give them.  Furthermore, this reluctance to adjust salaries of judges, which has persisted over many years, has operated to reduce considerably the effective levels of their real remuneration.</P>
    <P>Reference has been made to the position of the Chief Justice.  The salary of the Chief Justice was fixed at £4,000 a year in 1924 and the new rate, which will come into operation when this Bill is passed, will mean that the salary attaching to that office will have increased by only 33? per cent.</P>
    <P>Deputy Murphy said that the Chief Justice should not be paid more than the Taoiseach.  He always has been paid more than the Taoiseach.  The person holding the corresponding office in every country is always paid at a very much higher rate than the Head of the Government.  There is, I think, the idea of symbolising in that highest judicial office the desire to ensure complete independence and detachment, and to emphasise the status of the judiciary, and the importance attached to that particular post.</P>
    <P>In the case of judges of the Supreme Court the rates of the remuneration which will become operative on the enactment of this Bill have been increased by 36 per cent. as compared with the rates originally fixed in 1924.  It is, perhaps, fair to say that in the case of the corresponding class of judges in the Six Counties, although in 1924 they were paid at a higher rate than the judges here, their salaries have since been increased by 85 per cent.  In the case of judges of the High Court, the rate of increase which on the enactment of this Bill will have been granted on the rate fixed in 1924 is 43 per cent. while in that of the High Court judges in the Six County area there has been an increase of 116 per cent. in their salaries since that year.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="564" /> In the case of judges of the Circuit Court, the salaries that will be paid on the enactment of this Bill will be 67 per cent. higher than the rate fixed in 1924.  In respect of the Six County area the rates paid have increased by 141 per cent. over the same period.  In the case of the ordinary District Justice, the rate which we are now proposing to bring into effect will represent a rise of 92½ per cent. on the rate fixed in 1924.</P>
    <P>There are two observations I want to make in that regard.  It is quite clear that the remuneration of judges in the Six County area, in so far as it is determined by the rates payable in Great Britain, would not be a proper standard for us to follow.  We are not following it; we think that the salaries of judges here should be related to the higher rates of remuneration prevailing in other branches of the public service and the income which a practitioner of the law in good standing could hope to earn at the Bar.</P>
    <P>I also drew attention to the fact that the changes in the rates of salary for the various branches of the Judiciary which have been effected since 1924 have resulted in giving a much higher relative increase to the justices and judges remunerated at lower rates than to those remunerated at higher rates. That has been a feature of all our salary adjustments in recent years, a feature on which I had very strong representations only very recently from the association that represents these professional and higher grade civil servants but one which I think we can justify in the special circumstances of a protracted period of inflation, of a decline in money values.</P>
    <P>Deputy McQuillan urged that there should be a special committee to deal with this matter.  I think there might be a case at some time to reconsider anew the basis of the judicial salary scales; I do not think this is the time for it.  I think we should be concerned now merely with making the global adjustment which the decline in money values requires us in equity to make. It is not necessary to set up a special committee for that purpose.  Indeed, I would regard the Members of the Dáil as just as competent to decide what is <Col N="565" /> just and proper in that respect as any committee that might be chosen.  I also see the possibility, having regard to the fact that the rise in the cost of living since the judicial salaries were last fixed has been 15 per cent., that such a committee might in fact propose to give the judges a higher rate of increase than that which the Bill provides.</P>
    <P>It is, of course, not correct to say that civil servants remunerated on scales which relate to judicial salaries are within the conciliation and arbitration scheme and I think it would be highly inappropriate that judges should be subject to such a procedure. I do not think we should, by any device, seek to lower the status of our judges.  If I have any anxiety about the position in regard to their salaries it is that, because of the much lower rate of remuneration paid to judges here as compared with other neighbouring countries, we appear to be representing them as less competent or entrusted with less responsible duties than judges elsewhere.  We know that is not so; we know that if we have to pay them at lesser rates than judges doing similar duties are paid elsewhere it is because of factors internal to our economy.  But if we cannot pay them at the same rates as judges are paid elsewhere, we must make it quite clear that that does not mean that we are proclaiming them, or regarding them, as being inferior in status or in competence to their opposite numbers in other countries.</P>
    <P>I think it is also fair and reasonable to mention in this connection that the Government are proposing to reduce the number of judges of the Circuit Court and justices of the District Court and in fact the over&mdash;all cost of these services to the community will be less than it has been notwithstanding the increase in the remuneration which we are proposing here by reason of these reductions in the number of judges and justices, which incidentally will mean that, to some extent, the judges of the Circuit Court and the justices of the District Court will have more work to do.</P>
    <P>I do not think that the changes which were made some time ago in <Col N="566" /> the jurisdiction of the District Court involves, as has been contended by the justices, some further increase in their remuneration.  At least, I assume that so far as these changes of jurisdiction preceded the report of the committee of 1953 they were taken into account fully by that committee in the recommendations they made to the Dáil and on which the Dáil acted.</P>
    <P>The question of principle which arises here is whether or not changes in the judicial salaries are in the public interest.  I would strongly urge that they should be so regarded.  Indeed, I believe that I could justify higher increases than are proposed.  I would like to think that there was no feeling of disgruntlement among the members of the Judiciary.  I hope they will regard this Bill as an indication of the Government's acceptance of their claim and a reasonable attempt to meet them.  I am quite certain that the vast majority of thoughtful opinion among our people will give an affirmative answer to that question and will, indeed, support the changes in judicial salaries for which the Bill provides.  I would regard that, and shall regard it, as a very small price to pay for the preservation of the independence and the status of the Judiciary.</P>
    <P>There is only one further thing I want to say.  Deputy McGilligan suggested here that we should provide for judges an arrangement similar to that which we provided recently for civil servants under which, without cost to the Exchequer, a judge could voluntarily give up portion of his retirement pension for the benefit of his widow in the event of his death.  I have informed the Judiciary that the Government would be willing to enact the necessary legislation to permit of that and I am awaiting their comments on that subject.</P>
    <P>There are other aspects of the present practice in relation to the Judiciary which are under consideration because consideration has been urged on the Government but no decisions have been taken and no immediate proposals for the Dáil are in contemplation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>Having regard to the importance of the personnel with whose remuneration we are dealing <Col N="567" /> under this proposal, I think that in this more than in any other measure before the House we should approach the matter with a full sense of responsibility and not be swayed by the popular mood or be directed towards anything in the nature of a partisan approach.</P>
      <P>Fundamentally, this is a question of principle.  Having listened to the Taoiseach in support of these provisions and understanding that the Minister made a somewhat different case I am now&mdash;I am sure other members will also be in the same position&mdash;unable to understand whether the Government's view is that these increases are <i>simpliciter</i> to meet the cost of living of 15 per cent. or whether the increases are imposed as a cushion against improper importuning of the Judiciary, making their independence secure and their dignity unassailable.</P>
      <P>It would be extremely easy for me in my other capacity outside this House to get a different but also popular view, namely, to support this proposal but so satisfied am I of the integrity and the due exercise of judicial functions by the members of the Judiciary from the District Court to the Supreme Court that I am enabled to come in here and oppose these provisions on the grounds stated by the Minister, in the first instance, and equally vehemently on the grounds stated by the Taoiseach.</P>
      <P>Indeed, the Taoiseach's intervention in this debate, if one were searching for a title for it, would well merit the title of The Great Conversion.  He served his apprenticeship for very many years with the author of the famous remark that nobody in this country was worth more than £1,000 a year.  In passing, it is interesting to note that, without any obvious qualm of conscience, the author of that remark is now drawing over £10,000 per annum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Nobody can underestimate the value of an independent Judiciary. While it cannot be altogether left out of consideration, I think that salaries have, in the main, got very little to do with the exercise of <Col N="568" /> judicial functions or the integrity that sustains the proper exercise of such functions.  Even at a lower salary than those at present obtaining, I am satisfied that the people of this country would get the same value from the people who occupy various positions in the different grades of the administration here.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFlanagan" hpid="Mr. S. Flanagan Mr. S. Flanagan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Flanagan</NameTxt>
      <P>You have to attract ability as well as integrity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>I am well satisfied also on the question of ability.  There are very few people who really appreciate that of the many appointments made by all Governments since the foundation of this State there was in each a degree of sacrifice involved for the appointees in giving up their practices either as barristers or as solicitors. It is true that the comparative security of the Bench provides some sort of compensation for relinquishing a busy and highly remunerative practice. Nevertheless, I would say that in relinquishing a highly remunerative practice an able person or a person of integrity has got within himself, irrespective of the salary commanded by the particular judicial office, the desire to serve and a full appreciation of the necessity that there should be a desire to serve.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister for Justice has come in here and acknowledged, at this stage of our political arguments on economics, that there has been a 15 per cent. increase in the cost of living and that these provisions simply mean that the Government propose to go two-thirds of the way towards meeting that increase of 15 per cent. by giving a 10 per cent. increase.  I think that is the least valid of all the arguments &mdash;and there are many&mdash;that could be made for increasing judicial salaries at the present time but when one looks, as one must to be realistic, at the level of the salaries obtaining now, and takes the example of the highest office enjoying approximately £100 per week, it seems to me, as I am sure it will seem to anybody who realistically faces the mathematics of the matter, that in order to cushion a person who is the recipient of £100 per week against a 15 per cent. increase <Col N="569" /> in the cost of living, it is strange that it should be necessary to give him another £10 per week.</P>
    <P>How will that be regarded by the person in receipt of £10 per week in any other avocation?  To give him a 10 per cent. increase would mean increasing his salary to £11.  Let us come down to the £5 per week person of which there are very many in this country.  A 10 per cent. increase for him represents 10/-.  I do not for a moment want to take away from the position which a judge of any court from the Supreme Court to the District Court occupies and the necessity for him to preserve a certain standard but if we are to relate that standard to a cost of living, it seems ridiculous in my view to suggest that it is necessary to give up to £10 per week in order to preserve that particular standard when we must realise that £10 per week is the average income of the majority of our people.  In fact, it is not even so high.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Old Age Pensions">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Old Age Pensions.</Title>
    <P>1.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFinucane" hpid="Mr. Finucane Mr. Finucane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finucane</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Social Welfare whether in view of the hardship imposed on old age pensioners by the present rate of pension, he intends to introduce legislation to provide for an increased pension.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJKennedy" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Kennedy) Michael Joseph Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Kennedy)</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that increases in old age pensions were granted as recently as August 1959, it is not proposed, at present, to introduce legislation to provide for further increases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister be prepared to reconsider his answer in view of the Bill we are now discussing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy took the words out of my mouth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFlanagan" hpid="Mr. S. Flanagan Mr. S. Flanagan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Flanagan</NameTxt>
      <P>They suit either of you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="570" />
    <Speaker pid="FlorenceWycherley" hpid="Mr. Wycherley Mr. Wycherley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wycherley</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister consider introducing legislation whereby a man getting workmen's compensation will not have to forfeit the old age pension as a result of getting workmen's compensation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a separate question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>2.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Social Welfare if he will double the old age pension for the week preceding Christmas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not proposed to make a special payment of the kind referred to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Parliamentary Secretary should take steps to have a double old age pension made payable for Christmas week.  It would not cost a great deal of money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is making a speech.  Has he a supplementary question to ask?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it cost a great deal of money?  How much would it cost?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>It would cost approximately £216,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>As I said when I asked this question this day twelve months, that is only a bagatelle out of the Taoiseach's £100 million.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is continuing his speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickGiles" hpid="Captain Giles Captain Giles">
      <NameTxt>Captain Giles</NameTxt>
      <P>They are leaving it to Santa Claus.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no Santa Claus in this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Legislation Translation Costs">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Legislation Translation Costs.</Title>
    <P>3.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he will state in respect of each of the years 1944 to 1958, inclusive, the cost of translating into Irish every law enacted by the Oireachtas in English.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Finance (Dr. Ryan) James Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The reply is in the form of a tabular statement which, with the permission <Col N="571" /> of the Leas-Cheann Comhairle, will be included in the Official Report.</P>
      <P>The statement is as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="4" colnum="4" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
            </entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Year ended 31st March</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Cost</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1943-44</entry>
            <entry>1,100</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1944-45</entry>
            <entry>1,300</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1945-46</entry>
            <entry>1,400</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1946-47</entry>
            <entry>1,500</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1947-48</entry>
            <entry>1,700</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1948-49</entry>
            <entry>2,000</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1949-50</entry>
            <entry>2,300</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1950-51</entry>
            <entry>2,300</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1951-52</entry>
            <entry>2,600</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1952-53</entry>
            <entry>2,600</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1953-54</entry>
            <entry>2,800</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1954-55</entry>
            <entry>2,800</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1955-56</entry>
            <entry>2,800</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1956-57</entry>
            <entry>2,700</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>1957-58</entry>
            <entry>2,700</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>The cost shown is the estimated annual cost of the proportion of the Oireachtas translation staff engaged on the work referred to in the question.  Other work is performed by this staff.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Medicinal Tablets">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Medicinal Tablets.</Title>
    <P>4.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce whether the recent imposition of duty on medicinal tablets affects tablets used in the treatment of (a) influenza and (b) septic throats; and, if so, what steps have been taken to ensure that adequate supplies of such tablets are available at reasonable prices to combat any widespread outbreak of such ailments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. J. Lynch) Jack Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. J. Lynch)</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the Customs duty recently imposed on medicinal tablets applies to tablets used in the treatment of (a) influenza and (b) septic throats.  The licensing provision which is attached to the duty will ensure that, to the extent to which adequate supplies may not be available from home sources, these tablets may be imported free of the duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister satisfied that the tablets can be supplied quickly enough in the event of a sudden epidemic such as frequently <Col N="572" /> occurs in the early part of the year, about January or February?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I am satisfied that there will be no danger of inability to meet such an emergency.  If the Deputy was here yesterday, he will remember that I told Deputy Dr. Browne that a list was being compiled of tablets that may not be produced here or that are not likely to be produced here between the manufacturers and the importers so as to make doubly sure that such an emergency can be met.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask the Minister, if a case arises where there is a proprietary brand of tablet of popular user which, partly on psychological grounds, gives relief from pain, is it the Minister's intention to allow that tablet to go on being imported even if some domestic manufacturer produces one with a similar formula, bearing in mind that the fact that the formula of the two tablets may be virtually identical does not give the user the psychological advantage of using a tablet which experience has taught him or her provides the relief required?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a matter on which I would be relying on the Department of Health for advice and, as I said last week, if these circumstances were positively established, I would be prepared to ask the Department of Health for their advice to see whether there should be any change in that respect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister say when the list of tablets to which he has just made reference will be available for public information?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot say offhand but the manufacturers have undertaken to supply a list in a very short time.  This will then be referred to the importers and an agreed list will be available for publication as soon as possible after that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Within a fortnight or a month?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I should say in a fortnight.  I really cannot say, but I should imagine in a fortnight.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="573" />
    <P>5.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce whether he is aware that some retailers of medicinal tablets have increased the prices of some products which are not affected by the recent imposition of duties on medicinal tablets; and, if so, if he will take steps to prevent this exploitation of sick people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not so aware.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>6.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he will state the pharmaceutical and medical qualifications of the civil servants entrusted with the responsibility of accepting or rejecting applications for the importation free of duty of medicinal tablets.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The civil servants who deal with applications for the importation free of duty of medicinal tablets have no pharmaceutical or medical qualifications; there is no reason why they should have such qualifications.  Processing of applications is an administrative function. The advice and guidance of fully qualified officers in Government service and of people in the trade are available at all times if required.</P>
      <P>The Deputy is, of course, aware that the responsibility of recommending or declining to recommend applications rests with me, and not with civil servants as stated in the Question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister state what pharmaceutical and medical qualifications he has?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>About as much as the Deputy, I would say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good.  That is nothing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I have such advice available to me.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Brosna (Kerry) Water Supply">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Brosna (Kerry) Water Supply.</Title>
    <P>7.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFinucane" hpid="Mr. Finucane Mr. Finucane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finucane</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if he is aware that there is an acute shortage of water in the village of Brosna, County Kerry; and what steps have been taken to ensure that an adequate <Col N="574" /> supply of water is made available for this village.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Health (Mr. MacEntee) (for the Minister for Local Government) Minister for Health (Mr. MacEntee) (for the Minister for Local Government)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Health (Mr. MacEntee) (for the Minister for Local Government)</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the Kerry County Council found it necessary to shut off the Brosna water supply at night-time during the summer months in order to conserve the yield from the source, because of the exceptionally dry weather, but that the full service has been restored for some time.</P>
      <P>The Council has engaged a consulting engineer to design an improved water supply scheme for the village. The outline proposals for this scheme have been approved by the Department, and contract documents are in course of preparation.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions." RHead="Oral Answers. - Road Safety">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Road Safety.</Title>
    <P>8.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government when he will introduce legislation for the purpose of ensuring greater safety on the roads.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot say at present when new legislation on road traffic will be introduced.  I hope to have final proposals approved for circulation in the near future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Late last year, I asked the same Question of the Minister for Local Government and the reply I got was that legislation would be introduced early this year. That is on the records of the House and I think it is most unsatisfactory, in view of the slaughter on the roads, that legislation has not been brought to this House sooner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="The Taoiseach Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The lorry driver should have let you pass.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Gowran races are on today and I will have to drive home against the lights.  I arrived on the scene of an accident in which three people were killed, and that is no laughing matter.  I arrived at the scene of another accident shortly after that.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Waterford Reconstruction Grants">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Waterford Reconstruction Grants.</Title>
    <P>9.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if he will state <Col N="575" /> the cause of the delay in granting a loan to the Waterford Corporation for the financing of their reconstruction grants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>A loan for the purpose of the payment of supplementary grants under Sections 10 and 11 of the Housing (Amendment) Act, 1952, as amended, was sanctioned on 9th May, 1957.  No application has since been received for sanction to a loan for the payment of supplementary grants in respect of works of reconstruction.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Offaly School Toilet Facilities">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Offaly School Toilet Facilities.</Title>
    <P>10.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. T.F. O'Higgins Mr. T.F. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.F. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Education when the work of providing necessary and proper toilet facilities for St. Ciaran's national school, Ballycumber, will commence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJohnHillery" hpid="Minister for Education (Dr. Hillery) Patrick J. Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Education (Dr. Hillery)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to carry out an extensive scheme of improvements, including the provision of water-flushed toilets, in the case of St. Ciaran's National School, Ballycumber.  The production of satisfactory evidence of title to the additional ground required in connection with the scheme is awaited in my Department.  When this evidence has been submitted my Department will be in a position to sanction a grant towards the cost of the scheme.  I am unable to say at present when the actual building work will commence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. T.F. O'Higgins Mr. T.F. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.F. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate the Minister's reply but, arising out of it, is it not correct that this proposal has been under consideration now for quite a number of years?  Is the Minister aware that there is, locally, considerable concern at the present state of affairs in the school? The school is right beside the church and the local cemetery and there is something approaching a public nuisance there at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJohnHillery" hpid="Dr. Hillery Dr. Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>My Department has been concerned but the Deputy will appreciate that title must be established before a grant can be given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. T.F. O'Higgins Mr. T.F. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.F. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>It will engage the Minister's attention?</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Courts of Justice Bill," RHead="1959&mdash;Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Courts of Justice Bill, 1959&mdash;Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="576" /> Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following amendment:</P>
    <P>To delete &ldquo;now&rdquo; and to add at the end of the motion &ldquo;this day twelve months&rdquo;. &mdash;(Deputies McQuillan and Dr. Browne.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach has said, in my view very properly, that you cannot purchase or buy integrity. That maxim can be applied with equal force to all sections of the community in whom any position of trust, however great or small, reposes.  I agree that integrity or honesty cannot be purchased.  There falls down the argument that in order to establish independence, in order to make a Judiciary immune from any improper advances, they must be paid, and paid substantially. Equally, of course, does the argument of the cost of living fall down when one looks at the present level of salaries and relates that level to the economy of a country such as ours.</P>
      <P>I know it is correct, as the Taoiseach has stated, that judges in the Six Counties and Great Britain are paid on a higher scale.  But Great Britain is an extremely wealthy country and the Six Counties, subsidised by Great Britain, can be regarded in the same light as far as the payment of these kinds of salaries is concerned.  In my view, to determine the salaries of judges, one cannot relate it, on the one hand, to the cost of living and, on the other, to the purchase of integrity.  It must be based, as very probably was done in 1924, on the selection of an arbitary figure related in composite way towards all qualities necessary in a judge for the proper dispensation of justice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to say a word on the system of selection.  I could not agree more than I do with the Taoiseach when he says it is the Government's right, as the duly elected authority by the people, to select judges.  I do not think, in deference to my friend.  Deputy M. P. Murphy, that there is anything wrong with a person taking part in the political life of the country, advising <Col N="577" /> the people one way or the other as a member of a political Party and afterwards becoming a judge.  More than any other country, this country has proved the success of an independent Judiciary which has, by and large, been formed on a political basis, and that goes for judges, no matter by what Administration they were appointed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not the point. The point is that you must be active in a political party before you can become a judge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>Some people have been successful in fooling political Parties they were so active and have reached the top.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Wisdom came to the political Parties too late.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>Be that as it may, the position is that, however they came to be appointed, whether it was for true or false service in a political Party, they gave satisfaction afterwards.  As I am on the subject, neither can it be said that a person who does not enjoy a large practice in the profession, either as barrister or a solicitor, would make a bad judge.  Experience has shown otherwise.  Very often on the Bench a man displays qualities which were hitherto undiscovered.  The system of selection, therefore, in my view, is perfectly all right.  Experience shows that politicians who are successful legal practitioners are those people who fail very often to become members of Dáil Éireann.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair has already pointed out that the question of the qualifications of the Judiciary is not under discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>There never seems to be an opportunity here to talk about the Judiciary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill deals with their remuneration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>What I want to say is that prior membership of this House is not a disqualification for membership of the Judiciary or does not render their administration of justice in any way doubtful or defective.  As put by the Minister, on the one hand, and by the Taoiseach, on the other, this is a <Col N="578" /> sort of conflict between money values and a question of principle.  I do not think it can be related to the cost of living, having regard to the high level. I do not think it can be related to independence and integrity, having regard to the universally accepted principle that one cannot purchase integrity. It resolves itself into an arbitrary figure and, having regard to the economic conditions obtaining here and the present structure of our economy and standard of living, I do not see that any case has been made for this increase.</P>
      <P>If a case were made for increases, I might be able, as others in the House would be able, to go a certain part of the way with the Minister.  For instance, if he were to distinguish between a Circuit Court Judge who sits in Dublin for every day in every term and the country-going Circuit Court Judge who does not sit quite so often.  The same distinction is made in the case of District Justices who sit in Dublin and those who sit in the country.  I want to support the view urged by Deputy McQuillan, and to which the Taoiseach has subscribed to some extent, namely, that the widows of judges, particularly of those who die in harness, should have some means by way of pension upon which to rely in the event of that sad occurrence which can take place at any time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That does not seem to arise on the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach referred to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>He refered to it very fully by way of a superannuation scheme and he referred to it to the extent of saying that, as head of the Government, he has been in touch with the Judiciary on this matter and is awaiting their comments on proposals made by him.  If any case is to be made for increases in the salaries of the Judiciary, it could well be made on this basis, that they might find, having regard to the standard of living expected of them, having regard to the standard of education they are expected to give their children and having regard to their exalted office and the consequent expenditure <Col N="579" /> they are called upon to make, that saving certainly becomes more difficult for them than in other cases.  In view of the conditions obtaining with regard to their widows and children in the event of a sudden demise in harness, that difficulty in saving must be an ever-present worry with them. If the case were made here that they wanted extra money in order to be able to save with greater confidence and make provision for a situation for which no provision exists at the moment, I would say there would be a basis to some extent for that.</P>
      <P>The Taoiseach in giving the percentage increases related them very cleverly to the figures obtaining in 1924.  He did that, I think, because, if he related them to the figures obtaining on the occasion of the last increase in 1953, the whole fallacy in this argument would be exposed.  An increase in salary, whether it be for the Judiciary or anybody else, must be related to some extent to the position occupied by the salary recipient, but, in the main, must be related to the country's economy and the taxpayers' ability to pay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to clarify the position in relation to our amendment in view of some of the statements following upon Deputy McQuillan's opening remarks.  First of all, in reply to the Taoiseach's suggestion that opposition to this Bill is an attempt at exploiting a situation in order to make the Government unpopular, let me point out immediately that Governments have on occasion to do unpopular things, but it does not follow from that that, because one speaks for the purpose of airing what one believes to be public opinion on certain matters, one is necessarily attempting thereby to embarrass the Government.  Indeed, had the Taoiseach given a little thought to the amendment, he would have found that, were he to accept the amendment, he would save himself and his Government very considerable embarrassment, since the recommendation to increase judicial salaries following upon the appointment of an independent committee of this House would be a recommendation by both sides of <Col N="580" /> the House.  The Government would thereby be saved both the embarrassment and the political odium to which the Taoiseach feels opposition to this Bill may possibly give rise since we would all be jointly responsible for the decision taken.</P>
      <P>It is because we fully appreciate that this question of assessing the proper remuneration for persons in these exalted positions in our society is so important that we believe we are not competent to say whether £4,000, £3,000, £1,500 or £2,000 is adequate compensation for the varying scales of responsibility which fall upon the shoulders of the different members of the Judiciary.  Secondly, if an increase is necessary, we do not feel competent to decide that a two per cent., an eight per cent. or a ten per cent. increase is desirable over all, or whether the percentage should be varied in such a way that those on the lower scales would receive a higher percentage and those on the higher scales a lower percentage.</P>
      <P>There are many considerations into which a committee of this House could usefully examine, with all the facts at their disposal, in order to reach an equitable decision.  When people say the members of the Judiciary are overpaid, they should remember that there are members in the lower categories of the Judiciary who are only moderately well paid by present day standards. To condemn the whole Judiciary because one section appears to be overpaid is, in my opinion, being unnecessarily extravagant and, to a certain extent, a little irresponsible. Despite Deputy McGilligan's comments, I still feel that the precedent established&mdash;a precedent which appears to have satisfied the House on a former occasion, and the Judiciary likewise&mdash; is a good precedent, and a wise precedent. As I have already pointed out, I believe its adoption now would save the Government considerable embarrassment and, for that reason, it should recommend itself to the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Like Deputy Lindsay, I found the Taoiseach's intervention, far from clarifying the position, only succeeded in making confusion worse confounded. <Col N="581" /> I cannot accept the proposition that there is a section in our society who must be paid to stay honest.  I do not say those are the exact words used by the Taoiseach, but that was the implication.  He implied that, in order to maintain the independence of the Judiciary, it is imperative that they should be paid at a particularly high level.  I do not accept that point of view.  There is some basic morality in all of us which determines our interpretation of what is right and what is wrong.  We do not become incorruptible because of a particular salary.  If that principle were accepted, surely it should apply right down throughout every section of our community.</P>
    <P>Consider the position of the Garda. They are in a very vulnerable position. They are the custodians of law and order.  As compared with the salaries paid for similar work elsewhere, they have perhaps a greater grievance than have the members of the Judiciary. From that point of view and from the point of view of their vulnerability to corruption, or their being prevailed on to indulge in dishonest practices, they are in a much worse position.  I do not think the case made in that regard is a valid one.</P>
    <P>My remarks would apply equally to higher civil servants, who have very responsible functions to perform; to politicians, who have very grave responsibilities and very important functions in the State; to Cabinet Ministers; and, in particular, to the Taoiseach himself.  All these sections in our society could justify the payment to them of fabulous salaries on foot of the argument advanced by the Taoiseach that, if the Judiciary are not extremely well paid, they will not remain honest.  I join with Deputy Lindsay in dismissing that case made on behalf of the Judiciary, It is one which does an injustice to the Judiciary.  I believe they are just as likely to remain honest and conscientious in the discharge of their functions without any increase in remuneration.</P>
    <P>I cannot join with the Taoiseach in the case he makes that, because of the greater remuneration paid in <Col N="582" /> Northern Ireland and Great Britain, there is necessarily a case for increasing the pay of our Judiciary here.  That argument could equally well apply to every single section that goes to make up our society.  It could apply with the greatest force perhaps to that section in which I am particularly interested, the old age pensioners, the unemployment benefit and unemployment assistance classes, and all the other classes dependent upon social services.  These are at a disadvantage compared with their counterparts elsewhere. I do not think that argument helps the Taoiseach's case at all.</P>
    <P>The Taoiseach suggested that there is no relationship between the attitude we should adopt to these people and the attitude to be adopted in relation to the higher civil servants. Now, Deputy McQuillan did not introduce that comparison of his own accord.  He introduced it because it was first introduced by the Judiciary themselves in their submission to the Commission in 1953.  On page 11, they set out the different scales of salary for the various higher civil servants, chairman of the Revenue Commissioners, various secretaries of Departments, the secretariat and so on, so the comparison has been made by the judges themselves.</P>
    <P>We believe it is relevant and we also believe it is permissible to compare these people.  On the general question of conciliation, we do not see why it should not be adopted.  It is a good practice; it is a fair practice; it is one which leaves no feeling of discontent in the mind of anybody, whether agricultural workers, rural workers, salaried workers, civil servants or whatever they may be.  So long as they feel there was a fair examination of their claim for increased remuneration, then everybody is satisfied, including, and most important, the public who will have to foot the bill.  Consequently, we believe the precedent already established is a good precedent and one to which the Government should continue to adhere.</P>
    <P>On the question of the other point made by Deputy McQuillan with regard to the conditions of appointment <Col N="583" /> and the facilitating of a committee to investigate those conditions, he became rather&mdash;heated is not the right word &mdash;concerned about this whole problem of the appointment of the members of the Judiciary.  He seeks to break away from the sacrosanct principle that the Judiciary must be appointed by the Government.  There may be a case for the continuation of the system whereby the members of the Judiciary are appointed by the Government, but I do not believe there is anything really sacrosanct about such a conception of appointment.  It seems to me that the slogan that they must be the supreme authority and that the Judiciary must be ensured of independence of the Government is one of those phrases which people have accepted from generation to generation without any very deep thought or examination.  It is rather like the idea which was accepted at one time of the divine right of kings.  Those slogans were not examined to see if they had any real validity.</P>
    <P>There may be a case for the retention of the present system, but I do not think that the suggestion that it ensures the independence of the Judiciary is correct.  I think the contrary is true, although I should like to make it quite clear that I join with other Deputies in believing that the Judiciary have been independent of successive Governments.  I do not think it necessarily follows, or need necessarily follow, that because the Government choose a member of the Judiciary, he is independent of the Government. That does not follow at all and, on the contrary, indeed a member of the Judiciary who may have been appointed by a particular Government may have less reason for feeling independent of that Government which appointed him particularly if he happens to have been closely affiliated as a political colleague with the men who appointed him, prior to his appointment.</P>
    <P>I suggest, if that is the case the Taoiseach makes for the retention of the present system, it is not a valid case.  It would be wise to examine the position in the light of the fact that <Col N="584" /> there is some public disquiet that the making of appointments to the Judiciary appears to be solely determined by the amount of political service and the quality of the political service rendered by the appointee before the Government came into office.  Whether or not the Taoiseach is prepared to face up to that, the Minister should be prepared to do so. That is a generally accepted belief amongst members of the public and it is no good pretending that is not so.</P>
    <P>I should like to reiterate the two points we have made in our amendment. The precedent already established should be repeated.  The Taoiseach asks: why single out the Judiciary?  We are with the Taoiseach in that question: why single out the Judiciary for special treatment?  We have no hesitation in saying that if a joint committee of this House goes into the case made by the members of the Judiciary for an increase in salary, and if, as the Taoiseach suggested, instead of 10 per cent., the increase recommended by the joint committee were 15 per cent.&mdash;I do not agree that it would be; I doubt if it would be 10 per cent., but if it were 15 per cent.&mdash;we are prepared to abide by that decision because it would be the judicially considered view of persons able to examine all the facts and come to, what we can and must accept, as the decision of our colleagues, as a fair, just and equitable decision on the facts as they had them before them.</P>
    <P>On the second point about the assessment of the conditions of appointment of the Judiciary, I do not think a case has been made by the Taoiseach for the retention of the present system.  If he really wanted to satisfy the public, he would allow a special committee to examine the whole question.  If that committee reported back to this House that there is no better alternative to the existing situation, then we would readily accept their decision.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. T.F. O'Higgins Mr. T.F. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.F. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say I find myself in agreement with a great deal of what Deputy Dr. Browne has said.  I do not entirely approve of all he has said but his speech has been a <Col N="585" /> helpful one.  We find ourselves in this House today necessarily discussing a Bill which the Minister and the Government felt they had a duty to bring forward.  It is known by anyone who was associated with discussions of this kind that there would be, and I think there have been, many unfortunate remarks in relation to the Judiciary.</P>
      <P>I should like to say as a lawyer, as an Irishman, and as a person interested in the welfare of this country, that we have been extremely fortunate in the high standard of our Judiciary since the State was founded.  When the State was founded, it was necessary for Irishmen to establish a really Irish Judiciary here.  I think that, generally speaking, that Judiciary has redounded to the credit of the country.  We have not had in this country a bench of judges that has in any way been subservient or servile to the Executive authority.  Deputies will appreciate that from time to time our judges have expressed not merely their independence but have very definitely established it.  There have been many Acts of the Oireachtas which to the annoyance and embarrassment of the Government in office at the time, our judges have held to be without the Constitution.  Indeed, it is not many years since, in the face of threats of violence of one kind or another. Irish judges gave first-rate evidence of their determination to carry out their duty in spite of what the cost might be.</P>
      <P>I appreciate, as a lawyer, that any member of my profession who speaks does so in relation to a profession that has never had the advantage of a good public relations officer.  Generally speaking, most people enjoy a good opportunity of attacking lawyers. Perhaps in some cases that may be justified but it is, whether or not people appreciate it or realise it, a very old profession and a profession I think in respect of which every lawyer is proud.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I suppose it inevitably follows that many people, when they discuss the position of judges, feel that this is one of the opportunities they have of attacking judges and attacking the Judiciary.  I think that is understandable. <Col N="586" /> It may be human nature. However, it is unfortunate because I do not think the question of judges' salaries and their terms and conditions of appointment can ever fairly and rationally be considered in view of the quite unreasonable prejudice that exists in the minds of many people.</P>
    <P>It is worth recalling here&mdash;I know it has been said already but it is no harm to repeat it&mdash;that the high standard of our Judiciary should be noted and that the pay and allowances of the Judiciary in the Republic are very much lower than those of a Judiciary with a far more limited sphere of activity in the other part of the island.  Judicial salaries here are lower than in Northern Ireland or in England.  While the judicial system is not comparable in other countries I think it is nevertheless true to say that judicial salaries here are a very much lower than in most other countries.</P>
    <P>There is also a fact to be considered which has already been mentioned but again it must be repeated.  We do not here provide any pension or means of subsistence for a judge's widow.  That is a regrettable state of affairs.  I know of the widow of a former judge who, in the autumn of her years, is forced to exist on the charity of friends or on her own desperate efforts, late in life, to earn her daily bread.  That appears to me to be quite a wrong state of affairs. Obviously, it is something which should be remedied and I think probably would be remedied by the good sense of this House if we were given the opportunity of doing so.</P>
    <P>This Bill has been introduced in certain economic circumstances in the country and introduced&mdash;it could not be avoided; I appreciate that&mdash;without any prior consideration by the different groups and Parties in the House.  While that is the correct procedure to be adopted under the ordinary Rules of the House, I think it is unfortunate in relation to judges and in relation to other persons in a capacity like that. I entirely endorse the view expressed by Deputy Dr. Browne.  The question of Judicial salaries and conditions is pre-eminently a matter to be considered either by some joint committee of this <Col N="587" /> House or by an independent <i>ad hoc</i> commission.  I am strongly of the view, in relation to the salaries of other groups of persons also&mdash;take Ministerial salaries and, indeed, the allowances of Deputies&mdash;that it would be a good thing if matters of that kind were considered independent of this House by some group of persons who would have no interest other than to see that the right thing was done.  I have no doubt that, following the view of such a commission, this House would be guided and would be in a position to act intelligently and properly.</P>
    <P>As things are now, the Minister, without any prior discussion, has proposed a Bill which is to provide for a flat 10 per cent.  increase of a retrospective kind for the four judges. It would, I think, have been more understandable if the proposal, instead of for an increase, were to provide a pension for a judge's widow.  It would be more understandable if that were the proposal in the Bill but it is not. The Bill was introduced by the Minister without any examination independent and apart from the House.  In these circumstances and in the light of other factors which cannot be ignored, the Fine Gael Party feel compelled to oppose the Bill.  I certainly feel&mdash;it is only a personal suggestion&mdash;that the Minister would serve the country better if, even at this late stage, he would withdraw this Bill and if, instead, with good sense and with reason, he and his colleagues in the Government established some independent commission to consider not only the question of judges' salaries but the question of Ministerial salaries, Deputies' allowances, and so on.  Such an examination would be understood not only in the House but throughout the country.</P>
    <P>There is a danger, a very real danger, that things of this kind, when they are thrown into the arena here, will become a political plaything.  As a result successive Governments are careful of taking a step which may be necessary.  We in this House are in very real danger of putting ourselves into a straitjacket, and that could best be avoided if this whole question were examined independently.  I <Col N="588" /> appreciate that people often say that one is inclined in face of a difficulty to establish a commission to inquire into it.  I suppose that is a tendency. It often is an easy way out of a difficulty but sooner or later a decision has to be taken responsibly.</P>
    <P>Deputies will appreciate that in the middle thirties when the then Government felt it necessary to reassess the level of Ministerial salaries and Deputies' allowances and, I am not certain but I think also, judicial salaries, they did establish an <i>ad hoc</i> body to consider them.  That body considered the views of persons in different walks of life throughout the country and carefully considered the whole scale of salaries.  Following that consideration, the then Government were able to report to this House.  They found the House to be receptive and that the House was able with dignity to take appropriate action.  No one at that time could feel that what they were doing was wrong or intemperate and I think the general public appreciated the manner in which the problem was faced up to then.</P>
    <P>The need for such a step is more acute now.  The Minister will have heard from Deputies that at the moment there are sections of our community who are facing very definite difficulties.  There is not in the economic conditions of the country now the kind of prosperity which enabled the Tory Party in England to sweep into power a month or so ago. Times are difficult for many sections and in times of difficulty of that kind a Government, anxious to discharge their responsibility, have a particular duty to do it prudently and properly. I have little doubt that whatever case there was for an <i>ad hoc</i> examination of a similar problem 20 years ago, that case is all the stronger now.</P>
    <P>I would urge the Minister not to proceed with this Bill at the moment. If he proceeds with it, inevitably in the course of a discussion of this kind things will be said which perhaps should not be said.  If the Minister and his colleagues consider this matter, give new thought to it and adopt the procedure which I have suggested and which Deputy Dr. Noel Browne suggested in another way, the Minister <Col N="589" /> will find sense prevailing in this House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJBurke" hpid="Mr. P.J. Burke Mr. P.J. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>It was not my intention to intervene in this debate but I do so because I feel from the various contributions that have been made to the debate that a principle is now challenged.  If any member of this House is prepared to obtain justice for one section of the community and do an injustice to another section, he is not worthy to represent the people.  There are a number of unemployed people in my area who are in very bad circumstances.  There are a number of people whom I am trying to help day after day.  I have presided over numerous meetings to bring about settlements between workers and employers.  However, there is a principle involved in this measure on which this House is being challenged.</P>
      <P>The principle involved here is that this House decided in 1924 to give a certain salary to our judges.  Are we to say here that the people who fixed that salary in 1924 were wrong?  If we accept the principle in relation to meeting the increased cost of living for every section of our people, this House has to be just and fair.  I am not in agreement with certain statements that have been made today. Are we to say in future: &ldquo;John Jones, you may go out on strike and get an increase in salary.  Pat Murphy, you are all right.  You stay at home because you have enough.&rdquo; Paddy Burke, Seán MacCarthy and anybody else like them are not supposed to do anything.  You cannot have one law for one section of the community and another law for another section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Nobody in this House or outside it can challenge me with not having tried to help every section of the community, but I am concerned here with one question.  If we have done a just act we should stand by it.  If an unjust act had been done in 1924 then this House should have withdrawn the allowance given to judges in all subsequent years.  Some of the Deputies who spoke here today wanted to be on both sides of the fence.  They are entitled to take that attitude and, as another gentleman once said, I would <Col N="590" /> die in defence of their right to say what they think.  However, are we to say that the increased cost of living applies to one section of the community and not to another?  I am very sorry that public representatives should make statements to the effect that one section of our citizens is entitled to an increase and that another section is not so entitled.</P>
    <P>I have the honour, for the time being, of being a member of this House, and it may be used against me by certain people outside that I stood up and defended a certain section of the people against another section.  I am defending no section. I am defending the principle that if the cost of living has gone up for one section, it has gone up for the others.  The Minister and the Government have gone into this matter very carefully.  The district justices are not satisfied.  They think they should get more and other sections think that they should get a great deal more, too.</P>
    <P>I say that we are establishing a precedent here today not on a judge's salary but on a principle that will react very badly against us because we shall be looked upon as people capable of making one decision for one section and making an adverse decision for another section.  We are here to try to be fair to all sections, irrespective of class or creed.  One man may be able to live reasonably well on a particular figure, while another man may not be able to live on the same figure. That is a matter into which I do not intend to go now, but we are here to be at least just and fair, and if we are not just and fair and if we do not give a decision according to our consciences, then we are not worthy to be public representatives.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Although he does not appear to realise it, Deputy Burke's speech would justify his voting against this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>He would not know that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy enunciated very flowery principles, all of which he said he was going to employ in the service of passing the Bill.  A lot of the <Col N="591" /> same arguments are convincing reasons why the Deputy should vote against this Bill.  The Deputy wants to do justice to everyone but this Bill is not being just to everyone.  This Bill deals with a small number of people and it is because the Government are not being just to everyone that the Labour Party cannot see its way to support a Bill of this kind.</P>
      <P>If this question of the remuneration of judges were a matter for the Government to decide, or for the Fianna Fáil Party to decide, that would be their business and their responsibility and this House would have no further concern.  But the action of the Government in bringing in this Bill dealing with the financial problems of the Judiciary imposes on every member of this House the responsibility of deciding on the merits of the Bill.  You cannot evade that responsibility; it is there and you must discharge it.  But I submit that as public representatives we are not entitled to discharge the responsibility just with one eye on the Bill and with the rest of our visual powers blank, so far as the rest of the community is concerned.</P>
      <P>This Bill can be considered only against the background of the economic position and by bringing into focus all the other meritorious claims which could be made by a variety of our people in all classes of life whose incomes are very substantially below that which is enjoyed by those who are to benefit under this Bill.  It is because that responsibility is imposed on each and every one of us that the Labour Party desires to explain its position. If justice were being done to everybody, we would be in favour of this Bill, but if this Bill is dealing with one section and ignoring the claims of everybody else, then we think it is a disastrous Bill and we are not prepared to support it while other claims, at least as meritorious, and in fact in many instances more meritorious, are left aside or ignored by the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Bill apparently has a number of facets.  The Minister for Justice defends it on the ground that as the cost of living had gone up, the remuneration <Col N="592" /> of the judges should go up also.  The Taoiseach, however, came into the House and he abandoned that side of the case.  Instead, he said that there were two convincing reasons for granting this increase. He said that the salaries of judges were higher in the Six Counties and in Great Britain than they were here, and that our judges should therefore be pushed up closer to the scales operating elsewhere in order to show that their intellectual capacity and integrity were high in our estimation and high in the estimation of anybody who considered a person's salary against the background of his intellectual capacity.  That was one of the claims advanced by the Taoiseach.</P>
    <P>The second claim was that you had to give the judges a certain income in order to be sure that they were incorruptible and that they were honest. I think the Taoiseach over-played his hand in this matter.  He was talking about incorruptibility and honesty.  At what point do we purchase those attributes or for what sum?  Incorruptibility and honesty are not just cattle at a market; they are not just pedigree cattle for which you pay so much to get the pure breed.  How much are we to pay for this incorruptibility? How much have we to pay for this honesty?  Can we purchase it only in a Chief Justice, for example, for a £500 a year increase? Can we get the same incorruptibility and honesty for £200 in a district justice ?</P>
    <P>I think the Taoiseach's statement here this evening, and his whole speech in that field, was a gross reflection on the Judiciary.  Nobody has questioned their ability; nobody has questioned their integrity or their intellectual capacity to discharge the obligations assigned to them under statute.  Nobody has ever dared to question the honesty or integrity of the Judiciary and arguments like giving them £100 or £200 a year to maintain their integrity and honesty must only recoil on those who make the statement and be, in fact, a reflection on the judges.</P>
    <P>I think sufficiently well of the Judiciary to maintain that if their salaries <Col N="593" /> were reduced, their integrity and honesty would remain unimpaired.  To talk of purchasing honesty by giving increases of this kind, as the Taoiseach did, is a gross reflection on the high reputation of a body which is not yet &mdash;and I hope never will be&mdash;before the bar of public opinion in Ireland, at which their credentials in the field of integrity and honesty would be questioned.</P>
    <P>What has it come to&mdash;this question of integrity?  If people have no sense of honesty or integrity, you just cannot buy it with money.  It would have been just as logical for the Taoiseach to point to the Minister for Finance, the man who handles all of the nation's finances, who controls its entire Civil Service, who has wide powers under statute and who is paid £2,125.  Does anybody question his honesty or integrity?  Did anybody ever question it with all these responsibilities? Did anybody ever question the honesty or integrity of the Minister for Industry and Commerce with the immense power he has, particularly in the licensing field?  Nobody denies that.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Industry and Commerce and the Minister for Finance have unimpeachable integrity at £2,125 per annum.  Why then is it necessary to give increases to maintain the integrity and honesty of persons with £4,800 per annum?  I want to know what is the justification, assuming the Front Bench are honest for £2,125 per year, for saying: &ldquo;We cannot keep these fellows honest unless we give them an increase of £500 a year on an income of £4,800?&rdquo;  Would somebody reply to that question ?</P>
    <P>As I said at the outset, this whole business is relative.  It is on the basis of its relativity that it has to be considered by this House.  Deputy Burke, who has now fled, said that he wants to be just to everybody.  He wants to do this for the judges, and he wants to give everybody an increase.  I put it to Deputy Burke, and to anybody else who thinks on this: is it not perfectly absurd to think that you are doing justice to people with an income of £6 or £7 a week by giving them a 10/- a week increase, while at the same <Col N="594" /> time, you give an increase of £500 a year to persons with £4,800 per year ? If your economy is such that we can afford increases of £500 per year, on incomes from £2,000 to almost £5,000 per year, how and why do we adopt this Lazarus-like attitude in respect of other classes of the community who are simply living hand to mouth?</P>
    <P>The Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare has said that the Government do not intend to increase old age pensions.  In 1959, with the cost of living higher than it has ever been in living memory, an old age pensioner is expected to live on 27/6d. a week.  He is expected to pay rent, buy clothes, milk, fuel and all the other odds and ends of things necessary for human existence for seven days a week on 27/6d.  That is the other side of the scale and we can do nothing about it.  The Parliamentary Secretary says &ldquo;No, the Government do not propose to do any more. These people got a half crown sometime ago.&rdquo; The old age pensioner today has a 1908 standard of living. All his pension will buy is what 5/- would have bought him in 1908, and the Government have no remedy for a situation of that kind.  However, they can find the remedy in the case of other people with incomes of from £2,000 to almost £5,000 a year.</P>
    <P>I do not think this Bill can be considered in isolation.  You cannot look at this Bill solely from the standpoint of the judges.  In equity, they may have a claim.  They press their claim on the grounds that they had a certain contract that gave them a certain income and they are entitled, from the standpoint of the reduced value of money, to have their incomes altered to allow for the fall in the value of money.  That is their claim, but so have other people claims in that respect among the hundreds of thousands of people who do not get £6 a week on which to keep a wife and rear a number of children.  How then can we look at the Judges' side only and not at the other side which concerns these people?</P>
    <P>The Government, by bringing in this Bill.  have imposed upon us the obligation of saying whether we will adjust the financial problems of a section of <Col N="595" /> the community which is high up in the social scale, and are, at the same time, to leave aside, without any amelioration whatever, the claims of those who, in my opinion, have a right to have their grievances dealt with by this Legislature.  By bringing in this Bill, the Government have imposed a special responsibility on each and every Deputy to say where he stands.  Is he going to look at this from the standpoint of the judges only and ignore the claims of many other classes?  If that point is put to us, we are going to say: &ldquo;No; we are not going to meet the claims of one section only at the expense of other and more needy sections of the community.&rdquo;  In presenting this to us, the Government have completely put it out of focus.</P>
    <P>We are not prepared to support this Bill until the Government give evidence of their intention to deal with the problems of other people, weaker and more helpless, economically and financially.  If they do that, then it is a new problem, but as long as the Government adopt the attitude that they cannot give any more to the sick, to the unemployed, to the widows, to the old age pensioners, or to a large section of their own employees who are also feeling the pinch of the increasing cost of living, then we are not prepared to underwrite this measure. If the Government deal with the other problems affecting large masses of the people, we shall look at the situation again, but we cannot be lead into voting for a Bill which deals only with a small and relatively privileged section of the community while the problems of the masses are left untouched.  In this Bill, so far as we know, they have no intention of dealing with the problems of these classes.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>A lot has been said about not saying anything about the Judiciary, and it has been stated that people spoke disrespectfully about them.  I was present during most of this debate and I did not hear anybody speak disrespectfully about the judges.  I think we have the right of public representatives to give our views on a measure like this and to convey the views of the people who <Col N="596" /> sent us here, and I can truthfully say that so far as the people I know are concerned, they would be against this measure.  I think that would be the response or the reaction that any Deputy would get if he consulted his constituents.</P>
      <P>I do not propose to speak disrespectfully of the judges but I should like to say this much to the Judiciary, that, from the privileged position they hold, they should themselves respect the feelings of witnesses and people who come into their courts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputies may not discuss the actions of judges.  We are discussing their remuneration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>It is claimed that this House must vote a 10 per cent rise to the Judiciary and the reason given is to offset the rise in the cost of living.  The people who will pay this are those of whom it has previously been said they are the main producers in this country, the people who breed livestock, cattle and sheep, and there has been a considerable fall in the price of these because the price of beef and mutton in Dublin shops is down.  I do not think we are as hard on the Judiciary as the French queen who said to the people that they could eat cake.  Our Judiciary can eat beef and mutton.  They have up to £5,000 a year and the security of their positions. When they retire, they have pensions.</P>
      <P>It has been said that if they die in harness, their widows should be provided for.  I do not see why we should provide for their widows when we have not taken any steps to provide for our own wives, if we should die before them.  I do not see why the Judiciary should be put into any privileged position.  Deputies should look to themselves.  The people of the country do not consider this rise should be given to the Judiciary any more than they consider a rise should be given to Deputies.</P>
      <P>It is very difficult to make a speech when other Deputies are talking.  If they spoke in whispers, I would not mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="597" />
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Conversations should not be carried on in the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>There was a complaint recently that we were not speaking loudly enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The manner in which members of the Judiciary are appointed was discussed here today and I have no fault to find with that. It was said that a man could be appointed because he attached himself to a political Party and got promotion for his assistance to that Party.  If a man has been of service to his political Party, he has had the courage to show that he has political opinions and I would rather see him advanced to the Bench or made a District Justice than see a &ldquo;cute boyo&rdquo; get on, the fellow who tries to play both sides.  If there were to be no advancement for members of the legal profession because of their political opinions, we would probably find very few members of that profession would enter politics. Many other professions have no interest in politics or in public administration and we should look to that and let that be a lesson to us.</P>
      <P>The members of the House give a great service to the country and that is something that is not recognised.  The country confers a great honour on a man who is created a judge and paid such a high salary.  It is a reflection, I think, on that man when he has such a salary to suggest that he might die without having provided for his wife and taken out an insurance policy. Outside the metropolitan courts, the salaries of District Justices are not great, but, of course, they get the smallest rise.</P>
      <P>Lastly, I want to say that I have been informed that the Department of Justice has been endeavouring to get the Judiciary to come together for some years past in order that they could make a statement or give a ruling on what should be uniform punishments the courts should inflict in certain cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that matter cannot be raised on this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="598" />
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is no harm to say that the Judiciary could not be got together for that purpose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The matter is completely out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the answer I got from the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare this afternoon, that the Government would not even consider giving a bonus to the old age pensioners for Christmas week, one week in the year, I could not support this Bill.  The Government have taken up the attitude of Scrooge as far as the old age pensioners are concerned and the attitude of lán a' mhála, as far as the Judiciary are concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrancisLoughman" hpid="Mr. Loughman Mr. Loughman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Loughman</NameTxt>
      <P>I have listened to a great, portion of this debate, and it was completely unrealistic to me.  I happened to hear the last part of Deputy Norton's speech and his objection at that stage was that we could not consider only the judges, that we should consider a variety of other people.  All these people will be considered and have been considered in their proper course, but, in my opinion, it would be very hard to bring the judges in with all these other cases that have been mentioned.  I think it was a poor argument, although perhaps the Deputy made better ones earlier in his statement.  Why he should use that as an argument that judges should not get an increase is beyond my understanding.</P>
      <P>Deputy Lynch said that every Deputy had a right to give his views. Of course this House sees to it that every Deputy can give his views within the rules of order.  The Deputy was justly called to order on a couple of occasions, but so far as the matters relevant to the debate are concerned, every Deputy is quite free to say anything he chooses.  I think that Deputy Lynch could have no complaint so far as that is concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>He stated that the people were against this measure.  Oddly enough, it happens that I had this question raised at a pretty important meeting in my constituency, at a meeting representative of the entire area of South <Col N="599" /> Tipperary.  The matter had to be explained and when that was done, I can assure the House that the meeting was 100 per cent. behind the Minister's proposal, and justly so, because if any increase could be justified, it is an increase to the Judiciary.</P>
    <P>Deputy Lynch misunderstood the Taoiseach's statement so far as widows are concerned.  If I understood him properly, he said we should not provide for the widows.  If he had listened to the Taoiseach, he would know that what the Taoiseach said was that some arrangement was to be made whereby the judges would forfeit portions of their pensions and have them transferred to the widows but that that would involve no expense whatsoever to the State.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I did not say that the Taoiseach said anything about widows.  I said &ldquo;other speakers&rdquo;, and the record will prove it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrancisLoughman" hpid="Mr. Loughman Mr. Loughman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Loughman</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall see what is in the Official Report.  I am going on what I heard the Deputy say; perhaps I did not take him up correctly, but I want to draw attention to the fact because it seems to be a sore point with him.</P>
      <P>The Taoiseach said that, in 1924, £4,000 was fixed as the salary of the Chief Justice and the proposals in this Bill, if carried through, will bring the salary to £5,300.  In 1949, we had a devaluation of the pound.  I think everybody agrees about that and it involved a reduction in the purchasing power of the pound of one-third.  If you take one-third of £5,300, you will find that on the basis of the 1924 valuation, it is now worth £3,500, which is £500 less than was granted to these judges back in 1924.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I heard some of the Deputies talk about the old age pensioners, among a number of other people.  It is very grand to talk about 170,000 people. All of them have votes.  I suppose it is popular to groan about their distress and say that nothing is being done for them, and that nobody wants to do anything for them who has the power to do it.  Many people who <Col N="600" /> have not the power to do it are anxious to do everything for them but, strange to relate, when they had the power, they did very little for them.  That, to my mind, is the odd part of it.</P>
    <P>If you gave an increase of a farthing to the old age pensioners, it would amount at the end of the year to much more than the total which will be needed to provide the judges with the increases which are being given to them now.  According to my calculations, a farthing per week to the old age pensioners at the present time would amount to more than £9,000 per annum.  We are not now giving to the judges anything like £9,000.</P>
    <P>I should like to know what the salaries of the judges were in 1900. If these salaries are examined, it will be found that they have not been much increased since then, and that the judges, above all people, were given no attention as far as increases were concerned, whereas every other section of the community have had their salaries trebled, quadrupled and in many cases increased five times. The old age pensioners about whom we weep so much have had their weekly pensions increased over five times.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>Five times ?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrancisLoughman" hpid="Mr. Loughman Mr. Loughman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Loughman</NameTxt>
      <P>I remember the pension being 5/-.  Since 1924, they have not been increased that much. Perhaps they were increased three times.  From 1929, they have been increased.  I do not see why judges, considering their importance and the wonderful record they have up to the present, should not have a chance of having the losses which they sustained because of the reduction in money values made good.  Even the £5,300 which the Chief Justice will get will be very seriously cut by income tax.  In fact, I should like to know how much of the increase which is being granted will be recovered by the State, by way of income tax.  I rather think it will be cut, so that the amount will be very small, indeed, when everything is paid up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We should realise that judges must live according to a particular standard. <Col N="601" /> We should see to it that their remuneration will enable them to live at that standard.  All this talk we hear about all that the judges will get and that nobody else will get anything is, to my mind, playing to certain people. Judges have a right, as well as any other section of the State, to be treated according to the position they hold.  I suggest that there are many practising lawyers in this country who earn in a year much more than the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court.</P>
    <P>I know then when there is a judgeship vacant, they are happy to take it and we are happy to have people who will sacrifice increased earnings to have the steady post.  Very often, if they take up the post and become judges, they sacrifice themselves to some extent.</P>
    <P>At any rate, I welcome the Bill and I have no hesitation in doing so.  I have no doubt that the people will welcome it also.  As I said at the outset, I had this matter discussed at a very full meeting representative of the entire area of South Tipperary. I admit it was one section of it, representing, perhaps, more than half of the county.  They were 100 per cent. in favour of the Minister's proposal in so far as we were able to explain it.  I welcome the Bill and wish it every success.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankSherwin" hpid="Mr. Sherwin Mr. Sherwin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherwin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am objecting to the Bill on principle.  If we are asked to put the Judiciary above suspicion, I suggest that the members of this House should also be above suspicion. We make the laws.  If you like, we make the balls and they throw them. Comparisons were made by Deputy O'Higgins.  He referred to the setting up of some commission to investigate the need for increases, both for the Judiciary and the members of this House.  Other members made comparisons with old age pensioners and all those in receipt of social benefits.  I came into this House not for any gain. I could do much better outside.  I just like the vocation and that is why I am here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am concerned with the fact that this House should be above suspicion. Whenever the question of allowances for Deputies arises, some Party tries <Col N="602" /> to make political capital out of it.  Some members of the House are better off financially than others and, like the old members of Parliament, they could do without allowances.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Acting-Chairman (Mr. Cunningham) Acting-Chairman (Mr. Cunningham)">
      <NameTxt>Acting-Chairman (Mr. Cunningham)</NameTxt>
      <P>I would remind the Deputy that the question under discussion is the remuneration of judges and not Deputies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankSherwin" hpid="Mr. Sherwin Mr. Sherwin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherwin</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, Sir, but I think I am entitled to make comparisons. Comparisons were made by Deputy O'Higgins and Deputy Loughman and I think I am entitled to make comparisons. As I said, on principle, I object.  The whole question of the remuneration both of judges and members of the Oireachtas should be considered.  I hold that the Judiciary should be above suspicion because they have to administer justice and because they are only men, in spite of what some people might think.  I agree that they are all men of fine character, but even men of fine character can be tempted.  If a man cannot pay his way or live up to the standard he is used to, he will be tempted.  That was proved in the last War when men of high character were brought to the level of savages.  Men can be tempted. I agree that the Judiciary should be above temptation.</P>
      <P>It should not be a question of political tactics.  The remuneration of members of the House should also be considered.  I strongly object to Judges getting an increase when a poor man had to resign because he could not live on his salary.  Some members may think that this allowance may help to cover a man's expenses but where a man depends on it to make a living, it could also make a pauper out of him.  The members of this House should be above suspicion, as well as the Judiciary.  I do not think this matter should be opposed from the point of view of political tactics.  We should be above all that.  We should decide what is just and equitable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As we are dealing with the Judiciary and as this point has been touched on by other members, I object to the practice of members of this House being given priority in <Col N="603" /> judicial appointments.  It makes the members of this House suspect.  It could be and is in the public mind that members of this House are picked for judgeships.  I believe that that is true to some extent.  In my opinion, no member of this House should be chosen for a judgeship.  They should all be chosen from outside.</P>
    <P>There is not much that one can say on this measure.  I object to it on principle.  This whole business should be considered in an equitable way and other persons such as the members of this House should equally be considered. This is not the time for the arguments used by the Fine Gael Party.  They ought to be ashamed of themselves.  They ought to consider people in want.  This is above political tactics.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamMurphy" hpid="Mr. W. Murphy Mr. W. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>As one member of the House who very seldom stands up to speak on any Bill, I feel it is incumbent on me to do so and say a few words on behalf of the people in county Clare, the people whom I represent with the other Deputies for the constituency.  I sought to understand what their ideas are about this Bill and the way they would accept it, had they the opportunity to vote on it that I have.  In speaking on this Bill, I do not intend for one moment to criticise the Government for introducing the Bill, nor do I intend for one moment to attack the Judiciary for looking for what they think they are entitled to.  Yet, I feel that it is my duty, knowing the realities of life in county Clare, to say that it would be utterly impossible for me to vote for such a Bill.</P>
      <P>Reference has been made here to the salaries which the Judiciary in other countries receive.  I ask every Deputy listening to me this evening, who can compare this country with the countries where the big salaries are paid ?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would not for one moment dwell on the question of how the Judiciary are appointed.  That is no business of mine.  The main matter before the House tonight is: are we going to vote for this Bill or are we not?  Personally, I shall not vote for it and I shall give my reasons.  I believe, taking <Col N="604" /> one thing with another and the circumstances surrounding their case, their present salaries are far and away beyond the salaries of others who, perhaps, have to do more and to spend much more in carrying out their duties.</P>
    <P>If the Government have the money to pay the proposed increases, they should hold that money and any money that they might put with it and give it to the other section of our people who are today, one might say, scraping the very earth for an existence. Time and time again, through their representatives, they have asked this House for what might be termed the bare necessaries of life, necessaries of which this House has deprived them.  It is for that reason that I speak on this Bill.</P>
    <P>As I said, I do not want to be too critical or to be severe in my criticism, but, as a member of the House, I should like to put before the Government and the House what they are about to do.  Remember that in doing that, they are just opening the gap and placing us in the position that, no matter who may come in with demands, whether they are right or wrong, if this Bill goes through, we shall certainly not be in a position to say,&ldquo;You are not entitled to it.&rdquo;  The answer that will be slung in our face will be,&ldquo;Consider what the man with £4,000 gets and what the labouring man in Clare and the old age pensioner get.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I am not attacking the Bill in order to play to the mob.  I never play to the mob.  I do not mind the mob.  I have always expressed my views and will always express them, in this House or outside it.</P>
    <P>I consider that when the Judiciary looked for this increase, they went too far when they asked that it be made retrospective to 1st January last.  When increases were granted to old age pensioners and widows, they were not payable at the time they were sanctioned but became operative as from 1st August, four months later, when many of them had gone to their reward.</P>
    <P>I am giving my just and honest opinion to the House and the Government. <Col N="605" /> It does not matter to me what the Government do; that is their own business; but I would ask the Government to be wise and careful.  If they have this money in hand and if they have money to spend, let them think of the lower and middle income groups.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFlanagan" hpid="Mr. S. Flanagan Mr. S. Flanagan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Flanagan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not for a moment impugn the honesty of Deputy W. Murphy or question his sincerity, but I do feel that irrelevant matters have been dragged into this discussion, and, with all due respect to Deputy W. Murphy and the other Deputies who have mentioned social welfare benefits, these things have very little, if anything, to do with the provisions of this Bill.  I should be very surprised to learn that the sentiments expressed by certain members of the Fine Gael Party are held by a majority of the Fine Gael Party.  There are some members of that Party in the House at the present time who, I feel, must take a poor view of this attempt to drag a debate about the remuneration of the Judiciary into irrelevant mob appeals concerned with old age pensioners.  widows and other very deserving people.  Nobody would object to any provision for an increase in social welfare benefits but that matter is not relevant and should not have been brought into this debate.</P>
      <P>The suggestion put forward by Deputy O'Higgins and more or less touched on in the amendment in the names of Deputy McQuillan and Deputy Dr. Browne is that the question of the remuneration of the Judiciary and, incidentally, of Deputies. might be left to a commission. I do not know if they suggest a Select Committee of the Houses of the Oireachtas or some other type of commission. That suggestion is, indeed, a good one but I do feel that in the matter of the appointment of members of the Judiciary and in the matter of fixing the allowances of Deputies, it is this House and the Government which should accept responsibility and not any outside body.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy Lindsay said that he objected to the increases mentioned, that people practising at the Bar or practising as solicitors sometimes make considerable sacrifices in order to accept appointment <Col N="606" /> to the Bench.  I do not know that that is altogether accurate.  What I do know is that it is essential to attract ability as well as integrity.  It is admitted on all sides that the integrity of our judges and justices is unimpeachable.  That is a very good and essential thing, but it is something which the Government and the House should be very jealous in preserving. I believe the Government are jealous that that position of the judges and justices should be preserved and that it is because of that this Bill is now introduced.</P>
    <P>Although the Chief Justice is the head of the Judiciary in this country and as such, is paid more than anybody else, neither he nor the other members of the Supreme Court are in my opinion, the most important judges in the land.  I think the most important judges are those who decide the day-to-day small cases of the people in the District Court.  It is particularly important that we should try to attract the very best type into the District Bench.  It is very seldom, in the course of an average small country practice, that a solicitor will find himself pleading before the august Supreme Court assembly.  It is very seldom he will have an issue which will involve going that far.  But every week, every month, dozens if not hundreds of times a year, he finds himself in the District Court pleading small cases about this, that and the other.</P>
    <P>It is essential that the District Justice should be a man of integrity, a man of fairly wide experience of the type of problems he will be called upon to determine, and that he should have a fairly wide experience of the psychology and mentality of the litigants who give evidence before him. I do not propose to criticise the justices.  It would be invidious of me to do so, even if I had criticism to offer.  I have always felt that it is better, as a matter of practice, to appoint solicitors from the country to vacancies in the District Court.  I feel that because they have the experience of litigants and of the problems they will be afterwards called on to decide.  Without in any way disparaging members of the Bar, living and working in the Bar Library in Dublin, <Col N="607" /> they are not in intimate contact with the people and their problems in a way that would qualify them to sit on the Bench afterwards.  That, I must emphasise, does not involve criticism of any particular justice.  I do not want to be understood as offering any criticism of anybody on those lines. What I am saying is that I believe the important court is the poor man's court.</P>
    <P>As a logical corollary to that, I would suggest that this Bill, if anything, does not do enough to put the salaries of the District Justices on a par with the dignity and importance of the work they are called on to do. I am aware that on each of the two previous occasions when increases were offered to the Bench, some special consideration was given to the position of District Justices.  It is clear from the figures quoted by the Taoiseach today that their position has been more improved proportionately than that of the various other members of the Bench.  Even so, having regard to the increase in the jurisdiction&mdash;and therefore in the importance of the cases they are called on to decide&mdash;and to the fact that it is their court which hears the vast majority of the day-to-day problems of the people, I believe this Bill, if anything, does not go far enough in remunerating them.  As I said in an interjection when Deputy Lindsay was speaking and as I have repeated here now, it is essential to attract ability as well as integrity.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesLindsay" hpid="Mr. Lindsay Mr. Lindsay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lindsay</NameTxt>
      <P>Ability commands its own price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFlanagan" hpid="Mr. S. Flanagan Mr. S. Flanagan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Flanagan</NameTxt>
      <P>If we do not increase the remuneration of justices we shall not be able to attract the ability required of the occupant of the District Court.  All that sitting on the Bench has to offer is security. Of course, that is a consideration of very great importance to certain people.  They are prepared to sacrifice the probable income they would have from their continuing in practice for the security of a guaranteed future, more particularly when practice of the law is something intensely <Col N="608" /> personal which disintegrates very rapidly if the person falls ill or is otherwise prevented from carrying on his work.  It does offer security, but the time will come when the attraction of that security will not be sufficient to bring to the Bench the type of person we must have.  Nothing is more unsatisfactory than the feeling of hopelessness which prevails among the ordinary people when they get the impression after a period of time that the District Court Bench is occupied by somebody who is not competent or who does not understand their problems.  That has not happened very often, but it has occasionally happened.  Great care should be taken to ensure that it does not happen again.</P>
      <P>If anything, I think we are not giving enough to justices; but I have no criticism whatever to offer of the proposed increases to the other members of the Judiciary.  It was suggested by some speakers that we have no right to make comparisons with Great Britain and Northern Ireland in this matter.  I think it was clearly pointed out by the Taoiseach today that we are not, in fact, trying to make comparisons with Great Britain or Northern Ireland.  What the Taoiseach did was to show the percentage increase which occurred in both those countries in the salaries of the various occupants of the Bench in a period comparable to that from the foundation of our State.  He proved conclusively, taking the base year as 1924, that all the occupants of the Bench in Great Britain and Northern Ireland had done vastly better than their counterparts here.  It will be remembered that the base is very different, because the remuneration of their counterparts in Great Britain and Northern Ireland in 1924 was vastly better than that offered to and received by the occupants of the Bench here.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 5 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 4th November, 1959.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>