<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="13" Month="Dec" Year="1939" Vol="24" No="3" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 13 Nollaig 1939" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 13 December 1939" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="225">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="225" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Local Government and Public Health Provisional" RHead="Order Confirmation Bill, 1939&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Private Business. - Local Government and Public Health Provisional Order Confirmation Bill, 1939&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Bill passed through Committee without amendment.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take the Final Stages now.</P>
    <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    <P>Bill to be sent to the Dáil with a Message desiring agreement.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Ministers and Secretaries" RHead="(Amendment) Bill, 1939&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Public Business. - Ministers and Secretaries (Amendment) Bill, 1939&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. O Ceallaigh) Seán T. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. O Ceallaigh)</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill provides for the establishment of a Department of Supplies and for certain amendments in the Ministers and Secretaries Acts, 1924 and 1928, which experience has shown to be desirable.  The 8th September, 1939, is the date upon which the appointment of a Minister for Supplies was made by the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The new Department has, of course, been set up to meet emergency conditions, and while it may accordingly be regarded as in the nature of a temporary organisation, it will be necessary to have regard to the fact that the Minister for Supplies may find it necessary to enter into contracts and to appear as plaintiff or defendant in the courts.  It is desirable, therefore, that the Minister should be established <Col N="226" /> as a corporation sole, with the capacity to sue and be sued in a like manner as other Ministers in charge of Departments of State.  Incorporation implies, in law, perpetual succession, and the Government are advised that the establishment of a purely temporary body as a corporation sole would be open to objection on legal grounds. To put a term on the life of the Department in the Bill would leave the liability in law of the Minister and his servants obscure.  It is for this reason that the Bill has not been framed on the basis of establishing a temporary Department, and specific amending legislation to wind up the Department and to provide for matters in the nature of commitments, etc., arising out of its activities, will, in due course, be required.</P>
    <P>The Bill provides for various other matters not of a temporary nature, including, in particular, the office of Minister without portfolio, the transfer of Departments of State to and from Ministers, the arrangements to be made for the administration of Departments during the temporary inability of Ministers, the right of audience of Parliamentary Secretaries in the Houses of the Oireachtas, and the extension of the existing powers of delegation to Parliamentary Secretaries so as to include powers and duties of a statutory kind.</P>
    <P>The Bill repeals Sections 11 and 12 of the Act of 1924 and Section 4 of the Act of 1928, and provides in more suitable form for the powers of the Government under these sections, which relate generally to transfers of what may be termed subordinate functions of Departments, and to changes in the titles of Ministers and Departments.  It also gives covering statutory authority to the changes in the names of certain Ministers and Departments which were adopted on the coming into operation of the new Constitution.</P>
    <P>It is hardly necessary to deal in detail at this stage with the proposals, which are really self-explanatory.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister give me a little information?  There is <Col N="227" /> no reference to the Minister for the Co-ordination of Defensive Measures in this Bill.  Does that mean that the Ministry must disappear, since there is no authority set out in this Bill or in the Ministers and Secretaries Acts?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>As long as the Minister is not being given certain statutory functions, it is not necessary to have the Ministry specifically named under the Acts the Senator refers to, or under this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill does a great deal more than create a Department of Supplies and give statutory authority for a Department which can make contracts and sue and be sued, and so on.  First and foremost, it has retrospective authority; it goes back to the 8th September, 1939.  It goes to show, in the first place, that when the emergency arose and the war situation came on, although it had been brewing for at least 12 months, the Government was compelled to do certain things for which it had no statutory authority and about which it had taken no steps to ascertain whether or not it had statutory authority.  It is interesting, in spite of the efforts to give us a so-called new Constitution&mdash;which is not a new Constitution at all&mdash;that, at the very first impact of that so-called new Constitution upon an emergency situation, we had a collapse; we had to have an amendment of the Constitution with regard to a state of war and certain changes in the Ministry for which, apparently, there was no statutory authority in the Constitution or elsewhere.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Bill, therefore, is a Bill to make good the errors committed in the first few days of the war.  It also creates a completely new thing, a Minister without portfolio.  I am not sure whether that is within the Constitution, but that is not a point about which we need to worry here.  The Minister did not give in the other House, and has not given to-day, any indication of what a Minister without portfolio would be.  So far as I can gather from his reply to-day, the <Col N="228" /> Minister for the Co-ordination of Defensive Measures will now become a Minister without portfolio, because he will not be governing a Department of State with any statutory functions. In other words, when you have a Minister who has made a mess of a particular job over a period and you want to substitute somebody else who may, you hope, do the job better, you make the erring Minister a Minister without portfolio.  You continue to pay him his salary, provide him with transport facilities, give him a private secretary and you continue him for all purposes.</P>
    <P>It is not easy to see what functions the Minister without portfolio could perform.  One Government did very well without any such thing for ten years, and the present Government has done without one for seven years.  It is difficult to know what his functions will be.  I can imagine members of this House who, under no circumstances, should be made Ministers in charge of a Department, but you could say of them that they were nice people and you could make them Ministers without portfolio and give them the full salary.  The Minister without portfolio, it must be remembered, will have no administrative work to do, and will never have to face either House of the Oireachtas, or the public, with regard to what he has done in a particular Department.  He will never be up against any problem, so as to give members of the Dáil or Seanad an opportunity of judging how he deals with the problem.  But he will be in the enjoyment of all the amenities of Ministerial office.  I do not understand how that will work out.</P>
    <P>There is a point that I am not quite clear about.  In Section 5, the Taoiseach gets power to transfer Departments to and from Ministers, but in Section 7, during the temporary inability of a Minister to carry out his duties, it is the Government must make the change.  I do not see why it is the Taoiseach in one case and the Government in another.  Perhaps it is the Taoiseach without a difference, a colleague of mine suggests to me&mdash;that the Government and the Taoiseach are <Col N="229" /> one, and, instead of collective responsibility, we have the doctrine of collective faith.  That may very well be.</P>
    <P>There is another point with which perhaps we could deal on the Schedule, that is the changes in Irish spelling. Certain spelling was adopted.  A certain amount of work was done under the authority of a very accurate, very learned and very scholarly civil servant and apparently other spellings are being adopted now which are by no means an improvement, some of them to bring the Irish names of Ministers into harmony with the Constitution and some of them, apparently, purely for the sake of change&mdash;a part, I presume, of the Fianna Fáil mentality, that you want to enjoy the benefit of the Treaty and keep on pretending that you are not in the Free State, that you are in something entirely different and even calling yourself by a different name or when you are calling yourself by the same name spelling it after a different fashion.  I find it difficult to understand that.  Probably we will be able to deal with that in Committee.</P>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy of the Reeks The McGillycuddy of the Reeks">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy of the Reeks</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to protest against a Bill of this nature which is to a great extent increasing the expenses in this country to which we referred on the Finance Bill last week.  It seems to me entirely unnecessary and unjustifiable to make all these new Departments in a very small country like this &mdash;26 counties.  What our expenses will be once the North join us is almost incredible if we go on on this scale. We are forming now a Ministry of Supplies, a Ministry for the Co-ordination of Defensive Measures, and a Minister without portfolio.  In effect, whatever the British do we immediately copy them.  I really cannot understand what room there is in this country to copy the functions of Lord Chatfield in England who is dealing with the Air Force, the Navy and the Army as well.  I cannot believe that the public will understand it either. There is no war here at all.  As far as I can understand, in other countries, the Government Departments are working from 9 o'clock in the morning and just take time off for their meals and <Col N="230" /> come back after dinner.  That is going on in belligerent countries.  I cannot see why some effort in that direction should not be made here rather than saddle the taxpayers with the extra expense which is now being put on them.  I cannot see at all why the Minister for Industry and Commerce should not divide himself between two Departments&mdash;there would be certain personal inconvenience, I admit&mdash;to cover the question of supplies as well.</P>
      <P>There was no suggestion about these new Departments in last year's Estimates. How will the money be found for all these new Departments?  How is the money to be found for wages, salaries, office equipment and the various expenses?  I would suggest that before there are any new commitments in this country we should have some definite indication of what economies the Minister proposes to make.  He told us a fortnight or three weeks ago that there was going to be a saving of £400,000.  Up to this day we have no idea where the savings are going to be.  In any case, in the present emergency, they are to my mind practically infinitesimal.</P>
      <P>There is also no indication whatever as to whether the Minister is going to close down some of these non-paying industries which are an enormous drain at the present moment and in many cases do not give an adequate return even in wages for the labour employed.</P>
      <P>So far as I can see, everything the Government are doing at the present time is based on the British scale. Soon we will have probably more officials than there are ratepayers.  In regard to the loan that is being floated at the present moment: I noticed in the Dáil the other day that we have got a floating debt of £4,000,000 against our £7,000,000 loan.  That is not going very far.  I think in these circumstances we should be very careful before we agree willingly to have new Departments of State created at a moment's notice in the way we are doing it in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not a Bill which lends itself to very much debate on the <Col N="231" /> Second Stage.  To a considerable extent the position is there at the present moment and I suppose the Bill is to a large extent rectifying it.  I do not suppose that it is practical politics to defeat it.  Most of the points, so far as I can see, are ones which would be raised more properly on the Committee Stage.  I would be glad if the Minister would indicate when he is replying to the debate on this stage whether it is intended that the Minister without portfolio is to be a permanent institution or whether it is only intended because of abnormal circumstances during this crisis.  If the latter, I think the Bill should have a limitation in it so far as Section 4 is concerned.  Other things have been done and agreed to with a definite limitation or with power to extend them.  As a general principle, I think it is not a desirable thing in a country of our size to have a Minister without portfolio.  In most other countries where it exists it is provided for some old experienced politicians whose advice is wanted and who is too old or for various reasons unable to take charge of a Department.  I take it that this is really to deal with the present position.  If so, I think there should be a limit in Section 4.  I mention that now because if I were going to put an amendment to Section 4 I would like first to hear what the Minister has got to say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In regard to Section 8, I would like very much also before putting down a possible amendment to have an indication from the Minister as to why Section 8 has got to come into this Bill at all.  It seems to me to be very largely outside the scope of the Bill and to infringe on the constitutional provisions&mdash;that is if any Bill can do so, which I doubt&mdash;in relation to both Houses.  At the present time, by courtesy, a Parliamentary Secretary is always allowed to attend here and I have never heard anyone on any side of the House object on principle.  But the Constitution did not&mdash;and I think very properly did not&mdash;think it right to make a Constitutional provision that the right of attending and being heard should apply to Parliamentary <Col N="232" /> Secretaries.  When it was necessary to provide the right for Ministers in the Constitution it seems to me undesirable and improper to try and do this by a Bill.  Personally I do not think it does achieve it, because it is made perfectly clear in the Constitution that each House shall make its own Standing Orders.  The question of the attendance of any person who is not a member, unless specifically provided in the Constitution, is clearly a matter for the Standing Orders.  We are not now dealing with any individuals. Obviously, we are dealing with a principle. When a person who is not a member of a House has a right to attend he does not automatically come under the rules of the House and the House has not the same control over him.  In this case the House has control because it can withdraw the permission to attend.  If this Section 8 were passed and if it were valid&mdash; which, frankly, I do not think it would be&mdash;it would remove from the House the right to deal with a case in which, say&mdash;a very unlikely event&mdash;a Parliamentary Secretary refused to obey the Chairman, whereas the Chairman would be well able to deal with any member of the House.</P>
    <P>This may seem problematical, but I think it is well to watch the privileges of the Houses of Parliament.  Personally, I think this section is utterly unnecessary. There is no reason whatever to think that the Dáil would refuse permission to attend to a member of the Seanad who happened to be a Parliamentary Secretary or that the Seanad would refuse permission to a member of the Dáil, provided he behaved himself, which is always a reasonable assumption.  If that section is to stand, I think it should say, &ldquo;unless there is provision in the Standing Orders to the contrary, a Parliamentary Secretary who is a member of Dáil Eireann shall have the right to attend and be heard in Seanad Eireann.&rdquo;  It should further say that when attending he should be subject to the Standing Orders of the House which he attends.  Unless there is good reason given, I intend to put down an amendment to make some such provision, but I still cannot see why that has got to be there at all.</P>
    <Col N="233" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister in replying will tell us what does a Minister cost to-day?  I am not going to say whether he is value for the money or not but it is very relevant, particularly relevant, in view of the line taken by Senator The McGillycuddy.  We pay him £1,700 per annum.  There have been so many changes in the remuneration from time to time that people have lost touch, and are not quite clear as to the amount.  Ministers as I say are paid £1,700 a year, and in 1937 the figure given before the committee which enquired into the question of salaries and pensions, indicated that the cost of a Minister's car was at that time somewhere about £650 or £630. It would be very interesting to know what a Minister does cost to-day.  Perhaps the Minister would let us know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnLynch" hpid="Mr. E. Lynch Mr. E. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to know what exactly is meant by the statement in Section 2:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The regulation and control of supplies and services essential to the life of the community.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Are not these supplies to-day being regulated and controlled by private individuals?  As far as I understand, the supplies and services essential to the life of the community are under private control.  I would invite the Minister to say in what way the Minister to be set up under this Act will take to himself the functions now being performed by private individuals in relation to the regulation and control of supplies and services.  If there should be a conflict in regard to supplies or the provision of services, do I understand that the authority and rights of private individuals, who provide these supplies or give these services to the community to-day, will stand or shall they be overridden under this Act by the authority of the Minister to be set up under the Act?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>It is true as Senator Hayes said that when the emergency came upon us there were certain things done, for instance, the establishment of the Ministry of Supplies, for which there was not definite statutory authority.  To that <Col N="234" /> extent this Bill is retrospective.  I do not know that there is any great blame to be attached to anybody for not having foreseen that a Ministry of Supplies might be necessary when the new Constitution was brought in and accepted by the country.  I do not know that the very wise people who drafted the Constitution for which Senator Hayes has such an abiding affection were any wiser than those who drafted the new Constitution.  It is a new one&mdash;quite new.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>They were wiser to this extent, that they were able to keep in prisoners when they arrested them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>There were other things that they were not able to do. There were other things they tried and which they found impossible.  I doubt that even if the 12 Apostles, who were as wise men as ever walked this earth, drafted a Constitution there would not be some court or some lawyer who would not find his way around it.  I think anybody will have to admit that. What are lawyers there for, if they cannot drive a coach and four, as I think Daniel O'Connell once remarked, through any Act of Parliament?  Of course, nobody ever drove a coach and four through Senator Hayes' Constitution. The fact is that the new Constitution did not foresee the necessity for a Ministry of Supplies.  Senator Hayes can make as much as he likes out of it.  He is welcome to all the glory he can take out of it, and I am sure he will take as much as he can. Senator Hayes talked about errors committed.  There may have been an error in this but <i>non nostra culpa.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>This is only one added to the others.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>These are human instruments, and human nature and human intelligence are not almighty. <i>Errare humanum est.</i>  Senator Hayes talked about a Minister who made a mess of his Department and who is now to be made Minister without portfolio. No Minister that I am aware of made a mess of his Department.  Nobody <Col N="235" /> can prove such a proposition, even a member of this House.  All I can say is&mdash;and I can say it with greater knowledge now after seven years' experience as a member of the Government&mdash;that there are jobs in which a Minister without portfolio could be very helpful and very serviceable.  I have known occasions when it would have been a God-send to the Government to have at least one man who was not tied down by administrative duties.  Every Minister in the last Government and in this Government had enough work for an ordinary man to do in administering his Department. I do not care what Department is concerned, all Ministers have got a sufficient amount of work to do&mdash;some of them more than others, it is true. I think, therefore, it would be useful if there were in the Government two or three men who were not attached to any particular Department and who were not tied down by administrative duties, men who would have the job of co-ordinating the work of various Departments and acting as a thinking machine, in addition to the thinking that the ordinary members of the Government have to do every day.</P>
      <P>The problems that arise are sometimes problems of a very urgent nature and if you had two or three men whose hours were not taken up by administrative problems, they could perform the job of thinking out solutions of the problems that arise very frequently in the administration of the country. That would be very useful.  Even, if you had one man who could be turned to thinking out solutions for these problems it might be a help.  He might act as chairman of a sub-committee of the Cabinet.  Such a Minister would be of very great value and help in any Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>Would he not be usurping the functions of the Prime Minister?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so. It does not exactly follow.  The Taoiseach, as we call the Prime Minister, in this particular case happens <Col N="236" /> to be very fully occupied with Departmental and administrative work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>Why should that be?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>That is his own choice.  I quite agree with Senator MacDermot that he should not try to do so much, but he does.  That is his choice and in my opinion he has altogether too much to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>And it is impossible to do it right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a very heavy task for one man to take on himself. It means that he is in his office from 9.30 a.m. in the morning until 11 and 11.30 p.m. at night.  It is a very heavy burden for any one man to carry.  The burden of responsibility attached to the office of Taoiseach, or Prime Minister, is heavy enough in itself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister tell us how a Minister without portfolio can do a job which the Taoiseach is not doing, because he has not time?  I do not understand it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>As I say, there are many tasks that he could, with advantage, do to help the Government as a whole, and to help individual Ministers. A member of the Government of that kind would be very useful.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister name one job that he could do?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>I would rather not, but I could mention a number that have actually arisen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there not the danger that, if one roving Minister is given the special function of thinking, all the Departmental Ministers will think themselves dispensed from thought?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>Whatever may happen here in the Seanad in regard to that, it is not likely to happen in the Government.  We are all so built, including Senator MacDermot, that we <Col N="237" /> cannot absolve ourselves from thinking, whether we like it or not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>Not even at the Ard-Fheis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>Least of all there. If you are a member of the Government and have to answer in the Dáil and Seanad, and to the public, you will get plenty to think about.  You will be made think, or else you will not be in in your job very long.  There was a necessity for a Minister for Supplies. Indeed, it might very well happen that if the Minister for Industry and Commerce had on him the responsibility of dealing with the difficulties that arise in connection with supplies, especially in a time like the present, along with his other functions, sections of his Department would be at war with each other.  Difficulties would arise between sections of the Department of Industry and Commerce if the Supplies Department were under the one Minister.  I think it is for the benefit of the nation as a whole that a Department of Supplies has been set up.  The arrangement has worked out advantageously.  Speaking as Minister for Finance, I am not enthusiastic about the cost of a Minister for this Department, whatever the cost will be. I am sorry that I am not able to tell Senator Baxter what the cost is.  To be able to do so, I should require notice of the question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Then you are a very bad Minister for Finance if you are paying out money and do not know what it is for.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not a bit ashamed to confess that I do not know what the cost is, but if the Senator wants to put the question seriously I shall have it examined.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister should be able to give the House the information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it not be one of the functions of the Minister without portfolio to find that out?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="238" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  I would give him serious work to do.  What Senator Baxter asks is work for a clerk.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely, when the Minister is asked a question like that in the House be ought to be able to give the information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not answer a question like that right off without notice, and I do not agree that I am at fault at all in not being able to answer it without notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has a very happy conscience.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>I have, thanks be to God; a very tender one and a very happy one.  In answer to Senator Douglas' question, it is intended that this provision for a Minister without portfolio should be a permanent one in case this Government, or any Government that should come along in the future, may find it an advantage to have a man in that position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>But there is no limit to the number.  This could mean two or three.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but I think that is unlikely.  Senator Douglas suggested that an old experienced man might be useful in this position.  I often think that a young, inexperienced man might be equally useful in the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not really express an opinion on it.  I simply mentioned what I noticed had usually happened in other countries.  I really do not know myself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>Sometimes I think a new inexperienced man might be just as valuable as an old man in a position of the kind.  Senator Lynch asked a question about the control of supplies by private individuals.  Control will not be in the hands of private individuals. It will be in the hands of the Minister for Supplies.  He has, in certain cases, set up machinery to assist in obtaining those supplies.  As I understand it, <Col N="239" /> companies, not profit-making companies, have been set up, first of all to search for supplies, and then, when found, to make purchases, probably in a hurry.  The procedure associated with that kind of business, when done through a Government Department, is rather slow.  First of all, the Department concerned would have to examine the matter.  Then it would go to the Minister for Finance.  His Department would then examine it, and, if approved of, would provide the cash.  All that, as I say, is very slow.  Those who buy supplies of wheat, flour, timber, manures and things of that kind have to make up their minds quickly as to price and methods of transportation. Therefore, I take it that it is for the purpose of securing supplies quickly from the various markets, and arranging for their transport, that this special machinery that I have referred to has been set up by the Minister for Supplies.  It will assist him in endeavouring to secure that supplies will be made available for the people here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnLynch" hpid="Mr. E. Lynch Mr. E. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this statutory machinery or is it merely some effort on the part of the Minister to co-ordinate the activities of certain private firms in relation to certain commodities required in the country?  Paragraph (b) of sub-section (2) of Section 2 speaks of</P>
      <P>&ldquo;the maintenance and provision by or on behalf of the State of such supplies as aforesaid.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I do not see where the &ldquo;supplies as aforesaid&rdquo; are mentioned in the Bill at all.  Take the case of petrol.  As far as I understand it, the importation of petrol is in the hands of private individuals.  They may, for their own private reasons, refuse to import petrol.  In that event, what authority has the Minister for Supplies to bring in petrol if he has not statutory authority to do so?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not true to say that all the authority exercised by the Minister for Supplies is by virtue of the powers given under the emergency legislation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="240" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>That is so.  I know that the machinery I have referred to has been utilised in one or two cases to get in supplies.  The Minister for Supplies has set up this special machinery to make certain that supplies, when offered on the markets, will be bought quickly and transported here so that we may be certain of having the use of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnLynch" hpid="Mr. E. Lynch Mr. E. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>What I want to know is, will public money be available to the Minister to do that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnLynch" hpid="Mr. E. Lynch Mr. E. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Therefore, it seems to me that the Minister for Supplies has no statutory authority to do what the Minister suggests.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>That is so.  I said it was a matter of machinery&mdash;of arranging that supplies will be got.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not a fact&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnLynch" hpid="Mr. E. Lynch Mr. E. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we all realise that the Minister is quite capable of answering for himself.  We were getting along quite happily until Senator Douglas intervened.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Maybe he is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I understood the Minister to say that no public money was being made available, but is it not a fact that, in some cases, the Government have guaranteed to pay for goods coming in until they were resold?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not exactly what I had in mind.  I am not in a position to say whether it was at the Minister's suggestion or not that guarantees were given to pay for goods in certain cases.  Certainly, private non-profit-making companies were set up by people connected with certain trades, by merchants, importers and others.  Those companies were set up to purchase supplies&mdash;probably at the instigation of the Minister, though of that I am not certain.  At any rate, they were set up with the Minister's full knowledge and consent, with the <Col N="241" /> idea of watching the markets, seeing where supplies could be got, purchasing them and having them delivered here.  I take it that the Minister will see to it, when the supplies are landed here, that suitable arrangements will be made for their purchase and distribution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has said a good deal about the Department of Supplies, though I think we would be still inclined to doubt the necessity for it; but he has said nothing about the Department of Co-ordination of Defence, although Senator The McGillycuddy commented on that Department and suggested that it served no useful purpose in this country.  I wonder if the Minister would be inclined to develop a little the question of the utility of that Department, if he sees any utility in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry I did not take a note of all the points raised by Senator The McGillycuddy: evidently that one escaped my notice.  I had a note of those relating to the necessity for the Department of Supplies, to the question of economies, and to that of non-paying industries. There was need for the Department of Co-ordination of Defence; there were certain functions which were outside the ordinary work of the Minister for Defence and it was found advisable to have somebody to do them.  It is for that reason that this work has been given to the former Minister for Defence, Mr. Aiken.  I believe that, during his period there, he has satisfied the members of the Government that the functions performed by his office have been of national service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy of the Reeks The McGillycuddy of the Reeks">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy of the Reeks</NameTxt>
      <P>On that point, could I ask the Minister whom he is co-ordinating?  He has only got one coastal vessel, the airport at Baldonnel, and the airport at Rhynana. Is the Minister for Defence under his orders?  The whole position seems to be most extraordinary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to make it plain that I did not put that question in a spirit of criticism of the <Col N="242" /> occupier of the post; yet, in spite of what the Minister says, I cannot see the smallest likelihood of the existence of such a post doing anything but causing confusion.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When will the Committe Stage be taken?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I can find out from various Senators, there would be no objection to taking the various stages now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the position of amendments?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is a bad practice to rush this Bill through, and if we are meeting to-morrow I would suggest that its further consideration be postponed until then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with that, if we are meeting to-morrow.  I am sure the Minister has no desire to rush this Bill through the House; it was in the likelihood that we would not be meeting to-morrow that I suggested taking the remaining stages to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnLynch" hpid="Mr. E. Lynch Mr. E. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>If this Bill is to be taken to-morrow, I would like if the Minister could give some detailed in formation regarding the work of those companies that have been set up by the Minister for Supplies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That point could be raised on the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnLynch" hpid="Mr. E. Lynch Mr. E. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be glad if the Minister would give some detailed information as to what actually has been done in this regard, as I personally attach very great importance to such information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>I would strongly protest against the Bill being disposed of without time being given for the introduction of amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Committee Stage is taken to-day, would the Chair not be willing to take amendments without notice?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="243" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, if that meets the convenience of Senators, but the procedure may not prove satisfactory.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>To have a Committee Stage and not take amendments would be the height of absurdity.  We should take the Pigs and Bacon Bill now and take the other later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the reaction of Senators to the suggestion to take the Bill to-morrow?  Will the Minister be in a position to give to the House the information which has been requested this afternoon?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>I am entirely in the hands of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister says that the information can be given satisfactorily to-morrow there is no reason why the Bill should be taken now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>That is entirely a matter for the House to decide.  Even if we are meeting to-morrow, I do not know that I would have all the information which might satisfy Senator Lynch.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely, regarding the Department of Supplies, there should be no difficulty in supplying the information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Unless the Seanad is agreeable to taking the remaining stages to-day, nothing much would be gained, and it would be more satisfactory, to my mind, to defer the Committee Stage until to-morrow.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take the remaining stages to-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Pigs and Bacon (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1939&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Public Business. - Pigs and Bacon (Amendment) Bill, 1939&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>The expression &ldquo;the transfer date&rdquo; means the 1st day of January, 1940;...</P>
    <Col N="244" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the following amendment:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 2.  In lines 43-44, page 4, to delete the words and figures &ldquo;1st day of January, 1940&rdquo; and substitute therefor the words and figures &ldquo;1st day of June, 1940&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>My principal object in moving this amendment is to induce the Minister to institute negotiations with the British Government, with a view to having all restrictions removed on the export of surplus live pigs, at least for the duration of the war.  I am concerned on behalf of pig producers and farmers who, like myself, depend on the production and sale of pigs for a livelihood.  I am confident that if we had a free export market for live pigs it would very much increase the price of all classes of pigs, would create confidence in the future of the trade, and be the best means that could be adopted to increase production.  I know the bad effects of a market that is restricted to certain limited buyers. I know the effects of competition as well as the loss of competition in a market.  I also know how that affects any trade which has to be conducted in the way the pig trade has to be conducted at present.  In addition, I know the effect of issuing a limited number of licences for the export of live pigs to a favoured few.  I know all this very much better than the Minister or any of his advisers.  On the Second Reading I stated that the value of export licences represented from 35/- to £2 per pig.  It must be apparent to anyone that if an export licence is worth even 30/- to a pig exporter, that 30/- is not coming out of his pocket, but is coming out of the pockets of the producers.  That is not good for pig production.  Nobody will pay even 10/- for an export licence, unless he can see clearly that there is going to be considerable profit on the export of pigs.  In 1938, 74,120 live pigs were exported from the ports of Éire, and 1,044,779 were purchased by the bacon factories.  I do not know the figures for last year, but I think they would be slightly higher.  Possibly they will be greater next year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="245" /> If the Minister agrees to my suggestion for the free export of 1,200,000 or 1,500,000 pigs, whatever the figures may be, I am confident it would put between £1,500,000 and £2,000,000 into the pockets of producers which, otherwise, will go to the bacon curers, or to that section of the exporters of pigs that is fortunate enough to get licences.  I do not want to block this Bill.  The amendment will permit the Bill to be put on the Statute Book, but the Minister will have power to treat the bacon factories and the bacon curers as he wishes.  Under present conditions he can do that by order.  The Minister will probably say that the British Government will insist on having live pigs shipped under quota.  I do not believe the British Government will insist on that.  If the British are properly approached I believe they will agree to take our live pigs when and how we can send them, and that they will be glad to get them during the present crisis.  If the Minister can give any assurance about approaching the British Government to make arrangement for the export of live pigs, I will not press the amendment, but, if he insists on saying that that cannot be done, I am afraid I will have to press for a division, in order to see whether Senators in this House are more interested in bacon curers than farmers and pig producers.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Senator Counihan has made a very good case indeed for approaching this question of the free export of pigs with an open mind.  I know of one case where a farmer had pigs ready recently for the local bacon factory, and was told that the quota for the month was filled. He could not sell the pigs to the local bacon factory, and equally he could not export them because he had no licence. The result was that he had to keep the pigs for a month too long, and by the time they were finally sent to their destination, they were, probably, so fat that they were not graded as highly as they should be, and were worth less money.  Obviously, the remedy, if the local bacon factory cannot take pigs, is to allow completely free export of live pigs.  I am quite certain that <Col N="246" /> there can be no real difficulty at present about getting that freedom to export, so far as our British neighbours are concerned, because they are terribly short of both pigs and bacon. Normally they consume between 8,000,000 and 10,000,000 cwts of bacon in that country, of which we supply a beggarly 300,000 or 400,000 cwts.  They import the bulk of their bacon from the Seandanavian countries.  I think that more than half of it comes from these countries, but as we know owing to recent events, the British market must be simply clamouring for bacon or pigs, alive or dead.  I am sure as far as they are concerned that there is no obstacle whatever to the free export of live pigs.  If there is any difficulty it must arise on our side and as a result of our own policy.  I cannot see what national interest as a whole is going to be advanced by any restrictions on the free export of live pigs.  I suspect it may be that, possibly, certain bacon curers might not get as many pigs as they would like to get, if farmers were free to export live pigs instead of sending them to the factories. Is it part of our national policy that we should bolster up inefficient bacon factories at the expense of farmers and pig producers as a whole?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan) James Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not find it very easy to relate this amendment to the speech which Senator Counihan has just made.  The speech of the Senator appears to me to be a sort of threat to the Minister. The speech in effect is &ldquo;If you do not do what I ask you I will force the amendment&rdquo;.  That seems to be a sort of threat.  I do not see what the amendment has to do with the question. Live pigs do not come and never did come into this bacon legislation. It is a form of intimidation and the only way to treat intimidation is to take it as such and try to meet it.  Now dealing with the points that Senator Counihan has made I want to point out that there was no restriction whatever on the number of live pigs exported up to 1933.  Before 1933 there were live pigs going out but they did not all go out.  Evidently before restrictions were imposed on the export <Col N="247" /> of live pigs prior to 1933, the farmers themselves elected to send their pigs to the bacon factories.  The dealers in some cases elected to send them to the bacon factories instead of exporting them as live pigs.</P>
      <P>If the general tenour of Senator Counihan's remarks were true all the bacon factories would have been broken when there was no restriction on the export of live pigs.  But from 1933 up to September this year there was partial restriction on the export of live pigs.  Any exporter here sending pigs to England had to have a quota for exporting them.  More than half the pigs exported went to pork butchers and they needed no licence.  That shows that there was a large quota without restrictions and yet the export of pigs did not take place.  Yet it is assumed by Senators Counihan and Johnston that many more live pigs would go out if we had come to an arrangement with the British Government on this question. I do not believe that.  It is not deemed proper here to make a bet, but I ask Senator Counihan here to say what he thinks the position will be between March and August next and say how many pigs will then be sent out.  Our experience is that there is a flush of pigs in October, November and December, but from January until June it is the other way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>There was not a war on in those last six or seven years. During a war the position might be different.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it true that people are paying money for export licences for pigs?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>If export licences are worth money then it is a bare statement of the case to say that it would be in the interest of the farmers to be given licences to export these pigs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know.  A lot of the dealers go around saying that if <Col N="248" /> they had licences they could pay £1 more for the pigs.  But they are not paying £1 more for the pigs they are actually buying at the present time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>If everyone dealing in pigs was able to get a licence there would be more competition between the buyers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are speaking here at a transitional period in the British market.  The British have removed control and if they reimpose it after January 8th, whatever price may be paid for live pigs for export, there is no doubt but the factories here will have to pay the same price because we could not possibly carry on the pig business without the exporting of live pigs. If the exporters of live pigs pay more for the pigs than what the people can get from the factories, the factories could not possibly carry on.  But I think it would be a pity to upset everything in this country for the sake of three or four weeks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The ideal solution for the factories here would be to pay as much for the pigs cured in the factory as is paid for the pigs exported.  The board met last week and they thought they could meet that point.  I do not know if the board can meet it&mdash;perhaps they can. They might bring the present factory price up to what the live pigs are worth.  I think that is the only way in which it would be dealt with.  But if we were to remove those restrictions and if we were to say to the exporters here: &ldquo;You may export all the pigs you like now,&rdquo; I am certain 1,000,000 pigs will not go out as live pigs.  I am sure if 1,000,000 or 1,500,000 pigs did go out exported alive that would not put £1,000,000 or £1,500,000 into the pockets of the pig producers.  If there was an intention on my part to continue the state of affairs by which £1 or 30/- more is paid for live pigs exported than is paid by the factories, Senator Counihan would be right, but this state of affairs is not to continue beyond the 8th of January.  In the meantime, I urged the board to see that the farmer who brings his pigs to the factories gets as good a price for them as he would get from the man <Col N="249" /> who buys them for export as live pigs. It is extremely difficult for the board here to fix such a price as will ensure that, because the prices are changing daily.  They might bring up the price of pigs at the factory to-day and next day the value of live pigs exported may go up again.  However, this will arise only for a few weeks at any rate.</P>
    <P>There was one point raised by Senator Johnston, that he knew a farmer whose pigs would not be taken because the quota at the factory had been filled.  I take it that is true because there were factories which did have a particular production quota filled before the month was over.  They could not take any pigs that came after the production quota was filled.  We will try to get that position right. Senator Johnston suspects that the bacon factories would not like to see the export quota enlarged for live pigs. It does not make the slightest difference whether they like it or not. The whole position is this&mdash;that as long as the war lasts the British Government is anxious to control the amount of bacon and pigs going into the country as much as possible.  But the British Government want to know beforehand what we are to send them. Everyone will realise that if the British Government is bringing in a rationing system they must have a fair idea of the amount of food coming in.  Otherwise they could not gauge properly what the ration would be.  They have asked us (1) how much bacon we can send them in 1940; (2) to distribute that over the 12 months; and (3) to give a constant proportion of live pigs.  We cannot meet them on the matter of the distribution over the 12 months.  We could export much more in October, November and December than in May and June.  They accept that.</P>
    <P>We cannot have a constant proportion over the 12 months.  And we cannot get the exporters to send out the live pigs from March to August because the dealers would lose 5/- or 6/- a pig on the exports during those months.  We could say at the present time that we would make our exports 70 per cent. of live pigs during October, November and December, but <Col N="250" /> we could not send more than 15 per cent. or 20 per cent. live pigs from March to August.  We could probably get 70 per cent. for this month, but during other parts of the year we could not get more than 5 per cent. or 10 per cent.  For that reason we cannot say that we could make a proportion of 70 per cent. of live pigs during the year.  That is our position. Senators Counihan and Johnston are right in this.  I am quite sure that the British Government would not mind if we sent them 100 per cent. live pigs.  If we do that it would be 100 per cent. for the year round.  But taking the sort of seasonal differences in prices that take place here always, it appears more profitable to the producers to have their pigs sent to the bacon factories from March to August. It is after that they have to export alive.  For the balance of the year it is better that we should not send out a very large proportion in the form of live pigs.  We could send out an extra number of live pigs for November and December.  In the latter month there would be a fairly substantial number.  There is no objection to that.  It is the only way in which we can deal with this position and that is to arrange for a fairly definite percentage of our exports as live pigs.  Then when it comes to the months of October, November and December, when the number of pigs for sale is greater we could ask the British Government for an extra quota for live pigs.  So far we have not had any great difficulty in getting this export quota.</P>
    <P>We sent out a number of licences in November.  Senator Counihan here holds that these licences were worth money.  But the strange thing about it is that a good many of these licences were returned to us unused.  It must be that the holders of these licences did not realise their value because numbers of them came back unused. These licences were sent only to people who had exported live pigs in November, 1938.  No one got a licence except people who exported live pigs in November, 1938.  It is manifest that these people were in the business in 1938 and yet a good many licences came <Col N="251" /> back unused from these people.  If Senator Counihan wants an undertaking from me that I would not allow this condition to continue, where licences are worth money, in other words, that we would not compel people to send pigs to the factories when they are worth more for export, I think I can give that undertaking that we will not allow that beyond the middle of January.  It may be difficult to arrange things in the meantime, but we will try to arrange things as well as we can.  The amendment would be extremely awkward to accept, because the Pigs Board and the Bacon Board legally are going out of office on the last day of December and we would have nobody to take their places if this Bill is not passed.  Senator Counihan, I think, suggested that we could do something by means of an emergency order.  I am not sure if we could.  An emergency order has been taken to be applicable only to conditions arising out of the war.  I do not know if I could convince the Attorney-General that this arose out of the war because he would perhaps say: &ldquo;It has arisen out of your own neglect; why did you not bring in the Bill sooner?&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am disappointed that the Minister was not more sympathetic to the suggestion I made and I am sure that the pig producers will be also disappointed.  The Minister says that this control is only on for a few months&mdash;that pigs will be decontrolled about the middle of January.  I can assure the Minister that when they were controlled there was 3/- and 4/- more than the control price got in England by exporters of Irish pigs.  The Minister does not know the whole of it.  The Minister, like the British Government, may make orders, but from his experience of the economic war he should know that it is impossible to carry out these matters.  When he was issuing licences for cattle the condition on which licences were issued was that the exporter should pay 25/- per live cwt. for fat cattle for export.  He knows perfectly well that the majority of the cattle were sold under £1 per cwt.  He <Col N="252" /> knows well that the butchers were to pay 25/- per cwt. for cattle and he knows how many of them did it&mdash;at least I know how many did it.  I know I had to take £1 per cwt. when the control price was 25/-.  There are several ways of doing that.</P>
      <P>To come back to the Minister's statement about what will happen after the control, the Minister seems to forget that we are trading now in war time. All I have asked him to do is to approach the British Government to get free export and free trade for surplus live pigs in the British market. If he does that we will have more competition in the fairs.  Except you have an open market without licences the competition will be restricted and the price will be kept down.  An exporter having a licence knows well that there is a surplus in a particular market and that there is only a limited number of buyers.  The buyers for the curers and the buyers for export are a chip of the one block.  When nobody can buy for export without a licence, competition is wiped out and the price of pigs is not what it should be or even what the present control price is.  A very big percentage of the pigs at fairs at present are being sent to the factories. If the Minister continues this he will be restricting the number of pigs and there can be only 60,000 or 70,000 exported out of the 1,500,000 which we produce.  He will wipe out the export of live pigs entirely and throw us completely into the hands of the curers.  That will not be good for the producers and will tend to decrease the production of pigs in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If what I am suggesting were adopted it would be the best means of producing confidence in the future of the trade and it would be the best thing that the Minister could do to increase production, namely, to have free export for our surplus live pigs.  All I ask him to do is to approach the British Government and say, even for the period of the war, that we want free export for live pigs without any quota.  I am confident that if the Minister approaches the British Government they will not insist on any definite quota, but will be delighted to have all <Col N="253" /> the live pigs we can send them and whatever quantity of bacon we can send them without any restrictions as to quota.  But the Minister has his own ideas about it and his advisers have their own ideas.  He is probably more concerned with the bacon curers than he is with the farmers who produce the pigs, and for that reason I intend to press this amendment.</P>
    <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    <P>Section put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 3 to 11, inclusive, put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 12.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 12 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 4 (3) says that the commission shall consist of three members.  Then Section 12 (4) says that the commission may act notwithstanding one vacancy amongst the ordinary members.  I want to know is it a commission at all without the three members being present?  I am not quite clear on that point.  It seems to me that the commission is to consist of three members, namely, the chairman and two ordinary members.  But this section says that the commission may act notwithstanding one vacancy amongst the ordinary members.  There seems to be something contradictory in it.  Probably one section dominates the other, but I think it needs clarification. I want to be clear if it is a commission at all without the three members.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is.  This is put in to remove any doubt that there might be. The intention is to have three members.  Some of these orders, however, have to be made rather urgently. If, for any reason, an ordinary member were to retire, and if an order were made a day or two before the vacancy is filled, this provision is put in so that it could be done legally.  It is only intended to cover a case like that. Nothing of any importance would be done until the vacant seat was filled. Power is delegated at the present time <Col N="254" /> by the Pigs and Bacon Boards to the chairman to make certain orders which have to be made in a routine way. This provision is really intended to cover a case of that kind where routine orders might have to be made before the vacancy was filled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister is satisfied, I am satisfied.  It seems to me that one section ought to be related to the other section in some way.  You might make an order under Section 12, dealing with curers and you might find yourself in court at the instance of a curer who contended that the body which made the particular order was not a commission at all.  Perhaps the Minister would look into that matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know that they will ever have to use that power again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="Mr. Goulding Mr. Goulding">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Goulding</NameTxt>
      <P>This clause is a safeguard.</P>
      <P>Section agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 13 to 17 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 18.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 18 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>This section gives power to make various regulations.  Under the Act, the Minister made the regulations. In this Bill, the commission</P>
      <P>&ldquo;may make regulations in relation to any matter or thing.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I take it that these regulations will be made in conjunction with the Minister because they have to be laid on the Table of each House of the Oireachtas. A regulation would not be laid on the Table if the Minister was not prepared to stand over it.  It would seem to me, therefore, that these regulations can only be made in conjunction with the Minister.  That is an important point and I should like to hear the Minister upon it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the Act, the board could make certain regulations dealing with their own part of the business while the Minister could make regulations <Col N="255" /> arising out of his part.  About half that Act dealt with inspection and matters of that sort.  That was the Minister's business.  That part of the original Act still stands and the Minister makes the necessary regulations under it.  This Bill principally deals with the transfer from the boards to the commission and the making of regulations will mostly fall to the boards rather than to the Minister. What Senator Baxter says is right: they will not expect the Minister to defend any regulation before the Dáil or Seanad which they may make without first getting his approval.</P>
      <P>Section agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 19 to 33 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 34.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 34 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Under sub-section (2) of this section, the Minister may at any time by order declare there shall be no levy.  What exactly has the Minister in mind as to the circumstances in which the sub-section would operate?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>This particular levy is concerned with administrative expenses. The Pigs and Bacon Boards made these levies under the original Act.  I think they amount to about 4d. per pig.  The commission will naturally strike some sort of levy when they take over control.  Possibly they will leave the levy as it is.  What is contemplated, I take it, is that if they accumulate a fair amount of money, they will have power to stop the levy if they think fit.  Under this sub-section they would not be bound to strike the levy if they did not need it.</P>
      <P>Section agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 35 to 49 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 50.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 50 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="256" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister give us some information on this section? The Minister has retained the production quota under this Bill but has suspended its operation.  I am concerned now with the export quota.  I should like some information from the Minister as to what his intentions are regarding the percentage of the export quota which he took away from the southern curers and gave to curers in the north to help them in a set of circumstances which then existed but which no longer exists.  The southern curers are very anxious to know if the Minister intends to return them the percentage of the export quota which he took away.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The main export quota was, if you like, divided into three parts.  It was built up, in the first instance, by the system of application and undertaking.  When this export quota business came in first, in 1933, the Department asked the curers what export quota they would like.  The applications were, probably, somewhat above what we could export at the time and they were cut down by an equal percentage all round.  We also took into account what their exports had been up to that.  On this large block of export quotas, I think no curer had a grievance because some of those who held export quotas asked to have them reduced as time went on because the home market was a bit better.  Those looking for more got them.  For two or three years the curers got what they required by way of export quotas and it was fixed at that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the beginning, a certain percentage was reserved to deal with a problem in the North of Ireland.  At the time we brought in our Bill dealing with the regulation of exports, the British Government were regulating the bacon-production business and the Government of the North of Ireland were doing likewise.  The British Government, I take it at the instance of the Northern Government, said they would stop the import of carcases across the Border.  Senators from the North know that most of the pigs in Ulster were killed and brought to the market as carcases.  They were mostly collected <Col N="257" /> by factories situated in the Six Counties.  We got notice from the British Government that this would have to stop.  They said they would give a quota of in or about what had been going over up to then, but it would diminish by one-twelfth each month so that it would disappear completely in 12 months.  That quantity of carcases represented about 8 per cent. of our exports.  Eight per cent. of our exports was given to factories situated in the North so that they could absorb these pigs as live pigs now instead of carcases and, therefore, ease, so far as possible, any disturbance in the trade up there so far as the farmer was concerned. That appears to me to be a continuing problem.  It is not the sort of thing which we could deal with by saying we would distribute the quotas because we must assume that the pigs are still there.  The pigs will be there for all time and, therefore, it is the Northern factories that should deal with those, and I do not see that the factories in the South have any claim on that particular 8 per cent.  The matter has never been considered as being on a permanent basis, and it has always been referred to as a special quota given to those factories within reach of the Northern counties and, accordingly, I think that we should do something to put the matter on a permanent basis at some time or other.</P>
    <P>There is another point which I should like to make.  After concluding the agreement with England in 1938, we agreed to import something like 2,000 cwts. of bacon every year.  That came mostly over the Border and, in that way, went into competition with the factories again, and they claimed an export quota to get rid of that part of their bacon for which they had now lost the home market.  They got that quota, but it has been withdrawn again, so that we are back now to about 92 per cent., which is a permanent and fair basis for all, and about 8 per cent., which is given among the factories that we can reach in the North for the purpose of absorbing these pigs that are used as carcases across the Border, and now, presumably, will be taken up by the factories <Col N="258" /> in that area.  I agree with Senator Crosbie that something should be done to put this business on a permanent basis.  That has been the intention, but we have been postponing it from time to time, and I suppose one of the reasons for these postponements was that we were waiting for the report of the commission.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>But the Minister will consider that aspect of the trade?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, and I should like to have the Senator's advice on the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, because there is the question of such cities as Cork, Limerick, and so on, which are seaports, to be considered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but the producers in the North, naturally, must be taken into account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister will undertake to consider it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarMacFhionnlach" hpid="Peadar Mac Fhionnlaoich Peadar Mac Fhionnlaoich">
      <NameTxt>Peadar Mac Fhionnlaoich</NameTxt>
      <P>Is fusa dul thar an teorainn ná dul ar an fhairrge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to know from the Minister whether, when he exercises the power of suspending the production quota, that automatically implies that the whole business of production sub-quotas for each bacon factory is also suspended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume that that is the meaning of the words at the end of the section.  I should be glad to see the end of these sub-quotas, representing, as they do, one of the things that have been commented on unfavourably by the Prices Commission as keeping in existence factories that are inefficient and interfering with factories that are efficient and should be encouraged.</P>
      <P>Sections 50 to 54, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="259" /> SECTION 55.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 55 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>On Section 55, realising that the Minister wanted to get his Bill through and that it was a matter of urgency, and knowing also that this whole question of price had been raised and discussed at length in amendments that were moved, discussed, and withdrawn, in the Dáil, I decided not to put down an amendment here, but I do want a discussion on this section from the point of view of the basis on which prices are to be fixed for pigs in future.  This, as the Minister knows, is all-important.  People produce commodities&mdash;or at least the people who are farmers believe that farmers produce&mdash;when it pays them to produce.  The Minister has made certain statements here and I take it that it is his view that the price which is to be fixed for pigs is to be related to the price at which bacon is being sold. Apparently, his view is that the price of bacon, for some time to come at any rate, is going to be such as will pay the farmer for the production of pigs. In the other House, Deputy Dillon had down an amendment asking that the price should be related to the cost of a balanced ration, and while he withdrew that amendment, and while, apparently, there was general agreement on both sides of that House that something like that would be of value, I think the Minister said that it would not be helpful to have it in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would be quite satisfied if we could have a statement from the Minister that it is going to be the policy of this particular commission to take that matter into consideration and relate the price of pigs to the cost of production.  I think that is the most important thing to do.  I consider that it is more important to relate the price of pigs to the cost of production than to relate it to the price of bacon, as far as the producer is concerned.  None of us can prophesy at the moment what may happen in the days to come with regard to bacon prices.  We may be going into a <Col N="260" /> period that, as far as bacon prices are concerned, would be looked upon as an inflationary period.  Bacon prices may be raised, through one cause or another, beyond what is a reasonable price.  You may have violent fluctuations despite anything that this Government think they may be able to do.  We have to wait in order to see whether or not they will be able to control inflation, and many people are very doubtful about the Government's capacity to do that.  I do not think that we in this country, if we want to get our pig production on a sound basis, wish to see a condition of things developed here whereby a man will get as much for producing seven pigs as he would get if he produced ten pigs. I do not think that would be good, even for his own people, to-day, and nobody knows what may happen to-morrow or in the near future.  It is quite possible that we might be up against the opposite situation, where prices of bacon will have fallen off for some reason or another over which we have no control.  What pig producers want in the future is stability in prices, and to have the price of pigs related to the cost of production.  The Agricultural Commission have given an indication of that, and I do not think it is disputed.</P>
    <P>I am rather disturbed about the line the Minister is taking, however.  He has said here&mdash;and I do not say that I am in disagreement with him&mdash;that it would be quite an impossible situation for this Government to find itself in, if they had to subsidise the export of bacon to England at the present time; in other words, that, if you fix a price for pigs, related to the cost of production, and the price which you can get for bacon will not meet the price, the only way in which you can keep producing is by subsidising the export of bacon to England, and that that would be unpopular for the Government and an unjustifiable policy for them to pursue. I do not think the Government should be put in that position, and I think it would be very difficult for them to justify export subsidies for pigs or bacon to England during war time, but I do not think that that argument is a justifiable argument by which to <Col N="261" /> relieve the Minister or this commission from paying to the farmers a price that will more than cover the cost of production of pigs.  If the price of bacon in England is not sufficiently high to enable the producer of pigs here to get a price that will relate the price of pigs to the cost of production, is it fair to expect the producer of pigs in this country to carry the burden of exporting bacon to England at a price that, really, is not above the cost of production? If we are up against a situation in which either the Government will have to subsidise the export of bacon, or the producer of pigs will be expected to send bacon to England at a price under the cost of production, I do not think the producer ought to be expected to do that.</P>
    <P>If we have to face that situation, let us face it, but let us all face it together, Government, commission and producers, but let not the Government leave on the farmer the burden and the responsibility of producing pigs, on dear food, and selling them at a price that will not pay.  It may very well be that if we have to meet a situation like that, the Government will have to say to the British people: &ldquo;You are going through a war.  Our farmers are paying so much for meals to feed their pigs to-day that they cannot sell bacon to you at that price.  We cannot send it to you unless we subsidise it, and we are not going to do that.&rdquo;  If you have to face a situation like that, it may very well be that the circumstances in the market at a particular moment might determine that you would have to finance a scheme of putting bacon into cold storage for three or six months, and carrying it here at home, or to subsidise the curers in order to let cheaper bacon and more bacon out to our people at home, or some other method, rather than to try to carry on a policy like that.  The one thing I am convinced of is that whatever else we are to do, it is not enough to say to the producers to-day that the price of pigs must be related to the price of bacon and that that is what is going to govern the price of pigs. That is not going to be satisfactory at all.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="262" /> As I say, the Minister may be so optimistic about the price of pigs that he feels there is no necessity to give any undertaking to the producers, but if there is going to be no danger in giving an undertaking, if the price is going to be so high, the giving of the undertaking is going to cost nothing. The undertaking is going to be a burden on the Government only when the producer is not getting as much for his pigs sold as is covering his cost of production. I suggest that it is much better to be prepared for that situation long before you have to meet it than to come right up against it, and against the chaos, the disorder and the discouragement which the producers are going to encounter.  It may very well be that you are going into a period when some such scheme as Mr. J.M. Keynes was suggesting in relation to British saving might be applied to the bacon industry here, for some time to come.</P>
    <P>My opinion is that it would be much better for our farmers to be guaranteed something more than the cost of production, to be guaranteed stability and security in the market, than to have a situation in which, in the Dublin market to-day, because there are a certain number of licences available and because certain curing factories in England want pigs, we are going to have inflated prices, which, on this day week, are going to be altogether different. That is one of the worst things we could experience in the production of bacon, and I suggest to the Minister that, whatever may be in the Bill, it should quite definitely be the policy of this commission to relate the price of pigs to the cost.  It is up and down now every week, and what it is going to be in two or three months' time, we do not know.  It may be less, and it may be much more than it is to-day, depending on whether certain boats come into this country or not.  While I am on that point about the cost of production, along the Border at present a certain policy is being carried on. Ill-off as we seem to be in the matter of feeding stuffs, the situation is no better, and, in fact, is much worse, on the other side of the Border.  Certain <Col N="263" /> quantities of feeding stuffs are coming into this country, and although it is an offence to bring these foods across the Border into Northern Ireland, they are to-day actually being smuggled into the Six Counties.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>What sort of foodstuffs?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Feeding stuffs for pigs. The Press reported the other day a fine of £5 on a farmer in some town in the North&mdash;Aughnacloy in the County Tyrone, I think&mdash;and I heard of a farmer with a ton of foodstuffs on his cart, whose horse and cart and foodstuffs were seized.  His horse and cart were kept for three or four days and eventually he got them back, minus the foodstuffs.  It shows how stupid Governments can be.  One would think that these people would be delighted to get in all the foodstuffs they could, and to have them available for their farmers.  When foodstuffs come into this country, it ought to be made an offence to take them out of the country in any form other than meat or products of that kind.  I think it is something the Minister ought to look after, because, in my own part of the country, I know that it is difficult at present to procure feeding.  The millers have not got it, and I know that some of the food being sold to traders in the Twenty-Six Counties is being taken across the Border.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We want it here because it is essential for our production and I would be very insistent that the Minister's policy, and the commission's policy, should not be to relate the price of pigs in future to the price of bacon, because that is a fluctuating figure. So are the costs of feeding stuffs, but particularly now, when we are going into a period when our production will depend to a great extent on our imported foods.  If you want to keep us in production, if you want to secure that we are paid for our production, relate our pig prices to the cost of the things we have to buy to feed them. We will be better paid, in my judgement, if you give us a reasonable profit over the costs of production than if <Col N="264" /> you give us to-day a very greatly increased, or inflated, price for pigs which, to-morrow, related to the price of bacon, may drop again.  If the Minister will give the House a statement on that point, I think there will be much more security and much more encouragement for the pig producers than in any statement that we are going to get £9, £10, £12 or £15 a cwt. for pigs because bacon is going to go very high.  That is very problematical and, in my judgement, it is not a sound basis at all on which to build increased pig production here.</P>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy of the Reeks The McGillycuddy of the Reeks">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy of the Reeks</NameTxt>
      <P>I support what Senator Baxter has said about the relation of the price of pigs to the cost of production.  I have always held that, even in peace time, the top and bottom of our agricultural success, and of any profits the farmer makes, depend on the price of feeding stuffs, and I have urged the lowering of the prices of these feeding stuffs again and again in this House and elsewhere. In war time, it is more important still, and if you reach a point at which the cost of feeding stuffs is equal to, or greater than, the actual price obtained for the pig, instead of having a campaign from which you get large numbers of pigs for export, you will finally have no pigs at all, or very few.  The tendency in regard to war prices so far as feeding stuffs are concerned, is that they will rise.  They have already done so, as we all know, and there would be every possible effort both on this side and on the other side of the House to keep down the price of human foodstuffs such as bacon.  It is necessary, therefore, if we are to get the farmer to produce pigs, that the price of pigs should be related to the cost of production.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam O Buachalla Liam O Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam O Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Níor cheap mé go mbeadh aon díosbóireacht ar an mBille seo indiu go mór-mór tar éis an méid a dubhradh an lá cheana faoi. Ach ós rud é go bhfuil an díosbóireacht ar bun, ba mhaith liom poinnte no dó a luadh.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I did not think we would have very much discussion on this Bill to-day, and <Col N="265" /> the way the matter proceeded down to this particular section led me to believe that there would be no difficulty about it.  Senator Baxter has raised a very important question, and that is the cost of production He appealed to the Minister to see to it that the price made available for pigs is closely related to the cost of production.  He also mentioned that it was the recommendation of the Agricultural Commission that the price of pigs should be closely related to the cost of production. I agree with that.  I think everybody will agree that the price of the pig should be closely related to the cost of production, but there is a danger in that, and, besides, there is also a very great difficulty.  I do not intend to take up much of the time of the House, but I should like to recall to you the observation of the Agricultural Commission on this particular point.  In paragraphs 24 and 25 of the interim report they say:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The big secular factor making for decline in pig production in Eire is the lack of competitive power in our pig products.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;High production costs and low output are keeping profitability down.  Lack of technical competence and of close attention to the details of economical production contrast unfavourably with the rapid increase in productive capacity attained by our competitors in the export market.  To these fundamental causes must be ascribed the relative decline in the profitability of our pig producing industry.  We consider that to ascribe quantitative impor tance to any other factor would indicate lack of a correct sense of proportion.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There lies the difficulty, I think, in this whole question of Irish pig production. The commission has had evidence, time and time again, that most of the difficulty is due to the fact that the producers lack technical competence.  How we are going to get over that is another matter.  The commission was convinced eventually that most of the difficulty arose on account of the lack of adequate technical education; the producers <Col N="266" /> were not trained as to the proper ration; they were not educated on the whole question of housing, heating, breeding, and so on.  How are we going to get over those difficulties? The cost of production may be anything, there can be many different costs of production, but normally it has to be related to something definite.  We in Ireland have to relate it to the cost of production of our competitors.  Can we produce bacon, above all commodities, as we cheaply as our competitors?  If we cannot, we have just got to go out of the industry.  I believe in paying subsidies over a certain time, but we cannot go on indefinitely paying subsidies. The whole industry will have to be reorganised, but where we have to start is at the technical training of the producers.  We cannot get away from that.</P>
    <P>There is only just one other point to which I want to refer, and that has reference, in view of this Bill, to the possibilities of this particular industry in the Gaeltacht.</P>
    <P>Tá súil agam go gcuirfe muinntir na Gaedhealtachta spéis fa leith san tionnsgal seo feasta.  Feileann sé go maith dóibh agus má theigheann siad 'na bhun go ceart agus le stuaim, bainfe siad airgead maith amach air.</P>
    <P>Tá buntáistí faoi leith a' baint le tóigeál múc sa nGaedhealtacht.  Ar an gcéad dul sios, bionn riar mór fataí annsiúd&mdash;ceann de na h-ádhbhair bídh is tábhachtaighe le haghaidh muc.  Dá fheabhas dá bhfuil fataí á saothrú annsin, is féidir tuilleamh feabhais a chur ar an obair.  Tugtar tuilleamh aire do sgéal na síolta, leasú, draénáil, agus rl. agus cuirfear go mór le torthamhlacht na talmhana.</P>
    <P>Tá na tighthe acu le h-aghaidh na muc freisin&mdash;sí an Ghaedhealtacht, b'féidir, is fearr atá réidhtighthe i gcóir an tionnsgail ó thaobh tighthe go h-áithrid.</P>
    <P>Tá congnamh maith, fial le faghail i gcomhnuidhe le h-aghaidh na gcró seo agus is ar na daoine iad fhein an milleán mara mbí a lán eile de na tighthe seo a gcur suas.  Maidir le saothar, nó oibridhthe tá sé le fagháil <Col N="267" /> go líonmhar sa nGaedhealtacht.  Má théigheann na daoine isteach agus muca a thóigeál agus a bheathú, beidh deis mhaith saothair acu, deis a íocfas go binn iad.</P>
    <P>Ach ar nós dream ar bith eile sa tír, ní dhéanfa nósanna cuma liom cúis. Tá dhá shlighe le gach rud a dhéanamh agus tá dhá shlighe le muca a bheathú &mdash;an tslighe cheart, éargnamhail&mdash; agus an obair a dhéanamh ar nós cuma liom.</P>
    <P>Brathann a lán ar an sórt oideachais atá ag na daoine i dtaobh an tionnsgail. Chualamar a lán le tamall mar gheall ar na deacrachtaí a bhaineas le ceárdamhlacht san ngnó&mdash;tói geál na muc atá i gceist agam.  Na daoine ar fad a bhfuil eolas faoi leith acu ar an ngnó, deir siad, morán iad go léir, gur uireasbaidh eolais, nó oideachais, i measg na bhfeilméara agus muinntir na tuaithe i gcoitcheann is mó a chur cúl ariamh le méadú nó forfhás an tionnsgail.</P>
    <P>Ba mhaith liom go dtiubhradh na Coisdí Talmhaidheachta agus a gcuid teagasgóirí aire fa leith feasda don ghné seo den sgéal.</P>
    <P>Ar chaoi ar bith, tá seans anois ag an nGaedhealtacht tionnsgail atá rífheileamhnach dí, a bhaint amach dí féin.  Tá súil agam nach ndéanfa na daoine inti faillighe sa sgéal.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>The House may be interested to know that I found myself in thorough agreement with the remarks which Senator Buckley has just made, in so far as they were made in a language which I understood.  I should like to go further and say that even when he speaks in the other language I like listening to him, even though I do not understand a word he says in that other language.  In this matter, I think the enthusiast and the technician and professional economist&mdash;I am glad to welcome the new Senator in that capacity as well as in his other capacity in this House&mdash;are fundamentally the same.  As far as I understand it, the policy which inspires this Bill as a whole is a policy of so relating the production of pigs and bacon in the country to the cost of producing those pigs over a long term that the production <Col N="268" /> of pigs will show a steady upward trend, and return a steadily increasing income to the farmer and to the community. The object is also that that result should be obtained without increasing the price per unit to the consumer, apart from temporary war conditions, but on the contrary that it should be compatible with a reduction in the price of bacon, if only we can get our production up to such a point that the cost of turning the pig into bacon is reduced on account of the greater volume of pigs to be dealt with. With that policy I am in thorough agreement, and in operating that policy the commission will, of course, have to take into account the cost of production. But the whole conception of cost of production is terribly difficult to be precise about, because there are as many costs of producing pigs&mdash;as indeed of producing anything else&mdash;as there are persons producing them, or even, one might say, as there are pigs being produced.  The cost vary with the efficiency of the individual farmer, with the efficiency of the housing of the pigs, with the knowledge possessed by the farmer of the best combination to build up an economic ration, and, of course, with the price of the various things that have to be bought because they cannot be produced on the farm.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is another aspect of this question of the relation of feeding costs to pig production.  There is what is known as the pig cycle.  As far as I understand that rather complicated and controversial phenomenon it seems to be this, that at the time when pig prices are high the cost of pig feeding tends to be relatively low, and the farmers proceed to increase their production. By the time they have increased their output the pig prices come down, and feeding prices go up, so that you have a kind of curve of pig prices which is not related to the curve showing variations in the price of pig feeding by way of parallelism, but rather the curves belly out in opposite directions.  They are concave to one another at one point and come quite close together at another point. Where the margin of gross profit contracts, owing to pig prices falling and pig feed being high, then you have <Col N="269" /> causes operating to diminish the production of pigs.  When you have the opposite situation, when you have a wide margin, owing to the low cost of feed and the high price of pigs, you have a situation in which the farmers try to get back into pigs.  But, farmers operating with only their own instinctive foresight, and without regulation and guidance from persons having wider knowledge and authority, are sure to be at least six months late for the fair every time; they are sure to be getting into pigs when they ought to be getting out of them, and getting out of them when they really ought to be getting into them.</P>
    <P>As I understand the policy underlying this Bill, the industry is to be so controlled that there will be at one time a fund to subsidise the price to farmers when otherwise they might be under a temptation to get out of pigs, unwisely, and at other times the farmers will get perhaps a smaller return for their pigs than the actual prevailing price would appear to justify; from one year to another the price of pigs should be so related to the price of food and other elements in the cost of production that pig production will be maintained and increased.  That is the policy inspiring the Bill.  I hope the Bill will be successful in achieving the results aimed at by that policy, but neither the Minister nor the House can be quite confident that that result will be fully achieved, although we hope that it may be.</P>
    <P>There are many wheels within wheels in this matter and, in trying to cater for the public interest, there are many private interest, to be considered that are, to some extent, in conflict with one another.  It will be no easy matter for the Pig Commission to ensure the prevalence of the national interest in dealing with this complicated question of the pig industry.  I hope the other problem, the problem of some more thorough-going reorganisation of the pig industry in order to ensure the prevalence of the public interest in every department of it, will meet with the study it deserves from the Agricultural Commission, and we should be ready to legislate in that broader sense <Col N="270" /> if and when it becomes necessary to take some more comprehensive measures for the proper establishment and carrying on of this very important national industry.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>As rather wide issues have been entered on during the discussion of this section, perhaps I might be permitted to ask a question. Otherwise, I should have hesitated to consider it relevant.  The question is, whether the Minister is aware that a very large sum of money, something like £250,000, is outstanding at the present time, owing to Irish bacon exporters by the British Ministry of Food and, if he knows that to be the fact, whether he is taking active steps to correct that situation, as it involves a very great hardship, especially in the case of the smaller exporters?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the question asked by Senator MacDermot, that matter happens to be under discussion between my Department and the Department of Food in London at the moment&mdash;they are discussing it with relation to these outstanding amounts.  Undoubtedly, the total amount outstanding represents a very severe strain on a number of the factories.  It is a very large amount, but I think we may hope that there will be an improvement from this onwards when the Ministry of Food are better on their way and able to meet those bills more promptly.  I do not say that the Minister has not the money.  The point is that when the organisation is perfected, he will meet the accounts more promptly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>Will it be a matter of days, of weeks, or of months?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a hope that the whole thing will be cleared away in a matter of days.  With regard to the point raised by Senator Baxter, undoubtedly the ideal way to have this thing arranged would be to have the price of pigs related to the price of foodstuffs; that would make for a permanent solution of our difficulties and for the encouragement of pig production. During the summer, before war <Col N="271" /> appeared on the horizon, we were preparing in the Department a very comprehensive Bill dealing with the whole pig and bacon industry, which would have the effect of rescinding all previous Acts, and we intended to bring in a new measure to replace them.  We meant to bring in what we considered reforms.  That had to be put aside when the war came on, because we had to deal with a situation not contemplated in the Bill.  In the Bill I was anxious to make it legally possible to have a scheme under which the price of pigs would be related to the price of foodstuffs.</P>
      <P>When you come to examine that rather closely you will find there are certain difficulties that, perhaps, at first sight, are not suspected.  First of all, we have no great control over the price of foodstuffs.  We do, it is true, produce a good deal of our own foodstuffs, because many pig producers rear pigs on their own potatoes, grain and skimmed milk.  At the same time, the price of foodstuffs under a scheme like that would have to be decided on what is called a balanced ration.  The balanced ration would be composed of a certain amount of maize, barley, pollard and meat-meal, some mixture such as that, although probably that particular mixture would never be made up, but it is taken as the representative foodstuff.  Whatever the price of that balanced ration is for the time being, the price of pigs is going to be related to it, but, as a good deal of what would form the balanced ration is outside the control of the Government, we cannot foresee what the price of foodstuffs would be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If we commit ourselves to a scheme like that, the price of pigs must necessarily be related to the price of the balanced ration.  I am talking now of a time of peace.  We were dealing with a peace situation when we were drawing up this scheme.  We could proceed, to a certain extent, on the levy and subsidy principle.  We could levy a certain amount on home-consumed bacon and pay out on exported bacon and in that way we could keep a level price and enable the factory to pay a <Col N="272" /> fixed price for pigs and the formula. The price of bacon on the home market might, however, go too high under that scheme.  If we put bacon too high on the home market, the consumption might go down and we would have more for export and, therefore, more to subsidise.</P>
    <P>If you study the scheme carefully, you will have to come to the same conclusion as I did, that you cannot work it unless you have a State guarantee behind it.  If you have a State guarantee it is not so difficult.  You could work it like this, that the price of pigs is to be related to the price of feeding-stuffs, according to a certain formula. We will take what we can for our exported bacon and raise the price of what is consumed here to a certain level, but beyond that we must not allow the bacon on the home market to go.  If we have to meet anything beyond that, it must come out of State funds.  I have been studying this problem for a long time and as closely as I could.  It is impossible to work it unless there is some sort of a State guarantee, so that the State will not let the scheme go down or go wrong. That is, now, for peace times.  I do not say that it should not be done even if the State has to come into it.  I would have been prepared if the war had not taken place to press the Minister for Finance to allow me to bring in a scheme of that kind and give the necessary State guarantee but, now, the war is on.</P>
    <P>Senator Baxter is right when he says that I said it would put the Government and the country in an impossible position if we were to adopt that scheme now and have to export bacon, say, to Great Britain and pay a subsidy on it.  I think it would, whatever we might have differences about such a scheme in peace times.  I think that Senator Johnston, for instance, and other Senators on that side hold very strong free trade views.  Senator Counihan said here on the last occasion that he was a die-hard free trader. Certainly no Senator who holds strong free trade views could agree to such a scheme.  In my opinion, they would have to oppose it and would have to <Col N="273" /> let things take their course, as it were. In the present instance, I think things are more difficult to approach, if you like.  We negotiated with Great Britain for prices for bacon.  Suppose we say to Great Britain, &ldquo;We have adopted a formula; we have to pay a certain price for bacon because the price of feeding stuffs is so high and if you do not give us that price for our bacon we will have to give a subsidy on the export.&rdquo; I think that would leave Great Britain in a very nice position because she will say, &ldquo;That is all right; carry on.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>But I think it is only fair that we should say to the British Government, at the present time anyway: &ldquo;If you do not give us a better price for our bacon, our people will have to go out of production because they cannot afford to go on feeding pigs at that price.  They will not go out of production to such an extent that our own people will be left hungry in Ireland. We are sure to have enough bacon for ourselves.  But we cannot afford to subsidise the production of bacon for British consumers during a time of war.  Therefore, if the price is not improved we will be compelled to say to our people that the price is not, in our opinion, sufficient and if they do not think it is sufficient the only thing is to go out of production.&rdquo;  I think we are driven to that.  I do not know if Senators agree or not.  The only alternative is to bring that scheme in now; we will have to subsidise the export of bacon; we will have to say to the British Government: &ldquo;It is very unfair that we should subsidise the export of bacon at the present time but, even so, under the scheme we must do it and there is no way out of it.  We will have to go on and do it.&rdquo; Personally, I do not think we should do it.</P>
    <P>There is another difficulty, too.  At the present time we are getting the same for our bacon here as the bacon factories are getting in England.  We are getting the same at the port here as they are getting ex-factory in England. That means, of course, that we are getting about as much for our pigs here in the factories.  If things go <Col N="274" /> normally, I mean, if we allow the price of home-consumed bacon to take its course and be ruled by the same conditions as the export bacon, our farmers here will get about the same price for our pigs as the English farmer gets for his pigs.  But the English farmer has a big advantage because he is getting feeding stuffs very much cheaper than our farmers are getting them.  The British Government is buying all the feeding stuffs coming into the country.  They are still selling grain to the maize mills in England at the pre-war price.  The British Government is, I assume, paying about £2 10s. 0d. a ton or £3 0s. 0d. a ton more for maize and is selling it at the August price to the mills.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Minister any evidence for that statement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, yes, absolute evidence.  The British Government is bringing in that maize and other feeding stuffs, and selling it, as I say, at the August price to the mills.  The mills can, of course, turn out their feeding stuffs £2 10/- or £3 cheaper than our mills here.  In that way again if the Food Controller pays the same to British factories for bacon as he pays to our factories here and the factories then in turn are able to get the same price for pigs, the English feeder is getting much better value for his pigs than the Irish feeder for his. It is put to me, why does the Government here not do the same with regard to feeding stuffs?  That would be a subsidy.  It would be a hidden subsidy. It would mean that we would be subsidising our bacon going into England.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot afford it anyway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think we could afford it in any case.  However, although I gave this matter very full consideration during the summer months, before war was declared, in an effort to work out a permanent scheme for peace time, I do not say that since the war started we have been able to examine every aspect of the case.  I am hopeful that when this commission <Col N="275" /> is set up they will be able to give a fair amount of time to the whole pigs and bacon problem.  The two officers who will be on the commission, of course, will carry on in the Department as they have been carrying on but they are dealing with pigs and bacon there and their minds will not be diverted to any great extent to any other problem. When they consider this whole question, if they should make any recommendations for a better basis for the fixing of the price of pigs I would be very glad to consider it and to give my approval if I think it is right.  But I am afraid that for the present, until I get some better suggestion, we must try to fix the price of pigs here on the price of exported bacon.  That is not so at the moment because, on account of the particular position that arose when control was removed in England and on account of the very high jump in the value of live pigs, the Pigs Board here had to put the price of pigs up higher in the factories than could be justified, I should say, on the price of exported bacon.  But we regard that just as a temporary measure.  At least, I hope it will not be necessary to try to meet this present situation for very long. As I said before, when I spoke on Senator Counihan's amendment, if I thought this present situation was going to last longer than the middle of January we would have to meet it in some other way.  We are meeting it, if you like, in a temporary and provisional way because we have been told that it is the intention of the Food Controller in England to bring back control some time about the 8th or 10th January.</P>
      <P>A few other matters arose.  I think that there is prohibition against the export of most feeding stuffs.  I think it is an offence to export feeding stuffs from this country into the Six Counties or anywhere else.  However, I mean to look into the matter further to see if that should be tightened up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I quite agree with Senator O Buachalla that the whole industry will have to be reorganised.  As a matter of fact, I said in the Dáil on two or three occasions, and I think I said it here, <Col N="276" /> that my big object in setting up this commission is not merely, as far as the boards are concerned at present, to carry on the functions, but really to try to make suggestions for a reorganisation, a fundamental reorganisation, of the whole thing because I think I can understand from the speeches made here by all Senators that we all agree that when the war is over we are going to be up against the real crux.  We are going to be up against the old competitors who are very well organised.  There will be a great tussle for the export market&mdash;I do not know whether it will be as good or not&mdash;and unless we are as well organised as our competitors, as Senator O Buachalla said, we will have to go down in the contest.  I am hopeful that with the recommendations already made by the Prices Commission and the Agricultural Commission, this commission, taking all these things into consideration, may be able to make suggestions for a permanent scheme for the reorganisation of our pigs and bacon industry which we will have in operation, if possible, before the war is over so that we will be ready to get what we can out of foreign markets when the war stops.</P>
    <P>I quite agree with Senator O Buachalla that the pig industry is a suitable industry for the Gaeltacht and our poorer areas because they do grow a certain amount of food that is suitable for the pig and, under housing schemes and so on, they have suitable housing.  It is an industry that if they got some little help they might be able to go into much more rapidly than they could go into the production of milk.  If we could help in any way the people in the Gaeltacht and the poorer districts in the country, we would be doing good for the country as well as for these people individually. Senator Johnston raised a point about the cycle of prices.  The whole object of the legislation from 1935 was to get as near as possible to a straight line rather than to have a cycle both with regard to the number of pigs and the prices.  We had hopes that if we could get fairly level prices all through, that would result in having a fairly level number of pigs <Col N="277" /> at all seasons and there would be no violent fluctuation in the number of pigs as between one season and another.  I hope we may be able to improve the position at least for the present and in addition to get a satisfactory permanent scheme within a reasonable time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not complaining that the Minister's statement is not fairly satisfactory but to me it lacks positiveness.  He did say something which, if he put it into operation, would transform the whole position.  He said, indicating the difficulties, that they might go over to the British and say: &ldquo;If you do not give us a better price for our pigs our people will go out of production.&rdquo;  I think that is the kernel of the whole problem.  Those who are in production in the country know that we are up against this kind of situation. The bulk of our home-grown foodstuffs are being used up and we are coming to a thin, lean period. Feeding stuffs cost about £12 10s. per. ton, and the man across the Border will give £14 per ton for what is being sold here for £12 10s. or £13.  It seems to me that a great many farmers are going to find it very difficult to pay 13/- per cwt. for feeding stuffs, when we remember the condition of gambling which exists at the moment on the market.  I believe if we had a definite statement of policy whereby the producers of pigs were guaranteed that the price in future was going to be based on the cost of the feeding stuffs, there would be an assurance, as far as the producer was concerned, that you would get as many pigs as he could give you.  Our aim at the moment is mainly to get increased production. It is awfully difficult, in the insecurity of the present time, to get farmers, quite a number of whom have neither credit nor cash, to go in for increased production.  We may come into a period next year when our production will have fallen appallingly low unless we get the attitude of mind amongst our farmers now that they are prepared to take chances.  The best way to secure that attitude of mind is to ensure that prices are going to be <Col N="278" /> based on the cost of production.  I think that is the fundamental thing.</P>
      <P>I am not going to set my opinion against that of trained economists in this House who tell us that there are other factors to be taken into account. I know there are other factors such as the processing of bacon and the price to be paid for processing, but what we are concerned with is to get more pigs. I think the Government should decide its policy now because unless we keep as many people working on the land as possible unemployment will be increased. It would be much better to tell the British Food Controller here and now that unless he can say that the prices paid for our bacon will ensure that our producers are going to get something in addition to the costs incurred in feeding, there is going to be less production.  Like ourselves the people in England are not very farseeing, and they have been so accustomed to getting their requirements out of the labours of farmers from the ends of the earth, that they may feel secure in the present crisis, but they are not secure.  It would be no harm to bring it home to them that the Irish farmer is not going to do this job unless he knows that he is going to be adequately remunerated.  I do not wish now to enter into a discussion of the policy of compulsory tillage, although it is somewhat related to this subject.  I believe that we should have a plan for pig production as far as the British Food Controller and the consumers over there are concerned.  I think our farmers will have to get guarantees in future in regard to production or you are going to have less, rather than more, production.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not want to talk about the industrialist who is guaranteed a price for the commodity which he manufactures before ever he turns a wheel, but next harvest, if we work, if we have machines, manures and seeds and if God is good to us, we shall probably have a larger harvest than we had this year.  We shall have more food of our own, and possibly we shall have a larger number of pigs for export.  I believe that here and now we should have a guarantee with regard to these exports, <Col N="279" /> and if we are going to be compelled to grow oats, barley or any other crop, the fruits of which have to be marketed in England, we should know now that we are going to be assured of something more than the costs of production.</P>
    <P>The Minister has raised a question in regard to this whole policy which is fundamental and which should be tackled now.  We ought not in my opinion relate the price of pigs, as far as the producer is concerned, to the price which we are to get for bacon and then have the producer in the position which the Minister referred to in the other House when he said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;We may say four months ahead that, if feeding stuffs are £8 a ton, then the dead-weight price would be such a price, but we might find when we reached that period, that the export value of bacon was very much lower.  If anything goes wrong the State must take the risk and must come in to make things right.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I say it is very unfair that the producer should be asked to carry the whole burden of the risk involved in feeding pigs.  I say that, as between the Minister here and the Ministers of the British Government, it is essential to have a long range policy on this matter.  The Minister wants, as we want, to see our farmers secure in their efforts at increased production.  The farmers have passed through so many vicissitudes in recent years that you have to give them some unusual encouragement in order to get from them that production which is essential.  The only way to do that, judging from what I have heard at the Agricultural Commission and in other places, is to guarantee that if they feed pigs and have to buy or produce food to feed them, the price which they are going to get for their pigs will be so related to the cost of production that they will have some little profit left as the fruits of their labour.</P>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy The McGillycuddy">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy</NameTxt>
      <P>Another difficulty arises out of the Minister's statement and also out of what Senator Baxter has stated.  Both the Minister and <Col N="280" /> Senator Johnston said that the country could not afford this subsidy.  Surely you will get back a very large amount of the subsidy, if not the whole of it, in the shape of increased production of pigs which are then exported.  I see no way of increasing the production of pigs other than that suggested by Senator Baxter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>In the scheme as Senator Baxter sees it, suppose we were to get some formula going, and mind you I think that any formula that might be put up at the present time would show that pigs are paying, it would mean that we would probably be taking a levy off the bacon factories at the present time.  Suppose we succeeded in doing so well in the marketing of bacon that we were able to get a levy of 10/- per cwt. or so off the bacon factories, I wonder would the farmers be contented with their lot if they were not getting something out of the profits that were there.  The profits would go into the fund, but I wonder would they be content if we explained to them that the profits were going into the fund to be available in a lean time?  I would like to know if that is the sort of scheme that Senator Baxter has in mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>In the interests of the pig producers of the country, and of the stability of agriculture generally, I have not the slightest hesitation in saying that I believe the Minister's suggestion is far sounder than the proposal in the Bill.  I would much prefer it to going into a period of inflation, to be followed by a lean period in which our people would have nothing to fall back upon.  A situation in which you had inflated prices would mean that consumers of bacon here would have to pay inflated prices for it, and in turn that would lead to demands being made on every section of the community. It would throw our whole economy out of balance.  In my opinion it is only by paying attention to these problems now that we will be able to preserve our stability and economic life which are essential to the maintenance of our whole social structure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="281" />
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy The McGillycuddy">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy</NameTxt>
      <P>To raise the price of home-cured bacon on a population of 1,000,000 adults would simply mean that three-fourths of our people would be paying exactly the same thing as a subsidy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is so.</P>
      <P>Sections 55 to 59, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Schedule and Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Housing (Gaeltacht) (Amendment) Bill, 1939" RHead="( Certified Money Bill )&mdash; Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Public Business. - Housing (Gaeltacht) (Amendment) Bill, 1939  (  Certified Money Bill )&mdash;  Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Cathaoirleach has given permission to the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Lands to attend and be heard on the Housing (Gaeltacht) (Amendment) Bill, and on the motion in the name of Senator Johnston.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOGrady" hpid="Rúnaí Páirliminte don Aire Tailte (Seán Ó Gráda) Rúnaí Páirliminte don Aire Tailte (Seán Ó Gráda)">
      <NameTxt>Rúnaí Páirliminte don Aire Tailte (Seán Ó Gráda)</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá an Bille á thabhairt isteach chun Achtanna na dTithe (Gaeltacht) 1929 agus 1934, do leasú le breis airgid do chur ar fáil. Cuireadh dhá chéad agus caoga míle púnt (£250,000) ar fáil fé'n bhPríomh Acht, sé sin Acht na dTithe (Gaeltacht) 1929, chun tithe comhnaithe sa Ghaeltacht do thógail nó d'fheabhsú, agus chun cróite cearc agus cróite muc do thógail nó d'fheabhsú freisin; agus méaduíodh an suim sin go sé chéad agus caoga míle púnt (£650,000) fé Acht na dTithe (Gaeltacht) (Leasú) 1934.  Tá an suim sin curtha in áirithe agus ionnus go bhféadfaí leanúint leis an obair ní mór breis soláthar do dhéanamh anois.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Tá 2,673 tithe comhnaithe tógtha, agus 2,015 sean tithe feabhsuithe fés na hAchtanna agus tá congnamh ceaduithe chun 1,240 tithe nua eile do thógáil, agus chun 508 sean tithe d'fheabhsú; chomh maith leis sin, tá <Col N="282" /> 4,593 cróite ceare agus 2,927 cróite muc tógtha nó feabhsuithe, agus tá congnamh ceaduithe i gcóir 2,077 cróite cearc agus 1,460 cróite muc eile. Ioctar an congnamh airgid a ceaduítear fés na hAchtanna i dtráth-chodanna, do réir mar theidheann an deonaí chun cinn leis an obair, ach ní íoctar an tráth-chuid-deireannach go dtí go mbíonn an obair ar fad críochnuithe chun sástachta na Roinne.  De ghnáth, tógann sé tuairim is dhá bhliain chun tigh comhnaithe do thógáil sa Ghaeltacht.  Ceapfaí, b'fhéidir, gur tréimhse ró fhada é seo, ach ní mór cuimhneamh go mbíonn ar an deonaí cuid mhaith den obair do dhéanamh, agus nach mór dó, ag an am céadna, aire a thabhairt dá fheirm nó do pé gnó eile a bhíonn ar siubhal aige chun slighe bheatha do bhaint amach.</P>
    <P>Chífear ó'n a bhfuil ráidhte agam go bhfuil cuid mhaith oibre déanta fés na hAchtanna, ach ní mór a thuigsint go bhfuil a lán le déanamh fós. Deineadh an scéal d'iniúchadh tamall ó shoin, agus meastar go bhfuil tuairim is deich míle (10,000) tithe nua eile ag teastáil sa Ghaeltacht agus go bhfuil tuairim is dhá mhíle (2,000) sean tithe ann, go bhfuil feabhsú in easnamh orra. Obair tabhachtach í, ceist na dTithe sa Ghaeltacht do réiteach, agus táim cinnte go n-aontóchaidh gach Seanadóir gur cóir an obair do choimeád ar siubhal agus do chur chun cinn chomh fada agus is féidir é.  Is baolach go mbeidh deachrachtaí ag baint le soláthar na n-abhar tógála go fóill beag, go mór-mór adhmad, toisc an cogadh atá ar siubhal, ach mar sin féin sé mo thuairim láidir agus tuairim an Riaghaltais, nach ceart staona de'n obair an fhaid agus is féidir aon dul chun cinn do dhéanamh.</P>
    <P>Sa Bhille atá á chur os bhúr gcomhair anois, níl dá iarraidh ach céad míle púnt (£100,000) agus meastar gur leór an suim sin chun an obair do choimeád ar siubhal, go ceann dhá bhliain nó b'fhéidir trí bliana, do réir mar a bheidh.  Níl aon athrú á dhéanamh fé'n Bhille ar na coiníollacha ar a dtugtar congnamh fés na hAchtanna, agus mar sin, tairgim go léighfear an Bille seo de'n dara uair.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I suggest-though <Col N="283" /> it may not be in order to do so &mdash;that it is unfortunate that certain subjects should be selected by the Department as those that are always to be dealt with in the Irish language. If it is desired that those who have not got a knowledge of Irish should take an interest in Gaeltacht housing and education, Ministerial utterances should not be uniformly in a language they do not understand.  If it is the policy that there should be a certain number of Ministerial utterances in Irish, I would venture to suggest that they be scattered around amongst the various subjects in a certain proportion rather than that those utterances should be confined to one or two subjects, making them a closed book to those who do not understand Irish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarMacFhionnlach" hpid="Peadar Mac Fhionnlaoich Peadar Mac Fhionnlaoich">
      <NameTxt>Peadar Mac Fhionnlaoich</NameTxt>
      <P>Os rud é go mbaineann an Bille seo leis an nGaeltacht agus leis an nGaedhilg, tá sé nádúrach agus ceart go rithfear i nGaedhilg é.  Tá súil agam&mdash;agus ní uathbhásach an nós é&mdash;go gcuirfear gach rud annseo ins an Seanaid i nGaedhilg.  Nílimíd ábalta é sin do dhéanamh go fóill, ach tig leis an Seanadóir Mac Diarmada agus leis an Seanadóir MacSheoin dul ar ais ar scoil ar feadh tamaill, go dtí go dtigfidh leo labhairt annseo i nGaedhilg. San dteanga san, is ceart Bille Tighthe na Gaeltachta rith.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mícheál O hAodha Mícheál O hAodha">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál O hAodha</NameTxt>
      <P>Is Dóigh liom go bhfuil nós déanta ag Rúnaí an Aire labhairt i nGaedhilg annseo faoi chúrsaí áirithe.  Ní fheadar an é sin an slighe is fearr chun an Gaedhilg do chur chun chinn.  Nuair bhí an Rúnaí Pairliminte ag tabhairt an Bhille seo isteach, do léigh sé amach ó'n bpáipéar; ní fheadar an é sin an rud is fearr do dhéanamh chun an Ghaedhilg do chur i bhfeidhm.  Is dóigh liom-sa chó fada agus nach dtuigeann na Seanadóirí nach bhfuil Gaedhilg aca, cad tá sa mBille seo, gur ceart seans do thabhairt dóibh an Béarla do labhairt, fiú amháin san scéim seo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Meadair le cainnt an tSeanadóra MacFhionnlaoich, ni fheadar an ceart <Col N="284" /> limistéar speisialta do dhéanamh de'n Ghaeltacht, agus gan ach Gaedhilg do labhairt mar gheall air.  Ba cheart go dtuigimís go léir cad tá ar siubhal mar gheall ar an nGaeltacht, óir táimíd go léir ag díoladh na gcáineacha.  Ba mhaith liom a rá leis an Rúnaí nár cheart rudaí do thabhairt isteach annseo agus gan focal Béarla do labhairt fútha, i dtreo is go mbeidh rudaí déanta ag na Seanadóirí nach dtuigeann siad rud ar bith díobh.</P>
    <P>This idea of making a reservation of the Gaeltacht and talking Irish on certain subjects seems to me merely to be putting up a kind of linguistic defence and make-believe which is not accomplishing anything.  I am in favour of the speaking of Irish on a great many occasions but think it is entirely wrong to pick education as one of those topics, as parents are entitled to know what is happening.  Similarly, in the case of Gaeltacht housing it would not be any harm for people who do not know Irish to hear what is happening. Until Irish is made obligatory for entry into the Seanad or entry into the Government&mdash;which, by the way, it is not; one can become a parliamentary secretary without knowing any Irish&mdash;it would be no harm to let people know the facts as to what is happening with regard to education and taxation.  In the other House the practice is followed of having an elaborate speech in Irish in the beginning of the debate and of having the Minister conclude in English, for what reason I will not say at the moment, but it is not very far to seek.  While I sympathise with the use of Irish, it is not fair to use it as a defensive screen, as sometimes happens.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOGrady" hpid="Seán Ó Gráda Seán Ó Gráda">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Gráda</NameTxt>
      <P>Ma's maith libh go ndéanfainn cainnt i mBéarla, b'fhéidir gur fearra dom cúpla rud do rá i mBéarla.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarMacFhionnlach" hpid="Peadar MacFhionnlaoich Peadar MacFhionnlaoich">
      <NameTxt>Peadar MacFhionnlaoich</NameTxt>
      <P>Ná déan é.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Micheál Ó hAodha Micheál Ó hAodha">
      <NameTxt>Micheál Ó hAodha</NameTxt>
      <P>Déan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOGrady" hpid="Seán Ó Gráda Seán Ó Gráda">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Gráda</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní dubhairt aon Seanadóir do labhairt i nGaedhilg, ní dubhairt sé aon nidh mar gheall ar an <Col N="285" /> mBille seo gidh go raibh a lán le rá aca faoi cheist na Gaedhilge.  Ba mhaith liom a rá go bhfuil gach aon nidh maidir leis na tighthe san nGaeltacht á dhéanamh tríd an Ghaedhilg amháin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Micheál Ó hAodha Micheál Ó hAodha">
      <NameTxt>Micheál Ó hAodha</NameTxt>
      <P>Is maith an rud é sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOGrady" hpid="Seán Ó Gráda Seán Ó Gráda">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Gráda</NameTxt>
      <P>Nuair do bhí na Seanadóirí ag labhairt i nGaedhilg, ní dóigh liom go ndubhairt siad aon nídh ag baint leis an nGaeltacht ach bhí siad ag cainnt faoi cheisteanna eile.</P>
      <P>For those who have not understood what I said, perhaps I had better explain that this Bill is introduced for the purpose of making available a further sum of £100,000.  It is considered sufficient to carry us over another year or two.  I do not think that anybody in the House or outside it will object to granting that money. It is doing very useful work for the people in the Gaeltacht who are amongst the poorest in the country.</P>
      <P>With regard to the question of introducing measures in Irish, I should like to inform the House that everything pertaining to Gaeltacht housing, and Gaeltacht services generally, is done through the medium of Irish. That policy is being enforced, particularly in that Department.  That it is not being done in other Departments is due to the fact referred to by Senator Hayes&mdash;that public servants are in the same position as members of the Oireachtas inasmuch as they do not all understand Irish sufficiently to carry on the business through the medium of that language.  If there is one Department which should transact its business through Irish, it is Gaeltacht services and, so far as possible, that is being done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarMacFhionnlach" hpid="Peadar MacFhionnlaoich Peadar MacFhionnlaoich">
      <NameTxt>Peadar MacFhionnlaoich</NameTxt>
      <P>Abair é.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOGrady" hpid="Seán Ó Gráda Seán Ó Gráda">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Gráda</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl a thuille agam lé rá.  Is dócha go bhfuil gach Seanadóir ar thaoibh an Bhille.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining stages now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="286" /> Bill put through Committee, without amendment, recéived for final consideration and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Irish Currency" RHead="and Sterling&mdash;Motion">
    <Title>Public Business. - Irish Currency and Sterling&mdash;Motion.</Title>
    <P>The following motion stood on the Order Paper:&mdash;</P>
    <P>That Seanad Eireann would welcome a statement of policy by the Government regarding the Irish currency and its connection with sterling.&mdash;Senators MacDermot and Tierney.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say that I am postponing the introduction of the motion standing in my name and in that of Senator Tierney in order to accommodate the Minister for Finance and not because of any unwillingness to deal with the matter forthwith so far as we are concerned.  In the circumstance I understand it will not be taken until the Seanad meets again after the Christmas recess.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Mount Street Club and" RHead="Agricultural Production&mdash;Motion">
    <Title>Public Business. - Mount Street Club and Agricultural Production&mdash;Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That in view of the importance of increasing agricultural production and alleviating the condition of the unemployed, Seanad Eireann is of opinion that, suitable estates in the possession of the Land Commission, which it is not practicable to divide at present, should be offered to the Mount Street Club, on favourable conditions as to rent and equipment, for cultivation and management on the same lines as its Clondalkin farm.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wish to bring before the House for sympathetic consideration some knowledge of the experiment in social organisation that has been made during the last five years by a body known as the Mount Street Club.  I should say at the beginning that, personally, I have no direct connection with the Mount Street Club.  I have only had the same intelligent and sympathetic interest in this problem that other citizens have, probably, taken.  So far <Col N="287" /> as the present motion is concerned, the circumstances which led me to bring it forward are as follows: It was suggested to me that those of us who sit on this side of the House, and who are usually found in opposition to Government policy, should not maintain a merely negative attitude to any proposals for dealing with the more acute economic problems that agitate the State, so I began to cast round to see if there was anything whatever that has to do with unemployment and unemployment relief, that I could wholeheartedly recommend, and that I could advise the Government to be prepared to spend State funds on, or to use State credit to support. It occurred to me that possibly the Mount Street Club organisation was something of that kind, as it had been doing something to alleviate the condition of the unemployed, and it was spoken of as being highly successful, and had recently gone further and extended its activities by taking over and running quite a large farm at Clondalkin.  It is running this farm on the most modern and approved fashion, and producing food for the consumption of its own members, both on the farm and in the Mount Street Club workshops.  I then proceeded to interview one of the directors of that institution.</P>
    <P>I should explain that although the Mount Street Club came into existence as a result of the philanthropic exertions of a number of public-spirited citizens, it is essentially a self-governing organisation, so far as internal discipline is concerned.  The function of the directors is to maintain contact between the Mount Street Club and the outside world.  It was through the generosity of the outside world that it acquired the means which enabled it to start workshops in Mount Street, and later raised £3,600 of hard money which was paid for the farm that it is now running so successfully at Clondalkin. The directors then represent, so to speak, the element of philanthropy in relation to the club, but the club itself is organised on a democratic self-governing principle, both on the farm and in the workshops.  That is to say, as far as internal organisation is concerned, <Col N="288" /> every possible concession is made to democracy.  So far as responsibility for the technical efficiency of the work done is concerned, the directors, of course, are in a position to ensure that the person responsible for organising work in Mount Street Club is a thoroughly competent and efficient person, and also that the farm steward and his wife, who are, so to speak, the central pivots of the organisation at Clondalkin, are thoroughly reliable and competent persons.</P>
    <P>One of the difficulties that confront the State in attempting to deal with unemployment is that if the State finances and organises the work of the unemployed, in order to produce ordinary consumers' goods for sale in the open market, the State would be competing in a way that would be quite unfair to existing institutions that employ people in the ordinary way, and produce the same kind of goods. That would give rise to a sense of unfairness on the part of those affected and, I think, quite legitimately, so that in practice the State finds itself unable to create work artificially of the kind that produces consumers' goods and ordinary necessities of life for circulation through the ordinary channels of commerce.  That drives the State back to the necessity of employing by way of relief work, labour on the production of so called capital goods, that is, works of construction like drainage schemes, housing, sewage schemes and things of that kind.</P>
    <P>Capital goods, of course, have their use, but the objection from the economic point of view to devoting too much effort, especially in a time of international war, to the production of capital goods, is that money spent on employment (for those who are unemployed), and on public works of that kind, is going to increase the monetary demand for consumers' goods here and now.  Capital goods in process of construction will make no appreciable contribution to the volume of consumable services for any period we have to concern ourselves about in a time of national emergency.  While it is desirable, from the economic point of view, that the unemployed should be increasing the production of consumers' goods by the same measure as they are likely <Col N="289" /> to increase their own consumption of consumers' goods, when you are concerned with public works of construction character, you have a situation in which the persons employed on such works are going to increase their consumption of consumers' goods, but what they are producing will make no appreciable contribution to the volume of consumable services available in the immediate future.  That process, even if the money necessary for financing public works is acquired by way of public loan or from private investors, is likely to alter the pattern of consumption in the community as a whole in such a way as to raise prices, especially of the necessities of life.</P>
    <P>We have in this country the phenomenon of unemployment, in the cities especially, and also in the country, and we have the other phenomenon of under employment in the agricultural community and the inadequate use of land, or land not being properly cultivated or adequately used to fill the stomachs of the unemployed in the towns.</P>
    <P>That phenomenon is one about which people are liable to get very cross and I have had occasion to refer to it from other points of view in criticising other policies.  But the fact remains that that is a paradox and a challenge to thought.  I agree with the view that the commercial exchange between country and town, between the surplus produce of the countryman's labour and the surplus produce of the townsman's economic activity is the taproot of commerce and that it is in the best interests of public policy that fertile exchanges between country and town should increase and multiply.  I believe that it has been the intention of Government policy in the last seven years that a desirable exchange between country and town should be fostered and developed in every way.  But the sad fact remains that the intentions of the Government have not been carried out and the facts of the case are very different from what the Government contemplated or desired when it set out to develop, especially, commerce between town and country.</P>
    <P>One aspect of this commerce is the value of agricultural produce which is <Col N="290" /> consumed by the so-called non-agricultural community or if you like, by the townsman, and the other the value of the urban produce which is consumed by the agricultural producers.  In 1929-1930 the value of Irish farm produce consumed by the non-agricultural community was £13,400,000.  In 1936-1937 that value had only increased by a beggarly £1,000,000.  In other words the effort to develop increased consumption of agricultural produce by townsmen had been a comparative failure.</P>
    <P>On the other side again, to what extent has the farming community been able to increase its consumption of the produce of urban industry?  According to my calculations in 1929, the farming community had £44,000,000 available for expenditure on industrial goods&mdash;either of Irish or foreign manufacture&mdash;at all events industrial goods.  In 1933 it had available £21,000,000; in 1936 the amount available was £31,000,000, and in 1938 the figure was £33,000,000 So that the farmer on his side had less money to spend on industrial products of any kind in 1938 than he had ten years previously.  We may assume that that desirable side of the exchange had not developed in the way that was contemplated and desired. The real cause as I think of this failure of the development of that desirable commerce is the fact that there is what one might call a disparity in terms of trade between the labour of the countrymen and the labour of the townsmen.  That disparity will be seen if you bear in mind that we have 1,200,000 persons gainfully occupied in this State.  Of these one-half are gainfully occupied in agriculture and the other half are gainfully occupied in other economic activities.  It is true that the average income per head of the persons occupied in agriculture is only £70 in money or money's worth, and that the average income per head of the other 600,000 persons gainfully occupied in commerce, etc., averages £170 per head per annum.  So we have a situation in which the countryman's two-and-a-half hours' work is exchanged for the produce of one hour's work of the townsman.  That being so, the countryman has to accept the products of eight or ten hours' work for <Col N="291" /> the proportionate amount of urban produce of three or four hours' work by the urban worker.  Then we have the situation that the townsman is able to purchase with the produce of three or four hours' work the produce of the countryman's eight or ten hours' work. In fact, we have had a situation in which the urban section of the community has been steadily expanding production for the enjoyment of the urban section of the community only. But the consumption does not circulate downwards, because by reason of the lesser value of the countryman's produce he is not able to absorb an adequate share of the produce of the townsman's labour.</P>
    <P>This is only an introduction but it does provide some explanation of what I might call the social and economic backgrounds of this problem with which the Mount Street Institution is an effort to deal.  To my mind if the average income per head of the countrymen was somewhat higher and the average income per head of the townsmen was somewhat lower we probably would have a greater volume of exchange between country and town and we might have a smaller volume of urban unemployed.  The principle on which the Mount Street Club is worked is to exchange the produce of one hour's work whether in the country, farm or in town work, for the produce of one hour's work.  They have no trouble in finding a satisfactory outlet in the way of consumption for every article which their organisation has enabled them to produce.  I come now to some brief account of the history and philosophy of the club as set out in the pamphlets explaining its aims, objects and plans.  I would like to have an opportunity of having some of these plans on the records of the House.  I am sure the House will have patience if I read a few extracts from these. Here is a special extract from the <i>Irish Press</i> of the 16th January, 1939. It begins:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The Mount Street Club is one of those institutions which, born of the vision and initiative of one or two men, cast roots so deeply and so swiftly into the soil that, almost <Col N="292" /> from the moment of birth, their permanence seems assured.  Although it is no more than four years in existence, it has already begun to attract nation-wide attention.  Statesmen and social reformers have given it their blessing; men of all classes and creeds are associated with it.  Its main object is&mdash;we quote the club's own official description&mdash;&ldquo;to supplement the assistance given by the State by providing opportunities for members to preserve their morals and their mental and physical fitness during periods of idleness, and to enable young men who have never had work to build themselves up into useful citizens.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The State has done and will continue to do its part.  But the Mount Street Club is setting out to do things which even the State cannot do.  It is not only helping to provide work for the workless but it is giving new hope, new strength, and a tougher moral fibre to those whom it enrols as members.  The whole atmosphere of the club is one that is inimical to &ldquo;lead-swinging and to the work-shy mentality&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>A similar article in praise of the club and a description of its philosophy appeared in the <i>Irish Times</i> of the 18th January, 1939.  It says:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The victim of unemployment&mdash;let him be plasterer, mechanic, barber, musician, tailor, electrician, plumber, gardener, cook, carpenter or just general labourer can become a member. He works with the club according to his ability, and partakes of its benefits according to the measure of his labour.  No money passes from the club to its members or from members to the club.  Instead every man receives payment for his labour in the form of tallies, and with these &lsquo;tallies&rsquo; he can purchase the products of other members' toil.  The system in fact, is one of simple exchange.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The club was founded in November, 1934, at 81 Lower Mount Street, Dublin, is non-political, non-sectarian, and non-residential.  As I have already explained, its internal control is by a democratically elected committee, and the so called directors represent the <Col N="293" /> element of external guidance and philanthropy. One of the fundamental principles is that you will get nothing for nothing in the Mount Street Club. Everything obtainable in that organisation must be paid for; it can be paid for only with tallies, and tallies are obtainable only as a result of work done for the club.  Another fundamental principle of the organisation is that none of the final products of the club's workshops and farm may be sold through the ordinary channels of commerce outside the club in any shape or form.  Now, the object of that self-denying ordinance is to prevent jealousy and the sense of injustice that would arise from outside interests that might feel themselves injured if the labour of the club was being used to project commodities on to the open market in competition with trade union labour there, and so on.  To avoid that real danger the club submits itself to the self-denying regulation by which none of its products may be sold outside.  In other words, all that it produces is for sale to and for consumption by its members, and its members alone.</P>
    <P>In my view, so long as that principle is maintained, the club must be, to some extent, a dependent organisation, dependent either on private charity or on some kind of support from outside&mdash; public help of some kind&mdash;because clearly there are certain things which the club must buy from outside: machinery and equipment of various kinds for its workshops and farm.  If the club is debarred from selling in the outside world, it must acquire means of buying the things it needs by a process which involves some degree of charity somewhere.  That, perhaps, may raise problems, but problems with which, at any rate, we are not concerned at the moment.  At the moment the essential thing, from the point of view of the club's members, is that, whereas the State gives them unemployment money amounting to, I suppose, about 10/- per week in the case of a single unemployed man, with other allowances for dependents, they are able by their organisation and by their mutual co-operation to produce for consumption by one another at least three or four times the amount of real <Col N="294" /> value represented by that unemployment money.  Every 10/- that comes into the pocket of a club member by way of subsidy from the State is multiplied by at least three or four in terms of real advantage to the individual member and to his organisation.  That is done in a way that can give rise to no legitimate offence on the part of any outside interests, because none of the ordinary currency that reaches the pockets of club members may be spent on products of the club's workshops. Every penny that they get in the way of legal tender money or its equivalent is spent in the ordinary way in shops outside, just like your money and mine.  Consequently, there is no real ground for any jealousy on the part of outside interests.</P>
    <P>The idea of associating a farm with their other activities came to the club late last year, because they had already had experience of the ability with which their members, in spite of their being men with a purely urban outlook and urban industrial training, had successfully tackled the problem of working allotment gardens.  They had made a wilderness out at Merrion, which many of you have seen from the train as you go past&mdash;a wilderness which is also a marsh&mdash;blossom like the rose, so to speak, and produce quantities of fresh vegetables which those members sold for tallies through the club's workshop and which enriched the tables of their fellow-members. There was, therefore, already a fertile association between the products of the land and industry, and it seemed to them that it would be only following in the same direction in which they had already made a successful advance if they went further and acquired a real farm of their own. Therefore, early this year they bought Larkfield, Clondalkin, a farm of 130 acres, for which they paid, I think, £3,600; quite a substantial sum of money which they acquired by their success in whipping up subscriptions from persons interested in the welfare of the club.</P>
    <P>At present, the club has some 300 members, but that membership is not what you might call a stagnant total. It is what the statistician calls a <Col N="295" /> renewable total, just like the total membership of this Seanad which is occasionally varied in its individual composition by the chances and changes of human life.  In other words, although the actual membership at the moment is only 300, far more than 300 ex-members have appreciated the benefits of the club, because many persons have passed through that club and, by improving their efficiency for work and their general industrial character, were able to get real permanent jobs elsewhere. The Mount Street Club proudly claims that their ex-members, when they get a job, keep that job.  In other words, when you become employed in the ordinary way outside you cease to be qualified to be a member of the club. Therefore, at any given moment, the club consists only of unemployed men who are members.  But there are also hundreds of ex-members of the club who are now in permanent employment and who have reason to rise up and call the club blessed.  Its 300 members are, all of them, I suppose, townsmen&mdash;Dubliners.  Many of them work, not necessarily 48 hours per week, but, at all events, a few hours every week, as often or as long as they can, at whatever work they find themselves able to do in connection with the club's workshops in Lower Mount Street.</P>
    <P>But the farm has greatly expanded the outlet for their surplus energy.  I visited the farm about five weeks ago and there were 37 workers in constant employment there, living and sleeping on the premises, and having the time of their life both in industrious exertions during the day and in the games and recreation which they enjoyed in the evening.  I am told that it was most interesting to observe the reaction of these townsmen when they came out there to work.  They had voracious appetites, God help them, and they certainly enjoyed themselves for the first day or two.  But they soon settled down to the new routine; they proved most adaptable and were able to make a thorough success of their job as agricultural labourers.  That alone, I think, is one of the greatest <Col N="296" /> achievements of the club&mdash;to have disproved what was almost regarded as an axiom, that once an agricultural labourer became a townsman he was lost for ever and ever to rural occupation, and could never become a successful agricultural worker again.  The Mount Street Club has proved that it is possible to reverse the trend to the urban cesspool and to bring back labour from the city to the country. That labour, in spite of, or because of, its urban tradition and outlook, is able to make good in the work of properly conducting a large-scale agricultural undertaking.  I should mention that, to comply with the regulations regarding the drawing of unemployment money at urban rates, persons actively occupied in Larkfield have to return periodically to the bosom of their families, so to speak, in Dublin.  They are treated as merely being on a temporary visit&mdash;in fact they <i>are</i> merely on a temporary visit&mdash;to Clondalkin. In other words, they come in relays to work on that farm.  There are only 30 or 40 of them, but the personnel would be quite different if you went out there to-day and in three months' time.  The fact that the organisation has been able, with that continual renewal of staff, to get satisfactory results is a great tribute to its efficiency, because they have had the trouble of training new people and, in many cases, people who were unacquainted with work in that environment.</P>
    <P>The Clondalkin farm specialises in the production of vegetables&mdash;potatoes &mdash;and milk for home consumption.  To a certain extent, they produce eggs and pigs.  They are not yet in a position to produce as much butter as the members and their families would be able to consume or to undertake the production of beef or the rearing up and breeding of young heifers which would, eventually, become cows.  They hope to have, eventually, 30 or 40 cows.  At the moment, they have about 13.  Although their activities are very creditable and have attained to considerable development in the short time in which they have been employed, there is considerable room for expansion at Clondalkin and for expansion in other directions in other parts of the country as well. They have a tractor with which they <Col N="297" /> plough.  I am told that, with that tractor, they could plough considerably more land than they have available for ploughing on that 130-acre farm.  It would be a real economy for them if they could get hold of another large, undivided farm, not too far from Dublin, where they might use their tractor to do additional ploughing and where they might house other workers who might like to escape for a few weeks at a time from the somewhat dismal air of a Dublin slum.</P>
    <P>When I visited the farm, one of the first persons I met was the dairy-man or dairy-boy who, six months ago, was a messenger in the city and became unemployed in that capacity.  After joining the Mount Street Club, he became one of their specialists in looking after cows, having never had anything to do with cows before.  As I have said, he is now by way of becoming an expert in dealing with the milk in the dairy, keeping the vessels clean and sterilised and doing other highly technical and responsible work.  He is only one of several persons who have found specialised occupations which they are carrying out and carrying out successfully there.  One of the recommendations of a large-scale farming organisation in contrast with a small farm is that in a large-scale farming organisation there are so many specialised occupations possible that you can find an outlet for almost any kind of talent. The kind of person who would be utterly useless on a small farm finds useful work to do because he can be fitted into the right niche for his peculiar talent in a large-scale organisation such as that at Clondalkin.  One of the most useful members of the society out there is a former accountant whose health is now such that he is unable to do any physical work whatever.  His skill in secretarial work makes him very useful in that organisation and he is regarded as one of the most valuable members of the community at Clondalkin.  You can find occupation on the land in agricultural production by a large-scale organisation for almost any kind of specialised talent whereas, if you consider only the method of the small farm, you require an almost impossible combination of <Col N="298" /> talents in the same man and in his wife if you are to have the human conditions of success.</P>
    <P>The workers employed at Clondalkin in rotation obtain a tally for every hour they work.  They work 48 hours a week, or more if agricultural necessities are such that they should over-exert themselves for the time being.  About half the tallies they earn are paid back to the club in consideration of the housing and keep they receive in Larkfield. The other tallies can be disposed of by the members as they wish.  They can use them personally for buying products of the club's workshop or, as many of them do, they can send these tallies to their dependent family-members living in Dublin.  They, with these tallies, can buy milk or vegetables or other produce from the farm which is available for sale at the club workshop in Mount Street.  Actually, the number of tallies earned every week is now about 5,000 and they anticipate about 300,000 in the year.  Of these 5,000 earned every week, about 2,000 are earned on the farm and about 3,000 in the workshop.  A tally is a ticket which a member gets in return for an hour's work.  It is supposed to buy the produce of an hour's labour, as well as that can be estimated.  An effort is made to equate, as far as possible, the purchasing power of a tally to the purchasing power of a shilling and, let us hope that, in time, as the organisation becomes more efficient the tally will increase in purchasing power and buy as much as a shilling will buy outside.  At the moment, it is not claimed that it will buy more than about 8d. worth outside. However, with it they manage very well.  Their economy by means of this tally system is, so to speak, insulated from the rest of the national economy and they produce and circulate for consumption for themselves alone additional consumers' goods which could not be produced and, certainly, could not be consumed if it were not for this organisation which they have built up.  I think I may claim that the existence of this club has considerably expanded that desirable commerce between country and town which it has been the object of Government policy to promote and which, as I have shown, could not be promoted through the <Col N="299" /> operation of the ordinary economic system during the past seven years.</P>
    <P>If you take the tally as being worth 1/-, the total turnover of the Mount Street Club Organisation will amount to some 300,000 tallies, or about £15,000, and a substantial part of that turnover represents agricultural output and trade, so to speak, between country and town.  They have shown a way in which we can expand desirable consumption and exchange between country and town, and I think it is a way that they should be encouraged to follow and even develop with the blessing and help of the nation.</P>
    <P>A tally is issued in exchange for an hour's work, and when that tally is then exchanged for an article produced by the club, it is said to be &ldquo;redeemed&rdquo;, and the tally itself is taken back and cancelled, and that is the end of that tally.  Sometimes, however, tallies accumulate unspent.  Tallies have to be given out for every kind of work which is done and, of course, most of the work done is directed especially towards creating consumable goods, things which satisfy the needs of members here and now, but a certain proportion of tallies must necessarily be devoted to the payment for such services as plumbing, for example, which do not produce directly measurable quantities of consumable goods which can be availed of here and now.  So, in one way or another, it is liable to happen that at times there may be in circulation a rather uncomfortably large number of unredeemed tallies.  They do not mind anything up to 5,000 or 6,000 tallies being out at any given moment, but if the number of tallies in circulation and unredeemed should rise to, say, 15,000 or 20,000, then the problem of maintaining the purchasing power of these tallies would begin to arise.</P>
    <P>Now, if they are faced with the problem of maintaining or increasing the purchasing power of their members, they would never dream of issuing more tallies to add to the number already in circulation and unredeemed; they would at once see, as you will see, that it would be a fantastic idea to think that you could increase the purchasing <Col N="300" /> power of their tallies by adding to the number of tallies in circulation.  No; what they do in that case is that they send around a whip to their generous supporters and ex-members, and they get in an additional supply of old boots, old clothes, and this or that, or they get up a concert which people have to pay to attend, and in one way or another they create additional wealth on which these tallies may be spent.  In that way, they teach us a lesson, which is the most fundamental lesson of the whole business of money, and that is, that the only way in which the purchasing power of money can be increased is by an increase in the things which money purchases.</P>
    <P>Now, another reason why I should like to see a development of this farming experiment which the Mount Street Club have made is that large-scale farming, properly organised and properly equipped, is, in the nature of the case, more productive for the individual and for the nation than small-scale farming is or could be.  The average income of our 600,000 agricultural producers is £70 per annum, but that average is an average of wide disparities.  It is quite certain that on many small farms, especially in the poorer parts of the country, the average income per producer on that farm is far less than £70 per annum. I think it is quite certain also that the average income per producer on the 50,000 farms which employ 120,000 wage-paid labourers must be well above £70 per person per annum, for the minimum wage is £70 per person per annum, and if a farmer was making an output only equal to the minimum wage he must pay, that farmer, <i>ex hypothesi</i>, would be bankrupt.  So I think we may assume that the output per man on a large farm is likely to be in the region of £100 per person per year and could be made greater by the application of modern methods of agricultural economy and technique. I think we should favour the intensive colonisation of large farms and run them as single economic units, in the way in which the Mount Street Club has shown how to do&mdash;at all events during the war emergency&mdash;rather than commit ourselves finally, and for <Col N="301" /> all time, to the method of cutting up large estates for division into small holdings.</P>
    <P>One of the advantages of the large organisation, as I have pointed out already, is that you find outlets and uses for a variety of talents in a large organisation which would be quite useless on the land in the case of a small farm.  In Clondalkin, as I have pointed out, they have a specialised man for the dairying, and they also have a man who specialises in looking after the fowl, and I happen to know that looking after fowl properly is a job that requires a good deal of knowledge and experience and which requires all the intelligence and skill that anybody might find himself blessed with. There is also a man there whose special function is looking after the pigs.</P>
    <P>As I have already stated, I think it is a matter for much satisfaction that these ex-urban workers have been able to make good so well in this experiment in Clondalkin, and I think they could only make good in the kind of organisation which the Clondalkin farm represents.  You could not take the average urban worker, plant him down on the average small 20-acre farm, and expect that the results would be satisfactory in nine cases out of ten.  In the case of the larger organisation, if you have the right pivotal man at the head of administration, and if you have the right woman at the head looking after the domestic amenities, then I think you have the means by which success may be expected.</P>
    <P>Of course, if the club is offered the use of a large farm, now in possession of the Ministry of Lands, which for one reason or another it is not expected to be able to divide among claimants for land during the present emergency, we would have to take into account the legitimate interests and claims of the local landless men who may have looked forward to a division of such land at some time or another.  In one way or another the interests of ex-urban labourers and local landless labourers would have to be coordinated and amalgamated.  I think that you can have employed a greater <Col N="302" /> number of men for every 100 acres on a large, properly equipped and properly organised farm like Clondalkin than you could have if that farm were cut up into five or ten small 20-acre farms.  If that be so, there ought to be in the organisation, if it extends itself to farms now in possession of the Land Commission in other parts of the country, room for the ex-urban labourer and room also for the local landless men who are willing to join and form part of this local agricultural, co-operative, farming society.  It would be desirable that the matter should be approached in a truly national spirit, in which no jealousy between rural and urban workers should be allowed to stand in the way of doing something which is possibly going to be very advantageous to the nation as a whole.</P>
    <P>Already, the Mount Street Club has shown the possibility of fertile exchange between their agriculture adventure and their town workshops, but, as time goes on, and if this Clondalkin experiment is a success, and gives rise to other similar successful experiments, with the help of the Land Commission and the State, I can foresee a time when the urban industry, now carried on by the people working in the Mount Street workshops, might be transferred, bag and baggage, to the actual village or neighbourhood where the appropriate farm colony was established, and in that case you might have, around a 200-acre or a 300-acre farm, a cluster of cottages and, if you like, urban workshops working on their specialised urban pursuits and exchanging their products with the large scale farm carried on almost under their very eyes.</P>
    <P>In that way, you would have all the essentials of trade between country and town, but taking place under the much healthier conditions of life which you would have in one of those lovely ex-Ascendancy-owned park farms out in County Meath, County Dublin or County Kildare.  I think that in that way you would have the conditions in which there might grow up a new kind of Irish national civilisation which would be both new and old, because I suspect that our modern society is in some ways more isolated and less sociable than the old Irish society of, <Col N="303" /> say, 1,000 years ago.  The Irish of those days were very sociable and they did a lot of things together, work as well as amusements, and I think it is desirable that some of the isolation which is part and parcel of the small farmer mentality should, at all events, be qualified, and if we could have dotted here and there throughout the country farm colonies of this kind, we would bring a desirable element of variety, sociableness and understanding of both the urban and rural point of view into different parts of the country.</P>
    <P>This farm at Clondalkin is carrying on agriculture in a modern way, using the most modern and up-to-date machinery they can possibly acquire by gift or purchase.  They have, as I say, a tractor and they could get more good of that tractor, if they had more land to plough with it.  They also have a silo tower, made to their own specification, on a plan which Major Waller, one of the directors of the club, has devised and which has proved to be a great success.  This use of grass silage for winter feeding is one of the things which is going to make all the difference to the success of our agriculture, if it can be sufficiently extended, because it will help to solve the problem of maintaining a uniform output all the year round and help to diminish the burden of the purchase of foodstuffs from outside. In this matter of making more efficient use of grass for winter feeding, the Clondalkin farm is among the pioneers of Irish agriculture.  That silo tower they made with their own labour, but they are also in a position to hire machinery, so to speak, for making similar towers in the country round about, and to a certain extent I believe they have acquired profit for themselves as a club by such use of their machinery for making that particular type of silo tower which is now coming into fashion.</P>
    <P>If my vision of the future is ever realised, I can see, in every one of the eastern counties and in many of the midland counties, at least one or two large-scale 500-acre farms intensively cultivated by 20, 30, 40 or 50 agricultural workers of various types of talent and capacity and equipped with the <Col N="304" /> most modern machinery of every kind. I can foresee a time when, associated with these local farm societies, will be local agricultural labour, working on that farm occasionally, but, at other times perhaps, working with flying squads of labourers temporarily hired out by the co-operative farm to other large private farmers in the neighbourhood who may require the services of properly equipped labour at a busy time.  I think it would greatly simplify the problem of getting the right kind of labour at the right time, if individual farmers could count on being able to hire the services of a squad of labourers equipped with tractor and plough, with mowing machine and reaper and binder, and with this and that, at times of the year when, for one reason or another, they might require additional service.  In that way, I think you would greatly improve the organisation of the available personnel, both those who are fellow-members of the functioning agricultural colonies and the other labourers who might maintain a kind of associationship relation with such colonies in their neighbourhood.</P>
    <P>I understand that so far as the club themselves are concerned, they are perfectly willing to expand their experiments. They are satisfied that the Clondalkin farm has in it all the conditions of success, and they can lay their hands on the right people to fill the key positions in any new experiment that might be made on the lines of their Clondalkin farm.  They will have no trouble whatever in getting hold of the right people in whom they can have confidence to fill those key positions, and the only thing that holds them back from rapid development is, simply and solely, the want of money. I suggest it would be well for the Government to consider whether they could not make a grant outright of some £10,000, absolutely free of conditions, except that it was to be used on the general lines of the policy of which the Clondalkin farm is an example, and that they should be prepared to consider further a guaranteed loan of as much as £100,000 to finance further developments of this Clondalkin experiment. The main thing required from the Land Commission, however, <Col N="305" /> is that they should make available to the Mount Street Club, if and in so far as it wants them, or is able to make use of them, such undivided farms now in its occupation as that Mount Street Club feels itself to be in a position to make effective use of during the present period of European emergency.</P>
    <P>I am not authorised to speak in detail about this matter.  It may be that the Land Commission might offer the club a farm which the club, for one reason or another, would not be willing to take, but I think that the general idea of asking the Mount Street Club to consider doing with two or three or four other farms what it has already done with the Clondalkin farm is one which should receive the favourable consideration of the Government.  The cost to the State need not amount to anything worth talking about.  One of my reasons for advocating this scheme is that it seemed to promise a very definite return for a comparatively trifling expenditure, and I had heard so many rumours of wild-cat schemes of public expenditure being advocated that I thought I would like to get in first with this modest proposal of a small expenditure on relief of unemployment, in the hope of catching, so to speak, the public eye, and diminishing the popularity of those wild-cat schemes of which one suspects the existence.</P>
    <P>If those agricultural colonies are a permanent success, ultimately the element of subsidy would have to disappear in one form or another, and I should hope that it would be possible eventually to dispense with subsidy of any kind, but for the moment the Land Commission has farms which it is by no means obvious are yielding their maximum output of wealth in their present condition of Mahomet's coffin, so to speak, suspended between a former regime and a new regime which has not yet been finally decided on. If those farms can be made to increase rapidly the output of food for the nation with the help of an organisation of the kind that the Mount Street Club represents, then I think the nation should consider very favourably the question of making those farms available <Col N="306" /> on financial terms that the club could afford to accept.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg formally to second the resolution proposed by Senator Johnston.  I reserve the right to speak later if I should so wish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the Mount Street Club has done all that Senator Johnston has said it has, and I am sure the organisers of the Mount Street Club deserve to be congratulated on the success they have made of it, but after all we must remember that the club consists mainly of ex-soldiers, men who are amenable to discipline, who will take orders and carry out their instructions.  Does Senator Johnston think that the same thing can be done all over the country?  If we adopt the proposal of Senator Johnston that the Mount Street Club should get land, we cannot refuse to grant the same concession to any other organisation which sets itself up on the same lines.  I have a very definite objection to using State funds for subsidising any such body.  I have no objection to the Mount Street Club or any other body coming in and working farms on co-operative lines if they acquire the farms in the ordinary way.  I have no objection to letting them work the farms in any way they like then, and the better success they make of them the more I will be pleased.  If we look back on the history of co-operative farming we will find that it has been described time and again as the greatest curse that was ever put on the country.  Co-operative farming is not new in this country.  It is still carried on to some extent in mountain grazing and bog lands, but it is steadily disappearing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Time and again I have heard it suggested that the principal cause of the congestion in the West and South of Ireland was the system of co-operative farming on a small scale which operated in past years.  A farmer had perhaps 50 or 60 acres of land.  He divided that land into two or three parts&mdash;sometimes more&mdash;between his sons, who were supposed to work it on the principle on which the Mount Street Club are working their Clondalkin <Col N="307" /> farm now; each member of the family was to give the requisite amount of work and time and attention to the farm.  Eventually they all broke down. All those farms had to be divided and every member of that co-operative union had to get his own portion.  The greatest plague that the old Congested Districts Board and everybody else concerned, landlord or otherwise, had to contend with was the division of those farms into separate units.  That was the main cause of the congestion in the South and West of Ireland.</P>
    <P>Another point which I should like Senators to consider is the question of what is to be produced on those farms which the Senator wants to get for the Mount Street Club.  They are to be principally used for the raising of vegetables. We have sufficient vegetables raised, particularly in South County Dublin, Rush, Lusk and Skerries, to supply all the needs of Dublin.  I have heard it mentioned not later than a week or ten days ago that the vegetables in the Dublin market at the present time would not pay the cost of the freight.  If you are going to subsidise another institution to compete with those people, you will be depriving those people&mdash;who are not getting any subsidy&mdash;of their livelihood.  You will be subsidising an opposition body to knock them out of business.  I think that would not be right, and that, before anything else is done on the lines suggested by Senator Johnston, that aspect of the matter should be carefully considered by the Government. As I said, the Mount Street Club is an exception.  Senator Johnston is rightly proud, and everybody concerned with the Mount Street Club is rightly proud, of the organisation they have set up, but if they think they can continue the establishment of Mount Street Clubs all over the country they are making a grave mistake.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel that we are deeply indebted to Senator Johnston for the very lucid statement he made this evening concerning co-operative farming.  He developed a line of thought which has been agitating the <Col N="308" /> minds of a great many people, not alone of this generation but of earlier generations.  I remember when Standish O'Grady wrote a series of very interesting articles&mdash;I do not remember whether it was for the old <i>Sinn Féin</i> or the <i>Irish Peasant</i>&mdash;and the eloquence and limpid style of the writer made those articles one of the most interesting and readable things I have come across.  Senator Johnston's contribution this evening might be considered somewhat of an addition to that very able consideration of co-operative farming.  I feel, however, that he has rather injured the proposal by putting it within such a narrow ambit, limiting the proposal to the activities of one particular institution.</P>
      <P>I ventured to suggest here some time ago that it was very necessary that the land which the Land Commission has on hands at the present time should be made available to workers in the different areas for production; that is to say, at the present time it is very necessary that every sod of land that is available for production should be put into production.  I am sure the Parliamentary Secretary knows as well as I do, and possibly better, because of the more intimate contact in his Department with matters of this sort, that there are thousands of acres, even in our own county, which could very suitably be put into production.  There is the raw material there in the shape of the land; there possibly might be seed available to go into it, together with manures, fertilisers and so on, and there is the labour.  We have lying almost idle&mdash;of course, they are not absolutely idle&mdash;thousands of acres which could be put into valuable production. We are getting some 30 or 40 per cent. production out of thousands of acres of land where there might be obtained the full 100 per cent. production.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Government ought to give very serious thought to that aspect of the proposal that is put before them. Whilst Senator Johnston and I agree on some matters of great importance, I think there are fundamental differences arising between us on many other matters.  In regard to this proposal, <Col N="309" /> I suggest, in the first place, that the motion should be more general.  If the Senator wants the Mount Street Club to acquire extra land, that could be accomplished more easily by approaching the Land Commission and, by negotiation, to see if they could not be put in a position of having some land transferred to them, if the Land Commission and the Government thought that that would be a good policy.  I think that should be the line of approach.  If the Senator wants to extend the matter and if he wants to establish the principle of co-operative farming, his motion might be worded in this manner:&mdash;</P>
    <P>That in view of the importance of increasing agricultural production and alleviating the condition of the unemployed, Seanad Eireann is of opinion that suitable estates in the possession of the Land Commission, which it is not practicable to divide at present, should be offered to the Mount Street Club, and other approved associations, during the period of the present crisis, on favourable conditions as to rent and equipment, for cultivation and management on lines approved by the Department of Agriculture.</P>
    <P>I do not suggest that the Land Commission should give land indiscriminately to every person seeking it.  They should be somewhat conservative in that matter and should exercise some care as to the type of man who would get a holding.  In that matter I think they might possibly make trustees or holders either of county councils or county committees of agriculture.  These bodies might possibly help the Land Commission in seeing that the land was put into proper commission and utilised to the best advantage.</P>
    <P>I know that Senator Counihan has a good deal of right on his side when he says that co-operative farming has not been a great success.  In our own county, unfortunately, where it was tried on an extensive scale in Raheen, it was not a very pronounced success, but that was not because of the people who were concerned.  It was largely the fault of one individual, the indiscretions of one individual.  It was not because the principle was bad, but <Col N="310" /> largely because of that one individual. I think Senator Counihan is not correct in saying that the cause of the congestion in the West was co-operative farming.  I think the Senator is confusing the rundale system and co-operative farming.  Everyone knows that a farmer with 20 or 30 acres will divide the land among his family and none of them has sufficient to live on; but they do not make any particular fences between the portions of land; they hold it in common, but there is no co-operative farming.  You get your definite share of land, but that is not co-operative farming in the sense that I understand it.</P>
    <P>Senator Johnston says that there is more to be got out of big farming operations; that big farms would be more economic than small farms.  I do not know that I would agree entirely with him.  I would like Senator Johnston to free my mind from the doubt that he was not speaking in favour of the big farms we were used to 20 or 30 years ago.  The point, it seemed to me, was whether we would not develop towards the trust element in the farming industry instead of the small peasant holder.  The peasant proprietor is a sort of tradition in this country.  A lot of sacrifice and suffering and a lot of activity have been put into the establishment of peasant proprietorship, ownership of the soil by the peasants of the country.  We should be very careful that we do not develop towards the large trust in the farming industry.</P>
    <P>While Senator Johnston seems to be anxious to maintain the Mount Street Club, I am more interested in seeing that the land in possession of the Land Commission should be utilised for production.  I will ask the Parliamentary Secretary, as I asked the Minister on a former occasion, to endeavour to see that all the land available is put into commission, whether by the Mount Street Club or some local association, or individuals getting portions of it for cultivation purposes.  The machinery is there, the raw material is there, there is plenty of land available and the labour is not wanting.  In those circumstances, I hope there will be some effort on the <Col N="311" /> part of this Government to see that production is increased.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>This debate has reminded me of a speech made by Senator Hogan, the speech to which he referred just now, when he made the suggestion that the land in the hands of the Land Commission should be put into cultivation.  I meant to refer to it at that time, and I am glad that he has now reminded me of the matter.  I am in thorough agreement with him in that.  I believe every effort should be made to utilise all the land in the hands of the Land Commission.  In the present circumstances a definite effort should be made to put any of that land that is suitable into the production of wheat.</P>
      <P>With regard to what Senator Counihan said about congestion in the West being due to co-operative farming, I am not quite in agreement there.  I believe it is due to the fact that at a certain time the Irish people got orders to go to Hell or Connacht.  A lot of them went to Connacht, and their descendants are still there.  The reason congestion still exists there is because of the fact that, despite the Government's best efforts, it has not been possible to relieve congestion to the extent that many would wish it to be relieved and to undo that wrong.  I am glad that a very definite effort has been, is being, and will be made towards that end.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to Senator Johnston's speech, I was quite interested when I saw his motion on the Order Paper.  I have been for a considerable time hearing about the Mount Street Club, and I was quite interested when I heard him explaining all about it.  Not alone was I interested, but I was quite prepared to examine the matter with an open mind, and I was inclined to be favourable to it&mdash;until I heard Senator Johnston's speech.  Notwithstanding his speech, and what anybody could not fail to see implied therein, I am still prepared to say that the suggestion contained in it is certainly worthy of serious consideration.  I believe good things have been achieved and that there must be several very <Col N="312" /> useful things which could be gained from an examination of the problem by the Government.</P>
    <P>Unfortunately, Senator Johnston could not avoid dragging in what we might call the political angle.  After he told us about the Mount Street Club, he went further to suggest that the large holding was far preferable to the smaller holding.  It is quite evident that behind his enthusiasm for the provision of work for the unemployed and the provision of further economic large-scale farms, there was that thing which we find here in every debate, the element which would go out whole-hog for the continuation of the big ranches in the country as against the division of the land into smaller holdings.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>I never said a word in favour of ranches.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Johnston goes on to explain to us how greater productivity could be got from the bigger holding worked by up-to-date methods, and so on.  That statement is contrary to anything we know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator saying that bigger production will be obtained by using primeval methods?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not mention primeval methods.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator denied the opposite.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be time for the Senator to ask me that question when I mentioned that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>Sorry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>What I do say is that anybody who knows anything about this country or who has studied the situation knows that greater productivity has been got on the smaller holding per acre.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>I am talking about production per man.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I am getting to the production per man.  Production per man means nothing but what people can be maintained.  A greater number of people can be maintained and have been maintained on the small farms of <Col N="313" /> this country per acre or per 20 acres, if you like, than have been maintained on the bigger holdings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree, if they are content with bare sustenance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>The smaller holdings, an average holding of 20 or 25 acres, if you like, and even smaller holdings than that have in the past succeeded in maintaining an average family which in this country is taken at six.  Has the farm of 100 acres or 200 acres maintained the same number of people per acre?  I say it has not.  The smaller holdings have produced a greater number of people, which are an asset to the State, a greater number of poultry, a greater number of pigs, a greater amount of milk and a greater amount of farm produce and, in fact, a greater amount of cattle per acre than have the larger holdings.  Any policy which drifts in the other direction is in my opinion detrimental to the national interests here.  I believe that it is unfortunate that Senator Johnston has taken that line and that he has in fact put up the suggestion as a possible way out for the Government from the further division of land.  I believe that there was no necessity whatever to advance that argument.  I believe that if it is deemed desirable to provide land for the Mount Street Club, there would still be plenty of land available for that club side by side with the policy of the continuation of land division as we have had it in the past.  We have it suggested here and there that the policy of land division would not be carried on as in the past, some suggestion that it should be slowed down because of various reasons.  There may be some reasons of which I am not aware but in my opinion the present time is really a time when land division should receive even more attention than it has received in the past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have had a promise from, I think, the Minister for Lands here on a previous occasion that any land in the hands of the Land Commission at the present time or &ldquo;in the machine&rdquo;, as, I think, he called it, would be divided and that after that he did not think it would be possible for the Land Commission <Col N="314" /> to acquire further land for division. All I can say is that, if that is so, it is a policy with which I certainly do not agree.  I believe that, apart from the desirability of further land division, which means further production, which means the maintenance of further people on the land and off the land, we have to look forward to the time when the war is over.  All that is desirable while the war carries on but what will be the position when the war is over if we find ourselves left with a few what we call co-operative farms here and there and the rest of the available land left as it is at the present time?  As we all know, it takes a good many years to get any big machine working and we know that the same thing will apply to the Land Commission.  When the post-war slump comes, as it must come, we do not want to find ourselves in the position of having that huge machine standing idle, rusty, if you like, while there is plenty of work to be done and plenty of men available to work the land.</P>
    <P>Co-operative farming is to my mind a different thing from the suggestion that we have before us and I believe that this suggestion of the Mount Street Club might work when co-operative farming might not work.  In this country co-operative farming, for some reason or another, has not been very successful and we find in ordinary communities that it is very hard even to work the community potato digger. That is probably something which is peculiar to our race or probably comes from past experiences and, in any case, we have to face that fact.</P>
    <P>I do think there is something in the proposition of having what might be called communal farming, and I would be in favour of having a thorough examination of the possibilities of such a scheme.  I have in my mind something which would not be exactly the same as the Mount Street Club, but I believe that it would be quite possible that very useful information could be got from the scheme already in operation by the Mount Street Club.  We have all been puzzling our heads from time to time to find some method whereby unemployment could be reduced by putting people to work, and <Col N="315" /> I have repeated time and again that it is beyond me to understand how it is that some such scheme could not be devised by somebody.</P>
    <P>I am not in favour of the introduction of high-power machinery, if you like, in the taking over of a big tract of land by the Government or anybody else and working it.  I believe in taking over a big number of men and putting them to work, if you like, on the crudest methods as against the big machine.  I believe it would be very desirable if men could be employed to produce something even if they produced that something at a loss, but I do say that any scheme of that kind should be run under Government control.  There are various objections to any scheme which would be run either wholly or partly on charity.  We know that the working people of this country have, naturally, a decided objection to anything of that kind.  It ought to be possible, as I say, to get as much land as possible into production and an attempt should be made at the same time to get every possible man in the country to produce something. It would not be necessary at all, as Senator Counihan has suggested, that they should go into competition with the people who are already supplying vegetables to the City of Dublin or to any of the other towns.  There must be an export market available for a very considerable amount of that particular type of produce, especially at the present time, and if men were put to work, even with spades and shovels, to produce such things as celery and various other vegetables of that kind for export I believe that it would serve a very useful purpose.  To begin with, it would absorb a certain number of the people already unemployed; it would utilise a certain number of acres which are at present remaining idle, and it would at the same time bring into the country revenue which will be required as we go along.  I think that is very important and it would be very desirable, particularly under existing conditions. Whether a scheme of that kind could be worked under the executive officers of county committees of agriculture or not I do not know, but I think some <Col N="316" /> attempt should be made along those lines, by an elaboration, if you like, of the present allotments scheme.  The allotment schemes have been a success in certain areas.  In other areas they have not been.  The allotment schemes were more or less for small-scale operations, but I believe that in the outskirts of any town of a reasonable size it would be possible to run something along those lines, and to use whatever information could be got from the scheme already in operation by the Mount Street Club.</P>
    <P>With regard to large scale farming: When I was raising objection to that Senator Johnston felt inclined to interrupt me.  One of the reasons why I object to large scale farming or farming by high power machinery is because any move in that direction is a move to make farming in this country completely dependent on outside supplies.  The reason why I say that is this: If we are to go along and develop farming on the basis of the tractor I believe it will be disastrous. We all know that a good many years ago we had people in this country&mdash; a considerable number of people&mdash;who could follow a pair of horses and a plough.  We have to-day, thank God, still quite a number of people who can do that, but if we allow tractors to supplant horses and ploughs on Irish farms, we shall eventually reach a stage when we will not have a man capable of tackling a horse to do ordinary farm work as heretofore.</P>
    <P>I am quite agreeable at the present time to the use of tractors because we are in a position where we must have immediate results and, with all the tractors we have, we shall be able to get the necessary results within the shortest time, but it is quite obvious that under existing conditions we may reach a time, and that in the very near future, when we shall find ourselves in the position that we cannot get spare parts, the necessary oil or lubricants for the tractors, and that then things will have to come to a standstill.  We have plenty of time to prepare and rather than have a drift towards this large scale farming with tractors, I should like to see a drift towards self-sufficiency, if you like, on the farms. <Col N="317" /> We have the horses in the country at the present time despite the drain by way of purchases for foreign armies that we have had for the past few years, but all the available horses are not trained for farm work.  I believe that people have come to realise the importance of having a sufficiency of trained horses since the initiation of the compulsory tillage scheme, and that in a short time we shall have a reasonable number of trained horses ready for farm work in this country. I believe that is a far more sensible scheme than one of employing expensive machinery on the farms, and that any move in the direction of high-power machinery is definitely a move in the wrong direction.</P>
    <P>The effort to employ ex-urban workers, as Senator Johnston described them, under a scheme such as that of the Mount Street Club is, I think, very desirable.  I quite understand how hard it would be to get urban workers to work successfully under any other system.  For instance, I think it would be very difficult to expect the average unemployed man in the city to make a success of a 20-acre holding, but I do think that there are a very considerable number of men, even in the City of Dublin, who, within the past nine or ten years, have come directly from the land, and I think that these people could be utilised as ordinary allottees all over the country.  I know from my own experience that a good many of these people are very anxious to get back to the land, and every possible effort should be made to accommodate them. I do not want Senator Johnston to think that I am trying to throw cold water on the whole idea.  I merely regret that he has dragged a political element into the debate.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ProfMichaelTierney" hpid="Professor Tierney Professor Tierney">
      <NameTxt>Professor Tierney</NameTxt>
      <P>I think all Senators will agree that this has been an unusually fruitful and instructive debate.  Whatever slight differences of opinion may have arisen on Senator Johnston's motion, everyone will thank him for having brought it forward, and agree that he has probably opened up a splendid field of opportunity for the <Col N="318" /> country in doing so.  I am rather inclined to agree with Senator Hogan that in some ways this motion is too limited.  On the other hand, it is worth while having the matter brought down to one particular instance where it can be shown, as Senator Johnston has shown, that success can be attained in this kind of work.  The matter has a great number of aspects, and the idea that has been put forward by the Mount Street Club, and by Senator Johnston, could be extended in a number of directions that might be very beneficial to the country.  There is, first of all, the problem he mentioned of drawing off some of the unemployed from Dublin City.  If we could secure some alleviation of the unemployment problem in Dublin by these or any other healthy and sound means, that in itself would be a tremendous advance and a tremendous benefit.  It is quite true, as Senator Quirke has pointed out, that a large number of the unemployed in Dublin are men who, not so long ago, were brought up in the country and are experienced to some extent in country work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The whole problem in Dublin arises from the fact that under the operation of the particular industrial and commercial system that we have in this country&mdash;and that they have everywhere&mdash;the tendency is to gather workers from the country into the big city, to drag people, boys and girls, off the land by every possible agency, whether it be the school, the factory or the shop, and having dragged them into the city, to depress, in order to make room for these incoming people, a large section of the city population into the slums.  You have a continual invasion of Dublin by people from the country.  Every shop, every office, every available form of occupation there is in the city, is largely filled by people of recent country origin.  In order to make room for these people the system is such that a huge number of Dublin people&mdash;people born in Dublin and whose ancestors were born in Dublin&mdash;have to be pushed down to the lowest step on the social ladder, so to speak, driven into the slums and more or less kept there.  One way of <Col N="319" /> getting over that terrible process that is continually going on would be provided if you could gradually take off some of these people who cannot get work in Dublin, and give them work, as is done by the Mount Street Club, either in the country or in Dublin.</P>
    <P>Personally, I have no axe to grind on behalf of the Mount Street Club, any more than anybody else.  My acquaintance with the club was purely accidental. When Senator MacDermot and I put down a motion here about vocational organisation, some members of the Mount Street Club, I think under a misapprehension, got the idea that I was interested in their scheme of vocational development for the unemployed, and they asked me to come along and see them.  Major Waller then kindly showed me over the club. I have seldom had a more interesting or instructive experience.  I came away from that visit to the club with the impression that if this idea could be taken up and extended, the whole problem of unemployment might ultimately be solved.</P>
    <P>There are many aspects of the prolem of course.  I am not competent to deal with all of them.  There are economists here who can go into them, but the proposal to take this particular section of the unemployed and, as Senator Johnston said, to insulate them from commercialism, so to speak, for the time being, while at the same time giving them every opportunity to get back to work as soon as possible again, to create for them a sort of self-contained system under which they would be enabled, in decency and honesty, without any slur of charity about the system, to earn their own living, seems to be an absolutely splendid idea, one that could well be extended until you had something equivalent to the Mount Street Club in every parish in the country.  If you could extend it still further, and accentuate the degree to which those bodies would be self-supporting by helping them to get land, so much the better.</P>
    <P>That is one problem.  The Mount Street Club aspect of it largely has reference, <Col N="320" /> of course, to the question of the unemployed in Dublin and in other cities.  Its work could be greatly helped by putting land at the disposal of the club or similar bodies, wherever they arose, and I think it highly desirable that the State should do so.  There is, as everybody knows, a good deal of land available.  There are demesnes, for instance, that have remained in the hands of the Land Commission for a considerable time and that it is not now possible for them to distribute in the ordinary way, and will not be possible for them to distribute for a considerable time to come.  If the Mount Street Club, or similar bodies, were allowed to go in on these lands and work them for a year, or for two or three years, the benefits resulting from that would be enormous to the community as a whole, and to the unemployed.  It would be well worth while having a thorough-going, competent investigation into the possibility of this method of draining off a proportion of the unemployed from Dublin.</P>
    <P>There is another aspect of the motion, which in a way it was quite right to bring in, but which at the same time it would be a pity to confuse too much with this question of the Mount Street Club.  That is the desirability of co-operative farming in general.  You could well afford to assist the Mount Street Club in its limited function, and try to spread its work widely among the Dublin unemployed, without prejudicing the matter by arguments about the rights and wrongs of large-scale and small-scale farming.  The two subjects could be very well kept apart.  Before I leave the question of the Mount Street Club, I should like to say, in reply to Senator Counihan, that from what I have learned about it, the statement that its beneficiaries largely consist of ex-soldiers does not correspond with the facts.  Everyone knows&mdash;it stands to reason&mdash;that those men who are engaging in agricultural work cannot be, to any large extent, ex-soldiers from the Great War of 1914 to 1918.</P>
    <P>Whatever chance there is of converting young unemployed men into agricultural workers, I should say there would be very little chance of so converting the veterans of the Great War, at their age.  The fact that they <Col N="321" /> have succeeded with as many men as they have, is in itself proof that their people are not ex-soldiers.  As far as I have heard, there is no question of ex-soldiers, or anything of that sort, in the Mount Street Club at all.  Anyone is free, as far as I am aware, within the limits of the club's resources to go in and join the club, become one of its members and work in it like everyone else.</P>
    <P>I would like to say one or two words about the other question that was raised, because I think it is an important question and one well worth considering, even though, perhaps, it is rather irrelevant to this business of the Mount Street Club.  Senator Johnston himself was largely responsible for raising it.  It is a pity that the question of large scale farming and small scale farming and land division should be always considered in a black and white aspect.  You have one Senator on one side of the House accused of being in favour of ranches, and a Senator on the other side looked upon as if he was in favour of giving every man an acre or two of land and no more.  It is in that sort of extreme fashion that this question is usually debated, as if it was not possible at all to have a diversified economy.  When Senator Johnston talks about large scale agriculture he is treated as if he wanted to go back to the worst evils of landlordism.  There is surely a difference between one kind of large scale agriculture and another.  Large scale agriculture, when operated for the benefit of a single capitalist, and operated without regard to the welfare of the people who work for him, is one matter.  Large scale agriculture, if it could be worked co-operatively in order to secure a degree of common self-subsistence between a large number of people who otherwise would probably not be able to get work at all, is a totally different thing.  I think Senator Quirke will agree with that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfMichaelTierney" hpid="Professor Tierney Professor Tierney">
      <NameTxt>Professor Tierney</NameTxt>
      <P>You could well afford to have at one and the same time a very large measure of peasant proprietorship, and a considerable degree, alongside it, of large scale <Col N="322" /> agriculture, provided the large scale agriculture is worked in the right way, and provided that it is used for the purpose of giving employment, for instance, to men who cannot get employment on the lines of peasant proprietorship. I speak as the son of a peasant proprietor.  I am probably as familiar as any member of the House with the conditions that prevail on small farms, and I have felt for a long time that this Government, and the last Government as well, have tended to go too far with the infinitesimal subdivision of land.  It is not a healthy thing for the country to have all its eggs put in the one basket in that way. There is everything to be said for dividing the ranches.  Let there be no disagreement on that.  There is everything to be said for peasant proprietorship, and I imagine that Senator Johnston is as much in agreement with that as Senator Quirke.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Question!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfMichaelTierney" hpid="Professor Tierney Professor Tierney">
      <NameTxt>Professor Tierney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is desirable, at the same time, that alongside that peasant proprietorship you should have some diversification of your agriculture. The ideal system would be the English one that prevailed a couple of hundred years ago.  It never prevailed in this country because the landlords were always a foreign body that never did their duty by their tenants. But under the old system in England the landlord acted as a local leader, as the protector and helper of his tenants, and lived in their midst.  He was a sort of social and cultural centre for them.  A system like that had a great deal to be said for it, even though it meant that one man was very rich and the remainder of the community comparatively poor.  It is a terrible and dangerous mistake, to my mind, to think that you can manage the whole economy of the country in such a way that you will not have differences between rich and poor, that you will not have some people wealthier than others.  That is a tendency that seems to be always active in the minds of Fianna Fáil speakers on this matter.  They seem to visualise an Ireland where nobody has more than ten or 20 acres of land.  Such an Ireland, if it were possible to bring <Col N="323" /> it about, would become more tied to the foreign market that Senator Quirke spoke of than an Ireland in which you had a much more diversified economy.</P>
      <P>The old system of land holding in England, under which you had a single proprietor who acted as the leader of the district and who owned the greater part of the property in the district, never operated in this country at all, and is impossible now.  You could not dream of trying to restore anything of the kind here.  As a modern alternative to it, I have often thought that it might well be worth while taking a leaf out of the Bolshevik book and trying to have some system of communal farming.  We have a lot of demesnes scattered all over the country.  In the centre of every old estate there still remains a considerable demesne which might well be taken over and worked in that way&mdash;land which might be used to give an opportunity to the second, third or fourth son of the local small farmer.  One of the greatest difficulties about our situation at present seems to me to be this: that the second, third, or fourth son of every small farmer is encouraged, and helped, to do anything else on earth except to become a farmer himself.  The hardest thing in the world for the second, third or fourth son of a small farmer in Ireland is to became what his father was.  He can become a doctor, a lawyer, a clerk, a priest, a teacher or anything else you like.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>A professor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfMichaelTierney" hpid="Professor Tierney Professor Tierney">
      <NameTxt>Professor Tierney</NameTxt>
      <P>But the one thing that he cannot do, without for him at least an enormous capital endowment, is to become a small farmer himself. That fact alone means that the country is draining off continually an enormous proportion of its highly-skilled agricultural population, and that population is being diminished steadily. Every agency that we have in the country is diminishing the number of Irish people who are country people, and that, to my mind, is the greatest disaster than can befall Ireland.  Once the majority of Irishmen cease to be farmers and farmers' sons then, to my mind, there is no more Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="324" /> Ireland will have lost its character, and will have become a different nation.  It will not be the same as it has always been.  It is the tendency to have no outlet but the town for the second, third and fourth sons of the farmer that is largely helping to hasten that process, and it has already gone a great deal further than many of us realise.  Some means should be found, on the lines that have been suggested here, by way of communal farming or co-operative holdings, for using those large farms. There are some of them still in existence of a considerable size, far bigger than 120 acres; some of them I am sure go up to 1,000 acres.  Instead of being fractionalised and divided up as is being done at present, to my knowledge, amongst people who do not want the land, if they were kept under some central control and used to create those co-operative centres, I think a great step forward would have been taken in re-establishing a sound agricultural economy in the country.</P>
    <P>A large amount of land is being given to people who do not want it.  I am speaking from experience, for I have seen this happening in parts of Galway.  Everybody who has lived in the country for the last 20 years knows that since 1923 this tendency to fractionalise the land has been going much too far.  All sorts of people have got land who do not want it and who cannot do anything with it when they get it, unless they sell it.  There is no use in blinking our eyes to this and talking about peasant proprietors and about giving people farms of two, three or five acres, and thinking you are serving an ideal or going to produce good results.  What we need is a diversified rural economy, and unless we get that there is nothing surer than that our tendency will be to let the bulk of our population drift into Dublin or go across to England.  Sooner or later we will have to get a social system and an economy which will encourage our young country people to stay on the land and work on the land.  It is because I think this motion offers a possibility of something of this nature being done that I welcome the opportunity to try to urge it forward.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall not detain the House very long, but there are one <Col N="325" /> or two things I would like to mention before this debate closes.  Firstly, I would like to join with the other Senators in thanking Senator Johnston for the excellent account he has given of the Mount Street Club.  I was very interested and very anxious to hear all about it.  However, as he developed the policy of the club and their attitude to economics and to social policy generally, I got something of a start. In the first place, we were led to believe&mdash;and most of the Senators were inclined to believe&mdash;that there is something new in this policy of the Mount Street Club.  Their idea is that of a communal farm.  There is a great difference between a communal farm and a co-operative farm; for myself, I am very much in favour of co-operative farming, but very much opposed to communal farming.  We are inclined to think that there is something new in it, but, as a matter of fact, there is nothing new in it.</P>
      <P>This idea of a communal farm and tallies has been tried, of course, in France in the last century.  It was tried by our own people in South America early in the last century.  We had a fine example and a fine record of it in the Irish commune down at Ralahine, in County Clare.  If I may say so, we have seen it tried under the most ideal conditions imaginable in Russia.  This idea of communal farming and tallies has failed.  There are a great many points raised by Senator Johnston to which I would like to refer, and many questions which I would like to ask, but, in view of the time already taken up by this discussion, and in view of the peculiarity of the question, this may not be the ideal time in which to discuss it.  Perhaps it would be better to discuss it over a cup of tea in the restaurant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In regard to the motion itself, I see a number of objections to handing over farms to the Mount Street Club or any other club.  In the first place, I think the Mount Street Club should try to get land in the ordinary way.  There must be large landholders very sympathetic to the people in charge of the Mount Street Club, and very sympathetic to the unemployed, who are not willing to work <Col N="326" /> their land themselves and who ought to be very happy and very willing to hand over their land to an institution like the Mount Street Club.  If they want land, I would certainly like to see them getting it in the ordinary way, by getting the land on the market or getting it from their own particular friends.</P>
    <P>The point has been made by other Senators that there is great danger in any group of people coming together in the country and making a claim to land like this.  Where the danger lies is not so much in a group coming together and asking for land, but rather in the private people who propose to go on to the land.  When they do get on, it would be very hard to get them off.  Although this is only a temporary measure, a time will come when the land must be divided.  We have had some little experiments in Ireland, and some little examples of Sovietism and Communism, and it might be a difficult thing for the Land Commission to evict these people once they get on the land, claiming themselves as unemployed and claiming a special amount of sympathy from the community and from the Government. This will, therefore, have to be approached with the utmost care.</P>
    <P>There is also the point with regard to the idea of the Land Commission handing land over to clubs or institutions of this kind.  I do not like it, frankly, as I think the function of the Land Commission is to divide the land among the people.  That is their function, and I would like to see them get on with that.  In this case I would say the cobbler should stick to his last. Senator Tierney twitted Senator Quirke here because he was inclined to exaggerate and say that anybody who spoke on the other side was in favour of the ranches.  Senator Tierney was inclined to go a bit too far on the other side.  I do not think the policy of Fianna Fáil ever was, or is, or that it will ever be their policy, to establish four-acre holdings in this country.  I do not think that is so.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, if you let people in on the land under these temporary conditions for the duration of the war <Col N="327" /> there is grave danger that the land will be abused.  If a person has only a temporary interest, he is likely to work the land to death, and after four or five years there will be nobody willing to take it.  If it is put on the market the price will have depreciated so much that it will have a very bad effect on land all over the country.</P>
    <P>These are the few objections I think should be brought before the House. Mainly, I would not like that either the House or the people in general should think that there is anything novel in this idea or that it has not been tried out before.  I am afraid it has and it has been found by economists that it will not work.  The public <Col N="328" /> itself has found that it will not work, and I think economists in general are agreed that we have to reject the teaching of Robert Owen on this matter.</P>
    <P>Anything that can be done to assist the unemployed and anything that can be done to make land available to those who are willing to work it, should be done, but at the same time, we should not get it into our heads that this is going to provide a solution for all our unemployment and other difficulties.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.5 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Thursday, 14th December.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>