<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Fri" Date="17" Month="Jul" Year="1931" Vol="39" No="18" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 17 Iúil 1931" DateEnglish="Friday, 17 July 1931" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="2333">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="2333" /> Do chuaidh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Road Traffic Bill," RHead="1931&mdash;First Stage">
    <Title>Road Traffic Bill, 1931&mdash;First Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Minister for Local Government and Public Health (General Mulcahy) Richard (General) Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government and Public Health (General Mulcahy)</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask leave to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to amend and consolidate the law relating to mechanically propelled vehicles, the regulation and control of road traffic, and the use of mechanically propelled vehicles for the carriage of passengers, to make provision for compulsory insurance against liabilities arising from negligent driving of mechanically propelled vehicles, and to make provision for other matters connected with the matters aforesaid.</P>
      <P>Leave granted.</P>
      <P>Bill read a first time.</P>
      <P>Second Stage ordered for Wednesday, 14th October, 1931.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Electricity (Supply) (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1931&mdash;Fifth Stage">
    <Title>Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Bill, 1931&mdash;Fifth Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. McGilligan) Patrick McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. McGilligan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the arrangement that has been come to, to discuss the motion on the Order Paper in my name later, I do not propose to object to this motion.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Report of the Commonwealth Conference." RHead="- Motion of Approval (Resumed)">
    <Title>Report of the Commonwealth Conference. - Motion of Approval (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:&mdash;</P>
    <P>That Dáil Eireann approves of the Report of the Commonwealth Conference, 1930, and recommends the Executive Council to take such steps as they think fit to give effect there-to.&rdquo;&mdash;(Aire Gnóthaí Coigríche.)</P>
    <Col N="2335" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>When speaking last night I pointed out to the Dáil that acceptance of the motion on the Order Paper would involve the acceptance of the contention of the Minister for External Affairs that the national aspirations of our people can be realised in full as a member of the British Commonwealth group of nations.  I asked the Dáil to reject the motion on that account, and to maintain, as successive leaders of the Irish people throughout the years have always maintained, that the aspirations of this nation can only be fully realised when the complete political independence of the country has been secured and the last vestige of control by Britain has been removed.  I proceeded, however, to deal with the motion as it affected the point of view of those who agreed with the Minister, and I urged its rejection on the grounds that even for those who hold that point of view, its passage would mean an impediment to, and not a facilitating of, their professed desires.  The motion asks us to approve of the Report of the Imperial Conference of 1930.  The principal matter, of course, in that Report is the draft of an Act which it is intended to submit to the British Parliament this year, after it has been approved by resolution in the Parliaments of the various British Dominions.  I pointed out that the principal flaw in that Act was that it did not destroy, as the Minister has alleged, the theoretical legislative supremacy of the Imperial Parliament.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister for External Affairs told us when speaking that this Act was in the nature of an act of renunciation. I say it is nothing of the kind.  He said that it destroyed British legislative supremacy in the Commonwealth, and I invite him or any other member of the Dáil to show in that Act what section, recital or phrase can be interpreted to have that significance. I say that, on the contrary, the Act has been very carefully drafted to preserve the theoretical right of the British Parliament to legislate for the whole of the British Empire.  It provides mainly that no British Act passed by the British Parliament after the enactment of the new statute, shall <Col N="2336" /> operate as part of the law of any Dominion, except at the request, and with the consent of that Dominion.  It is undoubtedly true that the enactment of that statute will in practice mean that the Parliaments of the various Dominions will be able to legislate without British interference, but the theoretical supremacy of the British Parliament is maintained.  Its legal right to legislate for the British Empire is not destroyed.  On the contrary, the power to legislate, is by inference, confirmed.  The Minister told us that he was concerned in these negotiations only with the end to be achieved and not with the method by which that end was achieved.</P>
    <P>I think that was his fundamental mistake.  I think that had he concerned himself a little more with the method he would have realised that in the proposal before us the very principle for which he maintains he fought has been surrendered.  I want to point out to the Dáil that if the legislative independence of the Oireachtas of the Free State or the Parliament of any Dominion is to depend in law upon a British statute then it is dependent upon the consent of the majority of the British Parliament.  What one British Parliament has enacted another British Parliament can repeal and the position will be that, at any time, by simply repealing that Act the British Parliament can reassert its right to legislate for this State or any other Dominion without the consent of the Parliament of this State or of that Dominion.  The Minister made a number of statements the accuracy of which I beg leave to doubt.  He told us that when the proposed statute is enacted in England that the position will be that this Parliament will be able to abolish any of the Royal prerogatives in so far as they relate to the Free State.  I say that is not so.  I say there is nothing in the Act which justifies that contention.</P>
    <P>I ask the Minister to state definitely, for example, whether it is possible for us to abolish the King as a factor in legislation here.  Is it possible?  That is the kernel of the question.  Can we abolish the King as a factor in legislation here?  Can we amend our Constitution <Col N="2337" /> in accordance with our own wishes?  Can we abolish the Act which prescribes that anything in our Constitution which is not in conformity with the Treaty of 1921 is null and void?  If we cannot do these things all this talk about our legislative independence is so much humbug. All that talk is only an attempt to deceive the people as to what our real status is.  If it is the desire of the Executive Council or the Minister for External Affairs to get to the position in which the last vestige of British domination here will be destroyed, then we are with him, but we do not think he has helped us to get to that position by pretending that we are already there.  No cause was ever brought to victory by its champion pretending that it was already won.</P>
    <P>If the British Parliament is prepared to do what the Minister says it is prepared to do, to recognise us as an independent State equal with them in all respects then there are two ways and two ways only in which it can achieve that end: either they can pass an Act declaring our independence, such an Act as that which declared the termination of the British sovereignty over the United States of America&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="HughALaw" hpid="Mr. Law Mr. Law">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Law</NameTxt>
      <P>And which it can repeal by the Deputy's own argument.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Undoubtedly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Therefore, you are stuck as you are for all time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>If the British Parliament wants to concede independence to us there are two ways in which they can do it.  That is one of the ways. I put it to the Minister that the British Parliament conceded independence to the American people after the American people had got it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>How did they do it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>By passing an Act terminating their sovereignty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>By an Act?  Therefore, according to the Deputy's argument they can repeal that Act tomorrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Let the Deputy continue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>If they were able.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2338" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>They would never have passed it if they were able to continue their sovereignty.  The Minister has revealed the position exactly as it is. The British Parliament maintains its sovereignty in any State in which it has the power to maintain it.  It has not destroyed its sovereignty here by this Act because it has the power to maintain it here.  If the British Parliament was, as the Minister said it was, willing to concede a status to us equal in every respect to the status enjoyed by Britain itself, then it would not succeed in that end by the passage of such an Act as is contained in this report.  It could do it by passing an Act similar to that which terminated the sovereignty of the British Parliament over the people of the United States.  It could do so perhaps by destroying the legal principle of the unity of the Crown, by dividing the King into six Kings and making each of the Dominions a separate kingdom which it has not done.  It has done neither of these things.  In this new Act they are, while appearing to concede something, merely strengthening their position. While pretending to remove legislative anachronisms they are affirming afresh their theoretical legal superiority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I put that to the Dáil.  I maintain that on the very face of this Act it is obvious that the description which the Minister applied to it is not an accurate one.  I maintain that what he said &ldquo;that they will have brought to an end the whole chapter of the legislative sovereignty of the central Government of the old Empire&rdquo; is not true, that although the British Government is binding itself to limit itself in the exercise of that sovereignty not to pass Acts having the force of law in the Dominions except at the request of those Dominions, nevertheless it is retaining for itself the legal right to do so.  The legal right is not being destroyed.  The British Monarch, as King, the Minister said, was finished entirely as far as the Free State was concerned, and everything was done at the will of the Irish people.  I say that is not true.  I say it cannot be true unless we are absolutely free to abolish the King as a factor in legislation, and to amend our <Col N="2339" /> Constitution in the way we desire ourselves without reference to anything else except the interests and the desires of the Irish people in national matters.  Even if the Act was as the Minister declared it should not be accepted by us, because it means that we are accepting the theory that our national aspirations have been realised in full within the British Empire. Even if we were prepared to accept that theory, nevertheless we should reject this Act because it does not achieve what the Minister pretends in that direction.</P>
    <P>There is one other matter that I would like the Minister to deal with when replying, and that is the position concerning the Privy Council.  Declarations have been made here from time to time by members of the Executive Council that they wanted to abolish the right of appeal to the British Privy Council.  I expressed the fear here last year that they were weakening in their attitude in that respect.  The Minister went to the Imperial Conference and presumably the matter was discussed there.  We do not know what attitude he took. We know that no change was made as a result of that Conference.  It is true that the Press here came out with glaring headlines announcing a great victory for Irish diplomacy, the victory being that the position in respect to the Privy Council was left unchanged. The Minister came home and announced the decision of the Executive Council to introduce in the Dáil proposals for legislation to amend the Constitution in respect to those appeals.  He was pressed time and again to state when those proposals for legislation would be brought before the Dáil.  He contented himself with the vague reply&mdash;&ldquo;in due course.&rdquo; They have not appeared yet.  I suggest that they will never appear and that the Executive Council in this matter, as in others, are merely humbugging the people.</P>
    <P>I want the Minister to tell us, if the Executive Council are maintaining their original stand in the matter, why there is this delay in introducing proposals for legislation?  What does the Minister mean by the phrase &ldquo;in <Col N="2340" /> due course?&rdquo; What is the position concerning this?  Is the Minister standing upon our rights in the matter and proceeding upon the basis of those rights or is he attempting to effect a compromise by negotiation with the British Government?  I think the Dáil is entitled to have that information. These are some of the principal matters that I wish to refer to.  I hope the Dáil will be very slow to do what the Minister asked it to do, that is to approve of this report.  It is not necessary for us to approve of it. Remember the Minister has assured us that what this Act purports to abolish as a matter of law has already been abolished as a matter of practice.  I maintain it is much better for us to leave the position indefinite than that we should consent to the enactment of a law which, in defining, will limit our legislative independence.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HughALaw" hpid="Mr. Law Mr. Law">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Law</NameTxt>
      <P>I always notice in debates on External Affairs two curious characteristics of the Opposition.  In the first place, they never are willing to allow any possibility of progress or development.  What someone said in 1923 or 1916 or 1885 or 1798 or 1641 for them constitutes a kind of secret canon of Scripture which it is heresy and impiety to question.  It must be regarded as verbally inspired and not subject in any way to the ordinary human considerations of time and circumstance.  We had a rather curious example of that last night from Deputy Seán T. O'Kelly.  Deputy O'Kelly quoted some well-known, not to say somewhat hackneyed, words of Mr. Charles Stewart Parnell&mdash;&ldquo;We have never set bounds to the march of a nation and we never shall.&rdquo;  He quoted that as though it was a plenary justification of his impossibilist attitude.  If you look at the context of these words, the meaning is perfectly plain.  What was Parnell doing?  He was arguing in favour of a Home Rule settlement&mdash;a settlement which would give him very much less power, obviously, than our present Constitution.  Whom was he arguing against?  He was arguing against the Seán T. O'Kellys of his day&mdash;the people who said we must not accept this because it is a derogation of what <Col N="2341" /> Deputy Lemass has called &ldquo;the position as defined by successive leaders of the Irish race.&rdquo;  Parnell was saying to them: &ldquo;Let us take now as much as is possible.  It does not block our march.  We have never set bounds to the march of the nation and we never shall.&rdquo;  Parnell was right. But he did not say &ldquo;Do not let us take this now.  Let us wait until the great ideal is achieved.  Let us have nothing else.&rdquo;  He said instead: &ldquo;Let us take this and let us go on.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have gone on.  We went on from Parnell's time to the Constitution of the Free State and the acceptance of Dominion status.  That that represents an advance on every Home Rule scheme conceived since the time of Butt nobody will dispute.  To that status we have come on, and the proof of it is to be found in the reports of successive Imperial Conferences.  None of us would care to speak as an authority on constitutional law, but I challenge anybody who has been a student, even in a small way, as I have been, of international affairs, to say that there has not been development and progress in Dominion relations since Dominion status was accepted here in 1922.  We have another curious factor about the attitude of Fianna Fáil, besides the extreme melancholy which always marks these discussions, and it is a very curious note of the Fianna Fáil mind.  They always seem to think that they can get rid of what, to them, is an unpleasant fact by ignoring it.  We had a curious example of that in the brief interlude which took place last night between Deputy O'Kelly and Deputy Collins-O'Driscoll.  Because the Oath or Declaration signed by members of this House does not please certain gentlemen opposite it does not exist and they never signed it.  The converse of that attitude is that to recognise a fact it is necessary to approve of it.  So we have a long jeremiad from Deputy O'Kelly on various things connected with this Act and contained in this report, particularly in respect of the fact that the Minister for External Affairs joined, according to the practique of diplomatic life, with which Deputy O'Kelly is not unacquainted, in an address to their <Col N="2342" /> Majesties.  In that, Deputy O'Kelly was, rather to my surprise, seconded by Deputy Lemass.  They both fastened upon the declaration of the proposed clause in the statute to be passed at Westminster:</P>
    <P>No Act of the United Kingdom passed after the commencement of this Act shall extend or be deemed to extend to a Dominion as part of the law in force in that Dominion unless it is expressly declared in that Act that that Dominion has requested, and consented to, the enactment thereof.</P>
    <P>That, according to Deputy Lemass, is useless and inoperative because a statute passed by a Parliament in Great Britain can be repealed by a subsequent Parliament.  Curiously enough, he went on to suggest a method by which our independence could be properly recognised and established&mdash;by the action of the Parliament of Great Britain.  That is very curious, because it involves, in the first place, the very principle he has objected to&mdash;that the Parliament of Great Britain should have anything to say to our status here. Secondly, under the British Constitution there is no such thing as fundamental law, and there is no statute which cannot at some time or other be repealed.  The Act recognising the United States could, of course, be repealed. But we are concerning ourselves with practical affairs and not with nightmares.  There are certain things which, theoretically, can be done but which every human being knows will never be done.  That is one of them.  It would be possible for the British Parliament, if it passed this supposed statute, to repeal it in a subsequent Parliament.  That is perfectly true.  But let us look at the facts and realities.  Why is it proposed to do this at all?  Because of the whole trend of constitutional development in the Commonwealth during the last fifty years. Because, as everybody knows, the strict, technical, legal position had lagged far behind the real position.  If the position were the other way I could understand the objection, but when the whole development is in the opposite direction what fear can there be of such action as is suggested?</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2343" /> Deputy O'Kelly is not content with that.  He thinks this Act will actually make things worse&mdash;far worse.  Not alone are we being brought into the Commonwealth against our will, but we are really being nailed and copper-fastened, further chains are being forged and we are being manacled by further links.  Because the British Parliament does what only that Parliament can do&mdash;renounce the powers which, undoubtedly, it theoretically had formerly to pass laws affecting the Dominions, powers which they had long ceased to exercise&mdash;and because we recognise the fact known to every constitutional lawyer, that there was such a power, though it had long since fallen into disuse, and though there was, undoubtedly, no intention whatever of using it&mdash;because the British Parliament says we formally and definitely renounce our right in that respect, the fact that we take cognisance of that renunciation constitutes a chain which, according to Deputy O'Kelly, is to bind us.  If people are determined to look at the black side of things, if there is a black side, and if they are determined to invent a black side if there is not one, there is really no hope for them.</P>
    <P>I listened last night to the speech of Deputy O'Kelly.  His whole trouble seemed to be that we are now recognising the existence of the British Parliament. He does not like that and, because he does not like it, all the world is full of woe.  We are recognising the existence of certain rights in the British Parliament in this matter in the same way as you might say that you recognise the existence of a man when you cut his head off; in the same way as the Red Queen in Alice in Wonderland realised that if the Cheshire Cat was not there you could not cut his head off.  The prophet Jeremiah was really a gay dog compared with Deputy Sean T. O'Kelly.  &ldquo;Woe, woe,&rdquo;&mdash;he will ingeminate woe to the end of the chapter.  I fear he will be found weeping in the glory of the courts of heaven.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I wondered, as I listened to Deputy Law, who was the real Jeremiah in the case.  The jeremiad which he has delivered just now <Col N="2344" /> would only be possible in the case of a man who had got away from the realities of the situation, made no attempt to get down to bedrock and recognise that there is a fundamentally different outlook politically at the moment between the two sides of the House.  Now let us get down to bedrock and see where we are.  Otherwise a debate like this is bound to be unreal.  We are forced here in these circumstances to deal with questions of this kind simply by putting ourselves in the position of the people opposite, as far as we can and trying to view the matter with their eyes in order to judge whether the policy that they are adopting, even from their point of view, a good one or not. Let us get down to bedrock to see where we are in this.  I have here a quotation from a speech made by the Vice-President of the Executive Council which gives us the position in a nutshell.  He says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>With regard to the point as to whether we are aiming at the establishment of an Irish Republic, we are not.  We believe that this country as a member of the British Commonwealth of Nations can enjoy greater freedom and greater security than she could outside the British Commonwealth of Nations and our policy within it is really to remove the anomalies that exist in the relationship between the members of it (Vol. 22, cols. 1645-6, Official Report).</P>
      <P>That is the difference and the issue. Members of this House who do not aim at the ultimate establishment of a Republic, such as the Ministers on the opposite side, may have some reason for satisfaction in what they call the progress that has been achieved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy Law says that we are blind to progress; that we do not want to give credit for any progress that has been achieved.  It is all a question of whether the progress is forwards or backwards.  With respect to what our ultimate aim is, if we are being put into a position which makes it more difficult ultimately to establish a Republic in this country, I say we are opposed to it as, not progress, but <Col N="2345" /> retrogression.  If, on the other hand, it is simply a question of facing the facts as you find them, taking whatever you get without committing yourselves or in any way putting up barriers for the future, then we will not be found opposing them.  The quotation from Parnell was referred to just now by Deputy Law.  He said it was used by Parnell against the Seán T. O'Kellys of his day.  What was it used for?  It was used by Parnell to tell the people, who were doubtful whether he was progressing or not, not to be afraid.  He told them: &ldquo;Do not be afraid.  I am not putting any barrier in the path of the advance of the Irish nation.  I am not going to commit you to remain eternally in the state in which we find ourselves.  This is going to be a unilateral matter as far as England is concerned.&rdquo;  But we have gone away from that unilateral position.</P>
    <P>The position is whether we should or should not take cognisance of facts. As far as I could, I have been preaching all the time the necessity of taking cognisance of facts.  The world in which we live is a world of facts, but there are gentlemen, of course, on the other side who have been trying very assiduously to represent to the country that we are always in the clouds. It is we who have been trying to take cognisance of facts.  When the Treaty was brought here we said: &ldquo;If you do accept that you are not going to make any Constitution you please.&rdquo;  That we were right was proved true when the draft Constitution, which was supposed to give an Irish interpretation of the Treaty, was handed to Lloyd George he blue-pencilled it and sent it back here to a Dáil which was supposed to be a constitutional assembly. It was a Constitution in regard to which we were told that there were thirteen Articles in which we could not change a comma.  Who faced the facts in that case?  Did we, or did the gentlemen who said: &ldquo;You can sign the Treaty and the day you sign it you can ignore it&rdquo;?</P>
    <P>We said: &ldquo;Be careful before you sign this document.  It implies consequences which you will find it very difficult to get rid of.  It implies these consequences: that you are disestablishing <Col N="2346" /> the Republic which you declared here; you are incorporating the British Crown as part of your Parliament here; you are going to give power to a section of our people, if they want to exercise it, to partition this country; you are going to get into commitments, the extent of which you have no idea of from the monetary side.&rdquo;  We are the people who read the document, who had no interest in it but the interest of seeing what it might lead to.  Gentlemen who had never construed a line of a document came along when our people were weary, and they felt they were anxious to get a certain interpretation out of it, and they put that interpretation over upon them.  We did not do that. We faced the facts.  We realised what the consequences would be.  You have an army to-day in this country supplied with British ammunition.  They depend upon an outsider to supply them with ammunition for the only thing for which ammunition is likely to be needed, for the coercion of the people of this country who are still true to the aim of ultimately establishing a Republic, if they can.</P>
    <P>These are the consequences: Civil war in our own country; a position that obtains in this country which does not probably obtain in any other country&mdash;a position in which the elected representatives of the people are being obliged to maintain an army for the express purpose of denying power to that section of our people who have as their aim the ultimate establishment of the freedom of this country as a whole.  That is the position the Treaty has landed you into.  That is why we objected to the Treaty, and that is why we tried to face the facts of the situation, and tried to get a settlement which would be consistent with the position that had been taken up by this country, and yet would be such that the other facts could also be taken into account.</P>
    <P>Last night Deputy O'Connor said that away back in 1921 we sought for external association.  He tells us that here we have external association.  I say we have not.  The proposal of the Republican Cabinet in 1921, if it had been accepted, would have left you with the <Col N="2347" /> Republic, as it was then declared.  It would have left you with a united Ireland.  It would have left you the power of remaining neutral in any British war unless you deliberately chose to enter it.  That was known by the British.  The excuse given by those who went to negotiate the Treaty was that they were prevented from pressing for this settlement by a threat of immediate and terrible war.  If there was no difference, as was pretended at that time, between the settlement involved in the Treaty, and the settlement involved in the alternative of external association, why were the British so anxious to prevent the one settlement, and were prepared to make immediate and terrible war rather than accept it? You cannot have it both ways.  The English knew what the difference was.</P>
    <P>The London &ldquo;Times,&rdquo; expressing the point of view of the British, said that the status that was contemplated in that settlement was not that of a Dominion.  It was that of an independent power, loosely associated by Treaty with Great Britain and other States.  If I saw in this present proposal a step towards the establishment of the complete freedom of this country I would welcome it.  Even as it is, I would not object to it provided we were not asked to give any assent to it, to give express assent by asking the British Parliament to pass the measure.  I would imagine that the Minister for External Affairs, from his point of view, if he were willing to apply the &ldquo;ruthless logic&rdquo; which he has been talking about to the situation he would have allowed the other British Dominions to carry on and pass their law, holding to the position which he took up, namely that we did not require a British Act of Parliament to confirm our rights.  He would have said &ldquo;All right, if you want this, have it; we do not object to it.&rdquo;  He would not have taken up the position that we are asked to take up, to agree that we are voluntarily a member of the British Commonwealth.</P>
    <P>We are not voluntarily a member of the British Commonwealth.  No statements that the Minister can <Col N="2348" /> make can make it voluntary. Entrance into the British Commonwealth, after the declaration of the Republic, was effected by the threat of war, by force.  It was assented to in the sense that it was not opposed reluctantly. There was not a member of the House who spoke at the passing of the Treaty with two exceptions who regarded it as anything except as a Treaty that they were compelled by superior force to accept.  That was the position and nothing that the Minister can say now can change it. We are not voluntarily members of the British Commonwealth and we object to being associated with any preamble of any British law which embodies any such implication of assent on our part.  We do not assent.</P>
    <P>Our position in the matter is, therefore, very clear.  We are not a British colony.  We are not a British Dominion.  We are a separate people, a separate nation.  Our rights are inherent.  We do not admit that they derive from any British donation.  The British invaded this country, coerced our people, interfered with and prevented them from exercising their natural rights in the past.  The British have ceased, in a measure, to interfere now.  And to the extent that they have ceased to interfere our people have been set at liberty again to exercise their natural inherent rights.  That is all.  The British have partitioned this country, and they have done it against the will of the majority of the people of this country.  As long as that situation obtains, as long as the country is forcibly divided and the choice of our people in their governmental institutions is not a free one but determined by a threat of war from Britain, a nation physically stronger than we are, so long we cannot admit, and it is a falsehood to assert it, that we are associated with the British in a free association.  The British Crown is not a symbol of free association of our nation with the British.  It is a symbol of a forced association, and although superior force may compel us to submit we can, and we should, avoid the misrepresentation of our position contained in this proposed preamble and make it clear that though we may be forced to <Col N="2349" /> bear these chains we do not regard them as ornaments.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickTReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that document No. 3?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'Connell Mr. T.J. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>The resolution here before us asks us to say &ldquo;That Dáil Eireann approves of the report of the Commonwealth Conference, 1930, and recommends the Executive Council to take such steps as they think fit to give effect thereto.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The report of the Commonwealth Conference is a bulky document, containing 22 sections, and all the discussion which has taken place up to the present has had relation merely to one of these 22 sections&mdash;Inter-Imperial relations.  I want to know from the Minister, or from anybody, why it has come before us in this particular form and why we should be asked to approve not only of Imperial relations about which we have heard so much, but of the principles involved in the other 21 sections.  We are asked, for instance, to approve of the recommendations regarding the quota of wheat and the quota of commodities other than wheat, an Imperial Shipping Committee, the Antartic and a whole range of recommendations and statements of one kind or another, including the statement by the Minister for Industry and Commerce on the policy for industrial development in the Free State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am not prepared to take that document and to say that I approve of everything that is in it as I am asked by this Resolution.  That is the position in which I find myself placed. We are asked to bind ourselves beforehand to recommend the Executive Council to take such steps as they think fit to give effect thereto, not alone to this Act, that has been discussed so much, but to everything in the report.  I think it is quite unfair to the House to ask us to commit ourselves beforehand to an approval of everything that is in that document. That is what the resolution means, and because it asks us to do that is one reason why I am not prepared to vote for this resolution.  If the Executive Council thought fit to take steps with regard to any one of these recommendations they could take these steps and seek approval for <Col N="2350" /> the step or steps taken in regard to any of these recommendations.  Their action would always be open to question in this House, but to put before us a document of this kind, and ask us in bulk beforehand, and without any explanation with regard to twenty-one of these recommendations and paragraphs, to accept them and approve of them and commit ourselves to them is asking too much altogether.</P>
    <P>With regard to the matter about which there has been so much discussion, there is one point which I made before when it was under discussion here, and which I make again, and that is, I think it is not right that this Parliament should put itself into the position of asking the British Parliament to pass legislation to put us into a position which we already claimed and have always claimed we are in.  I think it is something almost tantamount to admitting that up to the present, at any rate, we were not in that position, if we formally, by an Act of this Parliament, ask Great Britain to pass legislation which will put us into the position which we claim to have been in already.</P>
    <P>I do not agree, however, with the line taken by Deputy O'Kelly that this action which has been taken is in effect more closely associating us with Great Britain than was the position, say, eight or nine years ago.  I think anybody who has followed the course of events from 1921 up to the present must acknowledge that there has been progress towards a position of greater independence for this State than was the position in 1921.  I think there can be no doubt on that point whatever. I think there can be no doubt that, so far as the right of the British Government to interfere in the affairs of this State is in question, any such right has very definitely disappeared. I would suggest that statements such as Deputy O'Kelly made here yesterday are not helpful and are not in the long run the wisest kind of statements to make.  They may be taken down in writing and used as evidence against him.  It may be that, at some time or another, Deputy O'Kelly will find himself in the position of asserting the independence of this State, and it may be awkward for him if he <Col N="2351" /> finds the statements which he made yesterday evening rooted up and quoted against him.  For that reason, I rather think that the line we should take would be to assert what we believe to be the truth, that the British Government have no right whatever to interfere in the affairs of this State, any more than this Government or Parliament have the right to interfere in the affairs of Great Britain.  That is the position as I understand it and believe it to be.</P>
    <P>I will go further and say, what I have said before and what I think cannot be denied, that if this Parliament of the elected representatives of the Irish Free State were to say in the morning that they would have no further associations of any kind with Great Britain as a member of the British Commonwealth, there is nothing to prevent them doing that. I have never heard any section of our people in this State making any such declaration, and I do not think it is likely they will do it.  When the wider question is opened up, there is a different problem altogether that we have to face.  I agree and accept the statement that has been made, and that I have made on another occasion, that no one has a right to put a limit to the march of a nation.  As I say, in what has been done during the last nine years, I can see nothing that I would admit, in any case, to be putting a limit to the march of the nation towards its ultimate goal.</P>
    <P>I am objecting to this resolution on the grounds which I have mentioned, first, because we are asked, not alone to signify our consent to this particular inter-Imperial Relations paragraph, but the other twenty-one paragraphs which are included, and about which we have not heard a word from Ministers.  I do not know why that procedure should be necessary.  No explanation has been given as to why we should be asked to approve in this formal manner of this report and everything in the report.  And for the second reason, that I do not believe we should put ourselves in the position of asking the British Parliament to pass legislation to put us in the <Col N="2352" /> position that we have always declared we are already in.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>We have heard some five or six declarations on the report, or at least on that part of the report which has been discussed, because that is really the only part which is relevant to the motion.  There were many declarations on the other side as to their aims and objects.  But I want to point out that in all the speeches which have been made, so full of fervour, and, having at any rate the pretence of enthusiasm, there has been a rather careful picking of phrases.  Deputy O'Kelly would like us to restore Ireland's proper national status and undo the work of the last ten years. He spoke about the degradation and the partitioning of the country, and said that it had been forced into the British Empire.  The latter I deny. Deputy Lemass made a speech which, I suppose, was intended to satisfy those who have had their fears his principles were weakening in the last year or so so.  If that speech is searched through I do not think the stalwart Republicans of the country are going to find a great deal to chuckle over in the statement of the Deputy.  Deputy de Valera advanced cautiously to the use of the word &ldquo;republic&rdquo; in the phrase that certain people would &ldquo;ultimately establish a republic if they can.&rdquo; And that is all in relation to the document that is before us and the approval that is requested for a particular thing! Such approval has been questioned.  Deputy O'Connell had a special point, that there are many more items in the report than Part VI. The approval I seek is, in the main, in reference to Part VI, and if it refers to any other part at all, it is only where those parts contain recommendations, and only so far as these recommendations have application to this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>To Part VI the objection is made that we are asking the British Government by statute to give us a position which we assert we already have.  That has to be read in conjunction with what I said in introducing the motion.  We do make that assertion as to our present position.  I went into great <Col N="2353" /> detail to show that we were joined in a particular association with other nations, some which wanted this provision, wanted to have their position made absolutely and entirely clear. Hence, we joined with them, having made our position clear with regard to the statute, and having specially got the declaratory side of it agreed to at least in one particular.</P>
    <P>There is, I am told, a fundamental objection to a British statute.  What one British Parliament can do by statute another British Parliament can undo, and, therefore, the whole situation is jeopardised.  How is the Republic going to be established, if certain people can ever ultimately establish it?  Is it going to be jeopardised if a British statute takes cognisance of it, in so far as the setting up of a republic means the separation of a particular piece of territory which the British at present, as evidenced by their Parliamentary associations with it, believe belongs to them?  How are the British going to deal, say, with the Six Counties, if and when a republic is declared and established for all Ireland?  Are Deputies going to state, if the British do pass an Act of renunciation with regard to the Six Counties, that that is not going to be accepted because the moment after they pass that they can repeal it?  Deputy Law dealt with that.  General Hertzog dealt with that.  We dealt with that in the discussions in the Imperial Conference, and in those discussions the act of renunciation with regard to America was on occasions referred to.  General Hertzog on one occasion said that if he was asked to face up to the theory that the legislative supremacy of the British Parliament was always there and that by a legislative Act it could to-morrow take over again the American colonies, he could afford to laugh at such a theory and could afford not to pay attention to it.  Further, the statement was made by several Delegates to the Conference, and joined in by General Hertzog, that if there was ever any question of a British Parliament later repealing this statute of Westminster which the Dominions now wanted, the answer was that the moment that repeal was attempted the <Col N="2354" /> whole Commonwealth of Nations would be broken up.</P>
    <P>There would be precedents for secession all over the Commonwealth if and when that happened.  No British Government of this day would dare to declare that its Parliament had the right of itself to legislate for any of the members of the Commonwealth. Deputies opposite have, however, to get themselves out of the dilemma of their own making.  The freedom of the country has to be got some way. It is to be got by force apparently, because, we understand from Deputy de Valera, America got her freedom in that way, and it is the only way, apparently, that freedom can be got. When we are in possession of superior force and able to impose our will upon the English people, then a republic and separatism and everything else is to be achieved.  How is it to be recognised? The British Government must recognise that fact for themselves.  Is the whole of the new situation to be jeopardised simply because there must be an Act of the British Parliament recognising it, and if it is not to be so jeopardised, then how is what is happening here jeopardised by the fact that there is to be a statute passed at Westminster, particularly when that statute is limited to certain items, and particularly when this statute has been demanded by the nations of the Commonwealth, most of whom are not supposed to be, nationally, so far advanced as we are, and yet demand that statute now as of right.  The situation facing the British is that if that were not passed as requested, in the face of the request of the Dominions, or if it were repealed afterwards, then the Commonwealth of Nations is definitely at an end.</P>
    <P>The position we find ourselves in at the moment is this: The only difference which I can see in the constitutional position of the Free State now and what it might be under a declared republic amounts to this&mdash;that at the moment there is a constitutional monarch who is supposed to represent the will of the people of this country. In the other situation there will be somebody called the President, also supposed to represent the will of the people of this country.  And nobody <Col N="2355" /> has dared to say that at present the constitutional relationship between this country and the King is such that the King can deviate in the slightest way from the advice tendered to him on any and every point by the Government of this country&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Suppose he did.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Suppose he did. Suppose the President of the Republic also failed to recognise the will of the country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Keep to the King.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The situation applies to both, the one is as likely to err as the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>And suppose he did.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Deputy to face up to the same question with regard to the President.  Then the situation would have changed and&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be easily dealt with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>And the other would also be easily dealt with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>How?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the point at which to make it clear you are not having that interference.  The situation as accepted is that of a constitutional monarchy in which the monarch definitely obeys the will of the people, and if he ceases to obey, he ceases to be constitutionally monarch.  As to what is likely to happen in the future let us look at what has happened in the past five or ten years.  There has been no deviation from the advice tendered to the King.  Let us look over ten years after all the bogies that were raised. We were told that legislation passed would not be signed; the King would intervene at almost every point; he would delay legislation.  Yet never was there an example given by anybody where the King deviated from the advice tendered to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Because there was never an occasion where there was any likelihood that he would.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good; there never was an occasion&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>You were doing what was required of you by the other side.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2356" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The situation is such that for ten years the will of the Irish people has been made effective; that there never was any reason even for the King to attempt to deviate from that binding advice.  Ten years!  and the possibly worst ten years constitutionally in the history of this country, when it was fitting itself into the new situation and yet no example of deviation can be quoted! So far from it that Deputy de Valera now says there was no reason for any deviation.  The President or the King, both subject to the will of the people, as expressed through their Parliamentary institutions, yet we are going to have more trouble, something approaching chaos if necessary, in order to get the difference established as between a President obeying the will of the people and a King obeying the will of the people!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not the difference.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us get to the Republic.  Deputy O'Kelly kept to the phrase about the national status of the country and the degradation and partitioning of it.  Deputy Lemass was on much the same lines. I do not think Deputy Lemass breathed the horrid word &ldquo;Republic&rdquo; throughout his long speech.  If Deputy O'Kelly did so it was in a very halting way, and Deputy de Valera only used the phrase &ldquo;the Republic that is to be established ultimately if people can.&rdquo;  There are certain signs said to evidence the non-existence of the Republic which I suppose the Deputy will recognise as such.  If the Deputy is empowered to do what he can are we to understand that the Republic is going to be declared?  Will Deputy O'Kelly declare the Republic if Deputy de Valera is not strong enough to do it, and if neither will, will Deputy Lemass step into the breach and say that he at any rate will declare the Republic if and when that Party are empowered by the people to carry on the Government of this country.  What are the marks of the non-existence of the Republic?  We have heard them frequently.  They are numerous, but there are at least five items which have been prominently put <Col N="2357" /> before us: the Oath, the King, the Governor-General, the Six Counties situation, the presence of certain troops in this country, and I take it from to-day's debate, even if all these were cleared up the final position is prejudiced as long as it was recognised by an Act of the British Parliament.  Is Deputy Valera, if empowered to do what he can for this country at an election, going to declare a Republic, which involves getting rid of the King, removing the Governor - General, abolishing the Oath, taking over of the Six Counties and forcing the evacuation of places at present occupied by certain troops?  And all this is to be achieved while the British Parliament is to be forbidden to regularise the new position by a statute.  Will Deputy O'Kelly say these are his aims, if Deputy de Valera defaults, or will Deputy Lemass make up for the weakness of his two strong brethren and say that is what his aim and object is, and that aim and object will be achieved as soon as he gets power?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. Gorey Mr. Gorey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gorey</NameTxt>
      <P>And there is silence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Republic when they can.  Deputy Corry interrupts me.  Possibly Deputy Corry will. The country, at any rate, is not lost. There is one man that is going to tackle the Oath, the Governor-General, the King, the Six Counties situation, and the troops in certain parts of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJohnCorry" hpid="Mr. Corry Mr. Corry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corry</NameTxt>
      <P>And the Freemason rule.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJohnCorry" hpid="Mr. Corry Mr. Corry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corry</NameTxt>
      <P>And Cole and the Orange drums.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>You might as well declare a &ldquo;grand slam&rdquo; and go down magnificently.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJohnCorry" hpid="Mr. Corry Mr. Corry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corry</NameTxt>
      <P>The Freemasons are stronger than ever, as Cole said in Cavan.  Do not forget that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>With all the enthusiasm that has been put into the speeches to-day, Deputies opposite have not given us a declaration of what they are likely to do if and when they are empowered by the Irish people to do something.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy O'Kelly made the assertion last night that he took no oath entering this Dáil.  He did.  Not merely did he take it, but he signed an unreserved <Col N="2358" /> declaration prior to taking it that he would do so, and he sits here as much an oath-bound member of the Assembly as any other member of it.  But he and other members of that Party have, by their conduct, put themselves in such a position that they are the last people in the world who in honesty should try to deal with the British Government on the question of the oath.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has broken silence at last.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That will be done. That is one of the things, and the others&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>As they can be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, as they can be done.  It may take ten years or&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>It may.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>So that the rate of speeding up is all that is in question. Ten years' progress there has been, but the Deputy was going to do all these things at the moment he became empowered.  It is now a question as to how and when they can be done.  That attitude of progress is the attitude most of us have on these things.  The pace alone is the difference between us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The Vice-President&mdash; is that his attitude?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, the Vice-President's attitude, in the circumstances in which he conceives the British Commonwealth of Nations to stand, agrees, as between that status and the sort of Republic the Deputy is going to declare either one or ten years after he may get power, that there is no difference between them.  Fianna Fáil, by taking the oath, did not consider that they were setting bounds to the march of that part of the nation which they represent. Neither did any of us.  Yet that is one of the causes of the dispute between us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We are told by Deputy de Valera that there is an army in this country supplied with British ammunition to shoot down certain people.  There is an army in this country.  That is a fact.  They would be of very little use <Col N="2359" /> if they had no ammunition.  That is another fact.  They will get ammunition wherever they can get it cheapest, and nobody would object more than Deputies opposite, when the economy fit was on them, if they bought it dearer.  That ammunition would certainly have to be used against people who do not obey the will of the majority of the people, if they go out and try to subvert the will of the majority of the people by force.  Dragging in British ammunition only reveals a weakness in argument.  There is the ordinary situation that any ordinary State will find itself in&mdash;that it has an army, that that army is going to be at the will of the majority of the people of the country, and is going to prevent any attempt to subvert State institutions by force.</P>
    <P>Deputy de Valera wound up by saying that he regards this country as a separate nation and a separate people in no way dependent upon British statutes.  I have said that at three Imperial Conferences, asserted the separateness of the nationhood of this country, the separateness of the people in a lot of their ideals and in the generality of their make-up and asserted that we were never in the past and were not going to be dependent on a British statute for that separateness. So in that I agree with the Deputy, but is that in conflict with the documents before the people to-day? Deputy Lemass thinks that we might have come to the point of separating up the King and so have achieved six kingdoms.  I wonder how far we are off that?  I think the division as between that situation and that in which we now find ourselves is very slight indeed.  There is the single person of the King.  We might say there is a single physical crown upon his head, but outside these two items there is no question of unity as between members of the Commonwealth. The King moves and acts in relation to Irish affairs as Irish Ministers tell him to move and act, and nobody else can tell him what to do in relation to Irish affairs, while Irish Ministers cannot tell him anything of what he is to do, except in relation to Irish affairs.  The difference between that and the six kingdoms specially <Col N="2360" /> and clearly announced is very slight indeed.  That is where we have progressed from the 1921 point.</P>
    <P>The last thing is the question of the Privy Council.  I definitely did not refer to that because that will come up as a separate and special item by itself when legislation is introduced.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>When?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That legislation is in process of preparation.  I do not know when.  It depends entirely&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>When you can, I suppose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Possibly.  It would not be a bad answer to the Deputy who has to-day revealed his weakness in face of the general situation.  But we do know what we can do in this.  It is, however, difficult legislation.  It is very easy to do one small and simple thing in regard to it, but it is not easy to deal with that big question in a comprehensive way.  It may take a considerable time to draw up the Bill required.  As far as the Imperial Conference Report is concerned, as the Deputy said, it left the situation as it was.  I agree, but his view of the situation as it was is not likely to be the same as my view of it. What was the situation?  The 1926 Conference Report states it.  We brought this matter up at the 1929 Conference. It was not quite appropriate to that discussion.  It was brought up again in 1930 and there is nothing in that Report for or against the 1926 position and the 1926 position, as far as the principle was concerned, was quite satisfactory to us.  The matter was definitely discussed in 1930, and remembering that discussion, I would like to say that there is no British Government in existence or likely to be in existence for many years, which would dare to say to the Commonwealth as a whole that if it wants to get rid of the Privy Council that wish cannot be accepted.  Into that situation we will fit our particular case and fit the particular legislation we have to deal with it when we consider it suitable.  That will be as early as we can get the question thoroughly considered and get legislation properly brought forward.</P>
      <P>Question put.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="2361" />
      <Col N="2362" /> The Dáil divided: Tá, 63; Níl, 46.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Aird, William P.<br />Alton, Ernest Henry.<br />Beckett, James Walter.<br />Bennett, George Cecil.<br />Blythe, Ernest.<br />Brennan, Michael.<br />Brodrick, Seán.<br />Byrne, John Joseph.<br />Carey, Edmund.<br />Cole, John James.<br />Collins-O'Driscoll, Mrs. Margt.<br />Conlon, Martin.<br />Connolly, Michael P.<br />Cosgrave, William T.<br />Craig, Sir James.<br />Daly, John.<br />Davis, Michael.<br />Doherty, Eugene.<br />Dolan, James N.<br />Doyle, Peadar Seán.<br />Duggan, Edmund John.<br />Dwyer, James.<br />Egan, Barry M.<br />Esmonde, Osmond Thos. Grattan.<br />Fitzgerald, Desmond.<br />Good, John.<br />Gorey, Denis J.<br />Hassett, John J.<br />Heffernan, Michael R.<br />Hennigan, John.<br />Henry, Mark.<br />Holohan, Richard.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Jordan, Michael.<br />Keogh, Myles.<br />Law, Hugh Alexander.<br />Leonard, Patrick.<br />Lynch, Finian.<br />Mathews, Arthur Patrick.<br />McDonogh, Martin.<br />McFadden, Michael Og.<br />McGilligan, Patrick.<br />Mongan, Joseph W.<br />Mulcahy, Richard.<br />Myles, James Sproule.<br />Nally, Martin Michael.<br />Nolan, John Thomas.<br />O'Connell, Richard.<br />O'Connor, Bartholomew.<br />O'Leary, Daniel.<br />O'Mahony, The.<br />O'Sullivan, Gearóid.<br />O'Sullivan, John Marcus.<br />Reynolds, Patrick.<br />Rice, Vincent.<br />Roddy, Martin.<br />Shaw, Patrick W.<br />Sheehy, Timothy (West Cork)<br />Thrift, William Edward.<br />Tierney, Michael.<br />White, John.<br />White, Vincent Joseph.<br />Wolfe, George.<br />Wolfe, Jasper Travers.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Aiken, Frank.<br />Allen, Denis.<br />Anthony, Richard.<br />Blaney, Neal.<br />Boland, Gerald.<br />Boland, Patrick.<br />Bourke, Daniel.<br />Brady, Seán.<br />Briscoe, Robert.<br />Buckley, Daniel.<br />Carty, Frank.<br />Clancy, Patrick.<br />Clery, Michael.<br />Colbert, James.<br />Corkery, Dan.<br />Corish, Richard.<br />Corry, Martin John.<br />Crowley, Tadhg.<br />Derrig, Thomas.<br />De Valera, Eamon.<br />Doyle, Edward.<br />Everett, James.<br />Fahy, Frank.<br />Flinn, Hugo.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Fogarty, Andrew.<br />Gorry, Patrick J.<br />Harris, Thomas.<br />Hayes, Seán.<br />Houlihan, Patrick.<br />Jordan, Stephen.<br />Kennedy, Michael Joseph.<br />Kilroy, Michael.<br />Lemass, Seán F.<br />Little, Patrick John.<br />Maguire, Ben.<br />MacEntee, Seán.<br />Moore, Séamus.<br />O'Connell, Thomas J.<br />O'Dowd, Patrick Joseph.<br />O'Kelly, Seán T.<br />O'Reilly, Thomas.<br />Ryan, James.<br />Sheehy, Timothy (Tipp.).<br />Smith, Patrick.<br />Tubridy, John.<br />Walsh, Richard.<br /><br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Deputies Duggan and P.S. Doyle; Níl, Deputies G. Boland and Allen.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Question declared carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Report of the Commonwealth Conference. - Adaptation" RHead="of Enactments Bill, 1931&mdash;Fifth Stage">
    <Title>Report of the Commonwealth Conference. - Adaptation of Enactments Bill, 1931&mdash;Fifth Stage.</Title>
    <Col N="2363" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: That the Bill do now pass.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Report of the Commonwealth Conference. - Fisheries (Revision" RHead="of Loans) Bill, 1931&mdash;Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Report of the Commonwealth Conference. - Fisheries (Revision of Loans) Bill, 1931&mdash;Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Minister for Lands and Fisheries (Mr. Lynch) Fionán Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Lands and Fisheries (Mr. Lynch)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: That the Bill be received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>With the consent of the House, I suggest that the final stage be taken now.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
      <P>Question: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass,&rdquo; put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill has been certified by the Ceann Comhairle as a Money Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Financial Resolution. -" RHead="Tariff on Harness Leather">
    <Title>Financial Resolution. - Tariff on Harness Leather.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>1.  That a customs duty of an amount equal to twenty per cent. of the value of the article shall be charged, levied, and paid on all harness leather, whether dressed or undressed, of any of the following classes imported into Saorstát Eireann on or after the 17th day of July, 1931, and before the 17th day of July, 1936, that is to say:&mdash; harness hides or parts thereof, harness sides or parts thereof, harness backs or parts thereof, harness bellies or parts thereof, harness shoulders or parts thereof.</P>
      <P>2.  That, notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing paragraph of this Resolution, the duty mentioned in that paragraph shall not be charged or levied on patent leather, chrome tanned leather, dressed collar hides or parts thereof, or dressed bridle butts or parts thereof.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>3.  That a customs duty of an amount equal to twenty per cent. of the value of the article shall be charged, levied, and paid on the following articles imported into Saorstát Eireann on or after the 17th day of July, 1931, <Col N="2364" /> and before the 17th day of July, 1936, that is to say, all harness, whether completely or partially manufactured, and all parts of such harness other than parts which do not consist of or contain leather and at the time of importation are not attached to any harness, whether completely or partially manufactured, or to any part of such harness or consisting of leather.</P>
    <P>4.  That the provisions of Section 8 of the Finance Act, 1919, shall apply to the duties mentioned in this Resolution with the substitution of the expression &ldquo;Saorstát Eireann&rdquo; for the expression &ldquo;Great Britain and Ireland&rdquo; and as though articles chargeable with either of those duties were mentioned in the Second Schedule to that Act and were so mentioned as goods to which three-fourths of the full rate was thereby made applicable as a preferential rate.</P>
    <P>5.  That the value of any article for the purposes of this Resolution shall be taken to be the price which an importer would give for the article if the article were delivered, freight and insurance paid, in bond at the place of importation, and duty shall be paid on that value as fixed by the Revenue Commissioners.</P>
    <P>6.  It is hereby declared that it is expedient in the public interest that this Resolution shall have statutory effect under the Provisional Collection of Taxes Act, 1927 (No. 7 of 1927).</P>
    <P>This resolution follows the application which was made by the Irish Free State Tanners' Federation for the imposition of a Customs duty of 25 per cent. ad valorem on sole, insole and harness leather and manufactured harness imported into Saorstát Eireann. The opposition to the application came chiefly from the Irish Free State Boot Manufacturers' Association. There were five tanneries existing at the time of the application.  Of these, the principal one is in Limerick and has a present capacity of 1,200 hides per week.  There is another in Thomastown with a capacity of 50 hides per week, one in Clonmel with a capacity <Col N="2365" /> of 75 hides, and one in Ballytore with a capacity of 100 hides per week.  The three smaller ones manufacture only harness leather, and in the case of the principal one, 60 per cent. of the output consists of harness leather.  The maximum capacity of the four factories would be about four-fifths of the requirement of the Saorstát.  The number of people employed was 65 in May, 1928, and 44 in March, 1931.  If the tanneries were developed not only to their maximum capacity but so as to meet the full requirement of the Saorstát, the possible employment would be from 300 to 400 men.</P>
    <P>The boot industry, from which the opposition came is, of course, much more important.  For instance, in the boot factories in the Saorstát, in September, 1926, there were 973 workers; September, 1927, 1,019 workers; September, 1928, 1,074 workers; September, 1929, 1,128 workers; and September, 1930, 1,227 workers.  There has been an increase in the output.  In 1926, there were 501,840 pairs.  In 1929, there were 521,340 pairs.  In the year 1930, the number of pairs reached 700,000.  The development, so far, in the boot industry has been chiefly in heavy nailed boots.  Even of these, the Saorstát factories have only captured about 40 per cent. of the market. Taking into account all classes of footwear, only about 10 per cent. of the home requirements are being supplied by output.  In the case of heavy nailed boots, the better class has been captured, so that the market that remains to be captured is chiefly the cheaper line.  In the case of welted and machine-sewn boots, on the other hand, the progress has been in the cheaper lines and the prospects of the development of the industry depend on getting cheaper leather.  To put the relative importance of the tanning and boot-making industry in another way: the capital invested in the tanning industry is about £75,000; in boot factories it is over £200,000.  The employees are over 1,200 in one and under 100 in the other.  At the conclusion of the public sittings, the applicants intimated that they were prepared to amend the application in respect of the rate of duty by substituting 15 per cent. ad valorem for the original <Col N="2366" /> 25 per cent.  This Resolution proposes to give a duty of 20 per cent., with imperial preference at the rate of 15 per cent.  For effective purposes, therefore, the rate of duty proposed in this Resolution will be the rate asked for by the applicants when they amended their application.  The following is the summary of the conclusions of the Commission:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;In our report on the schedule to the Tariff Commission Act, 1926, we give this conclusion in a more detailed form.  If the application could be granted in full without involving any serious prejudice to other important trades and industries, the development of the tanning industry would not, in our opinion, assume the proportions suggested by the applicants.  The present output of the Saorstát tanneries is approximately 270 hides per week equivalent to 13,500 hides per annum.  We doubt whether with their present premises, and assuming that a market could be found for the leather produced, a greater output could be achieved than 1,200 hides per week equivalent to 60,000 hides per annum.  We estimate that this output would give employment to no more than 120 persons.  The Saorstát boot manufacturers, having regard in particular to the strong competition which they have to meet must use many varieties of sole and insole leather not produced in Saorstát Eireann.  Most of the sole and insole leather which they and their competitors use is made from dry hides.  The applicants do not find it expedient to manufacture leather from dry hides and made it clear that they have no intention of so doing.  Even some boot manufacturers who use wet hide leather cannot obtain leather suitable for their purpose from the Saorstát tanneries.  If the application were granted, the Saorstát boot manufacturers would still use imported leather.  The increased cost of imported leather resulting from the imposition of a tariff would be reflected in the cost of the manufacture of boots and would adversely affect an important and developing industry.  When the evidence at the <Col N="2367" /> public sittings had been taken, the applicants, recognising the validity of the case made by the nine boot manufacturers who appeared in opposition to the application intimated that they were willing to amend their application so as to exclude from its scope the sole and insole leather required by these manufacturers. If the nine boot manufacturers were allowed to import their sole and insole leather free of duty, a similar concession would, in equity, have to be given to small factories and hand bootmakers.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That is elaborated.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;We are satisfied that the case for granting the application as far as sole leather and insole leather are concerned has not been established by the applicants.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;As regards harness leather, different considerations arise.  The Saorstát tanneries produce harness hides, harness sides, harness backs, harness shoulders and harness bellies quite suitable for the purpose for which such leather is required.  This leather is of good quality and is sold at a price which compares favourably with the price of imported harness leather of similar type.  Furthermore, native hides, whilst not suitable for heavy sole leather are eminently suitable for the manufacture of harness leather.  We are satisfied that harness leather of the types mentioned above is being manufactured efficiently by the Saorstát tanneries, and that the tanneries are capable of producing such leather in quantities sufficient to meet the whole of the home demand.  A tariff on harness leather would give them a reasonable opportunity of capturing the home market without imposing an undue burden on the consumer or adversely affecting any other trade or industry if accompanied by a tariff on manufactured harness.  In the event of a tariff being imposed on harness leather, it would be necessary to impose a counterbalancing duty on manufactured harness so as to ensure that Saorstát manufacturers of harness would not be placed in a disadvantageous position as compared <Col N="2368" /> with their competitors.  The placing of a restriction on the importation of manufactured harness would also help to create an increased demand for home-produced harness leather.  We recommend the imposition of a customs duty of 20 per cent. ad valorem on dressed and undressed harness leather of the following classes, viz., harness hides, harness sides, harness backs, harness bellies and harness shoulders, or parts thereof, excluding patent leathers, dressed collar hides, bridle butts and chrome backs.  We recommend the imposition of a customs duty of 20 per cent. ad valorem on manufactured harness or parts thereof, excluding all unattached non-leather parts.  We recommend that there should be an imperial preferential rate equal to three-fourths of the full rate.  We recommend that these duties should be imposed for a period of five years.  We do not recommend the imposition of a customs duty on sole and insole leather or leather intended for the manufacture of machinery belting.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The tariff imposed on harness does not include saddlery.  It is difficult to know what is the annual importation of harness as distinct from saddlery. The two combined are in the neighbourhood of about £20,000 per annum. What this tariff will do is, it will give the Irish tanneries security in the harness leather market, and harness leather is at present their principal output.  It should, by giving them security there, give them increased output and make it possible for at least the one tannery which deals with sole leather to do better in the manufacture of sole leather.  As the Commission points out, it would not be possible for any one tannery to supply the various classes of sole leather required, but if it is helped in other directions it may be able to do considerably better than it has been doing in respect to sole leather.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that any useful purpose would be served, in the absence of the report on which the Resolution is based, in delaying the Dáil discussing the Resolution.  I take it that the Report of the Tariff <Col N="2369" /> Commission will be circulated immediately to Deputies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>In the course of a few days.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>When the Resolution comes up on Report an opportunity will be available for Deputies to express their views on it.  I take it that by that time the information made available to the Tariff Commission will be in the hands of Deputies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'Connell Mr. T.J. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is hardly fair to bring in this Resolution on the last day of the Session.  The tariff will be in operation for three months or more before Deputies will have an opportunity of discussing it. We have not the evidence before us on which the Resolution is founded.  The only evidence before us is contained in the few extracts that the Minister for Finance read when moving the Resolution.  It seems to me that this tariff is going to put an increased burden on people who can least afford it, that is the small farmer&mdash;in fact, all farmers&mdash;as well as men in a small way in the cities and towns who now use horses and donkeys as a means of transport.  It is not going to fall on the hunting or racing community, because saddlery is definitely ruled out.</P>
      <P>The boot manufacturers made their case successfully against the imposition of a tariff on sole and insole leather. I do not suppose that the farming community was represented at or took the opportunity of putting their case before the Tariff Commission.  From what the Minister has said it seems to me that the price of harness will undoubtedly be raised because he said it was necessary to put a customs duty on imported manufactured harness in order that the harness manufacturers here would not be placed at a disadvantage by having to pay more for their raw material.  If they have to pay more for their raw material naturally they will have to charge more for their manufactured goods.  In that way an increased impost will fall on those who have to purchase harness.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not want to go into this matter at any great length except that I would like to be satisfied that we would wait until we have the findings of the Commission <Col N="2370" /> before us and the evidence before us.  I would like to be satisfied that the game is worth the candle in this matter.  If I think it is I will support it but I would only do so again expressing the belief that I do not think that will go very far, any more than it has gone in the boot industry, to establish a tanning industry on a proper basis in this country.  I do not know the number of men employed but if it only gets on at the rate at which the boot industry has progressed I am of the belief that the tariff on this is not going to do a very great deal.  In any case, we can only wait until we have the report before us and we will be in a better position then to judge of what our action should be in the matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to join with Deputy O'Connell in entering a strong objection to the Minister bringing in this proposal on the last day of the session.  I do not know that there is any reason why it should be brought in at this particular moment.  It seems to be a peculiar thing on the part of the Minister for Finance that he appears to avail of these moments when the House is engaged on a number of other important matters to try and get through these Resolutions.  I do not know whether it is unfortunate on the part of the Minister that he cannot avoid this or whether it is a deliberate policy to bring these matters forward in that particular way.  At all events, it is most unfortunate.</P>
      <P>I think it is one of the outstanding weaknesses in connection with our Parliamentary system that we are called upon to approve of these particular tariffs before we have any opportunity whatever of looking into the evidence; in fact, before the evidence is before us at all we are asked to give a verdict.  That seems to be the same in connection with every tariff.  First the approval of the House has to be gained and afterwards we see the evidence.  It seems to be an astounding way of achieving a change of tariff policy.  Judging by what we have done in this direction in the past.  I am not at all happy about allowing these tariffs through without discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In connection with the last tariff <Col N="2371" /> which we had before us there was a somewhat similar proposal to this one in that it impinged upon existing tariffed industries.  We had to make an alteration in the tariff on imported cloth, and we were rushed into a conclusion on that particular subject though some of us doubted the wisdom of that proposal.  We found almost immediately after that, owing to the hasty way in which the tariff was put forward, that it was going to injure seriously the clothing industry and do far more injury in connection with employment in the clothing industry than it was going to do good in the matter of giving employment in the manufacture of cloth.</P>
    <P>With that sort of experience before us it is unwise to rush into these proposals without due consideration.  It appears to me, as one of those who does not know a whole lot about this particular industry beyond what is known in a general way, that it will be very difficult to separate the leather used in connection with the bootmaking industry from the leather used in the harness-making industry.  I am afraid that it will be found that in our efforts to protect the harness-making industry we are going to add to the cost of the manufacture in connection with the boot industry.  I am interested in this matter from the point of view of the common welfare of the industries of the country.  I have stressed before in this House the serious situation that has arisen in connection with the increase in the cost of living in this country.  The cost of living in this country is very much higher than it is in adjoining countries.  That particular factor, though it has been stressed several times during the recent debates, does not, I believe, get the attention that it ought to get.  This country lives by its ability to export agricultural produce to the most competitive market in the world.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>Everything that adds to our difficulty in selling our goods in that particular market is against the interests of this State.  As we add to the cost of living in this country we add to the cost of production of <Col N="2372" /> agricultural produce, and as we add to the cost of agricultural produce we add to the difficulties of the farmer in selling his produce in the most competitive market in the world.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any other section in the community but the farmers to be considered?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>The farming section of the community is the section on which most of us are living and the Deputy amongst the others is living on the farmers.  This is not the most opportune moment to discuss this subject, but there are principles lying behind these proposals that do not get the attention they deserve from the Deputies here.  As far as I am concerned I am prepared to offer a protest against this proposal.  It is a proposal like the other proposals in reference to tariffs that will add to the cost of living, and that will be followed by similar results.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Whatever one may think of the fitness of bringing forward this Resolution at this late hour in our proceedings we can have only one opinion as to the effect of the Report of the Tariff Commissioners.  It means that the Executive Council have decided that there is to be no leather industry in the Saorstát.  One more negative is to be added to the other negatives.  There is to be no coach-building industry, there is to be no paper-making industry, there is to be no flour-milling industry, and there is to be no leather-making industry in the country.  God knows how many other &ldquo;no's&rdquo; are to be added.</P>
      <P>When the Minister said that the effect of giving a tariff on harness leather is going to help on the tanning industry and certain sole leather, of course, he is not serious.  He is not to be taken seriously at all.  The effect of the decision with regard to sole leather will be that those who are at present engaged in trying to manufacture it will close down.  The one little bit of leather industry that will then be left in the country will be the manufacture of harness leather. That is an extraordinary position for a country that is producing so much raw material for the manufacture of leather.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2373" /> The Minister for Finance, in face of his repeated assertions that there is no room in this country for an increase in the agricultural population, must have a very despairing outlook with regard to the future of this country. The Minister who holds that there is no room for an addition to the agricultural population ought surely be extra enthusiastic about the establishment of industry.  But the Minister has not shown that he regards his announcement to-day as having any effect on the general economic position. Whereas, of course, it means that he has really nothing to offer to the people of the country.  One industry after another is finding it impossible to exist, thanks to this wonderful Commission which the Minister has established.  There can be little industrial future and no agricultural future from that policy for the people to look forward to in this country, so far as one can see.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Deputy Moore that the statement that the Minister has read out from the Tariff Commission is most disappointing. There is one very efficient tannery in this country&mdash;at Limerick.  That tannery seems to be the only tannery which is making leather for boots.  I happen to know that that tannery is a very efficient tannery, and there can be no doubt whatever about the quality of its products.  I think that we should have further information as to the position of the boot industry if the boot industry in the Irish Free State is to succeed in capturing a substantial portion of the heavy trade in footwear.  I see no reason why they should not be asked to give special support and therefore to absorb a certain proportion of Irish manufactured leather.  Otherwise, we are in the position that we are protecting the boot and shoe industry which is not itself prepared to support another Irish industry.  This is an industry which was protected with the intention of trying to encourage improved production all along the line.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Everybody knows the Irish people have, what we might call, a particular sentimental regard for the tanning industry.  Every small farmer, and <Col N="2374" /> for that matter every small boy, has a weakness for the tanning industry. Practically every town twenty or thirty years ago had a little tannery. We thought when an effort was being made to build up the boot and shoe industry, that it was an essential part of the Government's programme to restore tanneries.  Will this industry in Limerick be allowed to fall through?  I think the people who are interested in that industry will admit that the most the tariff will do will be to enable them to carry on for a few months, or perhaps a year or two.  Deputy Moore pointed out that, as far as the manufacture of boot leather is concerned, the Government has practically decreed that it cannot continue to exist.</P>
    <P>Deputy O'Connell has very rightly stressed the fact that the agricultural population will have to bear the extra cost in this case.  I think Deputy O'Connell might have gone further in connection with that matter.  He claims it to be the policy of the Labour Party that these industries ought to be put on a proper foundation and made more up-to-date; that more capital should be invested in them.  The three existing tanneries are in a very weak position.  Even with this tariff, I doubt whether they will be able to improve their position very much.  I think the Government should intervene with a view to seeing whether they could not reorganise the industry and have machinery installed in order to enable manufacturers to take proper advantage of the tariff without imposing an undue burden upon the community.  I do not think Deputy Good is quite right when he says that the effect of this tariff will mean a general burden.  I think the cost of living here is due to the bad system of distribution.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>It is aggravated by 15 per cent. tariff on boots.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>If the members of the Dublin Chamber of Commerce would only direct their attention to the question of reducing prices and to the question of profiteering, particularly in the matter of foodstuffs, and also to the question of rent, in which Deputy Good is somewhat interested&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2375" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Deputy Good Deputy Good">
      <NameTxt>Deputy Good</NameTxt>
      <P>Rents must follow costs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;perhaps they would do more good for the community as a whole.  Deputy Good seems to be concerned about the community and possibly he will consider what I have just stated.  With other Deputies, I am disappointed at the manner in which this Resolution is being rushed.  I am very anxious to have the boot industry thoroughly scrutinised, particularly in view of this tariff.  I think we have now reached the point when we should ask those engaged in the boot and shoe industry to do something to help the tanning industry.  Their attitude seems to be simply to declare war on the application of the Tanners' Federation. I think we rather expected they would have a more patriotic outlook in this matter.  I am sorry the Minister has not given us further information which would enable us to discuss the matter in more detail.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the imposition of this tariff and of any tariff that will help to develop industries in this country. I am surprised at the attitude the Labour Party has taken on this tariff question.  If the unemployment problem is ever going to be solved, and I speak as one with some knowledge of economics, it can never be solved without the aid of tariffs.  Whenever a tariff is suggested here, there is a doleful, pitiful cry about the rise in the cost of living.  A rise in the cost of living would be immaterial if sufficient employment were found for the unemployed in this State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When Deputy Good was speaking about this tariff, I was thinking of the effect of it upon the unemployment situation in Dublin.  Deputy Good knows there is a burden on the city through unemployment and that burden has been increasing during the last couple of years until it has reached about £250,000 per annum.  Deputy Good did not mention what effect the lack of employment had on the cost of living or upon the industries in the city and the trade and commerce of the city.  The Dublin Chamber of Commerce is an antiquated organisation from which nothing can be hoped as <Col N="2376" /> far as the development of the country is concerned.  We hear a lot about the farmers and how, if anything is added to the burden of agriculture, our great industry will be killed.  I have no sympathy with that point of view.  Anyone who gives consideration to tariffs is aware that the Danish farmer does not object&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy must confine himself to the question before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I am doing so.  I am entitled to refer to the agricultural industry, because it has already been mentioned, and I am entitled to refer to what is happening the agricultural industry in other countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot have a general debate on tariffs now.  I am sure the Deputy will agree on that.  It would be most unfair to deal with the matter in a general way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to enter upon a general debate.  I merely wish to rebut the statements made by Deputy Good.  He said that the agricultural community will object.  In my opinion the agricultural community are inclined more and more to the imposition of tariffs, and Deputy Good, in his statement is not representing the point of view of the farmers.  The farmers of other countries have accepted these tariffs because they are for the national good.  They have been imposed in France, Denmark and other countries, and the agricultural community have prospered.  When all the tariffs that we have imposed here have reached the stage when they will begin to repay the State, when they begin to operate effectively and advantageously, there is no doubt that the agricultural community here will benefit; the farmers will indirectly receive the same benefits as the rest of the community. To prevent unemployment we must have tariffs.  As long as we permit goods manufactured in foreign countries to enter this country we will have unemployment and a higher cost of living than would follow the imposition of tariffs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the tariff on boots been of benefit to this country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2377" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not discussing the boot tariff now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>We are discussing leather and that is very closely associated with boots.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We are discussing a tariff on harness leather.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I stand behind the Minister for Finance when he introduces this particular tariff.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>I must congratulate Deputy Byrne upon his changed attitude. I am glad to see that we have made at least one convert in the House.  Deputy Byrne has come around to the point of view of those who advocate whole-hog protection for the industries of this country. We have at least made a certain advance when we find the Deputy thinking that way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I have always favoured tariffs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>I think there will be general disappointment when the results of this proposed tariff become known.  As Deputy Derrig pointed out, it will sound the death-knell of the tanning industry.  As regards the amount of leather used in harness-making, it is really very little.  Most of the needs of the farmers are at the moment served by imported second-hand harness.  That has largely taken the place of the harness formerly manufactured here.  Does the Minister not think that the proposed tariff will have the effect of killing harness making, and, incidentally, the tanning industry?  There is no doubt there is a diminishing demand for new harness owing to the increased amount of secondhand harness imported.  I wonder are the members of the Tariff Commission satisfied on that point?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielBourke" hpid="Mr. D. Bourke Mr. D. Bourke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Bourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad the Minister had the courage to impose this tariff. He has adopted at least a portion of the Fianna Fáil policy, and I am proud of that.  At one time in Limerick we had 500 workers engaged; to-day we have only thirty. I believe when this tariff is operative that we will have the number increased again to 500.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2378" />
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no other method of dealing with the imposition of tariffs than the method that has been in operation.  If we allow the matter to be discussed fully before the tariff is imposed, there is bound to be forestalling, with the result that the object of the tariff will be defeated for a considerable period, and perhaps irreparable harm will be done to an industry.  There is no alternative but to ask the Dáil to agree to the imposition of a tariff in the first instance, and then consider the matter on the various stages  the Bill afterwards. It is, perhaps, unfortunate that this comes at the end of the session, but we received the report, and it was felt it would be undesirable to let the matter lie fallow until October. If the Dáil in October does not confirm what is done to-day, any tax collected in the meantime will be repaid. With regard to sole leather, the applicants, when they heard the case of the boot manufacturers, agreed that the requirements of the boot manufacturers should be exempt from the tariff.  The only thing that remained for the Tariff Commission then to consider was the sole leather used by repairers and small manufacturers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely the Tanners' Federation had to make a compromise when the alternative seemed to be that they were not going to get anything.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>That did not arise.  They were making their case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the amount of the imports of sole leather and harness leather?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not give it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister say if the leather for the uppers of boots is exempt?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>All leather for boots is exempt.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>How will they differentiate?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>I believe the Tariff Commission is satisfied, and the Revenue Officers, since they got in touch with the Tariff Commission, are satisfied that it can be done.</P>
      <P>Motion put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Financial Resolution. - Shannon Electricity" RHead="Board&mdash;Motion to Set Up Commission">
    <Title>Financial Resolution. - Shannon Electricity Board&mdash;Motion to Set Up Commission.</Title>
    <Col N="2379" />
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That in the opinion of the Dáil there should be set up at the earliest possible date, but in any event at a date not later than the 1st day of September, 1931, a commission with power to send for persons, papers and documents, and consisting of three persons, of whom one should be an accountant of international reputation as an expert in the economics of state electricity supply undertakings, one an electrical engineer of international reputation as an expert in the organisation and administration of large scale electricity supply undertakings, and one a person actively engaged in a manufacturing enterprise owned, controlled, and operated in Saorstát Eireann, to inquire into and report upon the following:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1)  The actual present position of the Electricity Supply Board in relation to assets, liabilities, expenditure, income, and capital expenditure;</P>
      <P>(2)  as to whether the present rates charged by the Board for electricity are economic having regard to the present and prospective market for electricity in the Free State;</P>
      <P>(3)  the existing staff and organisation of the Board, and whether same or what staff is most conducive to economic administration;</P>
      <P>(4)  the probable future income, expenditure and capital requirements of the Board in relation to the present and all further possible developments of the Shannon Electricity Undertaking;</P>
      <P>(5)  the most suitable policy for the future development and organisation of that undertaking particularly in relation to plant and finance;</P>
      <P>(6)  whether the policy pursued by the Electricity Supply Board over the period from its inception to the 14th May, 1931, was sound in the following regards&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  In the specific use of its capital;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2380" /> (b)  in the prices charged for electricity to different classes of consumers;</P>
    <P>(c)  in forming a monopoly in generation and in distribution;</P>
    <P>(d)  in not selling in bulk to pre-existing undertakers;</P>
    <P>(e)  in engaging in wiring and installation business:</P>
    <P>(f)  in engaging in wholesale and retail trade in appliances;</P>
    <P>(g)  any other matters relative to the present position and future development of electricity supply in Saorstát Eireann that may be useful to the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>As the time available for the discussion of this motion is short, I will be compelled to deal in a rather summary manner with the points involved.  Fortunately, the resolution is a rather lengthy one and, to a certain extent, is self-explanatory.  The resolution, in general terms, is that a Commission of Inquiry should be set up almost immediately, and should consist of three persons: one an accountant of international reputation as an expert in the economics of State electricity supply undertakings; one an electrical engineer, similarly of international reputation as an expert in the organisation and administration of large-scale electricity supply undertakings, and one a person actively engaged in a manufacturing enterprise owned, controlled, and operated in Saorstát Eireann, to inquire and report upon the following matters, which I shall deal with one by one.  As regards the composition of the Commission, our view is that the best constitution would be that we should have two experts dealing with the two technical sides, namely, the accountancy side and the engineering side, and that they should be people who would be accepted as acknowledged authorities upon the two sides of the expert work, namely, an accountant and an engineer.</P>
    <P>The need for an inquiry like this has been stressed so much in the debate that I wonder whether it is necessary to go back on it again.  We feel, at any rate, that it is necessary merely as an act of justice.  Here are men whose reputations are at stake.  We <Col N="2381" /> have been told that they so mismanaged a great enterprise, and left things in such a mess that the Minister for Industry and Commerce professes to be very aggrieved at the situation that has arisen, inasmuch as it is in conflict with all the plans he had for the control and development of this great undertaking.  We want to know the facts of the situation.  The House by a majority has given the Minister authority to dole out the money and, therefore, to control the new Board. He has changed his position absolutely and completely.  Those of us on this side of the House regret that there should have to be a departure from the original scheme.  I shall deal with the merits of that later on, but we think that before a judgment of the kind that is involved should be passed upon men like that they should, at least, get a trial.</P>
    <P>We have had one side of the case presented to us here by the Minister. The people who have the facts are not here to confront him and to point out wherein he erred, if he erred, and where he made misstatements, if he made misstatements.  We have no check on the statements of the Minister except a certain public statement. I say that as an act of justice we ought not to allow ourselves to be put into the position in which we have to pass judgment and destroy, as far as we can destroy, the reputations of people who came in to serve&mdash;I admit they got a salary for it&mdash;the interests of the country.  We ought to be very careful when people come into an undertaking of this kind, take their part in a scheme that is laid out for the general interests of the country, before we pass hasty judgments upon them and keep men of that sort from being prepared in future to enter into the public service in undertakings of this kind.</P>
    <P>Ministers have very often been ready to complain of our attitude as one which would deprive the State of the services of individual citizens of special ability, which it would be in the interests of the State to exploit. I never have denied that if there was anything that would really tend to that it should be discouraged.  But <Col N="2382" /> here is the Minister himself going to do something which does definitely tend to prevent the State from getting the services of citizens who are in an independent position, as business men and so on, to serve the State.  We have had the complaint about Parliamentary representation, that we cannot get the best of our citizens to come forward and to take their part in representative institutions because they are not prepared to face up to the rough and tumble, so to speak, of Parliamentary and public life.  It is a fact that very good men are prevented from giving service to the public interests because they do not want to get into that. They feel that they are much happier at their business.  There is enough of selfishness in most of us to get along without having to battle very often on matters that we consider insignificant. Let us admit that.  Here is a case in which certain businessmen, some of them anyhow, are in a position in which they need not have given this service at all.  They are prepared to give their abilities to the national service in this undertaking and here are we, by an act of ours, on one-sided evidence, going to destroy the reputation of these men, and certainly we are going to do something which will make it more difficult in future to get men of ability to come in and help us in an undertaking of this sort.  I say, therefore, as an act of justice and of wisdom, that if we do want to get the best men in the country to help us in business undertakings we ought not to allow the situation to remain where it is now. We ought to see that they get an opportunity of vindicating themselves, vindicating their ability, possibly proving that they were right and the Minister wrong.  That is the first point.</P>
    <P>Now let us come to it even more narrowly from the business point of view.  It is our duty, in my opinion, to set up this inquiry as we would if we were managing a private enterprise.  I put it to anybody here that if they had a business which was being managed by some committee or group, and if they found that the accounts were <Col N="2383" /> late, and that a statement from somebody in a position in relation to the group like the Minister revealed that there was something wrong on the part of the persons who were in charge, or about the business itself, if they were inclined to give any credence to the information supplied to them by the person in a position like the Minister they would immediately, as an act of ordinary business prudence, see that the matter was investigated home. They would not leave it in the situation in which it is now.  They would not offer their money to the Minister and tell him: &ldquo;Fling that good money after bad.&rdquo;  They would try to assure themselves that the situation was one which would justify the expenditure of further money, and they would say to themselves: &ldquo;We must take this opportunity which has been presented to examine the whole affair anew and to chart the road that we wish to travel in future.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>At the beginning of this enterprise a great deal was in the air; it had to be. There were estimates about things and the development was altogether in the future.  But the scheme has been in operation now for a certain period, and the fact that it has been in operation for a certain period gives a new set of facts and figures that we can go back upon.  It gives an opportunity of taking stock of the situation at its present point of development.  Accordingly I say we here, who are the people's representatives and guardians of the people's interests in this particular undertaking, ought to do what an ordinary businessman would do in relation to his own business affairs.  He would say there is a conflict of opinion here between my two sets of advisers, and I want to get this examined home. I will try to get outside, impartial investigation. We have often heard of auditors coming in, and so on.  The idea of bringing in auditors is to get some outside, thorough investigation. Why does not the Minister agree that in this case, in the national interest, something should be done; not auditors, however, because they would not be sufficient to do the work.  We want <Col N="2384" /> in this case men whose knowledge of the matters concerned is such that they can pass something like an authoritative judgment upon them.  I say that is necessary for us, if we are not to convict ourselves of plunging ahead wildly into further expenditure without knowing where we are.</P>
    <P>There is another matter.  There is no doubt anybody who attended carefully to the statement of the Minister will admit that he passed on to us a doubt that must be in his own mind, or else he would not have passed it on, namely a doubt as to the economic soundness of the whole enterprise. It is a very big enterprise, and there are very large sums of national money involved in it.  Surely before we expend further money without knowing where we are going to, we ought to get the question of the economic soundness of this enterprise put beyond yea or nay.  We ought to know exactly where it is.  For that we will have to depend largely upon the judgment of men competent to give judgment upon it.  I said during the last debate that if it lay between the Minister and his view whether this undertaking was or was not economically sound, and the views of the men on the Board, such as the chairman and the managing director, one of whom had experience of accountancy and general control of money, and the other who was an expert in this particular work, anyhow as compared with the Minister I would be bound to take the side and accept the judgment of the managing director rather than of the Minister.  I say that, but I do not want the Minister to interpret it as expressing more than what at one time he spoke of as a state of philosophic doubt.  I do not think any one of us is justified in going beyond the state in which we suspend judgment.  It is obviously a case in which we must suspend judgment if we are to be fair and just, because we have not the facts to enable us to come to definite judgment.  But we have enough, I contend, to determine us upon a certain line of action, and that line of action is to have this whole position investigated by a body as impartial and as competent as we can get.  I think <Col N="2385" /> therefore that any reasonable man approaching this situation with an open mind would agree with us that that inquiry should be set up.  There is another matter if we are dealing with the justice and merits of the case. One side is prepared to face an inquiry. The managing director in a public statement in the interests of the enterprise, and not less, I am sure, in his own interests as an individual, asks that this inquiry should be set up.  He asks for it as a man whose credit is at stake, and as a man interested in the success of this enterprise because he was the man who, to a certain extent, conceived and pressed it upon the Minister.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Not this distribution scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I am talking of the success of the whole scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to get the Deputy clear.  He said the managing director pressed this upon the Minister.  I make a division.  The generation of electricity, and its transmission certainly, but the distribution side, no.  The Electricity Supply Act represents my scheme in antagonism to his on distribution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Leave that aside.  I am talking of the success of the enterprise as a whole.  Obviously this man has an interest in seeing this lasting monument to himself is kept standing and not broken into pieces. He is prepared to face an inquiry and the Minister apparently is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>So are the other directors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr de Valera Mr de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>And so are the other directors but the Minister is not. The Minister is a man who is always talking about submitting to international tribunals questions in dispute and all the rest of it.  That seems to be his policy in external affairs, but here in internal affairs where he is one of the parties he does not want an inquiry because he fears the judgment of the inquiry might not coincide with the judgment he is able to pass in the House where he has a majority on his side.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I take it that the Minister is <Col N="2386" /> genuinely anxious to have the merits of the dispute examined, and&mdash;in fairness to himself unless he fears he has a very bad case&mdash;will acquiesce in the setting up of this inquiry. If he is right he is going to be justified.  Has he not sufficient confidence in his own position in the matter to believe that if an impartial inquiry is made he will come well out of the investigation?  If he has a case why not have an inquiry? The only evidence of his mind in the matter that has been given to us in the debate is that the materials that will enable a commission to come to a sound judgment are not available. Yet they were available for him to come to a sound judgment.  He can form a judgment where experts cannot! If the materials are not available for the experts the materials are not available for him.  If they are available for him let them be put before the experts who will be better able to appreciate, in our opinion, the facts of the situation and their implications than the Minister can.</P>
    <P>We have only a very short time at our disposal and I do not want unduly to occupy the time of the House in going into details in the matter, but lest some Deputy should not have read the terms of reference, as Deputy Flinn called them, which he suggested yesterday in his speech, I will go through them as rapidly as I can in detail as they appear on the Paper.</P>
    <P>I would like to stress one point which may not be apparent, that in the constitution of the expert commission we have suggested, in addition to the two experts, a third, who should be a person &ldquo;actively engaged in a manufacturing enterprise, owned, controlled and operating in Saorstát Eireann.&rdquo;  I think it is very important that on that commission there should be a representative, so to speak, of the Irish public, and particularly of that section of the Irish public which would be naturally interested in the development of this enterprise.  We believe that an Irish business man or a manufacturer, as outlined in the motion, would be a most valuable member of that Board.  He would be there with these experts to hear the case they <Col N="2387" /> put forward and to look at it from what I might call the Irish domestic national point of view, and therefore to add a valuable side to the whole investigation. That is as far as the constitution of the commission goes.  The next question is what are they supposed to inquire into?  The first item would be the actual position of the Electricity Supply Board in relation to the assets, liabilities, expenditure, income and capital expenditure.  That would be what I might call a general stocktaking, to find out what was the actual position in relation to these various items.  I think it is not necessary to elaborate upon each of them, because the meaning is clear and Deputies with the Order Paper before them will be able to appreciate their full significance.</P>
    <P>The next point is, &ldquo;as to whether the present rates charged by the Board for electricity are economic, having regard to the present and the prospective market for electricity in the Free State.&rdquo;  That is a question upon which there has been expressed a variety of different opinions.  There is certainly a definite conflict of opinion.  On that question depends the whole economic soundness of the scheme, and if the money sunk in it is ultimately to be remunerative.</P>
    <P>The next point deals with the existing staff and organisation of the Board. I take it that that, for instance, would mean that the composition of the Board would be taken into account. Some of us are not satisfied that the Board, as it exists, and as envisaged by the Minister, is the best type of Board that could be got for the conduct of this undertaking.  It is largely dominated by men who were civil servants. I do not want to be taken as implying any criticism of these civil servants as such.  I know they are estimable men who do their work very well, but for this particular kind of enterprise there is no doubt in my mind that you want experts, someone who has had some experience on the question of electricity supply, the organisation of the Board, the staff, the whole question of organisation, with a view to the work that has to be done. <Col N="2388" />&ldquo;The probable future income, expenditure and capital requirements of the Board in relation to the present and all further possible development of the Shannon electricity undertaking.&rdquo;  We know that various developments are contemplated.  We want to have these foreseen as far as possible and something corresponding to an estimate made as to their cost and as to the ultimate income from them.</P>
    <P>The next item is: &ldquo;The most suitable policy for the future development and organisation of that undertaking, particularly in relation to plant and finance.&rdquo;  I think it would be rather difficult to get any other words which would make what is there contained clearer than it is.  Then we come to the question of the inquiry, the real matter which would enable us to come to a decision as to whether the policy that has been adopted by the Board has in fact been a sound one or not. For instance, whether its policy has been sound in the specific use of its capital, whether it has used the capital wisely and in the best possible way, whether, for instance, it would be wise, as the Minister tried to compel the Board to do, to keep the £850,000 aside, as something that could not be touched but that otherwise would be at their disposal; to cut off that part of their resources and say that they must stand it in order to meet the capital liabilities of the acquired undertakings.  The next question is the price charged for electricity to different classes of customers. We have heard a good deal of complaint about that, for instance, whether it was wise to sell electricity at the rate it was sold to the Tramways Company and, I think, similarly in the case of Cork, and so on.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Who mentioned that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>It was mentioned in the debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not do so, at any rate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Deputy Flinn or some other Deputy did so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder where he got the idea?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2389" />
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>What idea does the Minister mean?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That these charges had been questioned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>The point is whether these charges are too high or too low in view of the capital cost of the undertaking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be better if Deputy de Valera were allowed to make his speech himself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>There were a number of questions raised, whether the electricity should be sold in bulk, etc., but all these associated questions are questions of policy.  I have no doubt the Board did examine this question very carefully, and whether we may differ from the point of view taken by Deputy Briscoe and with the wisdom of the Board for instance in dealing with Pembroke supply, I have no doubt whatever that the Board examined them and decided to do what they did only when they had satisfied themselves that it was the right thing to do. These are matters of policy.  The Minister comes in and proposes to pass judgment upon these matters, upon information which has been conveyed to him, not on something that he was able to get first hand knowledge of directly, but on something for which he had to rely upon other people, less competent probably to advise than the men on whose shoulders the responsibility actually devolved, namely, the Board. We want to know these things because they are being talked about and questioned. Let us know the facts about them.  Let us know the basis of the decisions which were made by the Board.  Let these things be examined by people who are competent to judge whether the Board was right or wrong. We will then have some material to go on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Ministers were very careful when setting up the Tariff Commission. The members of that Commission spent a long time considering questions.  They are people who will not do anything without very careful examination.  Even where things are almost obvious they have to be submitted for examination over a protracted period.  Here they burk examination. <Col N="2390" /> They will not allow us to get the services of experts to examine these highly technical matters, and to come to judgment upon them when they have the facts before them, the facts as revealed by the Board's activities and as examined by a body competent to examine and pass appropriate comments on their actions.  The other question is with reference to the wiring and installation business.  There we are coming, I take it, to one of the matters on which a big difference of opinion arises.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Between whom?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister made a reference to further possible developments, transmission and distribution.</P>
      <P>[<i>An Ceann Comhairle resumed the Chair.</i>]</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy is referring to item (e) of the motion he did not get my point.  However, I will explain it myself later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The next point is whether the Board was wise in engaging in wholesale and retail trade in appliances.  It might well be said that they had enough to do in other matters and should have let that look after itself.  It might well be asked why they should have gone into that side line.  I might have seen without examination the considerations which sent them in that direction just as I can see without examination why they were anxious to get in where power plant was in danger of being put in and where they would say &ldquo;we will supply that power.&rdquo;  I had an instance myself where there was a question of putting in Diesel engines and where there was a possibility that unless we could have been given power by the Electricity Supply Board at a rate something comparable to the rate at which we could supply power ourselves, we were not going to take their supply.  That was a big matter for them to consider. I have no doubt in all these matters they considered it from the point of view of business and the ultimate aims they had in mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The next item in the motion is &ldquo;any other matters relative to the present <Col N="2391" /> position and future development of electricity supply in Saorstát Eireann that may be useful to the Oireachtas.&rdquo; That is an omnibus clause to try to make the terms of reference sufficiently wide to enable the Commission which we propose should be set up to take cognisance of all facts relative to the situation which should be before us before we pass judgment on the Board as a business Board or plunge wildly into the further expenditure which has now reached a considerable sum, as the Minister has admitted.  One of the anomalies about the whole situation is that the Minister should want now two millions extra without taking into account at all, apparently, the necessity for liquidating any of the capital obligations of the undertaking, that he should require two millions of extra capital and that he should complain that the Board did not keep within two and a half millions.  He is taking four and a half millions to do what he was trying to compel the Board to do under two millions.  That seems to me extraordinary, and the whole of the situation is such that, in the national interests as well as the interests of the undertaking, if we are not going to convict ourselves as hopeless incompetents, we ought to set up an inquiry of this sort.  I might say for myself that I am not at all happy in seeing the Minister having two million pounds to play with, two million pounds to help him to squeeze these men on the Board into following whatever policy he cares to dictate. He has now got the power of the purse.</P>
    <P>We assented to the Second Reading of the Bill because he indicated that he was prepared to reduce that sum. He was prepared to be knocked out of the Bill.  He was prepared to do anything. We passed the Second Reading because we believed on that occasion that when he came to the Committee Stage, after reasonable arguments were put forward in a reasonable way, he would be prepared to modify the measure, and ask only for such sum as would enable him to carry on during the period that would have to elapse until we got an experts' report which would put us in a position to form a sound judgment and enable us to look <Col N="2392" /> to the future with some security.  We ask members of the House, by their votes, to compel an inquiry of this sort. We believe that if they do not they are not playing their part as custodians of the public interests.</P>
    <P>There is also, undoubtedly, the big question of control, the ultimate fate of the whole undertaking&mdash;in fact, whether a scheme conceived like this can be successful or not.  If unsuccessful it would be the severest blow it would be possible to imagine almost which could be delivered to the ideals which the Minister had when he introduced this proposal for the Shannon scheme originally. He referred to it in his Second Reading speech as an experiment of great sociological value.  We believe it is.  Such a scheme, in the manner in which it was laid out by the Minister originally, seemed to us fairly sound. In fact, looking back over it, and I have tried to think of some way which would give the necessary security and at the same time secure that there would not be undue interference with the conduct of the business side by the Board, I did not see any scheme which would improve upon that unless this present situation would suggest that before there was any removal from office in future there should be an opportunity given to the people concerned to have an inquiry.  I do not say that there might not be considerations which would make such a scheme inadvisable as part of the machinery.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this debate to end at 2 o'clock?  There are other speakers, I take it, as well as myself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall soon conclude. As I say, I intended&mdash;I need not now&mdash; to go fully into what is involved in this experiment.  We do not want to see it a failure unless it can be proved that it has failed.  We believe that if things remain in their present situation the natural judgment of the people upon it will be that it has failed.  We are thrown into this position, that there is a danger to the enterprise as managed by the Minister, and practically by a bureaucracy subject to him, by some board of civil servants who will ultimately be responsible to him and who will feel, every one of them, <Col N="2393" /> that they are not free to take independent action, because they will look back and see the fate of those who did dare to take independent action.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I formally second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a motion before the House&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'Connell Mr. T.J. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to say a few words before the Minister speaks. I will only take two minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy take his two minutes after I have spoken?  I shall leave him plenty of time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We may assume that the question of the adjournment has been decided to-day?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>We have not time to discuss it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>There is obviously inadequate time to discuss the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I will take the Minister now.  I understand the debate is to conclude at 2 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>There has been agreement to that effect.  It is regrettable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a long motion on the Paper which I am not going to read in detail, as the Deputy has done so.  It comes to this: it asks the assent of the Dáil to the setting up of a commission consisting of three persons of a particular type, with power to send for persons, papers and documents, to report upon certain things.  The Deputy has made his whole case upon this, that we must have certain facts and figures, and have an inquiry before judgment is passed.  There has been criticism, express and implied, of me for passing judgment in this case.  What judgment have I passed on anyone? That I should accept two resignations, and that I should accept these two resignations for what I thought were good and sufficient reasons, which I detailed to this House.  What were they?  That there was an undertaking admitted to have been given and admitted to have been broken; that there was not in the Board's keeping proper material in the way of records on which any decent accounts could be kept. That was admitted.  Thirdly, by implication from the admission of these two <Col N="2394" /> items, and also, indeed, clearly admitted that there was no budgetary system in the whole performance of the Electricity Supply Board.  At a point, these things being admitted, I was faced with a proposal from the people who allowed this situation to develop, and admitted that it had so developed, to give them more money.  In these circumstances, two resignations came to my hand and I accepted them. That is the judgment which has been passed.  Two resignations were put into my hand and I accepted them for certain reasons.  It may be said that the people of the country and of the Dáil are not clear about these reasons.  They are going to be clear about them.  There is not a document which I read which I will not have put before this House when public policy allows me to put them before the House&mdash;and that should be very soon. It will certainly be as soon as I shall have got the accounts and finance situation of that Board cleared up and some attempt made to readjust matters so as to put the whole thing on an even keel again.  That is the present situation, and in that situation we are asked to send for experts to report on the matters detailed in this motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I could query every one of the items in the motion if I wanted to go through them in detail&mdash;for instance, the question of the soundness of the Board's policy in certain respects.  It would seem from this motion as if the Board had unlimited capital at its disposal and that the Oireachtas had given no direction as to the use of that capital.  I should like to ask experts hereafter as to what should be done in the situation that will be revealed in the winter of this year or the spring of next year.  Then will be the time for experts, but only when the House has passed judgment&mdash;passed judgment on every document which I have quoted and on these items.  Was there an agreement made and was there any quibble ever made until we got to the newspaper stage of the controversy as to what that agreement meant?  Was there an admission that that agreement was broken?  Was there a definite admission that the Board did not know what its capital liabilities were at any <Col N="2395" /> time?  Was there a definite admission that the records were in an absolutely chaotic condition, invoices by thousands in arrear and so on, so that no accounts could be kept?  And was there a definite admission, arising out of the whole thing, that there never was a budgetary system in the whole course of the Electricity Board's operations? The House will pass judgment on that, and it is the proper tribunal to pass judgment on it.  Experts may say later on, after we have got this affair out of the atmosphere of this House, that these people in the circumstances did certain things right and certain things wrong, but all that will be after this House has considered it decided if certain people, by their actions, forfeited the confidence of this House with regard to (a) the exercise of elementary financial prudence in running a financial undertaking, and (b) the keeping of an honourable undertaking.  If you are going to have a Board set up as an independent Board, you must require the utmost punctiliousness in the observance of every agreement.  That is for the House to consider.  At some time or other&mdash;and very soon, I hope&mdash; the House will have before it the audited accounts for the year ended 31st March, 1930.  At the moment, there is an independent firm of auditors operating on the Board's premises in two capacities.  I said that there were certain staff on the spot&mdash;five or six men&mdash;I now understand that the figure lately jumped to seventeen and will likely jump to twenty.  This staff is engaged in trying to remake records, in trying to get what should have been in the Board's keeping and was not there, the only information on which any accounts can ever be based.  The audit staff was called in to help to get together those records, to write to firms in respect of whom there was some indication that an order had been placed, to find out what the order was and to remake all that sort of elementary documenting which is absolutely necessary for account-rendering.</P>
    <P>Then, these independent auditors, when the records have been made, when accounts on foot of these records in some way have been produced are going to be asked to audit these accounts.  When they have audited <Col N="2396" /> them, the audited accounts will come to me.  I can ask for a special report if I like and all the information will come to the House.  That will be up to the 31st March, 1930.  After that, this independent firm of auditors in whom this House must have confidence&mdash; it has no reason to lose confidence in them&mdash;will get to the accounts of the year ended 31st March last and report on those.  I can call on them for a special report as to the causes of delay about all these accounts, if those causes are known to them, and I can ask their view of the present financial position of the Board, its capital and general commitments, and how it has used its finances, in the sense of how much it has expended and on what. They are not the people to decide whether it was wise or unwise, good or bad expenditure.  That report will come before this House with all the correspondence and then it will be for somebody&mdash;I hold that the first people to intervene at that point should be the Executive Council &mdash;to make proposals with regard to the readjustment of the finance lay-out of the whole Board and to pass judgment upon any readjustment with regard to tariffs, if that is suggested, to make up deficiencies, if deficiencies are revealed. The House, on getting that, can send for independent experts, if they like, to decide on the readjustments made, whether the life assigned to certain articles is the proper life or whether it is too short or too long.  As regards sending for outsiders, to ask them whether the Board's policy was right or wrong in the specific use of its capital, who has the right to decide that but the people who gave the capital, who understood the circumstances and who will have the letters and admissions before them?</P>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>The people who passed the law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Inside the law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;Inside the law&rdquo; includes honourable agreements.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Inside the law as passed. There was no right to go outside the law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy exhausted himself yesterday&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2397" />
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I will exhaust you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>At one time he posed as an electrical expert when Europe required him in another capacity&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>You are getting personal now.  Anything but the facts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>And the British Government said: &ldquo;We have heard that yarn before&rdquo; and took him by the back of the neck and put him into uniform.  That drove him to literature, to the writing of pathetic letters&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us get back to the Shannon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;winding up with this wail about himself, &ldquo;Here I am, Lieutenant Flinn, First Lieutenant at 40, listed as C1, which means not fit even for garrison duty abroad.  That was the Deputy's description of his own inefficiency.  Deputy de Valera asked us not to fling good money after bad.  That was a peculiar phrase for him to use.  He is not at all certain that the money spent has been badly spent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister would have it, I would be inclined&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not put phrases into my mouth which I did not use. I want quotations for anything I am supposed to have said.  The Deputy says we ought not to fling good money after bad.  Let us leave out the past. He means that the money which is now being passed over to me is not going to be usefully expended.  I am not going to take the point of view&mdash; I refuse to accept it completely&mdash;that there was only one expert with regard to electrical administration and that he has resigned now, and that therefore future expenditure is certain to be bad.  I do not accept that point of view at all.  The Deputy has said that, as between myself and the late managing director, the late managing director had certain electrical experience. He had very limited experience. He had very little practical experience.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the expert you are relying on?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The managing director had, in fact, no special experience <Col N="2398" /> in electrical administration, but had undoubtedly done a great amount of reading.  He had certainly worked hard to make up a particular line of country, but when we were selecting the first Board there was a clear recognition by us that there were certain things in his make-up which, unbalanced and on their own, were not going to make for successful operation of the Board.  A team was got together in the hope that the team balance would get the good points out and prevent the defects coming to the top.  It failed to get out the good points and to keep the bad points under control.  I do not accept at all the statement that there is only one electrical expert and that because he has resigned there is nobody else to govern this scheme.  There are many requirements for success in this connection&mdash;a balanced mind in this should include a sound knowledge of electrical accounts, a conscientious appreciation of what the control of public money involves, and electrical talent.  I consider either of the two men now on the Board in a full-time capacity the superior of the late managing director in having such a balance..  If they had not helped to govern the late managing director the situation would be much worse than it now is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Deputy says that there is conflict of opinion between two sets of advisers.  What conflict of opinion is there?  There have been two resignations. I have stated certain things, and one letter has been written which, so far as I can learn has only served to confirm amongst the public what I stated.  There is no conflict of opinion. There are admissions on a variety of things.  Two resignations came in and we accepted them for the reasons I gave.  There may be a conflict of opinion hereafter on expert matters as to what is the proper way to expend the money that the Board receives, and as to what is the proper remuneration to look for on the money being used.  At that point we can call in experts, but at this point it gives a completely distorted view of the situation to say that there is a conflict of opinion between two sets of advisers, unless I am to take it to mean that the Electricity Supply Board had a policy, that they were working on that policy although <Col N="2399" /> they knew it was not the policy adumbrated in the 1927 Act, and that they believed, notwithstanding what the Oireachtas said in its ignorance of electrical matters, that the Board could go on and do what they pleased.  That is a matter that I will bring before the House.  It will be decided on by this House and by the people who set up the Board, not by technical experts but by the people who set up the Board and knew what they were setting it up for.</P>
    <P>The Deputy also said that I have passed on certain doubts as to the economic soundness of the whole scheme.  I wonder how far have I passed on certain doubts?  I was horrified to see in the Press reports the other day that I was supposed to have given satisfaction to the House by answering a very limited question which Deputy O'Kelly addressed to me.  I answered that question inside the framework of the limitation that the Deputy put down, and the reply had clear reference to this, that the prospects of the Board, now that certain people have gone, are much better than if those two people had remained.  As to the economic soundness of the scheme, I have no material at the moment to pass final judgment and have never passed final judgment on it.  I have before me certain disturbing facts on certain things regarding the finance lay-out of the scheme, but these may not be sufficient to warrant anything very much in the way of the raising of charges.  These facts I have still before me for examination.</P>
    <P>The Deputy said that the managing director pressed this scheme on me.  I made a distinction and again make it. As to the Shannon scheme proper, the £5,200,000 scheme which made provision for generation, long distance transmission, and so on I have always given the managing director credit for that whenever I have spoken on it.  On the Second Reading of this Bill I gave him credit for all he did on that, but I want to be clear on this that this scheme of the Electricity Supply Board was not the managing director's.  It was mine, and mine in conflict with the managing director's <Col N="2400" /> point of view.  I talked here the other day of a document that was sent forward by a Continental group, the Heinemann group for whom the managing director was acting in this country as an agent.  They urged the taking over of all the electricity supply in this country by an outside firm.  He, also, favoured that scheme, at that time and at a later date.  I would not have that.  In so far as there is a distribution system under an independent Board that is my scheme and not the managing director's.</P>
    <P>The Deputy wants to know why, if I have confidence in my case, why I will not have an inquiry.  I will have the inquiry, and I will split up that inquiry. An inquiry and a judgment of the House is required on certain aspects of the situation.  I am going to ask the House to pass that judgment as soon as there is material available for the House to pass judgment on it.  After that two items may stand out: One is a proper system of electrical accounts and a proper costing system for all the operations of the Board.  We can call in outsiders to decide upon that.  There is the second thing, what I would call the readjustments of the finance layout of the whole scheme.  That, to my mind, ought to come forward first to this House and should come forward as a proposition from the Government of the day.  If, when the proposition is brought forward people have anything to say on it, if there is anything to query in it, then let us get in these electrical economists whoever they may be, let us have their judgment on that. But it is for the House to pass judgment on what has happened up to date. In my opinion it will be in a position to pass that judgment in the winter of this year or early next year.</P>
    <P>The Deputy said that civil servants predominate on the Board.  There is one civil servant on the Board.  He talked about removal from office.  I am not faced with anything in the nature of removal from office.  I have two resignations.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>That is technical.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to get talking about this whole matter on the other assumption, because then I <Col N="2401" /> could reveal quite an amount of matter that I am not now revealing. The Deputy says that I complained of the Board saying that £2,500,000 was not enough.  I never complained of the Board saying that. I complained that when they made a promise to scale down their expenditure to £2,500,000 they did not do so. Their only excuse for not doing so was, (a) that they had spent in ignorance to the extent of a quarter of a million, and (b) that when their ignorance was dispelled and they discovered that they had overspent to the extent of a quarter of a million they spent another £225,000 because it was consequential on the amount spent in ignorance.</P>
      <P>In March of this year I wrote a letter to the Board stating that it should regard itself as being now in the position of having exhausted its available machinery and requiring to borrow, that it should give me such a statement of its present position and future prospects as any lender would require when considering a loan, such a statement as the Oireachtas would require if called upon to finance the Board's further operations.</P>
      <P>I could give many quotations from letters to show that the line I took was: &ldquo;You have broken your undertaking, you have given me certain excuses for that.  To my mind your excuses only show that you had maladministration in your affairs up to date.  Nevertheless, let me have some idea from you as to what you want. Make a reasonable case for it and I will see if I can get the money.&rdquo;  I never said that they should be put in a straight waistcoat and kept at two and a half million pounds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Deputy said that I made the statement on this Bill that if the House gave me a Second Reading of it, that when it came to the Committee Stage I would consider reducing the sum asked for and take myself out of the Bill.  I do not remember ever saying that I would consider reducing the sum.  I said that I would give details to the House on which Deputies could form a judgment about the sum.  I gave details with certain limitations. I would have been quite willing to get out of the Bill.  But if there was one thing made clear in the debate yesterday, <Col N="2402" /> it was that nobody would let the two Ministers out of the Bill.  There was no division pressed on that.  All that we had was a very faint &ldquo;No.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The main thing that we wanted was to see that the necessary sum of money was provided to keep the scheme afloat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Then the question of the Ministers being in or out of the Bill was a secondary matter.  After the Money Resolution had been passed, the Deputies opposite did not feel strong enough to press for a division on the point with regard to the two Ministers.  The two Ministers are in the Bill now.</P>
      <P>I say that this motion is absurd. If time permitted, I could point out flaws in every item of it.  As regards Deputy de Valera, Deputy Flinn and Deputy MacEntee, it is abhorrent to them to suggest that they have been in touch with anybody outside on all this.  Yet I assert that Deputy de Valera's speech on the first day ran clearly along the lines of the managing director's thought, even to the small point of jealousy with regard to my liaison officer.  The Deputy may not have been in immediate contact with him&mdash;that would be too simple&mdash;but his speech was the managing director's thought.  Deputy Flinn's oration, setting aside the peculiar vulgarity of it which is essential to himself, was also the thought of the managing director.  These terms of reference are the managing director's terms of reference, and I ask the House to reject the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'Connell Mr. T.J. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>This motion came into our hands this morning.  It is quite impossible to form a proper judgment on all the details of it.  On the Second Reading of the Bill I indicated that I was in favour of an inquiry into the affairs of the Board, but not for the purpose, as I think I made clear, of passing judgment on anyone or of attempting to apportion blame for what had taken place.  It was more for the purpose of easing the minds of the public, of removing any uneasiness that the disclosures made would have created.  I am convinced that there is no need for uneasiness with regard to the success of the whole <Col N="2403" /> scheme.  What I had in mind was that we should get some help or suggestions as to the line of policy for the future, and as to what our action should be in regard to the whole scheme.  I am still in favour of the principle of having an inquiry held, but I am not prepared to commit myself to many of the things that have been said.  Personally, I do not believe that you can have an inquiry until the affairs of the Board are fixed up in regard to the accounts.  I think that if experts were to be called in at the present time they would be faced with the position of having to do what the auditors are now doing.  At all events, until that work is done, experts will not be in a position to come to any useful conclusions.</P>
      <P>I would not on such notice and without very much further consideration be prepared to tie myself or commit myself to these terms of reference here or to the constitution of the Board either in its numbers or in the nature or kind of people that are supposed to be appointed.  I think that while, as I say, I am still in favour of the Board and of an inquiry, I do not think that it would be wise to commit ourselves at this stage in any case to the proceedings of a specific inquiry along certain stated specific lines.  There are many things on which I would like to have information, namely the working of the Board and its relation to the labour people, the wages question and that kind of thing, but I do not think that we could at this stage commit ourselves to an elaborate claim of this kind, such as the motion that has been handed in this morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to remind the House of the point made by Deputy de Valera in his opening statement, that by the action which it has taken in permitting the Electricity Supply (Amendment) Bill to go through its Second and Third Readings, this House has already passed judgment upon five men, the former Town Clerk of Dublin; the late Managing Director of the E.S.B. and three part-time members of the Board who have been associated with these two whole-time members in the policy which the <Col N="2404" /> Minister has condemned and which he has asked the House to condemn.  In putting his case before the House the Minister had access to documents which he denied to the House.</P>
      <P>The Minister has stated that we on this side here are in touch with the members of the Board.  We are not. We are here in discharge of our duty as a Parliamentary Opposition, to put before the House and to put before the public the other side of the case.  In doing that we have been fettered by the fact that documents which may or may not sustain the Minister and which may or may not vindicate the Board, have been kept from the House and the public.  These documents have been kept from the House and the public on the plea of public policy. Now the insincerity of the Minister in this matter and his bona fides can be tested on the very plea he raises.  These documents passed between the Executive Council on the one hand and an administrative body set up by them on the other hand.  The only third party that can be affected by these agreements is the Irish public.  The agreement could not have involved us in any sort of further obligation with contractors or other outside parties.  In a dispute of this nature we have a right to have these documents made public.</P>
      <P>At this vital moment, when this issue is being tried we are refused the documents, but afterwards when the Coroner's inquest is to be summoned to sit upon the bodies of the victims we are to have them, and to find that they were duly executed according to law&mdash;at this vital moment when these men's reputations may yet be saved or vindicated the the Minister refuses to divulge these documents to the public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The motion before the House shows that the whole question of the investigation which must be made is a very complicated and a very technical one. The Minister, who when the original scheme was being put before the country called in experts of international reputation to report upon it, now says that, in so far as the future development of the scheme is concerned, the matter will not be referred to men who will be competent to judge it but that it is to be brought forward to this House, <Col N="2405" /> and decided in this House by the votes of Deputy MacEntee&mdash;I am placing the names in the order of ascending competency&mdash;by the votes of Deputy MacEntee, Deputy Carey, Deputy Gorey, Deputy Sheehy and the votes of every single one of us who know absolutely nothing, comparatively speaking, about the issues that will be involved.</P>
    <P>The Minister is going to ask the House to decide in future something which it is obviously incompetent to decide.  He asks this House upon his own statement, without giving us an opportunity of hearing the accused, to determine that the late managing director was a man of limited experience, a man of incompetence, a man of little knowledge, and a man who was, in short, wholly incapable and wholly unfit from the very beginning to hold the position into which the Minister put him.  Before deciding these issues we have only heard the prosecutor and the prosecutor asks us to give our verdict on the issues without evidence.  The managing director held the position into which the Minister put him.  He was not fit to do so.  That is the statement which the Minister has made.  I do not know whether it is true or not. I am leaving it there to the House. The Minister is asking the House by a majority vote to say that what he has alleged against the late managing director of the Electricity Supply Board, his own nominee, is true, and that that man, having served the State for four years with enthusiasm, with all the energy of which he is capable according to the Minister, should now go through life for ever bearing the brand, the stigma, which the Minister himself, on his own unsubstantiated word, has laid upon him.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardSidneyAnthony" hpid="Mr. Anthony Mr. Anthony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Anthony</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister did not say he was incompetent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that fair or just? If any one of us here were branded in any way, would we feel that we would be treated fairly or justly by the legislature? Would we consider it fair treatment if we were not given an opportunity in public and open trial, under a searching investigation, to vindicate ourselves?  That is the issue we are asking the House to vote with <Col N="2406" /> us against the Minister upon.  The Minister is not allowing the House to exercise a free vote.  Yesterday he threatened, if our amendment on the money resolution was carried, that he would be prepared to resign.  The trial given in this issue that has arisen between the Minister and the members of the Electricity Supply Board has been an unfair trial.  It has been a trial by a packed jury, because the Minister, with his threat of resignation before the House, has secured the result.  He knew well that the Party machine, the majority, would back him, and that these men would be condemned, not on the justice of the case, but because the Party exigencies required it.</P>
      <P>We have tried to keep the partisan element out of this discussion.  We have endeavoured to make a case for the Board because we have considered it is our national duty, to the House and to the men who are involved and also to the scheme, to examine as closely as we could the statements of the Minister.  Those statements have been self-contradictory and have been inconsistent.  The whole case has been based upon an agreement which the present chairman of the Board and Mr. Fay, the Minister's representative on the Board from September, 1929, now admit was an agreement which, under no circumstances, could have been observed without deferring the financial success of the scheme.  If that is the position, upon whom does the responsibility lie for the present mess?  Upon whom could it lie except upon those who forced this agreement upon the Board, upon those who were insistent that the Board should keep it?  That is the inevitable, logical conclusion of the letter which the Board sent to the Minister for Industry and Commerce in April of this year, a letter which was signed by the present chairman of the Board and which was sent on behalf of every member of the Board, a letter stating that the agreement was one which in no circumstances could have been observed without deferring the financial success of the scheme.  If that is true, then the responsibility for the present mess rests, not with the men who have resigned, but with those who forced the agreement upon them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2407" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the huge sum involved&mdash;and the money will not be got upon the bushes&mdash;is the Minister still of the opinion that experts are not essential at the moment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2408" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Not at the moment. There is nothing for experts to work upon.</P>
      <P>Question put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Dáil divide d: Tá, 42; Níl, 74.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Aiken, Frank.<br />Allen, Denis.<br />Blaney, Neal.<br />Boland, Gerald.<br />Boland, Patrick.<br />Bourke, Daniel.<br />Brady, Seán.<br />Briscoe, Robert.<br />Buckley, Daniel.<br />Carty, Frank.<br />Clery, Michael.<br />Coburn, James.<br />Colbert, James.<br />Corkery, Dan.<br />Corry, Martin John.<br />Crowley, Tadhg.<br />Derrig, Thomas.<br />De Valera, Eamon.<br />Fahy, Frank.<br />Flinn, Hugo.<br />Fogarty, Andrew.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Geoghegan, James.<br />Gorry, Patrick J.<br />Harris, Thomas.<br />Hayes, Seán.<br />Houlihan, Patrick.<br />Jordan, Stephen.<br />Kennedy, Michael Joseph.<br />Kilroy, Michael.<br />Lemass, Seán F.<br />Little, Patrick John.<br />Maguire, Ben.<br />MacEntee, Seán.<br />Moóre, Séamus.<br />O'Dowd, Patrick Joseph.<br />O'Kelly, Seán T.<br />O'Reilly, Thomas.<br />Ryan, James.<br />Sheehy, Timothy (Tipp.).<br />Smith, Patrick.<br />Tubridy, John.<br />Walsh, Richard.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Aird, William P.<br />Alton, Ernest Henry.<br />Anthony, Richard.<br />Beckett, James Walter.<br />Bennett, George Cecil.<br />Blythe, Ernest.<br />Bourke, Séamus A.<br />Brennan, Michael.<br />Brodrick, Seán.<br />Byrne, John Joseph.<br />Carey, Edmund.<br />Cassidy, Archie J.<br />Clancy, Patrick.<br />Cole, John James.<br />Collins-O'Driscoll, Mrs. Margt.<br />Conlon, Martin.<br />Connolly, Michael P.<br />Cosgrave, William T.<br />Daly, John.<br />Davis, Michael.<br />Doherty, Eugene.<br />Dolan, James N.<br />Doyle, Edward.<br />Doyle, Peadar Seán.<br />Duggan, Edmund John.<br />Dwyer, James.<br />Egan, Barry M.<br />Esmonde, Osmond Thos. Grattan.<br />Everett, James.<br />Finlay, Thomas A.<br />Fitzgerald, Desmond.<br />Fitzgerald-Kenney, James.<br />Gorey, Denis J.<br />Haslett, Alexander.<br />Hassett, John J.<br />Heffernan, Michael R.<br />Hennigan, John.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Henry, Mark.<br />Hogan, Patrick (Galway).<br />Holohan, Richard.<br />Jordan, Michael.<br />Keogh, Myles.<br />Law, Hugh Alexander.<br />Leonard, Patrick.<br />Lynch, Finian.<br />Mathews, Arthur Patrick.<br />McDonogh, Martin.<br />McFadden, Michael Og.<br />McGilligan, Patrick.<br />Mongan, Joseph W.<br />Morrissey, Daniel.<br />Mulcahy, Richard.<br />Murphy, Joseph Xavier.<br />Myles, James Sproule.<br />Nally, Martin Michael.<br />Nolan, John Thomas.<br />O'Connell, Richard.<br />O'Connell, Thomas J.<br />O'Connor, Bartholomew.<br />O'Leary, Daniel.<br />O'Mahony, The.<br />O'Sullivan, Gearóid.<br />O'Sullivan, John Marcus.<br />Redmond, William Archer.<br />Reynolds, Patrick.<br />Rice, Vincent.<br />Roddy, Martin.<br />Shaw, Patrick W.<br />Sheehy, Timothy (West Cork).<br />Thrift, William Edward.<br />Tierney, Michael.<br />White, John.<br />White, Vincent Joseph.<br />Wolfe, George.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Deputies G. Boland and Allen: Níl.  Deputies Duggan and P.S. Doyle.</P>
    <P>Question declared lost.</P>
    <P>The Dáil adjourned at 2.10 p.m. until Wednesday, 14th October, 1931.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Written" RHead="Answers. - The Railway Wages Board">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Written Answers. - The Railway Wages Board.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he is aware that grave discontent still continues with regard to the findings of the Railway Wages Board relative to the lower grade employees; and if he will state whether the representatives of the members of the N.U.R. agreed to and signed the findings in accordance with Section 55 (1) of the Railways Act, 1924; and further, if he will agree to receive a deputation of the Union.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. McGilligan) Patrick McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. McGilligan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The answer to the first part of the question is in the negative.  The second part does not arise because Section 55 (1) of the Railways Act, 1924, does not require the assent of the trade unions to findings of the Railway Wages Board established under agreements which the N.U.R. has signed.  With regard to the third part no request that I should receive a deputation has been made to me by the N.U.R.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Written Answers." RHead="- The Shannon Electricity Contractors">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Written Answers. - The Shannon Electricity Contractors.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce whether he has received in any form whatsoever a claim or claims from the contractors to the Minister under the Shannon Electricity Act, 1925, for all the works carried out under that Act, which would make the total cost of the said works as completed, including capital charges during construction, exceed the £5,835,000 granted by the Dáil to defray such total cost; and if such claim or claims have been received, to state the number of them, the date <Col N="2334" /> upon which each claim was filed, its amount and the aggregate total of all such claims.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The contractors' final account dated 16th August, 1930, included, as it is not unusual in such accounts, a substantial number of extra claims.  These have not been allowed and are at present sub judice.  I am not now prepared to give more information on the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>