<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="21" Month="Feb" Year="1979" Vol="91" No="2" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 21 Feabhra 1979" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 21 February 1979" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="111">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="111" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Message" RHead="from Dáil">
    <Title>Message from Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has agreed to the amendments made by Seanad Éireann to the Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence) (Amendment) Bill, 1979.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 1 and 2 in that order; to take No. 1 until 5.30 and take the motion from then until 8.30.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Order of Business, Motion No. 15&mdash;the legal aid motion&mdash;has been on the Order Paper now for about ten months.  Whilst I am grateful that the Leader of the House is giving time today for the motion on housing I want to draw the attention of the House to the fact that on two occasions&mdash;the first was just before we rose last summer&mdash;I asked that this motion on legal aid be given some priority. At that time the Leader of the House said that he hoped it would be taken early in the next term.  Shortly before Christmas the motion still had not been taken and I asked again that it be taken. I cannot remember the exact words that the Leader of the House used but they were fairly much in the affirmative that the motion would be taken.  It is a most urgent motion.  For various reasons, primarily because since it was last discussed in this House the Pringle Report has been issued, we now have the Free Legal Advice Centre planning to close down the only fulltime community law centre in Ireland.  We also had recently <Col N="112" /> reports that the Government intend to fight fully Mrs. Joanna Airey's case in the European Court of Human Rights.  It is scandalous that this motion has been on the Order Paper for so long and, despite several assurances, has not been taken.  I would like the Leader of the House to inform us why it has not been taken, why it cannot be taken instead of the housing motion and, if it is not being taken, when it might be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasWhitaker" hpid="Dr. Whitaker Dr. Whitaker">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Whitaker</NameTxt>
      <P>Coming back to the matter I raised last week, I am disappointed that the recent White Paper entitled &ldquo;Programme for National Development 1978-81&rdquo; does not yet appear on the Order Paper.  I urged last week the desirability of this House being afforded an early opportunity to debate this paper which is concerned with matters of great public importance.  Particularly as Senators should have constructive and helpful comment to make on some of these policy issues, such as the development of pay in the immediate future and improvement of industrial relations, it is very desirable that the House be afforded an opportunity soon to debate the White Paper.  I wonder could the Leader of the House indicate what are the Government's intentions in this respect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GemmaHussey" hpid="Mrs. Hussey Mrs. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>I wanted to draw the attention of the House to Motion No. 17 which appears for the first time on the Order Paper: &ldquo;That Seanad Éireann notes the report of the Council for the Status of Women on rape&rdquo;.  This motion is signed also by Senator Alexis FitzGerald and Senator Robinson and therefore has support from all parties on this side of the House.  I had hoped for support from the other side of the House as well which has not, unfortunately, materialised.  This subject is of great concern and urgency for a variety of reasons I will not go into.  The report which the motion mentions was brought out last October and has not been commented on or replied to, except very briefly in the other House.  The only other motion down in my name now is No. 8 on the Order Paper, which directly emanated from the women's movement and was judged inadmissible because it <Col N="113" /> was <i>sub judice.</i>  Now, nearly a year later it still is not before the courts and has not been debated.  I want to appeal to all parties in the House to arrange together that Motion No. 17 be taken very early because it is time that Senators showed that they do have some interest in ensuring that these items of such importance be debated in the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to Motion No. 15, I cannot give Senator Molony any definite time when it can be taken. The Minister is not in a position to deal with it at the moment but I will certainly convey the urgency of dealing with it which Senator Molony has stressed.  As regards Senator Hussey's Motion No. 17, I will bear in mind what she said in regard to taking that as soon as possible. With regard to the White Paper, I have spoken to the Minister for Finance about that and I hope to be able to say when it will be taken.  It will not be for the next week or two but I will endeavour to have it on as soon as possible.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Fisheries Bill, 1979:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Fisheries Bill, 1979: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Minister for Fisheries and Forestry (Mr. Lenihan) Minister for Fisheries and Forestry (Mr. Lenihan)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Fisheries and Forestry (Mr. Lenihan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The object of this Bill is to give effect to the main recommendations of the Inland Fisheries Commission by securing the more effective conservation, protection, management and development of inland fisheries through the reorganisation and strengthening of the existing administrative structure.</P>
      <P>This will be done by replacing the existing 17 boards of conservators, which are responsible for the day to day work of conservation and protection of inland fisheries, and the Inland Fisheries Trust which conducts large scale development work on brown trout, coarse fish and sea angling, by a Central Fisheries Board and seven regional fisheries boards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The central board will be responsible for the co-ordination and, if necessary, direction of the work of the regional boards.  They will also have planning, <Col N="114" /> education, advisory and limited research functions.  Regional boards will have the function of identifying the fishery resources within their regions and of drawing up programmes for the development and protection of these fisheries.</P>
    <P>The regional boards will comprise elected members with a limited number of members appointed by the Minister for Fisheries and Forestry following consultation with relevant fisheries interests. The elected members will be elected in a democratic fashion by licence holders, ratepayers and trout and coarse fish anglers who avail themselves of their right to be registered in the Register of Trout and Coarse Fish Anglers on payment of an annual subscription.</P>
    <P>The number of elected and appointed members on each board will be fixed by order.  The size of a region and the nature of the fisheries therein will be a factor in deciding the membership of the board.  The rules governing the elections will be laid down in regulations and I have in mind a system of panelling the various groups and allocating a specific number of seats to each panel according to its strength in each region.  Pending the setting up of the system of elections the Minister will nominate all the members of the first regional boards but these boards will be replaced by elected boards within one year.</P>
    <P>Initially the staff of the Inland Fisheries Trust will be transferred to the central board and the staffs of the boards of conservators to the regional boards.  There is provision in the Bill for movement of staff between the central and regional boards.  I have provided that these transfers will not entail any worsening of remuneration or conditions of service for any person; neither will any superannuation allowances to which a person was entitled prior to his transfer be reduced.</P>
    <P>The central and regional boards are enabled, subject to the approval of the Minister for Fisheries and Forestry and that of the Minister for the Public Service, to appoint such staff as are necessary to carry out their functions.  I have included provision for the preparation of a staff scheme and a superannuation scheme by the central board for their <Col N="115" /> staff and the staff of regional boards. The staff scheme will provide for the regulation, control and management of staff, transfer of staff between boards and will indicate the remuneration, tenure of office, qualifications for appointment and conditions of service in respect of different grades of staff.  I consider that the introduction of more acceptable conditions of employment is overdue in the case of inspectors and waterkeepers engaged in the difficult task of developing and protecting our inland fisheries.</P>
    <P>Provision has also been made for the acquisition of fisheries and rights of way by agreement or compulsorily.  These acquisitions will be subject to the payment of fair compensation and there is also provision for appeal against compulsory acquisitions.</P>
    <P>The main thrust I see coming from this Bill is that of switching the emphasis from protection to development of our inland fisheries.</P>
    <P>As Senators are aware, illegal fishing for salmon is one of the major causes for declining salmon stocks.  Last year's salmon catch was just half that of 1975. Even more serious is the fact that the numbers of salmon reaching the spawning grounds are much reduced.  Rivers that carried fine stocks of salmon at one time have been almost denuded of spawning stock.  Every assistance will be given to the board to stamp out illegal fishing and in the matter the boards will have the full support of the Garda and the Navy.</P>
    <P>I have also included some new provisions in the Bill that should prove of great assistance in fishery protection. The most important of these is the increase of the penalties for fisheries offences to a realistic level.  The Bill prescribes penalties of up to £600 and/or six months in prison on summary conviction. For the more serious offences provision is made for trial on indictment and the penalty on conviction for such offences can extend up to £1,000 and/or two years in prison.</P>
    <P>It is provided also that the courts must disqualify any person convicted of a third or subsequent offence of a particular kind from holding a fishing <Col N="116" /> licence for three years.  I consider that it is only just that a fisherman should lose his licence if he flouts the law.</P>
    <P>The powers of protection staff at sea are also increased.  They may now take a boat believed to have on board unlawfully caught salmon to port, detain the boat and its occupants until it is searched and use such force as is necessary in bringing the boat to port.</P>
    <P>I have included provisions which will enable a commercial fishing licence to be used only by the licensee or his nominee. This will help to eradicate the practice of transfer or sale of licences by licence holders and make the work of the protection staff that much easier.</P>
    <P>The great potential of fish farming is recognised in the Bill.  Briefly, the new provisions make it an offence to engage in aquaculture unless one holds the appropriate licence.  The Bill enables an order to be made following the usual investigations and, if necessary, an inquiry designating an area of the sea as an area where aquaculture may be carried out, and licences may then be issued for the carrying out of aquaculture in that area. This procedure will obviate having to hold an inquiry in relation to the issue of individual licences.</P>
    <P>Implementation of the proposals in the Bill will, of course, require substantially increased expenditure&mdash;perhaps I should better call this increased outlay investment rather than expenditure in view of the many ways the fishermen will benefit the economy.</P>
    <P>At present those who benefit directly from inland fisheries development and protection&mdash;principally anglers and commercial fishermen&mdash;contribute by way of licence fees and fishery rates.  The receipts from those sources are supplemented by an annual grant from the Exchequer.  Obviously new sources of income must be found to meet a fair share of the greatly increased costs and greatly increased development envisaged.</P>
    <P>To secure additional income the Bill provides for payment of a voluntary subscription by trout and coarse fish anglers.  This subscription will entitle them to registration in the Register of Trout and Coarse Fish Anglers and such registration will carry a vote in elections to boards.  Quite apart from the financial <Col N="117" /> side I consider this to be a very important provision of the Bill as it recognises the increasing importance of trout and coarse fish angling and affords trout and coarse fish anglers an opportunity to have a say on the boards which hitherto they were not afforded.  The Bill also provides for the payment of a levy on the first sale of salmon which would be paid in most cases by salmon dealers or by hotels or restaurants.</P>
    <P>I have no doubt that, having regard to the development programme being implemented, fishery interests will have no reservations about their contributions. Even so, while these provisions will provide increased revenue, the Exchequer will still have to bear the major burden of the cost.</P>
    <P>The Government gladly undertake this commitment knowing that, not only is the protection of our inland fisheries heritage an essential obligation, but that it also makes very sound economic sense.</P>
    <P>Our inland fisheries provide very valuable employment in rural areas, particularly along the western seaboard. They provide exports running at about £5 million a year and add about £15 million every year to tourist earnings.  What is particularly encouraging is that the opportunity exists for a considerable expansion of the resources available.</P>
    <P>I recommend this Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as this party are concerned the general principles in the Bill are welcome.  We must all be agreed on the overall objective of the Bill, that is, to improve our level of fish stocks.  A natural bounty such as fish is something we have taken for granted and have not been sufficiently alert to or aware of the danger this natural bounty is in at present. Fishing has primarily a great commercial benefit for the country because it provides a livelihood for a great number of people.  As the Minister says, very often this livelihood is provided in what are called the disadvantaged areas.  It is very important that the State ensures that this livelihood will be in no way threatened by its source, the fish, becoming in any way diminished.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Next in importance of the benefits we have from our fish is the social or <Col N="118" /> recreational aspect.  Fishing is a widespread national pastime and forms part of our national pattern of life.  It is important that the opportunities to fish would be preserved.  Thirdly, there is the tourist element arising from our fisheries.  It is important that they be available as a tourist attraction, but I would put that as number three in my list of priorities.</P>
    <P>We are all agreed that our fish stocks need to be better protected, better managed and better developed.  It would appear from the report of the Inland Fisheries Commission&mdash;which I suppose forms the genesis of this Bill&mdash;that we have been less than successful in the protection, management and development of our fisheries up to now.  That report makes quite depressing reading with regard to the repletion of some species, particularly salmon, and the lack of development and protection in regard to brown trout and coarse fish. At this stage it is apt to pay tribute to the members of that commission for their report.  It is a very lively, commonsense report.  It is a pleasure to read a report written in straightforward, simple language, rendering its message very clear indeed.  The members deserve the thanks of everybody for the work they put into it.</P>
    <P>The new structures proposed by the Bill are those recommended, not precisely in that form or under those titles by the commission.  In regard to the expertise within the commission there will be total acceptance of the new structures proposed, the central board and the regional boards.  They are being given very wide powers under the Bill.  There is also in the Bill provision for the Minister to give extra powers to the boards.  I can well understand the Minister wanting to keep that right for himself so that, as the scene develops, he will have discretion to give extra powers to the boards.  But I wonder is it right that his discretion would be untrammelled by any lack of having to refer the giving of these powers to the Oireachtas in the first instance. It would be more democratic; more in keeping with the general nature of how legislation should be made, that it should come through the Oireachtas so that there should be a parliamentary input. <Col N="119" /> If the power is exclusively administrative there is that much lessening of the democratic control.  We should be conscious always of this element.  The Minister might indicate if he just kept this power as a general precaution or whether he has, even at this stage, anything specific in mind with regard to what extra powers he might be disposed to give the boards in due course, powers over and above those which they get, admittedly in general terms, from the Bill.</P>
    <P>I might mention just two of the powers which could be controversial&mdash;the powers of acquiring fisheries and the powers of acquiring rights of way to fishing waters.  It is quite clear from the arguments of the commission that these are powers which are needed and I do not quibble with the granting of them to the central board.  There is provision for compensation, as there must be, and provision for arbitration in the event of disagreement on the level of compensation.  Likewise with rights of way&mdash;as I read the Bill&mdash;there is provision for compromise with the owner over the exact route of a right of way or any other rights that may be acquired to provide access to fishing waters.  The implementation of these powers may disturb situations on the ground which would have inured possibly for many many years, possibly centuries.  I have no doubt that the spirit in which these new quite drastic powers will be exercised will obviously have to take that factor into account.</P>
    <P>The new bureaucracy decided on&mdash;I do not use that word in any pejorative sense&mdash;consists of the central board and a number of regional fishery boards. Provision is made for them to keep them in touch with each other, for the regional boards to provide details of their plans and estimates to the central board and the central board then to be in touch with the Minister <i>via</i> an annual report.  There is power for the Minister to direct the central board on what they should do and power for the central board to give directions to the regional boards.  I wonder is there room for conflict, duplication or even confusion between the three authorities, the Minister, the central board and the <Col N="120" /> regional boards.  It will be very important to see that there is a clear pattern of communication and responsibility as between these different authorities to ensure that sight will not be lost of the basic objective of the protection, management and development of our fisheries and a plethora of regulations and plans that may be duplicating and even possibly conflicting with each other.  The Minister, of course, will have an overview of the whole scene and presumably will be able to take steps to ensure that nothing like this occurs.</P>
    <P>The most important species of fish is the salmon.  This is the species in greatest danger.  The statistics, as the Inland Fisheries Commission in their report pointed out, are not terribly reliable. Nevertheless there are very clear trends indeed from statistics that are available to show that salmon stocks are diminishing fairly consistently.  If these trends are not rectified, halted and changed there is a real danger that salmon may become a very rare fish indeed.</P>
    <P>It also seems clear from the commission's report that conservation of salmon must be the priority for the new fishery authorities.  The conservation of salmon has to be looked at principally by the prevention of poaching.  It is notorious that off parts of our coast&mdash;particularly the south and south-west&mdash;there is salmon poaching on a wide scale by trawlers fishing well out to sea.  It is notorious, in these coastal areas, that this poaching is doing immense harm to salmon stocks.  It is notorious also, for example, that the nets which are being used are excessively long, they are excessively deep, 60-90 mesh deep instead of 30 mesh, which I understand is an approved norm.  I understand also that the mono-filament net in frequent and possibly universal use, is illegal.</P>
    <P>I understand that the Minister, shortly after taking office, indicated his agreement with the seriousness of the problem of poaching by illegal drift-netting and indicated that if he had not solved it within a year he might have to resign.  I will not hold him to that because it is a very difficult problem.  But it does indicate how seriously he considers the problem when he was prepared to say <Col N="121" /> that about it.  His year is up, indeed, two years will soon be up, and my information is that the problem is as large as ever.  Unless it is tackled and solved there is no point in setting up new structures or in us here making pious statements about the need to protect and develop our fishing if, at the same time, salmon stocks are being dissipated by illegal fishing.  That is the hard reality.</P>
    <P>The Minister recently restricted the salmon fishing season off the coasts in question and I think restricted the number of days in a week in which licensed fishermen could fish.  This was presented as a conservation measure.  Of course, it is not a conservation measure because all it does is make more salmon available for the poachers and it does not in any way help to increase the total stock of salmon.  Possibly it prejudices the men who are entitled to fish legally and who do fish legally.  This must be the priority for the Minister.</P>
    <P>I readily concede that it is a most difficult problem to try to stamp out illegal salmon fishing some distance out to sea. But the problem is so serious that, irrespective of how difficult it may be to tackle, some drastic approach will have to be organised.  The Minister did involve Naval Service boats but there are not enough boats in the Naval Service effectively to patrol all the areas of the coast, particularly the area I have mentioned, where illegal drift-netting is taking place. Because of the importance of the salmon in the whole fishing industry&mdash;its commercial importance to those who make their living from it, its social importance to our fishermen and its value as a tourist attraction, and as such an interesting part of our environment&mdash;it would be criminal if anything should happen to the salmon stocks.  I would urge the Minister to take whatever steps need to be taken to fulfil the promise he made and to save him having to implement that promise, even at the end of two years.</P>
    <P>It is also clear from the commission's report that there are other areas in which conservation of salmon has been neglected.  There has not been sufficient attention paid to scientific aspects of salmon spawning.  A great deal of damage is done to spawning beds, and <Col N="122" /> casual poaching on the rivers can do much harm to the breeding stock.  There is a necessity for strict implementation of the law to ensure that these things are ended.  In comparison with the problem of illegal drift-netting off the shores, the ending of those malpractices would be comparatively&mdash;I emphasise comparatively&mdash;simple.</P>
    <P>In addition I would recommend to the Minister for his consideration a matter touched on by the commission in their report.  That is the education of the people of an area where there are salmon rivers, particularly in the upper reaches or wherever spawning takes place.  There should be some special programme for educating the schoolchildren in those areas about the importance of this natural resource.  They should be told what happens in the salmon's natural cycle and made conscious of the need to protect the species and protect the environment in which the salmon live.  In using the schools to get that message across much good could be done for the idea of conservation.  That was a very practical suggestion in the commission's report.  I would urge the Minister to see what he can do about it.  It might be possible for the new regional boards to set up some system whereby they could provide the education needed to ensure that the next generation will be fully aware of what is involved.</P>
    <P>In relation to the question of enforcing the law and preventing poaching by illegal drift net fishing, I wonder is there any possibility of tightening controls on the disposal of the salmon?  Illegally caught salmon have to be sold and if some method could be devised for homing in on the problem at that point there might be a potential solution there.  As I understand it at the moment, illegally caught salmon are sold through the medium of licensees.  I am also told that the number of salmon sold by the licensees is so out of proportion to their numbers, that it is patently impossible for them to have caught them all.  If the licensees caught and owned all the salmon they sold they would be veritable millionaires.  So it would seem to me that it should be possible to devise some administrative system that might home in on the problem at that point.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="123" /> I would emphasise to the Minister that the preservation of our salmon stocks must be his number one priority and, through him, the number one priority of the new central board and regional boards.  It would be a terrible thing indeed if, through greed, we were to be condemned in the eyes of the world as a people who so misused this natural resource as to destroy it.  The obligation to ensure that our reputation remains unsullied lies with the Minister.</P>
    <P>Another element in the conservation of our fishing stock is the question of keeping our waters clean.  I recall receiving a booklet last summer from the new body which has been set up under the aegis of the Department of the Environment. It is a body set up to advance the cause of keeping our rivers and lakes free from pollution.  It is an attractive booklet about what is being done in this regard.  It draws attention to the statutory measures that are available to ensure that pollution does not take place. I thought it ironic that the body charged with enforcing this law is the local authority because I have not the slightest doubt that the greatest polluters of our waters are the local authorities.</P>
    <P>I live in a town on the Shannon and raw sewage from that large town is discharged straight into the Shannon.  The same happens with all the towns on the Shannon.  We are told by the experts that the Shannon is so big and there is so much water in it that it can safely absorb all this deleterious material.  But it is ironic that the body which is charged to see that factories do not pollute the water is itself polluting the water and it is no answer to say that this pollution does no harm.  Shortly after receiving that booklet I read in a local paper that Leitrim County Council had provided a new sewerage scheme for Carrick-on-Shannon and they wanted to add an extra stage to the treatment process. Carrick-on-Shannon had been discharging raw sewage into the river and this new sewerage works was providing some treatment but the council, on the advice of their professional advisers, wanted to add a further stage of treatment for the sewage before it reached the <Col N="124" /> river.  They were refused sanction by the Department of the Environment, the very same Department that had issued this book advocating the need to keep our waters clean.  They had been refused sanction by the Department of the Environment to spend the extra £10,000 or £12,000&mdash;whatever the amount, it was a comparatively small sum&mdash;on this extra stage, again on the grounds that the river was well able to take the partially treated sewage without danger to the river.</P>
    <P>At this stage we are too careless about the problems of water pollution.  There will have to be a changed attitude on the part of the Department of the Environment and, through that Department, the local authorities to ensure that the tragedy which occurred in Lough Ennel will never occur anywhere else in Ireland.  I confess with shame that I was a member of Westmeath County Council for six years and during that time the sewage from Mullingar town was pumped directly and untreated into Lough Ennel while, at the same time, the Inland Fisheries Trust were making a substantial and large investment in that lake and had reached a stage of development where Lough Ennel was among the foremost, if not the foremost, game trout lake in Europe.  Eventually the continued discharge of sewage killed that lake stone dead as far as trout fishery was concerned.</P>
    <P>I grant that the problem was compounded by a certain run-off of artificial fertilisers from surrounding lands but the expert opinion was that the lake would have been capable of absorbing the agricultural run-off if it had not also to try to deal with the discharge of raw sewage from Mullingar.  Lough Ennel was killed stone dead as a game lake.  It is a matter of great shame for us all that this should have happened but it should be a lesson, a terribly expensive lesson, to us that we should ensure that the like will never happen again.</P>
    <P>Lake Garadice in Leitrim is mentioned by the commission as a leading coarse fish lake.  One morning, out of the blue, the local people noticed something wrong about Garadice.  On inspection it was found that all the fish there had died and were floating on the top.  Putrefaction had taken place by reason of the <Col N="125" /> discharge of agricultural run-off of fertiliser and, more particularly, pig slurry. The lake has been poisoned and it had reached the stage that as there was no more oxygen all the fish died.  That lake too was killed.  While we are setting up structures here it is very important that these new boards be given the power to ensure that they will be able to carry out what the Minister says is their job, the more effective conservation, protection, management and development of inland fisheries.  Unless pollution is ended, particularly pollution by local authorities who are in a position, as part of the arm of Government to give a lead, we are only wasting our time setting up these new structures.</P>
    <P>Second in my order of priorities as to the value of our fisheries is the fact that they are a social and recreational amenity.  Fishing for trout, and coarse fishing to a lesser extent, are common pastimes throughout the length and breadth of the country.  Traditionally, these pastimes have been, to all intents and purposes, freely available and available free to any citizen of a mind to do a bit of fishing.  The commission in their report&mdash;and this is the one matter that caused much controversy at the time&mdash;recommended that there should be a charge or a licence fee for everyone who wanted to fish.  I am glad to see that that recommendation has not been brought into the Bill.  But I want the Minister to be explicit on this when he is replying to the debate.  I want him to confirm that it is not his intention to obtain licence fees through any sort of a backdoor method because I notice that the Bill provides for the setting up of a register of trout and coarse fishermen and by paying an annual subscription to the regional board a fisherman can get his name on that register and thereby be entitled to vote in the election of members to his regional fishery board. That is a commendable objective indeed. It is also provided that the people who are on that register will be entitled to fish free in the various waters controlled by the board and presumably by the other regional boards that are to be set up. There is nothing in the Bill to say that people who do not pay a fee and become registered will be entitled to fish free as <Col N="126" /> heretofore.  In other words, if I decide not to become a registered coarse fisherman or trout fisherman and do not pay a fee, can I continue to fish for pike or perch or trout as I and my forebears have done in the past?  I would like the Minister to be very clear on that.  Or is it to be the case in the future that the only people who can fish for trout or for coarse fish will be those who appear on the register, having paid their annual subscription?  The subscription is referred to as a voluntary subscription in the sense that a person does not have to pay it but if, by failing to pay it, I am going to lose my rights to fish then I am afraid it is very far removed from being a voluntary subscription.</P>
    <P>On the question of subscription, who is going to fix the level of subscription? Will it be the regional board, the central board or the Minister?  What level is it going to be fixed at initially and how are we going to be sure that it is going to be kept to a reasonable figure?  This is an important question.</P>
    <P>The new structures are welcome and the motivation behind them coming from the commission will have general support. But there are two essential preconditions necessary to ensure success for this new departure.  The first is that there should be adequate financial support for the new boards to do what has to be done.  We are coming from a long way back in terms of conservation and development of our fisheries and the efforts to bring them up to date and realise their full potential will be that much more difficult and onerous.  How successful we will be in removing those difficulties speedily and effectively will depend eventually on how much finance is going to be made available to these new boards.  The Minister, in his opening speech, made what I think is an important distinction.  He said that any money given to these boards will be an investment; it will not be expenditure.  That is an important distinction.  I have no doubt that, notwithstanding the rather threatening clouds that are appearing on the financial horizon, the Minister will be able to assure his colleague, the Minister for Finance, that this is an investment in jobs and livelihood for people and we <Col N="127" /> will be able to ensure that it will not be treated as expenditure on a purely recreational or frivolous object.  In assuring his colleague in the Department of Finance of the national importance of this from an investment point of view he will be able to procure adequate funds for the new central and regional boards.</P>
    <P>The other pre-condition that is essential is that these new boards be set up without delay and all the administrative work necessary got under way immediately because we are coming from far back in the question of conserving, protecting and developing our inland fisheries and every week that is lost is compounding the situation.</P>
    <P>I will conclude by urging the Minister to ensure that the new order prescribed by this Bill will be implemented without delay.  I wish also to express thanks to the members, executives and staff of the Inland Fisheries Trust for the work they have had to do and the work they have done over the years in preserving our fisheries and ensuring that we did not go even further back.  They were underfinanced and under-staffed and did not have the legal powers that they should have had but, within those serious limitations, they did an immense amount of good work.  It must have been a most disappointing experience for them having brought Lake Ennel up to being a premier lake in Europe and to see the lake being totally destroyed.  On that depressing but very personal note I will end and hope that we will never see that again.  I would like to see many Lough Ennels all over the country.  I would like to see fisheries, as a means of livelihood, social recreation and tourist attraction here, being second to none anywhere else.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mícheál Cranitch Mícheál Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to convey our congratulations and thanks to the Inland Fisheries Commission for the work they have done and for the recommendations they have made.  Likewise I convey our congratulations and thanks to the Minister for bringing in such an all-embracing Bill giving effect to most of the more important recommendations of the commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="128" /> While it is, in the main, a Committee Stage Bill with all its 86 pages, I propose to raise a few points at this stage.  The Minister stated that the object of the Bill is to give effect to the main recommendations of the commission by securing more effective conservation, protection, management and development of inland fisheries through the reorganisation and strengthening of the existing administrative structure.  That, indeed, is a very big task and I was glad to note that, so far as this sort of work is concerned, Senator Cooney mentioned some points about which I was also concerned.  The point was realised at one time and there will have to be a re-realisation of it that water&mdash;whether it be that in our rivers, our rain water or of the sea around us&mdash;has a very special significance for our people and our race.  It is something which we will have to emphasise in our educational system at all levels.  We came here mostly over sea.  The sea has been our road to prosperity in other countries in other times.  The sea always had a welcome for us.  It provided us, to a large extent with our food and so, indeed, have our rivers.  It was along our rivers that our peoples came when they came to this island first and the rivers fed them to a large extent.</P>
    <P>Our traditions, folklore and stories deal time and time again with rivers, water and fish, particularly the king of the fish so far as we are concerned, the salmon.  I could not help thinking, as I was giving thought to these particular points, that it would be nice if Fionn Mac Cumhaill could pass on some of the wisdom he got from the salmon of knowledge not alone to our Minister but to all those who will be working under him in completing the great task the Minister has had put before him.</P>
    <P>Another thing which should be of great help in the development of our fisheries is research.  Unfortunately we have not a great tradition as far as that is concerned in our fisheries.  There is a great deal to be learned from studies made by marine biologists, men who deserve every possible encouragement.  I had occasion last year to visit Sherkin Island off the west coast of Cork and there I saw excellent work being done by a man, mostly with his own resources, <Col N="129" /> Matt Murphy.  A tremendous amount of knowledge is to be obtained from such ventures.</P>
    <P>Similar study could be made so far as our inland rivers are concerned.  The great difficulty with our rivers is the matter of pollution.  We must make up our minds sooner or later whether we want polluted rivers followed by the extinction of our fish stocks or clean rivers giving us healthy fish.  Fish have always been regarded as the healthiest form of life in existence.  If we wish a neighbour well at any social gathering we always say: &ldquo;sláinte an bhradáin&rdquo;, &ldquo;the health of the salmon&rdquo;; no fish should be healthier.  We must take every step possible to keep our rivers and lakes clean.</P>
    <P>The stories mentioned by the previous speaker, Senator Cooney, about Lough Ennel could be repeated as regards many other lakes and rivers.  I always feel a pang of despair, I feel actually hurt, whenever I hear of a fish killed in a river whatever the cause of that killing may be.  One of the greatest tasks before the Minister is this question of avoiding polluton.  We must tackle this problem in a big way, otherwise fishing will cease to be a pastime or a tourist attraction to say nothing of the loss in revenue to so many of our people who make a living by fishing either inland or on the seas.</P>
    <P>The other great enemy we have is the illegal fisherman or the poacher.  The poacher should be outlawed just as his brother, the drunken driver, has been outlawed.  We will have to get a proper sense of proportion in our thinking so far as poachers are concerned.  There was always great sympathy for the poacher; he was the kind of person who was down and out, and perhaps something could be said for that sort of reasoning.  There was a time when people were forbidden to fish in certain parts of the river due to the rights, upheld by the law, of various landlords and foreign interests.  But if we want to preserve our fish for the honest fisherman, for the poorest and for those who take up fishing as a pastime and as a means of relaxation&mdash;and a good healthy pastime it is&mdash;we must deal with the poacher just as the drunken driver has been dealt with.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="130" /> The Minister mentioned fish farming.</P>
    <P>He said:</P>
    <P>The great potential of fish farming is recognised in the Bill.  Briefly, the new provisions make it an offence to engage in agriculture unless one holds the appropriate licence.  The Bill enables an order to be made following the usual investigations and, if necessary, an inquiry designating an area of the sea as an area where aquaculture may be carried out, and licences may then be issued for the carrying out of aquaculture in that area.</P>
    <P>I am sure the Minister will give consideration to representations made on behalf of Gael Linn by Domhnall Ó Moráin.  They have a very good case and they deserve every consideration so far as the oyster beds in Fenit, Tralee, are concerned.  There is a great potential in fish farming or aquaculture.  While it is not exactly a new concept it is in its in itial stages here and there is great potential for such a venture.</P>
    <P>I was very glad to see that coarse fishing gets honourable mention.  The Minister said &ldquo;To secure additional income the Bill provides for the payment of a voluntary subscription by trout and coarse fish anglers.&rdquo;  Coarse fishing is increasing in popularity and has become an outstanding tourist attraction.  I have in mind my own town of Fermoy where it has brought a considerable amount of money to the town and has resulted in great fishing activity.  Visitors come not alone from Britain but from the Continent and further afield.  The three great points so far as inland fishing is concerned are that it is a means of livelihood, a splendid recreational pastime and it brings in revenue from tourists.</P>
    <P>I commend the Minister for bringing such a comprehensive and thorough Bill before us and I hope it will get a speedy passage through both Houses.  I wish the Minister every success.  He will need all the knowledge from the salmon of knowledge to which I referred earlier to carry out the task facing him.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMoynihanKerry" hpid="Mr. Moynihan Mr. Moynihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moynihan</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of the Labour Party I welcome this Fisheries Bill.  The only criticism that can be offered <Col N="131" /> is that it is belated.  It relates to a very important aspect of our economy, our fisheries.  First, those fisheries have a tremendous bearing on the employment and livelihood of a substantial section of the community because of our long coastline and also because of our inland resources.  Secondly, they have a social and recreational aspect for the Irish community as a whole.  Thirdly, they are a tremendous attraction for tourists. Therefore, there is a responsibility on all of us to ensure that not only are our existing fisheries protected but that they are developed to their very fullest potential.</P>
      <P>In the past the enemy of the salmon and the trout has been the poacher.  In recent years poachers have been fishing illegally in our seas with massive nets and destroying our especially valuable salmon stocks.  Inland poaching has diminished over the years.  In fact, the poacher was never regarded as a criminal.  He was a legendary figure trying to beat a foreign law and a foreign landlord.  Our traditions had much to do with the respect the community generally afforded to poachers.  A substantial volume of fishing rights was held by outsiders or absentee landlords.  I am glad to see a section in the Bill setting out the basis on which they can be taken over by the new area boards.  Does the Minister feel this will be an easy job?  In the past it was regarded as a very difficult task to attempt to take into local control the rights that had been held for so long by alien interests in some of our best fishing areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The new and the greatest enemy of fish is not the inland poacher but the inland pollution.  As Senator Cooney said, the success or failure of the Minister and his Department in their effort to protect and expand the development of our fisheries to their greatest potential, with the resultant value to the country and to the State, will depend entirely on how we can control pollution of our rivers and lakes.  The lakes in my area and in other areas got considerable publicity in recent years because of the increasing loss of fish life.  It is a good thing that attention is being focussed on that aspect.  In my <Col N="132" /> own area there has been very substantial development in controlling pollution in lakes.</P>
    <P>All our rivers and lakes are equally important and unless there is the utmost co-operation between the Minister and his staff and the Department of the Environment the Minister's legislation cannot succeed.  He should try to ensure that local authorities, through the direction and guidance of the Department, no longer treat the pollution of our rivers and lakes in the haphazard manner in which it has been treated in the past. This is the most fundamental matter the Department of Fisheries have to look at. If we can bring back the crystal waters to our rivers and lakes, legislation within this framework will certainly guarantee that in the future we can look with pride on the very valuable fisheries we have to protect and safeguard.  On behalf of the Labour Party I congratulate the Inland Fisheries Commission on outlining the Bill originally, and the Department for bringing it forward.  I trust it will have a very speedy passage through both Houses with a view to giving the Department of Fisheries and the Department of the Environment the opportunity to go ahead with the full protection and development of our fisheries.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FlorenceCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to join with other Senators in welcoming this Bill.  It is a tremendous step forward in ensuring that mistakes made in the past will not be made in the future.  I think it was Hemingway who said: &ldquo;When we arrive a continent ages quickly&rdquo;.  He was talking about the arrival of the white man in Africa.  Where you have development, progress and prosperity, inevitably there is an invasion of the environment to a certain degree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is our duty not alone to provide industrial advancement for our people and give them the opportunity to get jobs and positions in their own country but also to ensure that we preserve the integrity of the whole atmosphere around us.  The combination of these two objectives is not easy to reconcile.  While there is a very strong and vocal lobby pushing for industrial development, the other lob by is not as strong and as vocal as it should be.  We have an obligation as <Col N="133" /> legislators to ensure that legislation is loaded very much in favour of conservation and preservation.  We may only get the opportunity once of ensuring that we conserve our rivers, our lakes, our seas with the life in them.  The Mediterranean became known as the dead sea because of massive pollution.  We do not want any dead rivers, dead lakes or dead seas within our area.</P>
    <P>It is important on occasions like this to reflect on what is gone and to try to ensure that in the future we do not make some of the mistakes we made in the past.  As Senator Cooney said, it is really an educational process the whole way.  It is very hard in rural areas&mdash;and Senator Moynihan touched on this&mdash;to find condemnation of the poacher.  He is looked upon as a fellow who is making a few dishonest shillings, but not in any malicious way.</P>
    <P>The only way we can get rid of this benign attitude towards the poacher is to ensure that all of the fishing rights and all of the rights in rivers and lakes are held by our own nationals and not by absentee landlords and I mean &ldquo;lords&rdquo; in the literal sense in some cases.  It is endemic in our nature that where we see the big landlord suffering a rebuff, no matter how slight, we relish it and take a certain amount of enjoyment out of it.</P>
    <P>As a priority&mdash;and the Minister referred to this&mdash;we must start immediately with the acquisition of all foreign-held rights in relation to our rivers and our lakes.  I am not too sure that some of those landlords are not the greatest poachers.  It is very hard to confirm stories and rumours but I suppose many public representatives have been told of the massive killings of salmon by so-called landlords and owners of the fishing rights in an area.  The sooner that situation is righted the sooner we will have respect for the law.</P>
    <P>I come from an area, south-west Cork, which is ultra-sensitive to all forms of pollution.  We have just had the disaster in Bantry.  Before that, there were so many instances of pollution, especially on our seashore, that every individual living in those areas which were affected became ultra-conscious of the necessity for proper supervision, proper <Col N="134" /> legislation, and strict enforcement of the law.  Senator Cooney rightly condemned the local authorities.  There is no doubt that the local authorities are the major polluters of our rivers and streams.  They have this schizophrenic attitude of pressing for conservation on the one hand and, on the other hand, allowing pollution to run wild.  If the ordinary individual is to have respect for the law he must be shown that the Minister and the Government mean business when it comes to prosecutions and the enforcement of the law for all, and not just for the individuals.  Local authorities should be proceeded against if they are seen to be breaking the law.  It is ironic that one section in the Department of the Environment are working assiduously day and night to try to protect the environment and another section are going about their business in a perfectly legal manner but contributing towards the pollution of our country.</P>
    <P>We all must be serious about this question of conservation.  We take clean water for granted.  We must remind everybody that this is something we cannot take for granted in the future.  Unless we now take the necessary actions and steps to ensure that we have clean water, we will not have it.  What a tragedy and a catastrophe that would be.  One has only to travel to countries abroad, and especially in the Middle East, to appreciate the value of water and to see how inconsequential oil is in relation to the importance of water.  We have one of the greatest national resources available to mankind: in the main clean water, clean rivers, clean streams and clean lakes.  The Minister is rightly placing a tremendous importance on this Bill because of the necessity of preserving those blessings we have from nature.</P>
    <P>Another aspect the Minister touched on is that of research.  In my area we have a unique lake called Lough Inagh. All the officials of the Minister's Department and the Minister are familiar with what is going on down there.  The research being carried out there and the good work being done should be passed on to the rest of the country.  By this type of research and this type of development we will be more and more able to take command and control of <Col N="135" /> our environment.</P>
    <P>The question of aquaculture was raised&mdash;fish farming.  On the surface this is a very good and a very wise idea, but in some cases you can act prematurely in relation to fish farming.  I had an unfortunate experience in my own constituency when people, probably well-intentioned, set up a fish farm and went through the necessary legal process in order to set up this fish farm.  They put an advertisement in the paper and got a licence eventually from the Minister.  The people of the area were not aware of what was involved in this fish farm. They were not aware that this fish farm was being situated and built on their traditional scollop fishing grounds.  This immediately created a conflict.  It created antagonism towards fish farming which should not have been the case.</P>
    <P>Everybody welcomes new development in relation to marine research and aquaculture, but let us make sure we bring the people along with us.  It is an idle exercise to have a development on one side of the fishing industry at the expense of fishermen on the other side who are making their living from catching other types of fish.  We have to set out on the educational process which is so necessary to make a success of this whole business.  I have no doubt whatsoever that the regional boards under the control of the central board is the right method of doing it.  I urge the Minister to ensure that these boards and the staffing of them are adequate and that they have enough finance to carry on, that they have their own officers who will be the watchdogs on behalf of the people of the area to ensure that we do not have a repetition of the type of pollution experienced up to now.</P>
    <P>Overall, everyone welcomes the Bill.  I do not believe there is a line in it that one could criticise.  We hope that in the years to come because of legislation such as this we will have the cleanest and purest country to live in.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish I could share Senator Crowley's optimism.  I have raised some of the problems which this Bill is tackling on a number of occasions in this House.  I wonder whether the <Col N="136" /> situation has not gone so far in some areas that it is beyond redemption and out of control.</P>
      <P>A great deal of the discussion on this Bill will take place on Committee Stage but I want to make some general points on Second Stage.  The first one concerns, the depletion of our salmon stocks.  This was recognised by the Minister when he said: &ldquo;Last year's salmon catch was just half that of 1975.&rdquo;  That is the catch for the whole island.  That is an absolutely frightening figure.  Clearly, if the deterioration goes on for, say, another three or four years, it is likely that our spawning salmon will be reduced to virtually nil.  I wonder whether the new legislation we are contemplating, the powers we are giving to the boards, the finance and the back-up we are giving to the central board and the various fishery boards, will be sufficient to remedy this situation.</P>
      <P>I have raised the problem on a number of occasions and I should like to quote some of the figures I quoted in this House previously.  In Volume 83, column 1881 of the Official Report I gave the Foyle Fisheries Commission's figures on spawning salmon.  In 1964 the number was 13,000; 1965, 22,000; 1966, 22,600; 1967, 15,000; 1968, 7,000; 1969, 3,800; 1970, 5,300; 1971, 4,300; 1972, 2,100; and 1973 1,500. The Foyle Fisheries Commission made it clear in their report that they felt that, whereas there may have been other contributory causes, the basic cause for this was the extent of the drift netting in the Foyle Estuary.  Today the Minister said:</P>
      <P>I have also included some new provisions in the Bill that should prove of great assistance in fishery protection. The most important of these is the increase of the penalties for fisheries offences to a realistic level.  The Bill prescribes penalties of up to £600 and /or six months in prison on summary conviction.  For the more serious offences provision is made for trial on indictment and the penalty on conviction for such offences can extend up to £1,000 and/or two years in prison.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wonder whether these penalties are sufficient to deter people considering that in a night's successful drift-netting one can <Col N="137" /> catch about £2,000 or £3,000 worth of fish.  I wonder if a fine of £600 will really deter people who on a good night will perhaps get away with a couple of thousand pounds worth of salmon.  I should like to quote from an article in <i>The Cork Examiner</i> of 26 June 1976 some remarks by the Chief Fishery Inspector, Dan Good of the Cork fishery area and I quote:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Army, Navy or special Garda assistance in a combined operation would be necessary to prevent a certain type of illegal fishing in the Castletownbere area&rdquo;, stated Chief Inspector Dan Good in the course of his monthly report presented to yesterday's meeting of Cork No. 5 fishery district presided over by the administrator Mr. G.E. Byrne.  Chief Inspector Good said that a 17 foot boat was too small for patrol work and most of the fishermen were only laughing at them.  He said he had taken the administrator on their last patrol to let him see for himself the size of the nets that were being used. These said another fishery protection officer present were a mile long in contrast to the legal limit of 800 yards, and some of the boats had two. He said that some of the nets were on rollers which meant one man could operate them.  &ldquo;We also visited the Dursey and Garnish area&rdquo;, continued the report, &ldquo;and it was obvious that the place was a minefield of fixed nets. The piers were full of nets especially mono filament and there were boats in that area where drift netting is prohibited.  No water-keepers will ever have a chance of preventing this type of fishing without the help either of the Army or the Navy or special Garda assistance and it will have to be a combined operation.  You would be attacked immediately by about 30 fishermen using oars, sticks and knives.  Yesterday, accompanied by Mr. Byrne, we visited the Ballycotton area and again the fixed nets were quite obvious and seemed to be an accepted fact.  Unless something drastic is done, little or no prevention of drift net fishing can be undertaken with our present equipment.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="138" /> One constantly reads reports of this sort of problem throughout the country.  I wonder whether the legislation we are discussing now will really remedy the situation.  At least from the tone of the speeches in this House, more people are aware of the problem than when I spoke in 1976.  It has got through more to the general public.  Will the legislation we are discussing affect the situation?</P>
    <P>Like other speakers I pay tribute to the Report of the Inland Fisheries Commission. In company with Senator Cooney I welcome the very straightforward way in which the recommendations are set out and in which the information is given.  I should like to look at the section dealing with our salmon and sea trout stocks and discuss some of the report's findings.  One of the illustrations is of the Bantry Bay fishery, and Appendix 11 of the report discusses the findings on that fishery.  In 1963, there were approximately two drift nets operating in Bantry Bay.  In 1971, the number had gone up to 76 and in 1972 to 150.  That was the peak.  In 1973, it dropped to 130 and in 1974 it dropped to 80.  The number of spawning salmon in the rivers in the Bantry Bay area at the last count which was 1973, 1974 and 1975 was nil. Since these counts were done fairly thoroughly by the Inland Fishery Trust over a three-year period, we can take it that salmon are extinct in the rivers flowing into Bantry Bay.</P>
    <P>In that situation the Minister should ban all forms of drift-net fishing and, if necessary, ban the local anglers from fishing in the Bantry Bay rivers.  If there is to be any chance of recovery all fishing must stop for a sufficient period and the rivers must be restocked.  As far as drift-netting is concerned it has been a case of killing the goose that laid the golden egg.  It was not very difficult for the drift-netters, legal or illegal, to operate because they were operating under legislation introduced in 1848 when the only power by which a boat was propelled was by oar or sail.  No boat propelled by this method could haul a very long or deep net.  It just was not possible.  In recent years we have been witnessing situations in which power boats are tearing around pulling nets a <Col N="139" /> couple of miles long at the mouth of the bay, even a bay as big as Bantry.  The result has been the virtual extinction of salmon in the Bantry area.</P>
    <P>The fisheries commission although certain representations were made to them, do not advocate in their report the total banning of drift-net fishing because they recognise that in some areas, particularly some of the western seaboard areas, the contribution to the livelihood of the local people is important.  These are areas in which farming is perhaps subsistence level farming and where it is a question of striking a balance.</P>
    <P>I would urge the Minister that in the areas in which the salmon stocks have dwindled to what is virtually extinction level the question of the revocation of all net licences should be seriously considered. Otherwise, there will never be any salmon in these areas.  Again drift-netters, draft-netters or anglers will never get anything from these particular areas.  On this question, paragraph 3.7.2 of the report reads:</P>
    <P>Salmon fishing in the sea is virtually unsupervised.  Regulations regarding nets, and particularly the permitted maximum lengths of drift nets, are ignored on a widespread scale, the weekly close time is often openly infringed and some fishermen fish without licences.  The extent of this problem should be fully appreciated as well as the consequences for the salmon stocks, and therefore salmon fishing in the sea should be effectively controlled.</P>
    <P>The report goes on to advocate the purchase of patrol boats by the board's conservators.  In some cases this has happened but further boats will have to be purchased if adequate surveillance is to be carried out.  The report also advocates the possibility of surveillance by air, light aircraft and helicopters, an operation that has been successfully carried out in Norway.</P>
    <P>There are other recommendations. There is the recommendation that penalties be greatly increased.  This Bill increases them, but whether the increases are large enough is open to question. The commission recommend that <Col N="140" /> all licensed nets be tagged in a prescribed manner so as to identify the licence owners and that the boats used for salmon fishing be clearly numbered for the same purpose.  They recommend that it be obligatory for salmon drift-nets to remain attached to the fishing boats at all times because in many cases they were either staked or they were just let drift and then collected later.</P>
    <P>These are problems which the central board and the regional boards and the Minister and his Department will be faced with, and it is not really a question of legislation although it is important that the legislation be updated, particularly the legislation that was brought in in 1848.  It is a question of will, and it is a question of feeling that there is public support for the saving of our salmon stocks.  This debate is showing that there is such support and I would urge the Minister to take the action that is necessary, however drastic to ensure that our salmon stocks are saved.</P>
    <P>Of course there are other reasons for the depletion of salmon stocks.  There has been fishing off the coast of Greenland.  There is the problem of pollution. There is the problem of arterial drainage.  These have contributed somewhat to the depletion of salmon stocks but I think the experts by and large agree that the main reason for the depletion has been excessive drift-netting. Unless that is controlled and regulated and unless the regulations which are made are strictly enforced, if necessary by the Garda, the Army and the Naval Service, there is little hope of saving our salmon stocks.  If we fail in this regard, then in five years' time when another piece of legislation comes up dealing with fisheries we will not be discussing the problem of salmon at all.</P>
    <P>I should like to move on to another problem of a more technical nature with which this legislation is concerned, that is the construction and the powers of the central board.  In a number of other countries where such central boards exist they are executive boards with executive powers.  This was clearly recommended by the commission in paragraph 8.1.2 of their report, I quote:</P>
    <P>We are satisfied that the varied complex and far flung functions we <Col N="141" /> have in mind could not be operated efficiently by the type of departmental Executive Office which the Public Services Organisation Review Group, 1966-1969, considered appropriate to non-commercial State-sponsored activities. They will require in our opinion an organisation which requires a high degree of continuity and specialisation at all staff level and a degree of freedom, flexibility, personal responsibility and general acceptability greater than that which is normally associated with conventionally organised departments of State.</P>
    <P>The commission go on to say that they are acutely conscious that the success of the new organisation will depend on its being acceptable on the whole to the various and often conflicting interests with which it will be involved.  They say that in a civil service situation this would not be readily achievable.  I do not want to appear critical of the civil service but I would tend to agree with that assessment.</P>
    <P>One matter that is distressing is that the central board is too much under the direction of the Minister and the executive powers which the commission recommended should be given to the board are all being vested in the Minister.  In other words, this gives his Department more control over the central board than I believe they should have.  I believe there should be freedom and flexibility and that the board should have more executive powers.  The commission's report made this very clear in paragraph 8.3.2 which reads:</P>
    <P>We envisage the Fisheries Minister as being advised by a small, highly-geared Fisheries Department of the type recommended by the Public Service Organisation Review Group.  In broad terms his function in relation to inland fisheries would be to indicate general lines of policy, set goals, and maintain overall control over the activities of the Fisheries Authority.</P>
    <P>In this case this is the central board.  It would appear on a close reading of section 7 of the Bill where are set out the powers of the central board and their relationship with the Minister that the <Col N="142" /> Minister has taken the powers which the commission's report envisages for the central board, and that the board will be so much under his control that they will not, so far as I can see, have the initiative and freedom or the flexibility they should have if they are to work effectively. I should like to draw a parallel which the Minister will recall.  I am sure it has not been completely worked out but it is something with which I sided with his party, against the recommendations of the former Minister for Agriculture in regard to shackling An Foras Talúntais.  We had a long debate in this House, during which there was a three-hour hold up, and I discovered that An Foras Talúntais had been set up by a treaty between the US and this country by means of money coming from the Marshall Aid Plan.  It was clear when one read the terms of this treaty that the Americans had insisted that An Foras Talúntais should be absolutely independent of State control.  This was right and far-sighted and it gave this institute, which has achieved a great international reputation, the flexibility to carry out the programmes that it wished to carry out and it did not necessarily have to have the say-so for every single item of its business from the Department of Agriculture.  The Department did not like this and did their best to bring An Foras Talúntais back into the fold.  I am glad to say that the Government have reversed the decisions of the previous administration concerning An Foras Talúntais.</P>
    <P>The Minister should look again at section 7 particularly in relation to the present position of the Inland Fisheries Trust because they operate with a good deal of freedom and a good deal of flexibility which I am advocating.  The commission give the Inland Fisheries Trust great praise.  I quote from paragraph 4.10.1 of the report:</P>
    <P>... the story of development work for brown trout, coarse fish, and indeed sea angling, is in large part the story of the Inland Fisheries Trust.</P>
    <P>In their present form, the trust have freedom and flexibility.  When they become a part of the structure set out here the researchers and the members of <Col N="143" /> the trust, and in fact their policy, will come much more under the direction of the Minister.</P>
    <P>I am against excessive centralisation of bureaucratic control.  I always protest about it on every possible occasion and I should like to protest on this occasion. The Minister should look again at section 7 and should see his way to giving the central board greater initiative and not have every direction coming down from the top which would be a sure way of dampening the spirit of enterprise which we want to see this board adopting.  As the Minister has said in his speech&mdash;and I welcome this&mdash;we are not just talking about the negative aspects of fishery development, about protection, about cutting out the drift-netters, about cutting out illegal fishing, we are also talking about the positive aspects, about the promotion of the whole area of our fisheries.  The board would have to be able to take the initiative that is required.</P>
    <P>The Inland Fisheries Trust, as well as doing the work in inland waters, have done a considerable amount of work in sea water particularly in the areas of the fish such as bass and mullet and anglers' fish such as sharks, skates and rays. This is work which complements work done by the Department which is mainly concerned with commerical species. What will be the situation regarding this development of sea fishing under the central board?  Will this be moved from the central board and operated by the Department of Agriculture?  I often find the jargon in which these things are set out rather difficult to disentangle but it seems to me that there is a danger that this work may not continue under the central board.  Section 7 (1) (g) refers to it but I should like more than assurances from the Minister.  I should like some changes made in this section and we can discuss them at the appropriate time. The main point I want to make is that the central board should have freedom and flexibility, should be allowed show initiative and be able to operate on their own lines.</P>
    <P>There are two other main points I should like to make.  One is the problem concerning arterial drainage.  Senator <Col N="144" /> Cooney has mentioned the difficulties experienced in Lough Ennel.  They were mainly from the problem of sewage being pumped into the lake but there is another problem which many of our inland lakes are suffering from, that is, that the drainage of rivers tends to lower lake levels and if there is a tendency to putrefaction this would greatly increase that tendency.  Therefore, drainage should only be carried out with great circumspection. I note that the commission are so worried about this problem of drainage that in paragraph 9 they recommend a change in the law which this Bill does not encompass.</P>
    <P>The report points out that the drainage commission of 1938 recommended that the drainage authority should be exempt from complying with the Fisheries Acts.  Essentially the Commissioners of Public Works have only to consult with the Minister for Fisheries but they are not bound in any statutory way by his advice.  They need only ask him for his advice and then they can go ahead.  The report recommends&mdash;and I am sorry that this Bill does not put forth this recommendation&mdash;that there should be some statutory obligation on the Commissioners of Public Works to receive the agreement of the Minister rather than merely to consult with him on drainage.  The commission submit, at paragraph 9.14.3, that when drainage is being carried out by the Commissioners of Public Works:</P>
    <P>... they be obliged by statute to conserve the aesthetic and fishery values of waters on which they operate.</P>
    <P>Public opinion has changed greatly on this question in the last ten years and what drainage people would have got away with some years ago is much more likely to be questioned for its effect nowadays than it was ten or 15 years ago.  There is no doubt that a great deal of damage was done to rivers in their fishery aspect by some of the large drainage schemes of some years ago. With a bit more care the drainage could have been carried out and the spawning beds and so on need not have been so drastically affected.</P>
    <P>I should like to see a statutory requirement in this Bill to insist that from <Col N="145" /> now on all arterial drainage carried out by the Commissioners of Public Works should have the agreement of the Minister, in other words, agreement that the fisheries would not be affected or if there was damage caused to the fisheries by the carrying out of the drainage that the commissioners would be obliged to repair this damage.</P>
    <P>My final point concerns aquaculture. Senator Crowley has spoken sensitively on this issue.  He has been directly involved in disputes which have gone on in his constituency.  There is no question that there is a fear among traditional fishermen that fish farming will affect their livelihood and their traditional fishing beds.  It is a question of balancing the rights of the traditional fishermen, the boat fishermen, with the developing industry.  It is an important developing industry and if we can strike the right balance a great deal of good can be done.  I do not think that section 51 of the Bill goes far enough.  I imagine that in the course of this discussion the Minister may be thinking of certain amendments.  It is right that people involved in aquaculture should obtain licences.  Aquaculture should be licensed and regulated because it can do a great deal of damage.  There is the question of holding an inquiry when a licence is issued. I am not against the holding of inquiries. Public discussion is a good thing.  In some cases an inquiry can dissipate a lot of heat locally if there is a reasonably frank discussion of the pros and cons of a case.</P>
    <P>I wonder what will happen, when this legislation is passed, to existing operators of fish farms.  How will their operations be looked at?  The legislation will affect them considerably and could, if operated harshly, put some of them out of business.  I do not think this sort of thing will happen but there are problems.  For example, there is the salmon levy.  I do not think that the levy should apply to farmed salmon up to the time of harvesting because the problem with fish farming from the financial point of view is that it needs a great capital investment and there is a considerable waiting time before one gets any return.  Perhaps the Minister would clarify the position regarding the levy.</P>
    <Col N="146" />
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>It will apply only on first sales of salmon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>But when salmon harvested from a fish farm are sold will there be a levy on the first sale?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be the sale by the operator?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>I would argue that perhaps the Minister should think again about that levy on fish farming.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>He is already thinking about levies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>One of the difficulties is that there is always a problem of malicious damage.  It is easy to put a fish farm out of business&mdash;if it is in the sea you just cut the nets or if it is inland a couple of handfuls of poison in the top pool would ruin the whole farm.  We could look at the problem of malicious damage when we are dealing with section 51.  There is a more positive thing that one might do; for example, one might insist in section 51 on the monitoring of the plankton in a fish farm in the sea.  This could help to give early warning of things like the red tide.  That might be done by way of statutory requirement or it might be done by order but it would help to increase the flow of information. If it were done by way of statutory requirement it could help to alert the people to problems such as those of the red tide.</P>
      <P>I do not think any of us is under any illusions as to the importance of this Bill. The most serious problem confronting the Minister is the problem of our dwindling salmon stocks.  The authorities I have asked about this Bill are of the impression generally that it has a good chance of doing good if it is put into practice in the right spirit and if the back-up in terms of resources is forthcoming.  I trust that the Minister is successful in this area as well as in the other areas which the Bill is designed to deal with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="147" />
    <Speaker pid="LadyGoulding" hpid="Lady Goulding Lady Goulding">
      <NameTxt>Lady Goulding</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like briefly to make a few points of a parochial nature.  Other Senators have dealt with the subject in a most interesting manner and I have learned a lot from listening to them.  I should like to speak as one who has no connection with fishing. However, we are lucky enough to have a small river and we allow young people to come and fish it for salmon.  Up to a year-and-a-half ago the salmon reached our part of the river beheaded having gone through nets which we took down every night but which were put up again. When they had been taken down about 50 times gunpowder was then thrown into the pond.  This was in one of the most beautiful counties in Ireland&mdash;Wicklow.  The tourist traffic was affected because people went to visit Wicklow to engage in some minor fishing which they enjoyed.</P>
      <P>I welcome this Bill very much but I should like to let the Minister know the good work that has been done in the past year-an-a-half by the fishery protection officers and the Garda in the Wicklow area.  These people have gone out at all times of the day and night, have caught many poachers and have brought them to justice.  Several of these young boys who come and learn to fish are now catching up to 10 lb. salmon.  At the same time, I should like the House to know that something is being done by the fisheries protection officers and the gardaí in the County of Wicklow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>The House is almost unanimous in welcoming this Bill.  For quite a number of years, pending the introduction of this legislation, we have had to renew the procedures for the election of boards of conservators.  Judging from the Minister's speech, the shadow of finance appears to hang over the successful implementation of this legislation. In quite a number of instances he mentions the need for greater finance, from no matter what sources.  He has mentioned the implementation of a levy, which has already bred some discontent in other quarters.  I hope it does not breed similar discontent among hoteliers, restaurant owners or fish <Col N="148" /> dealers.  However, that remains to be seen.  This legislation could be called a new deal as regards inland fisheries, preservation and development.  If it is a new deal, certainly as regards the working conditions of those most overworked people in the boards of conservators, it is to be welcomed.  Perhaps it will succeed in this respect.  The Minister has mentioned initially the figure of seven but I am glad to see that he has kept his options open to extending this number, or even restricting it, as experience will show.  We are, when all is said and done, asking seven boards to do the work of what 17 boards of conservators do at present.  The history of the existing boards of conservators, in the areas in which they operate, have something to show us as regards the problems and the difficulties which confront anybody involved in the protection of our inland fisheries.  It is imperative that the boards should not be too remote from the actual areas of operation; the boards of conservators, as geographically situated at present, would seem to have met this criterion.  Unfortunately, the boards of conservators had to cope with other difficulties, principally in relation to finance, staffing and inadequate equipment.  Whatever number of regional fisheries boards is adopted, it is essential that they should be localised, and I would ask the Minister to pay special attention to this, even after the introduction of the seven regional boards.  If the members of these boards feel it necessary that the number should be extended, that should be done.  It is not easy to exercise the proper protection and deterrent measures in regard to poaching, and the proper measures in regard to prevention of pollution, if the central bodies, the regional fisheries boards, are remote from the actual areas where these things happen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the democratic aspect of the election to the new regional boards. The Minister has not indicated when the boards will be set up or when he will introduce the first system of elections.  In the meantime, he indicates that he will nominate all the members of the first regional boards.  I would ask him to ensure that his nominees will reflect in <Col N="149" /> calibre, experience and qualification the type of personnel who will, let us say, be introduced by the electorate in subsequent elections.  It is important to begin on the right basis.  Certainly, the conditions of service of the people involved in this most important work must receive special attention.  The Minister has indicated that he will do everything in this regard to ensure that they have the same conditions of service as they have at present and that he will introduce superannuation schemes and the like.</P>
    <P>One of the greatest hindrances to personnel involved in the existing boards of conservators was lack of adequate facilities.  I found, from personal experience and involvement with complaints made to me by anglers, that there was a lack of even basic requirements, such as an adequate number of telephones, vans and the proper mechanised equipment to enable personnel in the boards of conservators to get around their areas.  Improved facilities must be put at the disposal of the personnel.</P>
    <P>The Minister said that the main thrust he sees coming from this Bill is that of switching the emphasis from protection to development of our inland fisheries.  I have been unable to find in the rest of his speech any elaboration on this concept that it will lead to a great development of our inland fisheries.  The speech seems to be concentrated on future personnel structures and their election, the penalties and other aspects of illegal fishing.  Would the Minister give some indication of how our inland fisheries can be developed in the sense envisaged in his speech?</P>
    <P>There is no doubt that we are all agreed that the attitude of the public towards poaching has changed in recent years, which is welcome.  With the introduction of these new regional boards, with their new personnel and staffing structures, the Central Fisheries Board and the regional boards should avail of the opportunity to show the public the unsocial and illegal aspects of poaching. The fisheries boards could do much through education in our schools and by adult education through the media.</P>
    <P>There is no doubt the question of pollution <Col N="150" /> has angered the public mind much more in recent years than in the past. Apart from the economic aspect of the £20 million indicated by the Minister as what the inland fisheries are worth to the national economy, clean waters and clean fish are two matters which we want to preserve and time is of the essence in this regard.  It has been disappointing to me that, since we put through this House the Water Pollution Act of 1976, so little has been done in regard to the employment and recruitment of properly qualified staff in this respect.  My own county council are, at present, only contemplating advertising for personnel to look after the implementation of that Act.  There is no doubt that even a couple of years of neglect in regard to keeping waters clean can have a most serious long-term effect.  We might never be able to catch up on the time that was lost.  Certainly, the fisheries boards that are being introduced will have a lot to do in regard to educating the public at large in regard to the unsocial and illegal aspects of poaching and pollution.</P>
    <P>The penalties envisaged by the Minister seem adequate in present circumstances. However, like all penalties introduced in an Act, they need to be modified at regular periods, otherwise they lose all power as a deterrent.  When all is said and done, these regional boards will need finance if they are to be successful.  Whatever the alternative sources of finance suggested by the Minister, the main burden will fall on the Government of the day, to ensure that adequate financial subvention is available to these boards to do their most important work.  I should hate to think that this would not be so.  As the fisheries board should avail of the different public attitude towards illegal fishing, the Government should avail of the different public attitude now, to ensure that the finance necessary to do this most essential work is available to the boards.</P>
    <P>We all welcome this Bill and wish it the best of success.  Whether it will be as successful in practice as in theory remains to be seen.  Given the present public climate towards the matters at issue, the Government should not spare, <Col N="151" /> in any respect, the financing of whatever is needed by the boards.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasWhitaker" hpid="Dr. Whitaker Dr. Whitaker">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Whitaker</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is an important measure of reorganisation.  The administrative reforms it introduces, and the increased penalties it provides for are urgently necessary.  I welcome the Bill for the prospect it holds out of effective future action in conserving and developing our inland fisheries, particularly our salmon fisheries, which I have described here recently as not only an important natural, but also an important national resource.  The effectiveness of the new structures will depend on the success of our efforts to ensure that salmon reach our inland waters in sufficient numbers at least to maintain, but preferably to increase, the breeding stock.  Clearly, there is no future in Ireland for the salmon unless the over-fishing at sea is stopped, unless commercialised poaching, poisoning and other forms of illegal predation in rivers, estuaries and lakes are stopped and unless pollution is brought under control.  Otherwise, the salmon faces extinction in a short space of years.  This fate has already befallen it in many other countries and in several famous Irish salmon rivers, such as the Erne, the Boyne, the Lee and the Liffey.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When I spoke here on 14 December, I mentioned two facts to highlight the salmon crisis.  Most important is the single figure which shows that salmon are no longer reproducing themselves, but are in steep decline.  The net reproduction rate for salmon, as established in what are virtually ideal conditions at Lough Furnace in County Mayo, is now not two, as it should be, if the population were to be maintained, but less than one.  The second figure I quoted on that occasion and, again, it is a hard figure, it is not an unreliable one, is the experience at Thomond Weir in Limerick where there is a complete count of fish.  The intake there, that is, of salmon entering the Shannon to spawn, is now only one-eighth of the average intake of the years 1963 to 1967; a mere 2,100 as against over 17,000.  The reason why so few fish are entering fresh water to spawn is that their survival at sea and in the estuaries is being <Col N="152" /> drastically reduced by over-fishing.</P>
    <P>The Minister, of course, is well aware that, apart from over-fishing at sea, stocks are being depleted on a scandalous scale and quite blatantly by commercial poachers&mdash;greedy, organised poaching.  These people defy and attack the inspectors and protective staff of the present boards of conservators.  Several Senators tried to conjure up a congenial picture of the hardy, jaunty native having a &ldquo;go&rdquo; at the absentee landlord.  Nobody would mind that, but the Minister knows what is happening and it is being applied not only to absentee landlords but to fisheries under his own ownership and control&mdash;by organised gangs raiding the fish constantly, and virtually with impunity.</P>
    <P>I am very glad to hear, from the Minister's speech, that the new central board and the new regional boards will be adequately staffed and equipped and have sufficient support from the Garda Síochána and the Naval Service to do their job effectively.  I hope, also, that the Minister will be able to ensure that the new close period will be observed.  As he well knows, scant notice has been taken by net fishermen of the present shorter period.  I would like to emphasise a point made by other speakers, that uniformly strict enforcement is necessary if the observers of the law are not to feel let down.</P>
    <P>To put the problem in perspective I would like to give the information I have gleaned about who is catching the fish and in what quantities.  Over the past 20 years, the official figures show a great upsurge in the total catch of salmon, rising to a peak in 1974-75.  For those years the catch, in weight and numbers, was nearly three times what it was 20 years ago.  Over the last few years, as the Minister has said, it has been cut by half. The strong upturn in the Irish catch began in 1962 and steadily increased as drift-nets caught up with, and passed out, draft nets as the main instrument of capture.  The drift-nets were responsible for less than one-quarter of the total catch in 1962 but they accounted for three-quarters of the total catch by 1974 and have roughly maintained their position since.  Draft nets are now down to less than one-quarter.  Between them, <Col N="153" /> drift and draft nets account for 93 per cent of the total catch.  Other forms of capture, including rod and line, are so small as to be negligible.  Anglers accounted for just over 2 per cent of the total catch last year according to figures given in the Dáil recently by the Minister.  When one bears this proportion in mind, it supports my suggestion that restrictions on anglers are something of an unnecessary penance. They may be part of the cosmetics of this situation but they make no real contribution to conservation.  Indeed, I would suggest to the Minister that there would be less poaching, less opportunity at any rate for poaching, in September if anglers were walking the river banks.  I am glad to see that the Minister has allowed the sea trout angler to do so.</P>
    <P>In the light of these facts about who catches the salmon, I suggested in December, and I repeat today, that the restrictive measures so far taken are quite inadequate.  The Minister cannot rely in the future, any more than he could in the past, on completely success ful enforcement of the law.  Conservation to be effective must do something more serious about drift-net fishing, if only because it accounts for three-fourths of the total catch.  I cannot see that it will curtail drift-net fishing greatly to prevent it starting before 15 March or continuing after 20 July.  The Minister might reassure me if he could indicate that a substantial proportion of the drift-net catch occurs outside these dates.  But I suspect that there is very little drift-net fishing before 15 March and not a great deal after 20 July.  The drift-net men still have the whole summer influx of grilse from mid-May to mid-July within reach of their nets.</P>
    <P>To sum up, I am worried by the possibility that all the new structures and dispositions may fail in their objective to rescue the salmon from extinction simply because the restrictions being imposed on salmon fishing are not adequate.  I would rather see restrictions that really bite being introduced for a few years, even if this meant compensating, within reason, those licensed fishermen who habitually draw their main livelihood from net fishing for salmon.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="154" /> I might be permitted to put two questions to the Minister for clarification. The first concerns aquaculture. Reference has been made to this point by two previous speakers.  Senator Cranitch referred to certain oyster beds. As the Minister knows, aquaculture covers also the rearing of salmon and rainbow trout in cages off the coast and possibly other forms of fish.  As I read what the Minister said in his opening remarks it seemed that the new provisions&mdash;by making it an offence to engage in aquaculture unless one holds the appropriate licence and by not being explicit that anyone who is already operating has, if not an automatic at least a presumptive entitlement to a licence&mdash;might put in jeopardy a lot of pioneering research, experiment and investment. Perhaps the Minister could reassure me on that point.  The second specific question relates to the entitlement to vote in elections to the regional boards.  It is quite clear that a person who subscribes and is registered as a trout and coarse fish angler will have that entitlement.  Will that also be the position of persons holding the ordinary individual's salmon fishing licence?</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasWhitaker" hpid="Dr. Whitaker Dr. Whitaker">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Whitaker</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyMcAuliffe" hpid="Mr. McAuliffe Mr. McAuliffe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McAuliffe</NameTxt>
      <P>Anybody having the interest of the fisheries industry at heart will welcome this Bill because it contains some excellent suggestions.  I do not think anyone could find fault with the Minister on the manner in which he has decided to elect the various boards.  It constitutes a democratic system after one year.  Also he has done something that has not been done before, he has given recognition to the people who spend their lives in coarse fishing.  If we take the example of the English tourist, he would prefer to spend one day on the canal than ten days on the River Shannon looking for salmon.  He prefers coarse fishing.  For that reason I believe that the Minister is right to give these people a say in the election of the board he is about to set up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In regard to heavier fines, the Minister was somewhat lenient in that, after a <Col N="155" /> third offence the provision is that a person would not receive a fishing licence.  That is too lenient altogether because there are offences every day of the week as regards the catching of salmon, trout and so on, in various rivers.  I come from the Boyne catchment area where there are three rivers.  In the month of November these three rivers are crowded with salmon coming up to the spawning beds.  I am ashamed to say that many times I have seen lights down the river.  When one sees a light on the river at night on can be sure that there is someone poaching salmon.  To take out a salmon cock is not too bad but when they take out the female of the species it absolutely murders our salmon stocks. In the Boyne area there are certain people who will not allow fishermen to fish at all.  The Minister is now making provision about rights of way by agreement or by CPO.  I fully agree that that should be done.</P>
    <P>The Minister says the main emphasis of the Bill switches from protection to development of inland fisheries.  Senators are aware that illegal salmon fishing is one of the major causes of declining salmon stocks.  It is one reason only; development in other directions is doing much more harm.  For example, we have the Boyne arterial drainage scheme. That has done more harm to salmon stocks than any other form of development and we can do nothing about it. The land must be drained, there is too much at stake.  But fishing will suffer anywhere arterial drainage is undertaken. It happened in the Moy and various other rivers throughout the country.  The gravel beds are taken out. There must be sand or gravel to have spawning beds.  If the gravel is taken out and perhaps sunk down to the rock they cannot create another spawning bed. Hundreds of salmon used to come up our rivers every year.  Now the water is so low that, unless there is extensive rain, they do not come up at all.  Until the heavy rain in November we did not see any salmon up the river.</P>
    <P>Fortunately, I saw fewer people trying to destroy salmon this year.  It is a move in the right direction.  The Minister says that the boards will have the full support <Col N="156" /> of the Garda and the Navy.  That is no good unless the general public and landowners near the spawning beds cooperate with the Garda in ensuring that these spawning beds and our salmon are not destroyed.  Salmon fishing is our greatest tourist attraction.  We must not allow our salmon to be destroyed on the spawning beds.  Everyone knows they come up the small rivers.  They do not stay in the big rivers; they do not stay in the sea; they come right up to spawn in the months of October and November and they must be protected at that time. It is child's play to take out salmon from small rivers like the Monagh, the Dell and the Yellow, three tributaries of the Boyne where it can be done with a lamp and a four-pronged fork.  I am glad to say there has been less of it this year.  I have not seen anyone on the river this year.  It is a good sign.  Every encouragement should be given.  As the Minister said at the beginning of his speech, we must educate our people to respect this wealth of ours and the dangerous period for the destruction of that wealth is during the winter months.</P>
    <P>I hope the Minister will not have to increase the penalties for illegal fishing.  I hope it will become a thing of the past, but it is unlikely to happen overnight.  It is realistic to impose heavy penalties on anybody who attempts to destroy that wealth.  It is well known that Lough Ennell is no longer a trout lake because of certain pollution.  But the Government are taking precautions in that respect, as they are doing in Killarney, to ensure the minimum amount of pollution of our lakes.  Something was done in Lough Ennel that never should have been done. Hundreds of tons of coarse fish were taken out and thrown in heaps on the banks; the finest pike were thrown there in tons.  The fisheries board took them out and left them to rot there where one could see them from any reasonable distance. It was a mistake because, when the pike were in the lake, there was less pollution.  Pike is a fish that will eat anything that comes its way.  The trout were stronger and better.  It was the survival of the fittest.  Everybody knows that trout can swim almost twice as fast as pike and for that reason we had better trout fishing when the pike were in the <Col N="157" /> lake.  It would not have been a bad thing to have left them there.</P>
    <P>I read about an estate in England where they said they would get rid of all the vermin, where there were pheasants and so on.  They spent a good deal of money getting rid of them on six square miles of land.  It was great the first year. But subsequently the pheasants got weak and inbred.  It was child's play to shoot them down, and when you shot them down they were not worth anything.  Fish are coming back into Lough Ennel but the fisheries board have not decided to stock it up.  It would be a worth-while exercise to consider what could be done with Lough Ennel because it was one of the finest fishing grounds in the country.</P>
    <P>I congratulate the Minister on introducing this Bill.  It is a step in the right direction and, as far as I am aware, there will be no division on it here this evening.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelMulcahy" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Many complimentary statements and comments have been made about this Bill, with most of which I would agree.  I shall not delay the House by repeating them but rather take them as read.  This is the first occasion on which the Minister has introduced a Bill in this House.  We welcome it, as we do also his trust in the Seanad to ensure it receives good treatment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The first point on which I should like to comment in relation to the Bill is the Minister's emphasis on development rather than conservation.  I think it was Senator Markey made the same point.  I hope that in his reply the Minister will develop that point somewhat.  When one changes one's strategy, when one adopts a development rather than a conservation stance it is inevitable that one must change one's structures as well.  This Bill is about changing structures.  It seems to me that it is a job well done.  Now it is just a matter of making them work.  I cannot help suggesting to the Minister that he might seek the help of people skilled in organisation development, one of the fields of study in modern management receiving a lot of attention at present, to help in getting the new groupings to work effectively together.  These things do not happen by chance.  There <Col N="158" /> will always be inbuilt inertias and power positions in various corners of an organisation that need to be moderated somewhat.  Their ways of doing this and possibly also those of some of the people in the Department of the Public Service who are becoming skilled in that area might help.  It might seem a light point to make at this point in the Bill but perhaps in a year or a couple of years' time it might not seem so light.</P>
    <P>The other aspect of the organisation side on which I would like to comment is the old one I have brought up many times in the House, that is, that the role of the technical people should be emphasised, that in setting up the organisations and in their staffing we should ensure that we do not get a reproduction of the dual system existing in the service, rather that the technical people who have the skills and who have to do the job will be those who have the responsibility.</P>
    <P>As a more particular point and arising from some of the comments made earlier by Senator Cranitch, and just recently by Senator Whitaker, I should like to address myself to the question of oysters.  Chaith mé tréimhse in mo shaol mar bhainisteoir ginearálta ar an eagras sin Gael-Linn agus san am sin rinneamar iarracht ar bheirtreacha oisri i gCill Chiarain a fhorbairt agus tá mé ag caint anois ar an mbliain 1969.  Ag an uair sin ni raibh an teicneolaíocht i gcomhair oisrí forbartha go dti an bpointe go bhféadfaí dul ar aghaidh go tapaidh, ach anois cloisim le déanaí go bhfuil an teicneolaíocht tagtha go dti pointe go bhfuil sé eacnamaíoch dul ar aghaidh le forbairt oisrí.  Tá an job seo á dhéanamh ag Gael Linn le cabhair ó Ghaeltarra Eireann agus an bord i gcomhair eolaíochta agus teicneolaíochta agus mar sin de.  Is breá an rud sin a fheiceáil.  Ach tá cúpla constaicí ann.</P>
    <P>I will switch back to English on the obstacles.  The difficulties existing have been raised already.  I gather the Minister will deal with them from the nod he gave to Senator Whitaker's point&mdash;that where an organisation already is working on aquaculture their rights should be recognised.  There is a sort of implication in the Bill that they <Col N="159" /> will have to go seeking them again.  I am sure the Minister will promise to&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Just to reassure the House, they will get a fish culture licence automatically under section 51 (1) (a).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelMulcahy" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Excellent.  That will be a relief to the people concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Existing operators.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelMulcahy" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Those who have existing rights.  There are extensive oyster beds running through Cill Ciaráin in the west which an organisation like Gael Linn for many years has been trying to develop.  Private organisations of that kind have contributed a tremendous amount to the development of technology in this area.  As I was saying in Irish, in my time the yield from a spat of oysters was 1 per cent.  Indeed, one was lucky if one got 1 per cent.  At that time we felt that if we could get that yield to within 2 or 3 per cent we were really in business.  More recently I gather the yields are reaching that economic level.  It might surprise Senators to know that there was a time in this country when there was consumption of oysters of the order of 50 million or 60 million a year.  It was the shellfish on which the ordinary man on the coast almost lived.</P>
      <P>Over-fishing and ill-treatment in earlier days depleted stocks to the position they were in in the last few years and from which they have been recovering only recently.  In that regard I would draw the Minister's attention also to the difficulty of protecting beds of those kinds where one is farming the sea, switching oysters from one section to another depending on the plankton count.  It would appear that the authorities can protect only the undersized oysters&mdash;the ones that will go through the ring&mdash;whereas for various legal reasons they will not protect those which have grown to the right size.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I hope all of this will be looked after in the new Bill.  I am very heartened to see there is a tightening up on the policing.  I recognise there are difficulties about this. It is very hard for a person who has been living on the coastline, who for many <Col N="160" /> years has been accustomed to sitting into a boat rowing out, drawing up a few oysters or whatever from the natural bottom of the sea, to understand that. When the economic conditions are taken into account attendant employment and everything else of a more utilitarian value protection must be provided.</P>
    <P>I know very little about salmon fishing as it has been developed; I am not going to add to it.  A figure was mentioned to me recently which really impressed me and, I think, highlights the point&mdash;that where a salmon is brought out by rod and line it is worth £240; where it is brought out by net it is worth its face value.  The Minister mentioned a figure of £15 million being the yield from the tourist industry.  Put in those terms&mdash;£250 when removed by rod and line, as opposed to the face value removed by net&mdash;it brings it home.  Taking a line, say, very roughly, west of Ballina and Cork we have some of the finest fishing attractions available.  Perhaps a few places in Scotland might come near them.  It is a pity that the netting of fish is a problem.  I know the difficulties, I know it gives employment&mdash;and Senator Whitaker again mentioned that point&mdash; but I cannot help being impressed by the fact that countries like Canada just said: &ldquo;No netting for one year&rdquo;.  In other words, some more draconian methods are needed.  Hopefully the powers in this Bill will place the Minister in the position that, if he has to, he can say: &ldquo;No netting for one year&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>It is interesting that Senator Whitaker raised the point that there might be some form of compensation given to make that possible.  I heard recently that in Limerick the ESB have lifted up all the gates on the weir in an attempt to let the salmon up.  Where they used to take out about 18 per cent they are not now taking out anything.  That is another indication of the way things are going.  I heard a story recently about a country like Kenya, which is a developing country and I gather they take a really strong line in relation to the protection of shellfish and other fish on their beaches, with marshals walking up and down making sure that they are not fished.  In fact they do not allow a rod within 480 yards of a beach.  We have been in this business for <Col N="161" /> a long time and it is about time we put it right.  The Minister has introduced a Bill which I think sets us on the way to doing so.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKilbride" hpid="Mr. Kilbride Mr. Kilbride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kilbride</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not from a maritime county.  I am perhaps what might be described as somebody at the other end of the sea, if such description were appropriate in any sense of the words.  I am what is known as a landlubber, an inland resident with no contact with fisheries to the extent that I would not be acquainted with what happens at sea, in the estuaries of our larger rivers or in relation to the effect of transport on our larger rivers as far as fisheries are concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to interrupt to ask the Senator to move the adjournment because An Seanad agreed that motion No. 2 would be taken at 5.30 p.m.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee of Selection:" RHead="Sixth Report">
    <Title>Committee of Selection: Sixth Report.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee of Selection reports that it has discharged Senator Eoin Ryan from membership of the Joint Committee on the Secondary Legislation of the European Communities at his own request and has appointed Senator Conroy in substitution for him.</P>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That the report be laid before the Seanad.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="House Property Costs:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>House Property Costs: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Item No. 2 on the Order Paper.  I am sure Senators are aware of the standing procedure regarding motions, that the proposer has 30 minutes, each subsequent speaker 15 minutes and the debate lasts 3 hours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann notes with concern the continuing escalation in <Col N="162" /> the cost of house property and calls on the Government to take steps to alleviate the difficulties being experienced by house purchasers.</P>
    <P>I have noticed that it is customary on these occasions to thank the Leader of the House for giving time for discussion of Private Members' Business or non-Government business.  I want, not in any ritualistic way, to thank the Leader of the House for giving time for the discussion of this motion.  I quibbled with him this afternoon on the Order of Business over why another motion was not taken. I quibble with him again about that. But I want to say&mdash;and I think it should be said as this is my first term in this House&mdash;that I understand from people who have been in the House before this term and from officials around the House that the Leader of the House on this occasion has been very fair and generous in the time he has given to non-Government business.  We all complain from time to time that the Seanad is not used sufficiently but, relatively speaking, I gather that during this sitting the Leader of the House has been fair and generous in the time he has allotted to non-Government business and I want to thank him for that.</P>
    <P>It is unfortunate in one sense that this motion has been on the Order Paper for some time now and the price increases that have occurred are perhaps slowing down somewhat now but it is nevertheless a very important matter for discussion.  I want to say at the outset that I do not in any way wish to be politically partisan or politically devisive in proposing this motion.  I have noticed that on almost every occasion that the question of housing has come up for discussion in the Dáil, whether it be on Estimates or on particular motions, it has often developed into a statistic-throwing match with somebody on the one hand relating what has happened in the past six months and someone else on the other hand comparing that with what happened some years ago.</P>
    <P>Whatever has happened we are dealing with the reality now that almost every Irish person is seriously concerned at the frightening cost of houses.  People who a few short years ago could have purchased a house without undergoing <Col N="163" /> enormous financial burden, nowadays find themselves in the position that they just cannot do it.  It is a pity that that should be the case.  Everybody would accept that it is a basic right of families to own their own homes.  I would hope that we could start on that premise.  It is the Opposition's job to be critical when we think the Government are wrong.  But if we could be objective and constructive in our criticism and look to see what might be done to alleviate the problems we have and to try to discuss ideas, that might be useful in trying to deal with the problem of house prices today.</P>
    <P>It is a very sad thing that our record in housing in Ireland over the past 60 years has been a bad one.  The simple truth is that, even though we may pay lip service to the ideal that every family should have their own home, the reality is quite different.  I do not come into the House today to blame this Government or to place full responsibility on this Government for the housing problem we have today.  The truth is that successive Irish Governments have failed to have a sufficiently dynamic policy in housing to satisfy the need that exists.  We are in a very serious situation now because our population is a young one and it is quite apparent that in future the demand for housing is going to be far greater than it is at present.</P>
    <P>The Minister, I know, wishes to solve the problem.  I know he does not like to see the rate of increase in house prices that we have seen.  Everybody in this House shares this view.  But the reality is that he has inherited a very big problem; he has inherited the absence of a sufficient policy from previous Governments, previous Fianna Fáil administrations and previous Coalition administrations. So I hope that we do not spend our few hours here this evening defending positions held or arguing as to the rights and wrongs of statistics or otherwise.  We have to be constructive. Obviously, we have to oppose what we think we should oppose, but at the same time I hope that the debate will be a constructive one.</P>
    <P>If we accept that every family has the right to own its own home then we have to accept that our policies in the past <Col N="164" /> have not been sufficiently dynamic, have not been good enough and certainly have not realised the end that they set out, or they say they set out, to realise. The absence of a real, good housing policy has manifested itself now in some appalling examples.  We have all seen on television or have experienced the appalling conditions in which some people live in Dublin particularly and in other heavily-populated areas around the country.  We have seen people living in squalid conditions, in unhealthy conditions. We have more recently seen the development of the so-called mobile home business where people living in these cardboard boxes&mdash;that is all they are&mdash;have to spend their savings to provide the only home that they can actually acquire.  Anybody who in the past winter, which we do not seem to have shaken off yet, has had cause to visit anybody in these houses could have seen the unsuitability of them as homes.  They are really an entrepreneur's delight because the amount of money that must have been made out of these in the past few years must be quite enormous.  People living in this type of condition, whether it be in overcrowded ghettoes in distressed areas in cities or whether it be in mobile homes throughout the country, are living in insecure housing.  A lot of social problems have emerged directly from these living conditions&mdash;I speak of broken marriages, alcoholism, delinquent children and so on.  There is a direct connection between these.  Having said that, we have to look at the Minister's job at this time in the light of his having inherited very many problems.  Unfortunately, the problems that have arisen in the past number of years have aggravated what was already a very serious situation.</P>
    <P>Another point that I have noticed in the past year or two is the emergence of a &ldquo;new poor&rdquo; in Ireland.  I refer particularly to young married couples who have purchased private houses at, to them, relatively enormous cost.  Because of the interest repayments and the financial burden that has fallen upon them for taking this very worthy and laudable step of buying a house, they literally find themselves in positions where frequently they cannot even feed or clothe <Col N="165" /> themselves properly.  That is something of the background to the problem.</P>
    <P>I will say just one word on local authority housing.  I am aware that the Minister for the Environment denies that this Government have a bias against local authority housing.  I know he has wondered where anybody could have got this idea.  But I think that paragraph 58 of the White Paper, &ldquo;National Development, 1977-80&rdquo;, is a sad reflection on the present Government.  I quote just two or three lines from it.  At the beginning of the paragraph it is stated:</P>
    <P>At present, apart from Dublin and some other areas, housing needs are being met almost as they arise....</P>
    <P>The paragraph later continues:</P>
    <P>The continuing and accruing subsidy of up to £1,500 per unit per annum for normal rented local authority dwellings now being provided is placing a very heavy burden on the Exchequer. In the face of these high costs and given the progress already made towards satisfying needs, the level of activity in the local authority housing programme and/or the extent of Exchequer subsidies will have to be subjected to continuous critical review in the light of available resources.  The local authorities will be requested to examine the circumstances of housing applicants in more detail to determine priority needs.</P>
    <P>Any public representative doing his job is well aware that that suggestion just could not be true.  The Minister refers to some other unspecified areas outside Dublin.  The author of the document gives the impression in that paragraph that housing needs are, generally speaking, being met in the local authority sector. There is no real foundation for that suggestion.  I do not know where the author of the document acquired the information that would give foundation to such a statement but I can tell the Minister for Economic Planning and Development or the Minister for the Environment, who is present, that there are thousands of people throughout the length and breadth of Ireland who would, from bitter personal experience, disagree with what this document says <Col N="166" /> and who would be quite pleased to put the Minister right on the matter.  I have complained in the past in this House that the present Government are adopting Tory-like policies and this is an example of such policy which is certainly not to the advantage of the Irish people.  It is understandable that the Minister for Economic Planning and Development should experiment with the economy with the excellent intention of trying to stimulate economic growth, particularly in the building industry.  But I think it is wrong that potential local authority tenants should be the guinea pigs of such experimentation.  There has been too much emphasis placed on the importance of the private sector in local authority housing.  If the experiment does not come off the only losers will be those people who are left unhoused and who because of present circumstances could not possibly finance houses for themselves.  That is unacceptable and I would hope that the policy expressed in that White Paper is one that will not be continued to the full extent that one might read into the paragraph I have quoted from.</P>
    <P>It is an excellent idea and entirely laudable that the Government should encourage people who might qualify for local authortiy housing to purchase their own houses.  That should be fundamental to our overall housing policy. However, it is clear that a situation has developed&mdash;through whose fault it does not matter&mdash;in which people in the lower income group cannot purchase houses of their own.  Being in that situation we decide whether housing is a priority or not.  If it is, we must be prepared to put the resources into it to facilitate those people.  The United Nations regard it as a basic human right.  I do not have any doubt but that everybody in this House will say that every family in Ireland is entitled to a home of their own.  If we say that, apart from the economics of it, we must be concerned socially and we must do whatever is necessary to put the situation right in that respect.</P>
    <P>In considering specifically the present explosion in house prices and all the consequential difficulties that have flowed from this, we have to look at it in two <Col N="167" /> contexts.  First we must look at it in the historical context which I have already referred to.  Successive Irish Governments have never been socially dynamic enough and have never produced a sufficiently good housing policy to try to solve the problems.  That is a problem the Minister has inherited.  It is not his fault.  It is the fault of all Irish people whatever side of the House they sat on at any stage.  This neglect in the past has created a very solid foundation upon which the present problems lie and makes it difficult for the Minister to find solutions.</P>
    <P>The more immediate reasons for the problems we have been discussing at length in various places have been most excellently analysed and commented upon by Messrs. J. Durkan and B.J. Menton in the Quarterly Economic Review of the Economic and Social Research Institute which was published in September last. In effect this report concludes that the impetus provided by both Governments in 1977, by the Coalition and Fianna Fáil, brought a demand into an industry that was experiencing a very low level of activity and that the result was that the inevitable free market reaction occurred; prices soared and the supply could not meet the demand.  The reasons given were the taxation changes in the budget of 1977; the tax concessions caused a big flow of money into building societies and consequently provided more money, particularly to better off people, to build new houses.  Another reason was the double effect of the £1,000 new house grant and the abolition of rates on private dwellings.  These Government moves created a demand far greater than the industry could meet with the result that a price explosion occurred.</P>
    <P>There are other factors more negative in nature than the ones I have mentioned which have undoubtedly contributed greatly to the problems that we have. First of all we have the cost of building which everybody has complained about for a long time.  I accept criticisms by the Minister in the past of the Coalition for not dealing with the Kenny Report or making up their mind on it more quickly. That is a valid criticism.  I know that <Col N="168" /> there are great problems in putting the suggestions in the Kenny Report into effect and there are some constitutional problems.  I would be interested to know whether the Minister has reached any conclusions of his own.  I know that he has been considering this for the past 18 months.  I would be interested to hear what ideas he has as to putting the suggestions of this report into effect or what he would propose to do.</P>
    <P>The second and negative problem, as I see it, is the absence in Ireland of sufficient serviced sites.  This is something which, particularly in rural towns, is becoming a very grave problem.  Obviously, in the area of private house purchasers there is a difficulty in buying sites with the necessity to buy half an acre in some counties where one is outside the urban area.  This adds to the cost and the State could, in some way, help to get over this problem.</P>
    <P>Another incredible and outrageous problem is the shortage of skilled labour in the building industry.  It is a sad reflection on our society.  Again, I do not blame this Government for it.  What happened was that when the demand grew so sharply the builders, at that time operating at a low level of activity, were not equipped to deal with it.  Clearly something should be done to ensure that skilled labour is brought back into service in that area.  We have enough people who could be trained.  More recently and since the ESRI Quarterly Economic Review was published last September, we have seen a further unfortunate development for house purchasers, whether they are recent or potential, and that was the increase in building society interest rates.  This is something over which we have no control; over the overall flow of interest rates fluctuations we do not have the control we would like to have.  Ironically the increase in building societies' interest rates is a double-edged sword for, as well as increasing the burden on people who have purchased houses, or people who are budgeting to purchase a house, it has also provided more money for the building industry because deposit rates have gone up and people are more inclined to put money in when interest rates in building societies go up.  I know <Col N="169" /> that when this report was published last September they felt very strongly that there was inadequate financing in the building industry.  I do not know what the present position is.  The Minister might be able to tell us whether there has been an improvement but I would suspect that there should have been quite an improvement as a result of the deposit rates and interest rates increasing.</P>
    <P>The ESRI Report at that time drew attention to what they saw as two particular problems facing the housing sector. I will quote from it:</P>
    <P>The immediate problems faced by the housing sector are therefore twofold: (i) the inadequate finance and (ii) the level of price increase.  Any measures taken to increase the availability of finance without ensuring that an adequate supply of houses is available to meet the ensuing demand could result in a further escalation of prices.  Therefore for a resolution of the present &lsquo;crisis&rsquo;, policies are required which not only increase the availability of finance but also increase the supply of housing.</P>
    <P>Clearly in the context of our present difficulty, or crisis as the ESRI terms it, increasing the supply of houses is crucial to the resolution of our house price problem.  Unfortunately, I cannot think of any easy way in which that can be done in the short term.  Obviously in the long term it is something that must be looked at and in so far as the Government can do anything something needs to be done.  To try to deal with this in the immediate future we have to look to other areas.  Direct aid such as subsidising interest rates or possibly increasing the £1,000 new house grant will help but as the report points out the danger is that when that is done it is likely that a further inflation in house prices will be created.  Consequently, we have to consider, in the short term certainly and maybe in the long term, direct control of house prices.</P>
    <P>I know that the Minister has said in the past that the Prices Commission are not competent and have not got the resources to carry out that function. Having looked at this area for the purpose <Col N="170" /> of this motion I see just how complex and difficult an area it is and I can appreciate why the Prices Commission could not do that.  The only system of control we have at the moment is the system of the certificate of reasonable value.  It is a system that was introduced by Deputy Molloy when he was Minister for Local Government some years ago and so far as it goes it is a good system but&mdash;and I am sure the Minister is aware of it&mdash;builders have found great fault with the system.  They have been frustrated&mdash;and there is definite evidence to indicate that&mdash;because of the inflexibility of the system or the inflexibility of the operators of the system. The Construction Industry Federation say changes could be made that would not alter the controls that exist and which would suit their members better.  I am just not competent to discuss that matter but I can see clearly that there are other facts which would back it up and evidence to suggest that more and more builders are now avoiding getting involved with houses where people will require a grant, or where people will require the benefits of the stamp duty. Where that occurs, there is no control.</P>
    <P>Two things have emerged from this. First, where there is the enormous demand that there is at the moment&mdash;and there is every indication that the demand is greater at the upper end of the income scale&mdash;houses are being built over which the Department have no control. People are saying: &ldquo;I will do without the £1,000 house grant,&rdquo; or, &ldquo;I will not qualify for it,&rdquo; whichever it is. Secondly, last year reports from the building societies indicated that a greater portion of their loan finance was going to people at the upper end of the scale.</P>
    <P>I do not know what the current position is there, but my understanding from the reports I have seen is that all the indications are that builders were going up market and that the limited building resources we had were being devoted disproportionately to the people in the wealthier brackets rather than to the people who, at the lower end of the scale, would not qualify for local authority housing but who badly require housing of their own and who are prepared to <Col N="171" /> save up and pay their deposit.  They have been priced out.  Builders are not interested in servicing them because they are dealing with the upper end of the market.  There are indications that there are bigger profits at the upper end of the market.</P>
    <P>I was interested to see in <i>Irish Business</i> published in October last, a short article headed &ldquo;Are House Prices Excessive?&rdquo;.  There is a table with it but the paragraph indicates some of the nice fruit available for builders at that level of the market.  They took an estate being built off Sandyford Road in Dundrum in Dublin.  They were five bedroom, detached, Georgian style, red-bricked houses.  They asked a leading chartered surveyor and valuer to break down the cost of the house and they published the findings.  The chartered surveyor costed everything on the high side but his findings showed that the builder is earning a minimum profit on each house of £10,821.  They said &ldquo;minimum&rdquo; because 56 houses were being built and went on to explain that this would reduce the cost of each house.  They estimated in their conclusion that the builder should earn a profit of about £12,000 on each house, and on each of 56 houses in one estate that is not too bad at all.  I can understand builders who would prefer to concentrate on that end of the market than elsewhere.</P>
    <P>The difficulty is that if we have limited building resources, if we have too great a demand, if builders can reap those sort of benefits&mdash;and they are excessive; there is no question about that&mdash;and if they have sufficient business at that end of the market for them to devote all their resources to it, it is understandable that they will do so.  That is one good argument for the introduction of overall price control.</P>
    <P>I find it difficult to make specific suggestions on what can be done or what should be done for the future.  I see areas of potential, and matters which might be considered.  As I have already said, in the longer term we must ensure an increase in the supply of houses.  Obviously we must ensure that there is not a shortage of skilled labour in the building industry.  Once we have increased the <Col N="172" /> supply, we must ensure that the supply is maintained at a steady level.  Many people to whom I have spoken&mdash;builders in particular&mdash;have explained that the biggest problem in the building and construction industry is the cyclical nature of it.  Sometimes there is a boom and immediately after a boom it goes into recession.  Obviously one cannot plan any type of housing policy in those circumstances. We must try to ensure that so far as possible supply and demand are equivalent.  That is a very difficult thing to do I know, but the up-down tradition in the construction industry is one of the great reasons for the explosion we have seen in house prices.</P>
    <P>We must also acknowledge that we have a young population and that the problem will get more serious in the future.  The demand will certainly grow and unless we do something dramatic and radical about it now it will get a lot worse before it gets better.  In the shorter term&mdash;and possibly in the longer term&mdash;we should introduce controls on house prices from the top to the bottom. This would have a flow-through effect right throughout the industry.  Greater finance should be provided for local authority houses.  I have already expressed my disagreement with what I regard as the Government's over-reliance on the private sector in this respect.  If we are to talk in terms of making sure the supply is there, and that the demand can be met, we must ensure that there is a sufficient supply of finance into the business generally.</P>
    <P>Part of this up-down or cyclical nature of the business is caused by the difficulty we have over interest rates. Building societies' interest rates are down.  It is easier for people to purchase and pay for their houses.  Unfortunately, funds tend to dry up in building societies when they are down too low.  On the other hand, when they go up the whole situation turns the other way.  One way or the other it seems to be a vicious circle. There must be some way in which we could introduce controls, whether through interest subsidies or whatever I do not know, but it is something that must be looked at urgently.</P>
    <P>There must be a greater availability of serviced sites and control, to some extent, <Col N="173" /> of building land.  This is covered in the Kenny Report.  I do not know whether the Minister has reached any conclusions on that yet, and I would be interested to know.  Overall it is an extremely complex and difficult area.  I have suggested some ways in which the position might be improved.  I acknowledge that I am not a competent economist, or a competent builder, or a competent house purchaser because I have never actually pruchased a house for myself, but I know that the problems involved are complex and difficult.  I wonder whether there is a good case to be made for establishing a permanent commission with the resources not only to control house prices but also to keep an eye on the variables and to advise the Government on how problems might be overcome.  It is only through some system like that that we will eventually overcome our difficulties.</P>
    <P>Finally, I know the Minister is as concerned about house prices and housing problems as anybody on this side of the House.  I know he has his difficulties, and I know he had inherited more difficulties than have been made for him in recent years.  I wish him well in the job he has to do.  I regret that the problems he has in this respect are so great but I would ask him to take a different view of things, to try, if you like, to abandon traditional policies and to introduce some dynamic thinking into an area that would richly benefit from it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion dealing with this very important subject.  As Senator Molony quite rightly pointed out, there is no doubt that it is the ambition of most people, young or old, to own their own houses one day. Unfortunately, I must be super-critical of a number of the Government's policies.  I was not entirely happy with the record of the previous Government. In the context of economic development the record of this Government in the past 18 months is nothing to shout about.  In the four years of Coalition Government 25,000 houses were built per year.  At the time it was hailed as a reasonable development.  It did not meet all the needs of house purchasers but it was done at a time when there was a terrible <Col N="174" /> depression not only here but in Europe.  In June 1977 we were led to believe that a new era had dawned in house building and house purchasing. What happened?  In their manifesto before the general election the Fianna Fáil Party said they would give a £1,000 grant for first-time house builders.  This generated a type of over-response in the building business which should have been anticipated by the authorities.  We were coming out of the doldrums.  The industry was getting back on its feet and did not need the injection of this grant.</P>
      <P>Instead of being of monetary assistance, which I am sure was originally intended, it made house prices much dearer than they had been the year before.  In June or July 1977 an average three-bedroomed house cost in the region of £10,000 to £13,000 depending on the customers and the area they lived in.  In February of this year the price of that same house would be £17,000 to £22,000, and in some cases much more. It would be very difficult to explain to a man who got a £1,000 grant for building his new house that he was better off under this Government because even at the lower end of the scale there was a jump of about £7,000, and even with the £1,000 grant he was £6,000 worse off. That £6,000 is a staggering sum because it has to be viewed in another light.</P>
      <P>In local authority housing £9,000 is the maximum loan with an income limit of about £68 a week.  Remember, we are still speaking about the first £9,000. Repayments over a period of 25 years at current interest rates will work out at something between £22 and £23 per week which is about 33 per cent of the purchaser's total earnings.  What standard of living could he provide for his wife and family on the remainder?  That is not all.  He has to find another £9,000 to buy the house.  Senator Molony mentioned the new poor society.  They are the people I am talking about.  What lending agency is likely to give that man the extra £9,000?  The commercial banks are not interested.  The other lending agencies are not interested and the Agricultural Credit Corporation would not be remotely interested in a man like him.  Nobody wants to know him.  There are literally thousands of such people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="175" /> On the other hand, the new rich in our community are the bigger builders.  They would not be very happy about a change in our building programme.  Some of them are new millionaires.  It is of very little use to the potential house buyers I am talking about to say that certain people have become almost millionaires because of what happened in June 1977. The whole question of our interest rates is causing a tremendous amount of embarrassment and hardship.  We thought we were near the pinnacle a few weeks ago but my information is that they are due for another hike before very long. The figure quoted now is 17 per cent and it may be 18 per cent before the position gets better.  If this is true it will be the straw that breaks the camel's back.  For the type of person I am talking about, the man who is confined to an income limit of £68 or £70 a week, times were never as bad from the point of view of actually owning his own house.</P>
    <P>There is another point I should like to bring to the Minister's attention.  Senator Molony spoke about the possibility of setting up some type of commission to monitor what is happening in the building industry and, more important, to do something about it.  It is obvious that the National Prices Commission cannot help house purchasers.  During the first 12 months Fianna Fáil were in office house prices on an average increased by 33 per cent.  At the same time the cost of housing materials, the input necessary for house building, rose by only 9½ per cent.  In fact, there was a reduction of 1½ per cent in the price of imported foreign timber.  I should like to know who got the gravy&mdash;the difference between 33 per cent and 9½ per cent.  It certainly was not the house buyers.</P>
    <P>Considering that the whole situation has been festering for the past 18 months I was astounded that there was not a change in the income limit in the budget.  To be meaningful the loan would have to be raised to £15,000 because £9,000 is utterly ridiculous at this stage. There is another important category of house building about which I am not too happy.  I refer to small farmers with a valuation of under £15 who, unfortunately <Col N="176" /> for themselves, live in very poor accommodation.  Heretofore in certain circumstances it was possible that the county council would build a house for them on their own land.  However, at this stage as a public representative I am beginning to see that a great number of these applications are being turned down, basically for two reasons.  One is that it is assumed by certain officials, under the direction of the Department of the Environment I am sure, that people in this category should be well able to build their own houses.</P>
    <P>I will give the House some figures which show how difficult it is for a small farmer with, say, 20 or 30 acres to build a new house at the moment.  By and large the only place he can get the money is from the Agricultural Credit Corporation in return for the deeds to his holding.  He will possibly have to borrow between £18,000 to £20,000 before he is finished because many of these people have not got serviced sites as we know them.  If he borrowed £19,000 or £20,000 at 17 per cent over 20 years, his repayments would be £3,400 per year or £65 per week.  With an income limit of about £68 a week he would have a very poor standard of living on what he had left.  There is no way those people will ever get a new house unless their interest rates are subsidised, or something to that effect.</P>
    <P>In some cases where small farmers have their applications for a new county council house on their land turned down they are referred to the local village or hamlet where four or five houses are being built.  This is totally unsocial because a farmer must be near his land.  I should like to hear the Minister's views on this because I believe it is a policy which does not suit rural Ireland.</P>
    <P>I should also like to ask the Minister how many local authority houses there are in Ireland at the moment with no sanitary service.  I believe there are quite a few.  I also understand that in order to qualify for a reconstruction grant for a local authority house the housing inspectors, rightly or wrongly, are demanding that sanitary services be included in the reconstruction.  Is that true?  Is it also true that because those houses have not got sanitary services it could be stated <Col N="177" /> that they are no longer a useful type of residence and would be condemned in some areas?  I understand that under the differential rent system their owners are being asked continually for an increase in rent.  I would like to know the actual number of local authority houses that have not got sanitary services.  I should also like to ask the Minister how many new local authority houses were built in the year ended December 1978&mdash;the exact figure in so far as it can be given.</P>
    <P>There are a number of points which might be regarded as small but which are very big to the people concerned.  A number of people in my constituency for one reason or another built houses five, ten, 15 or 25 square feet larger than the size which qualifies to be grant-aided, and they did not receive a grant.  If it happened through no fault of the builder or the owner it is a very hard penalty to ask a man to do without a £1,000 grant he thought was justly his.  A number of house builders found that their applications to the Department under the old scheme were lost along the way and they cannot be grant-aided because there is no proof, as such, that they actually applied. I cannot see why the Department could not devise a method of obtaining proof that the house was built, was the proper size, and therefore the owner is entitled to a grant.</P>
    <P>Much more effort, much more initiative and much more money will have to be pumped into housing by the Government.  There will have to be certain curbs.  Perhaps the new-found millionaires are building a few extra houses, but the problem is that the people who are buying them and have bought them in the past 18 months are subsidising the millionaires.  No Government would want that.  There must be some curbs or only the very rich will have houses and we will create a situation in the next couple of years which we will not be able to reverse, I hope a new policy will be devised in the next few months and that people will be able to realise their ambition to buy their own new houses.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a worthwhile motion but in the past there have been many housing motions and I am sure the dustbins in the Custom House are full of discarded plans and all types of suggestions <Col N="178" /> from many local authorities and Members of this House and the other House over the years.  No solution has been found.</P>
      <P>This is an enormous problem.  It is a long-term and a short-term problem and it must be examined on the basis of long-term and short-term needs.  Blame placing is no solution.  We need reasonable suggestions on the changes necessary to meet the changing situation here and in other economies.  The housing situation right across the board is in need of urgent and detailed examination.  The fact that houses of substantial cost are being built and purchased is not the answer.  Normally speaking that person has put on the market a lower-cost house and the housing pool has been increased.</P>
      <P>The basic factors are the input of land, labour and the cost of materials. These are the essential factors in the development of the housing programme and in meeting housing needs.  There are various other factors such as loans, grants and other matters.  We have reached the stage where the question of land is of vital importance.  A new and radical look must be taken at this aspect. Governments must be courageous in dealing with speculators who lie in wait and make substantial profits.  Farmers and other landowners can make substantial profits from the sale of land for housing purposes.  This is an area which must be tackled at the earliest possible moment.  Some type of system should be developed under which the value of agricultural land is set and 25 per cent or 30 per cent above that should be the maximum allowed to be paid for that land.  If the price of land is not controlled somehow, the price of houses can never be controlled.  The price of land should be controlled and the developer or the builder should not be allowed to put on additional charges.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is only on that basis that control of the entire house building situation can reflect in the price of the house and it must be reflected in the price of the house.  For far too long we have seen people lying in wait with substantial amounts tied up and substantial fortunes to be made as a result of land being zoned for housing needs and land being <Col N="179" /> made available for the provision of services&mdash;services that you and I and other people pay for.  This matter must be examined. The £1,000 grant is only a very small problem if, in fact, it is a problem at all.  The whole basic structure must be examined and we must make a radical effort to stop people lying in wait and making fortunes.  When we can eliminate this situation in relation to land purchase and stabilise the price of land, the cost of a house must come within the reach of the normal man.</P>
    <P>There is also the question of sanitary services and services on sites.  We have some local authorities with sites, and some adjacent local authorities with services and friction indeed between them. It is very disturbing when we have this friction.  Some type of national sanitary services authority should be set up to eliminate problems and to plan the sanitary services in their entirety.</P>
    <P>The whole question of sanitary services, pollution and development as it were, is a matter that must be divorced from the present type of tight grip that we have.  In order to speed up the process the local authorities must be given more power than they have because when matters are referred to the Department there is a time lag.  Between the Department and the local authority there should be some type of authority that could deal with this matter in order to expedite the development and to ensure that development can take place on a planned basis breaking across the barriers of local authority boundaries which are the cause of so much friction between a planning authority in one area and a planning authority in another area, where one has the services and the other has the land.</P>
    <P>The sanitary services situation is of major importance as, indeed, is the question of land value.  These are the two vital elements in the development of housing needs and in the development of housing costs because if we cannot control the question of services or the question of land values we cannot control the situation.  Regardless of whatever grants or aids of an artificial nature are given, whether the £1,000 is increased to <Col N="180" /> £2,000 or the local authorities' loans are doubled or trebled as the case may be, the real situation is not being dealt with because the whole matter is based on the aspects I have mentioned.</P>
    <P>An area that is in absolute need of overhaul is that relating to certificates of reasonable value.  Efforts to control the price situation have failed.  I do not think that a government can control the prices but if we could control the other elements the question of supply and demand would take care of the price situation.</P>
    <P>When one submits to the Department of the Environment or to the Department dealing with the assessment of what is reasonable value an application in this regard, very often their assesssment is not in line with what reasonable men would regard as reasonable value and there is a &ldquo;yes&rdquo; or &ldquo;no&rdquo; answer. That is not good enough if we want to expedite the development of housing.  If, for example, one applies for an increase under the consumer price index one will get an increase in relation to what the personnel who are examining the problem will regard as just and adequate. There is not any time lag.  Nor is there any tying up of finances to allow for a further increase when an additional application is made for a certificate of reasonable value.  It very often happens that the first application is made for £X and after it is rejected, the builder or the developer may hold it back for some time and then make application for a greater amount in the second instance. That application may be successful.  The present criteria may well have been justified in the early stages of this operation but we are moving in a different type of market now, in a different situation, with different circumstances and different problems and on the basis of the different problems we must examine and update the legislation we have and indeed the regulations we have to cope with the ever-changing situation.  I hope that the question of certificates of reasonable value will be examined in its entirety and that the application be treated in the same way as is treated an application for a price increase in any other area.</P>
    <P>There has been reference to the question <Col N="181" /> of the shortage of skilled personnel in the building trade.  I have been a member of a housing committee and, indeed, of a planning committee, for more than 20 years.  I understand the many problems of the past and indeed the development problems of the future in relation to skilled personnel.  On one occasion I remember a Minister indicating to Dublin Corporation that they should double their housing programme but they were unable to do that because of the shortage of skilled personnel.  That was at the time when there was full employment in the building trade. Although there are very many people on the labour market at the moment we are told by competent personnel in AnCO and elsewhere that there is required a substantial number of extra personnel such as blocklayers.  We are told also that an additional 30 places will be available there this year.  If we are to be serious about the situation on a national basis, if we are to tackle it in the manner in which many people would like to see the housing programme tackled, the question of an additional 30 places is farcical.  We must broaden the scope of apprenticeship in order to ensure that in a reasonable period we have enough skilled personnel to meet the development situation that we all talk about.  If we are successful in this sphere the question of the £1,000 grant or of the other aids will not be important.  A crash programme is needed to train 2,000 to 4,000 people. We are told by several people in the particular industry that this is the volume of personnel required.  Therefore, an extra 30 places in a particular centre will not alleviate the situation.</P>
    <P>I shall not refute what the previous Senator said about Government policy because perhaps all Governments have been at fault.  Perhaps not enough money has been devoted to housing in this year's budget but there are substantial increases.  If the basic situation is not rectified then the overall situation will not be rectified.</P>
    <P>I have one strong objection to building contractors and it relates to those contractors who leave estates unfinished. There is an estate in Tallaght, for instance, that is a fire hazard.  The sooner we reject applications from people <Col N="182" /> who are not measuring up to their responsibilities concerning the houses they build, the better.  They should not be given licences to build further houses until such time as they complete their previous contracts.  People who purchase houses have rights, too.  Hopefully, when the Minister is replying he will say a word about this whole matter.</P>
    <P>I agree with the Senator who said that it is a basic right of individuals to have houses.  I trust that this debate will yield some type of suggestion and that the Minister will be motivated to new and higher ideals to meet the development situation and that he will have a word with AnCO and other institutions who indicate the type of programme they envisage for the coming year and tell them it is not enough, that they must get on with the job, that we have a target, that we have problems but that we intend tackling them, thereby ensuring that more houses will be built.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyMcAuliffe" hpid="Mr. McAuliffe Mr. McAuliffe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McAuliffe</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to be associated with this motion because I believe it will get a good reception from everyone in the House.  One regret I have about it is that one of the people who signed it will not be here to contribute this evening.  I refer to Senator Lyons whom I consider to be one of the best local authority representatives in the country.  I trust that in a very short time we will see him here again.</P>
      <P>The big problem at present is the price of sites, even for local authorities.  In County Westmeath we found it necessary to devise a plan for the purchase of land in rural areas.  The idea was to buy land&mdash;five or six acres&mdash;and to persuade the IDA to come in as partners with the promise that if there was a need for small industry or any type of industry in the area the land would be available for that.  But we were tied by Department regulations.  There is a non-written law or it may be a written law that in rural areas you may not exceed £1,500 per statute acre for sites for houses.  There is not the slightest chance at present of getting sites for houses at £1,500 an acre.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have overcome quite an amount of our difficulties by the method I mentioned, by having the IDA work hand-in-hand <Col N="183" /> with us.  The maximum local authority loan is £9,000 and in order to qualify for the maximum loan one's income must not exceed £67 per week. The repayments would be £22 per week. It is common nowadays for men to marry. Assuming that they pay £22 a week for 30 years, they will have paid more than £34,000 for their houses by the time they reach the age of 50.  There is something wrong about the interest rate, to pay £34,000.  Many people could not get married at present were it not for the fact that the EEC regulations allow wives to continue work after marriage. They would not have a chance of paying £22 a week out of a £67 per week income. The income limits should have been increased in line with the increase in the amount of the loan.</P>
    <P>It is the policy of the Government to encourage people, to almost force them, to build their own houses.  During the past year there has been a considerable drop in the number of local authority houses being built while there has been an increase in the number of private houses built.  Therefore, the Government are succeeding to a certain extent.  The average for last year was the same as the average for the four years of the Coalition when more than 100,000 houses were built.  There were 25,000 built last year.  I welcome the hand towards the building of a greater number of private houses because when local authorities build houses, they encourage the tenants to purchase but this is very difficult for a person with a very low income.  The purchase period is 50 years and the repayments are about £10 per week. Because many people are unable to meet such repayments, houses are beginning to remain in the hands of local authorities.  That is not good for a local authority because they are responsible for all repairs for as long as the houses remain in their hands.  There would have to be some sort of more attractive figure to encourage people to purchase these houses and to take them off the backs of the Government and the ratepayers.</P>
    <P>In every local authority there should be a solicitor to deal with all loans because very long delays are experienced <Col N="184" /> in connection with loans.  I had a case this week of a man who has been carrying a bridging loan for three years.  His loan would have been paid this week were it not for the postal strike but he has been waiting a long time.  His full loan goes into the bank and what he pays is interest so that nothing is paid off the principal.  That should not happen. Senators Molony and Cooney would know all about equities.  There is great difficulty in this area in respect of clearance.  There is a holdup in the Land Registry office.  It is often impossible to get out a new folio for a new site.  It is a dreadful state of affairs that there are delays like that.  For that reason I think there should be one solicitor in every county who would deal with all loans and other such matters and deal with them with the minimum of delay. Perhaps solicitors would not be too keen on that idea because they do not make a lot from dealing with SDA loans.  For them the money is in dealing with building societies where people are getting loans of £25,000 and £30,000.</P>
    <P>The previous Minister introduced the low-mortgage loan.  This seems attractive but the first snag one encounters on trying to avail of such a loan is that if one is not on the housing list one does not qualify.  This is unfortunate because people who are inclined to build their own houses would not be on the housing list because they would always have it at the back of their minds to build their own houses.  One must be on the housing list for a year before qualifying for such a loan.  There is another snag: many people who should be on the housing list cannot get that low-mortgage loan and also this loan would give people every encouragement to purchase their own houses.</P>
    <P>The reluctance on the part of people in local authority houses to purchase is understandable when one realises that to purchase costs about £10.42 per week and that this is a repayment which must be made regardless of one's income whereas a tenant would have his rent reduced to perhaps about 75p per week in the event of his being out of work. That would be the repayment for an unemployed person with three children.  In that way there is a loss to the local <Col N="185" /> authorities and, consequently, to the ratepayers.</P>
    <P>There has been reference to a shortage of skilled labour.  There is no shortage of skilled labour but the problem is that those who are skilled do not wish to work with local authorities.  They prefer to work on the lump system, telling their employers to pay the tax and not to bother about a stamp.  They do the job quickly and move on to the next job. These people make very good money. There is no shortage of them as anyone building a house will confirm.  The difficulty is in their unwillingness to pay tax.</P>
    <P>I thought that people in differential rent houses should have been relieved of rates but I do not believe that everybody should be free of domestic rates.  One could regard rates as another wealth tax. It would have been better to continue the rates system.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelMulcahy" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Molony appealed to us to avoid a political-type discussion in dealing with the housing industry. Obviously there are some problems but I agree that these are not of any single group's making.  Despite the comments from Senator Connaughton. I should like to draw attention to one or two aspects of the problem.  It is very difficult to deal with it in any comprehensive way in this short time. First, there is the question of how many houses are required.  Senator Molony indicated that there should be a greater building rate but to my knowledge no reputable organisation have challenged the figure which has been agreed as a result of recommendations by the National Economic and Social Council, and repeated in the White Paper, that the required housing is somewhere in the order of 23,000 to 27,000 a year.  In articles that I have written I have mentioned a steady rate of 25,000.  I have never heard anybody say that more than that is needed in the given demographic social conditions.  I would agree with the Senator that the structure of housing might need attention.  Each year roughly 8,000 secondhand houses move and are financed and most of the owners concerned <Col N="186" /> will be going up market.  Of the 19,000 houses that are built, assuming that the other 6,000 making up the 25,000 are local authority houses 7,000 to 9,000 are being taken up by people moving up market.  As people move up market they are lifting the price so that is inbuilt into it.</P>
      <P>The other point is the cyclicality of the industry.  The facts are that since Fianna Fáil in the sixties managed to put the housing industry back on its feet we have managed to achieve our targets every year no matter what Government are in.  We might have varied in the mix of local authority and private housing. One figure I have seen is that we have been within 25,000 by about 8 per cent in the last few years.  One could say that the industry is not being subjected to cyclical trends, as in the case, for instance, in the UK where starts are something like 25 per cent down.  In America it is predicted that the starts are decreasing by 20 per cent.  This is a real problem in terms of using the housing industry to regulate the economy.  We have not had that but what we have had is that the proportion of funding costs going into local authorities and being financed by State funds as opposed to building society funds has changed.  That shifts the demand.  We have been noticeably good in keeping the industry on an even keel.</P>
      <P>Senator Molony referred to the ESRI document in which were challenged the predicted completions for 1978.  The people who threw out that challenge have been beaten.  In making their comments a good number of the variables which must be taken into account, like the CPI, cost of materials, average earnings and so on, have been off.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The public capital expenditure programme for 1979 on non-local authority housing is of the order of £79 million and if we take the low rise mortgage scheme into account that runs at £83 million.  There is a problem there because going backwards through the figures for expenditure on non-local authority housing the figure in 1978 was something like £48 million while in 1977 it was £27 million.  There one sees the inbuilt structural differences.  The Government have brought the figure up to £79 <Col N="187" /> million.  That reflects Government policy which is to regenerate enterprise.</P>
    <P>I should like to draw attention to the fairly important general point that people are now taking it for granted that we should all have known that the economy would recover from the mid-1977 situation and that, therefore, we should not have thrown in the £1,000 pump-priming incentive and that the rates concession was not necessary.  It is all very well to say, now that the economy has recovered, that those measures are regrettable because they might have tended to push prices up.  It is easy to be clever with hindsight.  If we look back on the Coalition Government's Green Paper there was a lot of misery in it.  It was not until the Fianna Fáil manifesto appeared that some optimism began to develop.  The policy factors in the manifesto were helpful in restoring confidence in the private sector and in encouraging expenditure on housing and up-market expenditure, which is what happened.</P>
    <P>As far as interest subsidies are concerned, it seems to me unwise to introduce subsidies at a time when there is a possibility of too much of a price-push. When the mortgage costs went to 13.95, nearly 14 per cent, the Coalition still did not introduce interest subsidies.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>I did suggest it in the context of price control.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelMulcahy" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but the Senator pointed out the difficulty of price control in an industry like this.  That brings me to the essential question, referred to by others, namely, the cost of land.  It is interesting to note that the going price at the moment for local authority contract houses is about £12,000.  I see a shake of the head.  It is of that order.  A contractor can go in on a contract with a figure of something like £12,500 and get serviced land, a designed house and supervision. If he himself wants to build, each serviced site will cost him something of the order of £5,000.  This land problem, referred to by others, does exist.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In regard to the Kenny Report and <Col N="188" /> the various unsuccessful attempts by the Coalition Government to deal with its recommendations, it is the market place that would dictate.  Irish people are land-hungry and property-hungry.  That hunger is innate.  I would agree that we need a great deal more serviced land.  If people realise that there is no guaranteed in-built natural inflation in the value of land, particularly in or around a big urban complex like Dublin, they will not speculate, they will not buy land, hold it for a while and sell, without ever putting anything on it.  I would recommend that the Minister should consider getting a lot of money from the Minister for Finance&mdash;possibly some of the money we might get from the EMS&mdash;for the provision of serviced land some two or three years ahead of requirement.  Serviced land which is just ahead of requirement will not influence the market.  It has to be so far ahead of requirement that it will take the bottom out of the market.  It would be worth spending an extra £20 million a year to do that.  As someone sitting on the Government benches I make that suggestion.</P>
    <P>It is unreasonable to use figures for price increases to suggest that they have gone from £11,000 to £19,000, or whatever it is.  We should take into account that the price range, for local authority loans for private housing, was £10,500 in 1977 and £13,200 at the end of 1978.  It is in that area that one can talk about the individual who is earning £70 or £100 a week, or whatever it is, and start working out that one third of his income goes on financing his house and he has to borrow.  You cannot rely on the figure of £19,000; it is an unreasonable use of statistics.</P>
    <P>The Minister will have to do something about the certificate of reasonable value.  The land cost is a problem.  At what value will the land be taken in assessment of that reasonable cost?  If we use replacement cost accounting, which has been advocated by many leading people, such as Dr. Paul Carroll and others on the banking side, the cost goes up again.  Some builders are selling houses on the basis of original cost.  I am concerned when I see local authorities selling land at the going <Col N="189" /> market value because they are adding to the difficulty by the creation of a market at the going market price.  A good forward provision of serviced land, maybe the expenditure of an extra £20 million a year, might help us in that regard.</P>
    <P>The European Monetary System was discussed last July in the Seanad.  The policy of the Government puts us in a position, <i>vis-a-vis</i> exchange controls operating between here and the UK, that we do not have to worry about shifting interest rates being passed on to our mortgage rates.  We have not got all the benefit from that yet, but it will come. The EMS will have a somewhat stabilising effect on the system, when it comes on stream.</P>
    <P>Finally, there is a shortage of manpower. The price of manpower in the building industry is fantastic.  I heard the other day that some people were trying to get bricklayers from the North of Ireland to help because of the shortage here.  They would come for £200 a week each, no tax and accommodation prepaid. We do have a problem there.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1965" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. J. O'Leary) Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. J. O'Leary)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. J. O'Leary)</NameTxt>
      <P>In discussing this motion, we have been traversing territory which is all too familiar because quite similar motions, Adjournment Debates and supplementaries to Dáil questions got repeated airings&mdash;indeed, I suggest over-exposure&mdash;in Dáil Éireann time after time in 1978.  I do not, for an instance, question the right of the Opposition Deputies concerned to use the time made available to them by that House as they considered appropriate, but, having made their case once or twice and having it effectively countered and their allegations proved to be without foundation, I can legitimately criticise the political acumen of the party leaders who decided to continue to make an issue of a cause which was lost before the debate even opened.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would have hoped that Senators on the benches opposite would have kept themselves sufficiently informed of the proceedings in the Dáil, or that, before <Col N="190" /> this, their backroom advisers would have got the message sufficiently clearly, to save the Seanad a repeat of this rather sterile exercise.  However, the motion is before the House and I will address myself to the assertions which it makes.</P>
    <P>The motion states that:</P>
    <P>notes with concern the continuing escalation in the cost of house property...</P>
    <P>Nobody, here or elsewhere, will challenge the fact that house prices have been rising steadily&mdash;not just over the past year or two, but for decades past; not alone under Fianna Fáil Governments, but during the occasional rare periods of administration by Coalition Governments.  This has not been a phenomenon peculiar to this country.  It is a trend which has affected every country in western Europe and, indeed, some neighbouring countries much more acutely than us.</P>
    <P>In the course of the Dáil debates on the topic, Opposition Deputies made considerable play of the big jump in new house prices recorded by my Department's &ldquo;Quarterly Bulletin of Housing Statistics&rdquo; during the first three months of 1978 as compared with the immediately preceding quarter and, on that flimsy basis, projected that prices would increase by up to 50 per cent over the full year 1978.  They persisted with this contention, even when subsequent Quarterly Bulletins made it evident that the rate of price escalation was being successfully curbed.</P>
    <P>May I point out to the Seanad, as the bulletin quite explicitly states, that while the statistics of house prices are useful as indicators of general trends in average house prices over a given period, they cannot be taken as completely accurate records of building or other housing costs at any given time.  For example, the houses concerned are not necessarily comparable, even from quarter to quarter or from area to area.  This applies particularly in areas where the number of loans approved in a quarter may be relatively small and the average prices influenced significantly by individual housing schemes.  Furthermore, the average price recorded can be influenced <Col N="191" /> from quarter to quarter by changes in the distributions of loan approvals among the lending agencies.  I intend to return later to deal with factors which can substantially influence the recorded trends in average house prices for which loans were approved.</P>
    <P>Subject to this reservation, over the four quarters of 1978 the rate of new house price increases recorded by the bulletin fell from 11.7 per cent in the three months to 31 March 1978, to 8.4 per cent in the June quarter, to 3.4 per cent in the September quarter, and I am glad to say that the bulletin for the quarter ended 31 December last, which will be published shortly, will record, not an increase but, for the first time in years, a small reduction.  Over the full year 1978 average new house prices, as recorded by the bulletin, rose by 24.8 per cent.</P>
    <P>Some Senators opposite, like their party colleagues in the Dáil, would give the impression to the public at large that this Government are unconcerned at increases in house prices and are unwilling to take effective action to curb the rate of increase.  Nothing could be further from the truth.  Contrast our record in this regard with that of the last Coalition Government, under whose four years of administration average house prices rose by an unprecedented 113.5 per cent, including a staggering increase of 36 per cent in the cost of house building in their first year in office.</P>
    <P>House prices have been rising continually in Britain, in Northern Ireland and on the Continent.  The fact that we have managed, to an appreciable degree, to bring them under control in the Republic did not come about fortuitously. It came about because the Government were conscious of the trend in house prices and aware of the difficulties to which it would give rise in the case of persons of modest means and because the Government kept the situation under constant review and took the necessary initiatives to deal with the situation.  This process of control was not an emergency operation begun early last year.  Our initiative to control the escalation in house prices was put in hands soon after we <Col N="192" /> resumed office in mid-1977, as part of a wide-ranging package of actions in relation to housing.</P>
    <P>When Fianna Fáil took over Government again in July 1977 they discovered that the controls on new house prices, as operated by the certificate of reasonable value system, which the previous Fianna Fáil Government had introduced in 1973, had not been strengthened, contrary to what should have been expected after a period of rapid price escalation. Indeed, the controls had been weakened by the drastic curtailment, in 1976, of eligibility for new house grants.  In those circumstances, the Minister for the Environment immediately extended the certificate of reasonable value system to all grant type new houses provided for sale, and also to flats.  Previously houses in schemes of three or less, and all flats, were exempt from the controls.  The effect of this and the liberalisation of the schemes of new house grants was to increase from approximately 40 per cent to 70 per cent the proportion of new private houses brought within the scope of house price control.</P>
    <P>When further positive action by the Government was needed last year, it was promptly taken.  House prices had been rising at an unacceptable rate during the first half of that year and evidence was available that this was being influenced by a definite move by builders out of the construction of modestly priced houses, eligible for grants and for which certificates of reasonable value were, therefore, required, and into the higher priced market where profits were greater and where they would not be subject to the system of house price control.</P>
    <P>Against this background, building societies were informed in August 1978 that the Government had decided that, for a trial period at least, 60 per cent of the total funds available to them for mortgages should be allocated in providing loans not exceeding £13,000 each and that at least a further 20 per cent of available funds should be allocated in providing loans of between £13,000 and £16,000.  The societies were also informed that certificates of reasonable value should be furnished by all applicants for loans not exceeding £16,000 for the purchase of new houses <Col N="193" /> and that the apportionment of loans as between new and previously-occupied houses should be maintained at the levels then current.  The Government decision was intended to ensure that available moneys should finance the purchase of the greatest feasible number of reasonably priced houses and that all purchasers of new houses with loans under £16,000 would be assured of getting reasonable value for their investment. This measure, while unpopular with building societies and with some builders whose profit-taking was affected, has shown significant results since its introduction in so far as the trend in average gross house prices is concerned.</P>
    <P>As I have said, I am keeping the general question of new house price increases under continuous review and will take steps as appropriate to deal with the situation.  In particular, I have had the certificate of reasonable value system specifically examined and changes in the system to strengthen it will be proposed in a Bill, the text of which will be circulated in the near future.</P>
    <P>The building cost of local authority housing is governed by the response to open public tendering and by the standards of design and construction of dwellings, and the environmental quality of schemes and the amenities provided.</P>
    <P>Senators will be aware that a feature of the local authority house building programme is the widespread use by local authorities of the open tender procedures for their housing schemes. This system has been generally satisfactory and has resulted in keen competitive tendering from building contractors when the work demand is not too high. The degree of competition for schemes has tended to decline in the past year due to the upsurge of alternative construction work coming on stream.</P>
    <P>There has been a notable increase in recent times in tender prices, particularly in urban areas.  This is worrying.  The cost of local authority housing is met by the almost 100 per cent recoupment of loan charges by the Government.  The high capital costs at present are imposing a heavy burden on the taxpayer.  The capacity to meet this burden is not unlimited. Serious efforts have been made to contain costs and these will have to be <Col N="194" /> intensified.  This will not, however, entail any cut-back in the high standards of current local authority housing which I consider it essential to maintain.</P>
    <P>Local authorities have been aware of the need to have an adequate land reserve and in recent years they have maintained a large reserve of the order of 55,000 sites over and above land being built upon or likely to be used in the short-term, to meet the longer-term needs of their programme.</P>
    <P>Housing authorities have been authorised to acquire whatever land is needed for their programmes for three years ahead, effectively giving them a five-year reserve when allowance is made for planning time.</P>
    <P>There is one aspect of house price increases to which I must specially refer. That is the standards of new houses and the quality of their domestic and environmental amenities.  The Government have attacked the problem of unreasonable levels of house price increases but have been at pains to ensure that these actions will not reverse the well-established trend towards overall improvements in housing standards. This policy is common both to the private and local authority programmes.</P>
    <P>With increasing national economic prosperity and rising social aspirations it is natural that our people's ambitions should be towards better and better housing.  The results of this understandable and commendable development will be illustrated in a very interesting analysis carried out by An Foras Forbartha into private housing estates in the eastern region&mdash;Dublin, Meath, Kildare and Wicklow&mdash;comparing the position in 1976 with that in December 1978. The survey, which I hope to see published, was based on an investigation of 11,580 houses in the region completed in 1976 and 10,197 completed in 1978. It shows that over the survey period the following important changes had taken place: (a) Substantial increase in floor areas of houses; (b) Increase in detached two-storey houses; (c) Increase in four bedroom houses and decrease in three bedroom houses; (d) Increase in garages and decrease in car-ports; (e) Almost no houses without central heating of some type compared with 40 per cent in 1976; <Col N="195" /> (f) Increase in timber ground floors with reduction in concrete floors; (g) Increased usage of brick facing; (h) Increase in tarmac roads and decrease in concrete roads.</P>
    <P>Indicative of the trend towards higher standards was the fact that in the eastern region the percentage of all houses constituted by detached two-storey dwellings rose from 6 per cent in 1976 to 34 per cent in 1978.  The number of four-bedroomed houses in the area rose from 27 per cent to 54 per cent of the total, the proportion with individual garages rose from 20 per cent to 49 per cent and the number with central heating increased from 60 per cent in 1976 to 99 per cent in 1978.</P>
    <P>I want to refer briefly to the question of control of the prices of previously occupied, houses.  While the rate of increase of prices of new houses can be regulated indirectly, for example, by means of the certificate of reasonable value system, by conditions attaching to the payment of the £1,000 State grant and by the direction of a substantial part of the inflow of building society funds to modestly-priced houses, there is no scope for similar machinery to regulate the prices of previously occupied houses. These prices are determined by market conditions generally and prices will vary considerably depending on the location, the amenities offered, the state of repair and the general potential of the property. The control of the prices of such houses by the Prices Commission would not be a feasible proposition.  The commission have no functions in relation to other previously used items such as secondhand cars or furniture, and houses which have previously been occupied are no different in general to such secondhand articles.</P>
    <P>While, for the reasons I have mentioned the prices of previously occupied houses are not susceptible to controls, it must be put on record that the average price of these houses, for which loans were approved by the main mortgage agencies, increased by 17.8 per cent as between the last quarter of 1977 and 1978 respectively&mdash;that is, at an appreciably lower rate than in the case of <Col N="196" /> new houses.  I am particularly pleased to mention also that over the last three months of 1978 the average prices of previously occupied houses fell by a whacking 6 per cent.</P>
    <P>I have said enough to deal with the first part of this motion and to prove to the Seanad that the Government, have taken appropriate and effective action to curb the rate of increase of house prices.</P>
    <P>The second part of the motion raises the need for Government measures to alleviate the difficulties being experienced by persons wishing to purchase houses. In drawing up our election manifesto in 1977, we accepted that the policies being operated at the time by the former Government gave rise to a very definite need for changed policies to assist intending house purchasers.  Our manifesto spelled out the steps which we regarded as necessary to deal with the situation and it undertook to implement them.</P>
    <P>Over the past year and a half we have honoured practically every one of the promises in relation to housing which we then gave.  I would like to remind Senators briefly of some of these steps which have been taken by the Government since mid-1977 to help house purchasers:</P>
    <P>Rates on houses have been abolished. I need hardly develop the significance of this concession which eliminated the heavy financial burden which previously had to be borne by house purchasers.</P>
    <P>The new house grant of £1,000, was introduced in July, 1977 to assist first-time owner-occupiers.  £13 million will be spent on new house grants in 1979 compared with £2.38 million in 1977. The sponsors of this motion should recall that, in 1976 the Coalition imposed severe restrictions on eligibility for the existing scheme of new house grants which, over a short period, would have had the effect of practically abolishing that scheme.</P>
    <P>The SDA loan limit has been increased twice and it is now double the June 1977, level.  The income limit was also increased by practically 50 per cent. Between September 1973, and June 1977, the Coalition failed to make any changes whatsoever in these limits.  They simply sat on the fence and ignored increases <Col N="197" /> in costs, prices and earnings and allowed the expenditure under the scheme to continue to drop.  This is reflected in the fact that payments under the scheme were less than £17 million in 1977.  Payments increased to £26 million last year and provision has been made for an expenditure of £43.5 million this year.</P>
    <P>The subsidisable cost limit on each housing site developed by local authorities and made available for modestly priced private housing was increased last year from £900 to £1,500. At the end of August, I asked local authorities to step up activities under this scheme.  At the close of 1978 they had on hands sites sufficient to accommodate 55,106 houses, over and above sites for dwellings then at planning and tender stages.  Local authorities have been pressed to make a substantial part of this large land bank available for modest priced private housing.  Not alone would this directly assist a particularly deserving category of potential house purchasers but it would help to secure a balanced social &ldquo;mix&rdquo; in the development of local authority lands.</P>
    <P>In order to improve the supply of serviced land and thereby help to curb increases in house prices, capital expenditure on water supply and sewerage has been increased from £24.5 million in 1977 to £40.4 million this year and the Government gave a commitment in the recent White Paper, &ldquo;Programme for National Development 1978/1981&rdquo;, that they will further increase the capital allocation for sanitary services in 1980 and 1981.  This assurance will assist local authorities in their forward planning of the necessary infrastructural services which are essential to our efforts to keep land prices from increasing unduly.</P>
    <P>A structural guarantee scheme for new houses, involving the Construction Industry Federation and my Department, was introduced from 1st January 1978.</P>
    <P>In April 1978 grants to voluntary housing associations providing houses for elderly persons were greatly increased. Local authorities were allowed access to the Local Loans Fund for the first time for the major part of the capital cost of such work and a subsidy <Col N="198" /> was introduced.  Recently a circular letter was issued by my Department giving detailed guidance to local authorities and to voluntary housing associations on an improved package of financial assistance for this purpose.  At this point I might comment that during their four-year term in office, the Coalition Government took no initiative whatsoever in assisting voluntary housing associations and housing co-operatives to provide housing.</P>
    <P>A new outline specification, introduced in August 1978 for new private housing, will come into operation on 1 July next and will up-grade thermal insulation and increase the conservation of energy in the private housing sector. These improvements have already been introduced in relation to new local authority dwellings.</P>
    <P>Tenants of local authority houses who wish to buy their houses may do so on very attractive terms.  The gross prices of houses under the 1979 tenant purchase scheme, which was circulated to local authorities, have been increased only very marginally over the price applicable to the 1978 scheme.  Tenants will continue to benefit from a discount of up to 45 per cent for length of tenancy together with discounts in lieu of the £1,000 new house grant payable to first-time owner-occupiers of private new houses and in lieu of rates remission which was applicable to new private houses prior to 1 January 1978.  Tenants and certain applicants on local authority waiting lists can also opt to buy private houses with the aid of the low-rise mortgage scheme, which was recently revised&mdash;for example, to allow one-parent families to benefit under the scheme.</P>
    <P>Where a person buys an existing house which needs repair or improvement, he can avail of the generous new scheme of grants for this purpose which was announced in December 1977.  I might again remind some Senators that in January 1977 the Coalition Government emasculated the rather miserly reconstruction grants scheme then in operation with the result that expenditure on these grants in 1977 was as low as £2 million.  The new scheme of house improvement grants is now so <Col N="199" /> popular that provision has been made for an expenditure of £17 million under this scheme this year.  Last year a total of 38,530 applications for house improvement grants was submitted to my Department compared with a total of 9,573&mdash;including applications for water and sewerage grants&mdash;received during the first half of 1977 under the Coalition Government's revised scheme of reconstruction grants.</P>
    <P>Fair-minded Senators will accept that this is a record of solid achievement by the Government in the interests of the house purchaser.  In the White Paper, &ldquo;Programme for Economic Development 1978-1981&rdquo;, the Government indicated that a target of 23,000 to 27,000 houses per year up to 1980 will be sufficient to cater adequately for housing needs arising in that period and will enable further progress to be made in reducing accumulated needs.</P>
    <P>Taking into account the generous provision made by the Government for SDA loans, the low-rise mortgage scheme, and local authority housing, and the mortgage finance which is expected to be available from commercial sources, we are confident that house completions this year should be in or around the 25,000 mark.  Sufficient finance should be available to enable almost 19,000 non-local authority houses to be provided.  In other words, the prospects this year for the house purchaser are good.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I feel it is necessary for me to make the very important point that, in the context of the national economy generally, housing activity cannot realistically be considered in isolation from other major branches of the constriuction industry.  When we resumed office in July 1977 the building industry was in a sorry state and its output was below the 1973 level.  Worse still, the average annual level of unemployment in the industry had increased very sharply from 12,464 in 1973 to 24,532 in 1976.</P>
    <P>The Government saw the need to increase substantially public capital expenditure affecting the industry and, at the same time, step up considerably the level of investment in roads, sanitary services <Col N="200" /> and telecommunications.  As a result, output in the industry improved during the latter half of 1977 and, last year, an increase of about 11 per cent was recorded and total output was an all-time record.  While there were signs of overheating in some sectors of the industry, nevertheless, the Government are determined to meet the challenge of expanding infrastructural investment rapidly.  We could have allowed the industry to grow at a modest pace of 4 per cent to 5 per cent per annum, but our dole queues would have remained as long as they were in 1977.  Since the change of Government, direct employment in the building industry has increased by about 7,000.  There should be a further substantial increase in direct employment in 1979, as a result of the increase of 27 per cent in the provision for public capital expenditure affecting the industry this year.  This assistance by the Government will also result in extra employment in ancillary services.</P>
    <P>In a nutshell, the overall scene in housing and the building industry is a complex one, but the Government have demonstrated that they have coped successfully with the challenge of getting the industry back on its feet.</P>
    <P>Senator Molony stated that our national housing record for years past has been a bad one, that not enough has been done to help every family to have a home of their own.  I do not agree with the Senator's view because, for the past six years, we have been adding more than 25,000 new houses each year to the national stock.  This represents nearly eight houses per 1,000 population which is well in pace with the highest averages in western Europe; in so far as home ownership is concerned, we have the highest proportion in Europe apart from Finland.</P>
    <P>In addition to new building it is only right that regard should be had to the policy encouraged and assisted by generous Government grants to bring existing houses up to proper standards. The new scheme of grants introduced by the Minister for the Environment in November 1977, has resulted in a huge expansion of this work with 38,500 applications having been received in 1978 more than double the intake in 1977.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="201" /> With regard to the issuing of certificates of reasonable value, 1,899 certificates were issued in 1978 compared with 1,502 in the preceding year.  The total of all price reductions amounted to £1.2 million, double that of the previous year.  I am happy to say that we maintained a good standard of service to house builders, the average time taken to issue decisions being only 15 days from the supply of the required information. The CRV system received considerable publicity during 1978 especially after the Government requested building societies to insist on CRVs before advancing loans of £16,000 or less for the purchase of new houses or flats.  It is not surprising that some house builders resent any form of price control but they must accept that, particularly where houses benefit from public funds by virtue of the £1,000 grant and relief from stamp duty, some degree of price restraint is indispensable. It would hardly be justifiable to bestow such benefits on excessively prices houses.  On a number of occasions during the past year I met representatives of the CIF to discuss various aspects of the CRV system.  The criteria are constantly adjusted to take account of changing cost factors and this system will be discussed at length in the context of the forthcoming legislation.</P>
    <P>Senator Connaughton was anxious to know the number of local authority dwellings completed during the past year.  The number completed in the year ended 31 December 1978 was 6,073.  I should like to remind Senator Connaughton that in 1978 over 12,000 people purchasing or building houses for themselves for the first time were approved for the £1,000 grant.  That certainly does not tally with his theory that houses have gone beyond the reach of first-time purchasers.  In relation to his allegation that it was virtually impossible for people in unserviced cottages or houses to reconstruct them, redecorate them and have them serviced, the position is that grants for the purpose of reconstructing and providing water and sewerage facilities for a house amount to £950 which is a substantial improvement on what the grant was over a year ago. <Col N="202" /> The total housing improvement grant is now £600 as compared with £200 which was formerly paid by the State; the full £600 is now paid by the State.  The water and sewerage grant has increased to £350 from a possible £75 to £100 prior to late 1977.</P>
    <P>I realise the spirit of the motion.  The Government are keeping a very close eye on the cost of house property.  We have been, we are and we intend taking all possible steps to alleviate the difficulties which may be experienced by house purchasers.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKilbride" hpid="Mr. Kilbride Mr. Kilbride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kilbride</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to delay the House very long.  I want to make a few observations on the subject matter of the motion from the point of view of a member of a local authority who realises the problems of many people seeking loans and anxious to acquire sites to build their own houses and the inhibitions that they experience.  As a local authority member, I have learned also the cost of the implementation of vesting schemes where persons seek to purchase their houses.  There is a contrast between the conditions obtaining at present for a housing grant and those that obtained during the term of office of the Minister's predecessor, when as the Minister is aware, the applicant had to have a low level of income.  He got the ordinary £300 grant, plus £300, then a supplementary grant of £150 from the State and the same from the local authority.  That brought the amount of grant paid, in a period of severe worldwide recession, to £900.  We got out of the recession.  The Taoiseach agreed that we were out of the recession in June 1977, when the new gift grant, as it was originally known&mdash;the £1,000 grant for newly-weds&mdash;was announced with a flourish.  Without belittling it that £1,000 was held out to newly-weds, or those who were about to be newly-weds, as something being given them as a wedding gift in addition to the £900 grant in respect of which legislation had been implemented. It was soon discovered that that £1,000 was not a grant towards the erection of a house costing from £2,500 to £3,000 but it was a grant towards a <Col N="203" /> house costing from £8,000 to £11,000 because in some cases, through no fault of the Government or the Minister, when the rush to acquire sites and to build houses started, the people in a position to bleed the unfortunate people buying the houses put up the charges.</P>
      <P>In reference to that I should like to emphasise what Senator Dowling said. Senator Dowling was not sneering at the Government and he was not on this side of the House when he made the statements he made.  I would like to emphasise, without casting any reflection on what is implied in the Minister's efforts in regard to housing, that the moneys provided by the increase of this £100 grant bears a very poor relationship to the increases in the cost of houses that were allowed by this Government to go unchecked.  A certificate of reasonable value can be based upon anything.  The basis of that certificate of fair value for a house could be affected in cases where the inspector took into account the location of the house, whether it had a back road or front road entrance or whether there was a particular sort of paddock or sportsground or anything else near it. These are the things that set the value up or down and unfortunately many houses were regarded as being fairly valued when it came to the question of higher valuations.  I think that had fair application in this city of Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In rural Ireland if a small farmer wanted to build a house he got his grant if he was the qualified person I referred to.  Having built it he considered that he was making ends meet between the loan and the grant and the cost of the house. The loan that can be got has been increased by roughly 30 per cent.  I accept that that is a considerable increase and commend the Minister and the Government for that.  However, it is insignificant in relationship to the cost of a house today in comparison with the cost then obtaining. The £9,000 that can be borrowed by a person with £68 or £70 a week is disproportionate to the cost of the house.  The Minister is a fair-minded man, and so is the Minister of State who is present, but let them not be under any <Col N="204" /> illusion as to the difference between the £15,000 or £17,000 which is the price of a house in rural Ireland and the £9,000 that the borrower can procure from the local authority.  If a person's income is such as to qualify for that loan, building societies do not want to hear anything about him.  This fact should be accepted. The Government are seriously interested in housing but they are providing an opportunity to builders to exercise their muscle as a result of the difficulties that exist in this matter.</P>
    <P>It has been said that local authorities had between 50,000 or 60,000 sites.  The majority of these sites might be around the city of Dublin.  Small numbers of them may be located around the towns under the administrative authority of county councils.  Collectively, the number of sites may seem large but it is inadequate.  A purchase scheme has now been announced by local authorities in County Longford.  As chairman of the county council and a member of the Town Commissioners I have first-hand information on the relative increase in the purchase cost under this scheme as compared to the 1977 scheme.  The 1977 scheme provided for an old house to be purchased at £680.  Today such a house will cost £2,100 or £2,200.  If that is not three times what it was before it is difficult to see where the practice of misconstruing and misrepresenting figures will stop.  It is escalation to an extent that should not be tolerated.</P>
    <P>There is another aspect of housing. The tendency of this Government and of county managers to influence people in rural areas to seek housing in towns and villages is becoming more apparent every year.  In County Longford there are 146 applications for rural houses and that is over and above what we are able to provide or are providing.  At this moment people are living in atrocious conditions.  They have not got a house and they are directed to go into Granard, Longford, Edgeworthstown or elsewhere to look for a house.  If a family has had roots and social and economic links in an area for generations it is a terrible thing to tell them that they cannot build on their own land but must go seven or eight miles away.  That is a policy that should not be promoted.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="205" /> Longford County Council, despite political differences, nailed that proposal from the county manager last year. Nevertheless, advertisements have appeared calling for people who want houses in certain named villages and towns in the county.  That is certainly not the county manager's policy because he is prepared to do what the council are anxious to have him do, which is, to let those who have roots in rural Ireland live in rural Ireland.  When people are taken into towns they develop an urban outlook.  They will have an anti-rural outlook.  A vast area of the country will become depopulated.  Ultimately there will be great ranches and certain arrangements will be made for improvement of estates on the lines envisaged in Europe.  The people who fought for this country and the generation which follows this one will regard this generation as the generation that left our country denuded of population.  I appeal, therefore, to the Minister to use his muscle to put rural Ireland on its feet and to stimulate rural housing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If it is the wish of the House to conclude the debate by 8.30, in order to give the proposer of the motion time to reply, I will have to ask Senators to limit their speeches.  We have 20 minutes after 8.30 which we could leave over for another day.  What does the House propose to do?  The proposer is normally given 15 minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>The House has made a decision and I will be bound by this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>There are two essential points that spring to mind which are fundamental to the issue being debated.  One is the availability and supply of serviced land and that has been discussed in some detail and at some length.  We will have to note the Minister's comments when he reminded the House of the capital expenditure provisions on water supply in the current year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Molony has suggested control of house prices.  In that context we are essentially talking about controlling also the price of serviced land.  I do not know what machinery can be devised for <Col N="206" /> that which would be effective or equitable.  There are certain difficulties about it.  One is that the machinery, if it is not efficient and smooth, can be entirely counter-productive and can disrupt the entire industry and adversely affect prospective purchasers.</P>
    <P>The second point is that anomalies may occur which are counter-productive. Persons who purchased before the controls were introduced and who are forced, through family circumstances or some misfortune, to sell shortly after the controls are introduced, can find themselves at a very great financial disadvantage.  Removal of controls can mean that a substantial financial benefit can accrue to those who are not entitled to it by any measure of fairness or equity but simply by being in the right place at the right time.  The record shows that attempts to interfere at the top in that way are fraught with difficulties.  It is much more practical to make progress where we know the economics of the business are capable of being effective.  I support the point made by Senator Mulcahy that substantial future investment in servicing land is likely to have a much more beneficial effect in reducing one of the basic costs in house construction.</P>
    <P>From time to time it has been suggested that in some way this problem can also be helped by adjusting stamp duties upwards or by additional capital gains taxes or something like that.  They may be good ideas for land speculation but as far as the consumer is concerned they are not likely to have much effect. They may also be counter-productive because the outlay on acquiring the land and bringing it into service must be reduced in order to benefit the consumer. That type of argument, while it may be well-meaning, is not really getting to grips with the problem.</P>
    <P>Another point which is of immense importance in the day to day working of the industry and as far as the consumer is concerned is the availability of money. We know the problems that exist with the high points and the low points.  The building societies are saying they must compete with many other financial institutions. Nevertheless, young people in particular trying to acquire their house for the first time, newly married people, <Col N="207" /> find that suddenly, because of a shortage of money, the deposit of, say, £1,000 has to be on deposit for a year instead of for six months.  Perhaps a month later, the position gets worse and they find it has to be there for two years.  That type of on again, off again decision is extremely disruptive to the industry and is extremely disruptive socially.  There is a case for the regulation of financing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator be prepared to give four or five minutes to Senator Harte?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I will conclude by saying that some form of financial equalisation provisions in the financing institutions may ease the flow of funds and even if it did not itself increase the volume of money available it would bring more order and regularity into the market to the betterment of the industry, the workers and the consumers.  In that regard may I say that the extension in the budget of the power to grant loans to the Trustee Saving Banks is an extremely important move in the right direction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>Because of the shortage of time I will have to express what I was going to say in different terms.  Irrespective of which Government are in power, people are entitled to ask the question and to have it answered: why is a house, which is an essential consumer commodity, not subject to the same checks and controls as other consumer commodities? Some will say it is not possible to control house prices.  I do not accept that.  By what mandate are any Government authorised to allow a basic human need to be subject to manipulation and manoeuvring by speculators?  I can only conclude that it is the result of manoeuvring and manipulation by speculators that one sees, over an 18 month period, an increase in price of 30 per cent through 36 or 37 per cent. Whether it is a Coalition Government, or Fine Gael Government or any other Government that are in power, it is a basic human right that is being denied to many people.  A decision is made on the basis of the length of their purse strings. <Col N="208" /> That is not in accordance with our social responsibilities.  All of us have responsibility in this sense.</P>
      <P>The Minister did not like the criticisms; he may have found that some of the criticisms were not constructive. The Opposition has not done enough to highlight the problem in the housing area.  It is the Government's responsibility to ensure that everyone has a chance to own a decent home or to rent with security of tenure.  Drastic measures are needed to implement this principle and the onus is clearly on the Government to take those drastic measures.  I read the Minister's speech and I agree that measures have been taken but the fundamental right of everyone is to have shelter, to have a home and to purchase a home.  That right should not be interfered with by the deeds of any pressure group or for any other reason.  A man who needs a mortgage has not got the capital.  Having worked excessive overtime, shift work and so on thereby disrupting his family life, he suddenly realises that he still cannot meet his commitments.  Lay people have a right to ask questions.</P>
      <P>We have been relying on competition to reduce prices and it has failed.  Land a house stands on is a consumer product and we should not make any mistake about that.  The material that is put into the building of a house is subject to price control; the equipment inside the house is subject to price control but the structure, which is built out of consumer products, is not subject to control.  We should say to the speculators that enough is enough and that they must come to terms with the fact that their profits are in excess of what they should be.  I am not in a position to produce figures, because of the short time which is left to me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the last 18 months we have put in jeopardy the basic human rights of a substantial number of people in order to allow people with private capital to make a quick buck.  That is not an emotional statement.  It is a statement of fact.  Thousands of people all over the country come with housing problems to public representatives.  They cannot provide their own homes and must look for local authority housing.  They find <Col N="209" /> that is not available to them either. There is a social responsibility there and we have to do something about it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to apologise that because of the shortage of time I will not be able to review and comment on many of the points made in the debate.  I hope I will be forgiven for that.</P>
      <P>Senator Harte, who has just spoken the few words that time permitted him to do and Senator Donnelly who spoke before him and also Senator Mulcahy who spoke earlier reflected the two different sides of the problem.  The reality is that economically&mdash;and what Senator Donnelly said made very sound sense&mdash;it is not a palatable thing to have to introduce price controls because it causes problems particularly in an industry like the building industry.  But, one has to look at it from another point of view as well.  Both Senator Donnelly and Senator Mulcahy have concerned themselves with the health of the building industry.  The reality is that there is a social side to it and that side was brought to light by Senator Harte.  I would be the last person to suggest introducing any type of artificial control but we must have regard to the circumstances that obtain in the housing industry. Whatever the Minister may say, house prices have increased by something in the order of 40 per cent in the past 18 or 20 months and, in the context of our history and our traditional house building, something must be done.  The simple truth is that people are skimming money off the top. Where the money is going I do not know.  It certainly is not the consumer who is getting the benefit of it.  Various reports indicate that excessive prices are being charged for houses.  That is a problem that must be dealt with and we will either try to deal with it or we will ignore it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I was most disappointed with everything the Minister had to say.  He came into this House with a supplied typewritten script of 14 pages.  He stitched the Fianna Fáil manifesto, everything he had done, on to the record of the House.  When I proposed this motion I specifically hoped that this would not happen.  He said that he regarded <Col N="210" /> this debate as a rather sterile exercise.  I am sorry that he saw the debate in that light.  It is a sad thing that a Minister of State responsible for this sector should see a debate of this nature in that light. That motion was tabled on 3 May last. The Minister of State is on the record of the Dáil, and on record here tonight, as having said that at the end of the first half of last year he was concerned about the unacceptable rate of price increases for houses.  We put that motion on the Order Paper before the six-month period the Minister had complained about was up.  We put it on, not to criticise the Government.  Of course, there will be criticisms and commentators have said that certain fiscal policies adopted by the Government have added to the problems of price increases and have acted as catalysts.  That criticism is made not simply to knock but because of a heartfelt belief on both sides of the House and also in the Dáil that something needs to be done.</P>
    <P>I am sorry, for example, that the Minister of State did not give us his views on the Kenny report.  He said in the past in the Dáil that he had considered the report.  I am sorry because land and the cost of land is a very significant feature in all of this.  Even apart from that there are problems.  I quoted an example from <i>Irish Business</i> of last October, where a builder was estimated to be making something in the order of £12,000 per house in an estate of 56 houses had the site cost allowed for and that £12,000 was exclusive of that.  The figure on that estate alone would work out at something in the order of £364,000.  There is something wrong when that can happen.  I did not knock the CRV system; I acknowledge that it is a good system; but I do not think it is as effective as it should be.  It is a system that could be used or extended so that all houses are included in it.</P>
    <P>Senator Mulcahy and the Minister both defended the housing records of successive Governments down through the years.  The reality is that there are parts of Dublin where people are living in conditions they should not be living in.  The reality is that in one six months last year the housing list for local authorities increased by 30 to 35 per <Col N="211" /> cent.  These are facts.  People are looking for houses and they want to be housed. If we say simply that we are building 20,000 or 25,000 houses a year and that that is enough, certainly we shall not go anywhere near solving this very serious social problem.</P>
    <P>I do not know where we go from here. I get the impression that the Minister is quite satisfied that everything is all right and that there is no need to take any further steps.  He said that the Government are keeping a close eye on house prices.  That is very fine but he has not acknowledged that a problem has arisen and it is not a problem peculiar to the last 18 months.  It is something that has happened before.  It happens largely because of the nature of the building industry, because of the difficulty about the availability of finance, because of recessions or economic booms or whatever it might be.  The stop/go cyclical nature of the business tends to cause problems.  Economically one can deal with it in one way but, unfortunately, there is a very serious social aspect.</P>
    <P>I am dreadfully disappointed that the Minister has not acknowledged the existence of any problem at all in this area.  I am hampered by a shortage of time.  I have points made out that I would like to have gone through one by one but I cannot do it.  If the Minister is satisfied on <Col N="212" /> those statistics that everything is all right I would suggest to him that he is wrong. The Minister should look at the position outside and see the reality and ask people who are not entitled to local authority houses and are trying to build their own houses out of their own financial resources and who cannot do it, who, as Senator Donnelly said, have not had the £1,000 with the building societies for a year or two years and who put in the £1,000 which is hard saved and wait six months and find that their budget is gone all wrong because house prices have gone up another 10 or 15 per cent.  Those are real problems affecting real people.  Unfortunately, the boom that we have had in the building industry for the past 20 months has been a builder's boom.  Some builders&mdash;not all builders&mdash;have made a lot of money out of this and have charged unjustifiably excessive prices.  At the same time the people who have been getting those houses are people who are well off and who, as many people are aware, were simply changing from one stratum in the housing league to a higher one. Unfortunately, time hampers me and all I can do is ask the Minister to re-think his present stand.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.30 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 28 February 1979.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>