<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="2" Month="May" Year="1979" Vol="92" No="1" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 2 Bealtaine 1979" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 2 May 1979" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 1, 2, 3 and 4 in that order.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Landlord and Tenant (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1979: Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Landlord and Tenant (Amendment) Bill, 1979: Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 7 to delete lines 29 and 30.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This section has been debated both on Second Stage and on Committee Stage.  I have considered the points made by the Minister of State on Committee Stage with regard to the retention of the section.  It is quite clear that there are cases which he has given which would justify an absolute exclusion of tenant right, such as in all cases under the section <Col N="2" /> which would result.  I still think the section unwise.</P>
    <P>I take the view that this whole code has been historically concerned with securing justice, the particular justice being the protection of the rights which somebody occupying a property as a tenant would develop by virtue of his own activity in that property.  It would be unjust to allow a landlord to take advantage of the tenant's desire to stay in the place where he is carrying on his business.  Because of his desire to stay in that place the landlord is able to rack rent him, is able to make the tenant pay to the landlord a price for what the tenant has created himself&mdash;the goodwill of his own business.  If that is a matter of justice as between the landlords of property and their tenants, I see no way in which, if the State is excluded, the State can be required as a matter of right not to exploit the tenant, not to force the <Col N="3" /> tenant to pay to the landlord for what is the landlord's own property at this stage, that is, the goodwill of his business.</P>
    <P>If it is regarded as just that the tenant should have this right as against an ordinary landowner, it seems to follow that the tenant should equally be protected if he finds himself the tenant of a Minister or of the State.  I said that I recognised the cases mentioned by the Minister of State, the position of the Minister for Defence, the position of the Minister in relation to airports, to the foreshore, the position of the Minister in relation to tourist development and such other cases as he indicated.  The way to deal with this&mdash;and it is not going to be dealt with here but I would like the Minister to think about the matter between now and this Bill reaching Dáil Éireann&mdash;is to provide for the known cases such as have been garnered by investigation so far where it is proper that there should be exemption and to provide for the extension of these exemptions, if necessary by ministerial order in appropriate other cases that turn up.</P>
    <P>No one should put the interests of any tenant ahead of the security of this State, the defence of this island.  Therefore, there could be no question of a position being allowed to arise where the Minister for Defence's control of his own property could be hampered.  That is an obvious case.  I understand the Minister's position to be that, although he has been very helpful to this House, in half a dozen cases where, as a result of investigation, like situations exist which he knows about, there may be other cases he does not know about because there have been Departments that have not replied, having completed their investigation. In the course of the business of running this country other cases like those he has given may turn up.  Let him take power so to provide, so that under an appropriate section in an appropriate case the Minister can be protected against that situation.  Let us have the normal situation exist in the normal case where the State may be given property.</P>
    <P>We have enacted Bills in this House in the last few years to provide for cases where property was given to the State, <Col N="4" /> not to investigate these particular cases but there may have been tenants in these cases.  I think there were tenants in some of these cases.  It would be unthinkable that a tenant of a private landlord with rights against that landlord&mdash;rights to stay on there, live there and carry on his business&mdash;should suddenly find himself stripped of his rights because the donor has given over his interests to the State and the tenant no longer has the rights that he had before the donor gave his interests to the State.  That is only one illustration but I gave others on Second Stage and Committee Stage.  This is a hangover of the old principle that the King can do no wrong.  This is a hangover of the proposition that in these matters the State should not be subject to the same control as private people.  In these kinds of matters the State should be, and nobody's laziness in the administration of the State's property should be an excuse for this section.</P>
    <P>I appreciate the background to the section.  I accept what the Minister said, that it was the legal view that if an Act did not say expressly that the State was bound by it, it was not.  Historically, that legal view is related also to the legal view that the King can do no wrong, a principle which itself was knocked down in the last decade and should stay knocked down.  I do not like this section.  I do not believe for one moment that my amendment is going to be accepted.  I would ask the Minister to give further thought to the matter on his way to Dáil Éireann to see if there is not another way of protecting the very real interests he desires to protect by this section and which I agree should be protected, while at the same time preserving the rights and the justice of the case from the point of view of the small men who may be affected by this provision.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Justice (Mr. D. Andrews) David Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Justice (Mr. D. Andrews)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very persuaded by what Senator Alexis FitzGerald has said; he presented his case in a new way.  This will be the third discussion we have had on this section. This is a new aspect to his argument.  It is the most persuasive argument he put forward in pursuit of his objective.  I will undertake to have a look at the matter <Col N="5" /> on the basis on which he has now placed it between now and its passage through Dáil Éireann.  I will have the officials look at it.</P>
      <P>The facts of the matter are, as the Senator said, on previous occasions I gave a number of examples where it was just not practical that the State should undertake the obligations set out in the body of this Bill.  If it is possible, as Senator FitzGerald says it is, to exempt the areas he mentioned&mdash;airport facilities, defence facilities and so on&mdash;and still leave the section more or less as it is, I will undertake to do that.  If he withdraws his amendment, I will give him that undertaking.  If he does not withdraw his amendment, I cannot accept it as it is presently constituted.  In regard to all the other arguments which were put forward in the past, I have the same arguments in front of me again.  I do not intend articulating them because he knows them, I know them and the House knows them.  I am grateful to the Senator for his consistent pursuit of his objective.  It is an admirable quality in every regard.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 7, line 37, after &ldquo;buildings&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;or is land in an area of special amenity as declared pursuant to the Local Government (Planning and Development) Acts&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This amendment relates to section 5. Section 5 defines the type of property which gets rights or protection under the Bill.  Historically, the type of property which was dealt with in the landlord and tenant code was urban-type property. To ensure that agricultural holdings did not come into the category, the definition provided that if the property consisted of land covered in part only by buildings that the portion of the land not covered by buildings was ancillary and subsidiary to the buildings.  This was intended to cover the type of situation where you might have a roadhouse in a rural area with a very large car park and possibly gardens beside it.  Those lands would be subsidiary and ancillary to the <Col N="6" /> buildings but if there were fields there as well it would be a matter for the courts to decide whether they were subsidiary or ancillary.  Historically, the intention was that such fields would not get the protection of the landlord and tenant code.  It was felt that the Land Acts would be the proper way to deal with the rights of tenants in respect of pastoral holdings and that it was no business of the landlord and tenant code which was essentially urban-oriented in its approach.</P>
    <P>I put down this amendment to extend the protection of the landlord and tenant code to a type of land which is between agricultural land but, one could argue, is not completely subsidiary and ancillary to the buildings, if one were to argue the words &ldquo;subsidiary&rdquo; and &ldquo;ancillary&rdquo; in a narrow way.  Because of the history of these provisions a court would interpret those words in a narrow way so as to exclude any efforts to bring in agricultural or pastoral type property under this code.  The type of property that I would like to see protected by this code is described in my amendment, that is, a holding with buildings on it, with more than just a subsidiary amount of land with it.  It could have a substantial area of land but this would be land in an area of special amenity.  I have used the Planning Acts to tell us what is an area of special amenity.  These would be areas as found by the planning authority to be areas of special amenity.</P>
    <P>The inspiration for this amendment came from a case which came to my notice.  I am well aware that hard cases make bad law, but I would argue that there is a good principle here as well as an opportunity for this House to redress what is a very hard case.  I will outline the facts of this case to the House as being the place where laws to protect citizens are passed.</P>
    <P>In Lough Ree, adjacent to Athlone, there is an island of 100 acres, an area of high amenity in terms of scenery and recreation.  This island was part of the estate of the Lords Castlemaine who were the landlords in that part of south Westmeath.  In the late twenties and early thirties their estates were acquired by the Land Commission on a voluntary basis under the Land Acts.  The lands <Col N="7" /> were distributed in due course to the various tenant farmers.</P>
    <P>This island was excluded from the proceedings under the Land Acts because it was used by the landlords mainly as a summer residence and as a place where they kept boats for boating and fishing on Lough Ree.  They did not make much use of it but the facility was there for them.  It was laid out in such a way as to be essentially amenity ground rather than agricultural ground.  Some cattle were grazed on it because the land was available for grazing, but it was essentially a place for summer recreation for the landlord.  A local family was looking after the island for the landlord. For many generations this family had looked after the island and acted as boatmen and ghillies and caretakers of the property and buildings and maintained the amenities for the landlords. Some time after the estate had dealt with the Land Commission the last of them went abroad and gave a lease at a nominal rent&mdash;a matter of £ per year&mdash;to the family who had worked for them for many generations.  The lease was given in the middle thirties and was for a period of 30 odd years.  That lease is due to expire this year.</P>
    <P>A couple of years ago, a gentleman from this city, who is a member of my own profession, was cruising on Lough Ree and from a discussion with some local people he became curious about the island.  He found out how the island was held by the people who had been on it for generations.  It was held on a lease which was due to expire in 1979 and the rent reserved by the lease was something like £10 or £15 a year.  He made approaches through a local agent to the person entitled to the estate who was then living in Australia and who was disposing of similar small rents around the town of Athlone.  This gentleman made an offer of £250 or thereabouts for the landlord's interest and it was sold to him in accordance with the policy of the estate at that time to sell these small rents. I think the landlord, in fairnesss, was not aware of the legal consequences of the sale.  This latter-day gombeen purchased the rent and constituted himself the <Col N="8" /> landlord in place of the old Castlemaine estate.  He then proceeded to inform the people who had been living on the island for generations that when their lease expired he would require vacant possession of the island.  By a quirk in the land code this lease did not qualify for protection because it was granted after a certain date beyond which the land code did not operate.  Consequently, the tenant farmers, whom the land code was designed to protect, found themselves without protection and at the mercy of this latter-day gombeen.  He has indicated to the two elderly people that he will let them stay there for the rest of their lives but that their successors will not be entitled to come and live in what has been a family home for many generations.</P>
    <P>This island is an area of special amenity and either has been, or will be so found by the local authority pursuant to the Local Government (Planning and Development) Acts.  I am asking the House to do justice to those people by accepting this amendment so that the family will have rights under the landlord and tenant code to maintain their rights established historically on this island, and so that equity can be done to them and that they and their successors will not be ejected from what has been the traditional family residence.</P>
    <P>The amendment has merit on a general application in the area of special amenity where the ground with the buildings has this special quality.  If a person is fortunate enough, by geographical or historical accident, to reside in such an area he should be entitled to continuity in it and not just be subjected to arbitary eviction because the land is, strictly speaking, not subsidiary and ancillary to the buildings.  It is the type of ground that is in between land that is subsidiary and ancillary to the buildings and land that is agricultural in character and use.  That type of in-between situation, which is now becoming more common as areas are developed around the country and as we are looking on our environment with different eyes, will be encountered more frequently.  Pressures on it from native gombeens or people coming in from outside will grow.  The people who have <Col N="9" /> been historically present in such areas are entitled to protection from the Legislature.</P>
    <P>I have no doubt that Senators will sympathise with the people in the case I have outlined to the House.  I hope that the Minister, representing the Government in charge of the welfare of all citizens, will see his way to accept this amendment and do justice to these people who are being harshly treated.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not the Government's intention to do an injustice to the people Senator Cooney has mentioned, these island folk, who, on the basis of the case which he has presented to the House&mdash;I am not aware of the facts but naturally I take the Senator's word for it&mdash;are being very harshly treated by latter-day gombeen men, as he described them.  I can only have the greatest sympathy for a case like that.  It is unfortunate if, as Senator Cooney says, the law as it exists does not cover their case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>However, Senator Cooney, in this instance, wishes to cure what he considers to be a defect in the law to protect these unfortunate people.  I do not think for one moment that his proposed amendment would cover the island folk he wishes to protect.  That is most unfortunate for the people concerned.  The reasons for this are set out clearly and, consequently, the amendment is not acceptable. Its effect would be to give the right to a renewed tenancy to a new class of occupational tenant, that is, where (a) the premises the subject of the tenancy are situated in an area that has been declared by order made under planning legislation to be an area of special amenity, and where (b) land other than is subsidiary and ancillary to the buildings is included in the tenancy.  For example, a farm in a special amenity area, no matter how extensive, would become a &ldquo;tenement&rdquo; under this legislation so long as it had any buildings on it at all and so long as it satisfied the other conditions in this section of the Bill.  It would become unnecessary to consider whether the land was subsidiary and ancillary to the buildings or whether it was the buildings that were subsidiary and ancillary to the land.  It is my intention to touch on this subject later when I come <Col N="10" /> to deal with another point on these amendments.  It relates to a suggestion made by Senator Alexis FitzGerald on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>However, what Senator Cooney's amendment seeks to do is to give renewal right to occupational tenants regardless of how much land is included in the tenancy along with the buildings, provided only the land is in a special amenity area.  On a matter of drafting, I would remind the Senator that he might have inserted &ldquo;Acts of 1963 and 1976&rdquo;, but I am not making an issue of that.  It was probably unnecessary to make the point.</P>
    <P>The important objection to the amendment is, that it seeks to introduce a fundamental change in the code of law and to do so on a basis that has only the flimsiest connection with that code of law.  It seeks to give rights to occupational tenants of properties other than buildings or built-on land.  I remind the House that this code of law originated as a code of law for town tenants and that even under the 1931 Act a &ldquo;tenement&rdquo; outside an urban area is defined more strictly than it is within an urban area.  In this Bill we are removing those very restrictions on non-urban &ldquo;tenements&rdquo; but we are not going to the length of abandoning one of the very bases of the code, that it concerns not land as such but buildings or built-on land.</P>
    <P>I might add a touch of humanity in defence of what Senator Cooney has said when we are considering all these matters&mdash;land and built-on land.  We might also have considered that the authors of the landlord and tenant code in years gone by obviously did not give too much consideration to the effect it would have on the human being who would be the occupier of the land.  That is unfortunate.  What we are doing in this Bill is to take into account everything, including the individuals concerned.</P>
    <P>In this connection the expression &ldquo;subsidiary and ancillary&rdquo; is the test that is applied to the unbuilt-on land in relation to the buildings.  This is the test according to which proprietary rights in unbuilt-on land are settled in this code of law.  The balance of those rights is not <Col N="11" /> something lightly to be upset, particularly in the case of land which is ripe for development.  I must point out that while the development value of land may indeed be affected by its being in a special amenity area, the balance of proprietary rights in that land, or the shares in that development value, should not be affected by the existence of a special amenity area order.</P>
    <P>There may be some case for clarifying the expression &ldquo;subsidiary and ancillary&rdquo;. It is difficult to see the case for simply getting around the principle represented by that expression by reference to areas of special amenity. The expression represents a well-established and fair guideline for determining the rights of the two parties involved&mdash;landlord and tenant&mdash;regarding any unbuilt-on area of land that is included in a tenancy of lands and buildings.  No general case has been made against the principle involved, which is fair enough.  What Senator Cooney is concerned about is the case he has given to the House, namely, the unfortunate position of these people who have been put into the position through no fault of their own and who are now being abused by a citizen who decides to use the lack of law to his own advantage and to the disadvantage of the individuals against whom he is working the injustice.  It is difficult to see the case for simply getting round the principle represented by that expression by reference to areas of special amenity.  As I have said, the expression represents a well-established and fair guideline for determining the rights of two parties involved.</P>
    <P>If, on the other hand, the purpose of the amendment is to permit renewed tenancies under landlord and tenant legislation of residential and other properties in special amenity areas &mdash;properties so extensive that they could not qualify as &ldquo;tenements&rdquo; apart from the amendment&mdash;so as to protect or preserve such properties from development, I must point out that not only is this not a function of the landlord and tenant code but it is a function of the planning code and it could not succeed even in that respect.  If the landlord's purpose <Col N="12" /> in recovering possession is to develop, section 17 of the Bill already caters for that situation.  That does not relate to the matter Senator Cooney has brought in. We can only anticipate the type of arguments that might be proposed.  In this instance we did not anticipate that Senator Cooney would bring up a case of this nature.  However, taking all the areas of argument into consideration, in all the circumstances the amendment proposed, worthy as it is and aimed at the curing of the injustice which Senator Cooney has brought to the attention of the House, is not acceptable.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a pity in the centenary year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that.  Hard cases make bad law.  The amendment would not improve the situation.  The Senator is aware of that.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 3:</P>
      <P>In page 9, line 30, after &ldquo;used&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;<i>bona fide</i>&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The credit for noticing this change in the Bill lies with Senator FitzGerald who noticed it on Committee Stage.  As Members of the House are aware, this amendment relates to that section of the Bill which provides for what is known in legal and business circles as the &ldquo;business equity&rdquo;.  The law as it presently exists provides that where somebody has been bona fide using premises for business for a period in excess of three years he would be entitled to a new lease.  That is the business equity.  It is a right acquired through building up business and goodwill in the premises owned by a landlord.  This Bill proposes to change the law in the particular respect; to remove the elements of good faith from the necessary qualifying period during which the business equity is acquired.  The Bill provides that the tenement must have been, during the whole of the period of three years ending at that time, used by the tenant wholly or partly for purposes of carrying on a business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="13" /> On Committee Stage the Minister gave his reason for the removal of the words &ldquo;bona fide&rdquo;.  He described the words as just a piece of superfluous jargon which lawyers are inclined to use. That may be and certainly lawyers are possibly inclined to use words that are properly described as legal mumbojumbo. I do not accept that in this case the words are superfluous jargon which lawyers are inclined to use.  I believe they were put there for a purpose and I would like to illustrate this by quoting case examples where it matters and where the removal of these words would bring out a change in the law.  It is for that reason that we propose this amendment.</P>
    <P>Lord Justice Bramwell in the case of Rex <i>v</i> Holl, 7 Q.B.D. 57S, said of the phrase:</P>
    <P>The correct province of this phrase is, therefore, to qualify things or actions that have relation to the mind or motive of the individual; and it has no meaning when joined to things or actions common to all mankind, though sometimes it is used in a figurative, but inaccurate, sense.  A fact completely within physical apprehension can neither be <i>bona,</i> nor <i>mala, fide:</i> a mental fact may be either.</P>
    <P>That is a perfect exposition of what that phrase means.  In other words one can have a bona fide traveller.  Members of the House who recall that law being in existence will remember what that phrase meant.  If somebody travelled over a distance further than three miles solely for the purposes of getting a drink, he was not a bona fide traveller for the purposes of the law; but if he was genuinely travelling a distance in excess of three miles for a purpose not associated necessarily with getting a drink, he was a bona fide traveller.  There lay the difference.  On the other hand, one could not possibly have a bona fide jockey but one could have a jockey bona fide not trying or trying to win a race.</P>
    <P>I put it to the Minister that in this particular context the words being removed from the law will create a substantive change in the law.  I cannot, unfortunately, quote a reference for the case, but I recall when going through my legal studies a case where a man had occupation <Col N="14" /> of a premises that were described in the course of the judgement as something in the nature of a dump.  He had not used the premises; they contained two or three articles of broken furniture.  He certainly did not use them bona fide for business purposes.  He argued that he did because he used them as a store.  It was true that inside the building there were two or three articles of broken furniture which had been there for a long time. The question the courts had to consider at that time was whether he was using them bona fide for business purposes. The courts had no difficulty in deciding that he was not using them bona fide for business purposes.</P>
    <P>The point that Senator FitzGerald made on Committee Stage is very important in this respect.  The courts must take cognizance of the fact that there is a change in the law; that the law at one time was that premises had to be used bona fide for business purposes; that the law is being changed so that premises are now used for business purposes and not used bona fide for business purposes and they will see some distinction in that.</P>
    <P>I know that the Minister may feel these words are but a piece of superfluous jargon which lawyers are inclined to use, but I put it to him that in the context of this legislation it would create a substantive change in the law.  I would urge him to accept the amendment. I would ask him to state when replying whether he still believes that those words are nothing but superfluous jargon which lawyers are inclined to use or whether he desires to bring about a substantive change in the law.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no reason to change my opinion.  I still think it is superfluous jargon which lawyers are inclined to use.  This has been a very courteous and civil debate and I do not want in any to interject a note of incivility in regard to what Senator Molony has said, but his argument proves my point with regard to mumbojumbo and jargon.  He did not give us the year of the case he mentioned and perhaps he might do so.  I do not intend introducing a note of acrimony into what has, after all, been a well-conducted <Col N="15" /> and very lengthy debate and I have no reason to change my posture in relation to the original statement I made. There is an awful lot of jargon still used in the legal code and as a result of that lawyers use it.  I am not in any way blaming lawyers for using it.  The language is there, but it is out-of-date language.  It has not been up-dated and consequently is meaningless to anybody who would wish to understand it, except lawyers.  This is not a condemnation of lawyers and their use of language which would have been proper to the middle of the last century or the century before.</P>
      <P>We have an obligation to make Acts meaningful not only to the people who practise the law but to people who actually use the law in defence of their interests. It is also a well-known matter of social justice that people in the capacity of private citizens are entitled to go to the courts without, dare I day it, the services of a solicitor or a barrister.  Consequently, to ensure that fundamental concept of social justice we have an obligation to make Bills in this House, which eventually become Acts, as meaningful as possible.  I have no reason to change my views in relation to the use of the words &ldquo;bona fide&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The amendment itself is not acceptable. The dropping of &ldquo;bona fide&rdquo; in the re-enactment of the relevant provisions of section 19 (1) (a) of the 1931 Act is purely a drafting amendment.  I undertook to have the point re-examined because it gave me as much concern as it gave Senator Molony and Senator Alexis FitzGerald.  I asked for a <i>resumé</i> of the reasons for leaving it out and I am quite satisfied on the advice I have been given that it is absolutely unnecessary to retain it in this section and that the text of section 13 (1) (a) is satisfactory.  In terms of drafting practice I believe it is an improvement of the 1931 Act provision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am also satisfied that there is no reason to fear&mdash;as Senator FitzGerald seemed to fear when he raised the matter in the debate, and as Senator Molony now seems to fear, re-echoing the views of Senator FitzGerald, though that, does not devalue Senator Molony's argument&mdash;that the courts will apply <Col N="16" /> this provision so as to hold that a tenant who is not bona fide using a property for business should be given rights as if he were a bona fide business tenant.  These are the arguments which we hold to be reasonable.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister say that this is a phrase which really should not appear in the legislation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  I would suggest that in the context of the legislation we are discussing it is out of date.  It is an anachronism and is unnecessary. Instead of putting in the words &ldquo;bona fide&rdquo; could we not use the words &ldquo;good faith&rdquo;?  Why do we use Latin phrases when we can use English, Irish or French phrases or whatever?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>We have not used &ldquo;good faith&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I know.  I am not talking in relation to this specifically but why can we not make it understandable to the laymen?  Why do we have to use Latin catchphrases when they could be put into plain English?  As we are discussing an English language text, why do we have to use Latin expressions?  That is all I am saying.  I do not think that is unreasonable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>If we changed it to &ldquo;good faith&rdquo;, would the Minister accept it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not under any circumstances accept it.  In relation to laws and in relation to the usage of language in laws, why do we not use &ldquo;in good faith&rdquo; rather than &ldquo;bona fide&rdquo; or whatever other pieces of Latin we use from time to time?  In relation to the principle involved here, whether the words &ldquo;bona fide&rdquo; or &rdquo;good faith&rdquo; are used, it still remains the same.  The amendment is unacceptable for the reasons I have outlined.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>The phrase does have an established meaning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>It does.  I am not saying anything about that, but I am <Col N="17" /> talking about the relevancy of where it is used and where it is not used.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I find it difficult to listen to people who are talking about what they should not know and talking as if it was a virtue that they did not know.  I have listened to Senators in this House speaking contemptuously of my own discipline of the law.  I think they do themselves discredit when they do that, as I should be doing myself discredit if I spoke contemptuously of any discipline of the mind, even one I have not been subjected to myself.  The truth would be best reached by us all if we had respect for each others' disciplines, at the least the respect of silence when we did not know the meaning of terms appropriate to the disciplines that we did not know.  It is hard enough to hear Senators talking about one's own discipline, as one has to, in the manner I have described when they do not pursue that discipline, but how can they be encouraged to have respect for the discipline of the law, as educated lawyers should have respect for the disciplines of economies or sociology or any of the natural sciences, when a lawyer such as the Minister does not himself have respect for the discipline?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I must make my position very clear.  I think Senator FitzGerald has been most unreal and unreasonable.  I did not attack the discipline of the law.  I did nothing to undervalue the discipline of the law or of lawyers.  I am sticking to my point and I am immovable from it.  I am speaking about the language of the law.  I am not attacking the Senator; I am not attacking the legal system; I am not attacking lawyers working within the legal system; I am not attacking the discipline of the law; I am talking about legal language.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We must get down to what is in the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>May I make my speech on the Report Stage of this Bill, which I can do without assistance? I am speaking about this amendment <Col N="18" /> and I am speaking in reply to what the Minister has said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator was attacking me in a personal manner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not attacking the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>By implication.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>If I want to attack the Minister I will do it expressly. The Minister says that he did not speak ill of the discipline of the law and yet during Committee Stage debate in this House he referred to the language which we in this amendment are proposing should be restored to this law.  He described the words &ldquo;bona fide&rdquo; as &ldquo;superfluous jargon&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I stick to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that is language which, even used by a non-lawyer, would show respect, because these words are not superfluous jargon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a matter of opinion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister would be assisting his own reputation if he would stop interrupting me and enable this debate to be finished quickly. The Minister referred to the language &ldquo;bona fide&rdquo; as if it were inappropriate to this day and age, superfluous in this particular section.  I could give the House half a dozen illustrations of how these words can most helpfully achieve what the Legislature may want to achieve in a particular case.  In fact I will give the Minister just one or two examples&mdash;perhaps three.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the case Morgan <i>v.</i> Davis, (1962) New South Wales Report 1013, Justice Wallace, dealing with a case where a lessee had ceased to be a bona fide occupant of premises, said: The words &ldquo;bona fide&rdquo; stress the substantial and genuine nature of the occupation required.  That was decided in 1962, not 1662.  There was a Canadian case in 1961, Carson <i>v.</i> Dunsmuir Construction Limited, 35 <Col N="19" /> W.W.R. 521.  Here are the number of words which were saved by using the two words &ldquo;bona fide&rdquo;, the superfluous jargon that has been got rid of: The expression &ldquo;<i>bona fide</i> secured&rdquo; was held to mean &ldquo;in good faith, not as a sham or a mere paper transaction, not collusively or as part of a scheme to defraud anybody, but being in fact what it is in form, a genuine transaction&rdquo;.  A lot of superfluous words were got rid of by using the two words &ldquo;bona fide&rdquo; in that case.  In another case, the Dougmor Realty Holdings Limited, Fisher against Wilgorn Investments Limited in 1967, Mr. Justice Lieff, interpreting the Fraudulent Conveyances Act which excepted transactions made to defeat creditors where there had been good consideration and the transfer was made bona fide, said:</P>
    <P>In my view, the phrase <i>bona fide</i> in this context ought to be taken to mean a sale to a real purchaser and not merely a nominee or put another way, the transaction must be more than a form of purchase.  The phrase <i>bona fide</i> signifies something done in good faith without fraud or deceit or collusion. There must be honesty in fact. There must be complete frankness.</P>
    <P>In this particular section it has been the law and is the law at this moment that the use by the tenant has to be bona fide for the purposes of carrying on of business, not anything other than genuine, not a pretence, not something lacking in truth or frankness.  It must be a substantial and genuine use and the word &ldquo;genuine&rdquo; is used throughout the cases on this.  I do not think the Minister is doing the law any good whatever in creating a situation where the use, it can be argued, need no longer be genuine. The Minister did not deal at all with this fact when speaking on the amendment. It is a very different matter to come to this House with a Bill without the words &ldquo;bona fide&rdquo; if this were legislation for the first time in this area.  Then the courts looking at that legislation would say it has to be bona fide, it has to be genuine, the Legislature must have meant real occuption, real user.  But that <Col N="20" /> is not the position in this case.  At this moment the words &ldquo;bona fide&rdquo; appear in the law and the Legislature is deleting them.  It is telling the courts to look at this new Act and read our intentions as meaning we do not want bona fide user. Just find out who is the user, genuine or not.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>That is nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister will not aid anything by saying &ldquo;that is nonsense&rdquo;.  It is a principle of statutory interpretation that when an Act of Parliament is amended by another Act, the new Act is construed in the light and in the terms of the Act which it is amending.  That is a proposition of law and the Minister cannot describe it as nonsense by way of interruption of my speech as a contribution to this debate. If he wants to argue that is nonsense, let him produce his argument and not contemptuously say it is nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Reynolds) Acting Chairman (Mr. Reynolds)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Reynolds)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should be allowed to make his speech without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I find it very difficult to listen to that sort of lecture.  The Senator knows very well that I am precluded from replying by the rules of debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>I would urge the Minister to accept this amendment.  I join with Senator FitzGerald in expressing disappointment that the point which we have made has not been answered, other than to say that the phrase is superfluous jargon and that it is nonsense to suggest there is any change being brought about in our law.  We have cited case examples to show how important the phrase is in this respect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Landlord and Tenant Commission considered the landlord and tenant law and these particular sections in great detail and reported at very considerable length on these matters.  They saw no need, and never referred to the necessity, to remove these words.  If they were thought to be &ldquo;superfluous jargon&rdquo; they would have recommended their deletion because the proposals they made were, <Col N="21" /> in my view, proposals that could give us a sensible and comprehensive and, in so far as it can be, a simple landlord and tenant legal code.  The Minister's intractable position is of no help to us at all. The Minister did not say it is the Government's policy to remove these words because they do not believe that they are necessary; that in the 1931 Act they felt it was necessary to say that business must be used bona fide for business purposes, and that now they have decided that it is necessary only that a person occupies a premises, whether it is for bona fide or mala fide business purposes.  That would be a policy decision.</P>
    <P>It will be the courts of law who will interpret this legislation as time goes on. The law is clear.  The words &ldquo;bona fide&rdquo; in this section carry a great meaning. Cases have been fought and tried on the issue of those words.  All I can do is express great disappointment that the Minister has seen fit to refuse to accept that those cases exist, and has refused to accept that a change in the law of a substantive nature is being brought about because of this.  I would urge him to accept the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say a word in relation to this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The debate is concluded. Is the amendment withdrawn?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 4:</P>
      <P>In page 9, line 42, to delete &ldquo;an unforeseen&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;a&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is another matter which was first discussed on Committee Stage.  Section 13 (2) is a new provision.  It arose from a suggestion by the Landlord and Tenant Commission that a temporary break in a business letting should not be regarded as being to the detriment of the right of somebody to a business equity.  For some reason or another&mdash;and we on this side of the House do not know why&mdash;the word &ldquo;unforseen&rdquo; was introduced <Col N="22" /> before &ldquo;temporary break&rdquo;.  The subsection now reads:</P>
    <P>...an unforeseen temporary break ...shall be disregarded if the Court considers it reasonable to disregard it.</P>
    <P>The introduction of the word &ldquo;unforeseen&rdquo; could have consequences greater than would first appear.  As matters stand, someone occupies a tenement on a two-year and nine month letting and, when the lease expires, there is a break of, let us say, a week which the landlord insists on before he grants a new lease to ensure that the tenant would not obtain a business equity. That break, being a foreseen rather than an unforeseen break, if this section stands in the law as it is now proposed that it should stand, would mean that that person would not acquire a business equity.</P>
    <P>We must make up our minds on a matter of policy here.  We either decide that a person who has used premises for a period in excess of three years, regardless of what his title has been, whether it has been from one lease to another, or whether it has been a five or six-year lease, is entitled to a new lease or he is not.  If we decide we do not want him always to be entitled to a new lease, that is fine.  If we wish let us use this way of doing it, although, again, there does not seem any particular reason why we should.  As I understand the purpose of this legislation, it is to ensure that the person who has built up a business, who has created his own goodwill, or who has built on the landlord's goodwill and has worked in premises for a period in excess of three years, is entitled to continue to operate in those premises.</P>
    <P>I know that there are hundreds of short leases around the country.  I know that, in very many instances, landlords insist on a break after the expiry of a lease.  Let us say the first lease is for two years and nine months and a month later or a week later the landlord grants a second lease of two years and nine months, thus ensuring that a tenant would not acquire a business equity.  I know this matter has been questioned by the courts.  I understand that a couple of cases have been decided in favour of the <Col N="23" /> tenant.  I understand also that cases have been decided in favour of the landlord. The fact that the law does not seem to be absolutely clear is another reason why we should, at this stage, make sure that the legislation we are now passing is clear.  The introduction of the word &ldquo;unforeseen&rdquo; is bad in that it goes against the spirit of this legislation.  I know of no reason why it has been introduced. Therefore, I would ask that the amendment be accepted.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate the spirit in which Senator Molony put down this amendment.  As he says, it was his intention undoubtedly to make the law, as he sees it, clear and more concise.  However, in all the circumstances, and on examining this and the other amendments which we received last evening, it is quite difficult to accede to Senator Molony's request, much as I should like to do so.</P>
      <P>If the amendment were accepted it would introduce an element of confusion into the law.  Foreseen temporary breaks may be arranged, as the Senator knows, under the law as it stands so as to ensure that a particular arrangement does not come within the scope of the landlord and tenant legislation.  Any doubt there might have been in this regard has been resolved by the recent Supreme Court decision in Gatien Motor Company Limited and the Continental Oil Company of Ireland Limited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Foreseen temporary breaks may continue to be arranged under the proposals in this Bill where both parties are agreed on such an arrangement.  This is something quite different from the subject matter of section 13 (2) of the Bill. Section 13 (2) says, in effect, that, where the court considers is reasonable, a tenant shall be regarded as having a three year's business user&mdash;and thus satisfy the condition in section 13 (1) (a) of the Bill&mdash;even though there has been a fortuitous temporary break in business use during the three years.  We say that to omit the word &ldquo;unforeseen&rdquo; would not only change completely the meaning of the provision, but would also introduce a degree of uncertainty bordering on <Col N="24" /> chaos into the question of renewal rights where there had been a break or breaks in business use.</P>
    <P>What the provision as it stands does is to enable the court to say, where it would be reasonable to say so, that a fortuitous break in business use shall not count against the tenant's right to a new tenancy.  We would respectfully suggest to Senator Molony that his amendment would ask the court to do the impossible, that is, not only to apply the provision as it stands in the Bill but also to apply it to the case of an intentional break, that is, a break expressly provided for so as to leave a particular arrangement outside the scope of this part of the Bill.</P>
    <P>We ask this of the proposer of the amendment: what test of reasonableness could the court apply to such a case? Either the court would have to introduce a general rule that a prearranged break either was or was not &ldquo;reasonable&rdquo; for the purpose of applying section 13 (1) (a) of the Bill&mdash;which would be at variance with the simple meaning of the provision as it would read&mdash;or else no one could know in advance whether any particular arrangement was outside the new Act.</P>
    <P>In this connection I should make the point that this Bill, like the 1931 Landlord and Tenant Act, must leave room for arrangements where rights of renewal do not accrue; must take account of circumstances where no letting arrangement at all can be contemplated if renewal rights are to be raised.  One such circumstance, for example, is the case of shop concessions within hotel premises, where the hotel proprietor for obvious reasons must be in control of his hotel, must be in control of the general premises, where the hotel proprietor must be in a position to insist on a certain standard of service since, if the service is not up to his own requirements, then his business can suffer. That is not unreasonable.  Representations from the hotel industry to this effect were received at the time of the 1977 lapsed Bill.  Basically this is one of the reasons why we think the words we suggest should stand.  The amendment proposed by Senator Molony is intended to make the section more meaningful and more concise.  We accept that is the <Col N="25" /> intention of the amendment, but it does not necessarily achieve its intention.  This word &ldquo;unforseen&rdquo; was to have been inserted into the lapsed Bill by way of an official amendment since the necessity for it had become apparent on the grounds I have just outlined.</P>
    <P>It is fair to say that the word &ldquo;unforeseen&rdquo; was to have been put into the 1977 Bill.  I got into some difficulty on the last occasion when I mentioned that it was a creature of the then Coalition Government, and maybe I should not have mentioned that.  They saw fit to have it in their Bill and we saw no reason not to have it in our Bill.  It was a reasonable proposition by the original authors.  We do not see any reason to interfere with it.</P>
    <P>I am grateful to Senator Molony for the manner in which he articulated his concern.  I certainly appreciate that.  I am very sorry I cannot be more positive in relation to his amendment and, indeed, the other amendments.  I have good news in relation to amendment No. 7 and I am sure the Senator will then see I am not as intractable as Senator Alexis Fitzgerald represented me to be on the last occasion on which he spoke.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister had his bona fide argument against my amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I used the words &ldquo;good faith&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>I am prepared to accept it.  The only point I would make is that my intention in putting forward the amendment was not to make the section any clearer.  I take a different view from that of the Minister on the question of policy in this matter.  I believe it is wrong that a landlord should be in a position where he can have a tenant in occupation of his premises for 20 years at the end of which he can throw the tenant out.  He can do this now by means of a continuous stream of leases under three years with daily breaks in between these two-year leases or just under three-year leases.  I accept that the Minister has his own reasons for disagreeing.  This is purely on a matter of policy.  In the circumstances <Col N="26" /> I will withdraw the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 5:</P>
      <P>In page 12, line 27, after &ldquo;may&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;if it thinks proper grant a new tenancy to the tenant and/or&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Section 17 provides for restrictions on tenants' rights to new tenancies.  One of those restrictions arise where a landlord who owns a block of premises or premises proposes to carry out a scheme of improvements.  The law proposes that where a landlord obtains planning permission for a new scheme, and wishes to go ahead with it, the tenant would not be entitled to a new tenancy.</P>
      <P>Subsection (4) provides that where after a reasonable time the tenant has vacated the premises and the landlord has not proceeded with his scheme of improvement, application can be made to the court on behalf of the tenant for damages, for compensation or indeed punitive damages.  He has been removed from his premises and the landlord has not proceeded to carry out the scheme of improvements he originally intended to carry out, or at least said he would carry out.  The purpose of this amendment is to give the right to the court, if the court thinks fit, to restore the tenant to the tenement, and to give the tenant a new tenancy, a new lease or whatever it might be, if the court thinks proper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I can envisage circumstances in which it would be quite inappropriate that the tenant should return, for example, a tenant may have moved elsewhere and established himself afresh.  The time in which one might expect a scheme of improvements to get under way might be a year, or two years, or longer in some cases and during that time the tenant may have set himself up elsewhere, or circumstances may have changed.  It might be inappropriate that the court should return him to his original tenement and grant him a new tenancy.  I am certain, too, that there would be circumstances in which it would be entirely appropriate. Where a landlord has had a tenant removed from premises, and has <Col N="27" /> had a tenant denied the right to a new tenancy, and the landlord has not gone ahead with the changes he proposed, it might be entirely appropriate that the tenant should be restored to the original premises.  For that reason I propose in the amendment that, as an alternative, or in addition to an award of punitive damages, the court should be given the right to restore the tenant.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Molony has obviously gone to a lot of trouble in presenting his case for the amendment. Without appearing negative in the context of this proposal, again I am afraid his amendment is not acceptable.  The reason for is unacceptability can be stated very briefly.  A landlord who, for any reason&mdash;good or bad is not proceeding with plans on the basis of which he procured the refusal of a new tenancy is by section 17 (4) of the Bill made liable for punitive damages.  That provision is enough to ensure that a landlord who fails to carry out these plans is, in his own interest, obliged to negotiate with his former tenant.  He may offer the tenant a new tenancy, or compensation in money, or he may offer both.</P>
      <P>Since the failure to proceed with a development or a rebuilding project does not usually become manifest for some time, during which time the former tenant presumably has to find fresh premises, the offer of renewed tenancy is not on the face of it an offer that is likely to be useful to that former tenant. However, it is certainly one of the factors in the situation.  If the parties cannot agree and the matter comes before the court, the court in assessing the damages to be awarded can take account of the factor I have mentioned.  That is to say the court can ask whether a renewed tenancy was offered, with or without an offer of money in addition, and whether refusal of that offer by the tenant was reasonable in all the circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There could of course, in particular cases, be other factors besides a renewed tenancy and money compensation.  Since to mention any one factor in the subsection&mdash;such as the offer of a renewed tenancy&mdash;could only throw doubt on the <Col N="28" /> relevance of such other factors, it is better that none be mentioned.  Accordingly, not only is the amendment unnecessary, as we suggest, or as the Minister for Justice suggests, but it could have the effect of making the provision less clear in its meaning than as it stands at present. I am quite satisfied Senator Molony does not want to do that.</P>
    <P>That is a matter of opinion.  Senator Molony might take the view that what I have stated is not altogether acceptable to him.  However, we take the view that the amendment he proposes is not acceptable to the Minister for Justice and, in the circumstances, I regret again that from Senator Molony's point of view I am being less than positive.  The amendment as proposed can only confuse the situation.  The Senator will understand my reasons for not accepting it.  He might find my reasons unacceptable, but he will understand them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>On this occasion I do not understand the reasons.  The last amendment was unacceptable but I do not appreciate the Minister's reasons on this amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 6:</P>
      <P>In page 13, line 16, after &ldquo;tenancy&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;(in which case it shall be served not more than six months before the termination of the tenancy)&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is a very simple amendment.  As proposed in this Bill, a tenant is obliged to serve a notice of intention when he wants to obtain a new lease.  Where he has a lease for three years&mdash;if I may illustrate my point in this way&mdash;or for five years, under this section he is obliged to serve notice of intention to claim a new lease when his lease expires. Because of the way in which the legislation has been drafted, he is in a position to a serve a notice of intention to claim relief, as it is called, or a notice to make it simple for a new tenancy the first day he goes into the premises.  The whole intention of serving notice is to draw the <Col N="29" /> landlord's attention to the tenant's needs.</P>
    <P>It is a bit senseless that, on the day a tenant signs a lease, or the day he goes into occupation of the premises, let us say on a ten-year lease, he should simply hand the landlord a notice of intention to claim relief, and say: &ldquo;When all this is finished, I will want another lease&rdquo;.  I imagine it will become part of the functions of his legal advisor, his solicitor, when the first lease transaction is closed, as well as handing over the first instalment of rent to also hand over a notice of intention to claim relief.  It makes a bit of a farce out of the intention behind this. The suggestion I make is that the tenant should serve his notice of intention to claim relief within six months of the expiry of the tenancy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment is unacceptable.  I do not say that in any facetious way.  Part II of the Bill, as the Senator is aware, is fundamental to the whole Bill.  Following the recommendations of the Landlord and Tenant Commission&mdash;second report, paragraph 225 and 235 to 237&mdash;the proposals in Part II of the Bill are designed to enable a tenant to apply for and obtain the grant of a new tenancy as soon as he has satisfied the necessary conditions&mdash;I gave the example before of a three years business user&mdash;and without having to await the termination of his tenancy. This is one of the fundamental changes the Bill proposes.  It was recommended by the Landlord and Tenant Commission. It was accepted by the Minister for Justice.  The amendment proposed would leave a tenant back in the situation that obtains under the Act of 1931 where his right to a new tenancy arises only in or about the time his existing tenancy terminates. I do not think this is what the commission recommended.  It is certainly not what the Bill proposes.  In all the circumstances, the amendment is not acceptable.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 7:</P>
      <P>In page 19, lines 24 to 26, to delete from &ldquo;as compared with&rdquo; to &ldquo;predecessors in title&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="30" />
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I said I will be positive.  I will put the House in good humour at the end of the day and at the end of the amendments.  I must acknowledge that this amendment is based on the arguments put forward by Senator Cooney.  I have to thank him for directing my attention to a flaw in section 35 (2) of the Bill when he argued, on Committee Stage, that the provision as it stands requires comparison to be made with the letting value when the property was last in the possession of the lessor, that this would have been a long time previously, and that the comparison could prove impossible to make.  I agreed with Senator Cooney that I would have it examined and, on examination of the matter, I agree that the reference to the letting value when the land was last in the lessor's possession could give rise to doubts, ambiguities and real difficulties, examples of which Senator Cooney gave.</P>
      <P>As the Senator remarked, the reference would be to a long time past, perhaps 100 years or more in the past, where comparisons could be baffling and where the very facts on which to base comparisons might be unavailable and probably, in many instances, unidentifiable. The reference is actually unnecessary and all that is in question are additions to letting values as a result of works carried out by the lessee, over and above the building work on foot of which the lease was granted, that is to say, over and above the original buildings that constituted the lease as a ground rent lease.  The amendment proposed permits the subsection to convey that idea not only more clearly but also without the doubts and difficulties to which attention was drawn on Committee Stage.</P>
      <P>Senator Cooney's views in this regard have prevailed and it is only proper that I should thank him for bringing the matter to the attention of the House and, having done so, to give credit where credit is due and acknowledge the authorship to which Senator Cooney's name must be attached.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stage today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="31" /> Bill, as amended, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Minerals Development Bill, 1978:" RHead="Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Minerals Development Bill, 1978: Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Government amendment No. 1:</P>
    <P>In page 5, between lines 43 and 44, to insert the following:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;13.&mdash; Without prejudice to the provisions of Part II of the Act of 1940 (which relates to prospecting for unworked minerals), section 12 shall not operate to prevent the owner of an estate or interest in minerals in any land from prospecting for such minerals, that is to say, carrying out any activities for the purpose of ascertaining the character, extent or value of such minerals and taking and removing reasonable quantities of such minerals for analysis, test, trial or experiment where such prospecting is conducted otherwise than as part of the operation of working those minerals if, apart from that section, he would be entitled to conduct such prospecting but such right of prospecting shall not apply in relation to minerals which are being worked by the Minister or are the subject of a State mining lease or a licence under section 16 (1) or be so exercised as to interfere with such working or with the lawful operations of the lessee or licensee.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Minister for Industry, Commerce and Energy (Mr. O'Malley) Desmond J. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry, Commerce and Energy (Mr. O'Malley)</NameTxt>
      <P>Since the text of the Bill was originally circulated, questions have been raised about possible difficulties arising from the fact that the definition of &ldquo;working&rdquo; in the Bill and in the 1940 Act includes searching for minerals.  One of the problems envisaged was that a person might qualify for exemption under section 13 if he were simply prospecting for minerals and not engaged in mining them or developing a mine.  This problem appears to have been adequately taken care of by an amendment to section 13 (1) introduced in the Dáil making it clear that, in order to qualify for exemption, a person must be lawfully working the minerals as a <Col N="32" /> mine or developing a mine.  The other question which arose is that if &ldquo;working&rdquo; includes prospecting, then by virtue of section 12, the Minister is acquiring the exclusive right of prospecting, which was neither necessary nor was it intended.</P>
      <P>The view which one takes depends on one's interpretation of the relevant provisions of the 1940 Act.  Part II of that Act, which deals with prospecting and the granting of prospecting licences, appears to draw a clear distinction between &ldquo;prospecting&rdquo; and &ldquo;working&rdquo;.  Section 7 (5) of that Part defines the right referred to in that Part as the right of entering and prospecting, as if to contrast this with the right of working.  Section 11 (1) of the same Part provides that it shall not be lawful for a prospecting licensee to work, sell or otherwise dispose of any minerals within the licence area.</P>
      <P>On the foregoing basis, the parliamentary draftsman has been reasonably satisfied that the new Bill should be drafted on the assumption that prospecting did not constitute working. Over the years, minerals legislation has been administered on this basis.  The mining industry and certain Members of both Houses of the Oireachtas have expressed concern about relying on the foregoing interpretation.  This tabled amendment is designed to meet this concern and, taken together with the amendment already made in section 13 (1), appears to put the position beyond any reasonable doubt.  The amendment is a useful clarification of what we have always understood to be the existing law.  It will be noted that it does not change, in any material way, the existing law in relation to prospecting, but simply provides that the right of the owner of minerals to prospect, if it is being done lawfully, is not affected by the vesting under section 12.  However, this right will not apply to minerals which are being lawfully worked by the Minister or another person.  Similarly, the right may not be exercised in a way which would interfere with the lawful working of, for instance, adjacent minerals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment is acceptable to me and improves <Col N="33" /> the prospect of the legislation being held to be constitutional.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 6, to delete lines 31 to 34, and substitute the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;15.&mdash;(1) Where, at any time after the registration of minerals as excepted minerals, the Mining Board is satisfied, on the application of the Minister, that the minerals are not being worked or are not being worked efficiently the Board shall cancel the registration.&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>During the Committee Stage debate Senator FitzGerald suggested that the possibility of cancellation of exemption should exist where minerals are not being worked efficiently, in addition to the existing provision which enables their registration to be cancelled where the minerals are not being worked at all.  This change would bring the wording into line with certain provisions of the 1940 Act and I am advised to accept it.  As subsection (1) of the section stands, the power of the Mining Board to cancel registration is implicit and the parliamentary draftsman now feels that the subsection would be improved if this power were made explicit. Amendment No. 2 incorporates the amendment suggested by Senator FitzGerald in the clarification which is favoured by the parliamentary draftsman.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a crumb, but gratefully gobbled up.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 3 and 4 are related and may be discussed together.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 3:</P>
      <P>In page 7, to delete lines 3 and 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The term &ldquo;State minerals&rdquo; as defined in the 1940 Act is referred to in the Bill and it is confirmed that the exclusive right of working vested in the Minister under section 12 of the <Col N="34" /> Bill constitutes State minerals for the purposes of section 5 of the 1940 Act. During the consideration of the draft text of the Bill by legal experts, the conclusion was reached that provision should be made in the Bill so that the exclusive right of working vested in the Minister under the Bill could be assigned to a third party by way of a lease.  As the Bill was originally drafted, it was envisaged that such an assignment would be by way of licence.</P>
      <P>As the Bill now stands there is technically, at least, the choice of granting a developer either a lease or a licence to work minerals which become vested in the Minister under section 12. The purpose of the existing subsection (3) of section 16 of the Bill is to ensure that various provisions of the 1940 Act which relate to the grant of leases will apply where working rights which are assigned are defined under the present Bill.</P>
      <P>Senator FitzGerald has expressed reservations about the manner in which this subsection is drafted and the position has been discussed with the parliamentary draftsman.  The problem appears to be, essentially, one of drafting rather than of substance.  The parliamentary draftsman has agreed that it would be useful to clarify the position somewhat and amendment No. 3 and the consequential amendment No. 4 are for that purpose.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 4:</P>
      <P>In page 7, between lines 7 and 8, to insert the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(4) A reference in section 13 of the Act of 1940 (which empowers the Minister to enter into an undertaking to grant a State mining lease) to a State mining lease shall be construed as including reference to a licence under subsection (1).&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 5:</P>
      <P>In page 9, in the third column of the Schedule, after &ldquo;subsection.&rdquo; to insert the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;In section 33 (5), the words &lsquo;by subsection (2) of this section&rsquo;.&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="35" />
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>This is purely a drafting amendment and has been proposed by the parliamentary draftsman in the interest of clarification. Section 33 of the 1940 Act deals with the constitution of the Mining Board and as the section stands it provides that while the chairman and one of the ordinary members are to possess special qualifications, the second member, who by tradition has been an officer of my Department, is not required to have specific qualifications.  Section 4 provides that the second ordinary member of the board will, in future, have the same qualifications as the other ordinary member and subsection (2) of section 33 is being amended accordingly. Subsection (5) of section 33, which provides for replacement of members during temporary absence, is now not quite in line with the amended subsection (2).  The minor amendment tabled to subsection (5) is bringing the wording of two subsections into harmony with section 4 of this Bill.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>I wanted to raise one point which was discussed but not decided on, on Committee Stage.  It concerns the definition of the term &ldquo;land&rdquo;&mdash;the phrase &ldquo;in or under the land&rdquo; in section 2 of the Bill.  I am advised that on scientific grounds it is important to clarify that the phrase &ldquo;land that contains or covers the territory&rdquo; would embrace the minerals which may be discovered in our territorial waters.  On Committee Stage, the Minister of Stage was not able to clear up this point and it was left hanging over, so the Minister will have a definite answer to my query at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Questions were raised on this point on Committee Stage by Senator West and some other Senators. They inquired whether the provisions of the Bill applied to minerals which were in the sea bed.  This is not an issue of much practical significance, because the Bill seeks to deal with the problem arising from private ownership of minerals and this problem cannot arise outside the land area.  As regards sea bed minerals, the question is not one of <Col N="36" /> ownership but of jurisdiction.  Under the Constitution, the rights of the State extend to its territorial waters.  Outside the territorial waters, the relevant legislation is the Continental Shelf Act, 1968.  Section 2 of that Act provides that rights over the sea bed and subsoil, for the purpose of exploring and exploiting natural resources are vested in the State.  The vesting of rights, which is the purpose of the present Bill, is therefore, not material, as regards minerals in the Continental Shelf.</P>
      <P>The question was also raised as regards the rights of owners of oyster fisheries, in the event of there being exploitation of sea bed minerals.  Under the existing licensing terms applicable to offshore petroleum exploitation, licensees are required to carry out their operations in such a way as not to interfere with fishing.  They are also required to ensure that aquatic life is not endangered by pollution from an offshore installation. There are other administrative safeguards.  Operators are required to give the Department of Fisheries advance notice of intended operation.  In the event of there being other types of exploration offshore, comparable restrictions will be imposed on licensees.</P>
      <P>Bill, as amended, received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stage today.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I only want to take advantage at this Stage to make one point, which I made also in my Second Reading speech.  I am recognising the reality that the Bill as it is finally shaped is not exactly as I would have wished it to be, but there is no changing that.  The point is that what is involved in this legislation is something very important and in a sense we do not know how important it may be.  Twenty-five or 30 years ago no one would have thought that resources would have been discovered in Ireland, which have been discovered during that period under the operation of the legislation which then existed.  We do not know the full extent <Col N="37" /> or significance for the common good of the resources which the successful operation of this Bill may make available.  It has the important effect of vesting in the Minister the exclusive right of working minerals.  This may be, in value, a very large number, and a significant number of persons may be affected. Certainly, if that vesting were in any way in doubt, a very much larger number of persons would be damaged if it were not possible successfully to work this Bill.</P>
      <P>The Minister has expressed himself, perhaps not personally, perhaps through one or other of his Deputies, as against the view which I now wish to put forward again.  That is that, in the manner which is known to be appropriate, the President should be invited to give consideration to the exercise of this power of reference of this Bill to the Supreme Court under Article 26 of the Constitution.  No doubt in the performance of his office he takes account of what is said in both Houses of Parliament. If there is any doubt as to the successful vesting of the exclusive right of working in the Minister, then at a certain stage in the administration of this Bill, when enacted, we may have a case, where something very valuable indeed has been found and where very large capital indeed may be ready to be invested, but some significant element of the capital involved may be hesitant in making the investment because of any successful claim that the Minister had not had the exclusive right of working vested in him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now is the time to establish that this exclusive right is, legally, bedrock.  Once this is done, the many interested persons can pursue the prospecting and all that will follow from that prospecting with certain knowledge that the Supreme Court holds, as I believe that in its present form the Supreme Court would hold, that the Bill is constitutional.  Even though the amendment which has been accepted by the House&mdash;the insertion of a new section 13&mdash;is a very considerable help in this matter of establishing the constitutionality, it is necessary to say that the matter still is not without doubt. Now is the time, where the interests of conflicting parties are not aggravated by <Col N="38" /> the presence of a treasure to be fought over, to clear away the doubt.  Otherwise, we may have a repeat, perhaps in a far more aggravated form than we have had already, with this Parliament and the courts getting into disrepute.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Reynolds) Acting Chairman (Mr. Reynolds)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Reynolds)</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not like to interrupt the Senator but at this Stage we must discuss only what is in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought that was what I was doing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The President and the Supreme Court do not arise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly, I wish to do what is orderly.  In those cases where there is not registration before a time which the Minister can determine&mdash;which is not spelled out in the section of the Bill as being anything other than a time which the Minister can determine&mdash;that there is doubt as to whether what is in the Bill concerning the vesting of the exclusive right in the Minister, in the event of a failure to register within a time under his control, will be held to be the law if there is doubt as to whether what is in the Bill will become the law, or will be held to be the law in accordance with the Constitution. That is my reason for, at this stage, making this point again.  It is the only point I want to make.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to thank the House for their reception of this Bill and Senator FitzGerald for his remarks in relation to it.  I agree with him that this is a very important Bill, much more so, perhaps, than people realise.  It has very considerable consequences, both legally and economically, in the country.  It has not evoked even the remotest public interest, but this is often the way, that the public have their palates titillated in respect of matters which are of no consequence. This Bill is of great consequence, and while I have very urgently and clearly seen the need for it from the very day that I went into this Department, it has taken until now to get the Bill finally into a form which should be workable and acceptable, workable from <Col N="39" /> the point of view of those who would prospect for and work our minerals, and acceptable in terms of the fairly narrow interpretation which has been put on some provisions of our Constitution by the superior courts in the last decade or two.  It is quite different from what the situation was when the parent Act of this Bill, the 1940 Act, was being enacted.</P>
      <P>An example is the care which has had to be exercised in relation to this Bill and the account that has had to be taken of possible constitutional snags, and the fact that one officer of my Department has devoted himself, virtually full-time, for 15 months to preparing this, in conjunction with lawyers and officials from several other Departments who have a good deal of experience in matters of this kind.  Indeed, I had, rather to my disappointment, to drop from this Bill one entire part which would probably be as long as what is left in it, relating to the registration of mineral ownership, which would have been very helpful indeed if it could have been enacted, in clarifying the position in regard to the ownership of particular minerals in particular areas for people who were interested in exploration. This is one of the great weaknesses of our present position, and that aspect of it will not be improved by this Bill.  But the consequences of it can be avoided by the provisions of this Bill.</P>
      <P>Senator FitzGerald expressed himself, in very general terms, as being fearful that some parts of this Bill might be still unconstitutional, notwithstanding the changing, the amendments and the polishing and honing that has gone on.  I did not clearly get from him, in his speech, what section or sections he felt there might be some element of risk in regard to.  Perhaps he has in mind section 14, or at least section 14 of the Bill as passed by the Dáil.  I do not see any danger in that section.  There are plenty of safeguards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I just state what the danger is?  Would it be a help to the Minister?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="40" />
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The danger is that it could be argued that it should not have been left to the Minister to determine the time for registration, which has the effect of taking from people what may be a very valuable right of working. But the time should be specified in the Bill, even if it is only an ultimate limit within which the Minister may specify, for the registration.  This is the precise point.  There is a not unworthy opinion on this matter and it is not mine.  It raises problems in relation to the Bill for all of us who want it to succeed in its purpose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The power that is given to me under section 14 to prescribe a time is in no way unique.  The rules of court prescribe time limits within which actions of great importance to the individuals concerned have to be taken. The Minister for Justice, as far as I recall, can make some of the rules and the ones he does not actually make, he concurs in the making of them.  Time limits are prescribed, for example, by the Minister for Social Welfare in regard to making applications for umpteen forms of social benefits; similarly, I would think, by the Minister for Health and by various other Ministers.  It is certainly not unique that some time limit should be fixed by the Minister.  It will not be an unreasonable time limit.  It will not be, for example, seven days from the date that this Bill passes, or something of that kind.  It will be a time that will give ample opportunity to interested people to apply for the registration of their minerals as excepted minerals.  The Senator will be aware that the section also allows somebody whose application to the mining board has been refused to go to the court, and the court has discretion under its own rules of court to hear or not to hear, as it may so decide, or as the Justice of the case may appeal to it to entertain such an appeal for a further application.  There are ample safeguards, therefore, in relation to that particular point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are greater safeguards, I would suggest, than exist in relation to an applicant for social welfare benefits, who, if he is a day late is out and that is it. While social welfare benefits may not be of major importance in overall economic <Col N="41" /> terms as something like this is, nonetheless, for the individual concerned, six months old age pension, for example, is an appalling loss if he or she would otherwise have been entitled to it.</P>
    <P>For those reasons, I do feel that there could scarcely be any great danger of the High Court or Supreme Court finding that this section, which allows me to fix a time within which to make application, could in any way be struck down.  If they were to strike that section down, they will equally have to strike down dozens of sections in all sorts of legislation.  I do not think this is very likely.  One does not very often hear complaints about the concept of time limits in applications.  One often hears complaints and moans that one was late in making the application.  But very few people would disagree with the concept of the necessity for some form of time limit.  In this case it seems particularly fair, as there is a fall-back position to the court.</P>
    <P>So far as references by the President to the Supreme Court are concerned, I do not propose to invite the President to make the reference.  Indeed, I am not certain that I have any such powers, other than in a purely advisory way.  It is a matter for the President himself to make such a decision after consultation with the Council of State whose advice he is not bound to accept.  Naturally, I cannot stop him if he wishes to do that, but I do not propose to invite him to do it.  I am not purporting to tell him what he should or should not do.</P>
    <P>A measure of our concern to ensure that the Bill is constitutional is the fact that I have had to drop a major part of it.  I did not like to do that especially when a great deal of work had been done on the registration of ownership of minerals.  I propose to ask the officials concerned, who have devoted a lot of time to this, to go back to the registration question to see if another Bill can be produced in three months or six months' time that would deal with the registration of the ownership of minerals.  I believe that this Bill will prevent the potential evils which it sets out to prevent, basically, what is commonly called claim-jumping.  It still does not give potential prospectors the certainty that <Col N="42" /> they would like to have in knowing exactly who owns what.  As the House knows, our system of ownership of minerals is rather vague, the State owning a large segment of our minerals, a certain segment being positively owned by a private individual and then a substantial grey area in between where nobody is certain until a great deal of research is done.  It would be ideal if we could devise a system that would do away with that grey area and make everything black or everything white. Because of constitutional problems, the first effort to do that would seem to be fraught with danger.  However, we will do our work on that task.  If all goes well, I hope to be back in the House before the end of the year with such a Bill.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Agriculture (An Chomhairle Oiliúna" RHead="Talmhaíochta) Bill, 1978: Second Stage">
    <Title>Agriculture (An Chomhairle Oiliúna Talmhaíochta) Bill, 1978: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMGibbons" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Gibbons) James Gibbons">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Gibbons)</NameTxt>
      <P>The main purpose of this Bill is to correct certain provisions in the National Agricultural Advisory, Education and Research Authority Act, 1977, to which I voiced serious objection during the debate on that Act.  At that time I promised that, with a change in Government, I would take corrective action. When returned to office as Minister I confirmed this intention and immediately set about getting this Bill under way. Before the Bill was drafted I had meetings, 17 in all, with various interested organisations and groups.  These meetings confirmed my belief that what I proposed at that time was correct, and this confirmation was strengthened by a number of independent OECD reports which recommended that An Foras Talúntais should remain separate from the advisory and training services.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is, accordingly, proposed under this measure that An Foras Talúntais be retained as an autonomous body responsible for encouraging, promoting, assisting, co-ordinating and undertaking agricultural research.  The Bill proposed also that a new body, An Chomhairle <Col N="43" /> Oiliúna Talmhaíochta, be established to provide training and advisory services in agriculture on a national basis and to make available the scientific and practical knowledge required by the agricultural industry.  The establishment of this new body is to be effected largely by way of amendment to the 1977 Act.</P>
    <P>Senators will be aware that a particular type of environment is necessary for successful research.  In speaking of a research environment I do not mean detachment from practicality or reality. We in Ireland need practical agricultural research that can be applied in realistic terms by producers and processors.  An Foras Talúntais, which this year celebrates its 21st birthday, has developed over those 21 years an expertise in research, an approach to research problems and a discipline in applying itself to research projects that have by now earned for it such a considerable international reputation that it is regarded as one of the premier European research institutions.  If agricultural research were allowed to become merely part of a large body with other functions, I am satisfied that its current favourable environment would be lost, that its research effort would be diluted, and that its effectiveness would be seriously impaired. Resources would, I fear, be diverted to other activities, whose shorter term implications would have a more immediate call on available funds than would the rather longer time scales which research work demands.</P>
    <P>If An Foras had been subsumed into the National Agricultural Authority which had responsibility for agricultural advice and training in addition to research, not alone would it lose its identity, its standing and its independence but, more important, it would also lose its objectivity.  The disadvantages to the research area would, I believe, be such as to completely stifle the initiative and undermine the morale of those engaged in that area to the extent that it would be found necessary after a few years to revert to the arrangement which, luckily, this Bill will now bring about.</P>
    <P>Research requires specialisation.  It can also be costly having regard to the <Col N="44" /> need for special equipment or facilities or can, as I mentioned earlier, involve a different time scale to other types of work.  Because of these factors, priorities and programmes must be decided objectively without undue influence by any particular sector.  In a National Agricultural Authority situation there could be undue influence from within the other areas of the organisation on the orientation of research programmes. Apart from a lack of objectivity in deciding on research priority there would undoubtedly be a strong bias towards confining research to the production aspect which, although of great importance, is not the only area of agriculture requiring R &amp; D input.  In this age of processing and packaging, it is not only necessary to produce a top quality basic product, it is also essential to ensure that quality is retained through the post-production process to the stage of final disposal.  With the everincreasing sophistication of processing and selling, and with strong international competition in the agricultural markets, research into processing and the provision of alternative products is an ongoing and increasing necessity.  The results of this research will be seen not just in added value to basic produce with consequent better return and improved income but will also mean increased employment in agri-business.  Such research would, however, be jeopardised under a National Agricultural Authority.</P>
    <P>In this context I should also like to draw attention to another vital factor regarding agricultural research.  The fact that the agricultural industry has, on a voluntary basis, donated very considerable sums to further the work of An Foras Talúntais is evidence of the confidence in which that body is held by the industry and a recognition of the need to continue such work.  It would not only be short sighted and foolish but an act of meaningless self-destruction to dissolve the Institute and to relegate its work to a subsidiary status in a body where it would neither have the confidence of the industry it is to serve nor the investment to enable it to do a proper job.</P>
    <P>The present Bill will continue An Foras as an independent entity with a <Col N="45" /> more satisfactory financial structure in that in addition to being the recipient of State grants specifically for research it will now have power to borrow and will also be able to use its endowment fund for capital purposes.</P>
    <P>The Bill also provides what I consider to be the most practical working relationship between An Foras and An Chomhairle.  The provision in relation to certain Board members being common to both bodies will provide a formal basis for improving the relations between the advisory and training services on the one hand and research services on the other.  I will be pointing out to the Boards of both these bodies that I expect an expansion of this formal arrangement through the establishment of joint committees of An Foras and An Chomhairle staff to ensure the best possible co-ordination and flow of information between all those engaged in the industry, whether they be producers, processors, educators or advisors.</P>
    <P>One of my criticisms of the 1977 Act was that it continued the concept of an &ldquo;Authority&rdquo; with the implications this brings of a condescending, superior and regimented approach to the farming public.  I want to emphasise the need for a spirit of co-operation and working together on the part of all those playing their part in Irish agriculture.  The change of title of the new body arises from two motives.  First, I want the body to have its title in the Irish language only and secondly the title now selected is intended to help engender the appropriate atmosphere for the new body to work in. The word &ldquo;comhairle&rdquo; has connotations of co-operation, and the word &ldquo;oiliúna&rdquo; has overtones in relation to developments which go far beyond any conceptions associated with teaching or training. The word &ldquo;training&rdquo; is also far less paternalistic than &ldquo;education&rdquo; and denotes more clearly and accurately the function of An Chomhairle, which will be concerned with training in skills and efficiencies and will pay particular attention to the greater degree of specialisation required by today's farmers.  There is no question of using this Bill to narrow the scope or range or to restrict the effort of the agricultural advisory and training services.  But by taking away <Col N="46" /> any connotation of condescension or superiority, this Bill will provide for even greater acceptability of these services by the farmers for whom they are designed to cater.</P>
    <P>The Bill abolishes the so-called guarantee at section 48 of the 1977 Act that the annual grant to the National Agricultural Authority would be not less in real terms than in respect of similar activities in the financial year before its establishment.  This was a doctrine of despair, envisaging a position of total lack of movement and of the old order continuing unchanged.  But there are vast changes taking place, changes that are obvious to everyone, even to those not closely concerned with agriculture. We must provide for these changes and provide also for the changes that are needed in the advisory and training service to take account of and to pave the way for the further change and further development that must take place in agriculture in the years ahead.  There is no room for stultifying provisions such as those appearing in section 48 (3) and (4) of the 1977 Act, and that is why they should be repealed.</P>
    <P>Consequent on the removal of An Foras and the research function from the National Agricultural Authority by this Bill, the size of the board of An Chomhairle is reduced to 15 members plus a chairman.  Universities, which were represented on the board of the National Agricultural Authority because of the reseach function transferred to it in the merger of An Foras Talúntais, will no longer need to be represented on the board of An Chomhairle as it has no research functions.  The universities will, of course, retain the right to nominate members to the council of An Foras Talúntais as heretofore.</P>
    <P>While, as already indicated, the autonomous status of An Foras Talúntais under the 1958 Act is being restored, the Bill transfers to An Foras the functions in regard to basic veterinary research which the 1977 Act provided for in relation to the National Agricultural Authority.  It is also my intention to assign to An Foras those other agricultural research functions which under the 1977 Act were transferred to the National Agricultural <Col N="47" /> Authority.  This can be done under the 1958 Act which set up An Foras and does not therefore require special provision in this Bill.</P>
    <P>The Bill also provides for a form of control on the remuneration of the staff of An Foras which will be identical with that to be applied in relation to An Chomhairle.  The need for identical treatment of both sets of staff in this respect is recognisable.</P>
    <P>Finally, in regard to general principles I should say that low output has been ascribed as the largest single problem in Irish agriculture and that the potential for increased efficiency is immense.  A national advisory and training service, which can make effective contact with the farmer and have the backing of specialised and intensive advisory expertise and a co-ordinated training staff, will be a vital element in helping Irish farming to achieve this potential.  It is my committed intention to get An Comhairle effectively under way as soon as possible after the enactment of this Bill.</P>
    <P>I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeJMcCartin" hpid="Mr. McCartin Mr. McCartin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCartin</NameTxt>
      <P>Though, in principle, I oppose the measure before the House, nevertheless my principal regret is that it has taken the Minister so long to get it here.  It is probably the second most important debate that we have had in the area of agriculture in the six years since I came into this House.  At that time we debated the Bill which the Minister is amending and we debated the farm modernisation scheme.  I think it is ten years since a previous Minister for Agriculture requested the General Council of the Committees of Agriculture to prepare a report on the reorganisation of the advisory services.  I regard them as ten of the most important years in the history of agriculture.  In those years we had the hope of our involvement in the European Economic Community and the encouragement which that hope gave to farmers throughout the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Those were the years when we saw the start of the effect of research and advice on agriculture.  Those were the years, too, when the EEC increased <Col N="48" /> prices and guaranteed markets and farmers got the encouragement to increase production.  For the first time they were given an opportunity to earn a comparable income in return for their labours, the sort of reward that it was possible to get in other industries.</P>
    <P>To a large extent we wasted our opportunities. We have not made the progress we should have made.  I am not blaming the present Minister entirely for that situation.  We failed to take advantage of our richest natural resource to create opportunities and to solve our unemployment problem.  We have wasted too much time.  For that reason I sincerely regret that the Minister has wasted two years in changing what was not an ideal solution to the problem but was at least as good a solution as any Minister could have devised at the time.</P>
    <P>Why, so many years ago, did one of his predecessors in the Department of Agriculture feel that it was necessary to reorganise the advisory services?  The General Council of the Committees of Agriculture, in common with all other interested groups, gave their views at that time.  Deputy Blaney left the Department and was succeeded by Deputy Gibbons who consulted and looked at the situation for years and years.  He left office without introducing the changes which everybody felt were necessary and desirable.  He was succeeded by Deputy Clinton who, after four years in office, succeeded in getting his proposals off the ground, proposals for the reorganisation of research, education and training for which there was wide agreement at the time.  At that stage it was already late.  The further two-year delay is inexcusable in a period when the agricultural industry was faced with so many new challenges. The sooner this Bill becomes law the better.</P>
    <P>What was wrong with the advisory services in the first place?  Most of the arguments being put forward are irrelevant from my point of view.  I am not trying to grind any political axe on this question.  The Minister could make many valid arguments in favour of doing what he is doing.  The previous Minister advanced many good reasons for his decision.  One way or the other, the <Col N="49" /> average farmer will not become excited about the difference between the two Bills.  The changes introduced by the present Minister will not make a great difference to agriculture five or ten years from now.</P>
    <P>What was wrong with the advisory services ten years ago?  The biggest problem was that they needed more advisers. This Bill has not changed the situation.  In my time the advisory services were never able to reach the number of farmers with whom they should have been doing business.  As it is, only one-third of all farmers have sought any sort of advice in recent years and a large number of those were probably not interested in advice but in seeking classification under the modernisation scheme in order to collect grants for projects or development. Nevertheless, the agricultural advisers cannot reach the people who are most in need of their advice.</P>
    <P>It has become popular to say that the modernisation scheme has involved them in all sorts of paper work.  I never completely accepted that.  The kernel of the problem is that the work of the average agricultural adviser cannot be done in a great hurry.  Classification under the modernisation scheme would take little time if the average agricultural adviser wanted to fit as many as possible into the day.  In order to give a good advisory service to a farmer, an agricultural adviser must be flexible.  He must not be tied to a timetable.  He must be prepared to match his activities with the requirements of the people he serves. He must be prepared to stay in his office on a good day when the sun is shining and nobody wants to talk to him.  He must be in a position to give service to farmers whenever they are ready to talk to him.  He must be in a position to search for those farmers with whom he thinks he might be able to develop a relationship.</P>
    <P>In the west we had another problem which we thought could have been solved.  Young advisers tended to start work in the west and then moved to better areas.  The result was that the less developed and poorer agricultural regions had a high turnover of young inexperienced advisers and farmers were <Col N="50" /> not able to develop the right relationship with them.  That was a problem that could have been solved without spending so long considering it.  That was the second biggest problem that we had.</P>
    <P>I never felt that there was exceptional difficulty in getting the results of research across to the average farmer or the average agricultural adviser. However the advisory services did not have the facilities to enable them to follow up their own education and experience. We had a situation where the best farmers in almost every area began to lose confidence in the ability of the local agricultural adviser to take them to the top of the ladder.  We had the best farmers in every sphere of agriculture seeking advice and assistance outside of the advisory services.  The top 3 or 4 per cent of farmers went abroad for their education and went to the top specialists in the Department and in the Agricultural Institute.  There may not have been official contact between farmers and the top people in the Department and the Institute.</P>
    <P>Nevertheless, I believe that is what happened.  As a result there was a drop in the morale of the advisory service, which was not entirely good.  An effort could and should have been made to render the agricultural advisory service capable of keeping up in the front at all times and in every area.  Therefore the necessity for the appointment of specialised advisers in the different areas was certainly more important than either the marrying of research and education or the dividing of them once the marriage had taken place.  The advisory service could have been improved considerably either way.</P>
    <P>There was the other problem, too, which we cannot and should not overlook.  Very often the committees of agriculture did not always contain a sufficient number with the expertise necessary to give the leadership to the advisory services which should have been given.  This could have been improved without the necessity for the radical change introduced in this legislation. There was a more important role for the local elected representatives, and as time went on the Minister could have found <Col N="51" /> other means to encourage county councils to select at least a number of better people for every committee of agriculture, so that this sort of leadership could be given to the advisory services. So much could have been done without the need to wait so long.</P>
    <P>When one listens to the argument being made in the other House and here today, I get the impression that most of it is not relevant to the needs of agriculture at the present time and will not make very much difference to the average farmer who is waiting for an opportunity to develop his resources.  In the past one could say that the Agricultural Institute had failed to get their message across. We had a number of examples of this. There is the difference between what the Agricultural Institute have proved it is possible to do on their own research farms and also on some of the extension farms selected by the committees of agriculture and, on the other hand, what is being achieved by the vast majority of farmers.</P>
    <P>There is the question of socio-economic advisers, a most important area when one considers that 40 per cent of the farmers in Connacht and Ulster had incomes of less than £20 a week, according to the most recent report published in 1977.  One can see the importance of the introduction of socio-economic advisers when one realises that 50 per cent of farms in the north and north-west are in the hands of terminal families.  The average age of the people in whose hands so much of this land is held is very high.  In all the debate and discussion there has not been a single word about socio-economic advisers. While this has been provided for in directive 159, and I understand that the people in Brussels have taken note of it, no progress has been made on this.  It is regrettable that we should have so much idle talk about irrelevant issues when something as important as this element has been entirely left out.  What the advisory service needs more than anything else is extra financing and the appointment of extra agricultural advisers. The Minister has not said that he is thinking of this problem.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="52" /> When we see the facilities for agricultural education being taken from Galway university we realise that it will be difficult for people from the west of Ireland to acquire degrees.  It will certainly have that effect.  We begin to worry about whether anybody at all intends that the necessary level of advisory services are to be provided.  When we consider the £150 million that has been offered to us from Brussels over the next ten years, we must ask ourselves where it will be spent, how it will be spent and who will organise the spending of it.  I would have seen in that area a most important role for the agricultural advisory services.  We can see at the moment the long waiting list of farmers who are looking for advice, looking for assistance with the drawing up of land reclamation programmes and waiting five months for a farm building inspector to come out to them, not to consider the fact that the staff of the Agricultural Credit Corporation are on strike.  All these things are militating against the development of such an important industry at the moment.</P>
    <P>We are shadow boxing here.  After two years we cannot find any better argument to produce than a whole paragraph of the Minister's speech trying to justify the title of a Bill, as if it makes the slightest bit of difference what we call it or as if the average farmer were remotely interested in whether the name of that Bill is in Irish or English or what the words or terms mean.  The average farmer wants assistance with development, and this country needs the development of the agricultural industry if we are to solve our unemployment problems.  We have processing facilities awaiting the produce to go into them. We have so many things requiring to be done and yet this is how we spend our time when the Minister has been two years in office.  We still have not got down to the basic necessity of reorganising the business so that we can get on with the job.</P>
    <P>The morale of the average agricultural adviser was never lower than it is at the moment.  They do not know whether there is any intention on the part of the Minister or the Government to extent the agricultural advisory services.  They <Col N="53" /> do not know whether it is intended that they will just be allowed to die a slow death and that the co-operatives will be expected to take up and to fill the vacuum.  It should be clearly indicated by the Minister and the Department at a time like this the direction he intends the advisory services and the research services to go.  Let us leave out the argument about whether they are on their own or not and let us clear the air as to whether the agricultural industry are intended to provide their own advisory services or whether it will be the policy of the present Government to provide from central funds all the advice and guidance needed by farmers; or what sort of combination of the two the Minister has in mind.  We owe that to the people who have acquired the education and skills, have accepted the job and embarked on a career in giving advice in agriculture.  At this late hour we owe it to them to clarify the road ahead, where they should see their future and whether the service they are in is coming or going. There is much unrest in this area.</P>
    <P>I remember 10 or 15 years ago when any group of people interested in agricultural advice could call on their agricultural adviser any time of day or night or Sunday morning and they found him willing and interested.  I have been in contact with people in Macra na Feirme who cannot find an agricultural adviser to come out and give them a talk in the evening, as traditionally agricultural advisers did.  They cannot find them, for whatever reason, and if there is some sort of a problem between the advisory service and the Department or the committees of agriculture, then we should know exactly what is going on and when this problem is to be resolved.  These things cannot be done in the middle of the day.  I always believed in giving the maximum freedom to the agricultural advisory service.  I have never seen the agricultural adviser as a nine-to-five man or woman.  That is the line on which I would expect them to go because they must be flexible in the services they give.</P>
    <P>Since the introduction of the farm modernisation scheme there is a lot of discontent in the whole area.  An agricultural adviser's role should be to give education and to take the results of <Col N="54" /> research from the Agricultural Institute and to bring it down to the farms.  He should be a development officer in his own area.  In most areas and parishes in rural Ireland they are the only development officers around.  They should have a wide function in relation to the advice they bring to farmers from the specialists in the various fields, seeking out and encouraging people to avail of the retirement scheme, deciding on areas of land in parts of the country which are suitable for different crops and uses.  In addition to that, the whole area of forestry should come into their domain.  Our efforts towards forestry have been a complete failure, and while that may not be totally relevant here it should be included in their area also.  It is another question concerning the use of land and the means of developing agricultural resources.  They are the people best equipped to deal with it.  This is not being done at the moment.  These are things which should be considered now.</P>
    <P>On average land in the west and north west of Ireland, a bad average, the Agricultural Institute can achieve, and have been consistently achieving, production of something like 800 gallons of milk per acre using their own techniques, an ordinary enough type of housing and their own developed techniques of drainage and reclamation.  Looking around at the rest of the region, at the best that has been achieved on the extension farms and by the top 3 per cent of farmers in the area, one realises that the Agricultural Institute have been doing a lot of work, the benefit of which has not been handed down to the average farmer and put into practice.</P>
    <P>We could also take the other example of the new technique in land drainage which was developed by the Agricultural Institute in some of their experimental stations in the north west as far back, I would say, as ten years ago.  After ten years we find that in Archdale, in County Fermanagh, the Northern Ministry can point out its effects over a seven or an eight-year period.  The farmers of a small area in the North of Ireland with similar land can have as many as 20 machines developed and designed to carry out the work which was pioneered by the Agricultural Institute <Col N="55" /> and here, in the South of Ireland, we have not taken it beyond the research stage and we have not more than one or two machines in the whole country available to do the work.  This is a sad reflection on the way in which the results of the advisory services have been passed on.</P>
    <P>Much of what is being talked about is almost completely irrelevant to the whole subject of the development of agriculture.  The matters we should be discussing are not being discussed.  The whole question is: when are we going to get down to the job of developing the advisory services?  Assuming the Minister gets his Bill, can he give us an assurance that some effort will be made to provide the agricultural industry with a level of advisory service that is necessary for its development?  If we look at the whole situation we must come to the conclusion that education, training and encouragement are most necessary.  This must come through a stronger agricultural advisory service.  We must not think in terms of increasing at the rate of 10 or 15 per cent.  We need to increase the level of agricultural advisory services by 100 per cent.  What hope is there that we can do this in the years ahead?  Already we are making it more difficult by the withdrawal of services from Galway University.  Already we are making it more difficult for graduates from the west to enter the area of agricultural training.  There is no sign that we are providing for more graduates in any of our universities.  If in the morning the Minister makes a decision, the graduates are not there.</P>
    <P>We know that in addition to the ordinary graduates we need socio-economic advisers and we will need a whole field of specialists in every area of agriculture, specialists for whom money will be provided to travel abroad to see the best that is being done, to know what is happening in Holland and Denmark, to be completely familiar with the most modern techniques.  We know that they have not these facilities at the moment; the average agricultural adviser is finding it difficult to travel to another area or another county to undertake any <Col N="56" /> research or education he wants to do for himself.  We know there is a pennypinching attitude.  I am not blaming the Department of Agriculture, because they can only spend the money that is available to them.</P>
    <P>These are the areas at which we must be looking if we are genuinely to seek to develop the agricultural industry, through research, through the tying up of research in education.</P>
    <P>A 40- or 50-acre farmer, who may not be making maximum use of the whole area he already has, can borrow £40,000 or £50,000 from the ACC and put it into an extension of his holding and I am amazed that our Department cannot see that money borrowed to invest in a stronger advisory service can be repaid. Whatever money is available is not being spent to the best advantage.  The amount of money being spent by the Department of Agriculture on the whole area of research is approximately £3 million.  It is an insignificant figure when one compares the increased production that should be achieved in a small area.</P>
    <P>If we look back at the result of the small farm incentive bonus scheme&mdash; and at that time we did not have the farm modernisation scheme and the agricultural adviser was not tied to a programme as he is today&mdash;we will see what a little bit of financial incentive, together with intensive advice, can do to increase production.  We will see it even in 1974 and 1975 if we take the figures of the people who borrowed the World Bank money when the average farmer was finding it difficult to maintain his standards.  We see an increase in incomes over those years by the people who borrowed this money because they were availing of advice at the time. When one sees what can be achieved on a small number of farms, given that sort of involvement, one realises what could be done for the country through the proper development of our resources.</P>
    <P>Then we see three years being wasted debating something which to my mind, is largely irrelevant to the question of the development of the agricultural industry. I know that the Minister and his advisers can sit down and make every sort of argument for any sort of change.  Indeed, one could pick any two lines in that Bill <Col N="57" /> at random and change them and produce strong arguments, but I do not think that the average farmer or adviser would be very interested in the sort of arguments being put forward because it does not make the slightest bit of difference to him.</P>
    <P>That is the most of what I wanted to say.  I have no desire to delay the Minister because I know that every minute we delay this we are living with the uncertainty in the industry. Whatever the Minister intends to do should be done as quickly as possible so that people will know where they stand. Before the Minister leaves the House I should be very grateful if he would tell us what plans he has for the financing of these services.  I know that the Department of Agriculture have already gone back on some of their commitments of financial assistance to the Agricultural Institute and I know the director has said in the last month that the work of the Agricultural Institute has been seriously hampered for lack of funds and that some of their programmes will have to be called off.  I know there are staff in the Agricultural Institute over the past two years who have been on notice from time to time that whether or not they will be kept on depends on the availability of money.  That is an area we could do well to discuss and clarify so that we will know exactly what is available and whether the Minister intends to finance the Agricultural Institute or whether they will have to earn their own keep in the future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamHyland" hpid="Mr. Hyland Mr. Hyland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hyland</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the introduction of the Bill, which lays the foundation stone and clears the decks for a further period of agricultural development and removes the clouds which have drifted over the research and advisory service since the establishment of the previous authority by the former Government.  Now that we know exactly where we are going, I know the Minister will not have any avoidable delay in relation to the setting up of the new authority.  It is important that we get on with the urgent task of developing our greatest national resource.  Legislation is open to different interpretations and many irrelevant things have been said in <Col N="58" /> relation to this Bill.  If anybody wants to talk about the delay in introducing the Bill, I would point to the almost ridiculous length of the debate in the other House and the irrelevance of the debate which has already taken place here.</P>
      <P>The present Minister with his solid, down-to-earth approach and his practical knowledge of farming, has contributed greatly to the credibility of the Bill and what he is trying to achieve in it. Far too many people have dealt with irrelevancies which have no bearing at all on agricultural development.  It is rather amusing to hear Senator McCartin refer to the delay in the introduction of the Bill.  The Bill does two things as far as practical farming is concerned.  It establishes the body which will organise and guide the destiny of the Irish farming industry for the future.  To that extent it must be the most important Bill ever to come before the House. Agriculture is our greatest industry, and there is no need to mention its contribution to our overall national development, or indeed its future potential.  It is this potential about which we are concerned, and it is this potential that presents the Minister and the new authority with their greatest challenge.  It must be our aim to develop the industry to the highest level of efficiency and production. We know from past experience that we have the ability to do this.</P>
      <P>It is true to say that at the top level of the scale we have in this country some of the most efficient farmers in the EEC.  A quick examination will reveal that they are the farmers who have availed to the maximum of the advice of the agricultural advisory services and have applied modern farming techniques to their business.  Regrettably, however, we still have a very high percentage of farmers at the lower end of the scale, due sometimes to circumstances outside their control, but due often to identifiable reasons which should be corrected if they themselves are to survive and the overall level of output is to be brought up to an acceptable national level.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Agriculture in terms of employment and output is of relatively greater importance to us than it is to any other member of the EEC.  It represents <Col N="59" /> somewhere in the region of 21 per cent of our workforce and 35 per cent of our exports.  Even though the trend has been towards a reduction in the number of people working on the land, I believe that a properly formulated national policy should lead to a reversal of this trend.  The sooner the better we tackle and control the restructuring of our land and land policies.  In this regard I want to compliment the Minister for Agriculture for the initiative he has already taken.  I also congratulate Macra na Feirme, an organisation who have put much thought and effort into the land restructuring problems of this country.  They have made worth-while submissions in relation to it.</P>
    <P>It is worth recognising the efforts which have been made by our Minister in relation to the redrafting of the Farm Modernisation Scheme or the directives in relation to it.  When we read that somewhere in the region of 80 per cent of our farmers are outside the development category, it is absolutely important to ensure that the maximum amount of EEC aid is made available to farmers to bring them into a worth-while development category and to enable them to have farm plans prepared for them under the new Bill.  The Minister has made a significant contribution to the development of agriculture in relation to these directives.  It is widely recognised by farmers all over the country that the need to reorganise the farm modernisation scheme is urgent and they readily recognise the effort which the Minister has put into this task.  Any attempt which might be made in Brussels to restrict or reduce in any way the development of the dairying or pig industry is something which farmers would regret and strongly resist.  I know the Minister has been doing his utmost in this regard and I have the utmost confidence in him to bring these negotiations to a successful conclusion for Irish farming.</P>
    <P>As we develop the efficiency of our farms and farmers and as we increase our output, it is important also that we increase the potential processing of these products as well.  It is only in that way <Col N="60" /> that the nation can really share in the overall benefit derived from the development of agriculture.  There is an urgent need&mdash;I know the Minister is very conscious of it and has been fighting hard in relation to it&mdash;in relation to the amount of aid which will be available for development such as arterial drainage. Our greatest natural resource is land and it is regrettable that we still have in the region of two million acres of underdeveloped land.  It is important that as soon as possible we get the maximum possible aid from Brussels and from our own resources to speed up the drainage of land.</P>
    <P>One of the most encouraging factors of the Bill before us is the method by which the Minister is approaching the whole problem of reorganising agricultural services in general.  The Minister is bringing down from national to county level the plans which he wants to see implemented under the Bill.  He envisages the county committees of agriculture as being the local development agencies in each county.  In conjunction with the county committees of agriculture and the farmers, the agricultural advisers will be drawing up plans for the implementation of the programmes in each county.  This is a very businesslike way to approach the problem of our national agricultural development at present.</P>
    <P>The point has been made by Senator McCartin that there is a need to increase the number of agricultural advisers in all counties in relation to the preparation of farm plans.  Although we talk a lot at present about job creation, I do not know of any job which could be created at present from public funds which would give a greater return to the nation by way of increased output than the employment of additional agricultural instructors.  I do not know of any more effective way of implementing a worthwhile, solid, positive agricultural development programme than the situation which the Minister envisages in the Bill where the agricultural adviser will go out and, in consultation with the farmer, prepare a farm development plan.  It is important that these plans can be fully serviced and that they can be followed <Col N="61" /> by the farmer and the agricultural adviser.</P>
    <P>I know I do not have to stress to the Minister the need and the importance of increasing the strength of the agricultural advisory service.  I know he has given sufficient thought to it already. On the question of agricultural development at county level, it is important that we continue to leave the development programme in the hands of the various county committees of agriculture.  The agricultural scene varies from county to county, and the potential for development varies from county to county.  In my experience&mdash;maybe I am a bit biased because I am a member of a county committee of agriculture&mdash;the members, regardless of their political views, are committed to agricultural development and in co-operation and in conjunction with the agricultural advisers, in the past they have rendered a good service to agricultural development at county level.</P>
    <P>I want to refer briefly to another aspect of agriculture development, that is, the development of off-farm enterprises.  The need to develop the pig enterprise at present is fundamental.  If we could organise pig production along more efficient lines, we would have many more young farmers deriving a livelihood from pig production.  This is an enterprise which has no relationship with farm size.  There are many farmers' sons who are very anxious to remain in farming and who could take up pig production provided we could improve the profitability of it, if that is possible, and improve the efficiency of it, and provide expert advice and guidance in relation to the running of a modern pig enterprise.  If you referred to poultry, many people would laugh at you.  But it is an off-farm enterprise which is successfully run in other countries and provides a livelihood for many farmers and farmers' sons and daughters.  As far as possible we should look at the entire farm scene and try to the best of our ability to develop all of it.</P>
    <P>This Bill restores autonomy to An Foras Talúntais.  This is one of the most significant features of the Bill regardless of what previous speakers may have said in relation to it.  It is only fitting when we <Col N="62" /> refer to An Foras that we should refer to the director of An Foras Talúntais and pay tribute to him.  Dr. Walsh is a man whose personal commitment far exceeds his call of duty and who has made agricultural development relevant not only to farmers but also to the non-farming community.  There has been a lot of idle talk about the Minister's intention to restore autonomy to An Foras.  I do not think that, on reflection, anybody with an elementary understanding of what research is all about could dispute the advisability of this move.  There can be no doubt that the research and findings of An Foras have been the forerunner of all our agricultural development and they have found it possible to translate their findings into practical farm application.</P>
    <P>The growth of agriculture, particularly over the past four years, has been significant.  Senator McCartin said that he regretted that agriculture had become dormant during the period of this Government and during the term of office of the Minister.  The reality is that agricultural output increased by 25 per cent over the past two years.  That level of increase was never achieved by any other Government or by any other Minister for Agriculture.  That undermines what Senator McCartin said by way of complaint about the delay in the implementation of this Bill.</P>
    <P>This growth has resulted in a sizeable increase in farm incomes.  It has also made a substantial contribution to our overall economic development.  This growth has come about because of the improved prices and marketing conditions arising from our membership of the EEC.  I doubt that there is any farmer who would question the ability of our Minister for Agriculture to negotiate on behalf of farmers in Brussels in relation to farm prices.  He has done an excellent job in this regard and, in general, regardless of politics, farmers recognise his efforts on their behalf.</P>
    <P>More noteworthy, perhaps, is the willingness of Irish farmers to respond to all the incentives which have been provided by the EEC and the advice and the assistance which have been made available.  Secure markets and stable prices have provided the confidence <Col N="63" /> necessary for Irish farmers to borrow and to re-invest.  This re-investment lays the foundation stone for further expansion not only for the benefit of the farm family but also for the benefit of the nation. I have not seen a figure anywhere&mdash;and I have been anxious to find such a figure&mdash;which would put some value, some monetary value, on farm re-investment.  It is important that nothing should be done which would restrict the willingness of Irish farmers to re-invest part of their farm profit in the development of the agriculture enterprise.  If anything happens&mdash;and I hope it will not; I believe it will not&mdash;to restrict Irish farmers ploughing back their profits into the enterprise for further development and expansion, this would not be in the national interest.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PierceButler" hpid="Mr. Butler Mr. Butler">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Butler</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask the Minister what was the real necessity for abolishing the National Agricultural Authority?  He said:</P>
      <P>If An Foras had been subsumed into the National Agricultural Authority which had responsibility for agricultural advice and training in addition to research, not alone would it lose its identity, its standing and its independence but, more important, it would also lose its objectivity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Having read that quotation from the Minister's speech, I think he has no confidence whatsoever in An Foras Talúntais. If he feels that they are so weak, that their strength has been diluted, by including them in this National Agricultural Authority he is making a mistake.  I know the personnel of An Foras Talúntais.  I know the work they have put into the development of the Agricultural Institute, the hours they gave to its development.  There is no way that the personnel there would bow down to any other body they would carry on their work, the work they have been appointed to do, the research work that is necessary.  There is no way any other body could influence them away from their research work.  The influence of the agricultural advisers, working closely with the people in the Agricultural Institute, would be of <Col N="64" /> benefit to the whole nation.  Working closely together they will be utilising all the brains of the agricultural industry and getting the full benefit from the lands of Ireland.  I have several quotations which will prove what I have been saying.</P>
    <P>I have a great respect for the Minister and I also have great respect for the previous Minister, Deputy Clinton. Deputy Clinton was a dedicated Minister for Agriculture, a man who went out of his way to do what he could for the farmers of Ireland and the farmers recognise that.  The people in the institute recognise that also.</P>
    <P>Some few years ago we had a man in the Agricultural Institute who stood out more than any other person.  I accept that Dr. Tom Walsh is an outstanding person, but the late Dr. Cowhig was better. He introduced modern milking methods for farmers.  He developed the use of the milking machine and the milking parlour, and took the drudgery out of farming.  He was not afraid to have discussions with the agricultural advisers, to listen to them and hear what they had to say.  He requested meetings with them and discussed the problems with the agricultural advisers and he accepted what they had to say.  The Agricultural Institute and the agricultural advisers together put the farmers of Ireland in a stronger position than they were ever in before.  That is the type of co-operation that is necessary.  We need research; and we need it more now than we ever needed it before.  We are in competition with other members of the EEC because of our membership of the EEC. Therefore research is necessary.</P>
    <P>The Minister said: &ldquo;The present Bill will continue An Foras as an independent entity with a more satisfactory financial structure.&rdquo;  Anyone reading what Dr. Tom Walsh said this week would think otherwise.</P>
    <P>I will quote what Michael Dillon wrote on the need for farm research on April 25 1979:</P>
    <P>The Government has apparently told Dr. Tom Walsh that there is no more money available for research... He pointed out that inflation has eroded the value of the £8 million annual <Col N="65" /> Government grant and the £3½ million which is collected from the revenue earned by the farms and from contributions from the agricultural industry and associates, and now they are just able to carry on and find it very difficult to initiate new research.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Senator give the source of the quotation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PierceButler" hpid="Mr. Butler Mr. Butler">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Butler</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>The Irish Times</i>, April 25 1979.  Dr. Tom Walsh made that statement. As other Senators said, anybody can stand over a statement made by Dr. Tom Walsh.  The Minister referred to &ldquo;an independent entity with a more satisfactory financial structure&rdquo;.  That is very contradictory.  The Minister's Bill has fallen down in that regard.</P>
      <P>I would not agree with him about leaving university representation out of the new board as he has proposed. University representation on the board would be beneficial to all concerned. Those people who are educating the young agriculturists of Ireland in the universities would have something to offer. Surely they have some proposals which would be beneficial to this new board. They are an educated body.  They have studied agriculture and they know what is required for the future development of agriculture.  We are all interested in its development because agriculture is our main industry.  The Minister is interested in agriculture.  I have no doubt about that.  So was Deputy Clinton, the previous Minister for Agriculture, and so were other Ministers for Agriculture.</P>
      <P>This is what is wrong.  Because Deputy Clinton introduced the last Bill there was some jealousy and some suggestion that no one could do anything for agriculture except Fianna Fáil.  The farmers today know what Fianna Fáil are doing for agriculture.  All Governments recognised the value of agriculture.  Since 1922 we can see the developments in agriculture and the help given by various Governments down through the years.  The new authority now being proposed is being set up by Fianna Fáil, and that is the reason for the introduction of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="66" />
    <Speaker pid="LiamHyland" hpid="Mr. Hyland Mr. Hyland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hyland</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a very good reason.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PierceButler" hpid="Mr. Butler Mr. Butler">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Butler</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is saying nobody has any influence on the development of agriculture except Fianna Fáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamHyland" hpid="Mr. Hyland Mr. Hyland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hyland</NameTxt>
      <P>That is all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator must be allowed to continue without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PierceButler" hpid="Mr. Butler Mr. Butler">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Butler</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not believe the Senator believes that; nor do I believe the Minister believes it.  I do not believe the people of Ireland believe it, or the people in Fianna Fáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamHyland" hpid="Mr. Hyland Mr. Hyland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hyland</NameTxt>
      <P>They do not forget 1974.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PierceButler" hpid="Mr. Butler Mr. Butler">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Butler</NameTxt>
      <P>If I went back in history I could tell the Senator a thing or two. What I am saying is factual.  If I quoted from the <i>Irish Farmers' Journal</i>, the Irish Farmers Association's &ldquo;Proposed Operational System for Agricultural Advisory, Education and Training Services and Links with Research Service,&rdquo;<i>Technology Ireland</i> October 1978 and the National Economic and Social Council Senators might think again.</P>
      <P>There is a place for the Agricultural Institute, and we all accept that.  The Agricultural Institute have done excellent work.  That is accepted.  In isolation they cannot give of their best.  That is what we are saying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We are saying there must be personnel attached to the Agricultural Institute working on the farms throughout the country.  The environment is very important. Nobody can tell me that the environment in Moorepark is the same as that in the west.  It is not.  There are personnel from the Agricultural Institute in the west, in the Minister's county, and in my own, but it is not enough.  They must get out on to the farms to learn what the farmers are thinking, to help to educate the farmers and enable them to produce more and to produce it better by developing better seeds, and to have better growth, better animals, and so on.  All that is necessary.  I do not believe we are half way up the ladder yet in our development.  We have a long way to go. <Col N="67" /> Unless we have co-operation and goodwill from everyone working in agriculture, progress will be very slow.</P>
    <P>I should like to quote from the document called the &ldquo;Proposed Operational System for Agricultural Advisory, Education and Training Services and Links with Research Service&rdquo;, produced by the Irish Farmers' Association.  Part 2 deals with &ldquo;General Problems with Advisory Service&rdquo;.  The paragraph dealing with &ldquo;Ties with Research&rdquo; reads:</P>
    <P>It is vital that an effective link be maintained with research activities. The absence of such link would be detrimental to the effectiveness of both the advisory service and the Agricultural Institute.</P>
    <P>That is what I have said.  It goes on:</P>
    <P>Without a continuous flow of practical recommendations suited to farmers' needs, the advisory service rapidly runs out of anything to extend. Without a close link with the advisory service and feedback from the field, research becomes excessively academic and unrelated to farmers' real problems.</P>
    <P>That is exactly the situation.  There is no doubt about that.  Part of Chapter 3, headed &ldquo;Reforming Advisory Service&rdquo;, reads:</P>
    <P>The goal is to develop a single modern professional service capable of giving farmers sound technical managerial advice on their entire farming operation.</P>
    <P>Who advises the agricultural officers or the Agricultural Institute against that? Both working hand in hand will do much more for this country than if they are divided.  I can assure the House, having spoken to them, that at this time they are divided and very jealous of each other. Is it good for the country to have the advisers and the research people divided and jealous of each other instead of complementing each other?  If each body is willing to help the other and willing to become part of one body, surely nobody will tell me that is a retrograde step.  It is not.  Let us have good will all round.  That <Col N="68" /> is what is necessary.  It is necessary in agriculture as well as in every other field. I have goodwill for every person here. Unless we are willing to debate this properly and listen to the opposition&mdash;whether it is between the agricultural advisers and the Agricultural Institute, or Fianna Fáil and Fine Gael, or the present Minister for Agriculture and the previous Minister for Agriculture, we will not get the best for the country.  I admit I could be wrong, but I feel this Bill was introduced to &ldquo;down&rdquo; the Minister for Agriculture in the previous Government.</P>
    <P>In page 15 of this booklet under the heading &ldquo;Research&rdquo; we read:</P>
    <P>To remain effective advisory work must be linked to a vigorous research programme, well tuned to farmers' needs.  Without research on which new recommendations can be based and without continuous feed back to research from the field, the advisory service will eventually have nothing to offer farmers, and the Agricultural Research Institute will lose touch with the real problems farmers face.</P>
    <P>There is no doubt about that.  That comes from a body who represent the majority of farmers.  Farmers are crying out for this development to help research and advisory services to come closer together, with the personnel of each having more confidence in each other to help farmers to develop.  That is what is necessary.  I am sure nobody reading this publication could find much fault with it. On page 12 we read:</P>
    <P>Advisory work, like other professional activities such as veterinary and human medicine, must rely on back up services to be effective.  In fact, the range of specialised services required is much broader than that required for other activities.  Firstly, the advisory service must employ the full range of subject matter specialists required to support the field advisers. Secondly, it must provide back up laboratories as required and these services, or at least the budgets for these laboratory services, should be under the advisory services jurisdiction.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="69" /> I do not agree totally with that.  There must be a degree of independence for the Agricultural Institute and An Foras Talúntais.  They must not be controlled by the farming organisations or any other body.  The authority being proposed by the Minister, and that proposed by Deputy Clinton when he was Minister, was representative of all the bodies concerned.  That is the way it should be done, not controlled totally by one farming organisation.  There must be a feed-back to farmers, to the institute and <i>vice versa.</i>  National Economic and Social Council, page 70:</P>
    <P>To achieve significant progress in both the grassland and dairy cow husbandry, a much higher advisory and research input is required.  It is all too often assumed that farmers can master these husbandries with little or no technical assistance.  The evidence clearly indicates that relatively few farmers have done so.  Improvement on past performance will require a much greater and more precise advisory and research input in the future.</P>
    <P>Nobody can deny that; it is the truth. Both must work closely together; there must be no jealousy.</P>
    <P>Research is a scientific study to discover facts.  The facts are easier to discover when you have the goodwill of farmers and producers, when you have the goodwill of farm advisers, and when you have the goodwill of the agricultural institute who do the research work and find out what is good for further development, and relay that, through the advisory service, back to the farmers.</P>
    <P>Television, in a way, is all right.  Much good work has been done by some of the people of the agricultural institute from time to time on television. who explain why this, that and the other is wrong and how better to feed cattle through a season such as we have had.  It is all very good work.  The agricultural adviser is doing the same thing by going out and meeting the farmer, and almost showing what should be done.  It would be a great thing if you had both in the one body, working for the one thing; that is <Col N="70" /> the betterment of agriculture and, thereby, the betterment of this country.</P>
    <P>I refer to <i>Technology Ireland,</i> October 1978, page 24.  This is a special feature headed &ldquo;Conclusions and Recommendations&rdquo;:</P>
    <P>In evolving a new policy on rd &amp; c the technological sector of higher education should take account of the real needs of the country, the nature and origins of technical/professional knowledge and the nature of information transfer in science and technology.  Clearly engaging in consultancy work is a key feature for any programme that is likely to be successful. At present there are many individuals within the technological sector who operate as consultants. However to apply the ideas outlined it is absolutely essential that the institutions as well as individuals engage in consultancy activities.  Unfortunately at present there is little evidence of any institutional consultancy.  This is a serious deficiency in that the institutions' response to the community and the individual's capacity to function as a consultant, are both severely curtailed. If the institution does not officially perform consultancy work the means by which the community gains access to its facilities is at best tenuous and at worst non-existent. Similarly, an individual consultant acting entirely on his own behalf will not feel free to use the full support the institution could offer and will consequently be less effective.</P>
    <P>Again, the message is there, that you must have co-operation.</P>
    <P>This Bill, in my opinion, is not anything as good as the previous one. The previous one encouraged dependence of one association or body on the other.  It encouraged help from one association to another.  That help and encouragement had the one thing in mind, the development of agriculture to its maximum.  From that development, all the people of Ireland would benefit, whether they be workers, trade unionists, farmers, producers, or technical people; all working together for one thing and recognising that we are all part and parcel of this country, and that we <Col N="71" /> all have something to offer.  By working together, without divisions, for the benefit of this country, then this country will prosper.  There are enough divisions in this country and we should get away from them.</P>
    <P>I oppose the Bill.  The previous Bill, and the setting up of a national agricultural authority by the previous Minister, is much better than what has now been proposed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill.  I take an opposite view to Senator Butler's.  I want to say something on behalf of those people who do pure research in agriculture and who have, as he and everybody else has said, established an outstanding name for our agricultural institute, An Foras Talúntais, throughout the world.  The principle that the Minister has made very clear, in his opening speech, is that the autonomy of this institute is to be preserved.  That seems to me to be the main difference between this Bill and the one introduced by his predecessor.</P>
      <P>I can speak from this point of view: I am engaged in pure research myself in a quite different area.  I do believe strongly that autonomy is necessary and independence is necessary, particularly in a crucial area such as agriculture, which plays such a huge part in our whole economic structure.  We must have a basic <i>corpus</i> of pure research going on and this should be given independence, freedom and autonomy.  I am in a position to make these comments from a non-party standpoint.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When the previous Bill was before the House, I did some work on the background of the Agricultural Institute and found that it was set up by money from the Marshall Plan; there was a specific treaty between the US and Ireland which established the institute.  It became clear from the debate in the Dáil, and from the remarks of Deputies de Valera and Dillon who led in that particular debate, that the Americans were keen that this institute&mdash;in fact, they wanted an agricultural university&mdash;should be established.  The American idea was that this body should <Col N="72" /> be independent, particularly, of the Civil Service.  I do not have any axe to grind there, but I am convinced that the Agricultural Institute should retain independence and autonomy.  I am glad to see that this is underlined in the Minister's speech.</P>
    <P>Having made that point, I would just like to make another point concerning one aspect of agricultural training.  I shall refer to one scheme of which I have some experience and which I regard as an outstandingly good, effective and economic way of training our younger farmers.  This is the farm apprenticeship scheme, in which, at the last count, there were something like 302 trainees involved in actual in-service training.  In this scheme, a young man who had not an opportunity to go to an agricultural college, for one reason or another, works as an apprentice with a master farmer.  There is another category where people who are unable to do this, for some reason or another, can be trained on their home farm.  With something like 275 apprentices with master farmers and 27 trainees at home, one can appreciate the scope of this scheme.</P>
    <P>I had some experience of trainees and, if my experience is repeated all round the country, they are people of outstanding calibre who can benefit tremendously from working with a master farmer. Master farmers are very carefully categorised and graded; they are people who are using the most modern methods and can impart a practical farming education to the trainees.</P>
    <P>I would appeal strongly to the Minister to give the maximum support to this scheme.  With 302 trainees, the Farm Apprenticeship Board have five permanent members of staff, two of whom are located in the head office and three of whom move around the country as training officers.  It seems that a little more expenditure and some more staff working from head office and around the country could help the trainees, in their assessment of them and could also help to support the master farmers in their work.  I know that these trainees would benefit from an increased input on the academic side of their education, <Col N="73" /> which is rather limited at the moment. They might, for example, be able to carry out some correspondence course in agriculture while they were farm apprentices. This would require additional support and additional staff.</P>
    <P>The scheme, as it is at the moment, is working, essentially, on a shoe-string; the cost to the country is absolutely minimal because the apprentices are paid salaries by the farmers who employ them, and they do an excellent job.  A farm apprentice, who is a person of some calibre, who goes into the farming business can start with a salary of £5,000 if he is a person of real ability. We should support these schemes.  It will pay the country greatly if the Minister can see his way to putting some more money into the Farm Apprenticeship Scheme, which is, in many ways, a prototype of a lot that is best in this sort of training, where people of calibre are trained actually on the job, working under the best farmers or the best and most modern of our farms.</P>
    <P>I would commend this scheme to the Minister.  I hope that it can be provided with some additional support for the additional back-up that it so badly requires.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I disagree completely with the Leas-Chathaoirleach in regard to his criticism of the Minister for the delay in bringing this Bill before the House.  The Minister, above all people, is the one person who should not be criticised for the delay.  If one considers the Minister's activities in the EEC over the last two years is he to be criticised for the input of 25 per cent under the common agricultural policy?  Is he to be criticised for gaining, for the first time, one of the best lamb deals we ever had with France?  Is he to be criticised for the drainage scheme that he initiated in Brussels and the last £150 million that he negotiated for restructuring of the west of Ireland?  Is he to be blamed for bringing about the complete eradication of TB and brucellosis and making the necessary funds available to do this work?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is now evident for the first time that as a result of the increased input into the <Col N="74" /> farmers' pocket, the Minister for Finance has to tackle, immediately, the very controversial item of farm tax.  If the Bill was delayed going through the House it was delayed by some of Senator McCartin's own friends here. We must not criticise the Minister for the delay.</P>
    <P>Were it not for the change of Government we would have a disaster in the agricultural sphere.  I could not see the synchronisation of An Foras Talúntais with the Department of Agriculture and the civil service.  They would be devoured in there; they would be dictated to in there and, eventually, they would be eliminated completely from the chore that they were given way back in 1958.  I think their term of reference was that of research, and research is a very specialised field and every facet of it must be done in an institution where you have available to you all the necessary equipment, both the land basis and the variation of size.  It is because of the variation of size that you have the rotation of the various An Foras Talúntais institutes around the country.  I do not think there is any reason to believe that this could be done effectively if there were an amalgamation with the Department of Agriculture.  I do not think it would work.  It was a good job that the Minister came in, in the dying minutes, to ensure that that did not happen and to bring about this Bill to give specific autonomy to An Foras Talúntais, who are doing a good job.</P>
    <P>Senator Butler referred to the information not being made available.  For every research facet they implement, they give a report to the Government and to the Department which, in turn, is used down the country, down to the most remote place.  The advisers, to date, have members of An Foras Talúntais at various seminars and EEC courses throughout the length and breadth of this country and they give a worthwhile service.  Only quite recently, I had the pleasure to chair a dairy seminar in Westport where we had two of the Moorepark people speaking on dairy equipment.  It was organised by the Committees of Agriculture, was very informative, and, indeed, a very worthwhile seminar.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="75" /> While I disagree with the criticism by Senator McCartin of the Minister, I do agree with him in regard to the creation of additional agricultural advisers.  In Mayo, the ratio is well over 450 farmers per adviser and, in my view, that should be in the region of something like 200 to 250 per adviser.  The implementation of the farm modernisation scheme does require a lot of clerical work and I would appeal to the Minister, in view of the additional clerical work under the farm modernisation scheme to appoint and create more posts within the various committees of agriculture.  That is something that we would welcome very much in Mayo.</P>
    <P>I would not like to see the devolution of the committees of agriculture, to any great extent.  The farming organisations are critical that they had not fair representations on the committees of agriculture in the past, but the people who elected their nominees&mdash;and I want to say that this came right across the board, politically&mdash;were people who were elected and got a mandate from the people to do this election.  In the event of a county councillor not going on a committee of agriculture himself, he was the person who nominated a particular individual. That particular individual often-times was a member of a farming organisation, but was not there officially nominated by that farming organisation. There was nothing wrong with that; they gave a worthwhile service and were the local watchdogs over the Department's activities and the administration of their schemes.  They were of an educational value and did some very useful work and I would not welcome at the moment any devolution of the existing committees that we have.</P>
    <P>I want to compliment the Minister on the farm modernisation scheme and the modification of it.  It is something that we, in Mayo, did not agree to at first and it was really under duress that we accepted it in the final analysis.  We would, otherwise, have denied some of the farming community of Mayo the opportunity to avail of the granted assistance that may be forthcoming from the Department for out-offices and for various <Col N="76" /> other farm developments.</P>
    <P>It is very interesting that it took these bodies that Senator West quoted from, since the change of Government, to produce documents that considered the amalgamation of both the institute and the Department of Agriculture.  This is the first time the IFA document was mentioned and I just wonder is it coincidental. Why is it that it is at this particular time the three quotations mentioned by Senator Butler should be made?  They may be coincidental, but I doubt it very much.  I do not want to evaluate as between either doctor, whether it be Dr. Cowhig or Dr. Walsh. I do not think I am in a position to do that, but I feel that it is necessary that there be an autonomous body.  I would agree with Senator West when he said that more capital was needed for the farm apprenticeship body.</P>
    <P>I want to compliment the universities on the worthwhile contribution they have made to An Foras Talúntais in research work over the years.</P>
    <P>I wish the Bill every success.  I hope it goes through as quickly as possible.  I have no doubt that there will be more co-operation in the future, under the new board, than in the past.  Co-operation is necessary between the Department officials, Civil Service and An Foras Talúntais.  That co-operation must be brought about and in the final analysis, only good can come from dedication and co-operation between the two bodies.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to have the opportunity of speaking on this Bill.  I very much regret that the concept of development or re-vamping or re-organisation in this sphere of agricultural education has been held up, unnecessarily, for the past two years. Nevertheless, at this stage we should hope to have it speedily implemented and passed into law.  Perhaps we tend to take agricultural education for granted. Having regard to the value and the importance of the agricultural industry to our economy, we ought certainly to devote greater resources to agricultural education, not just to the education of young farmers, whether they be male or female, but also to the education of farm <Col N="77" /> workers.  This is important because of the cost of agricultural machinery.  In the interests of the national economy there should be specialist training schemes for farm operatives.  The concept of farm labour is outdated.  These people are in the technician class now and we should provide release courses for them.  Under the development directives tremendous progress has been made.  I hope that this Bill will be given a speedy passage as it is badly needed.  I regret that there was an initial delay and I wish the Minister success.</P>
      <P>I am not too clear what the Minister intends to do about the transfer of the assets of the existing structures.  Will the costs be transferred?  Perhaps he might clarify the position in his reply.  By next autumn I hope a definite effort will have been made to improve the facilities available to the farming community through the county committees.  Instruction should be more widely available, especially instruction in farm accounts. The multiplicity of new taxes that the Government have levied so savagely and so fast on the farming community this year will cause confusion, especially among the older members.  I hope it will be possible for the Department of Agriculture and the advisory services to meet this challenge and to assist the farming community to make a fast transition so that they will be able to keep accounts that will be fair to themselves. We should continue to develop agriculture.  Even though agriculture has made considerable progress over the last five or six years as an industry it is still grossly under-financed.  In many respects we lack the facilities of the farmers with whom we compete in the lucrative European markets.  In this respect we should note and welcome the recent findings of the European Court in the Miaja case.  It opens up a new area which has nothing to do with agricultural education but it should give the farming community encouragement to face the future with greater confidence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In determining and providing for the costs of re-vamped agricultural education I hope the Minister and the Department have regard to the scarcity of <Col N="78" /> places in residential colleges.  Students who opt for an agricultural education get unfair treatment in comparison with other students.  I hope the Bill makes more generous provision in this regard. There is room for a greater number of short intensive courses in specific farm husbandries.  It ought to be possible for farmers to fit in intensive courses and for farm operatives to be released for specific courses.  These could be looked upon as an extension of the farm apprentice scheme.</P>
    <P>In the early sixties I remember cosponsoring with Professor Quinlan a Bill which was the forerunner of the legislation for the Farm Apprenticeship Board. When we were drafting that Bill our thoughts never came to fruition.  Sufficient thought has not been given to this aspect of agriculture.  At that time we thought that the Land Commission could have played a more dynamic role. In 1979, with the high cost of agricultural land and the cost of setting up a young person in farming as a career, the farm apprenticeship legislation should be looked at again.  That idea, which is such an excellent one, must surely be of value to the industry. In the area of land re-organisation or reform, a futuristic farm apprenticeship scheme should be of great benefit.  I hope the Government will look at this aspect of the problem.</P>
    <P>I would prefer to have the original Bill enacted and perhaps amended later.  One could make many criticisms of this Bill but I would prefer to see this Bill being given a speedy passage.  In a year or so we shall know whether the various reorganisations have improved the service. We will have an opportunity at that stage of reconsidering the matter.  We should welcome the Bill and give it a speedy passage in order to progress and meet the demands of the present.  I wish the Minister luck with this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnEllis" hpid="Mr. Ellis Mr. Ellis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ellis</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill.  It was necessary for the Minister to introduce amending legislation following the 1977 Act.  Agricultural advice and education and research should be separate.  As the liaison officer, it is the job of the agricultural adviser to help farmers to <Col N="79" /> advance.  If advice and research had been merged, as proposed in the 1977 Bill, one or the other would have been smothered.</P>
      <P>I should like to pay tribute to the work of An Foras Talúntais.  Since their establishment in the sixties they have done great work in different parts of the country.  I know this from my own experience in Leitrim.  Their work at the farm in Ballinamore has proved to the farmers from that area that they can become viable and progressive.  Many of them have copied the example given by An Foras Talúntais.</P>
      <P>Senator McCartin referred to the delay in bringing in a policy such as this. He also referred to the late sixties when Deputy Blaney was Minister for Agriculture.  The main opportunities for agriculture came when we joined the EEC in 1973.  Prior to that, farm incomes were very small.  When Deputy Clinton was Minister it took him from February 1973 until April 1977 to do what he said he would do in relation to agriculture.  His idea of merging the services was not in the best interests of the farmers.</P>
      <P>With regard to the advisory service, it is a pity that so much of the time of agricultural advisers is spent doing clerical work.  The Minister should recommend that the county committees of agriculture provide more clerical staff in order to enable agricultural advisers to spend more time doing practical work.</P>
      <P>It is important that the members of county committees have practical knowledge of and a general interest in farming.  People with no interest in and no knowledge of farming have been appointed to county committees by county councils.  This practice leaves farmers with little confidence in the county committees.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>More land should be made available to young farmers who are prepared to put into practice the knowledge that has been gained.  The Minister's next priority is the restructuring of the Land Commission. An Foras Talúntais have a number of impressive ideas in relation to land drainage and land reclamation and have <Col N="80" /> shown by their example that their ideas can help to provide a better future for our farmers.</P>
    <P>At present the farming community needs capital.  The ACC have done great work in this field.  The Minister understands the need for capital and knows that farmers have to reinvest their incomes in new machines and other projects. I sincerely hope that the farming community will continue to reinvest in agriculture.  The 25 per cent growth in agricultural output shows that the farmers have regained confidence after the slump and the losses which they suffered in 1974.</P>
    <P>I compliment the Minister on his interest in disease eradication.  Disease eradication has lagged behind, especially during the two years of the veterinary strike.  The status of our national herd could have been badly damaged by that strike.  Since the Minister introduced his new scheme, the national herd has been given a disease-free status.  I hope that the work in this field will be continued.</P>
    <P>This Bill provides for the research and advisory services to continue working as two separate bodies for the betterment of farming.  The amalgamation of both services would not have been in the interest of the farming community.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMGibbons" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Gibbons) James Gibbons">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Gibbons)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senators for their contributions to the debate and for the general constructive spirit in which the contributions were made.  Senators of different political allegiances could be pardoned for flavouring a few of their remarks with their allegiances because they did not affect the usefulness of the debate nor did they waste a great deal of time.  I thank them for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator McCartin, who opened the debate, made what I thought was a rather despondent speech.  His contribution and the contributions of other western Senators are welcome in that they reflect the views of an area with the most difficult agricultural problems, the problems of the smallness of holdings and the very pressing need for drainage. Senator McCartin mentioned that 50 per cent of farm holdings at present in County Leitrim are known as terminal <Col N="81" /> holdings.  All Senators and Deputies know that this is a fact and realise the implications of it.  For many decades there has been a pressing need to make some primary changes in the situation with regard to the condition of the soil in the West.  It is well that the EEC have recognised the dire necessity to give drainage in the West a special push.</P>
    <P>The type of advice which will be made available by An Chomhairle to farmers, especially in the more difficult areas, is a matter which will be determined in the future by the council of An Chomhairle Oiliúna Talmhaíochta.  I am glad, too, that Senator McCartin's last remark was that he did not wish to delay the House. Several Senators mentioned that there was an urgency to get on with the job. There has been a short delay in the genesis of the re-organisation of the advisory service.</P>
    <P>Let me recap slightly from memory. When I was Minister for Agriculture in the Fianna Fáil Government up to 1973, I had a White Paper in a very advanced state of preparation.  It was, in fact, the basis of my successor's White Paper.  It had introduced into it the amalgamation idea of An Foras and the advisory service. It was interesting to hear Senator West, who is a research worker, express an informed opinion.  I do not wish to denigrate the opinions of other Senators but we must all acknowledge that Senator West, coming from the field of research in the University, has a certain view of this which is not available to the rest of us.  This view is shared by a great many learned objective researchers.</P>
    <P>One of the most regrettable features of the NAA Bill in 1977 was its doomladen section 10 which, contrary to Senator Butler's assertion that An Foras would continue to retain its own identity, provided for the abolition of An Foras Talúntais.  That was a devastatingly negative provision in the NAA Bill.  Having regard to the extraordinary performance of AFT since they were established and their remarkable benefits to producers, the disestablishment of An Foras Talúntais to comply with some illconceived doctrinaire ideas on the advantages of a unified service, there is no great problem in getting over any difficulties <Col N="82" /> there may be about the transmission of information gleaned by the research workers.  It is vital to preserve the atmosphere in which these research workers operate and to preserve the situation which does not allow their research work to be interrupted by small tactical pressures which could divert them, possibly even permanently, from a research operation which might be spaced over several years at a time.  It is not necessary to dwell at great length on that paint as there was a great deal of discussion on it during the passage of the AnCOT Bill through the Dáil.  I have no doubt that retention of An Foras Talúntais in their present form was sensible.  It meant that the NAA Bill had to be restructured.  For the Senators' benefit I should like to say that practically all the other provisions in that Bill were in the White Paper which I had drafted in the Department of Agriculture.  It was altered during the interim period in the vital matter of the amalgamation of the two services.  In general, it remains more or less intact.</P>
    <P>Senator McCartin suggested that the funding of AFT was in the region of £3 million.  I should like to let him know that the provision for AFT is £8 million, which is a substantial increase on last year's provision of £7,354,000.</P>
    <P>One of the more important changes which has taken place caused some mystification to Senator Butler.  What I meant in my opening remarks was that we had a more satisfactory financial structure.  The more satisfactory financial structure derives from the grant, from the new power to borrow and the new power to use the endowment fund. This gives An Foras a more satisfactory situation.  If the £8 million provided by the Government and the funds derived from industry were to be diverted into the general fund of the old NAA organisation, it would be quite absurd to think that the research money would have retained its own identity within the organisation whose marvellous cohesion and co-operation has been boasted.  I am quite certain that that would not have happened.</P>
    <P>Senator Hyland spoke of the need for revision of the farm modernisation <Col N="83" /> scheme in order to deal with the unsatisfactory situation, mentioned by Senator O'Toole and others, which precludes a great many farmers in the west from being allocated development status.  I am expecting a development in the EEC on this matter.  It is not true to say that they are deprived of all grant assistance. The situation for transitional farmers, even as it is now, is a great deal better than it was before our access to the EEC.  I do accept&mdash;and it is generally acknowledged by Senator O'Toole's party&mdash;that it would be far better if a greater range of people could be embraced in the Farm Modernisation Scheme.  This is not strictly relevant to the An Chomhairle Oiliúna Talmhaíochta Bill, but it is a very important point and many Senators felt impelled to mention it because they were so acutely aware of its importance.</P>
    <P>Senator Hyland spoke of the desirability, as did Senator O'Toole and Senator Ellis, of the committees of agriculture carrying out a development role.  They have already a development assignment in existing legislation.  I believe that the council of the Comhairle Oiliúna Talmhaíochta will assign them the task of assisting in farm development. It is well for us all to remember, especially Members of this House, that at this moment there is more activity going on in the matter of land improvement and the erection of farm buildings than ever before in this country.  That is why there is very acute pressure on the Department of Agriculture officials, among others, and the advisory services in the counties, to deal with the applications coming to the Department of Agriculture.</P>
    <P>There was a question in the other House last week about the applications in County Mayo.  Speaking from recollection&mdash;I cannot say with certitude but it will be in the Official Report&mdash;there must have been a tenfold increase on last year.  A lot of this would arise from applications for the advantages of the drainage scheme, and that is what it is meant to do.  We want to get these applications; we may have some difficulty <Col N="84" /> but we will get extra staff to deal with them.  It is good to know that any technical difficulty we encounter in that regard originates from the degree of activity there is at present.</P>
    <P>I am laying no special claim to personal applause in this matter.  The very fact of our membership of the EEC, our participation in the common agricultural policy, the special provisions for disadvantaged areas that have been made for us, especially in the west of Ireland and in certain other areas as well, all create this situation and relieve us from the situation in which we found ourselves up to 1973.  It is so obvious that I can never understand people who criticise our membership of the EEC.  There are, and will continue to be, difficulties.  It is unreasonable carping to say that aids given under the different schemes in the Common Agricultural Policy are in some way defective.  Whether they are or not, there is more farm development going on now than ever before.</P>
    <P>The rate of development has been less in Connacht than in other areas in the country.  For that reason Connacht deserves to get more attention, and it is getting it in the matter of drainage and infrastructural development in the new schemes being introduced.</P>
    <P>On the main issue of the differences between the Comhairle Oiliúna Talmhaíochta Bill and its predecessor, the National Agricultural Authority Bill, Senators have on the whole taken the view that the retention of An Foras Talúntais as a separate parallel organisation for research is the better course.  It is worth the industry's while to await the passage of this Bill to secure that point.</P>
    <P>It is well for us all to remember that the change in Irish agriculture at present is very large.  The rate of change is also quite dramatic.  I would expect that we would have to adapt quickly techniques that may seem satisfactory at present, and I detect a strange absence of recognition of the rapidly changing scene in Senator McCartin's contribution. He did not envisage the dramatic shaping of the advisory service that we have seen begun before our eyes independently by some big co-operatives. It is a very welcome development.  I <Col N="85" /> would think that we want a great deal more specialist advisory work in other fields of production.</P>
    <P>Senator McCartin has pioneered very notable work in regard to pigs in County Leitrim.  In meat production and animal production, pasture management, in all these fields there is a great need for specialist advice and the incorporation of the assistance of co-operative societies in the securing of this better service and the determination of the course of advisory work on the basis of the rapidly changing scene in agriculture.  I do not share Senator McCartin's faint feeling of despondency.  There are certainly in Senator McCartin's, Senator O'Toole's and Senator Ellis's province quite acute problems and no amount of soft talk will make those very difficult problems go.  There is only one thing will make them go: hard work and money. Fortunately we have managed to provide a little of both, in fact, a great deal of money in the next ten years.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask the Minister to elucidate section 22.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This matter should be raised on Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>If you would not mind, we have plenty of time now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMGibbons" hpid="Mr. Gibbons Mr. Gibbons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gibbons</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the provision which refers to the change in the ability <Col N="86" /> of An Foras Talúntais to use the endowment fund and to borrow.  That will give far greater flexibility to An Foras Talúntais. Senator McDonald also asked a question relating to property.  The provisions in this Bill are almost precisely the same as the provisions in its predecessor and will involve the passage to AnCOT of the agricultural schools and the committees of agriculture offices, with compensation in the counties for any local input there has been, just as in the other Bill.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 16 May 1979.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamRyan" hpid="Mr. W. Ryan Mr. W. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We had ordered No. 4, but I regret to say that the Minister is not available and, therefore, we have no further business for this evening.  I suggest that we adjourn until Wednesday, 16 May.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>Do we take it that No. 4 on today's Order Paper will be coming up on Wednesday, 16 May?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamRyan" hpid="Mr. W. Ryan Mr. W. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We hope to take it then.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 7.15 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 16 May 1979.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>