<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="14" Month="Feb" Year="1979" Vol="91" No="1" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 14 Feabhra 1979" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 14 February 1979" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Appointment of" RHead="Minister of State">
    <Title>Appointment of Minister of State.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá orm a chur in iúl don Teach go bhfuarthas litir dar dáta 19 Nollaig, 1978 ó Rúnaí an Rialtais á rá go raibh an Teachta Dáithí Mac Aindriú, Aire Stáit ag an Roinn Gnóthaí Eachtracha, ceaptha chun oifig Aire Stáit ag an Roinn Dlí agus Cirt.</P>
      <P>Tá treoracha tugtha agam cóip den litir sin a leagan amach <i>in extenso</i> ar an ngnáthmhodh i gCín Lae an Tí.  De dhroim an chraolta seo, clófar í freisin i dTuairisc Oifigiúil na nDíospóireachtaí.</P>
      <P>I have to inform the House that a letter dated 19 December 1978 has been received from the Secretary to the Government stating that Deputy David Andrews, Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs, had been appointed to the Office of Minister of State at the Department of Justice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have given directions to have a copy of the letter referred to set out <i>in extenso</i> in the usual manner in the Journal of the <Col N="2" /> House.  Consequent on this announcement, it will also be printed in the Official Report of the Debates.</P>
    <P>19 Nollaig, 1978.</P>
    <P>Cléireach an tSeanaid</P>
    <P>Tá orm a chur in iúl duit go ndearna an Rialtas inniu, ar ainmniú an Taoisigh agus i bhfeidhmiú na cumhachta a thugtar dóibh le halt 1 (1) den Acht Airí agus Rúnaithe (Leasú) (Uimh. 2), 1977,</P>
    <P Just="Center">Dáithi Mac Aindriú, T.D.</P>
    <P Just="Center">(David Andrews, T.D.).</P>
    <P>Aire Stáit ag an Roinn Gnóthaí Eachtracha, a cheapadh chun oifig Aire Stáit ag an Roinn Dlí agus Cirt, le héifeacht ón 1 Eanáir 1979.</P>
    <P>D. Ó Súilleabháin,</P>
    <P>Rúnaí an Rialtais.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - The Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (Charter and" RHead="Letters Patent Amendment) Bill, 1978: Report from the Examiner of Private Bills">
    <Title>Private Business. - The Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (Charter and Letters Patent Amendment) Bill, 1978: Report from the Examiner of Private Bills.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="3" /> Report from the Examiner of Private Bills that in the case of the application for leave to introduce the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (Charter and Letters Patent Amendment) Bill, 1978, the Standing Orders have been complied with.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Tairgim:</P>
      <P>Go leagfar an Tuarascáil faoi bhráid an tSeanaid:</P>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That the Report be laid before the Seanad.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Meastar an Bille a bheith léite an Chéad Uair anois.  (B.O. 62).</P>
      <P>The Bill is now deemed to be read the First Time.  (S.O. 62).</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. -" RHead="Order of Business">
    <Title>Private Business. - Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6 in that order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasWhitaker" hpid="Dr. Whitaker Dr. Whitaker">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Whitaker</NameTxt>
      <P>Ar Riar na hOibre, a Chathaoirligh, ba mhaith liom ceist a chur.  Ba mhaith liom a fhiafraí den tSeanadóir Ó Riain an bhfuil rún ag an Rialtas díospóireacht a thosnú sa Teach seo faoin Pháipéar Bán ar fhorbairt náisiúnta a foilsíodh le gairid, the Programme for National Development, 1978-81.  Tá díospóireacht ar siúl faoi cheana sa Dáil agus is íonadh liom nach bhfuil fiú tagairt dó ar chlár an Tigh seo go fóill.  Creidim go mba é leas an daonfhlathais é cúrsaí móra polasaí a chur faoi chaibidil i dTeach seo an Oireachtais chomh maith agus é dhéanamh sula dtagann meirg orthu.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Rachaidh me i gcomhairle leis an Aire agus beidh scéal agam don Seanadóir ag an gcéad cruinniú eile.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="4" /> Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Fisheries" RHead="Bill, 1979: First Stage">
    <Title>Private Business. - Fisheries Bill, 1979: First Stage.</Title>
    <P>Leave granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to establish a body to be known as the Central Fisheries Board and to define its functions, to enable regional fisheries boards to be established and to define their functions, to dissolve Iontaobhas Iascaigh Intíre Ioncorportha (The Inland Fisheries Trust Incorporated) and certain boards of conservators established by the Fisheries (Consolidation) Act, 1959, to provide for other matters connected with the foregoing and otherwise to amend and extend the Fisheries Acts, 1959 to 1978.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the Second Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest Wednesday week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the Government are anxious to take the Second Stage next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a weighty Bill. However, we can order it for next week.</P>
      <P>Second Stage ordered for Wednesday, 21 February 1979.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Report of Joint Committee on the" RHead="Secondary Legislation of the European Communities: Motion">
    <Title>Private Business. - Report of Joint Committee on the Secondary Legislation of the European Communities: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That, in the period ending 31 December 1979, notwithstanding anything contained in Standing Orders and unless the Seanad shall otherwise order, if the Joint Committee on the Secondary Legislation of the European Communities lays before the Seanad a report containing a request for a debate thereon in the Seanad, one hour and a half shall be set aside for debate on a motion.  That the Seanad take note of such report, on the first day on which the Seanad shall sit after</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="5" /> (a)  six clear days have elapsed since the report was laid before the Seanad, and</P>
    <P>(b)  due notice of the motion has been received by the Clerk from a Member nominated by the Joint Committee.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of the Labour group I should like to thank the Leader of the House for moving this motion. When there is a suggestion from the Joint Committee on the Secondary Legislation of the European Communities that a report is important enough to be debated in this House we are very pleased that time will once more be afforded to it by the House.  I should like to thank the Leader of the House and I welcome the fact that this motion is being tabled and that the same procedure will apply for this year.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Defence (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1978: Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Private Business. - Defence (Amendment) Bill, 1978: Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. Molloy) Robert Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. Molloy)</NameTxt>
      <P>The main purpose of the Bill is to make provision in the Defence Acts for the commissioned Army rank of brigadier-general, which rank is not provided for at present.  On the seniority scale the new rank would come between the ranks of colonel and major-general.  The Bill also provides that the existing naval rank of commodore shall correspond to the new Army rank of brigadier-general and for the creation of a new naval rank of rearadmiral corresponding to the existing Army rank of major-general.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As to my purpose in introducing the Bill at this time, I have had the rank structure at senior level in the Defence Forces under examination recently and I have found that certain changes are necessary.  Arising from this examination, Senators will be aware that the ranks of the three principal military offices, namely chief of staff, adjutant-general and quartermaster-general, have already been upgraded&mdash;from major-general <Col N="6" /> to lieutenant-general in the case of the chief of staff and from colonel to major-general in the case of the adjutant-general and quartermaster-general.</P>
    <P>It is also my intention that the ranks for the appointments of assistant chief of staff and officers commanding commands will be upgraded from the present rank of colonel to brigadier-general. These upgradings, together with those already effected to which I have referred, will, having regard to the relative levels of responsibility, result in a more rational rank structure at senior level in the Defence Forces and will, in particular, rectify the anomalous situation hitherto existing in which officers in the rank of colonel held appointments at three different levels of responsibility. The situation in this regard has been that a brigade commander reported to an officer commanding a command who, in turn, was subject to controls exercised by the adjutant-general and quartermaster-general.  The rank of all those appointments was colonel until the recent upgrading of the appointments of adjutant-general and quartermaster-general. The provisions of this Bill will enable me to complete the task in relation to the appointments of officers commanding commands and the assistant chief of staff.  Officers commanding commands are, of course, also subject to directions issued by the chief of staff but, in that case, the rank for the appointment of chief of staff was normally higher than colonel.</P>
    <P>Precedence of rank is a very important factor in the Defence Forces.  The situation is, of course, unique having regard to the fact that members of the Defence Forces are subject to a code of military law, the operation of which depends on a system of command, authority and discipline.  The upgradings envisaged reflect this situation and are regarded as essential in the circumstances.</P>
    <P>The new rank structure will provide a better promotion progression for military officers.  It will also provide a pool of officers of general rank from which can be drawn officers for certain senior appointments with United Nations Forces.  Under the present structure, <Col N="7" /> any such officer has to be promoted exceptionally if he is to enjoy the rank appropriate to the appointment. I trust that the purpose of the Bill is clear to Senators and I commend it to the Seanad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of this party I welcome the Bill, because as the Minister has indicated, it clears up certain rank anomalies in the Defence Forces.  Particularly as members of the Defence Forces are serving abroad more frequently, it is important that the ranks in our forces would correspond, possibly not exactly but fairly accurately, with the ranks of the other forces which might be within the United Nations Force.</P>
      <P>There seems to me to be one anomaly still, but I do not know that it can be resolved.  The Minister might help us when he is replying.  It arises in the case of a brigade commander.  I presume the origin of the title brigadier-general is that it refers to the officer who is commanding a brigade.  In our Army structure we have brigades usually under the command of a colonel who ranks below the colonel commanding the command within which the brigade is situated.  We will have the commander of brigades holding the rank of colonel and being junior to the brigadier-general who will be commanding the particular command. It seems to be slightly anomalous but, no doubt, there is a good explanation for it.  I am sure it is not an anomaly. If it is an anomaly, or has the characteristics of an anomaly, the Minister would have used this Bill to cure that one as well.  That is the only question I have to raise on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill is generally welcome because, as the Minister said, it provides a pool of officers of general rank for promotions internally and to enable appointments within the United Nations to be filled. Any measure such as this is good for the morale of the Defence Forces.  It is important that that morale be kept high. While one could say the matters dealt with in this Bill are peripheral to the question of morale, nevertheless they are a factor.  Undoubtedly, the most significant <Col N="8" /> matter that touches morale is for members of the Defence Forces to be aware that the Government and Legislature are interested in them, and interested in the well-being and efficiency of the force.</P>
    <P>The morale of the Defence Forces was brought to a very high pitch some years ago by the intensive recruiting drive carried out by the Minister's predecessor, Deputy Donegan, and by his insistence that the equipment, the clothing and transport of the Army should be improved appropriately.  A considerable amount of money was spent in doing that.  In addition, the living quarters were improved at many Army installations and the new barracks in Monaghan is a showpiece.  The lift the Army got from that development should be maintained.  I am glad to note the Minister has commenced recruiting again.</P>
    <P>Speaking on a Bill concerning officer rank, I would urge the Minister to ensure that the system of making cadetships available to non-commissioned officers is persisted in and used to the widest degree possible.  We have to be careful about the quality of the people coming into the Army and ensure that there are promotional outlets available to the very top.  It is a comparatively new development to provide cadetships for non-commissioned officers but it is a good development.  It should be expanded.  I appreciate that the question of recruiting cadets will also have to continue but the ambition should be that the proportion of recruiting cadets and promoting cadets should be brought into line with each other.  This could be done without any danger to the quality of the officers in the Army because the Minister knows and, coming from a garrison town, I know that there is a very high quality of young men joining the Army at all levels today.  There are many non-commissioned officers who are well fit to be promoted to commissioned ranks and I would urge that on the Minister.</P>
    <P>I also urge him to keep in mind and listen to the soldier's traditional prerogative of the &ldquo;crib&rdquo; because, very often, these cribs, as they are called in Army language, are indicative of strong feelings within the Army.  Very often <Col N="9" /> they concern extra payments for extra duties.  Some time ago extra payments for non-Border duties were provided for. These should be kept under review and they should be dealt with as generously as possible.  The Army are always available.  There is never any question of industrial disputes affecting the Army. There is a great tradition of service to the nation within the Army.  The State, through the Government, should recognise that tradition and ensure that, in all their dealings with the members of the Defence Forces, generosity will be the keynote.  I welcome the Bill and I hope the new promotions will work out satisfactorily.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to add my voice to that of Senator Cooney in support of the Bill.  The Minister said the new rank structure will provide a better promotion progression for military officers. In the Defence Forces far more than just officers are concerned.  There is also the question of privates and NCOs. The whole question of promotional opportunities within the Defence Forces is an important one.  When it comes to the promotion of senior officers, which will be by way of appointment and not promotion, or even by way of promotion, I hope the promotional opportunities will be fair and reasonable.  In the not too distant past many factors were brought to light in relation to unfair opportunities for personnel, particularly in the senior ranks.  I do not want to dwell on that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The present Minister and the previous Minister, Deputy Donegan, did an immense amount of work to improve the situation within the Defence Forces. While some mistakes were made by the previous Minister&mdash;and I had many runins with him from time to time&mdash;he made very valuable contributions to the Army and made the service a better place for many soldiers.  There are to be changes in the structure of authority. Changes in authority sometimes mean substantial changes in organisation. Changes in organisation may mean that there will be changes in the role of the Defence Forces.  Sometimes one follows the other.  If there are to be changes in the role of the Defence Forces because <Col N="10" /> of changes in authority and organisation, then we are moving into a new situation.  Very often these changes have to take place before role changes take place.  Will the Minister indicate if any change in role is anticipated for the Defence Forces?</P>
    <P>I appreciate the problems and difficulties the Minister has at the moment in relation to the senior officer rank and the officer rank of the Defence Forces where problems can arise in relation to promotional opportunities.  In the Defence Forces we should have a positive career structure so that careers could be planned over the next ten, 15 or 20 years.  There should be a periodic factual assessment of officers to ensure that officers with potential would not be denied the opportunity of using the educational facilities that are available. If a man is a bad lieutenant he becomes a bad captain, a bad colonel and a bad major general or chief of staff or whatever rank he may rise to.  There should be an assessment at an early stage so that a man can equip himself for the life for which he is ideally fitted.</P>
    <P>Some people have been denied a promotional opportunity on assessment at a very late stage in their careers.  That is wrong.  The assessment must be made at an early stage so that a person can adapt himself to civilian life.  Having given his allegiance to the nation he should be able to avail of the opportunities, educational and otherwise, to equip himself for life outside the Army. There should be greater emphasis on the educational aspect for officers, NCOs and men in the technical field.  The soldier of tomorrow will be a technician, a technocrat.  The courses given in general are not the type of courses which will be of the greatest benefit to the Defence Forces.  In Galway University and elsewhere there are great opportunities for personnel but they must be directed in such a way that they will give the best and most beneficial service to the nation and to the Army.  The career structure must be a positive career structure. Officers must know at an early stage what their assessment is and whether they can attain what they have set their sights on, or whether they will be diverted into a <i>cul-de-sac</i> and have no <Col N="11" /> educational opportunities.  It is only right that people with ability and understanding and, indeed, people who are prepared to study and to compete, irrespective of their length of service, should be able to avail of educational opportunities.  I believe length of service is a factor in promotion.  We should give all the opportunities and all the information to the personnel so that they can equip themselves fully and effectively.</P>
    <P>People in the upper limits of the service are mainly well insulated personnel in the senior officer rank.  In many ways the senior officer rank in this Army, and indeed other armies, is a club and people operate in a small circle.  The Minister for Defence has enormous difficulties in that he is caught between the senior officers, or the Army commander on the one side, and the civil service on the other.  Few other Ministers are in the same difficult situation the Minister for Defence finds himself in.</P>
    <P>We must start at the other end of the ladder also and consider the privates.  At the moment many young men are being asked to joint the Defence Forces in the recruitment campaign.  I support the recruitment campaign and consider service in the Defence Forces is well worth while.  Again there must be a comprehensive career structure at that level because they too need to keep abreast of technical developments and modern requirements. They will be the technicians of the future, the military technicians. There are great opportunities but there will have to be changes in the basic situation at the lower level.  Many young men lay their lives on the line when they decide to become members of the Defence Forces.  What is the situation at the moment?  Many young men whose fathers and other relatives have served in the Defence Forces are offering themselves for service.  On too many occasions in the past after six or eight weeks in the barracks they were told they could go home, that they were not finally approved.  This is a vicious type of situation.  A young man tells his friends and parents he has joined the Defence Forces and, after six or eight weeks in the barracks, he is sent home <Col N="12" /> for some trivial conflict with the law. These are young men of 16, 17 or 18 years of age with no great police record. If a person breaks the military law, or is not prepared to conform to it, then the military assessment must be made and whatever action is necessary taken, whether it is a discharge or otherwise. Far too often because they were guilty of firing snowballs at a night watchman, or some silly offence such as that, people have been not fully approved and sent home.  This is a very serious situation. People are entitled to equal opportunities under our Constitution.  I fail to see how a young man with no record has been discharged and denied the opportunity&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is going a little wide of what is relevant to this Bill and I would like him to get back to what is in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>A soldier is a solider and if we are dealing with a soldier, whether he is a major-general, a lieutenant-colonel or a private soldier, he is a soldier as far as I am concerned. One cannot pigeonhole any aspect of defence because every aspect of defence has a bearing on the other.  The man at the bottom is the person who will have to obey the orders and fit in with the changes.  Any change within the structure of the Defence Forces is an overall change and not just something that affects the private soldier only.  The private soldier I am speaking about may some day be the man who will fill a senior position.  There were private soldiers who rose up through the ranks and attained very high positions in the Defence Forces&mdash;up to the rank of colonel and, indeed, other senior ranks.  I cannot see that I am deviating from the whole question of the changes that are taking place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill deals only with officer rank, I have allowed the Senator to refer to other ranks but he should now return to the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>The question of promotional opportunities from the private to the officer rank is very wide-ranging. I want to deal with promotional <Col N="13" /> opportunities from the ranks to the officer status.  This is important.  During a recruitment period it is necessary and desirable to say something about the other people who will also be affected.</P>
      <P>I take the Cathaoirleach's point and I will not dwell on the matter.  I should, however, like to complete what I was saying as it may be taken out of context. When we have a recruitment campaign we must be positive about the people we take into the Defence Forces.  They should be taken in and fully assessed. They should not be assessed by somebody else outside the Defence Forces.  If they are to be subject to military law and military promotional opportunities, that is a matter for the Defence Forces.</P>
      <P>There is one case which I should like to refer to.  A young man who spent six weeks in the Curragh was sent home as being not fully approved.  I wrote to the Minister in connection with this.  Some time after I met the young man in the House and I said I was very sorry the Minister did not see his way to giving him the opportunity to serve the nation. I told him I would try again.  He then told me he was working in the Department of Agriculture.  He was good enough to work in a Department of State but he was not good enough to serve the nation as a private soldier. There is something wrong if a young man can be rejected by the Army on one hand and taken into a Department on the other.  If his crime was not grave enough to deny him that opportunity, then it was not grave enough to deprive him of the opportunity of serving the nation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is disregarding the ruling already given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>To get back to the question of the officer rank.  If this is the total increased promotional opportunity then it falls short of what I would expect.  I would ask the Minister to give a clear indication that promotional opportunities in the senior officer rank are not the only promotional opportunities that will be developed within the armed services so that other people will have the opportunities <Col N="14" /> to display their skills and to get the merit and consideration to which they are entitled.  I find it hard to differentiate between an NCO, an officer or a man.  These senior officers are soldiers and so are the other ranks.  When we refer to the Army, we refer to soldiers. We do not pick out a man of very high rank and refer to him all the time.  He is part of a situation.  Our people have given service on Border duties and in foreign service and have done credit to this nation over a period; some of them are senior officers now.  It is sad that on occasions criticism was levelled against senior officers for accidents in the past; for their assessment of the situation on the facts relating to it.  Armchair generals are removed from the situation but are there to condemn them.  Factual assessment at all levels, times and places is desirable and necessary.</P>
      <P>The Minister has the manoeuvrability; he can appoint an officer who will look at the situation in relation to the NCOs and men, to the present defects to the additional opportunities and upgrading in relation to the present technological age.  I fully agree with the statements already made regarding the necessary and desirable opportunity to make the Army better and more effective.  I hope there will be a change in emphasis in many directions; a change in military outlook.  Basically, military outlook has not changed a lot since the forties.  While equipment has been updated and personnel have been changed to meet this change, the general thinking in relation to military affairs has not changed a whole lot.  I compliment the Minister on the recent equipment for the Defence Forces, a suitable type of personnel carrier and particularly equipment that meets the needs and requirements of the force.  As a result of such developments, we shall ensure that the Air Corps and other branches of the Defence Forces are properly equipped and that we shall have the type of effective force that everyone considers necessary and desirable.</P>
      <P>I feel that cavalry units are the answer to many of the problems because of the nature of our country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Sorry, Senator, if <Col N="15" /> you wish to discuss these things on a broader issue you will have to do so by way of a motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that the Minister might with the opportunity that is now available to him, direct somebody's attention to certain aspects of channelling personnel.  I assume that the personnel who are appointed will be in a position to examine the new and developing situations that arise in an ever-changing world.  I hope one of the senior officers, whose promotional opportunities will be increased, will look at the situation in relation to the discharge of personnel where there have been many grave defects over a long number of years.  The Minister will have to devote some time and energy to ensuring that the problems of the past will be rectified.</P>
      <P>There are very many aspects in relation to senior officers down along the line about which I would like to speak but it appears that we will not have the opportunity of a wide-ranging debate here, irrespective of the other important matters upon which Members must voice their opinion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry to have to remind the Senator that that is quite true.  The scope of this Bill is very limited and the Chair has already ruled to that effect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister clarify the situation in regard to the exact changes in structure and role that will take place and how personnel will be allocated new duties?  If we had this information we could then be in a position fully and effectively to discuss the spinoff situation in relation to promotional opportunities.  However, I will not detain the House any longer.  There is much more that needs to be said in relation to the Army as a whole.  I would like to wish the Minister well.  I understand his difficulties and his problems, being caught between two sections, unlike other Ministers.  Work that should have been done over the years has not been done, and for that reason a heavy load <Col N="16" /> rests on his shoulders.  Again I would like to compliment the people who have served this nation wisely and well over the years and have given loyal service both here and abroad, without question.</P>
      <P>I wish the Minister well in this piece of legislation.  I hope those who have the good fortune to get promotion will be the best men for the jobs and that they will meet the ever-changing situation in the ever-changing world in which the military service operates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>I also support very much what Senators Cooney and Dowling have said.  I welcome this Bill.  We should be grateful to Senator Dowling, even though he may have circumvented the rules of procedure somewhat because there is no doubt that he has personal knowledge of the Defence Forces, which is a very valuable thing.  I think his speech was an excellent contribution to the debate.  I feel that all the Members of the House will be proud of the record of our Defence Forces.  Our Army is about 50 years old.  After 1921 we had to build it from scratch, develop our own traditions and this was successfully done.  We can be very proud of the Army's role, to which the Minister has referred, particularly that of service with the United Nations Forces.  There may be a number of different reasons for the new rank structure but the Minister mentioned that:</P>
      <P>The new rank structure will provide a better promotion progression for military officers.  It will also provide a pool of officers of general rank from which can be drawn officers for certain senior appointments with United Nations forces.  Under the present structure, any such officer has to be promoted exceptionally if he is to enjoy the rank appropriate to the appointment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome that and seeing that we have established this tradition of service in the United Nations, of which we should be very proud, the change along these lines is to be supported.  The fact that we have been able to do this depended on our building up, maintaining and defending our neutrality.  Otherwise we could not be invited by the United Nations to <Col N="17" /> provide forces in trouble spots around the world.  That is something which we should be proud of and which we, in the Houses of the Oireachtas, should always strive to maintain.  I welcome the efforts made by the Minister and by his predecessors to re-equip the Army and bring their equipment up to the most modern standards.</P>
    <P>I should like at the same time to sound a note of warning because I think the Minister will be under pressure to make structural changes in our Defence Forces set-up for other reasons than those which would appear here.  I do not think that in this case this applies but it is something that we must bear in mind when we look at any structural changes in the set-up of our Defence Forces. Ultimately the Parliament and the Government are responsible for the structure of the Defence Forces.  The warning I should like to sound is that there is no question but that we are going to be under pressure to contribute to the defence of Europe as the Economic Community becomes more integrated. Our neutrality should come before everything and it is something we must&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator, that is slightly irrelevant as far as the Bill is concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West.</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not if it happens that changes are to be made because of the pressure from the European Economic Community.  In this case changes are not being made because of pressure from the European Economic Community.  But I think we will be under pressure to make alterations in the structure of our Defence Forces on those grounds. I do not think this Bill involves that but it is a danger and it is something of which the House should be aware.  I am not going to dwell on this point but it is important that, when we are considering a Bill which concerns the Defence Forces and any changes of structure, we should examine the reasons why the changes are made.  What worries me is that later on the Minister or perhaps his successor, may be under a great deal of pressure.  I think we should maintain our neutrality and any sign of that slipping would be very serious.  I regret to say <Col N="18" /> that two recent votes in the United Nations, or one, in the United Nations&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Sorry, but there will be other opportunities for the Senator to raise all these matters but certainly not on this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>I am going to move away from that but I would like to say that there have been signs recently that our neutrality is being allowed to slip.  I hope the Government will not allow this.  It is up to the Government to maintain this position of neutrality.</P>
      <P>I feel that the modernising of our forces, both in regard to equipment and to the structure of the ranks and the creation of a new rank, is to be welcomed.  We must give our forces the maximum support.  We must ensure, as Senators Cooney and Dowling have already said, that their conditions are the best.  I know from my own experience that the forces are getting top quality recruits and are providing them with extremely valuable training.  For some of them this is not a permanent training but the people we are talking about are permanent career soldiers and we must do everything we can to make their conditions the best.  Along with every other Member of the House I am very proud of the record of our Defence Forces, both at home and serving with the United Nations.  A Bill which puts that service into a better situation and which improves the opportunities for our senior officers serving at home or abroad is to be welcomed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardConroy" hpid="Professor Conroy Professor Conroy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Conroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to join in welcoming the Bill and in welcoming the Minister to the House in his capacity as Minister for Defence.  The Bill is a very short Bill and we could divide it into two main aspects.  One is that it is intended, in effect, to increase and improve the efficiency of our officer rank structure primarily for the benefit of the proper functioning of the Army, both at home and abroad.  It is a matter of great pride that our Army is playing such a very worthwhile role abroad.  The days seem to be long since gone when people queried what was the role of our Army. We now realise sadly, that it is necessary at home and that we have a particular role to play in the maintenance of world <Col N="19" /> peace.  Obviously, our role must not be one of having large numbers but one of acceptability and efficiency.  Our officers and men abroad have done this admirably and as well as, if not better than, any other armed force.  It is a source of great pride and joy that we are able to make such a very useful contribution.</P>
      <P>On a purely practical basis this Bill will play some small part in that.  This is a rank which is approximately suitable for the command of a small detachment on overseas service, or alternatively to play an administrtive role in relation to the United Nations during service abroad.  This is over and above its practical uses here.</P>
      <P>Secondly, one should note the fact that for the career structure of the Army officers themselves, for the officer cadets, it provides a very necessary and useful rank which completes the necessary organisation of officer ranks in the Army.  Basically, what we are doing here is amending the Defence Act of 1954 under which the Department of Defence and our armed services function.</P>
      <P>Hitherto we had as principal officers of the Defence Forces, and I quote from <i>An Cosantóir</i>, January 1977 issue.  We had in the chief-of-staff branch a major-general, then a series of officers, assistant chief-of-staff, director of operations, director of training and so on, all held by officers of the rank of colonel.  In the adjutant-general's branch, the adjutant-general, himself a colonel, one colonel assisting him as deputy-adjutant and so on down through the quarter-master-general's branch, technical and supply staff and various other establishments. From the point of view of organisation within the Army structure this situation, although it has in many ways functioned well because of the <i>de facto</i> acceptance and hard work of the officers concerned, in getting on well with one another and so on, nonetheless from the efficiency point of view, from the point of view of proper structures within an army is very much out of line with the normal procedure in most armed forces.  This meant that there was a very wide gap between the rank of colonel and the very senior rank of major-general.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="20" /> There are very many obvious circumstances from this list of principal officers of the Defence Forces where it would be totally inappropriate to have someone of the rank of major general.  Equally, it would be somewhat inappropriate to have someone of the rank of colonel undertaking duties which in any other armed forces would be undertaken by an officer of brigadier rank, a general officer in other words as it is, I understand, technically defined.</P>
    <P>The functions of the Department of Defence&mdash;and I sometimes think we do not quite realise what a wide range of functions the Department of Defence covers&mdash;are given here in detail and in various Acts and so on.  Many of these are very much of an administrative nature.  We attempt, with what is a relatively small force, and a relatively small number of officers, to cover an extraordinarily wide range of functions and it must be a matter of pride that this is done so well and that our officers have acquitted themselves so well often, perhaps, not getting the credit which they deserve.  It was only, perhaps, when these officers went overseas that it was realised that their efficiency, ability and training were, at the very least equal, and often superior, to those of many other forces.  We realised then just what a high calibre of officers and men we have in the Irish forces.  This is something in which we take great pride and is particularly due to the people themselves having often, in obscurity and with very little attention, worked extremely hard to improve their efficiency and ability.</P>
    <P>One area which is very important is that of the Naval Service.  The discussion so far has been almost entirely about the Army and that is, perhaps, natural.  It has the traditional role in this country, a role which, despite that fact, is, nonetheless, a little odd when we consider that we are an island nation and that, perhaps, we should devote more attention to our Naval Service than we have hitherto.  This in no way denigrates the importance of the Army.  It is just that at times we have neglected the sea a little. Something which we do not, perhaps, fully realise is that from the point of view of fisheries and of other developments, <Col N="21" /> we now have, a very large and crucial sea area under our responsibility.  It is important, therefore, that we should make provision in this Bill for a senior officer, the flag officer rank in the Navy. It does not necessarily mean that someone should be appointed to it forthwith but it does mean that the establishment and the possibility of appointment are there.</P>
    <P>If I understand rightly, and perhaps the Minister will correct me if I am wrong, at present in our armed services we have approximately 700 men in the Naval Service.  We do not differentitate in the sense that there is not a Naval Corps or an Air Corps or an Army Corps; they are all part of our Defence Forces; those who are part of the Naval Service at present number about 700.  If I understand correctly, the new ships, which I am delighted to say that we are getting, will provide an opportunity for our Naval Service to play the role it should be playing and an opportunity for promotion and the other possibilities which Senator Dowling mentioned.  The Naval Service will inevitably, with the number of ships that we already possess or are building or planning, require an increase in personnel to perhaps 3,000 to 4,000 men which means that we would be quadrupling the numbers in the Naval Service.  One can very readily see that this new rank in the Naval Service may well become necessary and may well, I hope, be filled earlier than otherwise might have been the case.</P>
    <P>I know that the Minister has taken a particular interest in the development of the Naval Services.  I also realise that this is an exceptionally difficult service to develop rapidly.  It is not just a question of placing advertisements in the newspapers and expecting to fill the vacancies with qualified people.  Many of the officers involved are technical officers in very heavy demand already in civil life, industry or elsewhere and it is very good indeed, that we have brought in this new rank which will provide the possibility of an advancing career structure to those officers who join our Naval Service.</P>
    <P>There has been some slight wonderment about the rank of brigadier.  Many of us, perhaps, tend to associate it with <Col N="22" /> the sister country across the water.  We talk about revising Irish history, which does badly need revising but in precisely the opposite direction to that fashionably wished by so many people at present.  It is a fact, I understand, that the rank of brigadier is actually a French rank.  It was brought in when they started to form army groups in which three regiments were grouped together and the senior colonel was called the brigadier.  Indeed one of the very first brigadiers to be appointed in military history was, in fact, Lord Mountcashel, Brigadier of the Irish Brigade in France when the regiments of Mountcashel and Dillon, the other Irish regiment, were brought together to form the Irish Brigade in 1691.  The term &ldquo;brigade&rdquo; is now a very normal one in many armies. It does not necessarily follow, of course, that the brigades which we have at present should necessarily be headed by a brigadier because we link together a small number of battalions, whereas, traditionally, it was the linking of regiments which themselves consist usually of at least two battalions.  I am pleased to see this ancient title which our Army and officers are as entitled to as those in other armies, once again restored to our Armed Forces.</P>
    <P>We have been inclined during this debate to go beyond the immediate confines of the precise changes in rank proposed in the Bill.  I do not propose to go any further, but I cannot help thinking that a particularly appropriate subject for a Seanad debate is a debate on the Defence Forces.  It is a debate which is of national importance and concern and perhaps, to a large extent we are inclined to put our heads in the sand and ignore many developments around us.  It is, perhaps, very understandable that we should do so but defence, and the questions of neutrality, such as those Senator West raised, are matters which would seem very appropriate for a Seanad debate.  They affect us in the country as a whole, perhaps more than in any particular constituency or area.  It is very interesting to note the number of Senators who have been anxious and willing to join in this debate, and that we have found ourselves limited in the comments we can make about it.  It shows our interest.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="23" /> In welcoming the Bill I should like to pay a tribute to the Minister for bringing it in and also for the quiet efficiency which he has brought to his job as Minister for Defence, the very best attributes in a Minister for Defence, and, in particular, his interest in developing our naval units.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondGoverney" hpid="Mr. Governey Mr. Governey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Governey</NameTxt>
      <P>Like previous speakers, I should like to welcome the Bill and congratulate the Minister on making the changes contained in it.  It is a short Bill, and the scope for discussion is very limited if we are to abide by the rules of the House.  I am glad to see from it that our rank structures which have been different from those in Western European nations will be brought into line with those structures and with those of the United Nations Forces.  That was necessary, and I can understand the difficulties which must have arisen at times when some of our Army officers went abroad.  Indeed, I should like to say how proud we all feel of our Defence Forces. We feel very proud when they go abroad and join with peacekeeping forces.</P>
      <P>I should like to place on record my feeling of appreciation of the improvements made in the conditions in our Defence Forces under the previous Minister for Defence, Deputy Donegan, and which are continuing under the guidance of the present Minister.  It is very important that those who serve in the Defence Forces should have proper conditions and be treated financially in a proper manner.  I noted when reading the brief explanatory memorandum accompanying the Bill that regarding the new post of brigadier-general there has been no mention as to what the salary will be for that post.  Perhaps the Minister will enlighten us when replying.</P>
      <P>I should like to know if the Minister feels satisfied that there are no changes necessary in the structure of the Air Corps?  Under this Bill we will have changes within the Army and the Naval Service but there has not been any mention of any changes in the structure in the Air Corps.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like to be informed if the <Col N="24" /> Minister has any intention of making changes in the structure of the FCA, another relation of our Defence Forces of which we are all justly proud.  At present the highest rank, as far as I am aware, is that of commandant, and I should like to hear from the Minister whether he intends making any changes in this structure.</P>
    <P>When one mentions the Defence Forces generally people take it that we are speaking of the Army but of course we are covering here all the Defence Forces.  I am glad the previous speaker mentioned that in this Bill there is also the change in the structure in our Naval Service.  That is also right and proper.</P>
    <P>The explanatory memorandum states that the new rank structures will provide a better promotion progression for military officers and provide a pool of officers of general rank from which can be drawn officers for certain senior appointments with the United Nations. That is terribly important.  I welcome the Bill and wish the Minister every success in his efforts during his term of office to carry out improvements for our Defence Forces.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill. There have been a number of anomalies in regard to ranks in the Army over the years which are gradually being eliminated.  Up to approximately the late forties we had the rank of major in the Army which, in fact, corresponded with lieutenant-colonel in other armies, and we had no rank of lieutenant-colonel. We also had, of course, the rank of commandant which corresponded with that of major in most other armies.  We changed the rank to eliminate major and introduced lieutenant-colonel, a very necessary change, and we left the rank of commandant because it had a rather historic association in the Defence Forces.  On balance that was probably the right decision to make.  In other armies the rank of commandant is an appointment rather than a rank but, nevertheless, on balance we were probably right to retain the rank of commandant. Now we are taking another step.  The Department of Defence move pretty slowly in these matters but they gradually get around to them.  I am glad <Col N="25" /> the Department decided to create the rank of brigadier-general and to eliminate the situation where, as the Minister said, a number of officers holding different responsibilities, responsibilities varying in importance, held the same rank.  The rank of brigadier-general will eliminate that difficulty and ensure that officers holding certain appointments which are more onerous and carrying more responsibility that the ordinary rank of colonel, will, in fact, have the rank of brigadier-general.</P>
      <P>I was interested in Senator Conroy's historical observations about the rank of brigadier-general.  It is true that the rank of brigadier-general was created for an officer holding the appointment of brigadier and I hope this will not be forgotten.  It is understandable at present when our Army is relatively small, that the rank of brigadier-general should not automatically be given to a brigade commander, that it should be reserved for the time being for command OCs and, possibly, a few other special appointments but I would hope, in the event of our forces being expanded, that the rank of brigadier-general should be given to brigade commanders, which, of course, is what the rank was originally created for.</P>
      <P>I should also like to approve of the fact that certain changes are being made and extra ranks created in the Naval Service.  Certainly, the rank of admiral is not likely to be used for the present or for some time to come but our Naval Service is expanding.  It will expand very much in the next few years and it is only appropriate that this opportunity should be taken of changing the structure and adding additional ranks for the Naval Service so that when the time arrives appointments and promotions can be made.  Possibly there will be an immediate appointment but certainly, in due course, these ranks will be availed of as our Naval Service increases in size because of their duties in regard to fishery protection and other duties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Reference has been made to the situation with the United Nations and this is of particular relevance.  I know that on occasions in the past the Defence Forces have been asked to provide officers to take very important commands with the <Col N="26" /> United Nations and although we had suitable officers, men who had the ability and the experience, and were in every way suitable for the appointments, they had not the appropriate rank.  This created difficulties for the United Nations and embarrassment for the man concerned if he was appointed in spite of the fact that his rank was not really adequate. It is a great pity where we have men who are suitable for those appointments and in every other way not only as good as any other officer from any other army but, in fact, in many cases better than other possible appointees, that this embarrassment should arise.  I am glad that we have created the rank of brigadier-general.  We have, in fact, upgraded a number of our senior officers and that will ensure that in the future when senior officers are required for the United Nations appointments they will have the appropriate rank and will be eligible and suitable in that and every other regard for the appointment.  From that point of view I welcome this Bill and I am glad that the Minister has taken this step.  I have no doubt that it will give satisfaction in many respects and in many areas as far as the Defence Forces are concerned.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of the Labour Party I should like to welcome the Bill. The Army are never in a very strong position such as many other professional groups in our society are and who, when the chips are down, can make their voices heard and see that they get their full whack in consultation, and get a full hearing of any of their grievances. Therefore, it is welcome when the Minister takes the initiative and gives the Army some advantage that seems from time to time to be overlooked.  It is very much the norm in industry, in the services and at other professional levels to force situations which can bring about upgrading.  Of course, the Army is not in that happy position.  The fact that the Defence Forces are not in this happy position makes it all the more pleasing that somebody does, from time to time, take some interest in them.  In this case I am delighted the Minister has ensured that some development as taken place on this question of ranking and upgrading. <Col N="27" /> Reading the Dáil Debates I was glad to note the welcome the Bill had in the other House and I am also glad to note the great welcome it is getting here.</P>
      <P>We tend to overlook outside factors.  I am glad Senator E. Ryan drew attention to the quality of the officers and the fact that they have to take up very onerous and difficult positions abroad, and not only with the United Nations.  Because of the world situation, if we were called on we would have to come to some agreement to supply officers for training, and so on.  It is very welcome to see a development like this.  Unfortunately the public do not have a full appreciation of the very useful and difficult role soldiers have to play.  This is because the Army do not have pressure groups and they are not very often in the position to flex their muscles.  It is up to us, and to the Minister in particular, to keep an eye on the situation and see that some developments take place that will make the Army realise that they are appreciated and that we as Members of this House understand the wonderful job they do, the onerous tasks that they perform and the honour they bring to Ireland when they are abroad&mdash;taking command and so on.</P>
      <P>When people die in the Congo, or somewhere like that, it has an immediate impact but once emotion dies down I do not think people fully understand what the Army are being called on to do.  As someone who was involved in guerilla warfare, as an ex-soldier, I can readily understand what the soldiers and officers abroad are going through.  It is worse than war because in a war you have some idea where you are going and where the danger lies.  The soldiers are really up against it.  I am delighted to see that this alteration in the line structure has taken place because it has been out of line with all the other western European countries.  As I said earlier, people do not fully appreciate the situations the Army have to deal with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would ask the Minister&mdash;I know it is not possible within the terms of this Bill&mdash;to have regard to the new role the soldier is playing and to look at his rates of pay compared with the pay of some <Col N="28" /> of the other security people who are doing much better financially, even having regard to the fact that the soldiers are bedded down, have their meals and so on.  When you look at their rates of pay and the onerous task they take on, in fairness there is a case there.  The Minister might have another look at this. Perhaps in the middle of the hurly-burly that may grow out of either a new initiative on a national wage agreement or free-for-all negotiations, something would emerge for the lower ranks.</P>
    <P>I would like to go on record as thanking the Minister for increasing the allowances of the people serving abroad who were badly treated.  This is a good development.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I too welcome the introduction of this Bill.  The creation of this new rank will have repercussions right through the officer ranks and, hopefully, right down through the noncommissioned officers and other ranks. The role of the Army has been changing for very many years.  I wonder, in today's circumstances, if the structure we have is the type of structure that is needed.  As has been said by some of the earlier speakers, there are very heavy and onerous duties on the administrative side connected with the officer ranks. The Army of today is basically an army which does not have the working conditions the armies of the past had to work in.  The Army of today is a technical army.  It is an army which needs very high degrees of skill in the technical area&mdash;communications, the knowledge of where your enemy is going to come from, how to deal with the massive technological changes that have taken place in aircraft, submarines, ships, in the armaments themselves, and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wonder should there be more emphasis placed on the provision of an officer grade, an officer who is highly technically oriented rather than the present situation where the majority of officers come up through the system of recruitment which we have had since the formation of the State, that is, recruitment at cadet level.  I believe there should be a change in the full method of recruitment.  The cadet grade should be abolished and everybody who joins the <Col N="29" /> Army should have the opportunity to go right through and be promoted from the initial recruitment stage to the top officer grade.  It can be said that this happened in the past, that people who had gone in as privates have risen to the very highest level in the officer grade, but this is the exception rather than the rule, and I think there is a need for change.  People who completed their secondary education are now joining the Army.  Their educational standards are as high as the people who go in at the cadet grade, but it takes much longer for a person who goes in at the private grade to attain officership than it does for a person with the same educational standards who goes in at cadet grade.  I do not think this is fair.  In the present day industrial sector I do not think that would be allowed to happen.  In industry a person with a degree would not have better opportunities than the person without a degree.</P>
    <P>Now that we have this new grade of officer hopefully it will create a situation where there will be more officers available to review the needs of the Army in total.  This review must take place from within the Army itself.  I do not think it should take place from the Department of Defence.  There is a need for a review of the conditions down along the line, whether it be in the lower officer grades, or in the noncommissioned and ordinary private grades.  As Senator Harte said, there are problems <i>vis-a-vis</i> the other forces which we ask to look after this country for us. We can see the difference when the Army go on duty in the prisons in particular. They work in worse conditions than prisons officers and gardaí because they are the people who are armed&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to remind the Senator to keep within the scope of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am suggesting that within the new officer grade possibly one of his duties should be to have a review carried out of the conditions throughout the Army.  I was reiterating what was said previously by Senator Harte in connection with the differences that are there as between other grades of gardaí <Col N="30" /> and prison officers in that particular area.</P>
      <P>There is a need also for a review, and it might be something that might be taken up by this new officer grade, of the methods by which punishments are carried out in the Army.  A person can be up for courtmartial and be waiting for that courtmartial for one month, six weeks or many months.  The sentence has to be reviewed afterwards and that can take a very long time.  This is an area that this new officer grade could look into.</P>
      <P>It has also been said that there has been an increasing awareness in our Defence Forces and thankfully that has happened.  There is a new awareness that we have a highly skilled force of men available.  They are highly trained and can go to any country where they are needed to do a very highly skilled job in very difficult circumstances.  Thankfully the conditions under which they work are improving but there is a grave need for further improvement.  I am happy to see that the Minister for Finance has provided extra money for accommodation for married quarters in many barracks and, hopefully, these accommodations will be brought up to the standards that exist in outside areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Again I would like to remind the Senator that much of what he has been saying throughout his speech has been irrelevant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that I may be drifting a little and I beg the Chair's indulgence. A review is necessary within the officer grade itself of the methods for airing grievances.  Too often you will find that it is very hard for an officer to get his complaint through because, inevitably, it has to go through his superior officers.  If the grievance is with the superior officer it is very hard to get it to the stage where he can get justice done.  These are areas in which reviews could be carried out by this new officer grade.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The impact the Army has on a city or a town where they are stationed is great. In Kilkenny it is the biggest &ldquo;industry&rdquo; we have&mdash;it is as big as the biggest industry, <Col N="31" /> but it is often not treated in that way.  The review I would like to see take place is of the total structure of the needs of a rapidly-changing Army.  The day of the foot soldier has gone.  The day of the highly skilled technical officer and man is here.  We will have to provide the type of training that is needed to bring these officers and men up to the level of skill which is necessary in any country.  They are working in foreign countries with very highly skilled armies who come from countries which are wealthier than we are, and they are expected to do the same job as the forces from these countries.  There will have to be an increase in the amount of money allocated for training in technical areas.</P>
    <P>I would like to thank the Minister for the interest that he is taking in the Army since he became Minister.  From what we have seen, he deals with a difficult situation. As has been said he is caught between the civil service and the Army and he has a difficult job at times trying to decide which area is the one that needs the most attention.  We should look after the men and the officers in the Army and let the Department of Defence look after the political end.  I should like to thank the Minister for bringing this Bill in and I feel that it will have an impact on the force in general.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. Molloy) Robert Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. Molloy)</NameTxt>
      <P>Ar dtús be mhaith liom mo bhuíochas a ghabháil dos na Seanadóirí ar fad as ucht an fáilte atá tugtha acu don Bhille seo&mdash;An Bille Cosanta (Leasú) 1978. Cé go bhfuil a lán caint déanta anseo agus a lán moltaí déanta níl sa Bhille seo ach céim nua a cheapadh san Arm agus céim nua a cheapadh sa Seirbhís Cabhlaigh&mdash;an céim nua, ná briogáidire&mdash;ghinearál san Arm agus Seach-Aimiréal sa Seirbhís Cabhlaigh. Beidh and briogáidire&mdash;ghinearál ar comhchéim leis an ceannasóir agus beidh an céim nua sa Seirbhís Cabhlaigh &mdash;Seach-Aimiréil&mdash;ar chomhchéim le Maor Ghinearál san Arm.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to thank Senators from all sides of the House for the welcome they have given to this Bill which establishes new ranks in the Army and the <Col N="32" /> Naval Service, that of brigadier-general in the Army and rear-admiral in the Navy.  As I stated in my few introductory words, it is proposed immediately on the passing of this Bill to appoint the command OCs to the new rank of brigadier-general and also to promote the assistant chief of staff to this new rank of brigadier-general.</P>
    <P>Even though I propose to add to the list of naval ranks by the addition of rear-admiral, I do not have any immediate proposals for the filling of that rank in the Naval Service.  I felt it is appropriate to include the rank now because this Bill gives me that opportunity, but I do not have any immediate plans for the filling of it.  The reason for that is fairly obvious.  The establishment in the Naval Service when I was appointed Minister was 600 and since then, in a year-and-a-half, I have increased that establishment to 800.  The establishment figure is not filled; there are many vacancies in the Naval Service.  The actual strength at the moment is nearer to 700, or indeed less than 700.  We have a long way to go to fill the establishment figure of 800.</P>
    <P>Reference has been made to the need for rapid growth in the Naval Service. Presuming that our plans succeed and that that growth becomes a reality, it might be possible that in the future we will fill the rank of rear-admiral.  At the moment it stands in the Defence Acts merely as a spare rank over and above the rank of commodore which has been granted, and which might be used as the rank for OC of the Naval Service in the future.  It is wise to have a spare rank as we have for Army ranks&mdash;we have this in the Defence Acts, as can be seen under the Schedule to this Bill, the rank of general.</P>
    <P>Senators raised certain points during the course of the debate and I will try to reply to them as fully as possible.  I do not often get the opportunity to discuss defence matters in the Seanad, or indeed in the Dáil, and for that reason I am pleased that this Bill has given me the opportunity to hear the views of Members of the Seanad on the Defence Forces.  It is obvious that they all hold those who serve and have served in the Defence Forces in very high esteem.  The <Col N="33" /> Seanad today expressed very great appreciation of the excellent loyal service that has been, and is being, given both at home and abroad by the men serving in the Irish Defence Forces.  May I on their behalf thank Senators most sincerely for their words of encouragement and appreciation as expressed here today?</P>
    <P>An interesting point was raised by Senator Cooney which was repeated by other Senators regarding brigade commands. Senator Conroy very interestingly gave us the historical background to the origins of the rank of brigadier-general, and I am very grateful to him for that.  I should explain that in this country military command is given to the command OC by the Minister and that a brigade is commanded by a colonel who is responsible to the command OCs.  It would not be appropriate in our circumstances to attach the rank of brigadier-general to the brigade commander because the military commander for his area of operations is in fact the command OC.  As I already informed the Seanad I propose to promote the command OCs to this rank.  It is possible that it is unique to the Irish situation, but in all circumstances I think all will agree that this is the most reasonable and proper step for me to take.  I am satisfied that the rank of colonel is appropriate for the brigade commander and that the rank of brigadier-general is more suitable for the command OC.</P>
    <P>Senator Cooney mentioned the question of remuneration of our troops, particularly in relation to those on security duties and other special duties.  Since my appointment as Minister, I have arranged for increases in the security duty allowances and in the allowances paid for those who do duty at the military detention barracks at the Curragh.  As was mentioned by Senator Harte, allowances for overseas services in all the theatres of operation have also been substantially increased.  As an example, allowances for services in the Lebanon have been increased from £3.80 a day to £7.30 a day for the private and the figure ranges up to £11.88 a day for a senior officer.  I want to assure Senators who expressed concern at the level of remuneration that all these allowances are kept constantly under review and <Col N="34" /> any adjustments regarded as necessary will be made.  I consider it my responsibility to ensure that those matters are kept constantly under review and that steps are taken to bring about improvements wherever necessary.</P>
    <P>Comparisons are made from time to time with regard to remuneration of the Garda who seem at particular times to be doing duties similar to those of military personnel.  It is difficult to make a direct comparison between the method of remuneration for both.  All I can say as Minister for Defence is that I will seek at all times to bring about improvements in the rate of remuneration to those serving in the Irish Army for whom I am responsible.</P>
    <P>At present we are running a recruiting campaign.  I would ask all the Members to avail of whatever opportunities may arise to encourage young men to join the forces, because if they do so they are assured of a very healthy life, a very satisfying career and the remuneration is very good in comparison with what was paid to those serving in the forces 20 to 30 years ago.  Conditions in the Army have improved very substantially in recent years and I acknowledge the interest shown by my predecessor, Deputy Paddy Donegan, when he was Minister for Defence.  I also acknowledge the very great work, and indeed the foundations, laid by his predecessor, Deputy Cronin. With all due respect to previous Ministers for Defence, previous to Deputy Cronin, many of us were neglectful of the services until the emergency of 1969-70.  Then there was a realisation on the part of the community that a lot was suddenly expected of the Defence Forces, that they were not up to the required strength or standard, the equipment had not been kept up to date and that there was need for a massive improvement.</P>
    <P>It is satisfying to record that since those years the whole image of the Army has changed.  The plans immediately set afoot for the improvement of facilities in barracks, the construction of new billets, and improvement in canteen-dining facilities, soldiers' recreational facilities and equipment all dated from that time. I think it is proper to include Deputy Cronin in any expression of appreciation <Col N="35" /> in regard to improvements in the Defence Forces.</P>
    <P>My task is to ensure that all these improvements continue.  I invite Senators to examine the Book of Estimates for 1979 and they will see there under the various subheads increases in the allocations to the Department of Defence to enable massive increases in the purchase of equipment for the Defence Forces to take place duing 1979.  I hope that when this year is out we will have made a major contribution by re-equipping the Army with modern equipment and providing it with an adequate supply of ammunition.  All the military items which are to be purchased are, unfortunately very expensive.  To equip our army with the most modern equipment involves heavy investment on the part of the taxpayers but I can judge from the response in the Dáil Debate and in this debate that the Houses of the Oireachtas fully support that expendiure, and for that I am very greatful.</P>
    <P>Senator Dowling spoke of the need for promotional opportunities for NCOs.  He has great experience of the Defence Forces, having himself served but I am glad the debate did not move along the lines of a class distinction between officers and men.  All those who serve in the Defence Forces are worthy of equal consideration by the Oireachtas.  Some will hold positions of greater authority and responsibility than others, and it is my intention to ensure that at all times the opportunities are there for those of the very lowest rank in the Army to rise to the very highest rank.</P>
    <P>In 1978 a course for potential officers commenced.  NCOs and men were invited to apply for positions which were available on this potential officers course which is now under way.  Quite a large number of men who otherwise would not have had the opportunity of achieving commissioned ranks are at present undergoing the course which should lead to commissioned rank for them.  I wish them success in that course and satisfaction and enjoyment in the Army when they become commissioned officers.</P>
    <P>We are very anxious that that door <Col N="36" /> will always be left open to provide a way in which men, who on leaving school may not have had the opportunity to gain a cadetship and take up a career in the Army as commissioned officers but who having joined as regular soldiers and having shown their <i>metier</i> would be given the opportunity to become commissioned later on.  I hope to ensure that these courses will be held on a regular basis to provide the path from the lowest private to the highest rank in the Army at all times.  We are all very conscious that there is no class distinction in the Army even though the military law and Defence Acts provide for a very strict code of discipline and a recognition of the authority of rank is a matter of great importance in maintaining morale, respect, discipline and dignity within any army.  At the same time while there is respect for rank all men are treated equally by me no matter what rank they hold.</P>
    <P>Questions were raised about the role of the Army.  Let me briefly say that it is not intended that there should be any change in the traditional role of our Defence Forces but I will come to that later.  Their primary task is to defend this country against external agression.  They also have a role to play in aiding the civil power.  Those who speak of our neutrality and of attempts to weaken the policy of the Government with regard to neutrality cannot point to any utterance from the Government with regard to such weakening of will.  It remains, and I hope it will continue to remain, the policy of this Government to maintain a neutral policy.  If any consideration is to be given to those matters it is not strictly speaking a matter in the first instance for the Minister for Defence but for the Minister for Foreign Affairs and of course for the Government.  Finally there seems to be some who from time to time make statements which indicate that there should be or might a change of will on the part of the Government in regard to neutrality but this is not so.</P>
    <P>A number of Senators referred to the question of education in the Army. There was an emphasis by some Senators on the modern soldier being a technician.  This is very true.  Deputy Gibbons, when Minister for Defence, initiated <Col N="37" /> university courses for young cadets.  That was a radical step at that time and has proved very valuable in giving young Army officers the benefit of a university education.  There may have been a tendency for cadets to opt for arts courses rather than technical courses such as engineering or science.  I have been concerned about that trend since I became Minister and have encouraged young cadets into a wider area of third-level education.  I have also opened courses in some regional technical colleges to cadets and extended them to the Physical College of Education in Limerick.</P>
    <P>I agree with those who expressed concern that too many of the cadets were following the BA type course.  There is in the Estimate for my Department a substantial amount of money allocated to cover the cost of officers and men attending special courses in order to help them gain greater expertise in their particular corps.  They have travelled to high level courses in different parts of the world.  This policy will be vigourously pursued by me.  It is in line with what was suggested by a number of Senators, that the technical training of members of the Defence Forces should receive more attention.  If there is need for further improvement in that area then I take the point.  I feel a lot has been done which may not be known by the general public. In fact this year an officer is attending a major course in India at the military college there.  That is the first time an officer from the Irish Army has gone there but, they regularly attend courses in Britain and on the Continent and at colleges in the United States.  The service which our Defence Force personnel give with the United Nations also helps to broaden their outlook, increase their knowledge of equipment, techniques and developments of other defence forces.</P>
    <P>Senator Dowling said that young men who wish to enlist in the forces are told after a number of weeks that their enlistment has not been confirmed.  I am aware of this and I hope to take some steps to change the procedures.  I would like to point out to Senator Dowling that there is very good reason for not confirming enlistment in some cases.  Events in this country over the past ten years <Col N="38" /> have highlighted the necessity to ensure that those who are enlisted in the Defence Forces are persons about whom there should be no doubts as to their security risk.  It has always been the practice that on application for enlistment an applicant's background would be reported upon to the enlisting officer before enlistment was confirmed.  That is essential and it is a practice which will certainly continue.  If there is any way in which we can ease the pain for those who eventually find that they are not accepted but I will be only too pleased to do so.  The matter is being looked at at the moment but the necessity to ensure that people are good security risks will continue.  It is important that that should be so.</P>
    <P>A number of Senators mentioned the fact that a Minister for Defence is in a particularly awkward position in that he is stuck between the civil service and the Army.  It may seem like that to the outsider that it is an awkward role to have to play and a delicate position to hold and maybe there were times in the past where there might have been strains or problems for people in my position.  All I can say is that I am not conscious of it.  I have the utmost loyalty from the civil service and from the military and I think I can say that the relationships between the military and the civil service are excellent and possibly have never been better in the history of the Irish Army.  I would like to express my appreciation to both sides.  I am very grateful for the loyal service which has been given to the State by the civil servants in my Department, and by the officers and men in the Defence Forces.</P>
    <P>With regard to the question of promotion procedures I would like to assure the Seanad that all promotion procedures are applied fairly and are made with due regard to the recommendations made to me by the Chief of Staff.  I hope that that position will continue and that whatever difficulties arose in the past no such difficulties will arise in the future.  I have always sought to ensure that all factors are taken into consideration when promotions are being made, a man's length of service and his performance in the tasks which have been assigned to him up to that time.  In <Col N="39" /> a peacetime situation&mdash;I suppose you could certainly call it that&mdash;the length of service must be a very primary factor in deciding on promotions.</P>
    <P>Senator West referred to the service of the Irish troops with the UN.  As the House probably knows this service stretches back over 20 years, to 1958, when the first group of observers went to the Lebanon.  It encompasses command by Irishmen of the United Nations forces in the Congo and in Cyprus.  I would like to assure Senator West that he need have no fear that any structural changes in the Defence Forces will be related to anything other than the needs of the Defence Forces for their roles. Their primary role is the obligation to defend this State against external aggression. Another role is aid to the civil power.  This means, in practice, the rendering of assistance when requested to do so to the Garda who have the prime responsibility for the maintenance and restoration of the public peace and for internal security.  Further roles are to aid civil defence, to contribute to the peacekeeping activities of the United Nations, fishery protection and such other duties as may be assigned from time to time such as search and rescue, ambulance service, assistance in natural disasters, oil pollution at sea.</P>
    <P>As I have already stated the establishment of the Naval Service&mdash;which was referred to in some detail by Senator Conroy&mdash;has been expanded from 600 to 800 since I took up office.  During that time the strength of the Naval Service has increased from 620 to 670.  Again, I would like to place an emphasis on the fact that there are many vacancies still to be filled.  Indeed, there is an urgent need that they should be filled, because of the programme for increasing the number of ships available to the service.</P>
    <P>Senator Conroy mentioned the difficulty that exists in attracting technical officers and in retaining the service of technical officers already in the Naval Service.  In industry those with the technical knowledge of marine engineers seem to be in very high demand, both on shore and with other shipping companies. Irish based and worldwide.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="40" /> We are in a position where we have to compete with the higher rates of remuneration which these organisations are able to pay marine engineers.  Every effort will be made by me to further improve conditions for marine engineers in the Irish Navy.  I ask the House for its co-operation in recruiting for this very vital service, particularly in those counties adjoining the sea where there may be a sea-going tradition in the family.  It is surely a great honour to serve the Irish nation in the Irish Navy.  With the expansion that is proposed with assistance from EEC funds, the number of new ships that have been added in recent years, those that are being built at present and those that are planned there will be need for the enlistment of hundreds of additional men at all levels into the Naval Service.  The conditions are constantly under review to ensure that service at sea is properly rewarded.</P>
    <P>I omitted to mention the salary of the brigadier-general, which was raised by Senator Governey.  The pay for the rank of brigadier-general will be £9,700 a year which represents the maximum rate of pay for colonel plus the responsibility allowance of £894 paid at present to the holders of Command OC.  In fact, there will be no change in the rate of remuneration of the officers holding the Commander at sea appointment on their promotion to brigadier-general.</P>
    <P>May I also inform the Seanad that for some time the whole organisation of the Defence Forces has been under review. Senators will be aware of the increased establishment for the Naval Service that I have mentioned and the creation of a new Command at the Curragh which was done by my predecessor in 1977. This review also embraces the Air Corps and the FCA.  It is hoped that the final stages of the review of the organisation of the Army will be announced shortly.</P>
    <P>I share Senator Governey's admiration for the Forsa Cosanta Áitiúla. There is no better force to introduce our youth to military service.  I intend to pursue vigorously a programme designed to ensure that the military skills of the members of the FCA are brought up to the highest possible standard.</P>
    <P>I anticipate, because of the increasing responsibilities of the Air Corps, particularly <Col N="41" /> on fishery patrols, it will be necessary to expand the Air Corps to meet these developments.  There are two areas of the Defence Forces for which very rapid expansion is planned in the immediate future, the Naval Service and the Air Corps.  As the House is aware a recruitment campaign is at present in progress in order to maintain strength and, indeed, increase strength in the Defence Forces.</P>
    <P>Senator Lanigan referred to the question of procedures in regard to court-martial. I am aware of the type of problem that he mentioned.  I assure him that the matter is receiving very active consideration.  There are some proposals coming before me from the Adjutant General's branch in regard to changes in military law which would affect procedures in regard to courtmartials which many would agree are outmoded and in need of revision and modern principles should be applied.  I hope to be able to update matters in that area in the not too distant future.</P>
    <P>We had a fairly lengthy debate.  I did not expect that we would have because of the restricted nature of the Bill.  I have attempted to make some reply to the points that were made.  Go raibh maith agaibh as ucht an fáilte atá curtha agaibh roimh an mBille seo.  Tá súil agam go mbeidh feabhas ar na Forsaí Cosanta de bharr an obair atá déanta againn anseo inniu.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    <P>Bill put through Committee, reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Tribunals of Inquiry" RHead="(Evidence) (Amendment) Bill, 1979: Second Stage">
    <Title>Private Business. - Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence) (Amendment) Bill, 1979: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Justice (Mr. D. Andrews) David Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Justice (Mr. D. Andrews)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill is to amend the Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence) Act, 1921 so as to remove certain defects which have become apparent over the years and to inroduce a number of desirable changes in the law in this area.  As Senators are aware, the <Col N="42" /> Bill is being introduced now so that the changes will be effective for the commencement of the inquiry which the Government have already decided to hold into the tragedy which occurred at Whiddy Island on 8 January last.</P>
      <P>The Whiddy disaster is, therefore, the immediate background to the Bill but I should like to emphasise that the 1921 Act and this Bill, when enacted, taken together, will form part of the general law relating to the holding of sworn public inquiries.</P>
      <P>Before I go on to deal with the main provisions in the Bill, I should like to place on the record of this House my own and the Government's deep sadness and sympathy at the tragic loss of life that occurred in Whiddy Island and to extend, once again, our sincere sympathy to the relatives and friends of all those who lost their lives.</P>
      <P>Senators who have examined the 1921 Act will have noted that it is a short statute providing the general framework for the holding of sworn inquiries by means of special tribunals.  It has been the basis for many important inquiries since the foundation of the State.</P>
      <P>Section 1 of the Act outlines the procedure for the setting up of a tribunal.  It provides that the Government or a Minister of the Government may be resolution passed in both Houses of the Oireachtas establish a tribunal for the holding of an inquiry into a definite matter described in the resolution as of &ldquo;urgent public importance&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Following the passing of the resolutions, the Minister or the Government by instrument appoint the tribunal and the appointing instrument may provide for the application of the Act to the tribunal so appointed.  That is how the wheels are set in motion, so to speak, and, therefore, as soon as this Bill becomes law, resolutions will be moved providing for the establishment of the tribunal to enquire into the Whiddy Island disaster. Senators will, at that time, have an opportunity of discussing the terms of reference of the Whiddy tribunal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The 1921 Act, of course, pre-dated the Constitution of Ireland of 1937 and it is, therefore, only good law to the extent that it is not inconsistent with the <Col N="43" /> terms of the Constitution and has only to that extent been carried over into our law by the terms of Article 50 of the Constitution.  As a result of a decision of the Supreme Court in 1971 and applying the reasoning of the court in that decision, it seems virtually certain that part of the 1921 Act is inconsistent with the terms of certain provisions in the Constitution and would, if challenged, be struck down.  The decision of the Supreme Court to which I refer did not, of course, deal directly with the 1921 Act; it was concerned with the Committee of Public Accounts of Dáil Éireann (Privilege and Procedure) Act, 1970 (No. 22 of 1970).  However, part of that Act followed in certain material respects part of the 1921 Act and this leads to the conclusion that the &ldquo;flaw&rdquo; the Supreme Court held to exist in the 1970 Act also exists in the Act of 1921.</P>
    <P>The provision to which I am referring is in section 1, subsection 2 of the Act of 1921.  It purports to enable the chairman of a tribunal to &ldquo;certify&rdquo; to the High Court the offence of any person who did any one of a number of things such as refusing to attend as a witness.  The High Court was then empowered to punish the person as if he had been guilty of contempt of that court.</P>
    <P>What the Supreme Court held in the 1971 decision was that the offence of contempt of the High Court was not a minor offence and, therefore, there had to be a right to trial by jury as the Constitution provides.  The inference, therefore, is that the law must either allow trial by jury or else make the offence a minor offence with penalties restricted accordingly.</P>
    <P>Section 3 of the Bill now before the House will rectify that defect.  The Bill, as passed by Dáil Éireann, proposed to make the offences in question minor offences, to be tried in a summary manner only, with a penalty on conviction of up to £500 or 12 months' imprisonment or both, but I should point out at this stage that an amendment will be moved at the Committee Stage in this House to provide for stiffer penalties.  To achieve that, the amendment will make the offences in question indictable offences&mdash;that <Col N="44" /> is to say there will be a right to trial on indictment before judge and jury&mdash;with penalties up to £10,000 of a fine or up to two years' imprisonment or both.</P>
    <P>There will still, however, be provision for dealing with alleged offences in a summary manner where the court is of opinion that the facts proved or alleged constitute a minor offence, the accused does not object and the Director of Public Prosecutions agrees.  When dealt with summarily, the offences will carry penalties of up to £500 by way of fine or 12 months' imprisonment or both.  Some Deputies in the Dáil were of the view that stiffer penalties than those it is now proposed to provide for on indictment should be provided.</P>
    <P>There was some suggestion in that House that a fine of £50,000&mdash;or maybe more&mdash;and up to five years' imprisonment should be provided, but I think we have to be realistic in this matter and not lose sight of the important principle that the punishment should not be disproportionate to the offences in question.  Looking at the particular offences, there ought, I believe, to be general agreement that up to £10,000 of a fine and up to two years' imprisonment goes far enough.  This will, I suggest, be an adequate deterrent.</P>
    <P>I should like to emphasise also that it would be only in the more serious type of case that trial by means of indictment would be contemplated but the Government accept the view put forward in the Dáil that it is right that the provision should be there.  There will also, I might add, be a further amendment of a purely drafting nature consequent on the amendment of the penalties provision, but I will deal with that at Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>I have started my discussion of the Bill with section 3 because this section is, as I have said, designed to remove a serious defect in the 1921 Act.  Before going on to deal with the other sections, I should like to mention one or two other matters in relation to section 3.</P>
    <P>What this section does is to substitute a new subsection for subsection (2) of section 1 of the 1921 Act.  Not everything is new, however.  Paragraphs (a), <Col N="45" /> (b) and (f) are substantially the same as paragraphs (a), (b) and (c) of the 1921 Act provision.  There are, however, minor differences.  In paragraph (a), which creates the offence of disobeying a summons of a tribunal to attend as a witness, we are allowing for the situation where a person would have a just cause or excuse for not attending such as, for example, if that person were too ill to do so.  In such circumstances, the person would not, of course, be commiting an offence.  The 1921 Act was silent on this but it can be contended that a court, in construing the old provision, would have read these words in anyway.  All we are doing here is making the position clear.</P>
    <P>As to paragraph (b), we are, for the sake of completeness, making it an offence to refuse to make an affirmation in addition to the offence under the old provision of refusing to take an oath and we are also making it an offence to refuse to produce &ldquo;things&rdquo; legally required by the tribunal to be produced in addition to the offence of refusing to produce documents under the corresponding provision of the 1921 Act. The word &ldquo;documents&rdquo; will be constructed as including &ldquo;things&rdquo;.  This is necessary to ensure that &ldquo;things&rdquo; will also be included where the word &ldquo;documents&rdquo; occurs earlier in the 1921 Act&mdash;in section 1, subsection (1) of that Act.</P>
    <P>The only change that paragraph (f) has over paragraph (c) of the 1921 Act is that we are providing for the offence of omitting to do something, as well as the existing offence of doing something which would amount to contempt.  In doing so, we are simply tightening up the law in this respect.</P>
    <P>Paragraphs (c), (d) and (e) introduce new offences.  Subsection (2), paragraph (c), makes it an offence to give false evidence to a tribunal.  This is necessary because of the uncertainty that exists as to whether the offence of perjury applies to the giving of false evidence to a tribunal.</P>
    <P>Paragraph (d) makes it an offence to obstruct or hinder the tribunal in the performance of its functions.  This provision will strengthen the powers of tribunals to deal with any attempts that might be made to interfere with evidence. <Col N="46" /> Paragraph (e) makes it an offence for a person to fail, neglect or refuse to comply with an order made by a tribunal. This provision strengthens the powers of tribunals to enforce compliance with their orders.</P>
    <P>I should like now to deal with section 2.  The 1921 Act did not specifically provide for the appointment of more than one member to a tribunal, although its terms, in other respects, envisaged that there could be more than one member.  This has led, in the past, to some doubt and so it is proposed to clear up the point.  Before leaving that I should say that, although it is not spelt out in the section&mdash;because it is not necessary to do so&mdash;a tribunal will reach its conclusions by means of a majority decision. That is the usual practice and it is also usual to have only one report. Apart from that, a tribunal will be free to decide on its own procedure and there is no need to make any further provisions in this respect.</P>
    <P>Section 2 also provides for the appointment of an assessor or assessors.  In any case where such persons would be appointed they would not be members of a tribunal.  Their function would be to help the tribunal by advising it, for example, on evidence of a technical nature. It would be a matter for a tribunal itself to decide on how best to utilise the services of assessors and it is thought best to leave it totally free to do so.  Hence, the Bill provides only the minimum necessary in this respect.  The position, I might add, will be analagous to that which obtains at present in the Superior Courts where, under the rules of the Superior Courts, there is general provision for the appointment of assessors but no detailed rules dealing with their role. It is left to the court in each case to decide.</P>
    <P>That brings me to section 4.  Doubt has been expressed in the past as to whether a tribunal appointed under the 1921 Act had general power to make orders corresponding to those which the High Court or a judge of that court could make.  The 1921 Act vested in a tribunal the powers of the High Court but only in relation to the specific matters set out in section 1, subsection (1), paragraphs (a), (b), and (c) of that Act. <Col N="47" /> Section 4 of the Bill will remove any such doubt and a tribunal will be able to make such orders as it considers necessary for the purpose of its functions and will have all the powers, rights and privileges that are vested in the High Court in respect of the making of its orders.  I should like to emphasise, in this regard, that a tribunal will only have the powers, rights and privileges of the High Court in making orders necessary for the purposes of its functions.</P>
    <P>Bearing in mind that the main function of a tribunal is to find facts and that it will not be concerned with imposing legal liability for any wrongs that might have been done&mdash;that is a matter of civil law and is reserved to the courts&mdash;it can be seen that the powers given to a tribunal under section 4 are quite restricted.  What is envisaged here is that, for example, a tribunal should have power to keep order at its sittings.</P>
    <P>Section 5 provides that statements or admissions made by a person before a tribunal or by a person being examined on commission or abroad&mdash;the power to examine on commission or abroad is contained in section 1, subsection (1), paragraph (c) of the 1921 Act&mdash;will not be admissible against that person in any criminal proceedings other than proceedings for the offence of giving false evidence to a tribunal.</P>
    <P>I will turn now to the last section of substance&mdash;section 6.  Under the 1921 Act, section 2, paragraph (b), tribunals have power to authorise the representation before them by counsel, solicitor or otherwise of any person appearing to them to be interested.  It has, however, been a matter of some criticism in the past that tribunals have had no power to award costs either to or against persons appearing before them and the Bill now proposes to empower tribunals to do that.  Certain criteria by reference to which this would be done are specified, namely, that the tribunal is of opinion that, having regard to the findings of the tribunal and all other relevant matters, there are sufficient reasons rendering it equitable to do so.</P>
    <P>The section would allow a tribunal to award costs against any person even if <Col N="48" /> such person were not involved in the proceedings at all and this has been criticised in Dáil Éireann.  Such a provision is necessary, however, to enable costs to be awarded against a particular Minister&mdash;in effect, the State&mdash;because, in many instances, the State may not be involved before a tribunal at all.  On this aspect, the Minister for Justice agreed in Dáil Éireann to have another look at the drafting of the section to see whether it could be tightened somewhat.  The drafting has been re-examined in consultation with the Attorney General but it is considered that it would be undesireable to alter the section in any way.</P>
    <P>Senators will appreciate what the Bill is seeking to do here.  It may be that some relatively poor persons will be represented before&mdash;to take as an example&mdash;the proposed Whiddy tribunal and that that tribunal will decide that some other person or body should be made to bear those persons' costs.  That, I think, is an extremely necessary and desirable power to give the tribunal. Moreover, the section has built into it the safeguard that the tribunal, in coming to such a conclusion, must be of opinion that there are sufficient reasons rendering it equitable to do so.  That ought to eliminate the risk of a tribunal acting arbitrarily.  If it were to act in such a way its order could be challenged in the courts and would be liable to be set aside.</P>
    <P>This is an urgent measure made necessary by a very tragic event.  It would, of course, be better if there had been more time available to devote to it. If such were the case, it might have been possible to consider repealing in full the old 1921 Act.  That would, however, have produced unacceptable delay because a great deal more consultation would have been necessary.  This Bill introduces only those changes which are considered to be essential to enable the tribunal which is to be set up shortly to function effectively.  I hope Senators will view the Bill in that light.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill is, of course, welcome because it is necessary to act quickly in the tragic situation it is confronted with.  Taking the Minister up <Col N="49" /> on the very last note he struck, I must say he personally can be exempt from the generality of my criticism here.  Really this is a very good example of quite unjustifiable delay.  I am not now talking about the five or six weeks since the Whiddy disaster.  I am talking about a piece of legislation which has been on the Statute Book since before this State was founded and which has been known to be defective for very many years of the existence of this State.  The most serious possible defect in it only came to the notice of the executive and their advisers in what must in their time period be a very short time indeed, that is, only eight years ago when in June 1971 in the Haughey case it was patent that this Act would have to be amended before a further tribunal could be established.</P>
      <P>I wonder would the Minister care to say how long this Bill has been lying on somebody's desk.  I suspect it may have been lying on somebody's desk for a long time, perhaps long preceding the existence of this Government.  I am merely concerned to know why these things happen, and how wrong it is that they should happen, and how right it is that we should protest when they do happen. There may be many other similar cases of things that ought to be done which could be done if there was a will to get them done.  We had this suggestion of the Aireacht with regard to policy formulation in Departments, whether there should not be some unit in every Department which would meet the members of equivalent units in all Departments and be, as it were, a legislative review unit which would see to it, particularly in regard to non-contentious legislation of this kind, that it was got out quickly and not debated against the background of a fearful tragedy of this kind.  I make that as a practical suggestion.  I do not know whether there is any merit in it, but the present situation is defective.  It is very wrong indeed.  It is quite clear from the amendment to the Act that the defects were there independent of what happened in the Haughey case.  They were already known to the advisers to different Governments.  I take that as my first point and I regard it as an important first point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The second point is equally important. <Col N="50" /> I do not want to traipse off into generalities, but recently somebody commenting on another controversy referred to &ldquo;political lambegging&rdquo;.  The only justification for &ldquo;political lambegging&rdquo; or the only thing which would make it tolerable, and not as seriously damaging as it might otherwise be, is to have the Executive going about the business of governing seriously and the legislators doing the business of criticising and the Executive listening to the legislators when they are talking.  In this case the Minister has been listening to what was said in Dáil Éireann and we had a ministerial amendment in the Dáil which showed what further thought about any draft legislation can do.</P>
    <P>We have before us now another amendment which arises from a contribution made in the Dáil.  That is welcome.  It is good.  It is encouraging to the legislators to do their business with all the competition on them for their time.  Human beings tend to think a little too much about what will happen in the next six months and insufficiently about what will happen in the next six years.  I compliment the Minister on his reaction to the valid criticisms made in the other House.</P>
    <P>When we get to the proposed amendment, I will be asking am I correct in understanding that the application of the Criminal Procedure Act, 1967 means in effect that we are in a guilty or indictable situation, that the proceedings contemplated in the existing Act and the amendment Bill are summary proceedings punishable by a fine or imprisonment, or both, in which case you could have a proceeding with a conviction against the defendant.  Am I misunderstanding the application of the section of the Criminal Procedure Act, 1967, in construing it as meaning that the penalty and imprisonment provision for the minor offences only arises under that section of the Criminal Procedure Act if there is a plea of guilty, and where there is not a plea of guilty that section does not apply?  I may be wrong in that and, if that is so, are we left with the position that, if there is not a plea of guilty, there has got to be an indictment? If that is the position, I make no <Col N="51" /> criticism of it.  I just want to be clear that I know it is the position.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to me that it totally removes all difficulties that might arise from the Supreme Court not having solemnly pronounced on it.</P>
      <P>Is there provision here for recurring offences, or is that inherent in the whole affair?  On the first day a person may say: &ldquo;To hell with you, I am not giving evidence.&rdquo;  Shortly afterwards he is found guilty of an offence and is fined £500 and goes into court and sits happily there for the rest of the inquiry and there is no further offence he can be charged with.  I do not know anything about criminal law.  I just ask the question so that we can get it clarified.</P>
      <P>Section six covers the cost awarding procedure.  Is the section capable of the defence that any person may be named to pay any costs, any person named in the order, without necessarily notice having been given to him to be heard on the matter as to whether or not he should be required to pay the costs?  I should have thought that an amendment of that section could make it absolutely clear that there could not be a breach of natural justice involved for some person who spurned everything and was found to be responsible for what the facts disclosed, for one reason or another.  If he knew he had to pay X thousand pounds would he have the defence that the section which gave rise to the simple contract debt was defective in itself in that he had no reason to believe from the silent attitude of the members of the tribunal when he was giving his evidence that they would find him liable for everything and he did not know a single thing about it until suddenly he was told he had to pay the costs of the whole thing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I know the Minister had the Minister for Finance in mind, but that is easy enough to deal with.  I am thinking of a person other than the Minister for Finance who might find himself sueable as a simple contract debtor and who would be asking solicitors and barristers: &ldquo;Is there any way I can get out of this frightful bill?&rdquo;  They would look <Col N="52" /> at the section and say: &ldquo;Did you know anything about this?&rdquo;  He would say: &ldquo;Not until I was told to pay.&rdquo;  I would be afraid to mention the figure in case it would give rise to a further wage claim. A large sum of money might be involved in the award.  In that sort of situation people will go to great distances to see if they can get out of it.</P>
    <P>I thought the section could have been saved by putting a requirement on the tribunal.  No doubt it is open to the tribunal not to so order, but what is very likely to happen is that the tribunal will say: &ldquo;We have heard everything now. We have to go away and try to understand what we have heard and put our heads together and announce our judgment in due course&rdquo;, and we will find in the last paragraph something like &ldquo;Mr. A.B. or A.B. Ltd. to pay everything.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>They may not have said anything in the course of the hearing which would indicate that this was to be their finding. I should have thought that if they were finding that somebody was liable for the costs, he should be given a right to be heard as to why he should not be required to pay them.  After all, he will owe a big bill, or a small bill, or some kind of a bill, at the end of their decision on this matter, and he should be heard on it, or be free to be heard on it.  If the Minister wants to save his section and make quite sure that he recovers the money, he should not just think of the Minister for Finance.</P>
    <P>I am a little troubled about the question of assessors although I know the Minister has thought about this and has had the benefit of the Attorney General's thinking on it also.  Here again ignorance increases the number of words I use, because I am not as clear as I should be on what actually happens in the courts with regard to assessors.  I would have thought there was one distinction between the assessors in the courts and the assessors here.  In the case of the courts&mdash;I think I am right but I am guessing&mdash;the courts appoint the assessors. They choose the people apt for what they want to have assessed.  These are persons who, no doubt, they satisfy themselves are aptly qualified for the assessment. Therefore, they are in a control position which is very clear.  They <Col N="53" /> can tell the assessors what they want them to do, when they want to bring them in and make them act, and so on.</P>
    <P>Here we will have assessors appointed by the instrument setting up the tribunal which consists of one or more persons. Incidentally, I presume the Minister understands that he has beheaded the tribunal.  He has no chairman of the tribunal.  If I read correctly what he has done to the original Act, the chairman has disappeared with the deletion of subsection (2).  I do not know whether he wants to have a chairman but if he does he should describe him properly. Anybody might grab the chair first, but that might not be the most delicate way of exposing his authority.  The chairman should be named.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator looks at section six he will see the word &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Who picks the chairman?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>The chairman is already picked.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We read the papers but they are not always right. Would it be a good thing to provide &ldquo;consist of a chairman if there is more than one person&rdquo;?  I know common law says things are decided by majorities but a statutory tribunal is not an institution in the common law.  What if they disagree? Do they have to speak with one voice or with two?  I do not know anything about the miserable thing that happened down in Whiddy, but no doubt there are people on the other side who think they know this, that and the other thing.  I notice there is a provision there for a supplemental instrument.  I suppose that is there in case somebody dies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the instrument setting up the tribunal would appoint the chairman.  On the question of unanimity, in the event of there being more than one person the same situation would apply as would apply in the Supreme Court on a constitutional question. In other words, there would be only one report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="54" />
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it provided that there must be unanimity?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>There will be a report to the Government from the tribunal and in the event of there being more than one member sitting, that would be a unanimous report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I would have liked that to have been clearer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>While I accept the Senator's concern in relation to this and other matters, we could add so many more sections.  Within its terms of reference we should give the tribunal as free a hand as possible in relation to its own internal mechanics and procedure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>There might be value in my point about the assessors. I would have thought the tribunal will become better informed about this than anybody is at the moment.  Is the Minister satisfied that he has the powers to make a supplemental appointment of an assessor?  For example, the courts can appoint assessors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>The courts can appoint the assessors, as I understand it, under the rules of the superior courts, but the rules are silent on the exact functions of the assessors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>That is probably the way this should be too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>It should be in this instance, certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not dispute that.  The courts can get somebody else if they want to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>The tribunal should be left alone to conduct its own business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Say it does not have the right assessors?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I would fire the assessor and get in another one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not contemplated?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="55" />
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not contemplated, but I suggest the chairman of the tribunal would take that action in the event of having an unsatisfactory assessor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>He has no power to fire the assessor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I know he has no power to fire him directly, but I am sure he can tell him to disappear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Minister is being too serious about that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I am being very serious.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I invite him to be more serious still.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I will do my best.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The tribunal may consist of one or more than one person sitting with or without an assessor. The Minister is saying that if he finds the assessors he has are not adequate, he can sit without them.  I am talking about the situation where he wants an assessor to sit with him who knows about a particular branch of the subject.  How does he get him?  In the courts they can get him quite easily.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I will deal with that when I am replying to the Senator's contribution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good. The Minister in his speech dealt with a point concerning me.  I should be grateful if he would elaborate on how this question of privilege in publication of proceedings of the tribunal arises.  Is the Minister satisfied with the existing provisions, for example, for contemporaneous publication of court proceedings, with regard to the law of defamation; that the Defamation Act itself would save them in their contemporaneous publication of the proceedings of the tribunal?  I think the Minister is satisfied with it.  He seemed, if I understood him correctly, to deal with <Col N="56" /> this point when he was introducing the Bill, but perhaps he was referring to something else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardConroy" hpid="Professor Conroy Professor Conroy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Conroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to welcome this Bill and to congratulate the Minister on the speed with which it has been brought in and the alacrity with which it was realised that such an additional Bill was required in relation to a tribunal of inquiry.  I would like to join with the Cathaoirleach in the expression of sadness at the appalling tragic event which precipitated the need for both this Bill and the tribunal of inquiry.  The Bill before us is, of course, not specifically related to the particular disaster about which we all know and, as the Minister has indicated in his speech, there will, in due course, be an appropriate resolution, on which we can make our comments relative to that particular disaster, and to any particular tribunal which is set up to inquire into it.  This Bill introduces and, perhaps, brings to our attention certain general matters of principle.  Some of these I would very much like to welcome.  It is an excellent suggestion that witnesses brought before a tribunal who may not be very well off or who, if the tribunal is prolonged, would be taken away from their business or their affairs for a considerable period of time, should be without any undue financial hardship. That a tribunal should have the powers to do this is an excellent introduction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think it is also particularly relevant, in the modern situation, that the tribunal, or any tribunal, should have exceptionally wide powers as regards assessors. I am not a lawyer, but if I understand the position correctly, they are primarily there to provide expert or technical advice to a tribunal making an inquiry.  This may have been important in time past but it is infinitely more important now when matters of the most obscure advanced scientific nature may be extremely germane to any given inquiry. I can think of many circumstances in which it is absolutely essential. It is my opinion that a tribunal of inquiry should have the widest possible powers in relation to the appointment of an assessor or, if need be, assessors.  If the initial assessors are judged inadequate or unable, for one reason or <Col N="57" /> another, to give sufficient evidence, it should be possible to appoint further assessors. This is absolutely essential in the modern day and age.</P>
    <P>One further aspect of that which I hope will <i>de facto</i> be covered by the Bill and which is, perhaps, more relevant today than in the past, is the much more international scope of any tribunal of inquiry. The original Bill, as I understand it, and indeed much of what is in this Bill before us at the moment&mdash;might well be construed in a domestic sense, giving wide and full powers to a domestic tribunal of inquiry.  Of course we cannot exceed our legal jurisdiction in regard to witnesses and so on, and yet it is a fact that many inquiries, certainly inquiries into any form of marine disaster, air disaster or whatever of this nature, in actual fact involve not only international matters in the sense that the actual technical content might be of an international nature, but also the fact that those primarily involved might merely have been transients in this country, as in the case of an aeroplane flying over it, and that those primarily responsible might not only not be nationals of this State but may well have never entered the State; that it may be extremely difficult for a tribunal of inquiry to reach the actual people responsible.  The Minister has accepted that I am not entirely happy with the Bill.  There are many more things we would like to do.  I am not entirely happy that the law, as it stands at present, enables this country, or indeed any other, to effectively conduct an inquiry into matters which involve international affairs or multinational companies.  We will have to look at this aspect very closely indeed, both in general terms and in terms of the specific resolution relating to the disaster which is in all our minds at present.  This is a very crucial point.  It would be quite useless for a tribunal of inquiry to be merely able to bring as witnesses local employees, or local representatives, or local agents, of some international concern or company, persons or agents who are quite incapable, with the best will in the world, or under whatever compulsion of providing evidence which may be absolutely vital to any worthwhile inquiry. This is something which we will <Col N="58" /> have to look at and I imagine it would, in legal terms, be extremely difficult to do.  I am sure that in the present circumstances most reputable companies would fully co-operate but, nonetheless, it is something which we will have to bear very closely in mind.  Perhaps the Minister will explain; he refers in his speech to witnesses having a just cause or excuse for not attending.  I presume this is something we will leave to the discretion of the actual tribunal, as to what they would accept.  I would like to welcome the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>We, in the Labour Party in the Seanad, wish to be associated with the expressions of sympathy to the relatives and friends of those who lost their lives in this awful tragedy.  The Bill is, naturally, welcomed by all in the Labour Party and we wish to see its speedy passing through the Seanad.  I hope there will be no delay in setting up the tribunal and that both Houses will very soon get an opportunity to have a wide discussion on the motion to establish the tribunal.</P>
      <P>The Minister refers in his Second Stage speech to the terms of reference. These will provide for a much wider debate.  While the Bill itself contains very effective amendments to the Tribunals of Inquiry Act, 1931, the terms of reference will be of tremendous importance.  I cannot imagine that we will never again be in a similar situation and having regard to all the interests that would have to be served, I say that the terms of reference will be very important indeed.  They would be of great concern to the relatives and friends of all the victims; they will be of great concern to the people of south-west Cork and the country as a whole.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am one who complains very often about the privileged and favoured sections of the community.  I would like to take this opportunity of saying that in my opinion the terms of reference will be also of extreme importance to the Gulf Oil Corporation.  That is why I think that there will be plenty of scope when we get to the point where, in fact, we have a clear indication of what the terms of reference will be.  I do not think this is the time to start attributing blame; it <Col N="59" /> would not be appropriate and I should probably be ruled out of order, anyway. The other House has dealt with this Bill and we are now charged with putting it through this House.  Had I been speaking before Senator FitzGerald, I should have made an appeal that the people in the Seanad with legal minds would assist the House on this Bill in such a way that the lawyers acting for either side, when the tribunal is established, would be left with as little scope as possible to argue on the tribunal's authority or claim that it is what it is not meant to be or should be.  I should have appealed, had I been the first speaker, to those legal people in the House to assist where possible, the close examination of the Bill.  I look at the Bill and I can find no flaws in it but I have not the legal mind to examine it in depth. I would appeal for that to be done.  I missed Senator FitzGerald's speech but have no doubt he probably did raise some technicalities and that satisfies the situation from my point of view.</P>
    <P>I am also very pleased that the provisions refer misdemeanours to another court.  This is not the time to lay blame, but it is unfortunate that we have to have terrible tragedies before we see the need for stronger legislation, but that is one of those things in life; it is inevitable.  I welcome also the aspect of the Bill to bring about the fullest possible participation by witnesses and to protect against false evidence being given.  It is a very good development and will strengthen the Act.  It is worrying to the ordinary person that we seem to have advance protective legislation when dealing with banking, industry and industrial grants but when it comes to dealing with the safety of the person we do not seem to be so well equipped.  This is really a pity. I do not suppose we shall ever be able to do that to any effective degree, but we can do it in some areas.  We could in framing our legislation have regard to this, particularly in view of the type of industry developing or coming into the country at present.  We are going to be faced with more of these problems in the future, whether it be the nuclear energy developments in Wexford&mdash;I do not know whether that will become a reality <Col N="60" /> or not&mdash;or whether it be more exploration by oil companies.  We should try to pay as much attention as possible to the protection of the person in whatever legislation we draw up.  We exercise foresight in other areas; it should also be possible in this area.</P>
    <P>It is the job of the tribunal to discover where the blame lies.  They will decide whether or not the safety of the person was protected.  When we are drawing up legislation we should try as far as possible to see that any legislation enabling people to set up business has a very deep commitment to, and concern about, the safety of the person.</P>
    <P>Another point, which may be premature or irrelevant, is that we are going to have many French witnesses. There is a great difference between interpretation and translation.  I trust that that has been one of the considerations when dealing with the terms of reference.</P>
    <P>I have no argument with the setting up of the tribunal and I trust the integrity of the people who comprise it.  It is stressed in the Offical Report of the Dáil debate that the tribunal be held where the incident took place.  I am not too worried about that.  If the tribunal is established and if we accept that the people are of integrity&mdash;which, not doubt will be the case&mdash;and we accept the legislation as it is framed with the amendments, and accept that they are effective enough, it is irrelevant where the tribunal sits.  It might be psychologically good, from the point of view of the people living in the area, but not from the point of view of the French witnesses who have to come to give evidence, so it is a toss of the coin, really. I have no great difficulty about that, even though I agree with some of the remarks made about accommodation, air facilities and so on being available there.</P>
    <P>I shall end by saying that I trust the tribunal's findings will satisfy.  The legislation we are about to pass today, and I hope it is passed very quickly, will obviously be needed in new situations and in other tribunals.  That is why I have made the appeal to the legal people here to see that the Bill gives the lawyers on either side as little scope as possible.  I <Col N="61" /> know that is a peculiar request to put to lawyers.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mícheál Cranitch Mícheál Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a very welcome Bill and, in the context of Senator FitzGerald's opening remarks, we may truly say: &ldquo;Más maith is mithid&rdquo;.  We may sometimes ask ourselves, faced with an emergency, why such and such a regulation or an Act is not before us today.  There are parts of Ireland where we can point to what is now a safe, straight stretch of road which was not very long ago a dangerous bend and nobody thought of doing anything about it until some unfortunate person lost his life.  Arrangements were then made to have the corner removed and the roads straightened to make them safe.</P>
      <P>The tribunal cannot be set up until this Bill becomes law; then it will be set up and the inquiry can go ahead.  The Minister in his Second Stage speech says that we will then have a further opportunity of discussing the whole matter, and I very much look forward to that stage.  I shall not indulge in any futile speculation as to what was or was not the cause of this, that or the other thing leading to the terrible disaster.  The time for that will come later on.</P>
      <P>I am very glad to see that the Minister intends to bring in an amendment in connection with penalties, and has given particulars of these.  The amendment will make the offences in question indictable offences, that is to say, there will be a right to trial on indictment before a judge and jury, with penalties of a fine of up to £10,000, or up to two years imprisonment, or both.  In the Bill as initiated, we have reference to a fine not exceeding £500 or, at the discretion of the court, imprisonment for a term not exceeding 12 months.  A fine of £500 in this day and age is unacceptable.</P>
      <P>Finally, in the closing stages of his speech, the Minister says:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is an urgent measure made necessary by a very tragic event.  It would, of course, be better if there had been more time available to devote to it.  If such were the case, it might have been possible to consider repealing in full the old 1921 Act.  That would <Col N="62" /> however have produced unacceptable delay because a great deal more consultation would have been necessary. This Bill introduces only those changes which are considered to be essential to enable the tribunal which is to be set up shortly to function effectively. I hope that Senators will view the Bill in that light.</P>
    <P>Well, indeed, we do.  I make the suggestion that, at some future date, the Minister would consider going into that very point and bringing in a comprehensive Bill which will give the widest possible powers, or make such powers available to a tribunal which will be set up.  As sure as we had that terrible disaster, we will have other such disasters in the years to come, we hope not for a long time.  These things do happen and it is well to have our legislation ready so that tribunals and courts of inquiry can be established without any delay.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Mr. D. Andrews) David Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Mr. D. Andrews)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am most grateful to the House for the various views expressed.  If I may say so, the last view expressed by Senator Cranitch was an excellent and succinct contribution.  I often think that contributions in this House and in the other House are the better for being brief.  It is a pleasure to learn from the experts and I congratulate the Senators in that regard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Cranitch referred to the need for more time for the drafting of the Bill. I accept that point entirely, but here you have a situation which demanded urgency and the Bill was needed so that this particular tragedy in the nation's history could be dealt with immediately. Also, the Bill itself, as drafted, will amend and incorporate the provisions of the 1921 Act.  As regards the drafting of a Bill of the magnitude he would wish for, account must be taken of the mechanics of how a Bill is actually given birth to and how it grows to be a full person in the context of a Bill.  As I understand the situation, a scheme is prepared by the Department concerned, for example, by the Department of Justice and the Attorney General in this instance, and sent to the Government.  It <Col N="63" /> is then sent to the other Departments for comments.  It is returned to the Government and the Government approve it or add to it or amend it and it is then sent back to the Department concerned. After it has been drafted by the parliamentary draftsmen it is sent to the Government and the First Reading is then given in this House or the other House and the Bill is circulated to Members.  If we had decided to replace the entire 1921 Act we would not, because of the inevitable delays involved, have a Bill of this nature at this time.  It might be months in the future before we would.</P>
    <P>Senator Cranitch has a personal interest in the Bantry area and has spent his energy and time, with the other public representatives in the area, trying to alleviate the pain suffered by the various people during and after the tragedy.  He welcomed the amendment to add indictable offences, and this has been generally welcomed by those Senators who contributed to this legislation. It was people like Senator Cranitch, and indeed, in fairness, the Opposition in Dáil Éireann, who were responsible for the Minister for Justice recommending this particular amendment of the creation of an indictable offence, with trial by judge and jury, a fine of £10,000 and/or a prison term of two years.</P>
    <P>People have commented on the minor offence dealt with by a district justice summarily, with a fine of up to £500 and/or up to 12 months' imprisonment. We should not so much be looking at the financial penalty, which is important in itself, but rather at the prison deterrent. We are dealing with people who in the nature of things would be in awe of the courts of the land and in awe, by definition, of the tribunal.  I think that the people would be experiencing for the first time a tribunal of this nature and never have been inside a court in their lives.  Consequently, I believe that the imprisonment penalty is the real deterrent, and in that regard in addition to the summary offence, we are adding by way of amendment the indictable offence I have outlined.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="64" /> Senator FitzGerald made the point, with some justification, in his usual excellent contribution to the Seanad about the delay in amending the 1921 Act.  The blame for this, if there is to be blame, must be shared by those who are in Government and had the opportunity in Government to amend the Act.  Consequently, this Fianna Fáil Government, the last Coalition Government and previous Governments must share the blame, if there is to be blame apportioned. However, I do not think we are in the business of apportioning blame in this regard.  We are trying to deal as expeditiously as possible with a problem that must be dealt with urgently.  I should like to point out that, as Senator FitzGerald is aware, the staff resources necessary to keep all legislation up to date are not available although I feel that there may be an improvement in this regard in the not too distant future.</P>
    <P>In relation to the question of offences under the Bill the ordinary legal situation will apply.  I believe the question was in relation to recurring offences.  Was that the expression Senator FitzGerald used?</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Continuing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>However, under the Bill the ordinary legal situation will apply. Each time an offence is committed there can be a new prosecution on a separate count.  It is thought preferable to adopt this approach rather than attempt to draft a recurring offence provision. I am sure the Senator will appreciate our concern in that regard.  We could run into difficulty in relation to the defence of <i>aut refois convict.</i></P>
      <P>Senator FitzGerald raised the question of assessors.  It is a moot point whether there is any disadvantage in allowing a tribunal to appoint the assessors. The tribunal will have full control over the assessors and their role.  That is the important thing.  The Government, in appointing these assessors, could always consult with the proposed members of the tribunal but I feel the tribunal should have flexibility in this regard.  I do not think we should be too specific in regard to the appointment of these assessors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator FitzGerald raised the question of the awarding of costs against a <Col N="65" /> person who is not present at the inquiry. I believe the discretion of the tribunal could be exercised in this way.  For example, it occurs to me that the tribunal could invite a person against whom it is intended to award costs to attend the tribunal to be told why costs have been awarded against him.  That would be the answer to it.  I agree that the principles of natural justice which have been raised by the Senator would be of particular concern to a person like the judge who is to be the chairman of the proposed Whiddy Tribunal.  Having regard to his experience as a High Court Judge, he would ensure that the principles of natural justice are not overridden by the absence of that person or persons against whom it is intended to award costs.  Also in regard to costs, the question of the application of equity comes in.  I mentioned that in my speech.</P>
    <P>Senator Conroy mentioned the international aspects of this matter.  The 1921 Act allows for the taking of evidence on commission or abroad but witnesses outside this jurisdiction cannot be compelled to attend.  The position here, is the same as in the general law, where, for example, even in a murder case a vital witness outside the jurisdiction could not be compelled to attend.  Unfortunately, that is the reality of the situation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardConroy" hpid="Professor Conroy Professor Conroy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Conroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought there was some way in which international companies involved could at least be encouraged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>There should be some persuasiveness in relation to it by the international companies involved and I am sure that they will take account of what has been stated in the Houses of the Oireachtas.  It is an important point. They would be in dereliction of their duty if they did not ask in a persuasive fashion for the presence of an important witness.  I am satisfied that they will take the Senator's point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Harte made a comprehensive survey of the Bill and was humble enough&mdash;humility is a very important ingredient&mdash;to accept that Senator FitzGerald had made the legal points. He made the point that the safety of persons should be the primary concern <Col N="66" /> of any Government or, indeed, of any Act concerned with person or persons.  I accept that entirely.  He raised a point for the first time about the question of French witnesses coming to the tribunal and the need for interpreters.  He can take it that that will be provided for.  The location of the tribunal was also raised by Senator Harte and whilst it has been suggested that the location should be in the Bantry area he did not necessarily favour that.  The location is not strictly relevant because we want to get at the truth as to what happened.  Whether it is in Bantry, in Cork, Limerick, Galway or Dublin I do not think it will make any difference to the efficacy of the tribunal. The air in Bantry is very good and the people there are very hospitable people as, indeed, was witnessed by their concern at the time of this desperate tragedy.  They were wonderful in every respect.  I had the opportunity of being there for almost half a day at the time of the tragedy on behalf of the Government. Senator Harte said that the location of the tribunal was not the relevant thing, rather it was the findings of the tribunal which were important.</P>
    <P>I should like to return to the question raised by Senator Conroy of disobeying a summons.  The question as to whether a cause or excuse is just will be a matter for the courts if the person is prosecuted.  However, in the first instance it is a matter for the tribunal to accept or to reject the particular excuse offered.</P>
    <P>I should like to pay tribute to the Opposition here and in the Dáil for this all-party approach.  It has been very helpful and, as Senator FitzGerald has said, the attitude adopted by the Minister for Justice can only merit the highest of praise, in regard to amendments proposed, in fairness, as a result of discussions between the Minister and Members of the Opposition in the Dáil. It has been a worthwhile exercise.  I would very much appreciate if the Seanad would allow me the Committee Stage and subsequent Stages.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence)" RHead="(Amendment) Bill, 1979: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Private Business. - Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence) (Amendment) Bill, 1979: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="67" /> Sections 1 and 2 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 1 and 2 are cognate and may be discussed together.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 2, line 22, the delete &ldquo;following subsection&rdquo; and to substitute &ldquo;following subsections&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Justice (Mr. D. Andrews) David Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Justice (Mr. D. Andrews)</NameTxt>
      <P>The attitude adopted in the other House, arising from the consensus between the Minister for Justice and the Opposition spokesman who contributed so ably to the debate in that House, led to this amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 3 to delete lines 6 to 9 and to substitute the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;the person shall be guilty of an offence.</P>
      <P>(2A)  (a)  A person guilty of an offence under this section shall be liable on conviction on indictment to a fine not exceeding £10,000 or, at the discretion of the court, to imprisonment for a term not exceeding 2 years or to both such fine and such imprisonment.</P>
      <P>(b)  A justice of the District Court shall have jurisdiction to try summarily an offence under this section if&mdash;</P>
      <P>(i)  the justice is of opinion that the facts proved or alleged against a defendant charged with such an offence constitute a minor offence fit to be tried summarily,</P>
      <P>(ii)  the Director of Public Prosecutions consents, and</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="68" /> (iii)  the defendant (on being informed by the justice of his right to be tried by a jury) does not object to being tried summarily,</P>
    <P>and, upon conviction under this paragraph, the said defendant shall be liable to a fine not exceeding £500 or, at the discretion of the court, to imprisonment for a term not exceeding 12 months or to both such fine and such imprisonment.</P>
    <P>(c)  Section 13 of the Criminal Procedure Act, 1967, shall apply in relation to an offence under this section as if, in lieu of the penalties specified in subsection (3) of that section there were specified therein the penalties provided for by paragraph (b) of this subsection, and the reference in subsection (2) (a) of that section to the penalties provided for in subsection (3) of that section shall be construed accordingly.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to</P>
    <P>Section 3, as amended, agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 4 and 5 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 6 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to earn any discredit by using more words than necessary but I would like the Minister to comment on this section and on what I said on Second Reading in regard to it.  I said it was dangerous to have such a provision.  A real defect is being repaired and I accept that but it is dangerous to repair it in such a way as to leave any defect in it.  We have here a bald provision.  The tribunal is not a court though it has power to make certain orders, which cannot be looked at as always consisting of one or more persons who are judges and, therefore, conscious of what judges should do.  It is dangerous to have a provision whereby any person may be named in the order to pay all the costs without it being provided in the section which gives rise to the order that in relation to the making of that order he is to be heard, as a matter not of the good exercise of a <Col N="69" /> judge of his natural equitable discretion but as a statutory obligation that he should do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has made his usual perceptive observations on the section.  I would respectfully suggest to him that the section has built into it the safeguard that the tribunal, in coming to such a conclusion in relation to the awarding of costs to one person against another, must be of the opinion that there are sufficient reasons rendering it equitable to do so.  In that regard, whilst I accept the Senator's point about the fact that there is a judicial personage present&mdash;we already know whom he is&mdash;and that the other people may not necessarily be judges or persons with specific knowledge of the law, they would be guided by the chairman's deep knowledge of matters of this kind.  In that regard we need not have any fears.  I can understand the Senator's concern in this regard.  It is a genuine concern, a concern well expressed, but one will find that the chairman, or the persons assisting the chairman, will be very conscious of their obligations in regard to the hardships which might or might not be caused by the absence of a person who will find himself the following day being told that the tribunal had awarded costs against him.  The tribunal will be well aware of the situation and will take it seriously into account.  I could not envisage the tribunal awarding costs against the best interests of natural justice.  We know that one of the main principles of natural justice is that a person should be heard in his or her own cause, and can be represented in that cause.  I must tell the Senator that this point that he has raised in relation to section 6 is well catered for by the personnel of the tribunal and by the personage of the judge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The other aspect is that the Supreme Court has held, in the East Donegal Marts case, 1970 Irish Reports, page 317, that there is a presumption that discretions and adjudications which are permitted or provided for by a post-1937 Act, such as, for example, this Bill, will be conducted in accordance with the provisions of constitutional justice.  Not only do we presume that natural justice <Col N="70" /> will be applied but constitutional justice also.  That is the post-1937 presumption. This was articulated in that case.  I have that case in front of me and, to be absolutely honest, do not know anything about it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We are united in ignorance but I must persist to get expunged one delusion from the Minister's mind.  If that is the achievement of the day, it will be much.  That is that in this section and its language there is no relevance whatever to the tribunal that is now to be established to the validity of my point with regard to this section which is going to affect every other tribunal that may ever be appointed by virtue of the Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence) Acts, 1921 to 1979. Therefore, we must contemplate that there will be men not aware of these matters sitting on these tribunals some day.  We must see that such men are enlightened by our requiring them to do certain things before certain consequences follow.</P>
      <P>It is one thing to have the Minister for Finance deciding that he will go and look for a Vote for the thing, whether he should or should not is another matter in any given case but it is another thing to enact that some individual or body corporate is going to be made pay.  It is essential that we see that if they are going to be made pay they really are going to be made pay in such a way that they are liable and that the tribunal will do everything it ought to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I confess that I started off with some doubt about the validity of this section and some doubt about this matter of awarding costs.  I hope that the Minister is satisfied and is so advised that this is definitely not a judicial function.  I know we have this costs-awarding operation going on under various other tribunals of one kind or another but I have not had an opportunity of studying the various Acts.  For example, I think there is something like this in the town planning code and in relation to rating and that there are various other codes.  I would like to see this being as good and as justifiable.  I do not know to what extent the post-1937 point will be affected by a pre-1937 tribunal.  It is a tribunal set up <Col N="71" /> under an Act which is the Principal Act. A tribunal set up before the Constitution was set up by the enactment of &ldquo;the King's most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons ....&rdquo;  That is the preamble, or the opening words, of the Principal Act that we started off from.  I do not know whether the Supreme Court has been busy on that kind of situation.  On this question of recovery of expenses, when we are facing into this type of situation, and many others like them, it is terribly important to get this section right.  If there is anything wrong with adding a few words a few hours do not make that much difference to get it right if it can be strengthened in any way by a requirement that such an order shall not first be made without the person in question being given an opportunity to make his case as to why it should not be made against him.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>It is funny that the Senator should raise this point, because I raised this very point with the people who came to me with this Bill in the first instance and I was assured by them that, in fact, the Bill is watertight in regard to the point the Senator has raised.  As I have already mentioned, there is, in fact a constitutional presumption in relation to post-1937 statutes, that the court will act in accordance with constitutional justice.  They would not award costs, for example, in the absence of, as the Senator said, a body corporate or a person.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not a court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that, but there is the presumption that they will act in the manner I have outlined.  I might also remind the Senator that, whilst he makes the point about the costs and the awarding of costs, the question of costs arises in the 1979 Bill and there is no mention whatever of it in the 1921 Act.  All I can do is express the view that I raised the same point and that, having raised it, I had to be <Col N="72" /> satisfied on it.  The information and explanations I received were as I have articulated in my Second Stage speech.  I accept full responsibility and I will be the first to apologise to the Senator if the situation occurs which he envisages.  I do not think the exta words are necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Minister is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope I am right also.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 7 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported with amendments, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Electricity (Supply) (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1978: Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Private Business. - Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Bill, 1978: Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Energy (Mr. R. Burke) Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Energy (Mr. R. Burke)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Energy (Mr. R. Burke)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill is two-fold&mdash;to give statutory authority to the ESB's existing consultancy and advisory services work; and to increase to £1,200 million the existing statutory limit of £700 million on total expenditure by the ESB for capital purposes. Senators will be aware that the primary function of the ESB under the Electricity Supply Acts is to ensure the adequate supply and distribution of electricity throughout the State.  This is the reason for their existence and they have a standing remit from the Minister for Industry, Commerce and Energy and his predecessors to ensure that electricity is at no time in short supply.  The board have a number of other functions which I need not detail but these are subsidiary to their main function.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Since their establishment over 50 years ago the ESB have themselves carried out all design work on planning of power stations and on transmission and distribution lines, in this manner <Col N="73" /> gradually building-up a competent body of professional and technical staff covering a wide variety of specialised fields, including areas not directly related to the electricity supply industry, for example, fisheries.  Though there have been periods when demand for electricity was stagnant, over the past 50 years or so as a whole there has been a steady growth in the demand for electricity which necessitated frequent additions to generating, transmission and distribution capacity.  A brief comparison of the scale of operations in recent years with the scale in the early years is instructive.</P>
    <P>In the year ended 31 March 1930 the ESB generated 60 million units of electricity, some 43 million of which were sold to less than 50,000 customers; total revenue was less than £500,000.  In the year ended 31 March 1978 the corresponding figures were 8,800 million units generated of which 7,300 million were sold to nearly one million customers, total revenue being £210 million.</P>
    <P>The recession in recent years resulted in a fall in demand for electricity with the result that provision of new generating capacity was put off as long as possible and proposals for further expansion were deferred.  With the fall-off in electricity demand the board found themselves with surplus capacity among their highly-skilled professional and technical staff.  At about that time Córas Tráchtála indicated that there were openings abroad for ESB expertise and, with the consent of the then Minister for Transport and Power, the board ventured into the overseas consultancy and advisory services work early in 1975. The primary purpose of this radical development was to utilise the surplus staff capacity then available in the board by taking up the slack and in this manner protect employment.</P>
    <P>I am pleased to tell the House that the results of the board's overseas venture have been encouraging.  In all, work has been undertaken for electricity utilities in fifteen countries, but the board's major effort has been concentrated in Bahrain and in Saudi Arabia.  In Bahrain an average of up to 60 staff of all disciplines have been seconded to bring the managerial, financial and technical <Col N="74" /> aspects of the Bahrain State Electricity Directorate up to international standard.</P>
    <P>A recent report by an independent Swedish consultant recommended that the ESB be retained until an adequate standard is reached in Bahrain.  I feel that this reflects creditably on the board. In Saudi Arabia the board have been appointed consultants for the management of two regional electrification schemes including tender assessment, design approvals, supervision of construction, commissioning and overall financial management of the projects.  There are several other areas where the board have succeeded in winning, on merit alone, useful contracts, but Senators will probably think it unnecessary for me to indicate them in detail.  Let me say, however, that the ESB are alert all the time to the possibilities inherent in selling their expertise and specialised knowledge in those areas or countries where there is a demand for them.</P>
    <P>A satisfactory feature of the board's overseas involvement has been its extension from ESB staff going abroad on assignments to foreign staff coming to Ireland for training.  For example, about 90 engineers and technicians from Nigeria have already been trained in Ireland and are now back home successfully operating a new power station there; a further 29 Nigerians are in training at present and there are good prospects, I am told, of further substantial numbers of trainees being sent here.</P>
    <P>A major Saudi Arabian training contract has been secured with 32 staff from that country attending an English language school in Dublin for six months before undergoing a 12 months training course in the ESB.  These examples serve to illustrate the wide-ranging scope of the board's activities and the possibilities that have been opened-up since they embarked on their overseas venture.</P>
    <P>In addition to overseas consultancy and advisory services work the ESB have also engaged to some extent in consultancy work at home, in areas where they have and are known to have special expertise not otherwise available within the country.  Their services have been utilised by a number of public bodies or enterprises in this country, including the <Col N="75" /> Dublin Port and Docks Board, Bord Gáis and AnCO.  Whilst the ESB have been careful not to trespass on the field traditionally served by the consulting engineering profession in Ireland and have given assurances to this effect, I am particularly concerned that there should be no cause whatever for legitimate complaint by established consultants here about the nature and extent of the board's consultancy operations.  I have therefore sought and obtained from the board a positive undertaking that they will not interfere with the activities of other Irish consultants who have the competence to carry out the relevant project work in Ireland.</P>
    <P>I am confident that this undertaking will allay any fears that may have been entertained as to the nature of the board's activities in this field.  In these circumstances I am disposed to agree that the ESB should be authorised to engage in consultancy work at home to an extent consistent with full compliance with their undertaking to me.  It is my intention nonetheless to keep the board's activities as consultants under periodic review.</P>
    <P>The Bill provides that expenditure on consultancy work shall not exceed revenue, and I have arranged that the ESB will prepare separate accounts for inclusion in their annual report to me which will show clearly all relevant financial aspects of their consultancy activities. In this regard I should like to mention that in the three years ending 31 March 1978 the excess of income over expenditure on consultancy work, after allowing for all salaries, expenses, promotional costs and overheads, was about £1 million.  Apart from this favourable financial outturn, and the enhanced international status which we have acquired, it is worth noting that the ESB involvement in these large foreign assignments has drawn the attention of various public and private purchasing agencies to the possibilities of doing other kinds of business with Ireland, and as a result substantial exports of industrial goods have taken place to these areas.</P>
    <P>The ESB have kept in close touch all along both with my Department and <Col N="76" /> with the Department of Foreign Affairs as to their overseas activities.  I will, however, be consulting with the Minister for Foreign Affairs in advance of any future commitments which the board may propose to enter into in connection with their overseas business.  The Government regard this as a necessary step to ensure the closest possible cooperation and mutual understanding between the board and the Government Departments concerned.</P>
    <P>The undertaking of consultancy work overseas does not appear to come within the ESB's statutory powers as laid down in the Electricity Supply Acts, and there may also be some doubt that such work at home is covered by existing legislation. The board have found the lack of clear statutory authority to be a disadvantage on several occasions when contracts were being negotiated.  I am, therefore, promoting this legislation to eliminate any problems which the absence of statutory authority might create for the ESB in negotiating successfully for contracts or commissions.</P>
    <P>I now come to the other purpose of this Bill, which is to provide for an increase in the limit of capital expenditure by the board from £700 million to £1,200 million.  The existing statutory limit on capital expenditure by the ESB was fixed by the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1974 at £700 million.  The total capital expenditure approved by the board to date has risen to a figure little short of £700 million.  Whilst actual expenditure to date by the board only amounts to about £600 million or so, the standing practice is that proposals for capital expenditure are not approved by the board unless the total of the proposed expenditure, aggregated with previous expenditure and commitments to expenditure, is less than the statutory limit.  As further commitments to substantial additional expenditure by the board will shortly arise it is necessary, therefore, to increase the statutory limit.</P>
    <P>Senators will be aware that the electricity supply industry is largely capital-intensive and that the ensuring of an adequate supply of electricity in compliance with their remit necessitates heavy levels of capital expenditure by <Col N="77" /> the board virtually every year.  As the lead-times with capital investments in the electricity sector tend to be long the ESB must always look well ahead when formulating their capital programme. The board tell me that, during the year ended 31 March 1978, growth in electricity demand showed an 8.2 per cent increase over the previous year and the indications are that this level of growth is being maintained during the current year.  The ESB viewpoint, with which I broadly agree, is that they must plan ahead for an average growth rate in electricity demand of 8.5 per cent per annum over the next decade, but with an inbuilt strategy of maximum flexibility to respond to fluctuations in growth above or below the 8.5 per cent level.</P>
    <P>The existing generating capacity of the board's system is about 2,540 megawatts.  The Poolbeg station extension which is expected to come into commission very shortly will add 270 MW to the system whilst a further 80 MW generating capacity will come available when the industrial dispute at Marina has concluded.  The new station at Aghada, which is expected to come on-stream sometime in 1980, and the extensions to the Shannonbridge and Lanesborough stations expected to be completed about 1983-84, will between them add another 350 MW to the system.  This makes for a total capacity of 3,240 MW.  The cost of all new generating capacity, either already provided or in course of provision, is within the existing £700 million capital expenditure limit.</P>
    <P>To meet the projected growth requirements over the next decade, the board expect that they will have to approve over the next two years or so of further capital expenditure totalling about £500 million on provision of new generating capacity, additional and ancillary transmission and distribution lines, new premises and other miscellaneous items. Actual expenditure of this magnitude will not, of course, arise in the next two years or so but will be spread over a number of years up to 1985 or thereabouts.</P>
    <P>I am, therefore, providing in this Bill for an increase of £500 million in the existing statutory limit on capital expenditure <Col N="78" /> by the ESB, bringing the total permitted capital outlay by the board to £1,200 million.</P>
    <P>Before I elaborate on the purposes to which the proposed £500 million capital expenditure by the board will be put it might be useful if I reminded the House that essentially all that the ESB are proposing to do is to meet their expected consumer demand.  Senators are, no doubt, aware that electricity cannot be stored and that, therefore, sufficient generating capacity must always be available to the ESB to enable them to meet demand as and when it arises, if shortages of electricity with all the inconveniences and hardship that such shortages would entail are not to arise. Last year the ESB consumed 2.23 MTOE&mdash;million tonnes of oil equivalent&mdash;some 67 per cent of which comprised imported oil.  As of now the best available estimates suggest that the ESB will consume 5.5 MTOE by 1990. How best to meet this increased requirement is the problem.</P>
    <P>For a number of years past the ESB, like most other electricity utilities, have largely relied on oil as their primary energy feedstock mainly because of its cheapness, ready availability and versatility. Oil, however, is no longer cheap and there is no guarantee as to its continued availability in the future.  In an uncertain energy world it would be foolhardy to ignore these facts; it would also be foolish to forget that oil is a finite resource and that demand for it over the world as a whole is increasing.  The inescapable conclusion is that we must lessen our existing near-75 per cent level of dependence on imported oil as much as we can.  In our circumstances this can best be achieved by adopting the right policies in respect of the electricity generation programme.  That is why I recently sanctioned the provision of a major coal-fired station and also why I will not permit the ESB to construct any more generating stations to be fuelled by imported oil.</P>
    <P>Whilst I am hopeful that we can arrange in the not-too-distant future interconnection with the EEC electricity grid, with all the mutual advantages to member states to be derived therefrom, we must ensure at the same time that we <Col N="79" /> have optimum diversification in our generating plant programme at home.</P>
    <P>A large part of the £500 million proposed expenditure will be committed to the new coal-fired station which is expected to come on-stream about 1985, but there are other items and it might be helpful if I gave an approximate break-down of the total:</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="40*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
            </entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">£ million</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>New coal-fired station including provision for full site development works such as jetties, roadways and buildings as well as turbines, boilers and ancillary equipment for 2×300 MW units</entry>
            <entry>350</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Distribution system arising out of the need to provide electricity supply to an additional 25-30,000 customers each year</entry>
            <entry>60</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Transmission lines to provide improved supply to consumers, especially in outlying areas</entry>
            <entry>20</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Premises such as new district and area offices, and related items</entry>
            <entry>20</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Miscellaneous including provision for peak-load plant (small turbines) to meet sudden heavy demands for electricity</entry>
            <entry>50</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>500</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>This break-down is indicative only, and not definitive, but what I should like to make clear to Senators is that no provision is being made at this stage for capital expenditure on the ESB nuclear project.  Though this project was approved in principle by the then Government almost exactly five years ago there is no question of it now being proceeded with until the Government have fully assessed all the energy options now open to us, and made up their minds as to the nature and extent of the generating capacity needed to meet our expected electricity needs in the coming decade and beyond.  In this regard I have been impressed by the public reaction generally to, and understanding of, our major energy problems following the publication some months ago of the Energy-Ireland discussion document.  As I have already indicated, any submissions by <Col N="80" /> interested parties on this very important question will be fully considered by the Government.</P>
    <P>As I have already indicated elsewhere I will be putting my proposals in the matter to the Government in the near future.  If the Government should decide not to over-rule the existing decision of the last Government and that the ESB nuclear project should be processed further in accordance with the 1973 decision, a period of 18-24 months to permit of assembling of the ESB nuclear team, updating of plans and preparation of specifications, inviting tenders and so on will elapse from the date of the Government decision before there will be any question of acceptance of tenders and thus of an irrevocable commitment to the project arising.  I wish to make it very clear that before this final commitment stage is reached it will be necessary to place before the Oireachtas proposals to increase the ESB capital expenditure limits to cover nuclear station costs. Senators are thus guaranteed an opportunity for full debate on this issue before there can be any commitment by the ESB to building a nuclear station.</P>
    <P>I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeJMcCartin" hpid="Mr. McCartin Mr. McCartin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCartin</NameTxt>
      <P>While we welcome the provisions of this Bill which facilitate the varied expanding operations of the ESB I will deal briefly with the Minister's last point.  While it is always reassuring to know that both Houses will have the opportunity to have a full debate on the whole question of nuclear energy before any decisions are finally taken by the Government, nevertheless that is hardly sufficient assurance to satisfy the public generally who have taken such an interest in this matter over the last few years.  The longer this question goes on not only do the costs double from year to year but the question of pollution risks, danger to the environment, health and so on, become more serious as time goes on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>While on the one hand I accept the possibility that technology and science will reduce the risks, on the other hand through the years the public have experienced disasters, such as the recent disaster which happened in spite of all the assurances engineers and qualified <Col N="81" /> people could give us.  In spite of all the best brains and best intentions of planners, things will go wrong.  As our society makes progress, more of these weaknesses will come to light, more serious situations will develop and the number of people who take a direct interest in such questions will increase. Their views will be more educated and their political muscle will be strong.  For all these reasons a full and public discussion should start now on the whole question of nuclear energy.  We should set aside a year in which the maximum opportunity would be given to everybody with an interest in this subject to have their say, to listen to the experts, to advise the Government and the public generally.  I do not think this creates any problems for the Government.  As time goes on, it can only make the weighty decisions the Government have to make easier and it can only create a situation in which the public have complete confidence. I have complete confidence.  I know nobody in the Department of Industry, Commerce and Energy will take unnecessary risks.</P>
    <P>There are many people, even educated and concerned people, who do not understand the workings of these Departments, who still see behind the doors of Merrion Street and Kildare Street the faceless people making the decisions. Sometimes they may even consider them heartless.  While I do not see the situation like that, I think a full and open discussion on the whole question&mdash;call it an inquiry if you like&mdash;should take place.  If this has been done, all the matters have been teased out, and all the experts have given their evidence publicly, the position of the Government will be more viable.  When the Government eventually make their decision there is no reason why we should expect any disasters, but should things go wrong, even to a small extent, the Government will be more in the open than they will if decisions are taken without such an inquiry.</P>
    <P>I welcome the provision of the extra capital for the ESB and I welcome their expansion and development, particularly into the whole business of consultancy work and the supply of expertise and technology abroad.  It is a wonderful development that after our own experiences <Col N="82" /> here we have found within the organisation a surplus of brains, energy and expertise which we can export to our own profit and to the benefit of the people who need it.</P>
    <P>I would have thought entirely unnecessary the guarantees the Minister gave us regarding the whole question of competition by the ESB in their consultancy work with native industrialists, consultants, or whatever they may be.  I am not one of those people who is caught up in any ideological sense in the question of State or semi-State bodies as against private enterprise.  I have a completely open mind.  If a semi-State body, like the ESB, are in a position to go out on the open market and compete on fair terms with private individuals, I see no reason in the world why they would not be allowed to do that, assuming, of course, that that particular side of their operation is not subsidised from their profits which are made in the other areas in which they have a complete monopoly. On the other hand, I would deny to the ESB, or to any other semi-State body, the right to put themselves above competition from other sections.  The ESB have in the past been put into that position.  That gives rise to several questions.</P>
    <P>The question of personnel in the ESB came up in recent years&mdash;I did not know at what level it developed.  When a person wires private houses, industries, and so on, the ESB ask for a certificate showing that he was competent to do the work.  That should not be the question. The question should be whether the work is adequate and not whether the person has a certificate, or belongs to a particular union.  While I would give the ESB the right to compete, I would not deny to anybody the right to compete with them.  The same situation arises where individuals have built houses in country areas, sometimes in remote areas.  In the past they got subsidised supply, but at the moment these people who did not wisely calculate the cost of such connections are being faced with frightening bills for what I would say is a comparatively small amount of work.  If I say to those people that that is the cost to the ESB, that they cannot do it any cheaper and that the customers must <Col N="83" /> pay that amount, and if they come back and say that they want to put up those poles themselves and connect that service, the ESB will say that they may not do that.  I do not think the ESB should have the right to say that.  The individuals concerned should have the right to do their own servicing, provided always that that meets with the standards and specifications required for safety and all other reasons.</P>
    <P>The other question I would like to raise in this connection is that the Irish consumer cannot at any time, nor is he educated in any way to, know whether he is getting the supply of energy worth that money.  The average consumer has no idea what the cost of generating the power which he buys and pays for is, and he has no idea and no way of comparing it with what it costs in other countries.  At one stage I set out to establish whether industrialists who use a lot of electricity are getting it at a competitive rate.  From the facts and figures that are available from other countries, it would take some of the ESB experts to advise us what the real position is.  This is a subject on which the Minister should make it his business to educate the public and to inform us from time to time whether this supply is being sold to us at a competitive rate, since especially the company which supplies it is in a monopoly position.</P>
    <P>On the question of energy, which is an important matter at the moment, on the one hand we see the Electricity Supply Board advertising units, trying to sell their energy&mdash;and this may be what is economically right for them to do in the context of their own business&mdash;but on the other hand, we know that for every unit sold coal or oil has been imported that is costing our economy a lot of money.  There is not sufficient emphasis on the fact that we need to conserve energy.  We will now look at the question of the nuclear station and what it may cost&mdash;£400 million was the figure we heard in 1977, but the cost may be £700 million or £1,000 million before we get around to it.  We do not know where the money will come from and nobody has provided us with figures about how long <Col N="84" /> it would take to pay it back or what our requirements will be.  It is a very complicated subject.  We need not go into that aspect yet.  If the necessary steps were taken to conserve energy we would not need to face that problem for some years to come.  The average person building a house will not consider what it will cost to keep that house heated in one year or two years' time.  He will be more concerned about the cost of putting in double glazing or insulating the attic and so on.  The Government by way of an incentive should encourage house builders to insulate homes.</P>
    <P>The whole approach to this subject has been that energy could be generated from fresh air without any cost.  For years back there was not very much engineering advice into the design of houses available.  Even a casual observer could see that there has been an absolute waste of energy in almost every house that has been built in the last 20 years. The same is true in factories and other places.  Similarly, we have powergoing to loss at night.  Power cannot be stored and most industries close down and demand eases off at 9 o'clock.  If industry was sufficiently educated huge savings could be made.  Industrialists could organise some of their plants and equipment to work during the hours when power is being generated and going to loss.</P>
    <P>From my experience of the Electricity Supply Board in my area I have high regard for them.  I do not come into this House deliberately praising semi-State bodies when they do not deserve it, but as a person working in an area that needs a lot of development, I have always observed the sensitivity of the ESB to the need for extra jobs and their absolute and immediate concern for anybody engaged in the creation of employment. As a farmer living in a rural area I have noticed the same concern for the welfare of livestock and the other complications that arise in times of breakdowns.  The behaviour of the ESB, certainly in my area, is exemplary and I only wish that some of the other semi-State bodies who have similar monopoly would display the same standards of efficiency and the same concern.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="85" /> This leaves me with the question that I still do not know whether they are sufficiently efficient to sell us a product at a competitive price and whether by the use of that product it is possible to compete with the rest of our European neighbours.</P>
    <P>We must contrast the plight of three or four ESB workers coming out in the middle of a stormy windy night looking for the breakdowns, concerned to fix them and worried lest livestock and other goods are lost with the power suddenly going off with somebody deciding to go on strike 50 or 100 miles away When we contrast the two sides certainly we have to ask ourselves what is wrong in this area.</P>
    <P>I do not want to go into the details of this because I am not sufficiently conscious of it but I am sufficiently aware of the reaction of the workers generally.  I am sufficiently aware of what human nature is all about and how people, who are given responsibility and are respected will not let down the public. For that reason I believe there is something seriously wrong when we can have the sort of breakdowns through industrial action we have had in the past few years with the ESB.  I am completely convinced that money will not solve this problem, it is not a question of wages.  It is a question of building up the right relationship and getting management to come to a proper understanding with the staff that work with them and giving the staff some vision of what their real responsibilities are.  If they are left inside pressing switches and buttons where they become machines and do not see themselves directly involved in the giving of a service which lies in industry and work and on which economic competitiveness depends they will become frustrated.  If we can bridge that gap and let those people realise the importance of their position within the industry.  I genuinely believe that this problem will not occur again and again.  I do not think it can be solved by extra wages or better working conditions.  I believe it can be solved by better human relationships between the people concerned, the people at the top and the public generally. Generally speaking, I regard the ESB as a great organisation and one of the best <Col N="86" /> of our semi-State bodies.  Therefore I would like to know a little about costs and competitiveness.  I welcome the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I intend to be fairly brief in my comments in welcoming the Bill, which is of major proportions in the impact it is likely to have in the field of energy and the related benefits which that brings to our economy and to our society.  The Minister's speech impressed me particularly because it touched on a number of important and sensitive areas and, I feel, in a reassuring, constructive way.  I am particularly pleased to note the emphasis on diversion from oil to coal burning units.  This has the obvious advantage of lessening our dependence on what was becoming an increasingly expensive commodity and also diversifies into a commodity which, for a number of reasons, is much more reliable in its supply.</P>
      <P>We all know what has been happening in the past few months in Iran, one of the major oil producing countries.  Even a quick examination of the globe as to the situation and the circumstances of the oil producing countries indicates that generally, apart from problems of the question of the reserves of oil, there are particular problems associated with the political and social problems that exist in the predominant oil producing countries, I believe that there is very great evidence to indicate that the continuity of supply and the great security which that gives is much more available to us in diverting, as indicated in the Minister's opening speech, to coal rather than oil.  There are a great number of coal producing countries which have more stable political systems, which have a more natural access for us.  I believe that this type of diversion to coal will bring a surety as to continuity of supply which in time could become every bit as big an advantage as avoiding the escalating costs which have occurred in the acquisition of oil over the past five or six years.  That point was made towards the end of the Minister's speech but it strikes me as one of the most important and particularly to be welcomed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would also like to stress the need for continuing emphasis on conservation of energy.  I feel that an energy conservation <Col N="87" /> policy pursued to its national benefit can only reduce the cost of imports of the basic fuels which are involved but can divert money from foreign purchases into job creation at home.  A developing attitude towards conservation will give rise to industries based on conservation and providing the materials and consequently employment in a conservation industry, of which a far greater proportion of the raw materials will be available in this country.  A particular advantage for economic reasons at home is that we can provide employment here in providing service and materials for the work of conservation to be financed in the main by moneys which would otherwise have gone in importing basic fuels.  Not only, therefore, do we make progress in the field of conservation, but in so doing, realistically and intelligently we will provide employment and new industrial outlets here at home.</P>
    <P>The provision of expertise abroad by the ESB is a development which has been clearly successful and is to be welcomed both for its success and operation.  It is a very worthwhile and progressive development by our State services in developing countries and in Third World countries.  It brings a degree of expertise which is put to great use in the countries in which it is applied and it also establishes Irish goodwill in these countries and Irish influence in these countries.  In addition to that, it forges the industrial link and helps the industrial advancement of this country. It provides a base for a follow-up service which can continue for the benefit of both the country availing of the service and this country for generations to come.  In the past, industrial and imperial-type countries believed in setting up certain industries in the colonies mainly with a view to supplying them with their own goods to keep the industries going.  It was a form of industrial exploitation.  Here we have a case where it is of direct service to the country, mutually agreed, mutually progressed and advanced on an entirely non-colonial basis.  We are one of the countries most suited to provide that type of service in the new and emerging <Col N="88" /> world.  The ESB, in so far as they have been providing that service, are to be congratulated.</P>
    <P>The Minister's concluding remarks on the question of nuclear energy are greatly welcomed.  It shows a breath of realism and common sense, which the debate on nuclear energy theatened to eliminate from the situation.  I was glad to hear his reference to the Government considering all the options.  One point I would make generally is that there is a certain difficulty in public debate on this matter and in any question of a public investigation or hearing that we are, of course, dealing with a highly technical, complex and complicated subject It is very difficult for the average member of the public to make an assessment which we would be happy with.  I appeal to the experts, the engineers and the scientists, to be very mindful of this and when engaging in debate on the matter to do so with the full realisation of their responsibility to the public in the matter and to resist the temptation to win a debate in a highly technical and rarified atmosphere among experts.  We are dealing with an issue which is very important and we know it can become extremely emotive.  The best machinery for ensuring a mature and a beneficial debate for the public is that the ordinary individual, exercising his ordinary concern and. common sense, has an opportunity to do so.  He is greatly in the hands of experts in this debate.  I appeal that the debate be conducted by experts in such a way that the public can exercise their judgment and can participate.</P>
    <P>On the question of an inquiry or a commission I believe that that is not necessarily an issue at the moment.  I feel the time span which the Minister has indicated in his remarks will be of great benefit.  The time span as indicated at 24 months before any advancement to tenders gives ample time to assess the position here at home and to avail of the experience being gained abroad in this type of debate which is taking place in practically all of the developed countries. Those are the points which I consider to be of most concern on a particularly important Bill for the economy and our society, and I welcome it.</P>
    <Col N="89" />
    <Speaker pid="GemmaHussey" hpid="Mrs. Hussey Mrs. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to make a very brief contribution to this debate because I feel that it cannot pass without every opportunity being taken to say some words on the final part of the Minister's speech.  We are all very glad that there will be further debate on the question of nuclear energy and that no irrevocable decisions are being taken in the name of the people of the country.  It is a very strong belief of mine that this debate should not be confined to politicians or scientists.</P>
      <P>Of course it is a very complex technical issue.  The whole question of the future energy requirements of this country is a very complex and technical issue but one which vitally affects every one of us.  Every energy crisis throws the country into total chaos and brings a great deal of hardship to a lot of people. It seems obvious that the dependence on oil is a very bad thing.  Oil and politics are inextricably connected and they do not mix any better than oil and water. For that reason alone, we must seek out every possible means of lessening our dependence on oil.</P>
      <P>Of course, it is an emotive subject.  It is an excellent thing to find people in a small democracy becoming emotional about subjects like nuclear energy which so very closely concerns them.  I deprecate the inclination of people to give out about things because they are an emotive issue.  If one were to listen to people chiding one on that score one would hardly ever speak on any subject. One becomes motivated to speak on subjects because they affect one in very many cases, and this particularly applies to women.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The case has not been made against a public inquiry.  I cannot understand the extraordinary reluctance there is to have a full open inquiry on this issue.  Our judges are appointed to make decisions for the people and they constantly make them and interpret issues for the people. Therefore, we should have a public inquiry with judges at its head to decide on this extraordinary major issue and let the scientists, the technicians and the politicians put their arguments into layman's language because this country is made up of laymen and laywomen.  I believe that this debate has only just <Col N="90" /> begun and is by no means closed, and the Government are aware that the people have given them no mandate to go ahead with nuclear power.  I would like to give that small contribution to this debate and hope for a bigger one in the future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EileenCassidy" hpid="Mrs. Cassidy Mrs. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is fitting to preface the few remarks I have to make by repeating in this House the introductory words used by the Minister when moving the Second Reading of the Bill in Dáil Éireann and emphasised by the Minister of State in his speech to us this evening:</P>
      <P>... the primary function of the ESB under the Electricity Supply Act is to ensure the adequate supply and distribution of electricity throughout the State.  This is the reason for their existence, and they have a standing remit from me and my predecessors to ensure that electricity is at no time in short supply.  The board have a number of other functions which I need not detail but these are subsidiary to its main function.</P>
      <P>This criterion of the board's main function and statutory obligations appears to have been accepted in the Dáil by the leading speaker for the Opposition, Deputy John Kelly, when he introduced his speech with the words &ldquo;I wish to begin by taking up a couple of points which in the overall context of the Minister's speech may be relatively marginal.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>We learn from the Minister that the ESB have had and still apparently have a surplus capacity among their highly skilled professional and technical staff, and that this surplus has been employed for electricity utilities in up to 15 different countries around the world, including Bahrein, Saudia Arabia and Nigeria.  One of the purposes of the Bill before the House is to give legislative sanction to the subsidiary functions and operations of the board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I feel bound to suggest that before the ESB can properly or lawfully employ their technicians in subsidiary functions they must first satisfy the nation that they have discharged, are discharging and will discharge their main function so <Col N="91" /> distinctly set out by the Minister in the words to which I have just referred.  I suggest that they employ their surplus highly skilled professional and technical staff to work under the following main headings.  First, to consolidate and improve the efficiency of existing domestic installations.  I have lived with my family for over 20 years in an area where the slightest snowfall will bring an immediate blackout which will take sometimes up to 48 hours to correct. Indeed, on one occasion, we were without electricity for three continuous weeks, and this notwithstanding the fact that in a small town a mile from our house the supply of electricity is rarely interrupted.</P>
    <P>This suggests that if the ESB took steps to see that the electrical installations in our area were as good as those in the adjoining towns they would be taking steps&mdash;and I quote the Minister &mdash;&ldquo;to ensure the adequate supply and distribution of electricity throughout the State and to ensure that electricity is at no time in short supply&rdquo;.  One has only to read the national newspapers to see that there is nothing unique about our area, and that indeed many other areas, particularly backward areas, have similar interference.</P>
    <P>My second recommendation to the board would be to create better management-labour relations, to reduce the incidence of industrial action when a strike or other form of industrial protest is made, to have the negotiating skill to deal with it in an intelligent, understanding, sympathetic and diplomatic way.  My final recommendation is, by skilful anticipation and detailed and interested concern for the working conditions of all groups in the employment of the board, to know the areas of friction, unrest and dissatisfaction in time to iron them out before a strike instead of negotiating a settlement when the public are in the dark and industry crippled, a settlement which in all probability could have been reached before the strike.</P>
    <P>I suggest that if there is a case to be made for sending some of the board's highly skilled technical staff abroad they might be sent to Norway or some such <Col N="92" /> country, where they might learn how to prevent a fall of snow from throwing wide areas of the country into darkness. Again, if there is a case for sending the board's highly skilled professional people abroad, might we not benefit from a study of management-labour relations in Germany as recently suggested by the Minister for Finance?  My suggestion is a simple one: &ldquo;Put your own house in order; charity begins at home.&rdquo;  Of course it is important for the board to have prestige with the black man in the jungle and the Arab in the desert, but I exhort them to seek the respect and the confidence of the Irishman, whether he he an ordinary householder, a farmer or an industrialist, before spreading their missionary wings any further.</P>
    <P>Since the major part of the Bill before the House, however, is to provide for an increase in the limit of capital expenditure by the board for the reasons stated by the Minister, I must commend the Bill to the House and ask only that the observations that I have made be borne in mind by the Minister and by the board in the exercise by them of their new statutory powers.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKilbride" hpid="Mr. Kilbride Mr. Kilbride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kilbride</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill and I would like to add my voice to the observations already made by my colleague, Senator McCartin, in regard to the standards that I see in the service provided by the ESB as a semi-State institution.  I must make a general observation on the structure of that service and the extent to which it is pruned in the light of the difficulties which the ESB find themselves confronted with in providing a service, particularly in rural areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is common knowledge to every member of the House that single phase electricity is provided in most rural areas.  It is found, where milking machines or electrical equipment are installed to bring farming into line with modern industrial standards of efficiency, that the current is not sufficient to enable the uninterrupted use of the particular motors used in agricultural services on the farm.  The ESB have a constant deluge of complaints because television and lighting effects in homes are almost eliminated.  It is almost a blackout in some areas.  If a second <Col N="93" /> motor is installed or two or three extensive dairies are using single phase current in an adjacent area people have had the experience of not having television during the time milking was being carried on.  It is the same in regard to lighting in many of the areas.</P>
    <P>The Minister should examine how long it is since we looked at the standard of electric current that we are sending into rural areas and the difference now existing between what is required of electricity users in rural areas compared with what was the case in the 1920's or 1930's.  Everybody will agree that in those days electricity from 1926 on was in its infancy.  It was to a very major extent not found in any rural area, and when it was extended in the 1930's or immediately after the world war very many people felt that was the full complement of everything that we might expect and all that we might ever need. Since we have become more industrialised and we have a higher standard of living in the rural areas many people are installing electric appliances, which is putting a demand on single phase current which I do not think it was really intended to meet.</P>
    <P>We must provide a better standard of wiring and a higher voltage output.  I understand that where we had 220 volts in single phase, in order to conserve electricity and to lessen the immediate consumption in particular areas the ESB dropped the voltage to 212 or 215.  That is one of the reasons why there is less power in the electricity provided for use on farms and in homesteads.  I suggest that the Minister should ask the ESB to consider upgrading the output and transmission of current.  It is hardly right to load extra units of consumption on to particular lines which are not able to carry them and at the same time for the ESB to go abroad to show their exertise and, I hope, earn money.  The Minister should ask the ESB to take particular stock of that aspect of the ESB service.</P>
    <P>Nuclear energy generation has been commented on by all the speakers I have heard.  In the United States the authority who are the custodians of what is known as &ldquo;the catechism of safety&rdquo; in regard to the generation and control of nuclear waste have said: &ldquo;We are no longer <Col N="94" /> depending on this standard.  We have been proven wrong and that standard is no longer regarded as safe&rdquo;.  In other words, they were an authority a few months ago, and today they admit they are not an authority.  That is enough to make us realise that an inquiry is vital into all the implications of the generation and disposal of nuclear waste, and the use of electricity generated from nuclear energy.</P>
    <P>I understand that people who are not living in the immediate vicinity of a nuclear station are liable to contamination and that we have yet to learn a great deal about the implications of the use of nuclear energy and the extent to which it radiates into vast areas.  It behoves the ESB, the Government and the people to look at this aspect with great seriousness.  If a human killer disease with the disastrous effects myxomatosis has on rabbits was being promoted we would be all rushing to kill the person who was promoting it.  We would be inclined to shoot him.  We would feel he should be shot.  Yet this has that effect on human beings and we are afraid to face up to it.  We are afraid to implement the machinery&mdash;that is if we have machinery&mdash;to inquire into its safety or otherwise or to get somebody in authority to make a pronouncement on whether it is safe or can be tolerated.</P>
    <P>Electricity is the last word in the use of energy.  It puts at the fingertips of the individual the means of providing the heat and comfort that make life worth living, and the provision of which is a must for all of us.  In other places I have defended the Government's idea of looking at this question and I trust they will look at it with full responsibility and ensure that, before a nuclear station is built, there will be a full guarantee of safety.  They see, as most of us see that circumstances are radically changed on the basis of what the United States Authority have admitted about the safety factor in the generation of nuclear power.  I do not want to say that the people who suggested a public debate were naïve and talking about something that is above our heads.  It is very much above our heads.  We should not ask lay people to give a decision on something of which they have no experience except <Col N="95" /> to the extent that they know it is dangerous.  We heard and we saw on television hair-raising examples of the effects of nuclear generation given by people who are anti-nuclear generation.</P>
    <P>I should like again to emphasise the importance of upgrading ESB service to the rural population.  The dispersal of small industries into these areas makes it necessary to have a higher standard of electric power than we have at present.  I appreciate that the ESB are doing a fine job despite the inhibitions placed on them because of the many years which have elapsed since the start of the provision of rural electricity.  I welcome the Bill and I wish the Minister success.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CLambert" hpid="Mr. Lambert Mr. Lambert">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lambert</NameTxt>
      <P>It gives me particular pleasure to support the contents of this Bill, which we should not overlook in the looming problem of nuclear energy.  We are looking at an essential ingredient of our life as a nation: the continued provision of a high-quality electricity service for our people at home, at work, on the farms, and in industry.  It is as basic as that.</P>
      <P>For 13 years I had the satisfaction of participating in the deliberations and forward planning of the ESB as a member of the Electricity Supply Board to which I had the honour of being reappointed by different Governments.  I am aware, therefore, of the conscientious commitment of the directors and management.  I was glad to hear the complimentary remarks made by the Leas-Chathaoirleach and Senator Kilbride because they are there to serve the community to the best of their ability and to ensure the availability of electricity in parallel with our economic growth and at minimum cost to the Irish consumer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>For almost 50 years, the board's policy was the promotion of the use of electricity, but owing to the dramatic change of circumstances brought about by the oil crisis the marketing policy had to be re-adjusted so that objectives were focused on load shaping rather than stimulation of growth <i>per se.</i>  As the Minister said, even so the ESB experienced a growth in demand for electricity of over 8 per cent over the <Col N="96" /> previous year.  Because usage is closely linked with the rate of economic development in the country as a whole, it is obvious that the demand will continue to increase.  It is, therefore, vitally important to allow the board to plan ahead so as to ensure sufficient supply of electricity to meet our projected economic and social progress, with all its implications of job creation and opportunities for our young people in the future.  We must bear in mind that we still have a low usage of electricity per head of population when compared with other European countries.  The momentum of our increasing agricultural and industrial development will bring a significant increased demand for power in the next decade.  Taking all the factors into account, it would seem prudent that we should be planning to meet a growth rate in electricity demand of the order of 8½ per cent over the next ten years.</P>
    <P>From my experience as a board member, I am conscious of the need for forward planning in this regard.  The long time of seven years or more required for the construction of a generation station demands that we take steps now to meet the requirements of the mid-eighties and beyond.  Looking back over the 51 years of development of the ESB the prospect of building a coal-fired station was hardly contemplated in the past.  It is, therefore, a major step to allocate £350 million for the projected coal-fired station in County Clare.  This decision, with the extended use of turf at Shannonbridge and Lanesboro in line with Bord na Mona's third development programme, is an obvious one in order to reduce our over-dependence on oil.  I am glad that, as a safeguard, this new station will be capable not only of burning coal but of being adapted for oil or gas.  This decision is very much to be welcomed.</P>
    <P>In considering this whole area of the various options open to us, I am mindful at my age of the fact that, were it not for the foresight of people like Seán Lemass and Erskine Childers, and their commitment to the development of our natural resources of turf for electricity generation, we would be even more greatly dependant on imported oil today.  The determination displayed by these <Col N="97" /> men&mdash;and let us not forget it&mdash;added new concepts in the area of electricity generation.  Even though they were criticised at the time, it is an example of the approach we should take in our efforts to meet the future needs of our community.</P>
    <P>Looking ahead to the potential growth beyond the mid-eighties, like everybody else, I agree that we must consider urgently the introduction of nuclear power.  The availability of a nuclear station on the electricity system would help to secure the much-needed spread of fuel types and so provide protection against the effects of a sudden threat of withdrawal of one source as occurred in the oil crisis of 1973.  It is my view that a rational appraisal should be made of the nuclear option without blurring the issue by the introduction of a high level of emotionalism which, regrettably, has come to characterise much of the debate on this topic in recent months.</P>
    <P>Fears of the new and unknown are understandable and must be recognised. However, I would hope that, on examination, it would be found that nuclear power offers this country the additional resource of electricity generation, and a safe one at that, for the 1980s and beyond.</P>
    <P>In relation to the capital provisions of this Bill, it is appropriate to point out that the ESB in their 50 years of existence have not at any time asked for a subsidy from the taxpayer.  I know Members of this House are aware that we are discussing the granting of statutory approval to the ESB to expand the necessary capital requirement for their programmes by an additional £500 million.  However, it is important to make it clearer to the public at large that the ESB will have to raise this capital through internal resources and by borrowings on the home and foreign markets at the going rate of interest.  It is a measure of the ESB's standing with the financial institutions here and abroad that they have been successful in raising capital in the past for their development programme.  It is important in the future that this financial soundness of operation is sustained and thus the ability of the ESB to borrow externally should not be prejudiced by demands from other <Col N="98" /> State bodies without the full knowledge of the facts concerning our total national borrowing powers projected forward on an annual basis for the next decade, a point I stressed in the debate on the Appropriation Bill before Christmas.</P>
    <P>The Minister also mentioned that some of the statutory increase will be allocated to new premises.  It was one of my ambitions when I was on the board to try and ensure that new premises, particularly in the area of office facilities, should be the most advanced in the country.  In fact, an ESB office should be a prototype of energy conservation involving the latest building techniques, heating and lighting installations, and should exemplify this objective as well as the economic utilisation of space to keep administration costs to the minimum.  In other words, I should like to see the concept of office design reach the standard of technical expertise which we expect from the ESB and that they would show the same imagination and initiative in the area of developing new premises.</P>
    <P>Another aspect of the Bill which has been discussed by Senators is the consultancy advisory service.  I remember when this consultancy activity was undertaken following the oil crisis in 1973 and the recession which followed.  It provided the board with an opportunity to avail of some surplus manpower arising at the time.  It has now developed into a substantial activity, to the great credit of the ESB, and added, as some other Senators have mentioned, considerable prestige to the image of Ireland abroad.  It has earned valuable foreign currency and helped to bring an increase in recruitment now that the recession is over.  It also had off-spin benefits for other Irish industries because foreign countries are aware of our existence on the market place.</P>
    <P>At home the ESB are probably the organisation with the widest possible contact with the community as a whole. They now serve one million customers.  I know that, within the last year or so, the board have made a special effort to improve and broaden their customer contacts. Whilst one is aware of Senator Cassidy's comments, a customer information leaflet outlining the board's credit policy has been sent to all <Col N="99" /> domestic customers.  They have endeavoured to emphasise they they are willing to discuss his problems with any customer in relation to his electricity charges or other problems.  In introducing the saving stamp scheme some years ago the board showed an awareness of the easy payment system, and the free electricity allowance scheme which they operate on behalf of the Department of Social Welfare is unique in Europe and the envy of many countries.</P>
    <P>In dealing with so many customers&mdash;we are talking about a million, a third of the population&mdash;it is not possible to avoid difficulties and problems.  I hope Senators who hear individual complaints will keep this in mind.  The board have displayed an awareness of their social responsibility which will come out very well in the social audit in the public companies called for recently by the Minister for Finance.</P>
    <P>The importance of rural electrification was touched on by Senator Kilbride. There was a problem when I was on the board.  Difficulties arose about the interpretation of the Electricity Supply (Amendment) Act. 1976, and the subsidy provided under the Act was a great limitation to the capacity of the ESB to extend rural electrification as rapidly as required.  As far as top management are concerned, I should like to take the opportunity to pay a short tribute to the late Dr. Tom Murray who headed the organisation during their time of greatest expansion and unprecedented social change.  He was a man totally concerned with the welfare of our largest organisation. He was a most conscientious man and a man of great integrity.  Indeed, I am proud to be able to recall his commitment to his great responsibilities and his dedicated service to the ESB and his fellow men.</P>
    <P>We are fortunate that he has been succeeded in recent years by such a triumvirate of business and technical expertise embraced by the Chairman, Professor Charles Dillon, the Chief Executive, Jimmy Kelly, and Assistant-Chief Executive Paddy Moriarty.  When I left the board over a year ago, I approved <Col N="100" /> of the up-dating of the organisation structure which the Chief Executive was initiating by a regrouping of functions amongst the directors and heads of departments to meet the challenge of the future.  They were doing more research into improving the efficiency of fuel utilisation which will have great financial benefits.  I know corporate planning is in keeping with the ESB's reputation amongst the top 500 companies in Europe.  I have been impressed by their monitoring procedures which are now part of their corporate planning to improve productivity in the financial performance at all levels of the organisation.</P>
    <P>It is difficult to understand that, in a well-structured and efficient organisation like the ESB, who have improved their communications system with the staff enormously&mdash;and I can personally vouch for this&mdash;and shown internally deep concern and continual research into all aspects of industrial relations, there are still extreme pockets of dissatisfaction which can threaten our community from time to time.  Unhappily, like everybody else, I can recall outages. For instance, I was in Slgio last August and I witnessed tourists struggling in the dark trying to get even a cold meal.  I have heard of old people suffering because their electricity was cut off and we have had other examples of this, less dramatic, in recent times.  With such a committed management, with improved communications amongst the staff, with much better than most working conditions, and with better than most security of employment, some logical solution must be found for this national problem of unofficial disputes.</P>
    <P>The appointment of four worker seats to the board must bring new hope in this direction and certainly the contribution of worker participation towards more stable industrial relations in this and other State bodies will be anxiously monitored by the private sector. Generally speaking, unless some moderate solution is found in relation to the pay demands in the public sector, there is little hope of Irish manufacturing industry matching such demands, or being able to pay the increased overheads which will materialise and still <Col N="101" /> survive in free competition with other EEC industries.</P>
    <P>Finally, as someone deeply involved in Irish manufacture, I am keenly aware of the central role played by electricity in our industrial life, just as I am aware of the dedicated commitment within the board.  I wish them and the Minister well in the effective evolvement of the plans which this Bill will make possible.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ValentineJago" hpid="Mr. Jago Mr. Jago">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jago</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be very brief.  There are just a few points I wish to make.  The first purpose of this Bill is to increase the ceiling of financial allocations to the ESB from £700 million to £1,200 million. Everybody is in agreement with that, because we all look on the ESB as one of our successful bodies.</P>
      <P>The ESB's first venture was the Shannon Scheme which was our first attempt at converting one of our own resources into energy.  During the period from 1939 to 1946, the war years, we first saw the signs of the expertise which was developing in the ESB.  They could not get parts to keep the installation going, and yet they were able to manufacture what was necessary with their own expertise and keep this country going. Since then, they have also extended their field into our own resources by their peat stations.  Now we have another own recource, our gas stations.  Unfortunately we have not got sufficient resources of our own to convert into the energy we require.  I am glad to see that in the programme ahead we have the Marina gas station, the Aghada station, the extension to Lanesboro, and the extension to Shannonbridge, all of which are converting our own resources into energy.</P>
      <P>Like Senator Lambert I am glad to see that we have now been able to change the policy which almost became established that we would not use coal. World conditions are changing and, with the increase in the price of oil and the uncertainty in the price of oil, it is to be welcomed that we are getting the new coal-fired station in County Clare by 1985.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not wish to make any comment on nuclear energy.  The Minister has stated that a decision has not yet been made on whether we will go ahead.  If we do, we have still got two years to wait, <Col N="102" /> and an awful lot can happen in two years.  In the meantime, if we have to make any preparations like town planning, we should make them to safeguard ourselves.</P>
    <P>There is the question of conservation of energy.  I am glad to see that at Lanesboro the ESB and An Foras Talúntais have combined together to endeavour to use waste heat by cultivation under glass and I hope it is successful. There could be more co-operation in the field of conservation between our State bodies who are under different ministries.  I have one practical example. As Senators are aware, the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards give a free service to industry but they do not give a free service to other sections of our community.  In the case of a small hospital in which I was interested, three years ago we brought in the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards, and the fuel bill for 1977 was less than the fuel bill for 1976, and the fuel bill for 1978 was less than the fuel bill for 1977, which I attribute completely to the advice given by the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards.  Therefore I feel this service should be extended outside industry as well.</P>
    <P>One of our alternative sources is wind power.  We know than any wind power installation can be very small, but there can be a lot of them, and they could be provided by private enterprise.  There is a feeling abroad today that the ESB does not welcome this.  They feel any electricity being manufactured by private enterprise prevents their sale.  In this field, the ESB should make every effort to assist anybody who has the initiative to move ahead to endeavour to use wind-power for electricity.  Research on wave power is going on in Scotland and that research should tell us the right way to go, too, and I understand there is also research, in a small way, in UCC in Cork.  The third one is the use of biomass.  I understand that the acreage involved in this is preventing us from going ahead with research.  I do not think that should be the case.  We should go ahead and research in the field of biomass.</P>
    <P>The second part of the Bill is to give <Col N="103" /> the ESB the legal authority for the consultative services which they have succeeded in establishing abroad.  We welcome those services, especially when we see that they brought in £1 million foreign currency to us.  I do not agree, however, with some speakers that we should give the ESB a free hand in the domestic field.  This consultative service commenced because of the recession.  At that time there was a satisfactory private domestic consultative service in this country.  If you are going to allow complete freedom to the ESB within our country, it would affect that.  More important still is the ESB's concentration could be taken away from abroad and centred on home and we want them to maintain and carry out on the very good work which they have started.</P>
    <P>There is one area where the ESB may not continue to compete, and that is the field of retail trade, retail selling of equipment. Having looked at it in the ESB accounts I do not think it is suitable for the ESB.  I do not think it is their main aim, and it should be left to private industry. There is, however, another area in which they should do more, and that is the area of safety.  The ESB should be given power to do more.  At present if there is an installation in a private house the ESB test it to see that it is satisfactory before putting in a meter.  Nobody tests it five years later or ten years later when alterations and wear and tear can make it dangerous.  The ESB should be responsible for periodic inspection of all installations, not alone in private houses.  We have electrical regulations under the factory inspectorate; the ESB should have that power.  With those few remarks, I welcome the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Energy (Mr. R. Burke) Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Energy (Mr. R. Burke)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Energy (Mr. R. Burke)</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to commence by thanking Senators for the warm welcome they have given to this Bill and for their stated appreciation of what is in my view the primary function of the ESB under the Electricity Supply Acts, and that is the ensuring of adequate supply and distribution of electricity throughout the State.  I am glad that this very important primary function is <Col N="104" /> recognised by the various contributors to the debate from both sides of the House.  Within our rapidly expanding industrial programme and as our nation becomes industrialised, the need for an adequate supply of electricity becomes more and more obvious.</P>
      <P>I should like to refer to a number of the individual points.  On the question of consultancy, I welcome the points made by the various Senators.  I would mention to Senator Cassidy that the ESB at present have no surplus staff.  The rising demand for electricity has absorbed the slack that there was within the staff. Work at home is very much of first importance to the ESB.  The Minister has been at pains to ensure that there is no decline in standards at home by over-concentration on work abroad.  As regards the individual situation in which Senator Cassidy found herself, I deeply regret it.  I, regretfully, found myself in a similar situation on Christmas Eve.  This is, unfortunately, a problem of weather difficulties.  I appreciate the Senator's point with regard to Norway and the fact that the ESB should have a look at the situation there.  I shall bring the Senator's various points to the attention of the ESB.</P>
      <P>I also want to refer to the concern mentioned by Senator Jago and by a number of other Senators, about the overlap of State and semi-State operations. Particular care is being taken to avoid conflict between the consulting engineering profession and the ESB.  In the early years of the programme, in either 1975 or 1976, there were a number of complaints by established consulting engineers about the ESB trespassing on their traditional field. However, in the last number of months I am glad to say that there have been absolutely no complaints.  We in the Government are very conscious of the need to avoid such complaints.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I mentioned in my opening remarks we must all recognise and appreciate the work that the ESB have done since they have gone into the consultancy field abroad; the contacts that they have built up; the money that they have earned for this country; the goodwill that they have generated, not only for their own organisation and for <Col N="105" /> the country but also for many exporters. They have opened up tremendous fields of opportunities abroad for our exporters. This is something that we must all recognise and encourage.</P>
    <P>Great emphasis was laid by various Senators, including Senator Donnelly on the subject of conservation.  This is a matter that is recognised by the Government. It is intended to put increasing emphasis on the whole question of a proper and effective conservation programme.  Last week, in the budget statement, the Minister for Finance referred to the importance of conservation and extra efforts being put in in the coming year to have a fully effective conservation programme.  It is selfevident that it is a total waste of resources merely to generate electricity if we are not, at the same time, planning our buildings and various offices in such a way as to make sure that we are getting the greatest benefit of the power which we are generating.  I particularly take the point made by Senator Lambert that the ESB should be the leaders in the field of design of offices and of premises to make the best use of the power generated and also that they should be the leaders in conservation.  Not only should they be the leaders but should be seen to be the leaders.  I accept that point totally and I shall pass it on to the ESB. I have no doubt the Senator himself will pass it on on a number of occasions.  It is a very worthwhile point.</P>
    <P>I am also grateful to the Senators for recognising the importance of getting away from our over-dependence on oil and diversification into gas and coal. What this Bill is primarily about is the new coal-fired station in County Clare. The indicative rather than definitive sums that were mentioned, as I said earlier, show that of the extra £500 million involved, £350 million approximately is to be spent on the provision of a 600 MW coal-burning station in County Clare.</P>
    <P>This coal-burning station will be capable of conversion to native oil if such is found in economic quantities off the west coast, which we hope will come true.</P>
    <P>While we are removing our dependence on imported oil we are merely <Col N="106" /> transferring it, at the moment, on to imported coal and this also has problems.  We are happy enough that at least our supply of coal is from countries which have more stable regimes that those from which we are getting our oil at the moment.  It is, however, still imported coal and the further we can get away from this level of dependence on imported fuel the better.</P>
    <P>The events in the Middle East over the last couple of months must have shown anybody who had doubts about the level of our dependence on imported oil that we should not continue that dependence on imported oil.  No country with the programmes and the targets that we have set for ourselves, with the accompanying need for energy and electricity generation, can depend for its basic fuel for this electricity generation on supppliers from such politically volatile areas as the Middle East.  The Government have been examining this whole energy question.  Last July the Minister for Industry, Commerce and Energy, published a document &ldquo;Energy&mdash; Ireland&rdquo; on the options for the years ahead to the turn of the century, which set out the various options facing this country.  This document was widely distributed, I should have been happier if it had got greater coverage.  However, for the section of people who have read it, it sets out clearly the various options available to us and it lays great emphasis on the importance of removing ourselves from this over-dependence on oil.  It also mentions the nuclear option.</P>
    <P>There was some reference made by most Senators at one stage or another to the nuclear option and there were, as usual, some emotive words about the safety factors, and the Rasmussen Report and other items were mentioned. It is an option we must consider at this stage.  A Government decision, in principle, was made in November 1973, at the time of the last oil crisis.  Surely, with the way things are looking from present reports, we are in for another difficult period unless Iranian oil comes on-stream very soon and the situation in that country settles down.  The nuclear option is spelled out in the Government energy options report.  The Government are to review, in the next couple of <Col N="107" /> weeks, the decision of the previous Government, which was the decision, in principle, made in 1973 and declared in 1975 at the request of the ESB.  Even when they review it it will be merely a decision, in principle, to go ahead with the planning stage and no firm contractual commitments have to be entered into for an 18 to 24 months period.</P>
    <P>The question of a public inquiry or some sort of inquiry was mentioned by a number of Senators.  I would remind the Senators that there will be an inquiry into this nuclear proposal.  When the planning application is eventually decided by the Wexford County Council, no matter which way it goes, there will be a public oral hearing.  The Government have not closed their minds to some other type of inquiry but nobody has yet suggested what form it should take.  We are open to suggestions.</P>
    <P>Senator Hussey made the point that there should be an inquiry chaired by judges who would tell the Government as to what decision should be made or not made.  The Government were elected by the people to make financial decisions on behalf of the people.  Judges are not elected by the people to make those decisions. It is up to the Government to make decisions and to decide whether in the best interests of the country decision X or decision Y should be made.  As far as the safety and other factors are concerned, there is no doubt that many of those will be considered at the oral hearing in regard to the planning application. However, as I have already said, the Government have not closed their minds finally to the idea of some sort of inquiry, if for no other reason that to go through the democratic process of being seen to take some of the heat out of the situation and remove the head of steam that has been building up.  I am not clear in my own mind whether the head of steam is being generated, by some of the people involved, for motives other than those that they proclaim from the rooftops.</P>
    <P>The question of alternative energy sources were mentioned, wind power, wave power and biomass.  From calculations and on the levels of technology <Col N="108" /> available at this stage, it is estimated that they would meet only five per cent of our energy needs by the turn of the century. Surely we cannot work out and develop and plan a proper energy policy on the basis of the contribution of five per cent from alternative sources.  However, I do see that after the turn of the century, when the level of technology has been increased, there will be great potential for alternative energy sources.  The question of industrial problems was mentioned. We all regret the industrial problems, not only in the ESB but in many other semi-State organisations and in the private sector.  It is my firm hope and the hope of the Government and of everybody in this country that we shall see an end to the disputes that have taken place.  We all want to see this country going forward and we all want to see that sufficient jobs will be created for our young people leaving school; for those who at present are unemployed and for the school leavers in the years ahead.  This should be the great national aim.  We hope that it will be calmly achieved.  It can only be achieved with industrial peace, which we as politicians and genuinely concerned citizens all hope for.</P>
    <P>There were a number of other points mentioned by various Senators about the level of the power in the farming areas.  There has been such an increase in the demand for electricity in some areas that sometimes there are deficiencies. The ESB try, as far as possible, to make good these deficiencies as quickly as possible.  If any Senator has any particular item or area about which he is concerned, if he writes to me privately on it, I shall be delighted to examine it.</P>
    <P>In regard to the question of cost and the education of the public and generation costs and so on, and the consequent costs to the consuming public, the ESB do set out in their annual financial reports the various costs involved.</P>
    <P>The highly technical subject of nuclear energy was mentioned by Senator Donnelly.  I could not agree with him more.  As a layman on the subject I find that you can get two technical people on either side of an argument to prove exactly the opposite point of view, using exactly the same set of figures. <Col N="109" /> Senator Hussey mentioned that there is not a mandate to proceed with nuclear power.</P>
    <P>
      <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Mr. R. Burke Mr. R. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government have a mandate, on the basis that there was already a Government decision in 1973. Therefore, the question of a mandate does not arise.  For the other Senators' contributions and the general welcome given to this Bill, I am grateful and, in conclusion, I would join with Senator Lambert and other Senators who referred to the work being done by the management and staff, generally, of the <Col N="110" /> ESB.  This country owes them a great debt of gratitude and it also owes a debt of gratitude to the foresight of men like Seán Lemass and Erskine Childers. Thank you.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
      <P>Bill put through Committee, reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.20 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 21 February 1979.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>