<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="8" Month="May" Year="1968" Vol="64" No="15" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 8 Bealtaine 1968" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 8 May 1968" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1231">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1231" /> Do chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take business as on the Order Paper from Nos. 1 to 7 inclusive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>May I inquire from the Leader of the House if he is in a position to say when motion No. 15 is likely to be taken?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>As I informed the Senator last week, it will have to take its place in the queue.  There are other motions before it and when they are dealt with its turn will come.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to be going down the list.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask whether the Leader of the House is in order in saying it will have to take its place considering that motion No. 8, which is the first on this list, is the most recently added one?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Item No. 8 is concerned with Government business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any intention of taking it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order of Business has been announced&mdash; items Nos. 1 to 7 inclusive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Last week we were assured that this would be dealt with in due course and in order. We had about three hours to spare last week and the Leader of the House was not in a position to enable us to reach any of these motions.  Now we have a full agenda and it looks as if we will not reach them today either. I do not think this is satisfactory.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1232" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is long enough in the House to appreciate the difficulties which arise in connection with the scheduling of motions for any particular day.  On that point, I should say that I did have a motion lined up for last week at the request of an Opposition Senator and it had to be postponed because the Senator was not ready to take it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Order of Business Nos. 1 to 7?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is: &ldquo;That the Order of Business be agreed.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the position about the motion relating to Biafra?  Is there agreement on that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator heard the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to know what is the position.  Is it the intention to take it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>My attitude is that I do not think it is a right and proper motion to be discussed at this particular time, and I hope that by the time it comes to be discussed negotiations will have succeeded in bringing peace to Biafra.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We all hope that but, on the humanitarian issue, I am afraid of innocent people being killed while we are waiting for peace discussions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator has any suggestions as to the protection of civilians in the middle of a war I am sure that the belligerents would be delighted to hear it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Have we reached any decision as to the Order of Business?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader of the House has moved the Order of Business and the Senator can move an amendment if he wishes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I protest.  The Order of Business was agreed before Senator FitzGerald came in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1233" />
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It was not. As I came in the Leas-Chathaoirleach was asking if it had been accepted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I would remind Senator FitzGerald that on one occasion when he endeavoured to have a motion on Greece put down I persuaded him to withdraw it and I would hope that he could also be persuaded to withdraw this one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford) Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Longford):</i> I may have put that idea into Senator Ó Maoláin's head.  I have the same view that nobody doubts the good faith of Senator FitzGerald in putting down this motion.  Nobody suggests that it should not be discussed but I think that it would be better that we did not do so at this particular time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If the House wishes the motion can be discussed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford) Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Longford):</i> Perhaps Senator FitzGerald would accept the view that there might be a certain amount of risk in discussing this matter in view of difficulties that can arise even after peace has been restored.  I suggest that the motion should not be taken at the present time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we have an assurance from the Leader of the House that he will not wait until it is too late to do any good to anybody before he allows the discussion on the motion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order of Business has been proposed and if we go any further on this matter the motion will have been discussed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It was not my intention to discuss the matter today and, therefore, I will not press it any further.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair is convinced that it is better to have these matters discussed outside the House rather than inside it.  It is better to have them discussed outside <Col N="1234" /> than to bring them in and have a discussion in the House.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Chester Beatty Library Bill, 1968:" RHead="Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Chester Beatty Library Bill, 1968: Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="The Taoiseach Jack Lynch">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a short Bill which requires very little explanation. As members of the Seanad are aware, the world-renowned Library at Shrewsbury Road, Dublin, was built and endowed for the nation, by the late Sir Alfred Chester Beatty as but one of the benefactions&mdash;all of outstanding value and importance&mdash;which the Irish people owe to this most generous and public-spirited friend of our country. To give effect to his intention that the library should be maintained for the use of the public, Sir Chester Beatty, by his will, bequeathed it to certain named trustees and made provision for the appointment of additional trustees, including one to be appointed by the President.</P>
      <P>In view of the terms of Articles 12.1 and 13.10 of the Constitution, which relate to the powers and functions of the President, it is necessary to provide, by legislation, for the conferring upon the President of this power of appointment, which would, under the Will, be a continuing function in relation to one particular trusteeship.</P>
      <P>The President has indicated his agreement to this proposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We are more than willing to accept this Bill and are glad of the opportunity to pay a tribute to the late Sir Alfred Chester Beatty for the generosity of the gift of the library in respect of which we are now making trusteeship arrangements. It is a wonderful thing to have a library such as that provided and the fact that this Bill gives us the opportunity to pay tribute to its donor is also very welcome. We have no difficulty in accepting the Bill and look forward to the arrangements being finally completed <Col N="1235" /> so that the library will be vested in the Irish people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>As a representative of one of the universities and as a Senator, I should like to be associated with this tribute to the memory of one of the most munificent of our citizens in recent years.  Sir Alfred Chester Beatty, from his earliest years in the country, gave generously to our nation. He gave us a very fine collection of the Barbizon school of painting, now one of the treasures of our national collection. All during his life he helped the culture and the welfare of our State generously and he set an example to all rich people in the country.  I do not think we can remember in recent years anyone who served our nation so well in that way.  In the past, one thinks of Sir Hugh Lane and the Guinness family.  Such people are rare at present. I hope they will be more numerous in the years to come.  I am sure the House would like to record its gratitude, and I am very glad to share in Senator FitzGerald's expression of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="The Taoiseach Jack Lynch">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the debate calls for any special reply from me except to endorse that which Senators on the other side have said.  As is well known, Sir Chester Beatty's benefactions were not limited to matters of art.  He was well known to have helped a lot of people in need in different ways.  We are very grateful to him and this will be a very positive way in which his memory will be kept green.  There are many other people in the country to whom the memory of Sir Alfred Chester Beatty will always be green by reason of his benefactions to them personally. I do not think I need say any more except to suggest that the House might be able to deal with more than this Stage today.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
      <P>Bill put through Committee, reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Imposition of Duties (Dumping and Subsidies)" RHead="Bill, 1967: Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Imposition of Duties (Dumping and Subsidies) Bill, 1967: Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1236" /> Government amendment No. 1:</P>
    <P>In page 3, line 5, before &ldquo;and&rdquo; where it secondly occurs to insert &ldquo;in whole or in part&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley) George Colley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley)</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment which I hope meets an amendment put down by Senator FitzGerald on Committee Stage.  It ensures that the definition of the word &ldquo;produced&rdquo; includes any process in the manufacture of goods.  This also links up with the amendment which the House passed on Committee Stage to section 21 (2) relating to the country of origin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It meets my point in a neat and simple manner with which we should be more than happy.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 2 and 3 may be discussed together.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 3, section 1, between lines 13 and 14, to insert the following subsection:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(3) References in this Act to the country from which goods are exported are, in the case of goods exported to the State, references to the country from which they were consigned to the State and goods which in course of consignment from any country to the State pass through or are transhipped in any third country shall not on that account be regarded for the purposes of this Act as having been exported from that third country.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>This relates to a point raised on Committee Stage as to the original draft where the phrase was used &ldquo;or goods exported from any country&rdquo;.  It is generally agreed that this was not very clear and this amendment is designed to clarify the position. As well, we have added a definition of &ldquo;country from which the goods are exported&rdquo;, a matter we discussed on <Col N="1237" /> the last occasion.  Primarily the amendment is designed to clarify what is involved and I think it does so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the points made at that time are met by this amendment.  I do not think there is any problem about it and we accept it.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 3 and 4 may be taken together.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 3:</P>
      <P>In page 5, to delete lines 14 to 24 and substitute:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;dumped, and</P>
      <P>(ii)the Commission considers it probable that the goods to which the request relates have been or are being dumped and that the dumping was or is injurious dumping</P>
      <P>or</P>
      <P>(b)the Minister considers it probable that any goods have been or are being dumped, that the dumping was or is injurious dumping and that there are exceptional circumstances which warrant a request by him to the Commission to investigate whether those goods have been or are being dumped, and the Minister so requests,&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>This also arises out of a discussion we had on Committee Stage when I said I proposed to have a look at this to see if we could not improve the subsection.  The main point raised by Senator FitzGerald in that discussion, and one with which I was inclined to agree, was that on the face of it the Bill, as drafted, appeared to suggest that before an investigation could take place, the Commission, or in other cases the Minister, would have to be convinced that there had been dumping which, of course, was defeating the object.  That was not what was intended but I agree that one might have taken that interpretation out of it.  Substituting the words &ldquo;considers it probable&rdquo; meets the point made in this regard.  It also has <Col N="1238" /> the effect of providing that in the case of a reference by the Minister to the Commission you will not have the situation where the Commission is reviewing the Minister's decision as to whether there should be an investigation in the case of the matter being referred to the Commission by the Minister.  The Commission &ldquo;shall&rdquo; carry out an investigation.  In the other case the Commission &ldquo;may&rdquo;. I think both points which were raised in this connection are concerned in this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Frankly, I am not quite happy with this amendment. I must plead guilty in a sense to negligence because I proposed putting down an amendment myself but foolishly waited to see the Government amendment and waited too long. I should, of course, have put my amendment down and then I could have withdrawn it if it were entirely unsatisfactory.  Therefore, in a sense I am debarred from objecting to the form of this amendment but I should like to comment that while it may be said to improve the position it does not really get over the difficulty that the Commission is expressing a view on the case which it then has to consider in a judicial capacity.  I thought from the discussion the last day that the solution that would emerge was the one that I would have put down myself.  In fact, I did write it down at the bottom of a page of the Bill with wording along the lines &ldquo;in the view of the Commission there exists <i>prima facie</i> evidence that the goods have been dumped&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think there is a difference here. The statement here requires the Commission to make a judgment as to whether the goods have been dumped and to make a judgment as to the probability of that event which is judgment concerning an actual dumping of the goods.  It is not a firm judgment: it is a provisional judgment I admit.  To that extent it is better than the previous wording which involved the Commission &ldquo;being of opinion that the goods had been dumped&rdquo; but it still involves their making up their minds and reaching a <Col N="1239" /> conclusion of some kind on the issue. I do not think the Commission should be put in the position of having to express a view on the issue.  The wording I had in mind involves a different thing altogether.  It involves the Commission expressing a view that there was <i>prima facie</i> evidence in the matter.  That is quite different.  They are not really expressing a view on the merits of the case.  They are expressing a view that evidence has been put forward which <i>prima facie</i> suggests that the goods may have been dumped. I think one can legitimately permit a situation in which the Commission would express a view on <i>prima facie</i> evidence of dumping without committing them to the same degree on the merits of the case itself, whereas in this instance they are expressing an opinion on the issue.  I wonder whether the Minister would reconsider this and consider changing the wording to: &ldquo;The Commission considers that there is <i>prima facie</i> evidence . . .&rdquo;</P>
    <P>In the case of the Minister it is less important.  I am not so worried in that case.  It does not matter very much and it is fair enough in the Minister's case that he should consider that the goods probably have been dumped.  In the case of the second amendment, page five, line 28, again it is a case of the Minister and, therefore, there is not any problem.  The only suggestion I would make to the Minister is that he changes the words: &ldquo;considers it probable&rdquo; in the beginning of amendment No. 3 to: &ldquo;considers that <i>prima facie</i> evidence exists. . . &rdquo; or &ldquo;that there is <i>prima facie</i> evidence. . . &rdquo; I wonder if he would consider this.  I am happy to leave the wording in the other case where the Minister is at stake and not the Commission.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator FitzGerald will, I am sure, recollect that when we were discussing this on Committee Stage I actually used the analogy of the hearing by a district justice of depositions in a criminal charge as being analogous in a way to this.  He decides whether or not there is <i>prima facie</i> evidence.  For that reason I was myself inclined to the use of the phrase &ldquo;<i>prima facie</i><Col N="1240" /> evidence&rdquo; but I am advised by the parliamentary draftsman that there are technical difficulties in introducing that phrase, that it would introduce certain connotations which would be inappropriate in this case.  The advice available to me is that the original wording meets the point we had in mind but that in order to make it clearer the phrasing here &ldquo;considers it probable&rdquo; is as far as we can put it without importing certain legal things by the use of the phrase &ldquo;<i>prima facie</i> evidence&rdquo;.  On the basis of this, this is the best I can do in the way of amendment and I do not think I could consider changing it.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 4:</P>
      <P>In page 5, line 28, to delete &ldquo;is of opinion&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;considers it probable&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 5:</P>
      <P>In page 12, line 36, to delete &ldquo;are goods exported from any country&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;to determine the country from which the goods were exported&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I should just like to say a few words on the concluding Stage of the Bill.  First of all.  I should like to repeat that this is a very useful Bill.  It has taken a long time to get it to this point but I think that the care which has gone into it has been repaid in a Bill which will give the kind of protection that Irish industry will need with tariffs being reduced and at the same time conforming to the international obligations we have which are quite tricky and to conform with which is quite a difficult task. I think it is a good Bill now.  The only thing which concerns one is this question of the 1980 date but we were precluded from discussing that.  I am sorry I did not ask for clarification of that ruling because I cannot understand the reason for it or why it should be regarded <Col N="1241" /> as a possible charge on the Exchequer.  However, it is a bit too late now to bring that up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that was the reason.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>In that case my recollection is at fault.  Apart from that and one or two matters which we raised in the debate and which the Minister did not fully accept, it is a good Bill.  I feel it is a Bill which we have improved in this House.  There have been more changes made here than there were in the Dáil.  I think there were 14 amendments altogether. I feel it is a better Bill for having proceeded through this House.  There are Bills which are handled better in the Seanad and there are Bills which are handled better in the Dáil.  I think this is one of the former.  We are particularly grateful to the Minister for the consideration he has given to the amendments and his open mind on almost all of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to raise one point which should have been raised much earlier I suppose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I trust it is in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, I shall stick very closely to the Bill.  Section 10 subsection (1) paragraph (a) states that the Commission may &ldquo;request witnesses other than the Revenue Commissioners and their officers&rdquo; to attend before it.  Paragraph (b) gives it the power to &ldquo;examine the witnesses attending before it&rdquo;, and paragraph (c) says it may &ldquo;request any such witness to produce to the Commission any document in his power or control&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When Senator FitzGerald was raising difficulties about this business of witnesses this point was overlooked I think because the Minister's argument was that he did not meet the Revenue Commissioners or their officers before the Commission because their documents would be available and the documents in the power of the Revenue Commissioners would be the only thing in which the Commission would be interested.  As I read section 10, subsection (1) paragraph (c) which concerns <Col N="1242" /> documents it is limited to documents in the power of any such witness, that is, a witness under (a) or (b).</P>
    <P>Under (a) the Revenue Commissioners may not be witnesses and under (b) the reference is to witnesses before it.  So the Commission may not request the Revenue Commissioners to attend and, therefore, they may not examine them.  As (c) refers to such witnesses in (a) and (b) or (3) the documents under the control of the Revenue Commissioners do not appear to be in the power of the Commission to request.  It may be, of course, that this sort of thing would be done informally and one can well understand as between one Department of State and another this informality may operate quite well but this is not a Department of State.</P>
    <P>This is a Commission and whether a Commission which is not yet set up would feel itself in a position that it might informally approach the Revenue Commissioners and say: &ldquo;We would like to have certain documents&rdquo; and whether the Revenue Commissioners would say: &ldquo;Show us the power to ask for those&rdquo;, I do not know but I think it is a weakness that the Revenue Commissioners being debarred under (a) are assumed to be amenable to the Commission for the production of documents.  As to the Minister's argument on an earlier stage when there is this limitation such witnesses obviously refer to witnesses under (a) or (b).</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley) George Colley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley)</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Senator Sheldon's interpretation of subsection (1) is probably correct but I also think he has overlooked the provision of subsection (3) which specifically provides as follows:</P>
      <P>The Commission may request the Revenue Commissioners to furnish to it such particulars of information furnished to them in documents for customs purposes as are necessary for the performance of its functions and the Revenue Commissioners shall comply with a request under this subsection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am satisfied that the subsection covers the point which Senator Sheldon has in mind and that under it the <Col N="1243" /> documentary evidence which the Commission requires from the Revenue Commissioners will be available to it. The Commission can request it and when requested the Revenue Commissioners would comply with such request.  If the subsection were not there, I think Senator Sheldon's point would be a valid one and one we would have to take account of but, having regard to the evidence of subsection (1), I think the point he is making is covered.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to customs documents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be the only kind of information the Revenue Commissioners would have.  They would have factual information based on customs documents in their possession. As I said on a previous occasion, they are not necessarily confined to the particular goods in question.  They might have reference to similar goods imported at different times in order to arrive at comparative prices.</P>
      <P>I agree with Senator FitzGerald that the Bill has been improved as a result of the discussion in this House and I am grateful to the Seanad for the discussion which has taken place and the improvement which has been effected in the Bill as a result.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Continental Shelf Bill, 1967:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Continental Shelf Bill, 1967: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley) George Colley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the Bill is to provide the statutory framework for the exploration and exploitation of the natural resources of this country's part of the continental shelf, that is the sea bed and subsoil outside its territorial waters to where the sea bed falls to the ocean floor.  The concept that a State might have exclusive rights to explore and exploit the natural resources of the continental shelf adjacent to its coast assumed growing importance after the last war.  Technological advances were making it possible to <Col N="1244" /> explore and exploit such natural resources, but considerable uncertainty existed in international law as to the precise rights of individual States to the parts of the continental shelf adjoining their shores.  At the request of the United Nations, the International Law Commission carried out a study of the problem with a view to bringing the definition and control of these rights within the ambit of international law.  The Report of the International Law Commission was considered by the International Conference on the Law of the Sea, 1958, which was convened at Geneva by the United Nations, and this resulted in the drafting of the Convention on the Continental Shelf.</P>
      <P>The Convention was signed by this country's delegates, subject to ratification by the Government, but has not yet been ratified.  The Convention came into force internationally in 1964, after being ratified by 22 countries.  To date the Convention has been ratified by 37 of the 46 countries which signed it, including the West European countries Britain, France, Denmark, Portugal, the Netherlands, Switzerland and Sweden.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Convention clarifies the position in international law regarding the continental shelf, deals with the allocation of the shelf between adjacent States or States whose coasts are opposite each other and defines the right of the adjacent coastal State to explore and exploit the natural resources of its particular area of shelf, subject to the State assuming certain obligations.  The continental shelf is defined as the sea bed and subsoil of the submarine area adjacent to the coast but outside the territorial waters to a depth of 200 metres or beyond that limit where the depth of the waters permits exploration. The natural resources covered by the Convention are defined as mineral, including oil and gas, and other nonliving resources of the sea and subsoil. together with living organisms belonging to sedentary species.  I might add that this definition excludes all swimming fish.  Under the Convention, the rights the coastal State may exercise over its area of continental shelf are limited to such rights as are necessary for the exploration and exploitation <Col N="1245" /> of its natural resources.  These rights do not amount to full sovereignty which would be inconsistent with the legal status of the waters above the shelf as high seas and of the air space above these waters.  The exercise of the rights must not interfere unduly with navigation, the laying or maintenance of submarine cables or pipelines, conservation of the living resources of the sea or with fundamental oceanographic or scientific research carried out with the intention of open publication.</P>
    <P>While the potential of the natural resources of the sea bed has long been recognised, the exploration and exploitation of these resources did not become of real economic significance in most parts of the world until quite recently.  The development of these resources has been made possible only by notable advances in technology and it is still a very difficult and hazardous operation compared with similar work on dry land.  Metallic ores under the floor of the sea bed may still be developed only by driving shafts and tunnels from adjoining land and, in view of the inconvenience and the high cost of their exploitation, these minerals would not appear to possess much potential significance at present. Petroleum and gas are, probably, the resources of greatest value and potential to be found in continental shelf areas and some spectacular progress has already been made in the exploitation of these off-shore deposits in many parts of the world.</P>
    <P>I should mention, however, that the sea bed is not specially favoured with deposits of oil or gas as compared with adjoining land areas.  In general, the mineral resources of the continental shelf are similar to those of the contiguous land area.  In European waters the outstanding example of submarine exploration is the search for gas and oil in the North Sea.  The potentialities of this area had long been recognised but it was the discovery of a huge gas field in the adjoining land area of Northern Holland in 1959 which gave rise to the present intensive exploration, which has yielded such promising results.  Of growing importance is the dredging from the sea floor of sands and gravels for use as concrete aggregate and of <Col N="1246" /> banks of shells and other organic material for use as lime and fertiliser.</P>
    <P>This country's area of continental shelf includes half the Irish Sea area and an area of Atlantic shelf extending about 200 miles off the south west coast and 165 miles off the west coast.  These are very approximate indications of the extent of the area but it will, very probably, exceed the size of the national territory.  The amount of geological information available about our shelf area is very little and it is not possible to give at this stage any real indication of the exploitable resources likely to be found there.</P>
    <P>Lest spectacular success elsewhere should give rise to too much optimism as to the potential of our area of shelf, I think I should point out that the results of the search for oil and natural gas carried out over the whole country and the territorial waters by a group of American companies have not been encouraging and the limited geological information at present available does not suggest the presence in our area of shelf of gas deposits comparable with those discovered in the North Sea.  Some oil companies have, however, indicated an interest in exploring our area of shelf which suggests that the area has possibilities for oil and gas and there is no reason why we should not entertain hopes of success.  We know that sand and gravel aggregate is present in great abundance in the many banks and shoals fringing our east coast and beds of organic mud of possible use as fertiliser have been noted off the west coast.</P>
    <P>While the potential of our area of shelf must be regarded as largely unknown at present, the important fact is that technological advances have now made the exploration of this vast area possible and such exploration offers the exciting possibility of locating valuable resources, the exploration of which could prove to be of great benefit to our economy.  It is, therefore, considered desirable that we should now provide a statutory framework for the exploration and exploitation of the natural resources of the area.  We will then be in a position to grant licences and leases to competent parties desirous of exploring and exploiting <Col N="1247" /> the resources of our area of shelf.</P>
    <P>As I already pointed out, the rights which the coastal State may exercise over its area of continental shelf do not amount to full sovereignty.  Our existing laws could not, therefore be taken as applying automatically to our area of the shelf and it is necessary to extend the application of a number of existing statutes to the area so as to provide a basis of law and order for operations there.  Much of the Bill is concerned with the extension of the application of these statutes.  The interests of many Departments are concerned, and the Bill has been drafted in consultation with these Departments.</P>
    <P>The Bill provides that the Government may by Order designate the area of continental shelf over which the rights which accrue to the State will be exercised.  These rights are vested in and exercisable by the Minister for Industry and Commerce except where the Government may by directions vest the rights in another Minister.  The rights relating to minerals, oil and gas will be exercised by the Minister for Industry and Commerce and if the exploration or exploitation of any other natural resources, such as sedentary fisheries, should arise at some future date the Government will by direction provide for the exercise of the rights by the appropriate Minister.</P>
    <P>We are applying the provisions of the Minerals Development Act, 1940 and the Petroleum and other Minerals Development Act, 1960, which govern mineral and petroleum exploration and exploitation in the land area and territorial waters, to similar operations in the shelf area thus providing a legal framework for the grant of exploration licences and exploitation facilities to operators in the area.</P>
    <P>Provision is made for the extension of criminal and civil law to installations in designated areas and waters within 500 metres of such installations and in the case of other parts of designated areas, to any act or omission arising out of the exploration or exploitation of the natural resources of the areas and for the prosecution of offences taking place in the shelf area.</P>
    <P>The Bill also provides for the safety <Col N="1248" /> of navigation and installations in the shelf area and for the prevention of the pollution of the sea from pipe lines or installations.</P>
    <P>The provisions of the Submarine Telegraph Act, 1885 which deals with the wilful or negligent breaking or injuring of cables or pipelines, are being extended to all cables and pipelines and the provisions of the Wireless Telegraphy Acts, 1926 and 1956, which relate to the control of and interference with wireless telegraphy, are being extended to wireless apparatus on or near installations.</P>
    <P>Provision is also made for the extension of insurance cover under the Social Welfare Acts and the Insurance (Intermittent Unemployment) Acts to persons engaged in exploration or exploitation in the designated shelf areas.</P>
    <P>I am sure that the Senators feel, as I do, that the exploration and exploitation of the natural resources of our continental shelf area is highly desirable and I hope that they will agree that this measure will provide a satisfactory legal framework for the carrying out of such work.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We welcome the Bill though there are some things in it which we would welcome clarification on.  Certainly it is a useful Bill and one which we hope we will have to put into practical application in the not too distant future.  The Minister did not raise too many hopes on the question of the existence of oil deposits in the seas, which are relevant to the Bill. Nevertheless, it is something we should continue to concern ourselves with. There have been from time to time reports, possibly ill-informed ones, of the possibility of oil being discovered in the Irish Sea, and I think that we ought to, as I presume the Government are turning their minds to the question of how the exploration of those possibilities should best be carried on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the Dáil one of the speakers, Deputy Moore, seemed to blame God for our lack of national resources, and I suppose if anybody is to be blamed it must be God, but we have tended not to look for our national resources and to blame Him unfairly and prematurely, <Col N="1249" /> as indicated by our experience recently in regard to certain metal ores found under our soil.</P>
    <P>This reminds me of a Sinn Féin meeting I attended 11 years ago when the Sinn Féin Party was more active than it was before or since perhaps.  I went to it to inform myself of their point of view and to find out what they had to offer, not that I was thinking or desirous of joining them.  I thought that in fairness I ought to find out their viewpoint and whether there was anything in what they held that should be considered either with a view to resisting or accepting it.  So I attended that meeting in College Green and stayed there throughout the meeting.</P>
    <P>The thing that struck me about it was that the orator was saying then that there must be extensive and rich coal deposits under Ireland.  He had much more faith in his argument than Deputy Moore had.  He said this on the grounds that God could not have been unfair to Ireland by giving us less coal than England.  From that he drew the firm conclusion that the facility of bankers and others was preventing the exploitation of these coal resources which certainly existed.  I would not go that far in regard to either the sea or the land but I would hope that the possibility of exploring for oil will be followed up. This raises several questions.</P>
    <P>First of all, I should like to be clear as to the oil concession we have already given the Ambassador Company&mdash;I forget into whose hands it has now fallen; it has changed hands once or twice.  Does it extend only to the land area of Ireland or does it extend to any coastal waters and if it extends to any coastal waters, does it extend beyond, say, the three mile limit?  Are we, in fact, free to give concessions for exploration and development within the terms of the existing concession being given to this company and whoever their successor may be?  If the concession given to this company extends to any coastal waters, could we know what coastal waters?  My recollection&mdash; the concession was given some years ago&mdash;is that one quarter of the country was to fall in at some point.  They had to opt after five years in favour of <Col N="1250" /> giving up the concession in respect of a quarter of the country.  If the concession extended to all coastal waters, then this would involve the giving up of the concession to those coastal waters also.</P>
    <P>Could we know is there any relevance in this concession to the Bill or are we in the position that all the coastal waters, including the area between land and the three mile limit, are available to us and are not the subject to an existing concession to any particular company?</P>
    <P>As regards the exploration for development of these mineral rights, and particularly oil rights, I think that we should turn our attention as much as possible towards developing these rights ourselves.  We have tended hitherto automatically without much thought to hand over the mineral rights on a concession basis to various foreign concerns from whom we will get royalties in due course, although in some instances the concessions we have had to make to them will outweigh for a long time to come any royalties we could get.  This inability on our part of unwillingness to contemplate undertaking any of this work ourselves is in part at least a reflection of our general technological weakness and the fact that we simply are not geared to undertake or organise this kind of work.  It has been a serious problem that we have not had available to us the necessary expertise even to contemplate organising this on a basis in which the State would participate.</P>
    <P>In the North Sea if I recall correctly the British Petroleum Company is one of the concerns that has substantial concessions.  This is, of course, owned by the British Government to a very large degree.  I should like to feel that there is some prospect that the Government are looking into the question of ensuring that if there are possibilities here to be explored and possibilities of development they would not automatically be given as a concession to foreign concerns if a joint concern or, and this may be less probable, an Irish state-owned concern could do this work.  We should not allow ourselves automatically to assume that this is <Col N="1251" /> out of the question, that we have not got the necessary technological resources. We should certainly at least endeavour to ensure that anything of this kind in the future would be done by a concern in which the State had not merely a right to secure royalties but, through share participation, a right to share in the profits.</P>
    <P>We recognise, of course, that any such exploration work would be highly speculative and the Minister is right not to raise too many hopes in this regard in what he said.  The tradition has been in this country that the State does not engage in unduly speculative adventures, that these are very much for private enerprise.  This, I think, may have been a mistake.  Our tradition has been to discourage speculative activity by the State and, indeed, this is true in relation to industrial grants. We have tended to measure the success of industrial grant programmes by how small the trade relations can achieve.</P>
    <P>The Taoiseach speaking at Killarney at the Irish Management Institute conference said a couple of weeks ago that, perhaps, we had gone too far in that direction and that we would, perhaps, be more successful if we were not attempting to keep the failure rate down by being too stringent about projects but were prepared to take a chance occasionally.  I would agree with this.  I know that the contrary view can be held.  The contrary view is rigidly held about certain major projects which the Government walked into because they were attracted by the scale of the project and the possible gains not always of a purely economic character but perhaps of a political character which came after.  I would be critical of some of these projects such as the Potez project, some of these major ones in which I think errors have been made.  Nevertheless, even saying that, we should be prepared to encourage the State, while endeavouring to ensure that these types of major blunders are not made, to be prepared to speculate and to ensure that if there are any resourses that we benefit from these directly if in order to achieve this it is necessary to invest a certain amount of money very speculatively in exploration rather than to <Col N="1252" /> hand over the whole venture to foreign concerns.  I think that on all sides of the House we would prefer that would be done and that we would prefer that a certain amount of money be lost if it does not come off than that all the benefits of this, apart, perhaps, from some royalties, should accrue to interests outside this country.  It is worth making that point at this stage.</P>
    <P>One thing that puzzled me in what the Minister said here and in the Dáil is about the extent of the area over which we are taking to ourselves rights under this Bill arising out of the international Convention with which it is connected.  In his opening remarks here and in the Dáil he said that the area concerned ran into several hundred miles off the coast in certain directions and half way across the Irish Sea.  In reply to the Dáil debate he said that on one interpretation it might extend half way out into the Atlantic, if I understood him correctly.  This puzzles me a little because the Minister's opening statement referred to the depth in the area concerned as being not more than 200 metres or where exploitation is possible.  I should like to know up to what depth is exploitation possible because I thought the middle of the Atlantic was very deep and that nobody could even get to the bottom never mind to dig anything out.</P>
    <P>I cannot quite reconcile his statement that the area over which you can extend control under the Convention in this Bill is the area in which you can exploit these resources at the bottom of the sea but, at the same time, this could extend to the middle of the Atlantic unless the Minister is talking about sedentary swimming fish which are floating half way up in the middle of the Atlantic.  I should like him to expand that a little because there is a difficulty in reconciling his statements here.</P>
    <P>We ought to be as clear as possible as to what area of control we are potentially taking charge of.  It would be nice to think we might own half the Atlantic Ocean at least in respect of these rights here but is this realistic? Is there any possibility of exploiting this area when it goes to a great depth? What, in fact, is the depth to which <Col N="1253" /> these explorations currently go?  Is this 200 metre figure realistic?  Is it the actual depth to which it is now possible to exploit for oil, for example, or is the depth less or greater than this? We ought to have some indication as to what, in fact, is the practicable depth at this point in time, although, of course, due to development, it may be extended.</P>
    <P>Another point arose in the Dáil as to the possibility of having a map. The Minister evaded this point, understandably I suppose, as far as the Atlantic is concerned in view of the doubt as to how one might interpret a Convention in the Bill in that direction. One thing that is certain must be the dividing line in the Irish Sea because the one thing that is fixed is the position of Ireland, England and the Isle of Man.  They will not change much in the years ahead.  It should be possible to tell us where this line is within the Irish Sea.  It must be a little complicated to draw because what is the position of the Isle of Man?  Is it regarded as part of Britain and is the sea between it and Britain, therefore, regarded as an inland sea or do you disregard it and go half way across the Irish Sea and possibly draw your line through the Isle of Man&mdash;having it and the three-mile area around it as a separate enclave?  How, in fact, is this line to be drawn in the Irish Sea?</P>
    <P>We ought to be shown on a map what area is involved in this as far as the Irish Sea is concerned because there you do not have the same problem of definition which you have when you move in the other direction out into the Atlantic.  The Minister should clarify this.  Even if at this stage he can by description indicate to us what part of the Irish Sea is involved and what happens about the Isle of Man&mdash;I cannot quite visualise this&mdash;this would help us to have some idea as to what we are doing in regard to the Bill.  We have a right to know just what areas we are taking control of under this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Douglas and the Isle of Man are Irish during the summer months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Not as much <Col N="1254" /> as they used to be.  Every time I look at an Aer Lingus timetable there seems to be one flight less than there was when I used to be making them up about 12 years ago.  The distinction between swimming fish and sedentary fish in the Bill is also important because it might be that the Bill would extend our resources in this regard.  It is important that we should be told what the distinction is between these two types of fish.</P>
      <P>I seem to recall being told many years ago that under the Treaty the coastal waters of Ireland were vested in the Irish Free State.  When Northern Ireland opted out of the Irish Free State, and that is what happened because under the Treaty the island of Ireland opted out of the United Kingdom and about a month later Northern Ireland opted out of the Irish Free State and went back to the United Kingdom, and I seem to remember that this opting out of Northern Ireland did not include the coastal waters of Ireland and that they remain under our control and protection.  We have heard no more about that matter since but the question does arise under this Bill.  I would like to know what would happen in this matter between us and Northern Ireland, how do you propose to draw a line across the sea between us?  Is it the legal position that we have control over the coastal waters around the whole island and not merely that part of it which was formerly the Irish Free State and is now the Republic of Ireland?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the Dáil the Minister seemed to brush aside the question of the police problems that might be involved under this Bill and he seemed to feel that any exploitation of resources under the Bill would have to be more fixed and less mobile than fishing vessels and that the control and policing of these would not create problems of providing additional vessels of the fishery protection kind. I can see problems with policing involved if there is exploitation of resources around our coasts and I am not sure if we are equipped to cope with such problems, such as problems created by certain dangers that might be involved. Are we equipped, and I doubt if we are, to inspect and control such activities? <Col N="1255" /> Oil rights have been known to collapse and while the Minister seems to think that these activities will not create any such problems I feel that we might have to extend our existing resources to secure adequate policing.</P>
    <P>I should like also to ask the Minister what would be the position in the case of a pirate radio station or a station such as Radio Caroline operating within our half of the Irish sea?  Will it be within our power to control any such activities from a ship or from a fixed structure, because if that is so the pirate radio problem will no longer exist?  I am not quite clear if this problem is fully covered in the Bill.</P>
    <P>There is a point of detail which I should like to bring to the attention of the Minister although, perhaps, it might be better dealt with on Committee Stage.  I notice that in section 5, subsection (5), there is provision for costs to be imposed by a person holding an inquiry under this section on any other person who appears or is represented at the inquiry even if these costs are incurred by someone else.  I should like to know what exactly is the meaning behind that provision.  It seems odd to me but I am sure there is some quite good reason for it.  I should also like to know if there are any provisions for an appeal in this section.  The person against whom costs are given might like to appeal against that decision.  Such a decision in the courts can be appealed against but I do not see any appeal mechanism here.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It appears to me that the passage of this Bill will open up a completely new position as far as the jurisdiction of this country is concerned. At the moment it seems that we have jurisdiction to the 12-mile limit but this Bill is going to extend that limit.  It is mentioned in the Bill that the continental shelf includes half the Irish sea, 200 miles off the south-west coast of Ireland and 160 miles off the west coast.  It is probable that this matter was in the mind of the Minister when he did not mention what the area north of Ireland would be. Has the Minister considered the waters off County Donegal?  The legislation mentions the east coast, the south-west <Col N="1256" /> coast, the west coast but there is nothing about the northern coast.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>County Donegal has a west coast too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I know that but the north of Donegal has not been mentioned in the Bill and I wonder why that area was omitted from the Minister's statement.  I also wonder whether any consideration was given to the question of the northern part of Donegal and to the northern part of Ireland.  I feel that there are prospects for the finding of oil, gas and petroleum around our coasts.  We are moving with the times in bringing in a Bill of this nature.  We have seen what modern techniques are capable of achieving, and this Bill will prepare us not alone to deal with the implications of the advent of new techniques but also to put ourselves on an organised basis in so far as any discoveries in this field may arise.</P>
      <P>I noted in the Minister's speech that a number of European countries have not yet opted into this arrangement. The Minister may correct me if my interpretation is not right.  Spain, for instance, was not mentioned.  Spain is a very large country on the west coast of the Continent with a very large coastline, and when it was not mentioned in the Minister's statement I began to wonder if there is any reason why a country like Spain has omitted to make these arrangements or has decided not to take steps in that direction.</P>
      <P>I agree with Senator FitzGerald that with the aid of modern techniques, particularly depth sounding apparatus which we have now, we might have some kind of contour map made of the continental shelf particularly since we are bringing in legislation defining the continental shelf and conferring certain powers in regard to it.  It is desirable such a map should be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When reading the Minister's statement I was surprised in relation to the limit of the continental shelf to the west and south-west of Ireland.  There must have been some reason why our continental shelf limit was brought down to something around 165 miles or 200 miles beyond the coast of west <Col N="1257" /> and south-west Ireland.  Why is it that we have not the same arrangement as there is in the Irish Sea&mdash;that our limit should extend half-way between the US and this country?</P>
    <P>It has been mentioned that the new area which this Bill proposes to bring in will probably be bigger than Ireland itself and I have no doubt this new arrangement will bring with it further responsibilities.  There will be repercussions as far as the jurisdiction of the area is concerned.  Again, with the advance of technological knowledge, we may find ourselves having to do further policing of the continental shelf around this country.  Already we have to police the 12-mile limit and if modern technology brings us to a stage where the highly-developed countries will be able to get advantages from certain activities within the limits of that continental shelf, further responsibility for jurisdiction within that area will fall on us.</P>
    <P>They are just some of the implications of the Bill.  Bringing in this legislation was a timely move at this stage in anticipation of what may be discovered as a result of new techniques in relation to prospecting, particularly the exploration of the sea bed.  There is a length of 200 metres mentioned in the Minister's statement and it was not clear to me whether that measurement is from sea level or from a certain depth&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a depth of 200 metres.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought it was a depth of 200 metres from the sea bed itself&mdash;involving underwater mountains if you like.  Off the coast of Japan, for instance, you might have a depth of seven or eight miles in the Pacific. I misread it.  It is fair to say that the need for this legislation became clear as a result of the valuable discoveries by Holland in 1959 when they found a huge gas field adjoining Northern Holland.  In Britain, too, there is a movement towards the use of natural gas and I know that some of the hardware merchants are advertising, not alone in Britain but here, various gadgets which can be adapted to the use of natural gas.  It shows the trend.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1258" /> What has been done here in relation to the continental shelf around this country is negligible.  We cannot say yet if there is any potential in regard to gas, petroleum or mineral products. We know that underwater prospecting is extremely expensive and even if we make a discovery we shall be dependent on the larger financial resources of other countries to provide the various techniques and to take an interest in prospecting work because, it is so much more expensive to do this kind of exploration in winning gas or petroleum from the sea bed, that it is beyond our capacity to do.</P>
    <P>Another point which arises is this. Will the Minister have a prospecting licence arrangement such as there has been for the mainland territory of the Republic where prospecting licences are made available in certain circumstances? Have we reached the stage here in relation to the continental shelf when the Minister will consider it desirable to have the question of prospecting licences issued and if so will the conditions attaching to them be on the same lines as those attached to the mainland?  Because there is not much knowledge available yet in relation to undersea exploration, we should delay making a decision in relation to the conditions that would apply to the issue of prospecting licences for a reasonable time.  We have watched with interest some of the efforts in the North Sea, particularly.</P>
    <P>In the North Sea some very large pockets of natural gas have been discovered and it is quite possible similar deposits could be found inside our continental shelf.  Until we see these techniques developed I think the Minister would be advised not to make it easy for people to get prospecting licences which would be of great advantage to them and possibly a great disadvantage as far as benefits to this country would be concerned.  I welcome the Bill.  I think that it is moving along with the times and modern techniques.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>There are one or two points about this Bill on which I should like some clarification <Col N="1259" /> if possible.  It is entitled an Act to make provision in relation to the exploration and exploitation of the continental shelf.  The continental shelf is not defined in the Bill.  There are only two definitions in the Bill.  One of them tells us what a designated area is and the other tells us what the Minister is. Those are the only two items defined in the Bill.  The Minister in his speech referred, of course, to the International Convention on the Continental Shelf and he said: &ldquo;The continental shelf is defined as the sea bed and subsoil of the submarine area adjacent to the coast but outside the territorial waters to a depth of 200 metres or beyond that limit where the depth of the waters permits exploitation&rdquo;.  Two points arise out of that definition.  The first one is that the word &ldquo;depth&rdquo; is used apparently with two different meanings in the same sentence.  If I understand the Minister correctly &ldquo;outside the territorial waters to a depth of 200 metres&rdquo; means to a distance of 200 metres or does it mean as long as the water is only 200 metres or not deeper?  The second point is that apparently the continental shelf definition is flexible in that if it becomes possible to exploit further beyond that limit then it is still the continental shelf beyond that limit where the depth of the water permits exploitation.  Exploitation under present conditions or under future conditions?  With technical developments it might be possible to exploit down to a depth of half a mile, two miles or five miles.  I take it that this definition is in the Convention but is it a satisfactory one? Does it really cover only the continental shelf or what we might understand as such?  Is it, in fact, to be exploited beyond the limit of 200 metres where the depth of the water permits exploitation?</P>
      <P>In relation to the definition of our rights under this Continental Shelf Convention section 2, subsection (1) of the Bill says:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Any rights of the State outside territorial waters over the sea bed and subsoil for the purpose of exploring such sea bed and subsoil and exploiting their natural resources are, subject <Col N="1260" /> to subsection (2) of this section, hereby vested in the Minister and shall be exercisable by the Minister.</P>
    <P>This means any rights we have outside our territorial waters.  I take it this means rights under the continental shelf Convention.  Then we find from the Minister, rather to our dismay, that although we signed this Convention we have not ratified it yet.  The Minister mentioned that this had been ratified by practically every country concerned. Out of 46 countries 37 have ratified it, including Britain, France, Denmark, Portugal, Holland, Sweden and even Switzerland.  The Irish Republic is still pondering on this question.  I should like to ask the Minister why.  What has been holding us up?  I would say that, in general, Ireland's record in the ratification of international Conventions, duly signed, is fairly good.  We have been fairly quick.  I do not know why we have been so slow here.  The Convention came into force internationally in 1964.  It was first discussed in 1958. This is 1968 and of the 46 countries, nine have not ratified it and we are one of those.  Can the Minister tell us why?</P>
    <P>The only other point I should like to make is in support of the socialist point of view put before us by Senator FitzGerald that the State here should be a little bolder in its willingness to develop our resources itself and should not be too eager to pass over the powers of the Minister, which we give him under this Bill, to some private entrepreneur and private profit seeker. We got our fingers badly burned in the question of the Avoca mines.  We had this approved by both the big Parties and although Mianraí Teoranta had, in fact, been hoping to be allowed to develop the copper resources and had, in fact, made proposals for the slow development of these mines, a development geared not to world markets but to our own national needs, although this was put forward our worthy politicians decided that it would be marvellous to get Canadians to burn their fingers rather than the Irish and decided to lend them money to do it and then lent them money to pay us the interest on the money we had lent them and we took as security the mines which they were running with money we had lent <Col N="1261" /> them.  This is called private enterprise as interpreted by politicians of the big Parties in this country.  I hope that there will not be anything like that in relation to exploitation of possible deposits on the Atlantic shelf.</P>
    <P>I remember being told at the time the Canadians came over and had a look at the Avoca mines they were told by some of the Irish engineers who had done some of the prospecting that the Finns had developed a slow method of smelting the ore in Finland using local resources and that this might be possible here, whereupon the Canadians flew immediately to Finland. Within 10 days they came back with full knowledge of what was being done there and produced it to our Government and our Government accepted this as wonderful Canadian know-how in deference to the fact that they came from the North American continent.  I feel we have got a lot of know-how in this country and I think the present Minister is one of those politicians who is more prepared than most to place confidence in this local know-how and our local skills.  I should like, therefore, to support what Senator FitzGerald said in relation to a certain boldness in relation to those resources and in relation to State ventures in general because if mineral resources are to be discovered arising out of the powers we give to the Minister under this Bill, then I should like to feel that the major benefits will be spread to the community as a whole and not merely be piped off as profits to either local or outside speculators coming in for the purpose of satisfying their greed for profit.  I would prefer to see those kinds of resources which are not due to any individual in the country but if we are to claim ownership of them I should like to see the benefit from them accruing to the whole community.  I support, therefore, what Senator FitzGerald said in that connection and I support it with at least a measure of confidence that the Minister now before us would, in general, be in sympathy with that view.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the Bill is to provide, I hope, a statutory framework for the exploration and <Col N="1262" /> exploitation of the natural resources of this country's part of the continental shelf.  On the face of it that seems to be a very desirable objective and it is, but I do not think anybody should have any illusions whatever.  Judging by our exploitation and exploration of natural resources on land or under the country, we can see how far we are from reality in a measure of this nature.  There is no objection, of course, to the measure before the House but I should like to ask one or two questions on it.  It is ten years since this issue came up and it has taken the Government quite a long time to come to a decision.  I should like to know whether or not at present the Government have applications from companies, either American or Canadian, to carry out some prospecting on our continental shelf?  Would the Minister, when he is replying, comment on that?</P>
      <P>It is rather significant that we have had a rush of prospectors from all parts of the globe to this country over the last few years and it would not surprise me that a few more would be anxious to explore what they can get from our seas.  I always believe in first things first and priority for those things within our reach.  To judge from the attempts made to explore and develop our natural resources the record of various Governments in that field is disgraceful.</P>
      <P>Senator Sheehy Skeffington mentioned the Avoca Mines affair where the name of poor St. Patrick was involved. Whenever a shady venture is involved in this country you may be sure some Saint's name is attached to it or the shamrock is utilised to give it the appearance of being aboveboard. Let us take another mining area in this country to indicate how pathetic the Government's efforts are to utilise the resources of the skilled manpower we have in Ireland.  I refer to the Tynagh mines.  We allowed a consortium from Canada to pull out of the earth the greatest possible wealth we have for smelting in European industrial concerns.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have had statements by the Canadians to the effect that it is too soon yet to make any decision about setting up a smelting plant but, of <Col N="1263" /> course, they have no intention of doing that.  Their whole aim is to get as much as they can out of the country and produce financial reasons why it would not pay them to process in Ireland.  Of course, Tynagh benefits from the employment given to extract the ore but the profits go outside the country after the ores are dug up.  We pursue the lunatic policy of spending large sums of money on transport and on port facilities to permit the export of the raw material instead of insisting, if we want private enterprise and this type of exploration of our natural resources, that the material should be processed within the State.  Another natural resource we have is our fishing industry.  I am afraid we are not giving any help to that industry.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Sheldon) Acting Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will have to relate that to the Bill under discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>The fishing industry is mentioned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>There is just a passing reference.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is more than a passing reference in it.  There is the question swimming fish and other fish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Sedentary fish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>They all come under this Bill.  The swimming fish are excluded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no responsibility in that regard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>I know you have not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Senator had better get to the Bill as quickly as possible.  He is going far away from it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should not like to cross swords with the Chair.  I want to see the fishing developed, whether sedentary fish, swimming fish or flying fish are involved.  We are not doing much about any of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1264" />
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Flying fish are not in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>We have some board called An Bord Iascaigh Mhara making noises about the fishing industry at present.  They are not getting to the root of the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>They are too sedentary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator know what has happened in England and in Holland?  The Senator is talking so much about the fishing industry that we are anxious to discover if he knows what is happening in Holland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>That may be so but this is not in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>He talked a lot about Tynagh and now he is talking about fishing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Does Senator Ó Maoláin know anything about the fishing industry?  If he does he should be ashamed of his life because he has done nothing about it although he was in a position to do something about it. I forgive him because I think he knows nothing about it.  The only thing he knows about it is to eat a couple of herring on Friday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps we might discuss the Continental Shelf Bill now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator's question was not an intelligent question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an intelligent question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am precluded by the Chair from dealing with it.  If there are difficulties as far as the fishing industry is concerned and if there are difficulties as far as the fishing industry in Iceland is concerned that is no reason why we should hang our heads and say: &ldquo;We will not do anything about our own industry.&rdquo; Leave it at that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>You will.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1265" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>In deference to your ruling, I will until he trots it out again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a ruling. It is a suggestion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Our efforts in that regard have been pathetic.  Therefore, anybody foolish enough, when he reads this White Paper, to think because this Bill provides the necessary statutory framework that we will get great things is only codding himself.  I believe it is only an attempt to raise a noise to say we have already got applications for prospecting licences from some people outside.  Even if we were in a position to do any development work ourselves the question of protection arises.</P>
      <P>Are we being practical about matters of this nature at all?  Again, in relation to the fishing industry we are unable to keep an eye on our fishing grounds and protect the 12-mile limit. Is it seriously suggested that we have been in a position to enforce our legal and other rights 50, 60 or 70 miles outside the 12-mile limit?  What steps could be taken by this Government to ensure that our legal rights were safeguarded? We had this terrible tragedy off the coast of Wexford recently and were it not for our kindly neighbours we would not be able to do a thing about it.</P>
      <P>What could we do to protect something that we laid claim to off the coast that might be of value and that some outsider decided he would take control of?  Could we have any idea from the Fianna Fáil Government what steps they would take under such circumstances? Would they ask John Bull to do the job?  It is all very fine to put down here items in legislation but it is a different kettle of fish altogether when you go to implement them.  As I have said, we are not able to look after our fishing within the 12-mile limit not to mind talking of our mineral resources on the continental shelf from people outside who do not give a continental damn about us if they want to exploit what we have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is another point that struck me while the Minister was reading his brief, and that is the question of wrecks off our coast.  I do not know <Col N="1266" /> whether this is of great importance or not, but I gather that at the moment with the latest techniques available it is quite possible that valuable cargo which has been in ships sunk off our coasts for hundreds of years may now be salvaged.  If such a vessel lies on the continental shelf in our new territory and there is an attempt made to salvage it, and perhaps it is discovered that there are substantial valuable goods on it, who is the owner in such circumstances?  Have the Government under this legislation any rights in regard to treasure of that nature?  I am not talking about what is within the 12-mile or the three-mile limit.</P>
    <P>Again, in this field we should consider that only recently off the Kerry coast we had a little bit of competition with two groups, one amateur and the other professional, exploring the possibilities of salvaging a sunken vessel. Indeed, they are looked upon with amusement and astonishment by the local people who wonder at all this. The reason I mention it is that the very people who live on our coasts have lost the traditional feeling for the sea and the spirit of adventure in that regard, and when people come from Welsh coastal towns to exploit what is off our own coasts and to do it in their own time as amateurs the prospects do not look good as far as we are concerned as to going out and exploiting the continental shelf ourselves.</P>
    <P>I should like to support the views put by both Senators Sheehy Skeffington and FitzGerald that the State itself should be more interested in this development and show more drive.  I do not know whether I would be misquoting Senator FitzGerald in saying that he felt that the State should not allow private enterprise so much scope to reap benefits without giving to the community full measure in return.  We know that as far as the development and exploration carried out in connection with natural gas is concerned the British Government are taking a very keen interest in this to make sure that this natural wealth will not be exploited for the purpose of private greed but that the good of the community must come first.  In all the developments that have taken place in this country it was <Col N="1267" /> private greed that got priority, not the public good.  I think that we should alter our views in that regard and start off on the right footing as far as this is concerned whenever we do start.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>Obviously this is a necessary and acceptable Bill.  I share the view, however, of Senator FitzGerald that some further definition seems desirable.  When I took the Bill up first I expected to see a fairly elaborate schedule at the end setting out and defining limits and boundaries and so on, and I do agree with Senator FitzGerald that further definitions should be added.</P>
      <P>There is one particular point I would like to ask about.  Strictly speaking it belongs to Committee Stage but it may save an unnecessary amendment if I raise it now.  I find in section 7 that any person guilty of an offence under this section shall be liable to a fine not exceeding £100 on summary conviction. It appears to me that this is a most trifling sum in the eyes of big oil magnates making, perhaps, millions of pounds out of exploiting the oil on our continental shelf.  I should like to be assured by the Minister&mdash;I imagine he can do this&mdash;that the district justice or whoever it is who would be concerned with such an action is not liable to feel himself restricted to this £100 limit in the case of a major discharge or escape of oil.  What I am trying to clarify is, supposing you have a gigantic escape of oil from one of those machines on the continental shelf, and suppose this causes something like the disastrous conditions they had on the south west coast of England last year, I am hoping that our courts of justice would be entitled to put a colossal fine on the people responsible for it.  I would hope that our courts would not be limited to a £100 fine in those circumstances.  I take it that what would happen in those circumstances would be that the district justice would say that this was not a matter for summary conviction and there must be an indictment, but I should like to be absolutely certain about that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley) George Colley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley)</NameTxt>
      <P>If I may, perhaps, deal <Col N="1268" /> with Senator Stanford's point first, the question of the amount of the fine.  This provision of the Act applies only in the case of summary conviction.  In the case of a serious offence the conviction would be by way of indictment, in which case there is no limit to the fine that may be imposed, and, indeed, imprisonment may be imposed.  We have not got, as far as I know, any provision in other Acts of the Oireachtas for fines exceeding £100 on summary conviction, and it seems to me to be a reasonable practice that we should not depart from that provided we make provision for cases of much more importance than that by providing for conviction on indictment.</P>
      <P>There is also another point raised by Senator FitzGerald which I might dispose of.  That was in relation to section 5 subsection (5) regarding the imposition of costs of an inquiry.  This provision is similar to the provision in section 18 (f) and (g) of the Foreshore Act, 1933.  Senators will appreciate that what we are doing is to apply the existing civil and criminal law in the main to our area of the continental shelf, and in this case we apply this provision of the Foreshore Act to our area of the continental shelf.  The provision is, in fact, taken from the Foreshore Act, 1933.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the question raised by Senator McQuillan about our right to recover some of the lost treasure ships of the Spanish Armada or otherwise which are reputed to lie off our coasts, I am sorry to say that this Bill will not advance our efforts to recover them or our claims in respect of them.  The Bill deals only with the rights of this country to explore and exploit the natural resources of our areas of the continental shelf.  I am sure Senator McQuillan is well aware of our natural resources.  Senator McQuillan also asked whether there had been inquiries or requests by foreign groups or companies to be allowed to explore areas of our continental shelf.  The answer is &ldquo;yes&rdquo; and I said so in my introductory speech.  On page 4 I said that some oil companies have, however, indicated an interest in exploring our area of <Col N="1269" /> shelf, which suggests the area has possibilities for oil and gas and there is no reason why they should not entertain hopes of success.</P>
    <P>Some Senators displayed concern about the delineation of our area of the continental shelf and, indeed, I think one Senator suggested that we might have a map showing our area. There may be some misconception here.  Let me reiterate that the basis on which our area is defined is that in the case of our western coast our rights extend where the sea has a depth of 200 metres or we may go beyond that where it is feasible to exploit the resources. I shall return to that matter in a moment.</P>
    <P>As between ourselves and Britain, roughly speaking, the division is half-way across the Irish Sea because I believe most of it is not deeper than 200 metres.  I assume this is the reason. If it is not deeper it is certainly clearly within the continental shelf.  The question that arises on the east side of the country is the definition of the boundary between ourselves and Britain, as to where our rights finish and begin and <i>vice versa.</i> There is no problem about the main portion of the Irish Sea with which we will be concerned.  That is quite clear.  These are the areas in which we would be directly interested for some time to come.</P>
    <P>The definition of the boundary between us will depend on negotiations which will take place between us and the British Government.  In delineating the boundaries lines on maps must have regard to charts and geographical features as they exist at a particular date and reference must be made to permanent fixed points on land: so that, as far as the east coast is concerned, we do not propose to define the limits as yet, pending completion of negotiation with the British Government.</P>
    <P>In regard to the western coast the definition of the continental shelf to which I have referred allows of at least two interpretations.  The clause permitting extension of the area of 200 metres of depth where the waters permit exploitation of the area would give rise to the different interpretations. <Col N="1270" /> One concept is that while the coastal State may extend its jurisdiction beyond the 200 metre depth the area to which it may lay claim is limited by the phrase &ldquo;adjacent to the coast&rdquo; which is in the definition.  A separate interpretation is that exploitation ability is the only criterion and as that exploitation ability develops coastal States may extend their area to the deep sea floor, and they may extend to waters between ourselves and the United States.  This question will probably be clarified by international agreement before it becomes one of practical importance which it is not at the moment.</P>
    <P>The 1958 Convention may be revised next year, which is five years after its coming into force, and it is possible that it may be settled then but it is not a practical difficulty at the moment. I am sure Senators will see that in these circumstances it is not feasible for us to define ultimately the extent of our portion of the continental shelf. That is why we are providing in the Bill that this sea may be defined by order.  It will change from time to time depending on technical developments. Also, the case of eastern waters will depend on the result of negotiations with the British Government.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I raised a question about the Isle of Man and that was not entirely frivolous.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>This will be a matter for negotiation with the British Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The Isle of Man is not a part of the United Kingdom but is a separate territory under the control of the United Kingdom Government and the Minister should not too easily permit the British to claim that their area includes the Isle of Man, that it should be included as a separate enclave, ignoring it and then inventing it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate the Senator's point.  He may rest assured that at any such negotiations any point which may be of advantage to us will be used.  That brings me to a matter which I think Senator FitzGerald mentor' <Col N="1271" /> tioned.  It referred to the view he heard expressed that for technical reasons at the time of the creation of the State of Northern Ireland the territorial waters around that area remain with us.  I have heard this argument put forward but, as of now, I am not aware of the basis for the argument, nor am I aware of any practice that has occurred that has lent substance to it, but I am not to be taken as foregoing any rights we may have in that area.  I am not aware of that but if we have them we will claim them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be nice to see the Treaty coming into use again for this purpose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should not draw me on this further.  The question was asked whether it was proposed to proceed on the continental shelf area as we do on the land area; that is, the granting of licences to explore the area and subsequently, if necessary, the granting of mining leases.  This is, in fact, the way we propose to proceed as is provided for in section 4 of the Bill.  In general, what we are doing is to proceed in that area as we have proceeded on the land area and to import into these areas, as far as it is possible, the various legal entities in introducing the statutes which operate in our land area at present.</P>
      <P>A question was also raised as to whether as a result of this Bill we will be dealing with such institutions as Radio Caroline.  This is not contemplated as far as this Bill is concerned because our rights in this regard relate only to such rights as are necessary to us to explore and exploit the natural resources of the continental shelf.  This would not include dealing with such matters as Radio Caroline.  The reference in the Bill to wireless apparatus refers to wireless apparatus on installations within our area of the continental shelf.  If something like Radio Caroline was to be set up in that area on an installation put there for the purposes of exploration or exploitation of the continental shelf this would come within the terms of the Bill but this is unlikely.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1272" />
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely Radio Caroline is exploiting the continental shelf?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>That may be so but I am not aware of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>If the pop records are exploitation, then that is part of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>That is for the next Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to make it clear that in regard to our rights in this matter the better legal view is that these rights are not conferred on us by the international Convention but that they exist and obtain through our national sovereignty although they are not sovereign rights in that area.  The Convention had defined our rights but they exist through our national sovereignty. Some Senators have raised the question of the manner in which it is proposed to exploit them and have complained that we have in land areas allowed our resources to be exploited by private interests instead of having the State exploit them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>By private external interests.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Some of the people referred to are, in fact, Irish people. Many people who have been particularly successful in this regard are Irish people.  They may have acquired their expertise in other countries but they are Irish people, Irish born.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>A Canadian company.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  I wonder, when I hear people saying this kind of thing, how far back they cast their minds? It is not so far back when we were all told that we had no mineral resources in Ireland.  It is not so far back when the State embarked on mineral exploration and spent a good deal of money on it, apart altogether from the Avoca mines.  That is not so far back but it is some years and a good deal of money was spent and the fact of the matter is that we did not discover our mineral resources to any great extent <Col N="1273" /> until we engaged private enterprise to do this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>That was not so in the case of the Avoca mines. The prospecting was done and the discovery was made by Mianraí Teoranta but the exploitation was done by foreign interests.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is speaking of the Avoca mines in particular but I am speaking about the situation in general.  If Senators think I am exaggerating the importance of the inducements we are now offering in this regard I would ask them to have a look across the Border and to wonder why it is that all the mineral exploitation going on in this country is all going on south of the Border.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It must be God's fault again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>That is one particular explanation which I am not prepared to accept.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I can quote it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Not now, Senator</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very easy to say, when somebody has done a job, that we ought to take it over.  It is a different thing to say, before the job is done, that we ought to do it when we do not know where we stand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Like the Shannon Scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Any reasonable person looking at what has happened in this country in recent years is going to say that if we compare the two lines of approach there is no question as to which has been the most successful.  It might be argued that the State record in this matter could be improved and that, having learned from private enterprise in this field, the State could now go in and do the job successfully.  This may be correct but I doubt if it is so when we are talking about exploring and exploiting the continental shelf where the importance of technical know-how and of expense is a <Col N="1274" /> good deal greater than in the case of exploitation in the land.  The risks are far greater, the chances of success far less, and the capital involved much greater.</P>
      <P>I wonder if the State embarked on this and spent a number of years and many millions of pounds and paid high salaries to people with the know-how, people from outside with the know-how, and did not find any natural gas or petroleum, what the Senators would have to say about the extravagance of the Government and about their failure to do the job efficiently.  If there is any area of commercial enterprise in which private enterprise has a role to play and the State has not, it is in mineral exploration which is such a hazardous occupation and which is very largely a gamble, requiring a great deal of capital and technical know-how.</P>
      <P>There are many other areas of the economy in which the State could usefully play a much larger part than at the moment, but mineral exploration is not one of these.  People who believe that the State ought to engage in commercial or industrial activities as against private enterprise are very foolish to take this area as a basis for their argument.  It is the last area they should take.  There are other areas in which a more successful case could be made but in this area it seems to me quite clear that the correct line of approach is the one we are taking.  This is not to say that we propose to hand over completely the whole of our area of the continental shelf.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This whole matter is somewhat clouded.  Senator FitzGerald asked a question as to the position arising under the Oil Agreement of 1959.  The position is that an exploration licence under that Agreement was granted to the people who received it at the time &mdash;as the Senator has said, it has since changed hands&mdash;granting sole and exclusive rights to explore for and develop petroleum and natural gas resources, and I shall quote: &ldquo;the whole of Ireland including the sea bed and the subsoil beneath the territorial waters and high seas contiguous thereto under the control and jurisdiction of <Col N="1275" /> the Government of Ireland at that time or in the future.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There is some argument as to what that means and, naturally, the people who are in receipt of this licence&mdash;I am not dealing with the question of the surrender provisions of the licence &mdash;argued for its interpretation on the widest possible basis but that does not mean necessarily that they are correct. There have, in fact, been some discussions with those people.  They have made certain proposals which are under consideration at present, but the House may take it that the exclusive right to explore and exploit the area of our continental shelf will not be granted to one company or one licensee.  As I have mentioned, a number of inquiries have come from different international firms and these are being considered at present.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister satisfied that no interpretation of that will be upheld which would give this company, now holding the licence, this right over the continental shelf?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It sounds a very unfortunately worded concession.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>That may be so but the House will appreciate that at the time it was made nobody here or abroad contemplated what has since developed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say somebody should have, because, after all, there have been oilwells off the coast of Texas for much longer than eight years.  That is a rather weak explanation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator can inquire a little further and he will find that what I have said is correct.  I am satisfied that there is no question of an exclusive right to our continental shelf&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It is important that this should be brought out in a more developed way than the Minister has done in his statement.  I have heard rumours that this is what has been holding things up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1276" />
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not so.  The time the Bill comes forward is not related in any way&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been told that is what is holding up exploration in the Irish Sea&mdash;this dispute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>That has been said but I do not think it is true because the company concerned has been carrying out preliminary surveys, seismic and otherwise, which must be carried out first.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there a question of other companies being inhibited from doing so in the belief that the concession has been granted solely to this company?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so because the people who have made applications have been told their requests will be considered and when they have inquired further they have been told that what I have just said is so&mdash;that exclusive rights will not be given to one licensee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister should consider making a further statement in due course because, may I say, it is not satisfactory that it should come out&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>May I say that this should be left to the next Stage of the Bill?  It is not right to engage in a debate during the Minister's reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I have objected before to this question-and-answer racket which Senator FitzGerald engages in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ó Maoláin also engages in what he calls &ldquo;this racket&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I will engage the Senator one of these days and he will not like it.  I am tired of his quips.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, on the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am tired of him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Not half as tired as I.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>So is the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1277" />
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>The question of policing this area was also raised.  In so far as we need to extend our resources in order to police offences on installations in the continental shelf area we will do so, but some of the discussion here and in Dáil Éireann on this point was related to the concept of people coming in and taking away our resources in the continental shelf area without let or hindrance from us, rather in the way a foreign trawler might come in and poach our fisheries.  It was to this matter I was referring when I spoke in Dáil Éireann and Senator FitzGerald said he thinks I made rather light of it.</P>
      <P>If he realises this is what I was referring to, he will appreciate that I was not making light of it but that I was making the point that the resources we are talking about are fixed in the ground under the water, that they are not easily removable, that anybody who wants to do it on any economic scale must spend a great deal of money and instal more or less permanent apparatus.  Therefore, it is not a question of coming in fast and getting out fast and consequently I said that the policing would not present undue difficulties to us.  I believe that is so.  As far as I can see, I have covered all the main points raised in the debate.  The others will arise on the next Stage and can be dealt with then.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Acting Chairman (Professor Stanford) Acting Chairman (Professor Stanford)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Professor Stanford)</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Would Senators be agreeable to continue the Bill now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so.  There will be amendments.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 15th May, 1968.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Performers' Protection Bill, 1968:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Performers' Protection Bill, 1968: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley) George Colley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley)</NameTxt>
      <P>An International Convention for the Protection of Performers, Producers of Phonograms <Col N="1278" /> and Broadcasting Organisations was concluded at Rome in October, 1961. Ireland was represented at the Conference which drafted the Convention, which was held under the auspices of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation, the International Labour Office and the Bureau of the International Union for the Protection of Literary and Artistic Works.  The Convention was signed by 36 countries, including Ireland.  In accordance with the provisions of Article 25, the Convention entered into force on 18th May, 1964, following ratification by six countries, one of which was Britain.</P>
      <P>The provisions of the Copyright Act, 1963 which came into operation on the 1st October, 1964, meet those requirements of the Convention relating to Producers of Phonograms and Broadcasting Organisations, but there is no provision in this country for the specific protection of performers.  This Bill is designed to meet the Convention's requirements relating to performers and to enable us to ratify the Convention.</P>
      <P>Article 4 sets out a basic feature of the Convention in requiring each contracting State to grant national treatment&mdash;the same treatment as is given to nationals of the State &mdash; to performers whose performance takes place in another contracting State or is incorporated in a phonogram or a broadcast made or published in or broadcast from that other contracting State.  Section 12 of the Bill will enable the Government to satisfy this requirement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Certain acts in relation to performances which would infringe the performers' rights or would be contrary to their interests are set out in Article 7 of the Convention and the article requires that the protection to be given to performers shall include the possibility of preventing these acts.  It is not proposed to create a property right in a performance in the nature of a copyright, which a performer could enforce by civil action or which he might assign for enforcement to any group such as a performers' union.  It is proposed to meet the requirements of Article 7 in sections 2, 3 and 5 of the <Col N="1279" /> Bill.  The proposals in those sections provide for protection of performers by making it a penal offence to do certain acts in relation to performances. It will, for instance, be an offence, punishable by fine on summary conviction or conviction on indictment to make a record or a film of a performance, without the consent of the performer, to sell or hire such a record or film, or to use it for the purpose of giving a public performance.</P>
    <P>Article 12 of the Convention provides that where commercial records are used for broadcasting purposes or for public performance, the user shall make a payment to the performers or the producers of the records or both. Under the provisions of the Copyright Act, 1963, payment is required to be made by the broadcasters or users to the owners of copyright in sound recordings, that is to the producers of records, when their records are broadcast or used for public performance. Accordingly, our law already complies with Article 12 of the Convention.  It is understood that, under an agreement made between the recording companies and the various performers' unions, a percentage of the money which these companies receive for this use of their records is paid over to the performers' unions for the benefit of their members. The proposals in the present Bill will not interfere with this arrangement.</P>
    <P>This initiation of proceedings under the Act will be the responsibility of the person aggrieved.</P>
    <P>I recommend the Bill for the approval of the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>We on this side of the House welcome this Bill because we believe that the entertainment and the record industry in particular is very big business now and we feel that our artists and performers should have the utmost protection especially in view of the fact that the State has signed the documents relative to the Rome Convention, 1961.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>However, there are one or two points which the Minister might clarify for me.  Under subsection (4) of section 3 there is provision for Telefís Éireann being fined fines ranging from <Col N="1280" /> £100 to £2,000.  I believe that to an organisation like Telefís Éireann £100 is little or nothing.  It is just like a drop in the ocean.  I should like to ask the Minister would it not be better if members of the Authority were made to pay those fines or if the fines were levied on the specific officer or servant responsible.  I do not think that a fine of £100 to a big outfit like Radio Telefís Éireann would be any deterrent to not complying with the provisions of this Bill and the provisions of the Rome Treaty.  There are a few other points but, perhaps, the Minister could deal with them on Committee Stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill in so far as it affects members of trade unions in this country.  Those people and those unions are happy that the Bill is at last going through.  I will be requesting the Minister to look at certain aspects of it between now and Committee Stage.</P>
      <P>Having said that the Bill is welcome, I want to query why have we had to wait until 1968 for legislation to bring our law into line with a Convention signed in October, 1961.  October, 1961, is nearly seven years ago and I am very puzzled by the length of time that has elapsed between this matter being thoroughly ventilated and discussed at an international convention, at which I presume this country was represented, made its views known and contributed to the eventual agreement and the Bill being introduced. We have had to wait nearly seven years to have our law brought into line with that Convention.  I simply cannot understand why such a long time should elapse and I think this is also the view of the unions concerned whose members are involved in these sort of arrangements.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We had the Copyright Act in 1964 and at that time I remember raising what needed to be done to extend our legislation to fully comply with the Convention of 1961 if my memory is not at fault.  We are now getting this Bill in the so-called summer of 1968. The Bill is necessary.  It meets the requirements generally of the trade unions whose members are involved and as such it is welcome.  I should like the Minister in replying to the <Col N="1281" /> debate to attempt some explanation as to why this long period has elapsed between the signing of the convention and the appearance of the Bill before the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>There must have been an unofficial strike somewhere.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>I should also like to welcome the Bill.  It is quite clear that it is badly needed as the Minister has said.  Until now performers in Ireland had no rights in relation to the reproduction of their performances. Under this Bill they will have.</P>
      <P>Having welcomed the Bill, there are one or two matters I should like the Minister to elucidate for me.  The first is a query in relation to the circumstances under which Radio Telefís Éireann are entitled to make recordings. The basic proposition laid down in the Bill is clear enough.  If a performer has agreed to do a broadcast on radio or television, then Radio Éireann for the purpose of that broadcast can make a recording.  The Bill further provides that unless the performer agrees, that recording must be destroyed within the six months.  Where the recording concerned is of purely documentary value, then it can be kept for a longer period, in fact, permanently, with, again, the provision that it cannot be used for further broadcasting without the consent of the performer.  There are certain exceptions to this.  With regard to further recordings the exceptions are laid down in subparagraph (b) of subsection (3) of section 2 and I confess I do not understand what those relate to.  As I understand it, there are certain circumstances under which Radio Telefís Éireann are empowered to make a record which has been made by some other organisation.  This is allowed under various headings providing rebroadcast was not made for a purpose other than that for which the original performance was made.  I am not quite sure what was intended here and I should like some elucidation with regard to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a further provision which worries me a good deal more and that is about making copies of films.  This <Col N="1282" /> is in subparagraph (b) of subsection (3) of section 3.  If I understand this correctly, it would appear to me that Radio Telefís Éireann can make a copy of a film which has been made by somebody else and that then those copies could be made available without the consent of the person who made the original film.  This appears to be a blanket consent to Radio Telefís Éireann to make those films and to use them.  I should like to have some elucidation in regard to what this means and also what is its purpose.</P>
    <P>Section 6 strikes me as reading rather oddly.</P>
    <P>A consent to the broadcasting of a performance shall, unless the consent provides otherwise, be deemed to include consent to the rebroadcasting of the performance.</P>
    <P>The word &ldquo;rebroadcasting&rdquo; as defined in the definition section means the simultaneous broadcast by one broadcasting organisation of a broadcast of another broadcasting organisation. This could mean that television networks other than Radio Telefís Éireann could transmit those broadcasts.  They could be done through Eurovision or other networks outside Europe and they could be done without the consent of the performer.  I should explain straightaway that I am well aware that this is a practice with which Radio Telefís Éireann and, in fact, the unions are concerned.  Equity and the Federation of Musicians have an arrangement whereby for each extra broadcast a certain percentage of the fees would be given to the performer and in cases where the performers are not members of any particular union Radio Telefís Éireann pays similar increases. This being so, I cannot see the point of inserting in the Bill what amounts to almost a commission to Radio Telefís Éireann to violate all those arrangements which have been going on very satisfactorily for a number of years.</P>
    <P>I can see that Radio Telefís Éireann might be in a difficulty in regard to this.  They cannot always know before the contract has been signed that it is proposed by certain other countries to take the broadcast on Eurovision or <Col N="1283" /> through some other arrangement.  However, I should have thought that it would be a simple matter to put into every contract in small print somewhere a provision that in the event of any other network taking a broadcast a certain amount of fees should be paid and then anyone who signed this contract would have agreed to this being done.  There may be some reason I do not know about but on the face of it I cannot see the point at all of this section.  I should have thought the Bill would have been just as satisfactory and, indeed, more than satisfactory without this section.</P>
    <P>Another point on which I should like some elucidation is in regard to section 9, subsection (b).  This relates to defence in court proceedings.  Subparagraph (b) states:</P>
    <P>It shall be a defence to prove that the inclusion of the performance in the record, cinematograph film, broadcast or communication to the public to which the charge relates was only by way of background or was otherwise only incidental to the principle matters comprised or represented in the record, film, broadcast or communication to the public.</P>
    <P>I think the work &ldquo;principle&rdquo; in line 5 is misspelt.  It should be &ldquo;principal&rdquo;. I suspect that this goes rather further than is meant.  I can quite see that if someone was making a film and there was a crowd scene it would be ridiculous to say that you should pay everyone who happened to spend a fleeting moment on the screen and get permission from them to make the film. I have a feeling it could cover a case where music was used as background to a particular film without the permission of the performer.  I may be wrong but it seems to me that the section is worded more widely than is necessary.  On the face of it, it seems that it could lead to a wide variety of means by which background music is used, and should not be allowed in a Bill of this kind, without the permission of the performer.  The Bill is quite obviously a very considerable advance on the situation at the moment and I think we should all welcome it.</P>
    <Col N="1284" />
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>There is just one aspect of the Bill I am not too happy about.  The Bill makes it illegal, if I understand it correctly, to make a record directly or indirectly by means of a performance without permission in writing of the performers. It is quite common practice nowadays with tape recorders freely available to teenagers and others that they frequently make records for their own use privately and then play them back before they go out of fashion quite quickly.  This is a perfectly innocent thing.  I am not quite satisfied that the way to handle this is the way it is being done in the Bill.</P>
      <P>It seems quite wrong to me that this innocent practice should be dealt with by making it illegal and putting the onus that it was an innocent thing on the innocent party to prove it was made for purely domestic use.  I do not think we should put that into our legislation in this country.  Since that kind of recording is not done for any commercial purpose, I do not think it should be dealt with in this way by making it illegal and punishable either by criminal proceedings or civil proceedings. This is an innocent pastime which is carried on by those people. The onus is put on the people concerned to prove that it was innocent. We should direct our attention to the clause which is of so penal a character that it is quite inappropriate in legislation in a country like this.  We should try to reverse that and avoid getting ourselves into that position.  This is something which I will take up on Committee Stage.  I mentioned it here because it is a thing I am concerned about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am not quite clear about the significance of the Radio Telefís Éireann exemptions.  I do not fully understand the situation where performers have consented in writing to a recording but they have not consented in writing to this being recorded for the purpose of being broadcast.  This seems to be a rather unusual state of affairs.  It may be normal practice, but I would have thought that if Radio Telefís Éireann would have got the consent of performers to the broadcast of a performance which must be recorded before <Col N="1285" /> being broadcast they would not have objection to it being recorded.  I do not, perhaps, understand properly the process by which this is carried through or what is contemplated in the Bill, and I think that the Minister should explain a little further, as I presume that there may be good reasons but they are not immediately evident on first sight.  I appreciate that some broadcasts are live, but that is a different matter altogether.  If the suggestion is that people who consent to give a broadcast and then have it recorded are not being given an indication of when it is broadcast and then it is done without their consent, this seems a very dubious practice, but the Minister no doubt will clarify this matter and it can be taken up on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>In section 5 again I find it difficult to see what is contemplated here.  This contemplates the case where a person otherwise than by the use of a record, cinematograph film or broadcast, knowingly broadcasts or makes a communication to the public of a performance. If he does not do it by the use of a record, a cinematograph film or the reception of a broadcast how does he do it?  I am sure that there is a simple explanation but it does not strike me.  If this performance is being given, unless you record it or receive it on a broadcast and then retransmit it in some way, I do not see how you are knowingly making a communication of the performance.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>It must be live.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>But it says &ldquo;otherwise than by way of receiving a broadcast&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>He could be transmitting the recording live.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Would that not be by reception of a broadcast?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps Senator Yeats would leave it to the Minister to explain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I can understand and sympathise with Senator Yeats that it is irritating when you understand something that other people do not, but I would agree that, perhaps, <Col N="1286" /> what the Chair suggests is a more orderly way of doing it.  I would like some explanation of what is envisaged in this.  Perhaps, I have not thought the matter out.  Perhaps, the Minister would tell us.  I am also a little bit unhappy, though I do not want to stress this point, about section 9.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not like to have you unhappy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I should say I am slightly disturbed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>That is better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>In section 9 the use of the word &ldquo;background&rdquo; is unsatisfactory and it is used in a manner which is not defined.  Even accepting the misspelling of the word &ldquo;principle&rdquo;, which will be corrected, I presume, on Committee Stage, we need more definition of the phrase &ldquo;only incidental to the principal matters comprised or represented in the record, film, broadcast or communication to the public&rdquo;.  This is a point of pretty wide interpretation of what is incidental to a broadcast.  Is it adequately defined?  Should we try to deal with it more closely on Committee Stage?</P>
      <P>In the Minister's remarks he referred to the arrangements for payments to performers in respect of performances. I wonder if he would tell us something about how these arrangements are made?  Is the suggestion that the amount is left entirely to the performer or is it something over which he has no effective control?  If Radio Telefís Éireann broadcast a recording is the position that what they pay is a matter for the performer to decide or can they just decide what the payment can be?  I wonder if the Minister would explain this payment mechanism, because to those of us who are not familiar with it it is a bit of a puzzle to see how it works and if it is relevant to the general purpose of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is pretty obvious that virtually all the points which were raised on this Bill are really Committee Stage points and could be dealt with more adequately on Committee Stage.  I do not think that it <Col N="1287" /> would be either appropriate or possible for me to deal with most of these points at this stage.  Perhaps, I might say for the interest of the House, and the House may agree with this comment, that when the corresponding Bill was being introduced in the British House of Lords by Lord Mancroft he said, and I quote: &ldquo;This Bill is dull, technical, complicated and by general consent, largely incomprehensible.  It has, however, the compensatory merit of being both short and good.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>They did not have Senator Yeats, so it was incomprehensible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Those remarks could apply equally well to this Bill.  Most of the points raised are ones that could more appropriately be dealt with on Committee Stage, some of them because I would have to go into too much detail on some things, and others, quite frankly, because I would have to check on my brief myself to answer them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>That is very fair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>There was a point raised about the delay which occurred in introducing this Bill.  Senator Murphy, I think, it was who raised this. He will recall that the Bill had been introduced before but it lapsed on the dissolution of the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We hope that this does not presage another general election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>You never know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The first harbinger of spring?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>After that, further thought was given to the matter and very detailed and protracted negotiations took place both with Radio Telefís Éireann and with the representatives of the performers.  I think that it is pretty clear from even a casual perusal of the Bill that it is a very technical Bill and that the negotiations which were necessary to lead to the drafting of the Bill in conformity with the wishes of the parties concerned and <Col N="1288" /> at the same time in conformity with the Convention to which we wished to adhere were such as to delay the Bill for a very considerable time.</P>
      <P>The question of the amount of the fine which should be imposed in the event of a breach of the provisions of this Bill by Radio Telefís Éireann was raised by Senator McDonald.  All I can say is that the first offence to which he referred is a relatively minor one, and that is why the fine involved is £100, but the next subsection provides for more important and serious offences and there the figure is £2,000. I would agree with him that in the event of any serious offence a fine of £100 in the case of Radio Telefís Éireann would not be effective.  On the whole, the Bill does endeavour to strike the right balance considering that we are dealing with a State body which is likely to and should be presumed to want to conform to the provisions of the Act and which if it does not is liable to be very quickly exposed.  Having regard to that matter on the one hand, and on the other hand leaving it free to do what it likes in small cases, I think we have endeavoured to strike the right balance between those two in arriving at the penalties prescribed in the case of Radio Telefís Éireann.</P>
      <P>I should also say, perhaps, in regard to some of the remarks made by Senator Yeats, that a number of these provisions are not merely to deal with Radio Telefís Éireann, but also they are necessary notes to conform to the Convention and it is more a question of RTE having to conform to them than the Bill to have to conform to the requirements of RTE.</P>
      <P>At this stage I think I shall deal only with the general principles in the Bill, the necessity for it and the necessity for adhering to the Convention and I, therefore, propose to deal with the more detailed points which have been raised on Committee Stage.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 15th May, 1968.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Business suspended at 5.55 p.m. and resumed at 7.15 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Motor Vehicles (Registration" RHead="of Importers) Bill, 1967">
    <Title>Motor Vehicles (Registration of Importers) Bill, 1967.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1289" /> Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley) George Colley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill is to provide a statutory framework within which full effect can be given to agreed arrangements covering the assembly and importation of motor vehicles.  As was indicated in the public announcement in regard to these arrangements, made at the end of last November, their aim is to ensure the continuation of the motor vehicle assembly industry.</P>
      <P>The initiative in this matter was taken by the Government after the conclusion of the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Area Agreement when discussions were undertaken with British motor manufacturers and their Irish assemblers, with the co-operation of the British Authorities.  Although these negotiations were protracted and, in certain respects, complicated, the basis of the arrangements now agreed upon is relatively simple.  The manufacturers and assemblers of British vehicles have given me satisfactory assurances of their intention to support the continued assembly of their motor vehicles in Ireland on a long-term basis.  It is generally understood that what we have in mind is a period of not less than 25 years.  In return for these assurances, the Government agreed to implement immediately the duty reductions on fully built-up vehicles which would not otherwise fully mature until 1975 under the Free Trade Area Agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The assurances to maintain assembly are related to the level achieved immediately prior to the conclusion of the Free Trade Area Agreement when assembly operations were at a high level generally, and there is also an expression of intent to expand motor assembly operations, in so far as this may be consistent with the economics of the operations and the development of the market.  In connection with these assurances regard must, of course, be had to fluctuations in market demands which might affect the industry as a whole or the position of particular <Col N="1290" /> firms within the industry.</P>
    <P>Comparable concessions have been offered to assemblers of non-British vehicles, subject to satisfactory assurances being given by the manufacturers and assemblers of these vehicles and, as a result, these assemblers are also being enabled to participate in the arrangements.  The Government decided to implement the duty reductions provided for under the scheme as from the beginning of this year, on an interim basis by a system of licensing, under which the motor assembly firms have been given facilities to import fully built-up vehicles at the appropriate reduced rates of duty.</P>
    <P>Implementation of the arrangements in the longer term, however, requires the enactment of suitable legislation as provided for in the Bill.  The principal provision of the Bill is one for the channelling of imports of fully built-up motor vehicles through registered firms&mdash;principally the existing assemblers who have given me the assurances to which I have referred. This provision for approved channels of trade is necessary so that, as the duties on British vehicles are reduced under the Free Trade Area Agreement, the arrangements will not be undermined by the importation of vehicles by firms or persons who are not parties to the agreed arrangements.</P>
    <P>The Bill does not apply to agricultural tractors, large passenger buses and some other vehicles which were not subject to the former quota arrangements, but, apart from these, it embraces all the principal classes of motor vehicles.  It does not apply to vehicles of the motor cycle and scooter type.  It applies to second-hand vehicles because, otherwise, evasion of the scheme would be possible.  It is proposed to enable the definition of motor vehicle in section 1 to be amended by Ministerial regulations. This is considered to be desirable so that account may be taken of future technical developments and also to facilitate adjustment of the definition if the practical application of the measure should give rise to any difficulties or anomalies.</P>
    <P>All assembly firms which comply with the arrangements will be eligible <Col N="1291" /> for registration as importers of fully built-up motor vehicles of the makes and marques which they now handle. The only requirement for registration, in the case of assemblers of British vehicles, is the assurances they have given to maintain the level of their assembly operations.  All the firms concerned have already furnished me with the kind of information which I consider necessary to enable me, if the need arose, to form a judgment on whether a firm is complying with its assurances in this regard.  Registration will also be open to assemblers of non-British vehicles who give assurances to maintain, at least, their basic level of assembly.</P>
    <P>Subject only to a Free Trade Area duty preference for British-built private cars, it will be possible for these assemblers to do as well, in the aggregate, as assemblers of British vehicles. A firm may be removed from the register only where it is in breach of an assurance or undertaking given in connection with the arrangements or by agreement, where, for example, a firm merges with another or for some reason goes out of the business.</P>
    <P>The definition of motor vehicles does not extend to completely knocked down aggregates of parts for local assembly and there will, therefore, be nothing to prevent anyone from starting up in the motor assembly business. There is provision to enable such new entrants to qualify for registration as importers of fully built-up vehicles, subject to their achieving a satisfactory volume of assembly.</P>
    <P>While the principal purpose of the Bill is to provide for the channelling of imports through firms engaged in the assembly of motor vehicles, there is provision in the Bill to cover, in certain circumstances, the importation of fully built-up vehicles by firms which are not in the assembly business.  This provision will apply, for instance, to British cars of more than £1,300 in value c.i.f. which, in the past, were not subject to quota and are imported by certain firms who are not engaged in assembly.  These imports will be permitted to continue.</P>
    <P>Since the quota arrangements were <Col N="1292" /> abolished as from the 1st July, 1966, and up to the time the new scheme was announced towards the end of last year, a few firms, which are not in the assembly business, have been importing small numbers of vehicles in fully built-up condition.  It is the intention to enable them to continue importation on that scale.  The duty concessions provided for under the agreed arrangements will not, of course, apply to such imports since the concessions are available only to registered importers who are engaged in assembly.  The imporation of fully built-up vehicles on change of residence, by tourists and in a number of other special circumstances will be allowed to continue.</P>
    <P>There have, in the past, been some expressions of doubt as to the future prospects of the motor assembly industry.  This was understandable having regard to the views expressed in the report on the industry which was prepared under the auspices of the Committee on Industrial Organisation. The conclusion of these new arrangements alters the picture completely. The principal objective of the Government in seeking to have these arrangements concluded was to provide, as far as the Government could do so, an assured future for the industry and, in particular, for the workers in it.  That has been done.</P>
    <P>It has been suggested, in connection with the Bill, that one of its effects will be to restrict access to the trade, thereby adversely affecting the play of competition. In the first place, I would point out that the present freedom of access to the assembly industry is not being restricted in any way&mdash;any person or firm will be free to engage in the business of assembling motor vehicles from c.k.d. aggregates. Secondly, the point which has been made would only be valid if the existing situation in the industry indicated that there was a lack of adequate competition. I think anyone who considers the wide variety of makes and types of motor vehicle available on the Irish market and, in particular, anyone who has a knowledge of the trade, must admit that competition in the motor industry is just about as keen as it could be.  Since all existing firms <Col N="1293" /> engaged in the assembly or importation of new motor vehicles will be eligible for registration, it is clear that the Bill will not interfere with the present full and free play of competition.</P>
    <P>I mentioned in the Dáil and I think I should repeat here the appreciation not only of myself but also of my colleagues in the Government of the helpful co-operation which the manufacturers and assemblers displayed during the course of these negotiations. We are also appreciative of the assistance and co-operation afforded by the British Authorities.  In conducting the negotiations and in making the duty adjustments, the Government did all it could to ensure the success of the negotiations but success would not have been possible without the goodwill of the other parties involved.  These new arrangements have been welcomed by the industry and I am sure that the continued co-operation of management and the active support of the workers in the industry will ensure that the arrangements work out satisfactorily.  I should, however, like to stress that the future of the industry will continue to depend on the attitudes of those engaged in it, both management and workers.  The initiative taken by the Government in having the arrangements agreed and in promoting the legislation now before this House affords the industry an exceptional opportunity for the future.  Their own interest and the interest of the economy as a whole places on management and workers alike the obligation of ensuring that nothing is done to jeopardise the successful operation of these new arrangements for the long period ahead which is envisaged for their duration.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>While this Bill is an ingenious solution to the problem of preserving temporarily this particular industry in its present form and on its present scale, it is not a measure about which one can be too happy.  It runs quite contrary to the stated philosophy of the Government in regard to the adaptation of industry in this country to free trade conditions. It is based on the assumption either <Col N="1294" /> that we shall not join the EEC&mdash;and that is directly contrary to all Government statements and assumptions&mdash;or that when we join it we shall get a concession in this matter of a kind which is&mdash;I was going to say improbable but I regard that as a misleading word&mdash;one which it is almost certain that we cannot and will not get, a concession that runs so completely contrary to the philosophy of the EEC and to the way in which they have managed their affairs that there is, as far as I am aware, no grounds for believing that such a concession can be obtained. I shall go back to that again but on that basis this arrangement is one of a temporary character, a very temporary character except on the assumption that we are not going to join the EEC.  I have a feeling sometimes that the members of the Government say one thing and mean another on this particular issue and that while we are constantly being told that we shall be joining the EEC this is not believed to the point where practical Government policies are implemented on that assumption.</P>
      <P>This arrangement is one which will preserve quite effectively the industry in its present shape and on the scale on which it was operating in 1965 so long as we do not become a member of the EEC.  It involves an arrangement, one might say, in contravention of the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Agreement but one carried out with the agreement of the UK Government.  Of course, the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Agreement is one between two partners who are free to vary it any way they like and are not answerable to anybody. It is one, moreover, based on no philosophy as the EEC is but simply on considerations of practical mutual convenience and reciprocal advantage, indeed reciprocal advantage which I think has been greatly miscalculated on our part.  That, at any rate, is the basis of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There was, therefore, no problem in putting this proposal to the British Government and in securing their agreement.  All that was necessary was to convince them that certain short-term advantages from their point of <Col N="1295" /> view sufficiently outweighed any long-term losses involved.  There was no problem of persuading them to reverse philosophy of outlook or to change commitments that they have entered into with other countries.  It was a straightforward bilateral transaction. In one sense the Government are to be congratulated for having negotiated it successfully, if all that one is concerned with is the preservation of this industry in its present shape for a few more years, or if one assumes that we shall not at any stage in the next 25 years join the EEC.  I think that the Minister has done a disservice to the industry, to the workers in the industry and to the Irish economy not by making this arrangement, which is defensible up to a point, not so much that as by the terms in which it has been announced.  From the beginning a spurious picture of semi-permanency has been spread around, since the first leakage to all three national newspapers simultaneously, rather oddly, during the Cork by-election, through the speeches in the Dáil by the Minister right up to his introductory speech here today.  A figure of 25 years has been mentioned repeatedly as the period for which this will operate and the Minister in dealing with this in the Dáil, at column 153, No. 1, Volume 234 of the Official Report, spoke as follows:</P>
    <P>As I have said, it is not possible for me at this stage to say what the outcome of our negotiations in regard to entry into the EEC will be in so far as this concerns the motor assembly industry.  Obvously, I cannot give any concrete assurance in that regard, but, nevertheless, it would be unrealistic not to recognise the fact, as I pointed out, that this scheme, on a strict interpretation of the Free Trade Area Agreement, is contrary to it.  Nevertheless, the scheme has evolved and been agreed to as a result of negotiations.</P>
    <P>Secondly, as far as the Commission of EEC is concerned, it has demonstrated on a number of occasions in its operations that, while it is anxious to secure equal application of the rules of the Community <Col N="1296" /> within the Community, it has regard to special difficulties arising in the economy of any particular member and is prepared to make special arrangements where special difficulties arise.  While I cannot enter into any commitment in advance of such negotiations, I think I can say it would be unduly pessimistic to visualise that this arrangement could not carry on when we are within EEC.  There might possibly be some modifications of the scheme.</P>
    <P>I should like to ask the Minister what evidence he has in any case within the EEC at the moment on the basis of the extensive case law built up that an exception of this kind to the stringent provisions has been allowed in comparable conditions to the conditions we are concerned with here.  The case is less likely even than a normal case to be accepted because this industry is recognised as being one which in its present form is not viable.  It is the very kind of industry visualised as being a target for free trade, an industry which was set up not even because people wanted to manufacture cars and sought a tariff but because they were forced to do so by the Government telling them they would not be allowed to import cars unless they examined them here.</P>
    <P>This is artificial in its origin and in its economic character because in regard to most other industries here they have shown some concern.  We all know that many of those industries could not survive under Free Trade conditions.  This matter here is one which imposes substantial additional costs of a very arbitrary nature on the consumer as I will point out in a moment.  They are not following any reasonable pattern and under Free Trade conditions this industry would disappear.  I have no reason to believe that exceptions would be made in this case.  If the Minister has such reason which he may have received in any discussions he may have had with the Community, he should give that here. I have no example of this being done in comparable circumstances but if the Minister knows of such I should be glad to hear them.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1297" /> We are told here by the Minister that they have a period of 25 years in mind.  The Minister has not made any statement in the other House about any assurances he may have got.  If the Minister can give such assurance he should do so now and if he cannot, then he is failing in his duty in regard to the workers in this industry.  It is wrong that they should be deceived into believing they are safe for another 25 years.  It is wrong that they should be led into thinking that this can be postponed or that, in fact, a decision can be put off completely because of this spurious assurance that they can obtain semi-permanent employment in this uneconomic activity.</P>
    <P>The whole tenor of the Government's speeches and the Government's policy in other spheres has been to secure the adaptation of industry under free trade conditions and to secure that where existing operations in industries are not going to survive, alternative employment is provided and the industry itself is geared to another kind of activity which would be economic.  It seems that what has happened here is that the firm concerned are being allowed to proceed on exactly the same lines as they have done in the past.  As a result of the CIO report efforts should have been made to persuade those firms to undertake alternative manufacturing activities.  However, those people were not interested in this and were not interested in the livelihood of their workers.  They said: &ldquo;We are distributors and we are going on assembling as we have been doing. We are not going to get involved in some other activities.  When free trade comes along we will be prepared to take over some other activity.&rdquo;  The duty of the Government was to persuade those people to change their minds and take steps to introduce alternative activities, to phase out the industry and re-employ the workers in other kinds of activities for which they could be re-trained if necessary or could undertake without much retraining.</P>
    <P>The Government, instead of this, gave in to the pressure put on them by those people.  They took the easy way out, that is the safe way out, for <Col N="1298" /> the next few years.  The workers concerned may certainly be misled into thinking the Government have done them a good turn by preserving their present employment in its present form.  Workers are shortsighted in this respect The unions are also shortsighted. They are only concerned with immediate employment and are not so concerned with what happens ultimately.</P>
    <P>The assemblers have got the right to import any cars needed over and above the 1965 production.  They can bring in cars for shorter lines which are uneconomic to produce here.  The workers are satisfied because their employment has been preserved and they have been misled into thinking it will be preserved for 25 years, which if we join the EEC will not be the case.  The trade unions also are satisfied but I do not think that we in this House can be satisfied with this solution. It is dangerous to postpone this matter because it is by no means certain if we join the EEC it will be possible to establish some alternative employment for the 3,000 workers involved.  The very fact of creating alternative employment was so difficult that the Government found themselves unable to persuade the employers to change their minds.  Instead it has been put off until the last moment when the real state of those workers will be much worse.</P>
    <P>It is irresponsible to do this.  I would quite accept that the Government in introducing a Bill of this kind were doing so to ease transition.  If the Minister had told us that was so and that he was anxious to establish viable employment for those people, I would be satisfied.  If I was told that he was undertaking steps to ensure alternative employment was provided over the next few years and that if that was done this system would be phased out and that he was in a position to say at this stage by the time we join the EEC the employment of those workers would be safeguarded by being re-employed, I would be quite satisfied.  If the Minister had done so I would be prepared to congratulate him.</P>
    <P>Ever since the NIEC report there has been continual suspicion in the minds <Col N="1299" /> of the people concerned with this problem that it would be evaded like this. It has been the concern of all of us who have been concerned with this problem that this is what would happen. It is out of character with the rest of what the Government are trying to do.  Much good work has been done in the field of adaptation in the industrial sector.  We must regret that this record has been marred in this instance by adopting this procedure.  I want to make clear that it is not the actual arrangement I fault.  It is in fact that it is regarded by the Government as permanent and that it is stated by them to be so.  This is dishonest and misleading and it is something which this House and the Dáil will eventually hold the Minister and the Government responsible for when we join the EEC and face the problems which will be left to us by the legacy of this Bill and the Government's attitude to it.</P>
    <P>I do not think the workers concerned will readily forgive the Government for not having tackled this problem in the way in which it was recommended it should be tackled.  I said earlier that the old system of pricing in this industry is arbitrary.  I think if the Minister were serious about his price control mechanism, which is not very effective because it is a mechanism which is almost impracticable to operate under normal conditions; it is an emergency type of arrangement to meet an emergency type of situation and it cannot continue to work certainly under normal conditions, he would have used that mechanism to explore and investigate the price situation in this industry.</P>
    <P>The Minister is aware, or he should be, of an interesting study carried out by Doctor Nevin of the Economic Research Institute.  He may have carried it out privately and not under the Institute.  It concerns prices here and in Great Britain and the discrepancies between the different cases here which are of an order of magnitude which are not applicable to any known factor nor are those mentioned by the Minister in his speech.  He mentioned the case where cars had to be taken to pieces and where their price discrepancy was very great but not of <Col N="1300" /> the order of magnitude of price discrepancy shown in the particular article, which unfortunately, was not published.  It would have been an eye opener for people to see how in some cases they are getting extremely good value and how in some cases they are getting across here at a price which really is the British price plus the revenue duty charge here on assembled parts but in other cases are paying half as much again.  I myself did a very minor study of a similar kind in relation to French cars five years ago and what I discovered in relation to the three main makes at that time showed a very similar picture.  The Renault Dauphine showed the Irish price 20 per cent above the French price.  In the case of the other French makes the difference in price was 50 per cent and 80 per cent respectively.  This is not readily explained by any considerations which the Minister mentioned, and the whole question of this price relationship needs to be looked into. If we are going to give people this statutory monopoly and this right to make profits at the expense of the Irish people, then there should be a requirement that they should justify their prices.</P>
    <P>The Minister has shown genuine concern about prices in some instances and has even gone too far in his enthusiasm to tackle the problem.  He should show more concern here where he is conferring on firms in this industry a statutory monopoly and saying that we may not buy in this country a car from abroad and pay the duty on it, as we can do under the free trade arrangement for almost any commodity, and will be able to do without paying duty in the case of British goods in relation to other commodities in a few years time, but he says that we cannot do this, but must pay whatever price the Irish assembler wishes to charge us.</P>
    <P>I want to say&mdash;and this is an important qualification in making this point about different price levels&mdash;that some of these differences are not the fault of the Irish assembler.  There is evidence that in some instances they are charged for goods of different makes very different prices by the firm in France or Britain or wherever it may <Col N="1301" /> be.  The Minister has a duty to investigate and make sure that when that happens there is justification for these price differences.  Why should we be put into the position of being exploited by the British manufacturer in conjunction with the Irish assembler?  The Minister has a duty to investigate the charges made to the Irish assembler and the prices at which he is getting parts, which may be quite different from those at which they are sold to other countries.</P>
    <P>There are extraordinary variations in the prices at which CKD parts are sold by manufacturers to different countries.  There is an element of exploitation of us in this country by foreign manufacturers in addition to whatever exploitation there might be by Irish assemblers.  Where we are conferring a statutory monopoly at the expense of the Irish people the Minister has a duty, which he has not got in other cases where there is a free market system, to use the price control mechanism to investigate these differences and to publish the results of the investigation so that the Irish people may know whether they are being exploited by the British manufacturers or by the Irish assemblers.  We are having at the moment in a current case some insight into how the assemblers work and it does not give us reason for great confidence in the efficiency of the industry in all respects.</P>
    <P>The Minister has said that anybody can start up assembling without any difficulty and that this would not confer a monopoly on the existing assemblers.  I should like an assurance that where an English manufacturer is unhappy over the present arrangements and wishes to change them he can, in fact, do so, and that the Bill has not conferred a monopoly in respect of existing makes on existing assemblers as distinct from merely leaving it open for new makes to be assembled by new assemblers.  This is quite important.  Is the present position something which the British manufacturers are aware of, and is it the position that if at some stage they wish to change the assemblers because they are not satisfied with the efficiency of the work of the present <Col N="1302" /> assembler that this can be done and that a new assembler will get the same licence for the importation of assembled cars as the previous assembler had?  The Minister did not specifically mention this though it may be implied in what he said, and I would like a specific assurance on it.</P>
    <P>Those are the points which I wanted to make.  I should like to reiterate my concern at the lack of any real foresight and at this easy assumption that the problem can be solved with the EEC.  I have some knowledge of how it works, and while I cannot claim to know everything about it, everything I have seen in Brussels, everything I know about it, and everything I have read about the EEC suggests that this is a most unlikely concession for us to get.  We will get certain concessions in certain spheres regarding the industrial grants system and, perhaps, also in regard to export tax relief continuing to 1980 or 1983, or Shannon concessions, and concessions in regard to problems of dumping, which are very difficult ones.  But the concession required by this Bill is so much against the entire philosophy and practice of the Community that unless the Minister has specific assurances of some kind or evidence which I have not got of this being allowed, I think he has no right to suggest that it is pessimistic to think that this cannot be continued under the EEC, and no right to suggest to Irish workers that he is preserving their employment permanently by this Bill or doing anything to postpone the evil day when they must lose their employment, or to suggest that it can be preserved by postponing the time when this problem has to be tackled.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>As is not unusual in this House, when Senator FitzGerald has spoken on Bills of this kind he has thrown quite a great deal of light on them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>And heat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Generated, perhaps, necessary heat.  In my view it may be of some relevance to say that when I read this Bill I thought that it was a very curious measure.  It is extraordinarily difficult at times for Members <Col N="1303" /> of the Oireachtas to follow Bills of this kind, when what happens in the case of many Departments does not happen in the case of most Bills produced by the Department of Industry and Commerce.  That Department never affords to the Houses of the Oireachtas the courtesy&mdash;or seldom does so&mdash;of an explanatory memorandum. It is a great pity that they do not.</P>
      <P>At any rate, it became fairly clear from reading the Bill that it was designed or constructed so as to hide the purpose for which it was intended.  It is an extraordinary business, but, of course this is the kind of procedure that we are adapting that we should be getting rid of, that in order to effect what the Minister wants to do, that is, to enable motor assemblers in this country to continue in the business and to get certain concessions that they would not be entitled to, the Minister has to give a direction to the Revenue Commissioners to compile a register, as if the register could not be compiled in his own Department, and then the Minister will give a direction to amend the register and this has to be given to the Revenue Commissioners, and the Minister can give a direction to cancel a registration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have all this kind of outmoded procedure, and I do not know why the register cannot be kept in the Department of Industry and Commerce or by the motor assemblers.  If the Revenue Commissioners for customs purposes want to find out who is entitled to import these under the concessions provided, why could they not be sent a duplicate of every registration by the Department of Industry and Commerce? It would never do to do that kind of thing.  However, this is the Civil Service procedure, and until we have some kind of Government that is prepared to put a bit of new life into the Civil Service we will be saddled with this kind of rigmarole on Bills of this kind.  It is a pity that we do not have something in the nature of a political retreat from time to time like religious retreats and do a bit of contemplation about our political lives.  If the public were to take <Col N="1304" /> stock of this present Government now in 1968 and compare all the things that were promised them in 1965, with the performance, there would certainly be a very long confession to so-called clerics.  It would be a long confession and it would be mainly sins of omission, and some sins of commission too, I have no doubt.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Like the various Acts we brought in that we did not even promise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>There will be a great long confession of sins of omission and commission.  I recollect the former Taoiseach, Deputy Lemass, going around the country in 1965 promising the people of Ireland the youngest government in Europe and all that was implied in that.  Put against that their miserable, lame performance in this Bill.  I think that the Government owe an apology to the people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator expressed himself differently on other occasions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator care to read out the policy of the first Coalition Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Their record in agriculture, housing and industry has not been reached.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Go out to the Spring Show now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>There never was such a shortage of credit in the days of the inter-Party Government as there was in 1967.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to know what this has to do with the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am talking about the youngest Government in Europe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>What has that to do with the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Leader of the House will restrain himself and bear with me, I will explain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I find it hard to do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I understood that the youngest government in Europe <Col N="1305" /> were to introduce dynamic policies to prepare us for free trade.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>A school bus on every road for our children for a start off.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>A Fine Gael policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>It is long since that was done.  What do we now find?  We find a situation in which no attempt whatever is made to prepare the motor assembly industry for this free trade.  There is no preparation as far as I can see for the re-employment of the redundant employees in the motor assembly industry but they are being told by the Minister that if the Bill is passed their future is assured for apparently 35 years.  That is not to my mind the preparing of this country for free trade and I do not think the Minister will suggest that the Bill is in any sense a preparation of this country or the motor assembly industry for free trade.  It is merely a stop-gap, a temporary measure designed to prevent workers in the motor assembly industry from being disemployed in consequence of the full application of the Free Trade Area Agreement between Great Britain and this country. This is the way we will go on.  I saw what happened when we had competition in relation to the importation of motor tyres.  There was a great squawk.  New arrangements were made but the old system prevailed.  When I tried to get four radial three-ply tyres from Dunlops last year, I could not buy them in the city of Dublin.  They were not to be had and they would not have them for a month and that was for an ordinary make of car.  If we are to have a monopoly and to continue a monopoly in the motor assembly industry in this country we ought to do two things.  One, as Senator FitzGerald said, should be to investigate the prices of cars and see whether prices ought not be lower than they are. I think everybody will accept that the margin of profit on motor cars is quite scandalous and that this huge profit can be made at the expense of the unwary who do not have the capacity to bargain and do not know anything about trade and so on.  This should not be permitted.  It is a matter which <Col N="1306" /> the Minister for Industry and Commerce should investigate.</P>
      <P>There is an equally important matter which should be provided for in the Bill.  If we are going to make the Irish purchaser of imported motor cars pay higher than he ought to, we should insist on a proper standard of production and assembly from the motor manufacturers in this country.  I have no doubt that some people opposite will say that I am decrying the Irish manufacturers and you are trying to stab Irish industry in the back.  We all know that the standard of assembly of motor cars in this country falls very short of what it ought to be and the same applies to the assembly of motor cars in Britain.  Our Irish workers are no worse than English workers but a great deal better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad the Senator made that point because it is true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>It is true.  I want to make the point that the standard of assembly could be a great deal higher. In that context, why, when he was making his bargain with the motor assemblers did the Minister not insist on some body being set up to lay down a standard and investigate low standards in high priced and medium priced cars?  Every day somebody buys a new car, signs away his rights in a fraudulent document presented to him by the garage man and he gets no satisfaction from the garage man and the motor assemblers.</P>
      <P>The public should be alerted and it should be the duty of the Minister for Industry and Commerce to alert the public to the fraudulent document handed to the purchasers of motor cars which is headed &ldquo;Guarantee&rdquo;.  If they sign when they read the guarantee they think they will be entitled to free service for the first 2,000 miles or six months, whichever is the shorter.  In fact, what people are doing is signing away the implied warranties of maintenance and quality and to which there is no six months' bar.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I had the experience of buying a new car and in six to 12 months three sets of shock absorbers had to be fitted.  I was told that they were a bad set of <Col N="1307" /> shock absorbers.  I was not signing away any rights I had but this is the kind of thing the Department of Industry and Commerce should alert the public to. If they did we would have a higher standard of performance by the motor assemblers.  In any event, if we are to grant a monopoly to anybody, be they manufacturers of motor cars or anything else, the Department of Industry and Commerce has a duty to see that a corresponding standard of performance is maintained by those people who are given the monopoly.  It is most unfair that the public should be constantly called on to swell the profits of Irish manufacturers and receive no help whatever from the appropriate or relevant Department of State.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator explain what he means by a monopoly in this context?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>You must buy your car here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The only car you can buy in this country is one that is manufactured here.  Otherwise you will have to pay a very high duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>You can buy other goods from outside if you are prepared to pay the duty on them but you cannot do that in the case of cars.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what I mean when I use the word &ldquo;monopoly&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>But there is competition between the motor car assemblers, the same as there is in other lines of goods.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>There is great competition between the petrol companies, but at the same time they all charge the consumer the same price.  There is great advertising at the moment about the tiger and there is great competition amongst them, but still we all have to pay the same price for petrol.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>Some petrols are cheaper. You do not go to the right garages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>There is this kind of show competition between the petrol companies but they all charge the same price.  There is also that show competition between the motor car <Col N="1308" /> assemblers but they, too, also charge the same price and we have to put up with the same inefficiency.  This is where the Minister should protect the public and he should invite the public, where they have grounds for complaint, to report to his Department instances where they cannot get satisfaction from the assemblers.  In the long run such a procedure would be good for the workers and the manufacturers.  It would be good for them to know that a high standard was being set for them and that they would have to live up to it.</P>
      <P>The details of the Bill are very curious because I notice that the Minister is empowered to give a direction to the Revenue Commissioners to open a register and to put somebody on it. After that solemn direction has been duly complied with, the person on the register can then import motor vehicles in their knocked down condition.  I would like to know from the Minister will that register be open to public inspection or will it be a private, secret, Revenue document which only the elect can see?  The Minister says that he has got an assurance which he considers satisfactory, and in section 4 of the Bill we have the provision that where the Minister is of the opinion that the registered person has not complied with this assurance, he can then direct the Revenue Commissioners to cancel the registration of the person concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I object most vehemently to this kind of situation which arises when a Minister is empowered to give licences.  It will be clear from what I have been saying that I hold no brief for the motor assemblers but I always object to the idea of a Minister&mdash;I do not say this particular Minister&mdash;having the power to put pressure on a manufacturer, and the Minister can put pressure under this section because he can decide whether the manufacturer shall stay in the business or not.  If the registration of a motor vehicle importer is to be cancelled, it should be done by somebody other than the Minister.  It can lead to abuse if a Minister is in a position to put pressure on an industrialist and the industrialist always knows and feels that <Col N="1309" /> he must stay in the good books of the Minister.  That is an undesirable and unhealthy state of affairs.</P>
    <P>If a registration is to be cancelled, it should be cancelled on the complaint of the Minister but by somebody independent and outside of the Minister.  There does not have to be anything in the nature of a public inquiry or investigation but somebody quite independent of the Minister should be the person to decide whether an importer is to remain on the register. It would be in ease of the Minister in this and in similar Bills if he did not have to do the actual direction of cancelling somebody's registration, but, if it were found after official investigation that matters were not as they should be and that the assurances given were not complied with, the Minister would pass to somebody else the determination as to whether or not the assurance which had been given had been complied with.  I would urge the Minister to consider his own position in that regard under the Bill and whether he ought not to establish some other person, even in the half-hearted way in which that was done in the Livestock Marts Bill, of unhappy memory, of 1967.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>As regards section 2 and section 6, are we to take it that an individual will be free to import for his own use a car that is not assembled here?  Would a motor enthusiast, even if not registered, be free to approach the Minister to bring in a specific type of vehicle for his own use and not necessarily for sale?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A matter that has been interesting me for some time is the extremely high price the Irish public are charged for spare parts.  Perhaps the Minister might apply his mind to this and see if anything could be done to reduce this extremely high cost to the Irish motorist.  I read somewhere recently that the average life of a car in this country is seven years as compared with five years in Britain.  One of the reasons for this difference is that rural people who buy secondhand cars cannot afford to pay the extremely high rate of tax on the high-powered cars and therefore the bigger cars arrive on the scrapheap much earlier than the smaller ones.  It would be in the interests <Col N="1310" /> of the national economy if the Minister gave some consideration to giving taxation concessions to cars which reach an average life of seven years and over, provided they are otherwise mechanically sound.</P>
    <P>I was interested recently in the big trade in the importation of buses for the school free-transport scheme. Many buses are being imported and I do not think such imports come under the Bill.  What will be the position in the future in relation to this type of vehicle?  Will it be as bad as it is at the moment or will there be an arrangement whereby people can import these vehicles on a percentage scale of duty?  There is need to look into the existing situation. CIE manufacture their own vehicles and run them until there is little life left in them, but people in private business must import them either from Northern Ireland or Britain and are charged high rates. This seems to be unjust when one considers the important service they are giving to the public.  When the Bill is passed, will the position in this respect change or has the Minister in mind the introduction of a Bill which will deal with the categories not included in this measure?  There are a few other points which are more appropriate to Committee Stage and I shall leave them until then.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to make just two points.  I do not really understand how this Bill is intended to work out.  The Minister has told us generally that the Bill will be for the benefit of workers in the motor assembly trade and he said that the principal objective of the Government in seeking to have these arrangements concluded is to provide an assured future for the industry, and in particular for the workers in it.  That has been done the Minister said, but I am not quite sure how.  One of the basic requirements, as I understand it, for registration of these assemblers who are now to be allowed to import fully made-up cars&mdash;one of the guarantees they have to give&mdash;is that they will maintain the level of their assembly operations, which means.  I take <Col N="1311" /> it, that they will assemble as many cars as they used to do.</P>
      <P>As well, they will have the right to import more cars, fully built-up.  As well as that, some firms that are not assemblers will be allowed to import fully made-up cars.  My question is where is the market to come from?  I had been prepared to assume that there will be an ever-increasing market, or at any rate that the market will increase a bit more, but how will it absorb not only the present level of assembled cars but also the additional level of cars imported by these same assemblers, fully made-up, plus fully made-up cars imported by distributors who are not assemblers?  I fear that the very large number of cars which will be on the market in the circumstances will not be taken up by the public, with the result, as I see it, that in fact if the Minister thinks these assemblers will really be able to maintain the level of their assembly operations, he is deceiving himself.  I do not think they will be.</P>
      <P>Furthermore, why is it the Minister thinks apparently that the same number of workers will be required by an assembly firm which will in fact, I think, be assembling fewer cars&mdash;how does he think the distribution of already fully made-up imported cars will absorb the same labour force by those no longer assembling them?  In other words, it would seem that this is a well-intentioned Bill but one which in practice will not achieve the aims that the Minister has in mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>We had better face the facts presented by this Bill.  What we have here is a device to try to meet one of the bad effects of the Free Trade Area Agreement with Britain.  What we are doing here is entering into an arrangement with motor assemblers which will allow them to bring in fully-assembled vehicles at a lower rate of duty than would otherwise be the case, providing they maintain the existing level of assembly within the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill is welcome in so far as it goes but it seems to me to be a rather negative approach to the problem. What we are doing is trying to provide a device which will maintain the existing level of employment in an <Col N="1312" /> industry which should in fact be expanding, because I think we all accept that more and more cars will go on the roads and if we did not have this Free Trade Agreement, we would have the situation that more and more people would be finding employment in the motor assembly industry in this country.</P>
    <P>Instead, we are putting a maximum to that: we are saying that employment in the motor assembly industry will not increase as it would have done if the Agreement had not been signed by the Government.  In so far as it goes, the measure is welcome but I think we should realise that it is a rather negative device, because even though the Minister said that the period is generally understood to be not less than 25 years, if I live that long I shall be very surprised to find that this arrangement will have continued 25 years and that the motor assemblers or their successors have stood by this arrangement and that the number of people now employed in motor assembly will still be in employment in it 25 years from now. Frankly, I do not believe it.</P>
    <P>I do not know what the answer is because, as I have said, it is one of the ill effects flowing from the Agreement with Britain.  We in the Labour Party opposed that Agreement.  We warned that it would lead to unemployment. Now we are to have for this industry a rather complicated arrangement entered into which puts a ceiling effect on employment in an industry which otherwise would be expanding and providing more employment for our people at home.</P>
    <P>These remarks may appear to be critical.  In spite of that, I would like to congratulate the Minister on getting this arrangement.  I suppose it was the best he could do in the circumstances in which he is placed but I hope he will keep a very wary eye on the position and will see to it that no other arrangements are entered into which would in future years take from the value of the agreement he has made, because of course the agreement as it stands at the moment is to the benefit of the motor assemblers.  They are getting a concession which they would not <Col N="1313" /> otherwise get until seven or eight years from now.  They are getting an advantage and I hope the Minister will see to it that, having got that immediate advantage, they will stand by their part of the bargain and we will see no closures of motor assembly firms here with thousands of workers thrown out of employment maybe in two or three years time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Protection is the main theme of the Minister's statement.  That protection is no doubt a result of the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Agreement.  We remember that when that Agreement was announced, it was pointed out that the first industry to bear the brunt of it would be the motor industry and that the motor industry could just get ready to go out of business.  We now have this Bill brought in to provide protection for that industry.  There is nothing in the Minister's statement to show that the Minister is just as anxious to ensure that Irish motorists will be protected so far as the standard of assembly and the prices charged are concerned.  Most of us are shocked when we read a catalogue of prices of British assembled cars which are also assembled here and compare the prices in England with those here.  The Irish motor assemblers say the reason is that they are compelled to use parts which are manufactured in Ireland and that if they were not compelled to do this, they would be in a position to offer the cars at a price comparable with the price in Britain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the basis of the retail price of certain British assembled cars and the price of similar cars assembled here and the difference in the price, let us examine the argument the Irish assemblers put forward concerning the inclusion of Irish manufactured parts in the assembly of these cars.  When we see the difference, let us then tot up the difference between the cost of similar parts in the British cars and the parts put in in Ireland.  We find that there is still a difference that needs to be explained.  It must be remembered also that in England there is a purchase tax which there does not operate here.  That is a very big part of the retail price of a car in England and still the price of an Irish assembled car is <Col N="1314" /> higher.  Let us have an explanation of that difference.</P>
    <P>It may be argued, for instance, that we have no steel industries here to provide the necessary steel for the manufacture and assembly of cars and that we have not other necessary basic raw materials.  If we take the wholesale prices of those parts which are obtainable in Britain and originated there, we should only add to that the cost of transport because when we compare the rates of pay&mdash;I depend on Senator Murphy and the other trade union members to keep me right on this&mdash;I believe that those engaged in the motor assembly business in England are paid higher wages than those engaged in it here.  If that is so, the difference in the labour costs of assembling a car here, taking it that an Irish worker can give the same output per hour, per day or per week as an English worker, we see that transport should be the only difference between the retail price of a car in this country and the price in Britain.</P>
    <P>For that reason we should ask the Minister also if he has discussed with these motor assemblers whether they have ever considered the possibility of going into the export business. There are industries in this country importing raw materials, processing them and doing very well in the export market.  Is the motor trade in a position in which they are unable to import the parts, assemble the cars here and compete in the export market? Other industries are doing it.  Is there any hope at all that the motor industry will be in a position to go into the export business, because if not, it is obvious that the industry itself must go down unless Irish motorists are compelled to pay exorbitant prices for Irish assembled cars compared with similar makes assembled in Britain.</P>
    <P>That is a point which I feel should have been mentioned in the Minister's speech, the possibility of getting motor assemblers to realise that with the small population of Ireland and the number they hope to keep engaged in that industry, particularly having regard to modern techniques and working methods which are offset to some extent of course by a shorter working <Col N="1315" /> week, they would need to go into the export business.  When I mention a shorter working week, I know that in fact this point was brought up after the Free Trade Agreement.  It was pointed out that the way to keep the Irish assembly workers in the business was to reduce the working week, that that might have the effect because of course the output would be lower.  It is obvious that in our present set-up it should be possible for our Irish motor assemblers to produce more cars than the Irish people are capable of using.  The only prospect then for those assemblers to keep in business at a competitive price is to go into the export market.  There is no mention of that and apparently there seems to be no prospect of it.</P>
    <P>I would like to have the Minister's views on this because I feel that just providing protection is only subsidising or throwing a sop to the industry to keep them going.  I believe it is not a practicable proposition.  I believe that there will be big changes in the next 25 years and that the provision of a protection period of not less than 25 years will hardly have any effect even in ten years' time.  We must move with the times and with the changes in methods.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley) George Colley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware of any industry, in this country or anywhere else, whether motor vehicles or otherwise, which is purely assembling, which would compete on an export market.  An industry which is manufacturing and is not perhaps importing raw materials in my opinion has not a hope of competing on any export market.  Therefore, the suggestion made by Senator Rooney that the future of this industry depends on its ability to export is in my opinion not well founded.  There are, as distinct from that, some firms in this country which are manufacturing parts of cars. Indeed, some are exporting at the moment and others are developing export markets.  That, of course, will carry on under free trade conditions. Some of them I know are going to expand.  This is quite separate from the problem we are dealing with here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1316" /> Before I get to the basic points involved in the debate there are a few relevant small points I might get out of the way.  There was a reference to school buses.  The position is that buses carrying more than 16 people, inclusive of the driver, are not covered by this Bill which means that the regulations, which have applied heretofore, will continue to apply to those larger buses. The position will be as it has been up to now.</P>
    <P>Senator Sheehy Skeffington could not see how this scheme could work, having regard to I think he said the level of assembly, plus the import of fully built-up vehicles, plus the import of fully built-up vehicles by non-assemblers. I think he is looking at this from the wrong end.  The basic thing is the maintenance of the existing level of assembly.  An assembler who was importing so many cars that his level of assembly dropped would put himself in jeopardy in that he might be removed from the register provided for in the Bill, which would put him out of business altogether as regards imports of fully built-up vehicles.</P>
    <P>The pressure on him, in any event, will be to maintain his level of assembly.  The importation of fully-built-up vehicles can only arise over and above that in connection with the growth in the market.  If there should be any drop what has to drop first is the importation of fully built-up vehicles.  The basic thing is the maintenance of assembly.</P>
    <P>At the moment the market is quite buoyant.  As far as I know, most of the assemblers are working at full stretch with maximum overtime.  They are allowed to import fully built-up vehicles but even working at that pitch imports are working at about five per cent. Most imports of fully built-up vehicles by the non-assemblers, as I said on the Bill, would be quite small in relation to the market and would not affect the issue at all.  The important fact in this connection is the ratio between the cars assembled and the cars fully built-up by assemblers.  Their position is that they must maintain assembly.  If there is to be any cutting down in the number of cars operated by them it must be in the importation of fully assembled cars.</P>
    <Col N="1317" />
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the non-assemblers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a very small number involved here.  It is a continuation of something which existed in the past.  The numbers involved are very small.  There has always been a practice whereby tourists, to whom I referred, and people changing residence and that kind of case, may import fully built-up cars without paying the duty. Somebody made some reference to this importation by individuals.  The position will continue as before.  Each case is individually examined and decided on its merits.</P>
      <P>Somebody made the criticism that no explanatory memorandum was issued with this Bill.  All I can say in that regard is that there has been a very full public announcement explaining the details of the scheme and I do not think the issue of an explanatory memorandum would have been very much more effective in explaining what was involved here.</P>
      <P>Quite a lot was said about the price at which Irish assembled cars are sold as compared with British cars.  Senator Rooney spoke at some length about this.  I do not think he referred to the two major items which should be considered in any examination of this.  The first one is that the completely CKD aggregates coming into this duty are subject to revenue duty which up to last year was 20 per cent and is now 17½ per cent.  In addition, the cost to the assemblers of the CKD parts is a very important point as compared with the cost of those parts to the British manufacturer. There is a very substantial difference.  Those are two major points which must be taken into account. Reference was made to assemblers being obliged to use certain parts made here.  Frankly, I did not hear that explanation before although I could believe it was made.  I believe it is a very small point.  If it adds to the cost, I believe the amount involved is very small.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the usual excuse.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>The amount involved is very small.  Senator FitzGerald in referring to the cost of the CKD referred to the fact that they are sold at different <Col N="1318" /> prices in different countries.  This is true.  Apart from freight cost also relevant is the state of the knocked-down car when it comes. This affects very much the cost both to the manufacturer and the price he is going to charge.  Apparently it makes quite a difference to him and it does not follow if we will be able to supply 50 per cent of the knocked-down that this should be 50 per cent of the cost of a completely built-up one.  This does not follow at all.  In fact, it would be very much dearer. It would be 80 per cent because of the increased cost to the manufacturer in its disruption of the assembly line.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is far from the knocked-down price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>What comes in here?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not completely knocked-down.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Sometimes it is cheaper for the manufacturer to do it that way rather than knock it down.  The degree to which this is done differs.  It differs in different countries depending on the assembly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Murphy suggested that if we had not negotiated the Free Trade Area Agreement there would be more employment in this country.  This is a possibility, but there is one thing about which we can be certain&mdash;if we had not concluded that Agreement a great number of people in other industries would be out of employment. The growth of our industries, particularly our export industries, and the increases in employment in them in many cases is directly due and in other cases indirectly due to the opperation of the Free Trade Area Agreement.  The whole movement involved in getting into free trade, and which was unavoidable to us as we looked around the world, and was incorporated in this Free Trade Area Agreement, and our industries have been cushioned to a great extent against immediate free trade conditions in entering into that Agreement, in accepting that free trade was inevitable and that the best thing to do was to control the onset of it rather than to let it happen by chance, which was the basic thinking behind it.  It was <Col N="1319" /> generally recognised that we would have to pay a certain price, and one of the items in the price we were expected to have to pay was the disappearance of the motor assembly industry and of the jobs of many thousands of workers engaged in it, but in fact we have succeeded in concluding the Agreement and getting the benefits of it and in retaining the assembly industry and the jobs involved.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Temporarily.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am coming to that, but I am dealing now with the contention made by Senator Murphy that if we had not made the Agreement, we would be better off.  This is not true.  We would be far worse off; there would be no hope for the industry in the long-term or the short-term, and many more workers would be out of employment.</P>
      <P>Now on the question of the length of this scheme and the implications for us of membership of the EEC, I think that Senator FitzGerald must accept that it is not in our national interest to start putting objections into the mouths of the people who will negotiate on behalf of the EEC with us, and that it is not reasonable to expect me to state our position on this in detail, that is, the position which we would take up in the negotiations.  As I have said, on other occasions in connection with this matter, one cannot of course be absolutely certain what the results of this will be because it will depend upon the negotiations and one cannot spell out in detail beforehand one's stand in such negotiations, but I think it is not unreasonable that we should have regard to the general philosophy of the EEC&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;as it is operated in practice, and there are two items in this regard which I think are very important.  One is the point I have mentioned in the Dáil and which I think Senator FitzGerald quoted, and that is, that the EEC, particularly the EEC Commission, is very anxious to ensure that membership does not result in <Col N="1320" /> serious injury to the economy of one of its members, and it has on occasions gone to considerable length to avoid that kind of injury.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Giving 18 months maximum period to the French refrigerator industry, for example.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a different situation from what we are talking about, as I think the Senator appreciates. I would ask Senator FitzGerald if he is aware of the situation arising within the EEC at present and that has been there since the beginning despite the general philosophy behind it &mdash;is he aware of the position that obtains in regard to capital goods industries, particularly those with advanced technologies?  Does he think that there is free trade in those goods? Does he not know that there is no such thing operating, and that all the member Governments who have such industries give particular preferences to their own industries, and for very good reasons that it is accepted that the Commission knows that this is so, and deplores it in theory because it is contrary to the philosophy of the EEC but accepts that it must happen in practice?</P>
      <P>As I say, I do not want to go into too much detail about the position we would intend to take on this, but it is important that we should realise that the EEC, whatever its basic philosophy may be, is a human institution and does not adhere in practice to all its tenets and probably never will.  I do not suppose that any human institution ever will.  To the extent that it does not, it is necessary for us to avail of such opportunities in our negotiations with the EEC, and it is my belief&mdash;as I have said one cannot of course speak with certainty in this matter&mdash;from my knowledge of the situation that it should be possible for us in our negotiations with the EEC to retain fundamentally the structure of this scheme and whatever changes there might be&mdash;some, I would hope, fairly minor&mdash;in the way of concessions to EEC countries in it, the major portions of the scheme I believe could be and can be retained.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Again I would make the point I <Col N="1321" /> made in Dáil Éireann that this agreement on the face of it is completely contrary to the Free Trade Area Agreement and yet we have concluded such an agreement.  It is also true that it would be contrary to the principles of the EEC, but because it is so does not mean that we cannot carry it into our negotiations and carry it in substantially the same form as it will be now with us into the EEC.  I think it unfortunate from two points of view if we should give any other impression &mdash;one from the point of view of our negotiations, whenever they may come, and the other from the point of view of the people involved in the industry.</P>
    <P>There is some misconception, judging from a number of statements I have heard from Senators, about this, and apparently the general belief is that this scheme may have been brought in for the benefit of the assemblers.  The position to my knowledge is that certainly the majority of the assemblers, if not all of them, would make more money if we did not have this scheme, if the assembly industry disappeared and if they were depending solely on importing fully built-up vehicles.  That being so, I think it is unfair to suggest that they went along with this scheme in their own interests, or to say, as one Senator said, that they had no interest except their profits, that they were not interested in anything else such as maintaining employment, because, remember, whatever pressure the Government might wish to bring to bear in a situation like this, without the full cooperation of all the parties concerned it could not have been done.  The fact that it was done indicates that that full co-operation was forthcoming, and as far as I know, I believe that the majority of the assemblers at least stood to make more money by not agreeing to this scheme.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Quigley seemed to be, as was suggested, wandering somewhat from the terms of the Bill, but at some stage he was talking about the youngest Cabinet in Europe and about this Bill being an example of the miserable performance of this Government. All I can say about that is that I am very glad that this matter <Col N="1322" /> was not left in the hands of a Fine Gael Government, because we can see from what was said here this evening what would have happened.  Thousands of workers would have been thrown out of their jobs because it was believed that we could not do anything of this kind and negotiate with the EEC or because it was contrary to the Free Trade Area Agreement.  This Government succeeded in concluding the agreement and in avoiding the major difficulty which was arising out of the Free Trade Area Agreement, this Government that Senator O'Quigley has such searbhas on.  All I can say is I am glad it was not a Government of his Party who were handling this situation for the workers in that industry.  What would happen to them?  I hope they realise the attitude of the Fine Gael Party in this matter, that they have indicated they disapprove of this whole approach.  I do not wish to misrepresent what was said. I could very easily do so but it is not misrepresenting the attitude of the Fine Gael Party as disclosed here tonight to say that they are opposed to this approach to the situation that arises for the motor assemblers.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>As a temporary measure; you are getting temporary employment.  I said that specifically.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Anybody can make an airy-fairy statement about alternative employment.  I am talking about the problems in real life, about people working in an assembly industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>You are talking about seeking alternative employment for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Since Senator O'Quigley chose to speak as he did, I think I am entitled to draw the attitude of the Fine Gael Party to the attention of all those whose livelihoods depend on this industry.  I will do what little I can to draw their attention to that attitude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Misrepresent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I could easily misrepresent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1323" />
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is doing so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Read the speeches you made on the Free Trade Area Agreement in this House.  Go back to the debates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>One of the points made by Senator O'Quigley was that this Bill provided for the keeping of a register by the Revenue Commissioners and he apparently regarded this as another example of the tired kind of government being produced by Fianna Fáil. It is all right to say that at a crossroads down in Limerick but we could do better than that in this House.  The fact of the matter is that the practical operation of this Bill, in so far as built-up vehicles are concerned, is at the ports where the customs men are operating.  The most effective and efficient thing is to have it operated through the Revenue Commissioners and the customs men who are on the spot and not have it referred to the Department of Industry and Commerce all the time.</P>
      <P>This is the kind of thing Senator O'Quigley would say at a crossroad down in Limerick.  I do not know if he was there recently but maybe he is getting into form for next weekend. In so far as I had any part in this, though I do not claim to be the originator of the scheme, we have every right to be proud of what we have achieved and we are proud of it.  We have set out to get the benefits of the Free Trade Area Agreement and at the same time to avoid one of the major difficulties arising out of it.  We have succeeded in doing that and in doing so we have secured jobs for thousands of these workers, and we have, I believe, secured them&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Temporarily.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;in the long term. I do not think that Senator Garret FitzGerald is doing any good for the assembly industry, for the workers in it or indeed for our position in negotiating with the EEC by the attitude he is taking.  He is quite entitled to question <Col N="1324" /> this, as to whether it will be long term or not, but I do not think he is entitled to put forward arguments which take from the negotiations on the EEC and which undermine confidence in this industry.  There is no justification for that.  So far as one can judge matters of this nature, the jobs of the people in the motor assembly industry in this country are assured for a generation to come.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 15th May, 1968.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Merchant Shipping (Load Lines)" RHead="Bill, 1968: Second Stage">
    <Title>Merchant Shipping (Load Lines) Bill, 1968: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Minister for Transport and Power (Mr. Childers) Erskine Hamilton Childers">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Transport and Power (Mr. Childers)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill is to enable Ireland to give effect to the International Convention on Load Lines, 1966.  This Convention, which supersedes the existing Load Line Convention of 1930, was adopted at an International Conference of Maritime States, including Ireland, which met in London in March-April, 1966 under the auspices of the Inter-Governmental Maritime Consultative Organisation (more commonly known, from its initials, as IMCO).</P>
      <P>IMCO is a specialised agency of the United Nations concerned with shipping and maritime affairs.  It gives particular attention to the promotion of safety of life at sea, the development of the highest standards of navigation, and the exchange of information between nations on technical maritime questions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senators may recall that in 1966 they passed the Merchant Shipping Act, 1966 which was designed to permit of the ratification of the International Convention for the Safety of Life at Sea, 1960.  That Convention, like the Load Line Convention, deals with safety at sea, but is concerned more with such aspects as life-saving and fire-fighting appliances on board ship, radio equipment, the carriage of dangerous goods, and the traffic rules of the sea, whereas the Load Line <Col N="1325" /> Convention is concerned with the prevention of overloading and with ensuring the weather-tightness and stability of the ship's construction.  In view of the connection between the two Conventions, IMCO has decided to examine the possibility of amalgamating them into one document in due course.</P>
    <P>The Bill is of a technical character, and I am sure it would help towards a better understanding of its provisions if I were to give some general background information about load lines. Load lines are what are colloquially called Plimsoll marks.  They may be defined as marks required by law to be indicated externally on both sides of the hulls of sea-going ships to show the maximum depths to which the hull may be safely submerged in various sea areas or zones and at different seasons of the year.  The distance from the load line downwards to the bottom of the keel is known as the draught of the ship.  The distance from the load line upwards to the level of the uppermost continuous deck is the freeboard of the ship or, in other words, the height of that deck above the water.  Freeboard is assigned to a ship to ensure ample reserve of buoyancy and is dependent on the structural strength and hull form and on the efficiency of the closing appliances in the freeboard deck openings.</P>
    <P>The importance of the load line for the safety of ships is obvious.  A vessel which puts to sea in an overloaded condition runs a greater risk of being overwhelmed due to reduced freeboard, and there were, before the advent of load line legislation, numerous instances of the fatal results of having ships too deeply submerged in the water.  The reason, of course, why such risks were incurred was the desire to carry heavier cargoes of merchandise or greater numbers of passengers.</P>
    <P>The history of load lines goes back to the Middle Ages, when notable seafaring peoples of the period, such as the Italian Republics, Venice and Sardinia, took steps to compel shipowners and masters, in the interests of <Col N="1326" /> safety, to have their ships marked with a symbol which must be kept clear of the water.  However, this example did not find widespread acceptance, and a hundred years ago the position everywhere was highly unsatisfactory.  It was then that Mr. Samuel Plimsoll commenced his campaign in the British House of Commons to promote the safety of British seamen.  The first Parliamentary measures adopted were inadequate, and it was not until 1890 that British shipowners, and owners of foreign ships calling to British ports, were obliged by law to carry a load line mark in a position to be determined under rules and tables, known as freeboard tables, prescribed by the Government.  A series of bilateral international agreements served to promote the widespread adoption of the load line system, until, in 1930, a conference was called in London, which drew up the first International Load Line Convention.  This Convention secured in due course virtually universal acceptance, being ratified by 71 States. Effect was given to the Convention in Ireland by the Merchant Shipping (Safety and Load Line Conventions) Act, 1933 and the Load Line Rules, 1935.  The Act of 1933 was largely an enabling measure, and it was the statutory instrument of 1935 which actually reproduced the detailed technical provisions of the Convention.</P>
    <P>With the development of new building techniques and the tremendous increase in the size of ships, particularly tankers and bulk carriers, it was found necessary to bring the 1930 Convention up to date.  The old Convention provided for the assignment of freeboards to tankers of up to 600 feet in length and for other ships of up to 750 feet.  To cater for the larger vessels now being built, the new Convention covers all vessels of up to 1,200 feet and provides for a reduction of up to 15 per cent in freeboards for tankers and up to 10 per cent for other vessels.</P>
    <P>As already indicated, the freeboard is in fact related to the integrity of the deck openings and their means of closing. In tankers the deck openings are small in relation to the breadth of the ship and very efficient means are provided for closing these openings.  In <Col N="1327" /> addition, the cargo tanks are generally filled with oil.  These factors account for the reduction in freeboards for tankers envisaged by the new Convention.</P>
    <P>In the case of other ships a reduction in freeboards is permissible where improved methods of closing the hatchways and other openings are employed. For instance, a vessel fitted with steel weathertight hatch covers would have a smaller freeboard than a ship fitted with conventional wooden hatch covers secured with tarpaulins.</P>
    <P>The general effect of the Convention is to permit ships to carry greater loads than formerly while still maintaining high standards of safety.  However, in the case of future ships not exceeding 328 feet long, equivalent roughly to a maximum of 3,000 tons carrying capacity, the new Convention prescribes slightly greater freeboards, involving a certain reduction of draught and carrying capacity, if the ships are not fitted with steel weather-tight covers.  This change is considered desirable in order to improve the weathertight integrity and stability of these ships, and to prevent shipping of sea water on decks.  The change, however, will not apply to existing ships, but only to ships the building of which is commenced after the Convention comes into effect.</P>
    <P>The 1930 Convention applied only to ships of 150 tons gross or over.  The 1966 Convention continues to apply to these ships, but extends downwards to include all new ships of not less than 24 metres (79 feet) in length.  This length is equivalent to about 100 tons gross.</P>
    <P>The new Convention, like the old one, is confined to international trade, and does not apply to naval vessels, pleasure yachts or fishing vessels.  The question of load lines for fishing vessels was considered at the 1966 Conference, but it was decided to undertake further studies before drawing up minimum international standards for this purpose.</P>
    <P>As before, provision is made for the assignment of special load lines to <Col N="1328" /> ships carrying timber on deck.  A timber cargo on deck gives a ship an additional reserve of buoyancy by virtue of the nature of the cargo, and a greater degree of protection against the sea, and so justifies some reduction in the normal freeboard, provided the ship complies with certain constructional safety requirements.</P>
    <P>The Convention also affords discretion, as did its predecessor, for the granting of partial or total exemption to ships engaged on short international voyages of a sheltered nature, and to ships which, exceptionally, undertake a single international voyage.  So that strict adherence to the Convention may not have the effect of hindering research into new developments, the Convention allows for the exemption of vessels which embody features of a novel kind, provided always that the vessel meet adequate safety requirements. In view of present-day experimentation with hydrofoils and other new forms of craft, this is a timely provision.</P>
    <P>The Bill before the Seanad is primarily an enabling measure which will provide a statutory basis for the implementation of the 1966 Convention and it repeals, except for a couple of minor provisions, Part II of the Merchant Shipping (Safety and Load Line Conventions) Act, 1933, which enabled effect to be given to the 1930 Load Line Convention.  In substance, the new Bill differs only slightly from the existing legislation.  The main provision is contained in section 3, which gives power to make Load Line Rules incorporating the detailed technical provisions of the 1966 Convention. Section 29 provides that these and any other orders, rules, or regulations to be made under the Bill shall be laid before each House of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>As in the 1933 Act, the new Bill goes beyond the scope of the Convention, in that it applies in principle to all registered ships, that is, of 15 tons net register and upwards, apart from warships, pleasure boats and fishing vessels, whether engaged in international trade or not.  This wider scope is considered desirable in the interests of safety.  At the same time, power is taken under sections 19 and 20 of the <Col N="1329" /> Bill to grant exemptions to ships or classes of ships to which the Convention does not apply and also to grant exemptions to Convention ships in cases where this is permitted by the Convention itself.</P>
    <P>The Bill also provides, like the 1933 Act, for the machinery of control and enforcement.  As before, ships will be required not to be so loaded as to submerge the appropriate load line, nor to attempt to put to sea from an Irish port unless they have been surveyed and marked in accordance with the Load Line Rules, comply with constructional safety requirements, and carry a valid load line certificate. Customs officers, and surveyors, are empowered to detain a ship which contravenes these requirements.  It is intended that, in accordance with the Convention, load line certificates should be issued, as hitherto, for a period of five years subject to annual surveys.</P>
    <P>It is expected that the new provisions will be of substantial benefit in the case of the larger Irish vessels, particularly those of Irish Shipping Ltd., which will be enabled to carry heavier cargoes.  While there will be a slight reduction in the authorised carrying capacity of smaller vessels which may be built in the future, we must accept this as a measure dictated by safety requirements.  In practice, if we were not to implement the Convention, our ships, when in the ports of other countries which had implemented the Convention, would still be bound by its requirements, the only difference being that, since Irish ships would not be in a position to produce a 1966 Convention Certificate, they would be liable to be detained and to be subjected to the delay and expense of a detailed load line survey.</P>
    <P>The 1966 Convention is an international document which is the result of the deliberations of the Governments and experts of all the important maritime countries.  It embodies the fruits of experience and aims at allowing greater commercial advantage to shipping within the limits imposed by safety and technical development.  It has been accepted to date by a total <Col N="1330" /> of 19 countries, including Britain, the US, France and other leading maritime countries.  I consider it worthy of Ireland's support, and I therefore commend this Bill, which will permit of the acceptance of the Convention, for the approval of the Seanad.</P>
    <P>A few minor drafting changes have become necessary since the Bill was prepared.  They do not in any way affect the principles or substance of the Bill.  I propose to introduce these amendments at Committee Stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>First of all, I commend the Minister for introducing this Bill in this House, and indeed the Leader of the House for securing its introduction here, because, as we have said in recent times, a good deal of legislation of this kind can be examined here and this would enable us and the Dáil together to effect improvement in Bills in a way that cannot be done when we get a great number of Bills from the Dáil at the end of a session.  I am therefore very glad the Minister has brought this Bill into this House first.</P>
      <P>The Minister has said the Bill is a technical measure.  That is an understatement. The Title of the Bill at first sight meant nothing to me and reading the Bill without the Convention did not mean a great deal either; but, having read both Bill and Convention and having heard the Minister, one appreciates immediately the importance of the Bill.  The Minister can be assured of a ready passage of the Bill through this House after we have received his amendments and considered such amendments as we ourselves think proper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am gratetful to the Minister for the short résumé he has given of the matter of Plimsoll marks and load lines generally.  It will make quite interesting reading for those interested in boats.  I have very little knowledge of boats or ships but a few things occur to me on which I should like the Minister's views.  The Minister has indicated what the situation is and it occurred to me that fishing vessels ought to be covered by this Bill.  We have known the tragedies associated with trawlers leaving English ports in <Col N="1331" /> recent times.  However, I gather from what the Minister has said that the safety of fishing vessels is being studied by IMCO and that in due course a similar Convention will be drawn up with the same detail and specification as this.</P>
    <P>What I am not entirely happy with, and perhaps the Minister might clarify it at this stage, is that pleasure yachts are not included in the Bill or in the 1966 Convention.  I wonder whether a pleasure yacht used for trade&mdash;used in the harbour of Dún Laoghaire&mdash;is covered by any law or safety regulation, is covered by any legislation dealing with the extent to which they can be loaded or with their stability and construction.  We remember the disastrous end in England last year of a yacht from Dún Laoghaire.</P>
    <P>I have often been minded&mdash;as I have said, I am very much afraid of the water&mdash;to go aboard one of these pleasure yachts but I have not done so because I did not know whether these are certified by the Minister for Transport and Power as being safe.  If they are, how is one to know whether a particular yacht cruising in Dublin Bay or elsewhere has been certified and whether any supervision is exercised to ensure that no more than the appropriate number of passengers are allowed on board?  It seems to me that if that is not covered by the 1966 Convention&mdash;that the Convention excluded pleasure boats not engaged in trade and seems to have included those engaged in trade&mdash;if there is no international Convention dealing with those, the Minister's Department should address themselves to applying some standards analogous to the standards set for other types of craft covered by this Convention.</P>
    <P>Another matter which does not emerge from the Bill but which may be covered by regulation is the question of officers of customs and excise, and other people of that kind, being authorised to impound a ship and prevent it leaving a port.  What I am interested in is the particular training given to customs and excise officers to enable them to know whether a particular <Col N="1332" /> ship complies with the Convention. It would be interesting to know in what way they are skilled enough to exercise their judgment whether a particular craft complies with the requirements.</P>
    <P>Another thing which does not emerge and which is not clear to me is who issues the certificate of compliance with the Convention?  Is it somebody from the Minister's Department or from some other organisation? Do we have in this country people with sufficient skill to measure any particular ship against the specification contained in the annexe to the Convention of 1966?  Otherwise, I think the Bill is a very good measure, one which is heartily welcome in the interests of the safety of passengers and others on board ship.  The Minister can be assured of a speedy passage of the Bill in due course.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator O'Quigley for his co-operative speech. The reason fishing vessels are not included is that there are technical difficulties in providing the load line regulations.  This is still subject to IMCO consideration.  The customs officers, I understand, are trained in the course of their duties in the inspection of ships but of course the surveys of vessels are carried out on our behalf by international societies such as Veritas and Lloyds because it would be impossible for any small country, or any country, to do the work itself. These societies are firms of international repute who do this work.  I, as Minister for Transport and Power, issue certificates after the surveys have been made and I take action to carry out the terms of the Convention when it is required of me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Senator asked about pleasure boats.  If pleasure boats carry more than 12 persons, they are covered by the Merchant Shipping Acts.  They must have passenger certificates issued. If they carry fewer than 12 passengers, they are exempt.  This question has been asked before about vessels carrying fewer than 12 passengers.  There is no legislation of an international character covering them.  In the case of pleasure boats now operating in <Col N="1333" /> Dublin and Dún Laoghaire harbours, they have been inspected by my Department and they hold passenger certificates because they all carry more than 12 passengers.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 15th May, 1968.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Broadcasting Authority (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1968: Second Stage">
    <Title>Broadcasting Authority (Amendment) Bill, 1968: Second Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Bill be now read a Second Time.</P>
      <P>The subject covered by this Bill is, or at any rate in recent years has become, a controversial one and in dealing with it, it is difficult not to become controversial.  Indeed it is probably impossible not to become controversial. It will be necessary to talk frankly about the practical problems that have arisen in ensuring the impartiality and independence of our Television Authority. For my part, however, I shall try to keep the temperature down, and while going through the problem thoroughly and listing problems that have arisen and cases where there have been difficulties, I shall try to do so in as factual a way as possible.</P>
      <P>I should like to say at the outset that in any criticisms I have to make in regard to this matter, criticisms which the Bill endeavours to meet in part at least, the problems that have arisen are not ones that arise out of actions by the present Minister.  There is no evidence that the actions he has taken in regard to Radio Telefís Éireann at any time have belied his reputation for fairness and liberality.  Nevertheless, although he is the responsible Minister, difficulties have arisen both before he was Minister and since and they are ones which we have to examine and tackle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would also like to recognise at the outset that the problem of political broadcasting is a thorny one.  It is not susceptible of easy answer and this is not the only country in which we have difficulty in finding an answer.  However, we have the advantage of a near neighbour, Britain, which in this respect offers a target for admiration <Col N="1334" /> because of the way in which the independence of the broadcasting authority has been maintained even in the face of intense pressure at some times from certain Governments.  It offers us a model to work to.  We have in any event in this country inherited several British traditions, several fine aspects of British traditions&mdash;the incorruptibility of the public service, the tradition of free speech&mdash;and while we have not inherited a tradition in regard to broadcasting because we secured our independence before broadcasting came into existence in these countries, nevertheless the fact that we have close by this example is something which we can properly have regard to in this area, unlike many other areas.  For example, in other respects, I have criticised the fact that we tend to look towards Britain only.  In this case I do not suggest that we should look towards Britain only but we should look for examples of how to secure an independent broadcasting authority and free speech on political matters and impartiality in broadcasting.</P>
    <P>I should like to make a point&mdash;I shall come back to it later on&mdash;that Radio Telefís Éireann is a national service, not a Government service.  This is a vital distinction and it is one which I think has given rise to some difficulties and some confusion.  It is not clear that this is fully accepted by all those on the other side of the House.  There has been, I think, some confusion of thought here, not surprisingly perhaps.  In a Government in office for a long time there must necessarily be a tendency to identify the national interest and the interests of that Government.  This must be true of any Government.  I suspect&mdash;although I have not the historical knowledge to be sure&mdash;that it was probably true of the first Government.  It was, I think, true of the second Government here. It would be surprising if there were not some tendency of that kind in the present Government but it is important that any Government should make this distinction, and if it fails to do so that it should be reminded of this distinction and public opinion should be alert to this distinction.</P>
    <P>The Radio Telefís Éireann Authority <Col N="1335" /> is not an instrument of Government policy.  It is an instrument&mdash;if instrument is the right word&mdash;of national policy.  It must, therefore, be independent of Government, independent of Government to a greater extent than has hitherto been achieved.  It must be seen to be independent of Government and the Government must not feel that it is so close to it that it has a responsibility for it in the eyes of its own electorate at home or in the eyes of the outside world.  Here I think we can properly fault the present situation because, as I shall show later, for example, from remarks of the Minister for External Affairs in the Dáil on this issue, there was a clear feeling that the Radio Telefís Éireann Authority is so much a part of the Government machine that any action it takes would be regarded outside this country as an action of the Irish Government and one which the Government was directly responsible for.  This is something which is certainly not true of the BBC. The distinction has always been maintained. I thought that in the earlier years of the Radio Telefís Éireann Authority that distinction was maintained here.  It has been surprising and disappointing to find that this is not recognised fully by Government spokesmen.</P>
    <P>The problem is how to secure a really independent broadcasting service which is nevertheless a national broadcasting service and not a privately-owned one.  There are four aspects of this problem, four approaches we must adopt to it.  First, to secure this result you need an alert public opinion and Irish public opinion has not always been alert to threats to free speech.  It has become more so in recent years, and indeed much of the credit for this must go to the Radio Telefís Éireann Authority.  As well as an alert public opinion, you need a strong Director General who is willing and able at all times to stand up to pressure from any source, Opposition as well as Government, should it come from that source. You need an independent board, seen to be independent of political pressures, dissociated from political Parties, <Col N="1336" /> independent in such a way that people will feel confidence in the way it runs the service, for the public quite properly cannot know the details of the relationships between the board and the staff of the Authority.  It would be improper that they should, in any detail, and the only way the public can have confidence in the board, therefore, as they cannot know in detail how the board runs the affairs of the Authority, is by seeing that the personnel are independent, are not associated with particular political Parties or groups but are people who, having their own political views as everyone has, have not associated themselves particularly with one particular viewpoint.</P>
    <P>As well as an alert public opinion, a strong Director General and an independent board, you need a fourth thing, that is legislation designed to protect the independence of the Authority. Legislation alone cannot do the job.  Let us be clear on that straight away.  I make no claims that this Bill and the amendments it proposes to make in the original Act would do the job singlehanded.  It would make some small improvements I hope, improvements that will strengthen the independence of the Authority, that will offer greater assurance than we have at present of its impartiality and ensure that the Authority will not only be impartial but will be seen to be impartial and command the confidence of public opinion generally in its impartiality.</P>
    <P>We need all of these and we need them more than other countries which are larger than ours and more impersonal because in this country, small as it is, there are strong pressures arising out of close personal contacts between people, much more pressure to hush things up, to keep things quiet, to keep things cosy, to avoid making trouble, much more than in a larger country where people do not come into quite so much close contact with one another and where clashes on issues of public concern are not so much liable to become clashes between personalities.</P>
    <P>Before analysing in more detail those four approaches to the problem and <Col N="1337" /> ending up with the legislative approach which is what we are endeavouring to work towards in this Bill, I want to go over the record, not, as I said, with a view to being controversial but with a view to establishing that there is a need to take some action in this matter, and that standing back from it as far as one can go, and not getting too involved in the Party politics of it, there is a problem, that it is not simply a figment of the imagination of political opponents or of people with ill-will towards the Government, but a real problem that needs to be tackled.</P>
    <P>The problem which could arise could be at two levels.  It could be a problem of board intervention of an improper character in the affairs of the Authority, that is, seeking to influence it contrary to impartiality or it could be a problem of political intervention from outside, either from the Government or in certain circumstances from the Opposition. As regards the first, one cannot know what the position is because the relations between the board and the staff of the Authority are naturally confidential. In this area the situation is shrouded in mystery.  That mystery is in no way surprising.  As I said, it is natural because of the relationship there.  However, it has given rise to some suspicion because of the particular character of the board to which shall have to return later on.</P>
    <P>There are, I think, some cases, however, where there is some evidence that members of the board have intervened in a manner which causes a little concern. In one instance, for example, a member of the board sought to veto the names of lecturers in a particular series of lectures in a manner which did not seem proper for a member of the board of such an Authority.  To the credit of the Authority and of the people concerned in the programme this attempt was, in fact, resisted but, nevertheless, it was made.  That is not the area to which we have to direct our attention because although there may be other cases, or there may not, we simply do not know.  What we do know is the public record of public intervention, or intervention which has become public, of a political character with the affairs of the Authority.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1338" /> We also know something of one or two decisions the Authority has taken itself on political grounds which, I think, are open to question as to the judgment shown on those occasions.  It is to those I should like to direct my attention now, approaching them as far as possible in chronological order, simply to show how events developed. The first case of which we have a public record, ignoring for the moment the re-audition of all the orchestra after Fianna Fáil came to power, which was one of the interesting developments of 1932.  They all passed the re-audition and none, in fact, lost their jobs for any reason.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>If they were there Fine Gael had them long enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>What year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>1932.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>Had nobody listened to them playing before that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>There was none there in 1932.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Indeed, there was.  I refer you, when I come back to it, to page 83 of Mr. Gorham's book on the subject.  However, that is intended frivolously and not as a serious complaint.  The first occasion to which I want to direct attention arose in, I think, 1959 when &ldquo;a turmoil was caused&rdquo;, to use the words of Maurice Gorham, &ldquo;by the reports of what Neil Blaney had said at the Fianna Fáil Ard-Fheis (or Party conference) on November 20&rdquo;.  I am quoting from page 275 of Mr. Gorham's book:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Turmoil is not too strong a word. From the Council and Director right through the programme staff, there was a surge of indignation.  As one of the newspapers remarked, what was going on behind the scenes would make more exciting broadcasts than anything Radio Éireann could produce.  The Minister was reported as saying, among other things, &ldquo;I cannot blame those who criticise Radio Éireann.  Many of the <Col N="1339" /> criticisms were being made by myself not long ago, and are being made by me even now. . . The very arguments being used in favour of more independence for Radio Éireann were the strongest arguments against it. . .  It was in the past three years, since Radio Éireann got some freedom&mdash;since it got its own Director and Council, Comhairle Radio Éireann&mdash;that the programmes had disimproved&rdquo;.  It was surprising to see a Minister reported as speaking in this fashion of a department for which he was responsible, and surprising for the Director and Council to see him reported as having told a meeting that the programmes had disimproved since they took charge.  They had never heard this from him.  What especially incensed them was the reported statement that he had been criticising Radio Éireann and was criticising it now, when they had heard no criticism from him and in fact had had practically no contact with him and knew nothing of his views.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this all Gorham's book you are quoting?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  There is a reference then to Question Time in the Dáil on November 28th when the Minister was asked what was the Government's policy towards Radio Éireann, asked to state the arguments against its independence to which he was said to have referred at the ArdFheis. He was pressed to tell the Dáil what he really had said at the Ard-Fheis, asked whether the Council had tendered their resignations, asked whether he ever drew their attention to the fact that he was dissatisfied with any aspect of the programmes.  He was asked whether a member of the Rep. had been suspended, and why.  He was asked what the row at the hotel dinner had been about.  We need not go into detail about that.  Mr. Gorham then continues:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That was the last appearance of Neil Blaney as Minister for Posts and Telegraphs.  When the Dáil reassembled on December 4 the Taoiseach nominated Seán Ormonde as <Col N="1340" /> Minister and on the following day his appointment was announced.  So far as the Director and Council were concerned, the departure of the Minister ended the matter.  There was no point in resigning, or demanding a retraction or an expression of confidence from a Minister who was no longer responsible for the broadcasting service.  The Government however did not yet regard the incident as closed.  There were more special meetings of the Council; the Taoiseach intervened; the matter was not finished with until December 7, more than two weeks after it had begun.</P>
    <P>There is a reference to the next Minister being a man of very pleasant personality and of culture, sympathetic to what Radio Éireann was trying to do. That was the first occasion of which we have record of a ministerial intervention except in the sense it was nonintervention. The odd thing in this case was the Minister claimed to have intervened when, in fact, it appears he did not, at least not at the level of the Director and Comhairle Radio Éireann.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. Eoin Ryan Mr. Eoin Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Eoin Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you complaining about the fact that he did intervene or did not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am complaining about the fact that he claimed to have intervened but that there is evidence he did not intervene at the level of the Director and of Comhairle of Radio Éireann and assuming he was telling the truth, and I would hate to cast aspersions on the Minister's truthfulness, he must, therefore, have intervened at a lower level behind their backs, which is a matter for concern I think.</P>
      <P>The second case relates to another Minister, Deputy Boland, also in Mr. Gorham's book, Deputy Boland being Deputy Blaney's successor.  This is from page 316 of this book:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In October, 1960 public controversy broke out over a cancelled programme. Proinnsias Mac Aonghusa, who had done a lot of writing and broadcasting, arranged with Radio Éireann and the Department of <Col N="1341" /> Defence to write and record a programme on Civil Defence, which was then much in the news.  It was to be a &ldquo;packaged programme&rdquo;, produced by An Comhlucht Taifeadadh, a production studio, with the co-operation of the Department of Defence, and it was to include statements by the President and the Minister for Defence.  The programme was prepared and recorded, but the Minister, Kevin Boland, with two officials of his department, came to hear it in Radio Éireann before it was broadcast and expressed objections to it, and the broadcast was cancelled at 24 hours' notice.</P>
    <P>There was considerable disagreement about the facts, but one thing that seemed to emerge clearly was that the Minister for Defence dealt only with the acting-Director and the decision not to broadcast the programme was made by the acting-Director. The Chairman and Authority was not consulted at all.</P>
    <P>Sorry, I think I said he was Deputy Blaney's successor.  He was the Minister for Defence, which makes the intervention even odder.  That is the second reported case.</P>
    <P>The third case is the case of the intervention by Deputy Haughey, when he was Minister for Agriculture, when he asked for the suppression of a news item about an NFA statement, which was immediately conceded.  I would myself think it was an error of judgment to have suppressed an item in those circumstances.  What was disturbing was that the error of judgment, as I would regard it to be, was endorsed subsequently at a higher level.</P>
    <P>Another case of which we have a record is the inquiry by Deputy Boland, then Minister for Local Government, regarding a programme on Mount Pleasant Square.  In this instance, in fairness to the Minister, there is no evidence that he sought to have the programme suppressed.  It would appear that its suppression arose from a misunderstanding in that the Minister was misinformed that no such programme was going on, due to lack of communication within the Authority, and when the Director <Col N="1342" /> General discovered it was in preparation he felt to put it on would be a breach of what he said to the Minister. I would think again it was in those circumstances an error of judgment although, indeed, an apology to the Minister was called for for the misinformation. These are specific cases of which we have knowledge.  There are others that have been reported too on which we have not got the same authoritative knowledge.</P>
    <P>There were, I think, more than one programme on Nítrigin Éireann in the early days of that project when it was considered controversial which were prepared but which did not appear and this was stated to have been because of intervention from outside but of that we have no certain knowledge.  We also know of the programme on the Special Branch which was prepared but which did not appear.  We did not know if it was because of an internal decision or a decision given from outside or a ministerial intervention.  In fact, in that instance for all we know a directive may have been given in accordance with the terms of the Act in writing, but so far that correct procedure has not been employed to our knowledge.</P>
    <P>The next case&mdash;and in some cases the most striking because it raises broader issues than the others&mdash;is the Vietnam case.  This was the intervention of the Taoiseach to prevent not only a programme being broadcast but, in fact, an attempt to send a team to Vietnam to cover that event.  This is particularly important because it raises broader issues which I have referred to already in opening on this debate and I think we want to give it for that reason special attention.  The account of the Minister for External Affairs of this was, as reported in the Official Report, Volume 227, column 1961:</P>
    <P>. . .the first I knew of the proposal was when it appeared in a newspaper. As I could not get in touch with the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs at the time I called the attention of the Taoiseach to the matter.  Later the Taoiseach, after consultation with the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs at the time, <Col N="1343" /> spoke to the Chairman of Telefís Éireann and informed him that in the opinion of the Government the best interests of the nation&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>Given with a capital &ldquo;N&rdquo; in the Official Report&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>&mdash;would not be served by sending a Radio Telefís Éireann team to Vietnam. The project was then dropped.</P>
    <P>After an interjection by Mr. Cluskey, Mr. Aiken went on:</P>
    <P>The first I heard of any suggestion that this team were to go to North Vietnam, or to China or India, was after the matter was dropped and it appeared in the papers.</P>
    <P>It is difficult to reconcile that with what has been said before.  After further intervention by Deputy Cluskey he went on to say:</P>
    <P>. . . the Television Authority here was set up after a long investigation into what happened in other countries. Its function is to distribute information to the Irish people through radio and television.  I think that if there is anything in any part of the world the Irish people should know something about, it is the situation in Vietnam.  They have been deluged with pictures from Vietnam and they have been deluged with newspaper stories.  They can read about it in periodicals; they can read about in books and those who are interested in it have followed it very closely.  Radio Telefís Éireann is a semi-State body, set up by this Parliament.  There are many troubled spots in the world and it would not be believed that this semi-State body had not sent a team to Vietnam at the request, or with the approval, or at the instance of the Government.  If they went to Vietnam, I would be asked why the Government do not use their influence to send them to many of the other trouble spots all over the world.  Films and television programmes are very entertaining.  I think, however, it will be admitted that the television camera is a very crude instrument with which to describe or illustrate very highly <Col N="1344" /> complicated political, social troubles. I think, on the whole, if these were private individuals who were going, it would be all right.  We would have no responsibility for it.  If we want any more information; if anybody in this country does not know the issues in Vietnam, somebody could go at his own expense, or a group could go at the expense of people who send them out.  They would be able to go out there, learn the language, live there for a couple of years and describe it with their pens rather than try to describe it with a few odd pictures which have to be selective and which could give a wrong impression.  A camera team going out with all this equipment could only be a conducted and protected tour and would be regarded as such.</P>
    <P>After further interjections by Deputy Cluskey, Mr. Aiken went on:</P>
    <P>This Parliament sets out how the Government's affairs are to be run. I have the responsibility as a Member of the Government to look after external relations.  That is my responsibility. A very wise practice has grown up here&mdash;I think it always obtained &mdash; that where another Government Department, or a semi-State body, has contacts abroad or has to go to an international conference where a difficult question might arise, the Department of External Affairs is consulted.  This has always been the case.  It would be very wise for a semi-State body when they go outside their normal functions&mdash;and that takes them across the line of international relations &mdash; to consult us before they decide to send a team of this magnitude to the ends of the earth.  I do not know whether the team would even know the language spoken there.</P>
    <P>Now this is a particularly disturbing extract because it raises the whole question of the status of Radio Telefís Éireann, which is an organ of entertainment and information.  In its news gathering service and feature programmes its job is to keep the Irish people informed.  It is the sole medium for the broadcasting by vision or sound <Col N="1345" /> of news and features on world affairs and domestic politics in this country. It has a statutory monopoly and it has a duty, therefore, to inform the people fully and impartially within the limits of its resources.  Deputy Aiken's concept of it is one which has obviously some validity from his viewpoint but is based on a complete misconception.  He clearly regards it as a semi-State body analogous to Aer Lingus or Bord Iascaigh Mhara, but even seen in that light his ideas of the duties of such bodies and their relationship with the Department of External Affairs are narrow, and narrower than is the practice. I was for 12 years in Aer Lingus and I was never aware that when we went abroad to negotiate agreements the Department of External Affairs had to be consulted.  I gravely doubt if that practice has been introduced since I left the company, and I am sure that it is not the practice in other semi-State bodies.  Whatever the validity of the conception in regard to other semi-State bodies, this conception of a news gathering organisation being so totally a subservient instrument of the Government in its very means of collecting news, that it would be regarded as representing the policy of the Government, is totally misconceived.  Although the Minister may have difficulty in quarrelling with him in public on this issue, I find it hard to believe that he had not in his heart some sympathy with what I am saying on this.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>The debate was applied to one situation, not the whole dissemination of news.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>All I am doing is quoting what Deputy Aiken said about the role and function of Radio Telefís Éireann.  I have quoted his description of it and his statement of what its duties are if it goes anywhere outside this country.  He did not say that this was a special case unlike any other because of special factors which might have seemed important. He laid down a general principle arising out of a direction given, and applying the general principle and applying the concept in this particular instance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1346" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Obviously he was consulted when the cameras went to Moscow, Budapest and other places behind the Iron Curtain&mdash;John O'Donoghue, Brian Cleeve and Lelia Doolan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not understand the force of the Senator's intervention.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>You isolated one case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quoting the statement made by the Minister for External Affairs of a general character on that one case.  In what I have said there were certain statements relating to the particular case of Vietnam but this was a general statement made about Government policy in which general principles were laid down about the responsibility of a Member of the Government for the Department of External Affairs.  Mr. Aiken referred to&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>. . .a very wise practice has grown up here &mdash; I think it has always obtained &mdash; that where another Government Department or a semi-State body, has contacts abroad or has to go to an international conference where a difficult question might arise, the Department of External Affairs is consulted.  This has always been the case.  It would be very wise for a semi-State body when they go outside their normal functions&mdash;and that takes them across the line of international relations&mdash;to consult us before their decide to send a team of this magnitude to the other ends of the earth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>They must have consulted him about all the other Iron Curtain countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister was referring to a sensitive area, as the Senator knows perfectly well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Aiken's statement makes no reference to sensitive matters, and the concept of Radio Telefís Éireann which he clearly has is a disturbing one.  I do not think that it is fully shared in that form by all the Members of the <Col N="1347" /> Government.  It was in some measure an individualistic view.  In Fianna Fáil there are conflicts of interests and views.  We have among the other comments those by the former Taoiseach, Deputy Lemass, which I shall quote in due course.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Before drawing general conclusions I want to put on record the known statements and then we can consider them together and see what conclusions we should reach on them.  In regard to Vietnam, as an indication of another aspect of the Government's attitude we have the reply given by the Taoiseach when questioned on a television broadcast.  He was asked what was the real reason for banning the visit of an RTE unit to Vietnam and his answer, I think, was pretty well verbatim: &ldquo;What is going on in Vietnam that you do not know about?&rdquo;&mdash;which was not, in fact, as someone noticed, a reply to the question.  Again, the concept here of a news-gathering organisation is one which is totally alien to anything in western Europe. It is quite true that there are other <Col N="1348" /> organisations in which there is more political interference, I think, than there is in this country.  The French radio-television organisation is clearly under much more direct Government influence than here.  But the French radio-television as a news gathering organisation has normal independence, and it would be inconceivable, even in the French situation, that they should be controlled in this way as regards where they send teams, what they report and how they report.</P>
    <P>This is a peculiarly Irish phenomenon. Political interference is not, as I say, more acute in some other countries than it is here.  This particular problem, the attitude to the organisation, as a news gathering and disseminating organisation, is a peculiarly Irish one which I do not think has any parallel on this side of the Iron Curtain and north of the Pyrenees.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 10.5 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 15th May, 1968.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>