<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Tue" Date="16" Month="Jul" Year="1968" Vol="65" No="14" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 16 Iúil 1968" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 16 July 1968" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1453">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1453" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Business, as set out on the Order Paper, in the following order: Nos. 1, 2, 3, 5, 4 and 6. In order to complete the business, it is proposed to adjourn not later than 11 p.m. In view of the fact that all Parties have approved the proposals in these measures, I hope the House will agree to give all Stages today. For the information of Senators, I might add that it is my hope that the Seanad will be able to begin its Summer Recess not later than 1st August.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Leader of the House when it is proposed to make time available for Motion No. 15?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot give any indication to the Senator until the business on the Order Paper is finished.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator not think he is a bit optimistic when he talks about 1st August in those circumstances?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am always an optimist.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="An Bille um Thionscail na Gaeltachta (Leasú), 1968: An Dara" RHead="Céim. Gaeltacht Industries (Amendment) Bill, 1968: Second Stage">
    <Title>An Bille um Thionscail na Gaeltachta (Leasú), 1968: An Dara Céim.   Gaeltacht Industries (Amendment) Bill, 1968: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Tairgeadh an cheist : &ldquo;Go léifear an Bille an Dara hUair anois&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Question proposed : &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraigFaulkner" hpid="Aire na Gaeltachta (Mr. Faulkner) Aire na Gaeltachta (Mr. Faulkner)">
      <NameTxt>Aire na Gaeltachta (Mr. Faulkner)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is chun cumhachtaí Ghaeltarra Éireann a leathnú atá an Bille seo os <Col N="1454" /> comhair an tSeanaid anois. Trí bhliana ó shin a tugadh na cumhachtaí atá i gceist do Ghaeltarra&mdash;cumhacht chun páirt a ghlacadh i dtionscail i gcomhar le daoine eile agus cumhacht chun deontais a thabhairt do dhaoine gan dul i bpáirtíocht leo.</P>
      <P>Faoi mar atá na hAchtanna i láthair na huaire tá uasteorainn £2,000 leis na deontais a thugann Gaeltarra chun miontionscadail shomhaoineacha a chur chun cinn sa Ghaeltacht. Ní miste a lua gur ceadaíodh luach £50,000 de na deontais sin go dtí 31 Márta, 1968, agus go bhfuiltear ag súil le fostaíocht do níos mó ná 100 duine breise dá dhroim sin. De thoradh na taithí atá againn ar riaradh na ndeontas sin táimid sásta anois gur ceart an uasteorainn a ardú go £5,000 agus tá leasú dá réir sin sa Bhille. Ina theannta sin, más é ár mbarúil ar ball gur cóir deontais níos airde fós a thabhairt, beidh cumhacht agamsa faoin mBille, le toiliú an Aire Airgeadais, uasteorainn nua a údarú gan dul thar £10,000.</P>
      <P>Maidir leis an leasú eile atá beartaithe, feicfear go mbaineann sé leis na hionaid ina bhfuil tionscail faoi chúram Ghaeltarra lasmuigh den Ghaeltacht&mdash; is iad sin Ard an Rátha agus An Bhroclais i gContae Dhún na nGall agus Cloch na Rón i gContae na Gaillimhe. Faoi láthair níl ar chumas Ghaeltarra dul i bpáirtíocht le daoine eile sna hionaid sin cionn is gur leis an nGaeltacht amháin a bhaineann an chumhacht chun tionscail a reachtáil i gcomhar le daoine eile. Meastar anois, áfach, gur cóir go leathnófaí an chumhacht sin go dtí na hionaid atá luaite agam&mdash;mar a bhfuil foirgnimh agus foireann ag Gaeltarra&mdash;agus tá leathnú dá réir sin sa Bhille. Ní miste a rá go bhfuil feidhm éifeachtach á baint as an gcumhacht sin sa Ghaeltacht cheana féin agus nach fada go mbeidh suas le 100 fear agus 80 cailín ag obair i gceithre cinn de chomhthionscail.</P>
      <P>Is é mo bharúil gur maith is fiú cumhachtaí Ghaeltarra a leathnú mar atá beartaithe agus go bhfuil tuiscint ag na Seanadóirí do na cuspóirí atá i gceist agus go bhfuil bá acu leo. Iarraim ar an Seanad glacadh leis an Dara Céim den Bhille.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1455" />
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Cuirim fáilte roimh an mBille seo. Is ceart dúinn na cumhachtaí breise seo a thabhairt chun a chur ar chumas Ghaeltarra Éireann a bhfeidhmeanna a chomhlíonadh. Is réasúnta an tairiscint í, dar liomsa, an teorainn nua £5,000 i leith deontaisí do Ghaeltarra Éireann agus tá sé réasúnta freisin cumhacht a thabhairt don Aire an teorainn nua seo a árdú go £10,000 le toiliú an Aire Airgeadais.</P>
      <P>Maidir le cumhacht a thabhairt do Ghaeltarra Éireann páirt a ghlacadh le daoine eile i reachtáil tionscal lasmuigh den Ghaeltacht, is dóigh liom go bhfuil teorainn curtha sa Bhille leis an gcumhacht seo. Ní bhaineann an chumhacht seo ach le &ldquo;tionscail tuaithe atá in ionaid lasmuigh den Ghaeltacht&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Nach ceart dúinn, a Chathaoirleach, cumhacht a thabhairt do Ghaeltarra Éireann páirt a ghlacadh freisin le comhlacht onnmhairíochta comhoibritheacha, mar shompla&mdash;chun comhoibriú le comhlachtaí eile&mdash;comhlachtaí príobháideacha, chun a chuid onnmhairithe a leathnú? Cúpla bliain ó shin do bhí orm mar chathaoirleach chomhairle oiriúnú tionscail cniotála agus osánacht, an cheist seo do phlé le muintir Ghaeltarra Éireann agus is é mo chuimhne go raibh siad i gcruachás sa scéal seo toisc nach raibh cumhacht acu comhoibriú sa slí seo le comhlachtaí príobháideacha. Ba mhaith liom dá ndéanfadh an tAire an cheist seo a phlé.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Muna bhfuil dul amú ormsa sílim gurbh é seo an chéad uair don Aire teacht anso mar Aire na Gaeltachta agus, dá bhrí sin, ba mhaith liom fáilte a chur roimhe anso agus rath Dé a ghuí ar an obair atá idir lámhaibh aige i Roinn na Gaeltachta.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Maidir leis an mBille seo, is annamh a thagann Bille mar seo ós comhair an tSeanaid. Is dóigh liomsa gur mór an trua é sin. Is Bille é seo a bhaineann le fostaíocht mhuintir na Gaeltachta agus muintir na Gaeltachta féin. Is dóigh liom gur maith an Bille é agus gur rinne Gaeltarra Éireann sár-obair leis na cumhachtaí a tugadh dóibh trí bhliana ó shin. Tá mé cinnte go leanfar <Col N="1456" /> ar aghaidh leis an obair atá idir lámhaibh acu. Ba mhaith liom a fheiceáil freisin go leanfaidis leis an slí inar ghlacadar áit daoine eile i reachtáil tionscal sa Ghaeltacht. Tá mé cinnte go ndéanfaidh an Bille seo maitheas do thionscail na Gaeltachta go mór mhór toisc go bhfuil géar-ghá le fostaíocht a chur ar fáil do mhuintir na Gaeltachta agus aon Bhille go bhfuil mar aidhm aige obair a chur ar fáil do mhuintir na Gaeltachta ba chóir dúinn gach cabhair agus cúnamh a thabhairt dó. Molaim an Bille.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KitAhern" hpid="Cáit Bean Uí Eachthéirn Cáit Bean Uí Eachthéirn">
      <NameTxt>Cáit Bean Uí Eachthéirn</NameTxt>
      <P>Is mian liomsa freisin fáilte a chur roimh an mBille agus fáilte a chur roimh an Aire chomh maith. Níl a fhios agam an féidir an t-airgead seo a úsáid chun miontionscadail a chur ar bun agus an féidir an t-airgead a úsáid i gcóir oiliúint agus tréineál daoine?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonallOConallain" hpid="Dónall Ó Connalláin Dónall Ó Connalláin">
      <NameTxt>Dónall Ó Connalláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liomsa fáilte a chur roimh an mBille agus freisin fáilte a chur roimh an Aire nua mar a rinne Seanadóirí eile. Is í a chéad chuairt ar an dTeach seo mar Aire is dóigh liom.</P>
      <P>Tá moladh mór ag dul dó as a bhfuil déanta aige cheana féin ar son na Gaeltachta agus tá an Ghaeltacht agus muintir na Gaeltachta faoi chomaoin mhór aige go dtí seo. Ar ndóigh ní mór le duine ar bith againn do mhuintir na Gaeltachta pé cabhair is acmhuinn dúinn a thabhairt dóibh ach amháin cúram a dhéanamh de i gcónaí gur mar mhuintir na Gaeltachta atá an chabhair speisialta seo á tabhairt, is é sin, mar phobal a bhfuil an Ghaeilge mar ghnáth-theanga acu. Nuair atá tacaíocht mar seo á dáileamh orthu agus fostaíocht á cur ar fáil ba chóir i gcónaí cúram a dhéanamh de nach ndéanfar aon díobháil do leathnú na Gaeilge ná nach gcuirfear aon chaolú uirthi.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Is maith liom go bhfuil an scéim seo á leathnú chun cabhair a thabhairt do áiteacha nach n-áirítear mar chuid den Ghaeltacht iad de réir ráiteas an Aire. Ba chóir go bhféadfaí tríd an leathnú sin an Ghaeilge a thabhairt ar ais sna trí cheantar seo nach bhfuil i bhfad ón bhFíor-Ghaeltacht. Le leathnú ar obair Ghaeltarra Éireann ar fud na tíre <Col N="1457" /> d'fhéadfaí bheith ag súil le leathnú dá réir ar an nGaeilge.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraigFaulkner" hpid="Mr. Faulkner Mr. Faulkner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Faulkner</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom mo bhuíochas a ghabháil leis an Teach as ucht an fháilte a cuireadh roimh an mBille seo agus as ucht an chomhgháirdis a rinneadh liom féin. Ba mhaith liom a rá go bhfuil na cumhachtaí a luaigh an Seanadóir FitzGerald agus an Seanadóir Bean Uí Eachthéirn ag Gaeltarra Éireann laistigh den Ghaeltacht.</P>
      <P>Is é an fáth go bhfuilimíd ag iarraidh cumhacht áirithe a leathnú go dtí Árd an Rátha agus An Bhroclais i gContae Dhún na nGall agus Cloch na Rón i gContae na Gaillimhe ná go bhfuil foirgnimh agus foireann ag Gaeltarra Éireann sna háiteanna sin agus go bhfuil tionscail ar siúl ansin cheana féin ach cionn is nach bhfuil na háiteanna taobh istigh de limistéir na Gaeltachta faoi mar atá na limistéir sin leagtha amach, ní bhaineann an chumhacht atá i gceist&mdash;a tugadh isteach i 1965&mdash;leo agus níl ar chumas Ghaeltarra Éireann dul i gcomhar le tionsclaithe eile sna háiteanna sin. Anois, má ghlacann an Seanad leis an mBille seo, bainfidh an chumacht sin ní amháin leis an nGaeltacht ach leis na hionaid seo lasmuigh den Ghaeltacht chomh maith.</P>
      <P>Labhair an Seanadóir Ó Conalláin faoin tábhacht a bhaineann leis an nGaeilge agus le muintir na Gaeltachta ó thaobh deontais a chur ar fáil. Tuigimíd é sin agus sin ceann de na fáthanna go bhfuil an leasú eile againn chun an chumhacht atá ag Gaeltarra Éireann a leathnú ionas go mbeidh ar a gcumas deontais fhiúntacha a thabhairt do mhuintir na Gaeltachta agus an Ghaeilge a chur chun cinn ag an am céanna.</P>
      <P>Arís ba mhaith liom buíochas a ghabháil leis an Teach as ucht an dóigh inar ghlac siad leis an mBille.</P>
      <P>Cuireadh agus d'aontaíodh an cheist.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>D'aontaíodh na Céimeanna eile a thógaint inniu.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="An Bille um Thionscail na Gaeltachta (Leasú), 1968: Céim an Choiste agus na Céimeanna" RHead="Deiridh. Gaeltacht Industries (Amendment) Bill, 1968: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>An Bille um Thionscail na Gaeltachta (Leasú), 1968: Céim an Choiste agus na Céimeanna Deiridh.   Gaeltacht Industries (Amendment) Bill, 1968: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1458" /> Cuireadh agus d'aontaíodh Alt 1 agus Alt 2.</P>
    <P>Sections 1 and 2, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P>Cuireadh agus d'aontaíodh an Teideal.</P>
    <P>Title agreed to.</P>
    <P>Tuairiscíodh an Bille gan leasú.</P>
    <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
    <P>Cuireadh agus d'aontaíodh an cheist: &ldquo;Go nglacfar an Bille chun an breithniú deiridh a dhéanamh air&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Bill received for final consideration.</P>
    <P>Cuireadh agus d'aontaíodh an cheist: &ldquo;Go rithfear an Bille anois&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Question: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo; put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Social Welfare (Miscellaneous Provisions)" RHead="Bill, 1968: Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Social Welfare (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill, 1968: Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. J. Brennan) Joseph Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. J. Brennan)</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is necessary to implement the decisions of the Government announced by the Minister for Finance in his Budget Statement on 23rd April last to increase the rates of non-contributory old age, blind, widows' and orphans' pensions and unemployment assistance, to increase the rates of various social insurance benefits and pensions and to modify the means test for old age pensions in the case of veterans of the War of Independence. The Bill also includes a number of provisions designed to improve further the social insurance and assistance schemes, some of which are consequential on the decisions announced in the Budget Statement and others of which are the outcome of the continuing examination of existing provisions which is carried out as a normal part of the work of my Department.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1459" /> Of necessity, the Bill consists mainly of amendments to existing Acts and there may be difficulty in some instances in following the amendments without the text of the Acts. The explanatory memorandum which was issued with the Bill has therefore been made as comprehensive and informative as possible so that it will be clear what each amendment really does where the text of the Bill itself is not self-explanatory. I trust that Senators will find it of assistance.</P>
    <P>The Budget increases on the social assistance side, which it is proposed to bring into operation at the beginning of next month, will give an extra 7/6d a week to all existing non-contributory old age, blind, widow and orphan pensioners, making the maximum personal rate of old age and blind pension £3 5s a week and the maximum personal rate of widow's pension £3 3s 6d a week. An additional 2/6d a week will also be given in respect of each qualified child of a pensioner making the weekly rate 12/6d for each of the first two children and 7/6d for each subsequent child. These increases in the pension rates allow the scale of means and rates of pension to be extended in each case to bring in additional rates at the bottom of the scale and these will be payable to persons who cannot at present get pension because their means exceed the present limit. Also where a pensioner has qualified children, the means limit is raised in respect of each qualified child.</P>
    <P>The rates of unemployment assistance are also being increased by 7/6d a week for the recipient himself, by a further 7/6d where there is an adult dependant and by an additional 2/6d for each qualified child. The maximum rate will then be £2 11s 6d for a single person and £4 17s 6d for a married couple resident in an urban area. It will be £2 5s 6d for a single person and £4 9s 6d for a married couple resident outside an urban area. These increases of unemployment assistance at the maximum will have the effect of automatically extending the means limit for qualification for assistance.</P>
    <P>On the social insurance side the increased rates of benefit and pensions <Col N="1460" /> will come into operation at the beginning of January next. Recipients of disability benefit, unemployment benefit, maternity allowance, widow's (contributory) pension, orphan's (contributory) allowance and old age (contributory) pension will get an extra 7/6d a week. There will also be an additional 7/6d a week for an adult dependant and an extra 2/6d a week for each qualified child. The rates of unemployment and disability benefit will then be £3 5s a week for a single person and £5 17s 6d for a married couple. A widow without children will get £3 5s a week. In the case of old age (contributory) pension, a pensioner who is single will get £3 12s 6d while the rate for a married couple will be £6 12s 6d. The rates for children will be 15/6d for each of the first two and 10/6d for each subsequent child. Certain rates of unemployment benefit, which are payable after the first 156 days of benefit and are the same as the maximum rates of unemployment assistance payable in urban areas, are, however, being increased from the beginning of next month when the equivalent assistance rates are being increased.</P>
    <P>An increase in the social insurance contributions payable by employers and employees is necessary to meet the extra expenditure on the increased rates of benefits and pensions. In recent years, the Exchequer has borne considerably more than one-third of the cost of the social insurance scheme. Accordingly, as forecast by the Minister for Finance in his Budget Statement, the increased contributions provided for in the Bill have been calculated so as to adjust the Exchequer's burden nearer to the traditional one-third. Where all insurance benefits are covered, it is proposed to increase the rates of contributions by 3/4d a week. Where only some of the benefits are covered, there will be lesser increases. The increase of 3/4d in the ordinary rate of men's contribution will be shared equally by the employer and employee and the total contribution will then be 21/4d a week. The existing contribution of 2/1d in respect of occupational injuries insurance must, of course, be added to this while the contribution <Col N="1461" /> of 1/- under the redundancy scheme will be added from January, 1969, under a further provision of the Bill. Voluntary contributions will also be increased, those covering only widow's pension by 6d, and those which also cover old age (contributory) pension by 1/2d. The explanatory memorandum contains a table showing the present and proposed rates of contribution exclusive of the contributions in respect of occupational injuries benefit and redundancy. On the basis of this year's estimates of expenditure plus the additional costs incurred by the provisions of the Bill, and taking account of the expected yield in a full year of the increases in contribution rates proposed, it is estimated that the Exchequer contribution will be close to one-third of the expenditure from the Social Insurance Fund.</P>
    <P>There is provision in the Bill for some improvements in the occupational injuries benefit. The rates of unemployability supplement and of payments in respect of adult dependants and qualified children under that scheme are being increased from January next. These payments came into operation on 1st May, 1967, and were then equal to corresponding payments under the disability and unemployment benefit schemes but they were not increased when the latter were increased in January, 1968. The increases now proposed will restore the parity that originally existed. The annual cost of these improvements in the occupational injuries scheme will be about £75,000 but it will not be necessary to increase the present contribution of 2/1d to meet them.</P>
    <P>The Bill provides a new benefit for old age pensioners, both contributory and non-contributory, and for widows aged 70 and over who are receiving contributory pensions. The benefit takes the form of an increase of pension of 45s a week in respect of a prescribed female relative where the pensioner is so incapacitated as to require full-time care and attention and is living alone or has no other adult living with him who is capable of looking after him. It will be payable where a prescribed female relative with a reasonably good employment record <Col N="1462" /> specifically gives up employment to look after the pensioner. It is my intention to prescribe a daughter under the regulations to be made, as a daughter is most likely to be concerned in such cases. There will, however, be power to prescribe other female relatives as satisfying the conditions for the payment, if experience of the working of the scheme shows that this would be warranted.</P>
    <P>In his Budget Statement the Minister for Finance announced that, as a token of recognition to those who served in the War of Independence, Old IRA pensions and allowances would be disregarded completely in future when assessing means for old age pension purposes. Hitherto only the first £80 of these pensions and allowances was disregarded. I have arranged that the total disregard will also be extended to applicants for widows' pensions and unemployment assistance and provision is made accordingly in the Bill.</P>
    <P>During the period from August next, when non-contributory pensions are increased, until January next, when contributory pensions are increased, cases will occur where the non-contributory pension would temporarily be more favourable than the corresponding contributory pension. There is a provision in the Bill to prevent a person switching from contributory pension to non-contributory pension merely to gain them a temporary advantage. It was never intended that the statutory provision which enables such switching to be done should operate in these circumstances and the departmental machinery is not geared to deal with short-term transfers from one pension to the other and back again. The right of a pensioner to switch pensions where the advantage would be permanent will not, however, be affected.</P>
    <P>At present, redundancy contributions are collected by the Department of Labour by means of a separate stamp. As I mentioned earlier, the Bill will enable these contributions to be collected with social insurance contributions from the beginning of January next, by means of a single stamp and the necessary adjustments to be made between the Social Insurance Fund and the Redundancy Fund. This arrangement <Col N="1463" /> will, I believe, be welcomed by employers.</P>
    <P>A new superannuation scheme is being introduced by the Minister for Health to cover nurses and other persons employed in voluntary hospitals and by organisations providing district nursing services such as those providing Jubilee and Lady Dudley nurses. When admitted to the scheme, the position of these employees will be similar to that of their counterparts in the hospital and district nursing services of local health authorities who are insurable for widows' and orphans' pensions and occupational injuries purposes only. There is provision in the Bill, therefore, to enable the insurance position of those persons who are admitted to the new superannuation scheme to be modified so that they will be similarly insurable.</P>
    <P>In conclusion it may be helpful to Senators if I summarise the cost of the various proposals in the Bill. On the social assistance side, the improvements will require an extra £2,284,000 for old age and blind pensions, £406,000 for widows' and orphans' pensions and £810,000 for unemployment assistance, making a total of £3½ million in a full year. All of this will be borne by the Exchequer. The gross cost of improvements on the social insurance side will be £5,719,000. Allowing for an increased annual income of £4,656,500 from the increase in rates of contributions, the cost to be met by the Exchequer will be £1,062,500 in a full year.</P>
    <P>I have much pleasure in recommending the Bill to Seanad Éireann and I ask for speedy and favourable consideration of it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister asks for speedy and favourable consideration of this measure and I have no doubt that this will be forthcoming from the House because any proposal that is intended to ease the lot of the aged, of the disabled, of persons who are necessitous because of unemployment or otherwise calls for the most sympathetic and favourable consideration of any Government and of any public representative.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1464" /> In this measure we are implementing certain increases that are overdue. We are only too well aware of the decreasing value of money. In circumstances in which some of our people appear to have advanced in affluence, there are many sections of our population who are lagging far behind. In this latter category must be included in particular the aged who live alone. We know that were it not for the generous and most commendable local activities on the part of many organisations, there would be extreme privation in many instances where the State assistance provided is insufficient to maintain an aged person. All credit is due to those organisations actively engaged in the provision of meals that are brought to the homes of aged persons who have no member of their family to look after them properly. In this way the terrible consequence of these aged persons having to end their days in drab institutions is avoided. If the enactment of this measure will help to ease the increasing charges represented by the formidable increases in the cost of living, in the cost of the simple necessaries for these people, then the Bill should be passed by agreement.</P>
    <P>The Minister made a reference that puzzled me and I should be glad to have clarification. He referred to an increase of pension of 45/- a week in respect of a prescribed female relative where the pensioner is so incapacitated as to require full-time care and attention. The Minister said that this increase will be payable where a prescribed female relative with a reasonably good employment record specifically gives up employment to look after the pensioner. I know of instances where female relatives have never engaged in good employment or in any type of employment because of the fact that they were obliged to devote all of their lives to the care of a disabled relative or aged parent. I would ask the Minister to clarify as to whether such persons would qualify for the additional contribution. If it is confined to those who are compelled to give up employment for the purpose of caring for a relative, hardship may be caused in cases, which may not be numerous but which undoubtedly exist, where from the time <Col N="1465" /> that they would otherwise become eligible for employment persons are obliged because of domestic circumstances to remain at home in order to care for a disabled relative or aged parent. I ask the Minister to reply specifically to that point.</P>
    <P>In a recent statement, I was glad to see that the Minister adverted to the necessity for lowering the old age pension qualifying age. The time has come when the age should be in accordance with many of the neighbouring countries. I also feel that there are undue delays in the determination of appeals in the Department. They are dealing with people who are failing in health, many of them drawing close to the end of their days. To them the delays that occur are of considerable importance and people like myself making representations are often disagreeably surprised at the amount of time it takes to make a decision. I understand that inquiries have to be instituted and that certain delays may be encountered, but it has been my impression on many occasions that the delays are too long. If the Minister could expedite the decisions of the officials in granting these pensions it would be a step in the right direction.</P>
    <P>I have no further comment to make except to welcome this measure of relief for social welfare classes which the people have been called on to pay since the enactment of the Budget. They have been paying for these reliefs in increased taxation to meet, in part, the demands of the social welfare recipients. The people have been paying, and we are merely asking that the moneys which have been collected and which will be collected in time to come will be devoted towards easing the lot of those of our people who should be the first charge on us.</P>
    <P>What has been done is somewhat of a relief but it is scarcely sufficient to bring our social welfare code into line with that operating in the neighbouring island and in Europe. We have lagged behind in our consideration of those people who in their time have given so much to the country and to whom the country owes so much in their declining years. We hope that the work <Col N="1466" /> of those who are engaged in voluntary effort to improve the position of those people will continue. We know that with the prevalence of emigration, very many of our old people find they no longer have the comfort and assistance and home help that perhaps they expected to have in their advancing years. Many of our institutions are overcrowded with unfortunate people who have not families to care for them and the work of these voluntary organisations consists of helping these people. There is no work that is more charitable or more commendable than that being done by these societies in the capital and in the towns throughout the country. Quite often, sudden and unaccountable worsening of the position may occur in a family and some time may elapse before State assistance becomes available. It is gratifying to know there is a growing consciousness among our people of the necessity for doing, on a voluntary or personal basis, work of this kind and these people are to be highly commended for the work they are performing. It is hoped this measure will assist the categories it is intended to help to combat the increased demands on them in the ever-increasing cost of the necessaries of life. The claims which these classes make on our community are small, and I hope the increases will assist them in having an easier time at the end of their lives.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. J. Fitzgerald Mr. J. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Like the previous speaker, I also welcome the increased benefits provided in this Bill. We can assure the Minister we will grant his request and give speedy and favourable consideration to the Bill in the Seanad. I particularly welcome the section that gives those who took part in the War of Independence the benefit that their allowances will, in future, be completely disregarded when assessing their means for old age pension purposes. This was one of the greatest injustices that occurred in the past&mdash; that those people who did so much for the country should, when they were forced to take these pensions, find that those pensions were also taken into consideration in the means tests when they applied for old age pensions. We know unfortunately that their <Col N="1467" /> numbers are dwindling. It is time these people were given the recognition they so rightly deserve.</P>
      <P>While we welcome those increases in the Bill, there is one thing to which I should like to draw the attention of the Minister. It is that when the officials of the Department are investigating applications for pensions or increases in pensions under the social welfare code, it may be possible to speed up those investigations. In many cases great hardships are caused and when public representatives like myself make representations, we find there is undue delay. The hardship is very great on people who are dependent on social services for their well-being. This is particularly so in the case of unemployment assistance recipients. Grave injustice can occur as a result of delays and the over-zealous attention of the inspectors. Perhaps that is the way they are trained but one feels they could deal with the problems in a more humane manner than at present.</P>
      <P>Having said that, I welcome the Bill. I feel we are at last coming to realise the importance of social welfare services in this country, and I hope the trend indicated in this Bill will continue and that old age pensioners and other recipients of social welfare benefits may continue to receive increases and to enjoy the standard of living this country can offer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>We all naturally welcome the increases that the Government are giving in unemployment assistance, to the blind, the disabled, orphans and widows. In the second last paragraph of the Minister's statement, mention is made of the cost. We must, of course, consider the cost, which reaches something like £4½ million in all. I am not unaware of this when I say that, although the 7s 6d increase is welcome, I still feel that the total amount given to these people falls considerably short of basic human requirements. I recognise that in times past it was considered quite enough to give an extra 2s 6d and that the Government have in fact proposed in comparison with past occasions a <Col N="1468" /> reasonably substantial increase. But it is not substantial, I am afraid, in relation to the present cost of living.</P>
      <P>I would like at this juncture to support and amplify what Senator Fitzgerald has just said about the general treatment received by unemployed, blind and old age pensioners. In my experience, the generality of officials dealing with them have shown exemplary behaviour. They are sympathetic and humane. But this only throws into contrast the behaviour of those who bully and verbally maltreat those who are simply trying to get what is their due.</P>
      <P>I do not want to stress this overmuch because I think it is a problem which occurs only in a minority of cases. It is also a problem of which the Minister is aware. I think he and everybody would agree that when benefit of this kind is being given by the State, it should be given with the good manners on which Irish people can in general pride themselves. We tend in human relations to be good, but some of the people in official positions administering this kind of social welfare benefit do not come up to the standard generally applied.</P>
      <P>There is another point in this connection on which I would like to have the Minister's view. It is sometimes said, particularly in the winter, by the elderly going to collect their old age pension that the process of long queuing and long waiting is distressing to them. I do not know whether it would be possible to devise some manner of payment which would not require quite such regular queuing up and waiting. I do not know whether it would be possible to lodge the amount to the credit of the old person in a post office savings account. I recognise that the difficulty there is that the total amount in relation to present costs is so small that little or nothing would be left each week in the account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That brings me to the question of the amount. The amount being given for old age and blind pensions will now be £3 5s. The widows' non-contributory pension will be a shade less, £3 3s 6d. I do not know whether the Minister would like to give us his view as to what proportion of this <Col N="1469" /> £3 5s or £3 3s 6d ought to be spent on rent. In Dublin rents have been pretty steeply rising even for the most primitive houses. We are glad to see the more primitive houses being demolished, but very often they are replaced by houses where the rent is trebled or quadrupled. How much rent can one afford to pay out of £3 5s a week? The true answer would probably be a minus quantity, because the £3 5s is not sufficient in all conscience to provide for the cost of heating, lighting, clothing, food and minor consolations such as tobacco and the occasional visit to the cinema. In fact, in reality out of £3 5s one could afford to pay nothing for rent.</P>
    <P>Some of these old people have the good fortune to be living with their children and living rent free. But even there, I would suggest, they are going to be hard put to it to have what we would call a reasonably human existence on a total expenditure of £3 5s without any expenditure on rent. I suppose all of us here have on occasion been sent on a shopping expedition to a supermarket. We trundle around the basket. We allow ourselves to be tempted by this and that. When we emerge at the end, having done the shopping, it is quite frequent to find we have very little change out of a £5 note, particularly if we have extensive family commitments.</P>
    <P>This is merely food. What are the old age pensioners to do in the supermarket? How much do they spend. Do they go around and spend 7/- or 8/- a day? How much food can you get nowadays, even in the cheaper shops, for 7/- or 8/- a day? If you are spending 8/- a day, you have already spent 56/- out of your 65/-, or if you are a widow out of your 63/6d. I do not want to stress that further. I think everybody would be with me on that, the Minister first amongst them, to recognise that the amount made available by these extra allowances, at a cost to the State of not very much under £5 million, still remains a very small minimal amount.</P>
    <P>I notice that this 7/6d represents an increase roughly of 13 per cent and slightly more for the unemployed because what they are getting now is <Col N="1470" /> slightly less. It should be recognised that there is, as it were, a concealed percentage increase by reason of the fact that the means test is to be raised for old age and blind pensioners to £195 a year and for widows to £182 a year. The increase in the amount of means that these people can have before their pension is stopped means a concealed percentage increase. It would not be quite fair to say we are only giving them a 13 per cent increase. Nevertheless, this House has fresh in its memory of voting of 30 per cent increases to some judges, 40 per cent to others, and 50 per cent to ourselves, 66? per cent to Members of the other House, 200 per cent to the Leader of the Opposition and so on. I have a feeling that even with these increases in social welfare benefits, if they are taken in conjunction with the increases we have voted to the better-off members of the community, including ourselves, the differentials in the class structure of our society have not been narrowed.</P>
    <P>This is something that ought to make us uneasy. We live in a class society in which the gap between the well-to-do and the impoverished is very great. I feel that if we concede such large percentage increases to ourselves and to the others I have mentioned, we must feel a measure of shame at being able to permit increases of only 13 per cent or 15 per cent to the people affected by this Bill.</P>
    <P>I notice that the unemployment assistance rate at the maximum will be £2 11s 6d for a single person, man or woman. How do they live on that? How do we expect them to live? What happens to them? Can we really be content with this rate? I am old enough to remember the days when the old age pension was actually reduced from 10s to 9s I hope those days are gone forever. Are we really so far from them when in 1968 we expect a single unemployed person to live on £2 11s 6d a week and remain fit and actively seeking employment. How much do they pay for rent, for food?</P>
    <P>I think it is with a measure of shame that we look at these figures. The figures for unemployment benefit, of <Col N="1471" /> course, are better because the beneficiary gets £3 5s a week and that is not too much. There is also the means test. If an old age pensioner has £195, less than £4 a week, from some other source, he or she gets no old age pension. I suggest the means test is set at a very low level. It is even lower for the widow. The widow who is &ldquo;passing rich&rdquo; with £182 a year gets no pension. While recognising that the Minister has done something perceptible in raising the means test, something markedly more will have to be done before it can be regarded as a just test if, indeed, it should, and has to be continued.</P>
    <P>On page 6 of the Bill, we have the weekly rates of orphans' contributory pensions. I see that the pension ceases altogether if the orphan has means exceeding £39 10s a year. That is supposed to be enough to enable an orphan to get food and clothing. I think I am right in saying that in an institution the upkeep of such people costs anything between 45s and £3 a week. Yet, the orphan is expected to exist on £39 10s a year with no pension. How he can do so is beyond my comprehension.</P>
    <P>While we welcome the Bill and recognise that the Government have made a real effort and that benefits have increased to perceptibly more than ever before, nevertheless I feel that the class divisions in our society are being heightened by the scale of increases we allow to people at the top like ourselves and the scale of increases we allow at the present time to those at the bottom of the list, to the orphans, the blind, the disabled, the widows and the old age pensioners. We receive a weekly document showing us that we have 53,000 unemployed today in the Republic. The figure for emigration is not so clearly specified but it is hardly less than 20,000 a year and may be as much as 50,000. It is probable that the unemployed who have succeeded in remaining fit and who are of an age still to have spirit, leave the country and seek, even if it is only unemployment benefit, in Britain. I believe they get about £4 10s a week. It is by no means easy to live on that sum but it is <Col N="1472" /> appreciably greater than £2 11s 6d upon which our single unemployed man or woman is expected to live here.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I stress the point that it seems to me that even ameliorating legislation of this kind tends rather, by its failure to go further, to allow the gap between the wealthy and the poor to become larger in this country, a country in which there is a very real social democratic spirit in the sense that class division in many ways is an unnatural thing to the Irish mind. Consequently, perhaps many Senators here today will agree with me that this widening of the differentials between the well-off and the poor or, if you like, the failure to narrow more these differentials is something we regret while welcoming the small step forward represented by this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill in so far as it increases the rates of benefit of various beneficiaries under the social welfare code but I should prefer to see more comprehensive legislation brought in in order to eliminate the many injustices one finds in looking at the operation of these measures in detail. It is sometimes very difficult to explain to a widow who has just a house in a town where the rates are perhaps high and who has no income, that she does not qualify for a widow's pension.</P>
      <P>The entire social welfare code should be made more flexible. We know the plight of farm workers who some years ago, after the war, undertook the practice of conacring land and became self-employed. When these people came to old age pension age, they found they were not entitled to a contributory pension even though they had been insured under the Social Welfare Acts for 20 or 30 years and they received no benefit from the payments they made. That type of thing is wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Lately, I came across a case where a farm worker had three acres of land and became ill in 1953 and because he did not draw the dole in the meantime, he was not qualified to receive a contributory old age pension. Legislation that allows that sort of thing to happen should be amended and the entire <Col N="1473" /> thinking concerning our social welfare system should be brought up to date.</P>
    <P>Regarding old age pensions, I think the practice of the State in taking one-fifth or 20 per cent of the savings of people into account as income when in fact the National Loan pays only 7½ per cent is wrong and should be amended. There are many things that should be changed but unfortunately we cannot do it in this Bill, and so I earnestly ask the Minister to introduce as soon as possible legislation to eliminate the many injustices that the un-privileged section of the community suffer at present. Perhaps we should take a completely new look at all the measures and bring them up to date.</P>
    <P>The old age pension scheme is one that needs deep thought. When poor old people do not, for some reason best known to themselves, apply the very minute they reach the age of 70 but wait until they are 71 or 72, our social welfare inspectors are inclined to view them with the gravest of suspicion. They start digging into bank accounts and all the rest, assuming that these people delayed applying for an old age pension solely to dispose of the enormous wealth they must have put away somewhere or buried since they were 70. They very seldom take into account the low IQ of many of these people and it is disgraceful that simple, elderly persons who, perhaps, through senility are not able to look after their own affairs as well as most, should always get the wrong end of the stick.</P>
    <P>The social welfare officers do not do sufficient for these people. The people employed by the Department of Social Welfare should look upon themselves as being there to help the public, whereas the vast majority of them believe they are appointed for no other reason than to save the State as much as possible by depriving these people of the pensions and assistance to which they would otherwise be entitled. This is a wrong outlook and a wrong attitude, and I often feel that the people working in the Minister's Department must get the benefit of some incentive bonus scheme based on the number of people they knock off qualifying for the various benefits and pensions there are.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1474" /> Since our social welfare benefits and payments are not keeping pace with the cost of living, I would appeal to the Minister to ask, even unofficially, the officers to go softly on the poor and on the needy and meet the situation by not being as conscientious as some of them would appear to be. I welcome the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>My description of this Bill would be the &ldquo;Crumbs from the Table of the Rich&rdquo; Bill. Nobody can suggest that the Bill should be rejected, because it is improving in a slight fashion the present terrible position, but at the same time, in the year 1968, it is a sad reflection on society that an increase of 2/6 a week is being given in certain instances in respect of children. I ask the Minister or any Member of this House what he considers 2/6 will purchase at the present time. It is beyond denial that the cost of the bare necessaries of life are higher in Ireland than in any other European country, and if we make an assessment of the increases which are being given here now, we find they do nothing more than keep people on a subsistence level.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If anybody doubts the cost of foodstuffs and the exploitation of our people by the processing industries and by the distribution groups in this country, he has only to walk into the supermarket in any town in Ireland and compare the prices there with those that are in operation here in the city. Within the last week I had a typical example shown to me in respect of what could not be described as a luxury, marmalade. A jar of marmalade costing 1/10 in a Dublin supermarket will cost 2/2 in Galway or in any of the rural provincial towns. The argument has been put forward many times that foodstuffs are dearer in Dublin. The Members who have that view should get rid of it very fast. Foodstuffs in any part of Ireland are far too dear at the present time. When we expect the weaker and poorer sections of the community to make do on the miserable allowances which are being given to them, it is&mdash;perhaps it is wrong to use the word in the circumstances, but it is one that is used very often in the country and it may be <Col N="1475" /> understood&mdash;unchristian, if that means anything at all at the present time.</P>
    <P>The plight of the weaker sections of our community is discussed very much these days, and that is a hopeful sign. Especially when one sees a debate among our younger people on our responsibility towards the weaker sections, it gives hope that at least in their minds the intention is to alter the position in a radical fashion. Apart from the young people who have consciences in this regard, many of the older generation constantly deplore the fact that the old people, the sick, and so forth, are being so badly treated. The Minister is aware of that opinion expressed by members of his own Party in this House and by supporters all over the country. It is a mystery, therefore, with that feeling amongst the community, that the Minister does not take advantage of it and utilise his position in the Government to levy taxation specifically for the purpose of helping those who are less well off. I have not the slightest doubt that people who smoke, and smoke excessively, would gladly pay the extra money in taxation if they knew that it was going specifically towards social welfare.</P>
    <P>The Minister remarked on the extra cost involved over a year in giving increases. I do not think the public are too worried about the taxation in a matter of this nature. If people see £1 million extra going specifically to old age pensioners or to people who are unemployed through no fault of their own, they are prepared to pay for that. If taxation is raised for the purpose of achieving that objective and, at the same time, a grant for Potez is included in the same taxation, people are entitled to grouse and react bitterly. When we are dealing with a subject of this nature it should be clearly understood what the money is being raised for. If that could sink into the heads of the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Social Welfare, I believe the position with regard to social welfare benefits and allowances could be changed overnight. I hope something like that is under consideration at the moment.</P>
    <P>Another point which was brought to <Col N="1476" /> my attention was in connection with the facilities made available for old age pensioners who travel in buses. I gather that an old age pensioner has to produce his pension book in order to satisfy the conductor that he is entitled to travel at the expense of the State. I do not think that is proper procedure. Apart from anything else, these pension books are very awkward, and these people are being asked to carry them around in order to produce them on the buses. Surely there could be some kind of check, or a small badge could be issued, or a little certificate that could be produced by the old age pensioners? There is also the fact that if he has to carry around his pension book, it gets into a very ragged condition in a very short time. So, from the point of view of hygiene also, it would be better if he could produce a little certificate which would meet the requirements.</P>
    <P>On the question of unemployment assistance and unemployment benefit, I want to make my position clear on something with which I am quite familiar. In certain parts of the country, bad and all as it is to have to look for unemployment assistance, it is worse when you find that the officials of the Department go out of their way to strip away the dignity of these unfortunate people. I know for a fact that they have to wait in the rain, that they have to stand outside doors, and that they will not even be told when to come to collect this money to which they are fully entitled. This is due to the petty tyranny of the officials, and I want to make it clear to the Minister that it should not be tolerated.</P>
    <P>Another point which is not dealt with here but to which it is no harm to refer because it comes under social welfare generally is the question of making allowances available from the State where there is a disability in a family. I realise from the White Paper provision is being made for the payment of allowances to near relatives of old age pensioners where the pensioner is incapacitated or needs attention. There are many people not in receipt of old age pensions who need attention. They may be 60 or 69 years of age and be incapacitated from arthritis <Col N="1477" /> or something like that. There is no provision for them except in the disability allowances through the local authorities, and perhaps, after a very close examination, some additional home assistance. I do not think that is the right way to look after people in this category, and the Minister should have that matter examined as well with a view to making the same provision for such people as is made available for old age pensioners. The scope of the scheme should be widened.</P>
    <P>I hope that what we have heard recently about a new deal in the field of social welfare is not &ldquo;around the corner&rdquo; over the next 12 or 18 months, but that we will hear something about it during the Summer Recess.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The fact that this Bill contains benefits greater than those which have been given in previous Bills is a reflection of the growing social conscience which nowadays penetrates all classes and all Parties. Particularly over the past three years, there has been a growing recognition of our backwardness in many respects in social welfare and there is a willingness to accept an acceleration of the growth of the burden of taxation in order to provide for those members of the community who are most in need.</P>
      <P>Our social welfare system still has many serious defects. Quite apart from the inadequacies in absolute terms of the benefits given at every level, and under every heading, there is a multiplicity of means tests incorporated into the system. In recent years the Government have attempted to use the limited resources available and to concentrate the benefits of those resources to help the people most in need. Further complications in the means test system make it even more objectionable to the public generally than it has been hitherto.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We also have persistence in the practice of postponing the benefits announced until the following August or January in the case of social assistance or social insurance, the mechanism of announcing increased benefits in the Budget, which the Government are unable or unwilling to pay in the year <Col N="1478" /> in question. It is in no way convincing to suggest that this occurs because of administrative difficulties. That simply is not acceptable as an explanation of a postponement of up to nine months. It is a political device to enable the Government to announce that they are giving something which they are unwilling or unable to give in that year. It is also a bad practice because it preempts part of the finance of the coming Budget. It is a practice which we should endeavour to terminate as soon as possible.</P>
    <P>Another defect is a lack of graded benefits related to the income of the recipients. This is something which I have raised here year after year, and it is something which is now supported by the Labour Party. The Minister accepts it in principle. It does not seem to me that there are enormous difficulties about the introduction of such a scheme. It exists everywhere in the world except in Ireland, Britain and Iceland, and in Britain it is being introduced in relation to retirement pensions.</P>
    <P>So long as we have a system under which the amount paid out in benefits is tied to the amount which the Government feel they can properly exact from the lowest paid ordinary male worker outside agriculture, so long will our social welfare system be inadequate. It is completely wrong that the level of benefit, even for the higher-paid workers, should be tied in this way. It is not reasonable that a higher-paid worker, who would be willing and able to pay a higher contribution, should be deprived of the opportunity to insure himself in this way because of the inability or unwillingness of the Minister's Department to introduce a scheme of graded benefits and contributions such as exists in other countries. After pressure from the Opposition, the Minister said he was willing to introduce this change. When will he introduce this change? When will the £1,200 limit on non-manual workers be eliminated? It is an anachronism and a defect in our system.</P>
    <P>There is no convincing reason for this limit. It is a carry-over from a period when a certain class system was accepted but such class system is not <Col N="1479" /> now accepted. Therefore, I ask the Minister the question: &ldquo;When will we have a comprehensive insurance scheme?&rdquo; More and more clerical workers, for example, have earnings past this limit, without entering into a reasonable condition of affluence, but, when they pass this salary limit, they are deprived of benefits which they hitherto enjoyed and, in this way, are discriminated against probably because, in fact, of an attitude of mind which originally meant to discriminate in their favour. When will this be done away with?</P>
    <P>The inadequacy of the home assistance scheme, and its patchiness and unevenness because of the different attitudes of different local authorities, is another serious defect in the existing system which I think was also referred to in the Dáil on the debate on this Bill. Whether this could best be tackled by a uniform national assistance scheme or whether the present scheme could be improved to provide a better and more humane service, I do not know with certainty, but certainly we need to have the Minister's views as to what he will do about improving the home assistance system.</P>
    <P>Throughout the whole social welfare schemes, there is, as other speakers have said, a lack of humanity in the approach to the whole problem. In most cases, the people concerned in the schemes are human in their attitude within the limits of the enforcement of the bureaucratic system which is enforced as rigidly here if not more so, as in other areas. The problem is the inhumanity of the system which is still the poor law system: it has not changed in any serious respect. There have been improvements in the amount paid but the attitude of mind which underlies the scheme and the bureaucratic control exercised to protect the State from the mis-spending of one shilling or one pound is still a poor law condition. Other countries have departed from that and we should do likewise. These, then, are all defects of our present social welfare arrangements, other than and beyond the inadequacy of the amounts paid.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1480" /> We have been told that the Third Programme will contain a social programme&mdash;a serious gap in the Second Programme. Can the Minister give us any indication of what his Department have in mind, in relation to the matters I have dealt with, so far as the Third Programme is concerned? It has widely been rumoured that many new developments are under way or, perhaps, that there is new thinking in his Department. Some time ago, I had occasion to suggest the contrary; I said I saw no evidence of that yet. However, I was corrected by people in a position to know who said there was a change of thinking in that Department, although no signs had yet reached the public. I am prepared to believe it but I must say I should like to witness some overt signs.</P>
    <P>The absence of a social programme in the Second Programme for Economic Expansion was a serious social and economic defect. In that Programme, a certain amount was set aside for social purposes but there was no indication as to how it would be spent. The share in the national output for that purpose was inadequate. What has happened is that the Government, prompted by the growing social conscience and public opinion, and prompted, I daresay, also, by the election campaign of 1965 and pressure from the Opposition Party since, have not adhered to the Programme. This unthinking attitude behind the Programme envisaged a reduction in the share of national output to be devoted to social welfare. However, over this period, the amount devoted to social welfare has expanded beyond what was envisaged in the Programme. One of the reasons the burden of taxation has arisen more rapidly than was expected is that this has happened. We welcome this change of heart. However, we deplore the lack of planning which has created this unplanned burden on taxation&mdash;because there was no planning of the social progress to be made in this period. We hope there will be such provision in the Third Programme.</P>
    <P>Instead of throwing in a figure, taken out of a hat, for the amount to be devoted to social welfare&mdash;a figure obviously and clearly inadequate&mdash;we <Col N="1481" /> should seek a fully worked-out plan for development over this four-year period indicating, in broad terms, the amount to be devoted in this period. We should seek a realistic plan which could secure the enthusiastic support of all Parties. Can the Minister tell us what the shape of this social programme will be? Will it be in advance of anything we have had before? How soon shall we see it? Can he tell us anything about it?</P>
    <P>On television, some time ago, the Minister was involved in a discussion on the subject of social welfare during which there was some dispute over figures, over the comparability of figures and the proportion of the amount of national output devoted to social purposes in some countries. To a person not interested in statistics, the debate may have become arid. Although it may have been an arid debate for non-statistical viewers, nevertheless, the point is important. I should like the Minister to move away from the negative position of criticising the figures put forward by other countries purporting to show the amount of national output which we and other countries devote to social welfare and, instead, to tell us the true comparative figures.</P>
    <P>It is easy to pick holes in figures supplied by other countries but what we require is the true comparative figure. The holes the Minister picked in such comparisons did not look alarming. When he has made the appropriate adjustments in respect of coverage in this country, and in other countries, can he show us the percentage of our output, in terms comparable with those of other countries, that is devoted to social welfare? The figures he put forward, and which he rejected, were derived from the published data of OECD statistics which are supposed to be comparable. The statisticians of OECD have tried to render national data comparable both in terms of the national output figure and the social welfare figure related to it. He says they made mistakes and that the comparison is inadequate. What, therefore, is the true comparison?</P>
    <P>When all the pedantic changes have been made, we stand well behind other <Col N="1482" /> countries. I do not think the Minister can stand pedantically on this issue. We stand well behind other countries at the same or closely-comparable standard of living. The Minister is trying to hide that fact. I hope the problem will be faced up to fully in this Third Programme. I hope the justification put to the Irish public for increases in taxation that will have to occur under the Third Programme in order to improve our social welfare will be the simple fact that we are lagging behind other countries. We must face and state this fact. If the Minister pretends we are not lagging behind, he will never mobilise public opinion behind him in seeking priority for the major task of his Department, which is the improvement of social welfare in this country.</P>
    <P>One other point worth referring to is the institutional bias of our whole social welfare system in which, both in health services and social welfare generally, we tend to solve problems by putting people in institutions, where they are less happy than they would be at home and cost much more to look after. This is true as regards the treatment of children who are left without parents. It is true of old people and it is true of the whole system of health services, true of the Voluntary Health Insurance Scheme, and of the whole social welfare system where there is this bias directed towards institutional treatment which is more expensive and less satisfactory.</P>
    <P>Nothing has been done to get away from this. In the Fine Gael &ldquo;Just Society&rdquo; policy in 1965, one of the best thought-out and most useful parts of it was&mdash;and I can say this because I had nothing to do with this particular part&mdash;the part dealing with the proposal for domiciliary service, a home help service, designed to provide assistance to old people in their own homes rather than have them sent to institutions. If we are going to develop anything of this kind to help people in their own homes and reduce the burden on our institutions, it must have the real welfare of the people at heart. We are going to need more and more trained people and the Minister must direct his attention to this fact. <Col N="1483" /> We are turning out trained social workers in substantial numbers. I come here today from a conferring of degrees at UCD at which there were scores of trained social workers receiving their degrees. As they were receiving their degrees, a man beside me whispered to me: &ldquo;Most of them will be off to Northern Ireland or Britain in the morning because there are no jobs for them here.&rdquo; This is true.</P>
    <P>Many such workers go to the North of Ireland where they are welcomed and where there are many jobs for them. There are many times the number of jobs in that one-third of our country than there are down here. What is being done here? This need for trained workers exists but the Minister's Department does nothing to see that they are employed, and so far little or no progress has been made in this matter, beyond possibly some minor improvements, and the bulk of trained workers are still exported. Scores of them are required here but there exists this extraordinary bias against employing trained people. Whether it is in the Minister's Department, in local authorities, or in hospitals, I do not know, but there is this extraordinary bias against employing trained people. Perhaps they think it would be more expensive to employ trained people rather than untrained people but this is false economy.</P>
    <P>The Minister must look into this matter because there is a possibility for a real improvement in the humanisation of our social welfare services and in providing the kind of service which should be provided for our people, such as an adequate number of probation officers for the young. The people are there and it is not the case that we are short of them but they are being forced out of the country.</P>
    <P>Perhaps people think that it would cost more if they employed trained people but in fact it would save the country more because where people are appointed to help other people in their own homes, then there would be a saving through a saving in institutional costs. This is a matter to which the Minister must give attention and he <Col N="1484" /> must not allow scores of young people to be exported at the cost of a continuing low level of services in our social welfare system.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>To the Fine Gael Party, money means nothing and they can conjure it out of the moon or from the pages of that much bedevilled document, the &ldquo;Just Society&rdquo;, which we hear so much about. However, I recall that when Fine Gael were for the only time in their history the Government of this part of Ireland, as a single Party, and they needed money, they were the only Party ever in Government to cut the old age pension in order to find&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>How many years ago was that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the Fine Gael Party was founded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It ill becomes Fine Gael speakers to talk about neglect or slackness or slowness on the part of this Government in regard to social welfare. Certainly it ill becomes Senator Garret FitzGerald to talk about the increases in social welfare now being a reflection of the growing social conscience of the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I said &ldquo;the country&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Long before this growing social conscience of the country or of the Government of which Senator FitzGerald speaks, was referred to, the Government had instituted the scheme of social services which we have today. If the Senator will consult the records of legislation of the Oireachtas, going back to the time when Fine Gael were a Government by themselves, he will find that there was very little in the line of social services to talk about. It was not a case of waiting for a growing social conscience to institute the ameliorative services for the benefit of the people; it was a case that when the Government set out to do business in 1932, on the first occasion the Fianna Fáil Party took over Government, they began to legislate the charter of social services which has grown to such an <Col N="1485" /> extent that any Irishman can be proud of the progress made.</P>
      <P>We need not take second place to any country in Europe because in some ways we are ahead of some of those countries. I heard references by Senator Sheehy Skeffington, Senator McDonald and Senator McQuillan to unemployment assistance. That is a case in point. Until the Fianna Fáil Government took action in the matter there was no concern whatever for an unemployed man who was not covered by some type of insurance. It was the Fianna Fáil Government who introduced the principle of assistance for people who were unemployed and who were trying to secure work and who were not covered by any insurance stamp.</P>
      <P>The sneers directed at the amount of money available for unemployment assistance were not worthy of the people who made them and not worthy of any of the people who addressed similar sneers at what they described as the total inadequacy of the amount of money available for these benefits and the services generally. We all know that we have a good way to go yet before any of us can be satisfied that the whole code of social services is as good as we would like it to be or as good as we hope it will be by the time the Government are finished with the scheme for amplifying social assistance and social payments. It is capable of great improvements and the Minister has been devoting his attention to a review of the whole code. We are confident that when the time comes, he will come forward with proposals for the improvements we expect and which everybody who gives any thought to the matter desires. However, to think that this can be done overnight or that money can be manufactured by wishing it to be so is so silly as not to warrant any further comment. If it were that easy to do, it would have been done long ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One thing I would commend to all critics of the social welfare code and the alleged inadequacies of the payments is that if I remember rightly, and I am not much good at statistics&mdash; I leave that to Senator FitzGerald&mdash;it was once stated that some 30 per cent <Col N="1486" /> are keeping 70 per cent in this country. If that be correct, then the 30 per cent certainly deserve not to have their backs completely broken. They are doing pretty well by the community as it is. Those who are paying their taxes, who are smoking and paying more, having a drink and paying more, paying income tax and not grumbling, these are certainly doing their share and are willing to do it, but they must be given the opportunity to take it in slices and not all in one bulk or that will break their backs entirely.</P>
    <P>When Senator McQuillan talked about the proposals for the increases in the old age pensions being mixed up in the same Budget with grants for hotels, he showed how little was his understanding of the true position. Without these hotels and without the people who work in them&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>He said &ldquo;Potez&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;without the people who are enterprising enough to start them and without business and prosperity this 30 per cent could not afford to pay the money for the services we are talking about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>May I defend the Senator; he said Potez, not hotels.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>That, again, shows how little understanding the Senator has of the actual position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the workers there?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>That shows how little understanding the Senator has of the position. If he had any sense, he should know that there is a great potential in that factory and we hope that some day, despite the jeers and sneers of Senator McQuillan and others, and despite the men who wanted boiling water for their tea at a critical time, that factory will go into production.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that why there are no planes being made. I never heard that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Remember, it is not all Irish money that is in it either. The people who started it put <Col N="1487" /> their money into it as a guarantee of good faith and there is no reason why that factory should not&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Take off.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;deliver the goods. And if the Senator has a talk with them out there, they will tell him about the boiling water for their tea. Senator Sheehy Skeffington talked about the 50,000 unemployed, but he forgot the breakdown of that figure. If I remember rightly, there are only 7,000 or 8,000 genuinely unemployed people, people capable of and looking for work, in that figure. This was extended in recent years to small farmers and fishermen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Senator give the authority for the 7,000 or 8,000 unemployed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Go and look at the figures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>What figures?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>These figures Senator Sheehy Skeffington quoted from, the figures issued every week. Have a look at them and at the breakdown.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I have looked at the breakdown.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not need to talk statistics to Senator Garret FitzGerald; he can mesmerise me with them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>But the Senator is not mesmerising me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I can read good, plain print. If the Senator looks at the plain print, he will see the breakdown. Senator Sheehy Skeffington ought to give all the facts. He ought not to make the bland statement that there are 53,000 unemployed as if there were 53,000 men and women capable of working and of being absorbed tomorrow morning if jobs were available for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>What is wrong with them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1488" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I refer the Senator also to the figures. With regard to the kind of mournful attitude adopted by Senator Sheehy Skeffington about there being only £2 10s a week unemployment assistance here and £4 10s a week unemployment assistance in Britain and Northern Ireland, the Senator knows very well the explanation for that. He knows very well that you cannot do everything overnight. He knows very well that you cannot accomplish miracles overnight. You have to go slowly. We have been going fairly rapidly. The pace is increasing but you cannot go so rapidly as to destroy the good work done in the past, thereby wrecking the economy. In due time we hope our social services will be as good as, if not better than, those in neighbouring countries. If the Government continue to pursue the enlightened social policy they have adopted since they were first elected in 1932, I have no doubt whatsoever that we will be in the forefront of other European countries. Might I say for the benefit of Senator Sheehy Skeffington&mdash;I am sure he will be very surprised to hear it&mdash;that, if he looks at the history of these social services and the dates on which they were introduced, he will find that the people's republic of Ireland was in advance of the people's republics in other parts of Europe in relation to at least two or three of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>We are providing in this Bill the increases announced in the Budget in April last. Some of those increases will operate in August and others in January next. It seems to be the general practice now year after year to stage these increases and the impression is being left on the minds of a great many people&mdash;the recipients, of course, are only too sadly aware of the facts&mdash;that the social welfare classes are getting a number of increases every year, an increase in April, an increase in August and a further increase in January.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Senator ever ask any of them? They know damn well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>The people who are <Col N="1489" /> getting the increases know damn well but the ordinary citizens, who do not read too carefully, are left with the impression that here is a beneficent Government giving increases every few months to the social welfare classes. People have actually said that to me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>They must have been from Cork.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the impression that is being left on people's minds. I do not accept that this delay is due to administrative difficulties. We all know administrative difficulties can be overcome, where there is a will to overcome them. I regard this as so much political capital. Tomorrow, the <i>Irish Press</i> will blazen forth headlines:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Increases for social welfare classes passed by the Seanad&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>So will the <i>Irish Times.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>And, maybe, the <i>Independent</i> and, maybe, even the <i>Cork Examiner.</i>  People will just glance at the headlines, and say: &ldquo;Oh, they are getting more: good.&rdquo; Then they will read again next January about, they will assume, a further increase. Next April, there will be another increase, rightly and deservedly, because the value of money is changing. There will be another announcement of a further increase and again people will say: &ldquo;Thank God, we are doing more for the old age pensioners,&rdquo; etc., etc. There will be, if Fianna Fáil are still in power, again this impression of three increases when, in fact, there will be only one. Those are the facts. That is the impression being left with the public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Again the impression is being left that, because of all these increases, these people cannot be too badly off; we are not doing too badly by any of them. Those of us who visit these people in their homes know that the position is both shocking and humiliating. I am humiliated and ashamed when I have to visit these people because I am a member of a society in which this shocking position obtains. Various charitable bodies try to assist these people, and one goes along <Col N="1490" /> with a few bob, which means so much to these people, or a food ticket, and one sees the misery in which they live. It is a scandal and we ought all of us to be ashamed that this could happen in an allegedly Christain country.</P>
    <P>I grant Senator Ó Maoláin that the Government has done a great deal, but let us appreciate that this is not Fianna Fáil money. This is redistribution of income, of your income and my income and the incomes of the rest of the community. This is not charity. This is redistribution of income and the sooner we face up to that fact, and accept it, the better it will be for us all. There is a great deal of merit in Senator McQuillan's suggestion that some effort should be made to identify a particular class in this redistribution of income to the community. It should be brought home to every one of us that when we pay a few pennies extra for tobacco, cigarettes, petrol, or whatever it is, this money will go to assist those most in need. It would be a measure of practical Christianity that we should know why we are paying the money and that it is this money which is doing good for our less well-off brethren.</P>
    <P>Reference was made to the £1,200 limit. I want to return briefly to the pleas I made to the Minister on previous measures. We have had these Bills annually. I plead with him to take a fresh look at the whole social insurance system we have built up in this country. We have done some things&mdash; Senator Ó Maoláin says a lot&mdash;and we have made improvements and the time has come to take a fresh look at the situation. We have this limit, that people in non-manual employment in receipt of over £1,200 per annum go out of insurance. We have made a provision&mdash;and this is an amelioration of the situation&mdash;that they can, if they so wish, continue as voluntary contributors in order to maintain widows' and orphans' insurance. We all know&mdash;we have met tragic instances&mdash;where even though this opportunity was available, people neglected to take this cover and found that the time had gone and perhaps unfortunately they died and their widows then came and said: &ldquo;What about this insurance?&rdquo;, and found that <Col N="1491" /> there was no insurance at all, that she was not insured for widows' and orphans' benefit.</P>
    <P>We are talking about the more needy in our society, and, certainly, people in receipt of unemployment assistance and old age pensions are far worse off than the worker in receipt of £1,200 per annum, but, equally, none of us would suggest that the person with over £1,200 per annum is in such a well-off position that he can afford to make his own arrangements in regard to insurance for his wife and children in the event of his death. We need the State to step in here. We need to give the group assistance&mdash;that is what it is&mdash; the whole community sharing. The limit of £1,200 should be abolished and, at least, people should be kept in insurance and those who have allowed themselves to go out of insurance and who have not opted to maintain the voluntary insurance should be allowed in. In other words, we should share the burden. The people should be allowed to make that provision for that risk by the State insurance system.</P>
    <P>We exclude, as I said, people who are in non-manual employment who are over that limit of £1,200. How &ldquo;non-manual&rdquo; comes into it, I am not very clear. I think that a clerk in receipt of £1,205 is as much in need of this sort of cover as the mechanic or electrician or person engaged in what we regard as manual work, who is allowed to stay in the insurance scheme.</P>
    <P>There is another anomaly at which we might take a fresh look. It affects persons in what we term permanent pensionable employment who are exempted from social insurance. This is something we inherited from the British but which the British have abandoned long since. Such persons are not covered by the ordinary insurance scheme. I think they should be. Maybe many of them may object to paying insurance stamps but it is better all round that they should be brought into insurance which would give them cover for widows and orphans and for the old age pension, and there is the consideration that by their contributions <Col N="1492" /> they would help to support the fund. There would be a steady income to the fund which would in turn help to provide, I hope, better benefits for those who are unfortunate enough to lose their employment and it would provide cover for widows and orphans in the event of the contributor's death. The system we have inherited and maintained, even though the British have abandoned it, has led to some strange anomalies.</P>
    <P>I have a problem to which I cannot find an easy solution. People who were promoted into supervisory posts and who before promotion were fully insured workers contributing to social welfare find when they are promoted that they are exempted&mdash;the more correct term would be excluded&mdash;from social welfare. They have to join a superannuation fund for which they pay&mdash;the amount varies according to age&mdash;£1 or 35s a week and, despite their paying that amount, end up on retirement worse off financially than they would have been if they had never been promoted after paying fantastically high contributions to a superannuation fund in the meantime. This is the sort of anomaly created by this situation. The employer concerned says: &ldquo;We will step in and we will provide that the person promoted will not be worse off at 65 years of age than if he had not been promoted. We will supplement his income.&rdquo; They supplement it to what it would have been if the person had never been promoted and in spite of the fact that he had to pay £1 to 35s per week in the intervening years. That is a ridiculous situation. It is, as I have said, one of the anomalies produced by this completely out-of-date income limit and, again, the question of exempting what we term people in full-time pensionable employment.</P>
    <P>Another anomaly produced is that such people who live until 70 years of age find that other people are allowed free travel because they are old age pensioners, whereas they, who probably have as low an income or a lower income are not entitled to free travel. It happens, for example, in CIE. A person who while in employment had certain travel facilities finds on retirement that the facilities are severely <Col N="1493" /> limited or disappear. If he lives until 70 years of age, he has to pay his fare whereas a person who never worked at all on CIE has free travel because he is an old age pensioner, rightly&mdash;I do not complain about this&mdash;but the man who has devoted his whole working life to public transport finds that he has not got free transport on reaching 70 years of age. That is something that irritates the persons concerned very much. It is all right to think of people who can run cars and who do not need to travel on buses. I am talking about the person who is in retirement for five to ten years and finds his standard of living continually being reduced, who finds that at that level his income is as low as that of an old age pensioner&mdash;and that is low enough&mdash;and that the old age pensioner, simply because he has an old age pension book, has free travel while he has not.</P>
    <P>There was a tragically touching instance the other day. A chap like that who had retired and is living now where there is no rail service&mdash;he is not an old age pensioner because he was not an insured worker&mdash;finds he cannot afford to pay the fare on the bus to come to Dublin for medical treatment, whereas if he had never worked for CIE and were an old age pensioner, he would be entitled to free travel. This is the type of anomaly thrown up by the system we have. We have built up improvements but I suggest that we have got to take a fresh look at the situation.</P>
    <P>May I go back to my first point about the general inadequacy of the social welfare benefits and assistance we have got? Senator Ó Maoláin made the point that we have made improvements and I acknowledge that. He also expressed the hope that eventually we should reach the levels obtaining in other western European countries. I find this a bit difficult to accept because if I can read the signs at all, the gap is widening&mdash;the gap between the level of social welfare benefits being provided by us and by other countries. Despite the improvements, the gap is widening all the time and if we can continue as we are, I cannot see any prospect in this Government's lifetime of closing the gap.</P>
    <P>If we continue as we are, the gap <Col N="1494" /> will continue to widen and this is a deplorable situation. Senator Ó Maoláin made the point that the money comes from the people who have the money&mdash;that it is redistribution. I agree, but in the same Budget providing for these increases we provide for reliefs to surtax payers at a cost of several hundred thousand pounds. This redistribution would be better utilised by helping the people most in need, those covered by social insurance, by our social welfare code.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>All in the House welcome the increases that are being given and naturally we all urge that more should be provided. We are aware of the great amount required to meet even a modest improvement. Indeed more could be done by channelling some luxury taxes to the aid of social welfare recipients. In this Budget as in former ones, the luxury taxes have been dealt with far too lightly. These taxes could have made a considerable increase in social welfare scheme improvements.</P>
      <P>However, one of the real sources of increase here is to get people off the unemployment register and that can be provided by retraining and re-employment of such people. It is well therefore that we should look at the figures involved today. We can see that the level of unemployment assistance for a married man runs at about £5 a week. We all realise how low that is but if we capitalise that figure, it gives us £250 a year. This, during a lifetime, would be equivalent approximately to about 15 times its present value, or about £4,000. What this means is that it is financially profitable for the State to spend up to £4,000 to get an individual off the unemployment register. Indeed it would be worth more than that because if we spent more than £4,000 to create a new job, that means that a person taken off the register would be in gainful employment until he retired or died.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is the type of hard cold look at the situation we do not seem to be taking sufficiently seriously. When we were dealing with the Shannon Free Airport Industrial Estate recently, we found that even at present industrial prices, the rate put into the giving of <Col N="1495" /> employment to each worker there was £2,000, of which the State contributed more than £1,000. Those figures, or even considerably higher in more intensive capital industries, still make it good sense to help those on the unemployment register to get employment. This is especially important today when the unskilled workers&mdash;you would hardly call them unskilled&mdash;the people displaced by machines, are really the most deserving cases in our community because they have given good service, dependable, reliable, honest, down through the years and now at the end of their days, find that one of those machines comes in and makes so many of them redundant. It may be one of those supermarkets, one of those self-service stores or amalgamations of old-established businesses in our cities, all of which result in the creation of a considerable amount of unemployment.</P>
    <P>We should try to achieve much more co-ordination between the Department of Social Welfare and the Department of Labour so that it would be far quicker to anticipate such redundancies and to see that we have a positive scheme for retraining. It might appear that the cost would be high but as I have shown, they would be low costs, by our standards, to help such people to be retrained.</P>
    <P>Another great source of the increase in the unemployment register is those leaving the land. Many of those in close contact with the land hold that there are far too few trained workers available on the land today. I underline the word &ldquo;trained&rdquo;. Many are leaving but they are not trained for modern agriculture; yet we do not see any real scheme aimed at training such people, making them into the skilled workers who can be absorbed by agriculture today. An effort is required in this direction in the years ahead. There is a great source in agriculture from which to get worthwhile employment at home.</P>
    <P>The only scheme for training those young people to acquire the skills necessary on the land is the most paltry, mini-mouse ever produced, the farm apprenticeship scheme, in which the only incentive is the possibility that <Col N="1496" /> at the end of four years, the apprentices will qualify for an award of £500. If my figures are correct, that award should not be £500 but should be nearer to £5,000, especially if it succeeded in getting the people trained to give much useful work at home. This would help to reduce the numbers to be catered for in the unemployment register.</P>
    <P>I wish to support Senator Garret FitzGerald strongly in his plea in respect of domiciliary services and the extension of the great amount of voluntary effort available in the country today. Indeed, good work is being done by them but a great deal more could be done if they were given more resources by the State with less of the penny pinching and a ridiculous overchecking attitude. These are responsible people who have come forward in voluntary organisations and are giving of their time and energy. Therefore, the State should be prepared to trust them almost to the extent of giving them much more of the grant type payment rather than the type of help we are giving them at present.</P>
    <P>We all wish more could be done and we hope that next year there will be a further instalment. If a substantial boost can be given to social welfare by increased luxury taxes in the Budget ahead, I for one would feel very happy to see this done and to see the taxes labelled specifically for this purpose.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. J. Brennan) Joseph Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. J. Brennan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very pleased with the general trend of the debate. Most of the criticism was constructive and useful, the occasional political point being scored, as is to be expected. This is an emotional subject which arouses a good deal of bidding with somebody trying to outdo somebody else. I have always tried to refrain from being influenced in any way by that type of persuasion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the course of my reply, I shall try to answer most of the points made. I have dealt with them already in the Dáil. When talking about social welfare in a general way, there is some thing which must be very obvious to everyone. Recently, when studying the systems in the different European countries, I read a very good booklet produced by one of the Swedish experts <Col N="1497" />&mdash;and Sweden is regarded as the paragon in this field of social welfare. This man starts off by saying that the two pillars on which any form of progress in social welfare in any country must be based are humanitarianism and economic progress. We are not short of humanitarianism here but to find the money and set our priorities right is not so easy.</P>
    <P>If we have been able to reach the stage here where we are disbursing upwards of £80 million in social welfare, it is because our economy has come up in recent years. It has received the attention that enabled us to devote so much to social welfare. We must have regard to channelling money into things which tend further to increase production and expand the economy in the knowledge that it will give greater opportunity to improve social welfare further. It is not only the rates of benefit we want to increase. We can point to some expansion already and, as some Senators indicated, some anomalies. The rates themselves could absorb a lot more money. If I could get another £1,000 million from the Minister for Finance, I could use it in improving the rates alone, not to talk about expansion, that is, if we are to base our payments on the amount necessary to keep a person with no other means in decent comfort.</P>
    <P>We have criteria to guide us in regard to what rates we should pay. We used to boast years ago when we met the increase in the cost of living index, but that is not sufficient guide for us now. On every occasion we have exceeded what would be justified by the increase in the cost of living over the previous year. The better standard of living our people are enjoying today must also be a criterion if we are to bring the weaker sections up to a better standard of living than that they were prepared to accept 30 or 40 years ago, when there was virtually no social welfare. There was a time when old people were expected to become the responsibility of their families and relatives, whom they reared and brought up. I should like to think that family affection is not completely destroyed in this country yet and that most of our old people have good relatives who <Col N="1498" /> cherish what the old people have done for them and who want to see that they enjoy many of the luxuries of life which the few pounds we pay them could not give them.</P>
    <P>Senator Sheehy Skeffington asked what element of the social welfare payments should be devoted to rent. In that respect he has put his finger on a point emphasised by my predecessor, now the Minister for Local Government, some years ago when he gave an increase to what is regarded as the nil means section. He recognised that there is a section of old age pensioners who are in a much worse position than the others. These are the people who have to live alone without any relatives to look after them and to try to exist on what they get from us and from the voluntary social organisations which do so much good. In order to help that section we have done a number of things, in addition to the much-criticised 5/- we gave them over and above the other section. We have also come to their assistance by providing free electricity, free travel and free radio and television licences. These are things giving them a comfort they might not provide for themselves even if they got extra money. I regard them all as a step in the right direction.</P>
    <P>Senator Garret FitzGerald questioned the figures I gave on television recently. I did not merely stick a pin into a paper and produce figures substantially correct. I hope I pointed out clearly the fundamental differences in the different countries with which comparisons are sought to be drawn but which are not comparable by any means. First, in each country there are three sets of basic statistics which in themselves can be contradictory. We have a comparison of the percentage of the gross national product devoted to social welfare, the percentage of taxable revenue used for this purpose and we have the percentage of the national income devoted to it. All three throw up different percentages, some of which are very favourable to us and others of which are not. But in all three the comparisons can be wrong because each country regards social welfare in a different way. Many of the European countries have included the salaries, <Col N="1499" /> pensions and retirement allowances of the Civil Service, the police and even the army in their social welfare figures. Others have included their entire expenditure on health as part of social welfare.</P>
    <P>Social Welfare is a very wide field if you cast your net wide enough. I might be justified in giving the amount we spend on free education, on our health services and on our Garda and Civil Service pensions. By that way we could bring our figure up to a tremendous percentage of the gross national product. Even as it is at present, these figures compare quite favourably with those of any other country. Those familiar with the Convention recently signed at the ILO Conference will readily admit that the European countries found that we easily measured up to the minimum standard required before we could subscribe to the Convention. I think we considerably exceeded the requirements which, one might say, were not so wonderful but certainly, as regards basic requirements, they are available here more than in many other countries.</P>
    <P>I have been questioned on what I am doing regarding examining the problem generally and, as I have said so often, the one thing that surprised me most is that when people compare the present six countries of the EEC and our own as regards social security, we compare so favourably. Our position is such that the general scheme of social welfare here will not need to be changed; we merely need to build it up and expand it where required. Basically, it is as good as any other country's and better than most. I know the things to which I should like to pay immediate attention and those to which I hope to give attention in the not far distant future, provided the economic situation continues to move rapidly enough to enable me to get the money to do it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the Minister gets away from the figures, as he seems to be doing, could he give us any comparison with figures related either to national income, tax revenue or gross national product?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1500" />
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>The figures have been quoted in television and in other places. I have the figures from the publication known as &ldquo;The Cost of Social Security&rdquo; published by the International Labour Office. This booklet is in the Library and available to everybody. I think it is also procurable from the Stationery Office. It gives the different sets of figures related to gross national product, tax revenue and national income. Taking the one most commonly used, gross national product, you find that Ireland jointly shares tenth place with Luxembourg among the 16 countries quoted. However we argue about the way in which we may not be comparable as regards the different elements included by different countries to get these percentages, we rate tenth in the comparison made of 16 nations. It has been said that we are at the bottom of the scale but that is not correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister quote the table to which he is referring?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is another comparison which is even more interesting than the actual present day figures in that table. It is the one showing the rapid rise&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>What table is this?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>There are three tables quoted by the ILO publication. The one to which I am referring is the one dealing with the percentage of gross national product which gives Austria as 33.5 per cent in 6th place. I hope the Senator does not wish me to give all of them: Germany's figure is 8.8 per cent (15th); France, 33.9 per cent (joint 7th); Belgium, 31 per cent (12th); Luxembourg 33.3 per cent (joint 10th). That is exactly the same percentage as our own. Italy's figure is 65.5 (3rd) and Sweden 42.3 per cent (5th place)&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry to interrupt but it is important to get this correctly. What is this a percentage of? Is it related to national income or gross national product?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1501" />
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. Eoin Ryan Mr. Eoin Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Eoin Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should listen to the answers to the questions he puts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>Social welfare as a percentage of the gross national product.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Thirty three and one-third per cent?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes. I am quoting the increases from 1950 to 1963. I said quite explicitly that the rate of increase was much more spectacular than the actual percentage. The actual percentage for different years is also given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what we asked for.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall quote you the other three also if you wish, the percentage of tax revenue&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>No. What I am asking for is a comparison of social welfare or transfer payments with either gross national product or national income.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>The booklet I referred to gives the figures from 1950 to 1963 and it gives the rate of increase.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not asking for the rate of increase. The Minister keeps on dodging the question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>I can give the entire table if you wish but I do not think the Seanad would wish that. The 1963 figure is 9.3 per cent for Ireland&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Of what?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>Expenditure on social security expressed as a percentage of gross national product. The figure for Italy is 13.9 per cent&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>A country with the same standard of living as ourselves which is the only valid comparison and it is spending 50 per cent more than we are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1502" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has a habit of doing this sort of thing, putting questions and trying to get answers during the Minister's speech. I think that is most unfair. If the Minister wishes to reply, he should be allowed to do so without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall now desist; I have got the answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan) Acting Chairman (Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, without interruption from either side.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to go back to what I regard as the most important thing, the rate of increase in the past ten years. This is something to which we should pay more attention. As I said before, if we make the same rate of progress with social welfare, we shall compare very favourably with any country in the world&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We might eventually catch up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>Provided Fianna Fáil remain in power. Everybody knows statistics can create a very unreal picture. I am not defending our percentages on that basis but one has only to glance at the figures for Sweden and Italy and some other countries that we know to appreciate the position. Sweden is the outstanding country for social welfare in Europe but their percentage of gross national product does not show them to be any better than Italy or many other countries which, in fact, are considerably better. Again, it is a matter of the elements used in computing what is social welfare. These are not true comparisons. The very booklet in which they are published states this. It says:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Furthermore, differences between the social, economic and political developments and structures of the different countries make for differences in the nature and degree of social protection required; consequently, the relative importance attached to individual branches of <Col N="1503" /> social security often differs from country to country. For example, in one country the emphasis may be on sickness insurance and in another on pensions. As the development of the social security system has not reached its final stage and the cost elements for the various social security branches differ, the financial data presented in the present volume are not on their own sufficient for an evaluation of the efforts made in the different countries in the field of social security. In addition the cost of protection against a given contingency varies with the incidence of the contingency, for instance, a country with a high level of unemployment and in which large sums are spent on unemployment protection, or a country which has been hit by severe epidemics and has thus incurred heavy expenditure on health services, cannot be considered more advanced in social security than&mdash; other things being equal&mdash;another country in which the total cost of social security forms a smaller percentage of the national income, but solely because the level of unemployment has been lower or the health situation has been more favourable.</P>
    <P>International comparisons are relatively easy to make when they relate to countries with similar systems of social security and similar economic, social and political structures. The inquiries of the ILO, however, are universal in their coverage, so that comparability between countries is rendered more difficult.</P>
    <P>In relation to Table 2 the introduction includes the following warning:</P>
    <P>Furthermore, it should be stressed that, even if the figures in principle are calculated according to the United Nations System of National Accounts, there are great variations between the countries regarding the quality of the basic data, methods of estimating the various elements entering into the calculations, etc. The figures are also often subject to adjustments which sometimes prove extensive. The figures in this table should, therefore, be interpreted with <Col N="1504" /> caution. In addition, as mentioned above, it is difficult, on the basis of these figures, to draw conclusions regarding, for example, the relative standard of protection in the various countries, since such conclusions cannot be drawn from financial data alone.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The relative importance attaching to&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not here to argue with the Senator but to state the facts, outstanding facts, that may not be obvious from statistics. It is incontrovertible that reaching in the past few years the magnificent figure of almost £80 million in disbursements on social welfare is an accomplishment for a small country which at the same time is struggling to develop, a country that has a relatively small percentage of its entire population insured, that has to pay £45 million out of the Exchequer on the social assistance side. When we compare ourselves with countries which have compulsory insurance for every individual under a contributory scheme, that makes our position all the more favourable. If there is one thing more than anything else on which we have made great progress, it is social welfare. Nobody can contradict that for one moment.</P>
      <P>I was going on to discuss the possibility and the likelihood of our social welfare scheme being extended and approved in the near future. I did emphasise that it depends largely on the rate of progress we can make in the years to come. It is a very simple matter to have the desire, which I hope everybody in this country has, to do more and better for the weaker sections, particularly the aged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Garret FitzGerald spoke about graded payments, what we refer to as pay-related benefits. This is something which I have included in the memorandum that is before the Government at the present time. There are pay-related benefits, invalid pensions, and there is the problem of home assistance which is administered on the basis of the rather ancient formula of the Poor Law Acts. There is also the question of the age at which pensions <Col N="1505" /> may be payable. There is the old question, which has again been raised, of changing the insurance limit of £1,200. This is something which is adjusted periodically. Anybody who looks back will see it has been adjusted in our own time three or four times.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Always very belatedly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is then the question of the extension of the insurance scheme to self-employed people and to others, whether on a voluntary or on a compulsory basis. By having insurance paid by a greater number of our population, we are more likely to be able to afford schemes which will look of greater benefit anyhow.</P>
      <P>Another question is that of children's allowances about which nobody spoke and which I think is one of the most important of all the payments we make. It was one that was not increased in the Budget, and one that really helps the people who are rearing families. I attended a conference recently on the question of family payments in the social welfare code. One of the things that emerged was that practically every country pays family allowances on a selective basis. While we are all readily prepared to condemn means tests, children's allowances is one case where payments should not be made <i>ad lib</i> without a means test or without there being some selectivity that will ensure that the poorest people get the largest share. We are paying children's allowances to many families who, while I would not say they do not appreciate it, can get along without it, to put it mildly; and there are other families, and large families, who could do with substantially more than we are paying them. I would hope that one of the first improvements we would make in the social welfare code would be to adjust the family allowances upwards in favour of the poorer sections.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That brings me to this question of the means test. The Labour Party in the Dáil were quite prepared to accept a means test, if that were necessary. <Col N="1506" /> It may not be necessary to have a means test. There are other ways in which we might be able to provide the necessary money. However that may be, everybody will welcome an improvement in our social welfare code. Every person who quoted figures quoted the individual amounts payable to a single person and a married person. But if you take any of our payments and look at the allowances for adult and child dependants for a married man, you will find these payments are not too bad at all; they are certainly very much in favour of the person with dependants. Our latest legislation, the Occupational Injuries Act, is a generous measure and a decent addition to our social welfare code. We hope to do better as time goes on, and, as I said, not many years ago, very few countries had any worthwhile social welfare. The United States was one of the latest to get going with social welfare of any account. We had to start social welfare and try to create some industrial expansion at the same time. The two things are not very easy to achieve, and the extent to which we have succeeded gives us a great deal of encouragement and determination to proceed on the same lines in future.</P>
    <P>I should like to deal with some of the points raised. The question of queues at post offices is only a small point, but complaints in this regard would make it seem as if we had no humanity at all and that we are prepared to let old persons be jostled in crowds. We had that problem examined in the city&mdash;it does not apply in rural Ireland&mdash;but it is not at all of the magnitude people pretend it is. The accommodation is reasonably good all round. Pensioners have a whole day and need not all rush in the morning. Pensioners are permitted to have agents to collect their pensions, and some of them collect them on Saturday instead of Friday. Therefore, it is possible for any person to collect his pension without suffering any physical or mental stress as a result of having to queue up at a post office. I should not like it to go out that this is a really serious problem, <Col N="1507" /> because it is not. A large number of people turn up at the same time, but the collection of pensions can be staggered over the whole day or even on to the next day.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>It can be hard in the winter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>It may be difficult when there are big queues, but this can easily be remedied. I was asked to explain about the female relative provision. Provision is being made in the Bill to make allowance for a daughter. This is the beginning of something which I think is long overdue. Like every other scheme, for instance, the free travel, every section of the community pushes to have it extended to them. This is always the case when anything new is brought in. This is a scheme which, to begin with, provides for a female relative, namely, a daughter, who has to look after an aged person, thus preventing that person from being maintained in an institution at greater cost to the State. If our experience shows that it works smoothly we would hope to extend it to other female relatives.</P>
      <P>I would point out that the reason the insured person was selected is that we hope to remedy two anomalies in the one effort. Take the case of the insured daughter who has to give up work, who has a good record in insurance&mdash;we aim at 156 stamps spread over five years immediately before the cessation of work&mdash;and who finds herself in the position that she cannot draw unemployment benefit or even unemployment assistance because she is not available for work. It is to meet that type of case we make this provision in the Bill where the extra £2 5s will be paid to the parent she is taking care of. That gives her some compensation for the fact that she cannot benefit from her insurance because she is not available for work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator O'Sullivan and others said that we should do more for the old people who have done so much for the country. Unfortunately this applies <Col N="1508" /> even more to the people to whom we do not pay pensions. A thrifty hardworking man who provides for the future will be told that he does not qualify for a pension because he has certain means, while a man who was not thrifty, and did not do so much for the country, and has no means, will get the full pension. That is an anomaly of the scheme. I cannot hold out any promise here that we can abolish the means test now or in the near future. It would be lovely if we could get rid of it, but I gave the figures in the Dáil recently of what the cost would be. I still say that if I had all that money, instead of abolishing the means test, I would give it to those who qualify rather than spread it over everyone, without a means test. The time has not come by any means when we can abolish the means test, but every year the limit which deprives a person of a pension is increased, as it is increased in this Bill, so the means test is being relaxed automatically each year when this provision is made. In that way we are considerably alleviating the position of those who have some means.</P>
    <P>The question of ignoring the first £25 and charging five per cent on the balance has been mentioned here and in other places. I want to point out again that the £25 we disregard in the savings of an old age pensioner was not originally intended to represent funeral expenses but, perhaps, it has come to be looked on in that way. People frequently point out that if £25 was adequate for funeral expenses ten years ago, it would not be sufficient now to give a decent funeral to anyone. I always point out that the £25 is disregarded and the remaining £75 is assessed at five per cent, which would not deprive anyone of an old age pension. It is wrong to suggest that someone is being victimised because he has savings of £100. The £25 is not taken into the reckoning and the balance is assessed at five per cent, which would not deprive him of a pension. So, he can have savings of £100 for funeral expenses, if he wants to call them funeral expenses.</P>
    <P>Senator Sheehy Skeffington said that <Col N="1509" /> the general approach of the officers was good but that it was thrown into contrast by the attitude of the few who did not do the investigation properly. That has been said time and again. I do not deny that there are cases where the applicants become annoyed at the person investigating the case. It is hardly necessary to say that it is not the policy of the Department to send a man out to harass applicants for the benefits which we disburse. I might also say that it is sometimes difficult to get the true picture of a person's means, and he may become impatient. The applicants are not all angels either. The positive proof that the officers are not all too strict&mdash;and I am not taking their part in any way&mdash; is that they are, to use a simple term, codded so often. They do not always come away with the true picture. We have provided a means test in our legislation. We ask people to operate it, so let us not blame them for operating it. We laid it down that this would entitle a person to that, and then we send out a civil servant to ascertain whether people qualify. Sometimes their approach is wrong, but I would hope that they would make it clear that they are there to help people to get what they are justifiably entitled to. There is no need to offend.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. J. Fitzgerald Mr. J. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Very often when a local pensions committee have awarded a pension, it is turned down by the investigating officer but, on appeal to the Minister, in nine out of ten cases, the appeal is won.</P>
      <P>(<i>Interruptions.</i>)</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan) Acting Chairman (Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>The sub-committees do good work but there are some ghost committees that should not be there at all. Proposals that they should be abolished have been submitted to me. I was a member of an old age pensions sub-committee for many years. In fact, I think my name is still on the rolls, but I have not turned up in my capacity as Minister. These committees do <Col N="1510" /> a good job as buffers between the Civil Service and the applicants. They have some local knowledge. The investigating officer is entitled to be present at the meeting if requested, and he can be asked to explain his assessment of a person's means. The applicant is entitled to be present and is invited to the meeting. He can argue his case before that jury. One of the weaknesses of these committees is a tendency to grant benefits to everyone. I have frequently heard it said: &ldquo;Give him the full amount and let him fight it out on appeal&rdquo; rather than having a good solid examination of the case to see if the person conforms to the laws laid down. Some of these committees are better than others, but some are inclined to say: &ldquo;Give him the lot and he can fight it out on appeal.&rdquo; When a recommendation is brought before a committee and where the committee differs from the recommendation, an appeal is submitted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>If an inspector is never codded he is not human.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think I need go into any more detail. As I said, I have compiled and submitted by way of memorandum to the Government a complete set of suggestions as to the form in which the future social welfare code should be expanded and improved. I do not think I will make up my mind to publish it as a White Paper or make it known as the blueprint for future development, because I know that immediately I did that, I would be asked to implement it the next day. I should prefer to have it as a guideline on which we will proceed in the future. It is only correct to say that the children's allowances part of the scheme is already being prepared on the lines I have stated, on a selective basis which would enable more substantial payments to be made to those people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not think it necessary to go into any further details. I would again thank the Senators who had a very constructive approach even making <Col N="1511" /> allowance for the occasional political plug here and there&mdash;and perhaps I should like to get an odd plug in myself. However, I am serious when I say I would not allow myself to be hauled into an auction with regard to betting for the future of social welfare. There is a very simple and emotional means of currying favour with the weak section of the people. I would say&mdash;I think all Members of this House would agree with me&mdash;that we should all like to see not merely the payments improved as time goes on but the whole code expanded, covering the entire field in so far as there may yet be people left out who do not share in a proper redistribution of the national wealth.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    <P>Bill put through Committee, reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Business suspended at 6.5 p.m. and resumed at 7.15 p.m.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Turf Development Bill, 1968 (Certified" RHead="Money Bill): Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Turf Development Bill, 1968    (Certified Money Bill):    Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Minister for Transport and Power (Mr. Childers) Erskine Hamilton Childers">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Transport and Power (Mr. Childers)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill is to give Bord na Móna temporary relief from their obligation to pay interest on State advanced capital and to defer repayments of capital to the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Under the Turf Development Acts, Bord na Móna are obliged to pay interest at fixed rates on advances of capital from the Minister for Finance. The board are also required to commence repayment of capital as soon as the bogs in which the capital is invested have been developed and come <Col N="1512" /> into production. It should be noted, therefore, that all the board's State-advanced capital is subject to a fixed annual interest and is repayable on a 25 year basis. The board has no share or equity capital. The board is required, therefore, to meet a definite financial target each year.</P>
    <P>Since the establishment of the board, capital repayments have totalled nearly £4 million, while in the same period, interest paid on capital totalled about £8½ million. The board have met in full their obligations for interest and capital repayments in the normal way up to the payment made on 1st April, 1965. Since then, however, they have been unable to meet from normal revenues the payments due to the State and have been compelled to use capital funds for this purpose as far as they would go. A total of £2,235,000 was so used. The last remittance for interest and repayment of capital was that due and paid on 1st October, 1966. Payments totalling about £2,600,000 are still outstanding in respect of the amounts due on 1st April, 1967, 1st October, 1967, and 1st April, 1968. In the case of advances to the board from sources other than the State, the board's obligations have continued to be met in full.</P>
    <P>Bord na Móna's difficulty is that all their production operations depend fundamentally on natural drying conditions. This is particularly so in the case of milled peat production, which is very vulnerable to adverse weather. Heavy rain can cause substantial losses. In addition, briquette production is dependent on the availability of adequate supplies of milled peat. A measure of the suitability of weather for peat harvesting is given by an index known as Poulter's Index. This is a figure derived from three of the main weather factors which affect drying&mdash;temperature, duration of sunshine and rainfall. In the period from 1880 to 1960 the index for central Ireland did not fall below average on more than four successive years. Unfortunately since 1960 there has been a deterioration. The summer of 1967 was the eighth successive summer in which the index was below average so <Col N="1513" /> that, since 1880, the worst peat harvesting period has been the period from 1960 to 1967.</P>
    <P>To Bord na Móna the succession of poor peat harvesting seasons has meant men and machines lying idle and work partly done but written off because of the interruption of work schedules by bad weather. The board have been unable to meet their production targets&mdash;in the last five years, for example, the overall percentages of targets reached have been only 77 per cent, 81 per cent, 57 per cent, 75 per cent and 89 per cent respectively. The overall result has been the development of a financial situation such that, at the end of 1967-68, the board's accumulated debit balance is in the region of £5 million.</P>
    <P>I should point out at this stage that Bord na Móna have made many efforts to counteract the effects of the unsuitable harvesting weather. In an attempt to maintain the scheduled deliveries on which the capacity of the milled peat fired generating stations was based, they increased the area of bog under production by developing tracts on the fringes of the bogs, thereby accepting a reduced annual target of 70 tons of milled peat per acre compared with the original target of 100 tons. The board have carried out experiments in the milling and harrowing of milled peat for the purpose of establishing methods which would ensure the most efficient use of available natural drying. The size of the particle milled has proved to be crucial in this context and further work is being carried out by the board to determine the optimum particle size for the climatic conditions.</P>
    <P>The board have also carried out investigations into drainage of milled peat areas and milled peat pile compaction and protection. These investigations have led to a standard procedure for the protection of turf stock piles during the winter, involving the introduction of polythene covering for milled peat piles in an effort to defeat both high winds and heavy rains. Without this covering, losses would have been much heavier.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1514" /> Finally, Bord na Móna have embarked on a new experimental method of milled peat production&mdash;the Fóidín method. This involved the designing of new machines to produce, on milled peat bogs, turf in the form of small sods which, in the process of drying, would develop a surface resistant to weather like ordinary sod turf. The small sods so produced are subsequently crushed to form milled peat. This harvesting technique has been developed to supplement normal milled peat production in poor harvesting conditions: 85,000 tons were harvested by this method in 1967 at the board's works in County Mayo and at Boora and Derrygreenagh works in County Offaly.</P>
    <P>Of course, the Fóidín method is more expensive than direct harvesting of milled peat, but it should ensure a minimum harvest, irrespective of weather conditions. The board are pleased with the results obtained so far and this year they are extending the application of the new method to their works at Blackwater, County Offaly and Mountdillon, County Longford. All these efforts to overcome adverse weather conditions naturally increase the board's costs and are reflected in the present debit balance position.</P>
    <P>In view of the heavy and continuing losses suffered by Bord na Móna in recent years, I think it is very necessary to have a new and searching look at the overall operations of the board. To this end, I am arranging for the appointment of a firm of consultants to examine the turf production programme, both from the engineering and financial standpoints, and to assess the likely results of future operations. I should make it clear that, over the years, Bord na Móna have themselves employed consultants on various occasions to examine and report on different facets of their operations. The new investigation will be concerned with the totality of the board's operations. When this investigation has been completed and reported on, it should be possible to decide on the most appropriate financial structure of the board for future <Col N="1515" /> years and so ensure the continuation of the board's activities on a sound basis and preserve employment and other benefits in areas which otherwise provide very little opportunities. The purpose of the present Bill is to afford some immediate relief to the board in their financial difficulties pending the outcome of the report.</P>
    <P>The Bill proposes that Bord na Móna be given full or partial relief during a period of four years from 1st April, 1967, from their obligation to pay interest&mdash;now about £1.2 million a year&mdash;on State advances. In addition, the board would, if necessary, be permitted to defer all or part of the repayments of State advances&mdash;about £400,000 a year&mdash;due during the same period. The Minister for Finance would take a decision on the extent of the relief in respect of each year on examination of the board's financial position and after consultation with me. The relief would not apply to capital advanced to the board by the State for the provision of houses for their workers as it is separate from the board's main function of turf production, on which the losses have occurred, and the board would continue to make the small annual payments involved.</P>
    <P>The relief would be given by means of orders, which may include conditions suggested by the circumstances at the time, which would be made by the Minister for Finance and laid before the Houses in the usual way. The annual accounts of the board would also bring any waiver or deferment to attention.</P>
    <P>I think I should stress that the relief is an interim arrangement and not a final solution. As it will date for four years from 1st April, 1967, it will, in effect, cease in just over 2½ years time, March, 1971.</P>
    <P>The relief is designed to give the board some breathing space to cover the period while the consultants are examining the situation and their report is being considered. By March, 1971, we should be in a position to assess the <Col N="1516" /> board's prospects on a long-term basis.</P>
    <P>In 1965, on the occasion of the last Turf Development Bill, the House was given particulars of the projected development of the board's activities. The moss peat factory at Coolnamona near Portlaoise has since been completed and is now in production. Further development of the board's programme has, however, been somewhat disrupted by the succession of bad summers. As a consequence, the erection of an additional briquette factory has not been proceeded with. In any event, because of supply difficulties resulting from bad harvesting weather and also, perhaps, because of the fall in popularity of solid fuel generally, demand for peat briquettes has not increased as much as was expected. It is necessary, therefore, to make a careful re-examination of the prospects for sales of peat briquettes before substantial capital investment is made in a new briquette factory. This is one of the matters that, I hope, will be reported upon by the consultants.</P>
    <P>Now, despite the setback which is the reason for the submission of this Bill to the House, there is ample evidence of the success which has attended the endeavours of Bord na Móna in carrying out the duties assigned to them in 1946. They have now about 100,000 acres of bog in production, and they pay over £4 million a year in wages to 7,000 workers, of whom over 4,000 are permanent employees. Their contribution to the national fuel requirements, both for direct consumption and for electricity generation, is substantial. The board naturally expected to have bad years among the good years, but the recent succession of bad years has involved them in losses which demand that there be a thorough examination of their prospects.</P>
    <P>In the meantime, it is essential that the board be afforded some provisional financial relief. I hope that the recommendations of the consultants, coupled with the measures already taken by the board, will provide a basis for the avoidance of losses in the future and enable the board to meet their financial obligations.</P>
    <P>I recommend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Col N="1517" />
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a little too much for the Minister to attribute all the defects and bad luck of Bord na Móna to adverse weather conditions. Perhaps if he were the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries, he might have stronger reason for making that case. I cannot accept that the Board's present financial position is entirely due to the weather conditions over the past few years. The management of Bord na Móna certainly must accept some responsibility for the sorry figures presented to us today.</P>
      <P>The Minister mentioned the position in regard to peat briquettes and the unstable position of the market for this very desirable type of fuel. I should like to remind him that last autumn there were many complaints about the distribution of peat briquettes and their availability to some retailers. It was suggested to me that there was some type of ring in operation which certainly acted against some legitimate distributors who had been in the trade for many years.</P>
      <P>We also found that, while Bord na Móna saw fit to embark on a very expensive and widescale campaign of advertising briquettes and turf generally, they then increased the price of briquettes and when the demand for baled briquettes slumped in favour of loose briquettes, which were available at a cheaper rate, there was the ludicrous situation of the management of Bord na Móna employing men in cutting the baled briquettes into the cheaper form of loose briquettes. It would have been a much better form of advertising, if Bord na Móna were really sincere in pushing their product, for them to have given a special bonus, as many selling organisations now do, in respect of the sale of baled briquettes over short periods of a fortnight or month at the price prevailing for loose briquettes. In that way they would at least have saved themselves the cost of breaking down the bales.</P>
      <P>When there are such madcap ideas on the part of management in a large-scale organisation such as Bord na Móna, it is no wonder that they find themselves with problems.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In his Second Reading speech in Dáil <Col N="1518" /> Éireann&mdash;I seem to have missed it in his speech to the Seanad this evening&mdash;&mdash; the Minister said that the Board had met all their commitments other than to the State. I should like to challenge that statement. I know there are small farmers and landowners who have been waiting for five and six years for payment for land which was compulsorily acquired. Only this morning I met a man to whom the Board owed approximately £800 for nine acres compulsorily acquired from him at Coolnamona in Portlaoise. If the Minister will give me an undertaking here that Bord na Móna, on the passage of this Bill, will be in a position to pay these farmers and landowners the moneys legally and rightfully due to them, I shall welcome its passage. If, on the other hand, this large semi-State organisation are going to step in line with the Government and treat the Irish farmer as a second-class citizen, I would almost feel that I should vote against it. However, I do not think I will do that because, in the midlands in particular, Bord na Móna give reasonably good employment to quite a large number of people. While some of the personnel find the red tape attached to working for this organisation quite frustrating, nevertheless, the Board employ many thousands of workers and it is always to be hoped that management will catch on and will give the workers that ray of hope that many of them would like to see.</P>
    <P>I should like briefly to mention the fact that some years ago on another debate I mentioned that in the Blackwater bog district of west Offaly the operations of the Board cause pollution of the low-lying grassland. Time and time again the unfortunate landowners, who must pay high annual rates, find that the land is rendered completely useless as a result of pollution and the silting which occurs in the drains coming from the Blackwater bog. This, surely, is the responsibility of Bord na Móna. This is a very large semi-State organisation and they must face their responsibilities and must not allow their operations to endanger the livelihood of small farmers in their vicinity.</P>
    <P>I should like to ask the Minister if he can give us some idea of the expected <Col N="1519" /> life of the bogs which are at present either developed or in course of development. I recall reading some weeks ago of some rather stiff criticism of the operations of the people who are dealing with the reclamation of cutaway bogs and I should like to ask the Minister if, in his opinion, there is sufficient co-operation between Bord na Móna, An Foras Talúntais, the Irish Sugar Company and the Department of Agriculture in this regard. It is, of course, to be hoped that there is not duplication of effort in the sphere of reclamation of cutaway bogs.</P>
    <P>I have often wondered whether it is good policy, taking the long-term national view, to export so much peat moss to other countries, when it is possible that we could succeed in improving areas in the midlands, especially where we have heavy clay loams. Could we not perhaps introduce a scheme similar to the lime scheme whereby moss peat could be distributed on these heavy clay loams, rendering the land there more suitable for agricultural purposes, especially grazing?</P>
    <P>I am sure An Foras Talúntais might have something to say on that, but, to my knowledge, they have not attempted it on any of their farms. On a casual visit to Waterford recently, I noted the large quantities of moss peat being exported from there and considered that it would be a pity, after 20 years, to be left here with large tracts of brown barren desert while at the same time making our competitors in a united Europe much more competitive in fruit and vegetable growing.</P>
    <P>I hope the Minister will be able to give me an assurance that the farmers who have been made to give over their lands to Bord na Móna for their various operations will be paid when this Bill has been passed. So far the Board have been indolent on this score and I look forward to the Minister giving a specific undertaking that these people will not have to wait any longer, and furthermore that the Board will pay compound interest on the price during the years since the sales were made.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1520" /> I wish to say a final word or two on the type of consultants it is envisaged to employ in regard to the new thinking on Bord na Móna. Perhaps the Minister will be good enough to give us some idea of who they will be. I understood that Bord na Móna were the leading experts in the world on peat production. I read in one of the provincial newspapers a few weeks ago, when the Russian delegates were over here, an article to that effect. Are we to find now that we are still the leading lights in the world in peat production and if not, whom do we consult when we are in the red?</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Russia, maybe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>Will these consultants advise on the type of machinery or will they be consultants on management, on distribution, on labour? I know that in Bord na Móna there are many excellent hard-working people who could be employed to continue the work they have been doing to which is attributable any success the Board have had. Would they consider the introduction of a suggestion box for improvements on the lines of those installed by many factories on matters of day-to-day running? We know that everything is not right within Bord na Móna and let us hope, now that we accept the position as it is and agree to accommodate the Board as far as interest and repayments are concerned, that we shall ensure that their operations will continue to be successful during the coming year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryDavidson" hpid="Miss Davidson Miss Davidson">
      <NameTxt>Miss Davidson</NameTxt>
      <P>We of the Labour Party welcome this Bill, which aims at giving Bord na Móna temporary and much needed financial relief, though considerably less than is given by the Minister to some other semi-State bodies under the aegis of his Department. I can say, however, that an earlier introduction of this Bill would have been even more welcome: its belated appearance has not improved the financial situation of the concern. So far as I follow the situation, the Board have been able to meet their obligations to the State up to 1st April, 1965, in face of the fact that in <Col N="1521" /> the 1960-67 period, their operations were severely handicapped by abnormally bad weather conditions.</P>
      <P>That the Board had been forced by production losses to use capital money to pay interest was something which could not continue and indicated that the time had come when the Minister would have to take action. We believe this Bill meets the situation to a large degree and that it will give the Board the necessary breathing space. However, doubt arises on the four-year term which seems somewhat short to rectify such a heavy loss. Though it is accepted that bad weather is responsible to a great degree for the present position in Bord na Móna, it is known that a large portion of the deficit has been caused by the sale of peat to the ESB below cost of production.</P>
      <P>This situation was one of the causes of labour trouble in Bord na Móna where we had the situation that the Bord na Móna employees were paid considerably lower wages than the ESB employees who were doing exactly the same work. Could the ESB not have paid the full cost of the peat or could they not have shared jointly the loss suffered by Bord na Móna in supplying the peat at under cost of production? This would have seemed a reasonable arrangement between two semi-State bodies. However, in the four years ended 31st March, 1967, Bord na Móna sold peat to the ESB at £2,378,000 below the cost of production. In 1966-67 the loss on peat supplied to the ESB was more than £1,270,000 and in the previous year, it was £1,140,000. It would appear that Bord na Móna sold peat to the ESB at 21/9 per ton below the cost of production in 1967-68.</P>
      <P>It is not to be wondered at that in their last published report, dated 31st March, 1967, Bord na Móna stated:</P>
      <P>There is no prospect that the deficit which has accumulated over a number of years can be made good out of future profits.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Why should the Board have to face this situation alone? Why could not the ESB carry their share of the burden? Perhaps the Minister could explain the reason to me because I cannot see <Col N="1522" /> why two semi-State bodies, working together, should not aid each other in meeting difficulties of this nature.</P>
    <P>We have all heard of the reluctance, on the ground of cost, in certain quarters in the ESB to use peat for generating electricity. These officials would favour the use of peat only when peat production is necessary and then only at cut price. Those who would favour the discontinuance of the use of peat for electricity production might be reminded of the employment content of Bord na Móna and the situation which would follow if its activities were curtailed or ended. The effect of the resulting bill for unemployment benefit on the national economy might give them food for thought.</P>
    <P>It has been announced recently that two Ministers have appointed boards of inquiry into the affairs of Bord na Móna. The Minister for Labour has appointed a body:</P>
    <P>to identify the causes of strikes in Bord na Móna in 1967 and 1968 and to indicate any factors which hindered earlier settlement of the disputes.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Transport and Power has announced the appointment of a firm of consultants to examine and report on the financial and engineering aspects of the Board's operations. It has been public knowledge for nearly two years that Bord na Móna have been drawing on capital funds in order to make interest payments. I cannot help thinking that, had the Minister acted earlier, these possibly very expensive inquiries would not have been necessary.</P>
    <P>As a general rule, employers make strenuous efforts to avert major trade disputes. Newspaper and other reports reveal that in the two weeks before the commencement of the six weeks strike in Bord na Móna in February last, no effort at all was made by the directors of the Board to negotiate a settlement. At that time the Board and the Minister would have known that the accumulated deficit was of the order of £5 million; yet there were no signs of financial relief being forthcoming. One <Col N="1523" /> could be forgiven for thinking that the inaction of the Board in such a serious situation was a desperate effort on their part to force the Minister to take the remedial action he has now taken.</P>
    <P>In this connection, I would urge the Minister to appoint one of the members of the board of directors of Bord na Móna as a labour relations director, who would have the responsibility of meeting the trade unions at the conference table. The absence of such an officer could, in all probability, be one of the major causes of the recent strikes in Bord na Móna. To get maximum production in any industry, there must be a reasonable feeling of security among the workers; but much dissatisfaction exists among Bord na Móna employees not alone because of low wage rates but because of their unsatisfactory pension scheme. The Minister will know that the superannuation scheme of 1963 is unsatisfactory because the Board are not permitted to pay more than 50 per cent of the superannuation benefits. Some of these pensions are as low as a few shillings per week because of this restriction. There is no fifty-fifty condition in the Civil Service or Local Government Superannuation Acts. Perhaps, in order to build up a better atmosphere, the Minister might consider a minor amendment of the Turf Development Act of 1953 in order to permit of the payment of reasonable pensions to Bord na Móna employees?</P>
    <P>I would again say that this Bill is welcomed, but we would have welcomed it more warmly had it come before us much earlier.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill comes as no great shock to any of us who have been reading the papers and following the fortunes of Bord na Móna. There is a certain parallel between their difficulties and those of CIE over the last decade in regard to problems of modernisation and the provision of capital and other charges involved. We have to look at this realistically. We have committed the nation since the foundation of Bord na Móna, and rightly so, to a great capital expenditure in developing a <Col N="1524" /> resource we have&mdash;our turf. There can be quarrel with that. But we have got to look at it realistically for the future.</P>
      <P>On the one hand, we have a national asset that is producing and is providing employment for 4,000 people. On the other hand, we are dealing with a commodity, turf, that is gradually being beaten in the race to provide fuel for electricity generation. Therefore, we have, first of all, to look at the short-term effects. I do not think these should frighten any of us. The figures as given show £4 million in wages and a gross of somewhere around £6 million in production. Therefore, if we take one of the choices that might appear open to us in theory, that is to close down the whole enterprise, we can reckon the cost of that course, since the turf used for electricity generation could be replaced by oil. But that would mean a reduction in our national production of £6 million that would have to be replaced by the necessary additional oil imports.</P>
      <P>Senator Miss Davidson posed the question of why the ESB cannot pay more of the losses of Bord na Móna. The simple answer to that is that, according to the ESB accounting, electricity generated from turf is the most expensive form of electricity generation. Consequently, to increase the price of turf to the ESB, which at present is over-priced nationally for electricity generation, would only mean passing on the loss to the electricity consumer, which of course means to the nation as a whole. So that is no solution. It does not get down to the kernel of the problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Let us say for the moment theoretically that we might be able to close down the enterprise and replace turf for electricity generation by imported oil. The national output would then go down by £6 million. Taking account of the multiplying effect, this £6 million would be equivalent to about £10 million reduction in the national income figure. When this is taken into account in the national income figure the tax loss to the country, on the basis that the Exchequer gets back on average about 25 per cent of the gross national income, that is, 25 per cent of £10 million, or about <Col N="1525" /> £2.5 million. Accordingly, were we to close down Bord na Móna and substitute oil for turf, the tax yield would probably go down by about £2.5 million. Therefore, if the Minister uses some of that money to keep the enterprise going and flourishing, it is a good bargain.</P>
    <P>We must also look at the employment side of the picture. This involves 4,000 permanent men and 3,000 temporary, or the equivalent of 5,000 or 6,000 jobs. We can estimate what it would cost to face up to the national commitment of re-employing those people if made redundant. One might estimate £3,000 per person and that amounts to £15 or £20 million in capital. Capital is not the only limiting factor in that regard. There is also the question of thinking up enterprises that are likely to succeed and provide employment for those people in their present areas.</P>
    <P>There is no question then but that the Government must face up to the challenge of keeping Bord na Móna going and giving it a fair measure of financial assistance. Certainly if the writing-off of the capital involved to date were to achieve that effectively, involving the relief of the £1.2 million interest and the £400,000 capital repayments&mdash;about £2 million&mdash;it would be quite worthwhile for the Government to take this course.</P>
    <P>Bord na Móna is largely a rural industry which makes it doubly valuable because the money is being spent in regions where industries are scarce and where the likelihood of attracting substitute industries is not very great. Consequently, the Board is playing a very useful social role. We can see the great stimulus it has given to life in these regions. That must be kept going. On all counts we are committed to keeping it going.</P>
    <P>That is not sufficient. We must do it in the short-term, with the realisation that the long-term prospects are not great because nuclear power is a major factor today. In the US in 1966 for the first time the cost of producing electricity from nuclear fuel became less than that of producing it from conventional <Col N="1526" /> thermal fuels. The result is shown in the fact that in 1967, 90 per cent of the applications for permission to build power stations in the US were conventional types using thermal fuel and only ten per cent stations using nuclear power, while this year the position has reversed and the applications are now running 90 per cent for nuclear power and only ten per cent for conventional fuel. The change-over has taken place, perhaps, a little later than some of us foresaw in the early 50s but that was because the thermal fuels met the challenge from nuclear power at that time by highly successful research. A remarkable increase in efficiency was achieved by using high pressure jets thereby gaining a temporary respite from the nuclear challenge.</P>
    <P>That challenge is with us today and we must accept that in ten years time, requirements for additional power stations will have to be met mainly by nuclear stations. We need have no worry about this because we are ideally placed for nuclear power generation which requires a plentiful supply of cooling water and siting of regions remote from centres of population. There is no doubt that we have many excellent sites available. We might go further: not alone can we generate such power for our own use but we can export it directly to Britain and into the European network using modern direct current linkage. Consequently I urge that we must face the fact that turf, already outpriced for the generation of electricity, will be much more outpriced in ten years time. Consequently for the sake of the future of the 4,000 employed in Bord na Móna and the regions that depend so much on them, we must immediately get down to long-term planning under, I suggest, two heads. First, as regards the dependent regions a great deal of research is required into the uses that can be made of natural products available in those regions, with the emphasis shifting from electricity generation as the major use of turf, over to peat moss and its use in flower pots and other developments. These may appear small but they can be developed considerably. Turf can be put to many other uses but it will take a great deal <Col N="1527" /> of research to move into profitable new fields of use. In that research, in that common endeavour, where we are all anxious to help the employees of Bord na Móna to hold on to their jobs, the employees themselves must contribute a great deal. I suggest to the Minister that the industry might be used as a pilot for real partnership work. The future of these employees is at stake and it is therefore up to them to cooperate to the greatest possible extent with the State, and with research organisations and study groups to save their industry and their livelihood.</P>
    <P>In putting additional State capital at the disposal of Bord na Móna or writing-off a certain amount of existing capital or in giving modernisation or capital grants, I suggest that the Minister should explore the possibilities of making it easy for the employees, whether at the top level of technical management or at the lower levels, to acquire shares in the reorganised body so that they can then face the real challenge of survival. This will call for a great diversification of activities, not merely those associated with turf. The local Bord na Móna offices will have to become development centres for other industries which they must get into those regions, and which may mean the transfer of some employees on a planned basis over the next ten or 15 years from their present occupation to positions in new factories and new industries which I envisage a reorganised Bord na Móna developing in these areas.</P>
    <P>We must face the fact that the major activity as it is today, the production of milled peat, cannot survive the challenge of nuclear power after ten to 15 years, but if we take steps in time, I have every confidence that not alone will the employment in those centres grow but also its quality will grow, because it will have to become more scientifically based, more dependent on research, seeking out newer and more scientific uses for turf as a raw material and also developing many associated industries.</P>
    <P>I do not think any contribution on this Bill would be complete without <Col N="1528" /> paying high compliment to the technical staff of Bord na Móna. Their research approach to the work, their development of new equipment, and their adaptation of outside equipment, has won deserved recognition in many parts of the world. They have a high-class technical staff and that high-class staff who have made their homes in those rural areas can become the development corporations for those centres. Perhaps also some of the engineering staff there, when they become redundant in the turf area, or even before that, could be assigned to the investigation of nuclear power and its potential.</P>
    <P>The ESB have a study group on this, but much more action is required. It is time the Government stepped into this inquiry and this development on a basis much larger than that of the ESB. We cannot turn back the clock. We have no choice in this matter, but as I have shown, we have nothing to fear from the advent of nuclear power, with all the natural advantages we have for its generation. Indeed, in some of our remote areas&mdash;I am thinking particularly of parts of Connaught&mdash; the ability to generate vast quantities of power could result in the development in those areas of industries requiring a tremendous amount of power, like, for instance, the aluminium industry in the United States which is developing in rather unexpected areas, where the main requirement has been the availability of adequate power.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill, and I think that the employees in Bord na Móna, both technical and others, should know we are all anxious and ready to do everything we can to ensure that not only do we overcome the short-term difficulties&mdash;which are no real problem&mdash; but that we make the long-term adjustment to the nuclear age and that we preserve and strengthen those centres, both by diversification and research.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>We support this Bill, even though we regret the circumstances which have made it necessary. The Minister has explained that for some 80 years up to 1960 the index for measuring the combination of temperatures, drying conditions and rainfall <Col N="1529" /> did not fall below the average for more than four successive years. Indeed we have had eight successive years below the average, and we do not know what 1968 may produce. I feel for the Minister because the weather is bad not only for his responsibilities in regard to Bord na Móna but also for those connected with our tourist industry. We can only hope that a change of Government will bring with it a change in weather.</P>
      <P>I am interested in the question of bringing in consultants. I think somebody muttered under his breath: &ldquo;We should invite the Russians in to advise us, seeing we have already advised the Russians on the development of our bogs.&rdquo; I do not know about that, but I am told that when some Russians were looking at our Bord na Móna operations and its tie-up with the ESB, they asked: &ldquo;Why Bord na Móna and the ESB? Why not simply one publicly-owned undertaking to do the job?&rdquo; I do not know if this is a solution to the problem, but no doubt the consultants will consider this and have regard to the desirability of such a development in the report.</P>
      <P>What I want to deal with specially has been touched upon somewhat by Senator Quinlan, that is, the fact that here we have a publicly-owned undertaking providing a fair amount of employment, particularly valuable in the areas in which that employment is provided, and it is a relatively new industry. I would ask the Minister to consider the possibility and the desirability of experimenting in the introduction of industrial democracy into this undertaking. Senator Miss Davidson has referred to the number of strikes. I do not want to comment upon that. I have my own views, maybe, upon it, but it is unfortunate that these strikes have taken place. I suppose it is no harm to repeat what I have said so many times before, that the people who lose most and suffer most in strikes are the workers themselves. I think it is also fair to comment that in Bord na Móna we have had&mdash;maybe some of the trade unions would not necessarily agree with me&mdash;progressive management, forward-looking, outward-looking management.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1530" /> We hear a great lot of talk about industrial democracy. It has suddenly become popular and respectable since the time of Pope John. It is no harm to underline the fact that industrial democracy or, more correctly, self-management, is not something like a wage increase, or an improvement in conditions of service. In fact, of course, it is the putting of responsibility on the people actually working in the organisation. It is perhaps, in many cases, much easier to blame the boss than to accept a share of responsibility. It is time we started experimenting and moving forward even tentatively in this direction, not that it will necessarily solve all our industrial relations problems. That is not the point at all, but it is desirable to develop this in the interests of the workers as human beings. I do not imagine that if the workers should suddenly face up to the actualities of self-management, they would think it a great idea if they had to take on responsibility, but I do feel that, particularly with better educated people leaving the schools and coming into industry, it would be for their own good and the good of us all if more responsibility were placed on people in their work places. It would be better for them as human beings. It would enable them to develop much better and that, in itself, is desirable as we are all human beings.</P>
    <P>What I am saying is that here perhaps we have an opportunity. The Minister is inviting consultants to look at the whole operations of Bord na Móna and make recommendations. If we are making a new start in regard to Bord na Móna&mdash;and I am not saying anything about the workers or about Bord na Móna&mdash;this may be a new opportunity at least to start thinking about the problem, to have some experiments, and see how they work out. It involves a lot of education for the people concerned. I think the Minister might be progressive enough to throw out this idea and see if there is a possibility of making a start in this direction.</P>
    <P>I want to make one final point in regard to the export of peat moss. Senator McDonald raised this in a rather complaining tone of voice. I <Col N="1531" /> think he will agree that Bord na Móna are to be complimented on the development of this export market. I was in Geneva recently at the ILO, and I saw them putting peat moss into the beds there. I regret I cannot say it came from Bord na Móna: I think it came from Denmark. There is this export field for Bord na Móna. I think what Senator McDonald was saying&mdash; and I should like to support him in this&mdash;was that there is room for encouraging greater use of peat moss by our farmers in certain soil conditions. If that is so, it would be as sensible to subsidise its use as it is sensible to subsidise the use of lime and fertilisers. I am not an expert on this matter. I know peat moss is supposed to be good for gardens and for fruit growing, but how effective or helpful it is in pasturage, I do not know. Perhaps it could be used, and if it could it would seem desirable in the national interest that it should be used and subsidised the same as is the use of lime and fertilisers, and it would open up a further market for this native industry.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford) Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Longford):</i> We all regret that a situation has arisen which necessitates the introduction of a Bill to deal with the financial structure of Bord na Móna. So far the debate has been constructive and any criticisms made were minor. I agree that every effort possible should be made to continue to operate Bord na Móna as a viable concern. It appears it will be a hard thing to do, in view of the statement made by Senator Quinlan that the generation of electricity could be more economic by the use of nuclear fuel than conventional fuel. I take it that he had in mind the carbohydrates as he was dealing with the situation in America. In our desire to continue Bord na Móna operating as a viable concern, we are dealing with a social problem as well as an economic problem, because the operations and undertakings of Bord na Móna are situated in areas where there is contract employment, and it is more necessary to continue employment in those areas than it would be, possibly, in areas where there is a more affluent society.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1532" /> I was rather alarmed to hear&mdash;and I accept Senator Quinlan's word&mdash;that a situation has arisen in which electricity can be generated more economically, or as economically, from nuclear fuel, that this was a challenge to the people in the carbohydrate fuel areas, and that they overcame some of the difficulties, temporarily at any rate. If that is so&mdash;and I take it it is so, because I accept the statement quite fully&mdash;it would indicate that Bord na Móna, the Government, and all of us as a society, have a duty to study the ways and means by which Bord na Móna can be made more efficient.</P>
    <P>It is easy to say Bord na Móna started in 1946, and that a number of bad years, from their point of view, was the cause of the financial straitjacket. We must remember at the same time that before Bord na Móna was established as such, a great estate had been built up rather in a hurry under the name of the Turf Development Board. Bord na Móna inherited that estate. Because it was hurried, the build-up perhaps was not as well planned as it might have been. That build-up took place from 1940 to 1946.</P>
    <P>Many things could be done better I feel, if they had to be done again. Housing conditions, working conditions, and many such difficulties could have been overcome much more quickly were it not for the conditions that prevailed during that war period. It is only proper that we should pay tribute to the people who built up that industry at a time when a great challenge to our very existence occurred. Were it not for that, our ability to remain neutral during a war period might not have been as secure as it turned out to be.</P>
    <P>However, there is no use in referring at any length to past history: it is the future that counts. I agree that more research should be made into the undertaking with a view to better planning and to making it more economic. That would also indicate to me that research should be made into the human side. I cannot but feel, having heard others, having read newspapers and this and that, that some of the difficulty that arose by way of strike <Col N="1533" /> could have been avoided if people were talking to one another rather than talking at one another.</P>
    <P>A strike can sometimes be caused when there is a genuine grievance. A strike can be caused by professional agitators&mdash;the bulk of the men not understanding. Again, a strike can be caused because of an attitude adopted by management. My view is, particularly in relation to Bord na Móna, that if there had been better understanding and&mdash;to use a word I do not like to use although it is very often used&mdash;dialogue between the executives of the Board and the workers there would have been better labour relations. When a situation appears to exist&mdash;as to me, one does exist&mdash;the fault is not all on one side. I am not prepared to agree that the fault for the strike in February or March last lay with the workers but neither am I prepared to agree that it lay with management: it was due to a common lack of understanding. That is the sort of thing that could be avoided. Failure by Bord na Móna to be in operation during a critical period of the year is bound to make its whole operation for that year uneconomic. While it may be possible to indicate, from weather statistics, that the greater part of the trouble is due to weather conditions only, I think the greater part of it would be avoided with improved management-labour relations.</P>
    <P>The Minister mentioned a move away from milled peat as probably not as economic but as a safer method. When there was no better way, we had sod peat briquette production. Then we had milled peat. Now it would appear that the small sod system is a better system. I hope that that is so. I do not intend to express an opinion. However, if the small sod system can be more successful, I am wondering how far it would be more successful economically for the Board in their effort to sell fuel to the ordinary housewife. There are transport and packing difficulties, and so on. I should like to hear if any research has been made by the Board into that aspect. In the long run, there is this difference between ESB and Bord na Móna.</P>
    <P>I should like to see Bord na Móna <Col N="1534" /> continue as a viable concern. I know quite well that all the other Senators who have spoken have the same outlook. I should like to know if that sort of research is being carried out. I seldom go into this area: I leave it to the university people to deal with the question of research. However, it appears to me that there are too many people dealing with this matter. University undertakings seem to think that, apart from their teaching obligations, they have a duty to undertake search and research. Possibly that is so. Many authorities are saddled with responsibility for research. In my opinion, there is no co-ordination in this whole field of research. We have Foras Tionscal, the Department of Agriculture, the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards: they are the few that have occurred to me. It is my opinion that there is not the co-ordination or the co-operation and, without that co-ordination and co-operation, no research will be complete and exhaustive.</P>
    <P>Now, if we expect Bord na Móna, with limited resources, to carry out research, we might find that that research was not complete and exhaustive, that it would not be equipped to do that. Perhaps we can hear from the Minister that independent research officers&mdash;financial, social and economic &mdash;will deal with this matter in the hope of continuing Bord na Móna as a viable concern or, at any rate, as a concern as viable as it is possible, practically, to make it in view of the social obligations of Bord na Móna to this country. I trust nobody would argue that Bord na Móna should close down simply because it is showing that, in a long-term way, it cannot operate as a viable concern. I trust that that would be the view of the majority of Senators. I think it is certain that it would.</P>
    <P>There was one criticism from Senator McDonald about the case of a person from Laois-Offaly in relation to land acquisition. I do not know anything about the case but I have this experience. In public life, people will complain to one about land acquired by the Land Commission and they will claim that, even after a long time, they were not paid. However, in any case I <Col N="1535" /> investigated <i>à propos</i> the Land Commission, I found that the failure was not by the Land Commission but by the person from whom the land was acquired or not so much the person himself as his agent. Very often, a person employs somebody to do a certain type of work which that person does not do. For instance, he did not send in papers or he did not produce a document which it was necessary to produce. When, as a public representative, I had to go to the Land Commission or get after the Land Commission in any case of that nature I found&mdash;in the few little cases&mdash;it was not the fault of the Land Commission. Maybe I am wrong, but I am inclined to suggest&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course you are wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford) Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Longford):</i>&mdash;&mdash;that, if that particular case is investigated, the same answer will emerge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>There is more than one. They cannot all be wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyMcAuliffe" hpid="Mr. McAuliffe Mr. McAuliffe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McAuliffe</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry the Minister did not introduce the Bill last year because, since its introduction, the people working in Bord na Móna, from engineers down to the unskilled worker, realise they had no idea of the position of Bord na Móna. If the Bill had been published earlier, we might have avoided the disastrous strike we had during the spring. I come from an area in which nearly everybody works for Bord na Móna. There are 100 houses there which are occupied by Bord na Móna workers. I have a fair idea of the hardships they suffered by reason of that strike. Some people stayed out in sympathy while others were locked out. These were the people who had no income whatsoever during the period of the strike. I can assure the Minister that they did undergo severe hardship during that period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>For that reason, I would like to say that communications between men and management appear to be very bad. If communications were better, the strike might never have taken place or it could have been settled in a much <Col N="1536" /> shorter time when it did take place. It dragged on week after week and there were men in Bord na Móna who thought that they would put out the lights throughout the country but they did not even put out a 40-watt lamp throughout the period. The ESB told people to be careful about using power and lights, but in reality I do not think anybody was upset in any way by the fact that Bord na Móna were not supplying fuel to the ESB.</P>
    <P>The ESB were in the happy position that they could turn to oil or coal and were able to obtain their requirements. The men who were under the impression that they would embarrass the Government were under a misapprehension. I am not surprised that it was necessary to introduce this Bill because we see that capital repayments since the establishment of Bord na Móna were £4 million, while in the same period the interest paid was £8½ million. No firm could stand on its feet and pay £8½ million in interest over that period and, at the same time, pay £4 million in capital repayments.</P>
    <P>Since 1st April, 1965, the Minister was aware that the position of Bord na Móna had become rather hopeless and that they could not meet their obligations. He allowed something worse to happen by taking £2¼ million from their capital fund which did not help the Board and certainly curtailed development of all kinds. We know that the Board depend to a great extent on weather and it was rather interesting to learn that from 1960 to 1967 we had the worst seven years since 1880. I am glad to tell the Minister that this year we have had an exceptional run. Good weather in June enabled the Board to attain their targets for this year in many places. If we have an average autumn, they will reach their full targets, which would be very satisfactory.</P>
    <P>In last year's Bord na Móna report, the figures showed that there had been a substantial profit, and when the workers saw this it was natural that they should apply for a share of the profits which were made during that year. That in itself brought about the <Col N="1537" /> trouble in the spring. The workers did not know that the Board were in the red to the extent of £5 million. If that had been explained to them, if this Bill had been introduced earlier, we would have avoided trouble. A strike in a rural area is a disaster: it hurts too many people and it is something that should be avoided. As I said, communications should be better between workers and management and the workers should know about the financial position of Bord na Móna and be kept informed of any improvement or deterioration in the situation that might develop.</P>
    <P>The Board have certainly done their part in regard to trying to protect the milled peat by using polythene. The use of polythene has enabled them to keep peat dry for the ESB during the winter and during periods of frost. Before they used polythene, it was almost impossible for anyone to live within a radius of six miles of a bog because during a storm, even with windows closed and keyholes sealed, houses were still covered with milled peat. We have not had that nuisance since the polythene was used and I should like to compliment the Board on deciding to use it to such an extent.</P>
    <P>A number of workers to whom I have been speaking are of the opinion that the Fóidín method could never be a success. Perhaps the Board have experimented over too wide an area and invested too much money in machines, but I would not say that the method has been a success. It probably takes too long to harvest the crop. Recently the Minister made a statement which was published in the daily newspapers, and which he repeated here today, a statement which I regard as a grave warning to people in Bord na Móna. He said that it is necessary to have a new and searching look at the overall operations of the Board and he intends to appoint consultants to examine turf production. If these consultants do not come back with a remedy, if they report that turf production will never be an economic proposition, what does the Minister think he will do? What recommendation will he make? Will he reduce the number of bogs being used to a minimum, <Col N="1538" /> and only leave open the ones that might pay, or will he leave the matter as it stands and continue to subsidise Bord na Móna?</P>
    <P>I hope that when the consultants issue their report, we will find it will be favourable because so many people in rural areas depend on Bord na Móna for their livelihood that it would be impossible to place them all in other employment.</P>
    <P>The Minister is hoping the Board will be in a position to take up their liabilities after a period of, I think, 2½ years. I hope he is not being too optimistic in that. I can see the day when the Minister will come in here with a similar measure to allow Bord na Móna off. If I had my way, I should much prefer to see the Minister cross off the whole amount due, thereby giving the Board an opportunity to get off on a new footing, without looking forward to the day when they will have to come back and meet their liabilities. The biggest worry they will have, if they have to come back to meet their liabilities, will be the payment of interest, not the repayment of capital.</P>
    <P>We are glad, of course, that the Board has got a breathing space and we hope they will be lucky with the weather because all the operations of the Board depend on the weather. If the weather is good, it is only natural to expect that they will continue to make some profits during the period they have for, as it were, drawing breath.</P>
    <P>The Minister is disappointed with the sale of briquettes. I am not a bit surprised at that. The fuel is an excellent fuel but most of the cookers in the country are not suitable for the burning of peat briquettes; neither are the open fires. On a winter's night one would want two bales of briquettes to keep a fire going. In an ordinary standard range, one would want two to three bales of briquettes a day.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford) Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Longford):</i> Would the small sod be the answer?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyMcAuliffe" hpid="Mr. McAuliffe Mr. McAuliffe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McAuliffe</NameTxt>
      <P>The Fóidín: I said that was out. If briquettes are to be a success in cookers, people will have to <Col N="1539" /> change the type of cooker. Briquettes are bought in small quantities to help light fires or get fires going. They are clean fuel, but they are too expensive. I think most of the problem would be solved for Bord na Móna if the ESB paid an economic price for milled peat. I am told the price paid is not economic. If that is the case, then the Minister should do something to ensure that Bord na Móna gets an economic price for its fuel. We welcome the Bill and we trust that in a couple of years time we will be looking at a brighter picture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFlanagan" hpid="Mr. Flanagan Mr. Flanagan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flanagan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to make a few comments on this very important subject. In the first place, the whole concept of peat production is based on two main requirements. The first is the production of fuel and the second is the giving of employment. From that point of view, everybody in this House must support this measure. At the same time, one must learn by the mistakes that have been made, if mistakes have been made. If mistakes have not been made, well and good.</P>
      <P>I cannot accept the idea of charging a higher price to the ESB as any solution at all because, if a higher price is charged to the ESB, that higher price will ultimately be passed on to the electricity consumer and the net result will be that one will pay one way or the other. I am particularly interested in the appointment of consultants. I think there have been too many changes in the method of turf production. Somebody is to blame for that. Steps have been taken too quickly, without those responsible being absolutely satisfied that the result desired would be achieved. Somebody is to blame. I know that there are some of the best brains and some of the best engineers in the country in Bord na Móna. Knowing that, I cannot understand why or how they could allow themselves to be influenced into changing from one method of production to another. All the changes have resulted in very serious loss to the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I remember the early days when people like Professor Pearse Purcell, <Col N="1540" /> the late Ned Duffy of Meath and others were on the Turf Development Board. They were men of the highest intelligence and of the highest integrity. Bord na Móna was established after the Second World War. In the beginning, excellent fuel was turned out by macerating the entire face of the bog and turning out fuel which was spread out over 100 feet. The sod was very irregular in shape but never since have they produced a better fuel. It was an excellent fuel. Experiments were then carried out in connection with milled peat. Some of these were carried out in my own county, just north of Bangor Erris. In a good year, I was told it would be possible to turn out five, and probably six, crops of milled peat in the year from one surface. I wonder how did results, even during the best of those five bad years, compare with that prognosis. The particular bog was well drained. It was blanket bog as distinct from the deep bog in the midlands. Possibly conditions were quite favourable. I know that that particular summer was very fine. I could never understand how they arrived at an estimate of five to six crops in the year.</P>
    <P>When we were producing turf during the emergency period, we had a very limited period in which to produce sod turf. There was absolutely no hope of cutting and saving turf after 1st July and very little turf was produced until after the frosts of May. You were left then with the end of May, the months of June and July for cutting turf. Very little was cut in May. In very favourable bog conditions, we succeeded at that time in turning out two crops of sod turf, the second of which was harvested in that year in very few cases. To say that it would be possible to turn out five and, possibly, six crops in the year seemed to me to be very optimistic indeed. I wonder how that prognosis turned out.</P>
    <P>Suddenly, then, we sold off a great number of small machines which were used for producing sod turf. The future of milled peat seemed to be so good that machines were bought and, as far as I can understand &mdash; the Minister will correct me in this, if I am wrong, and I hope I am wrong&mdash;some of these <Col N="1541" /> machines were never even unpacked. They were sold. They were offered to county councils. Some were offered to my county and some were sold in the cases without ever having being opened or used. That changing about has resulted in mistakes and losses. I should like to know who have been responsible.</P>
    <P>I should like to suggest to the Minister that my experience has been that too much travelling abroad, too much seeing what they did in Russia and Poland in conditions which were not comparable with the conditions in our own country, has resulted in loss in production. If we have to have consultants set up. I hope they will be consultants from this country, consultants who will know something about the subject under investigation. I sincerely hope that when their findings are ultimately tabled in both Houses, we will decide then and there to go on from that, not to lose the capital that has been invested in bog drainage, and to give the best employment possible.</P>
    <P>When considering the question of the cost of peat production the fact must be taken into account that very many of those engaged in turf production live in areas where there is no other form of employment available. If they were not engaged in turf production they would probably be on the dole. In assessing the real cost of turf, one must take into account the difference between what people would be paid if they were on the dole and the amount paid to people in this country to produce something for the people living in this country.</P>
    <P>I support the measure wholeheartedly but I should like the proposed investigation to be thorough and to throw up the mistakes which there have undoubtedly been so that in future the mistakes may be corrected and we will have more economic production and greater production.</P>
    <P>Every time I come to Dublin, I see lorry loads of briquettes on their way to the West, to my own county. The Government should do something to try to compel people in the west of <Col N="1542" /> Ireland to use the resources of the west of Ireland. One must be cruel to be kind. I sent 330,000 tons of turf from Galway to Dublin during the war. It is a terrible thing to see at the present time foreign lorries using foreign petrol transporting to my county fuel which should be produced there. Something must be done about it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the House for their reception of this Bill. Senator Flanagan mentioned the disposal of surplus machines at the end of the war. In 1947 there was a fuel crisis and, as a result, it became necessary to get large semi-automatic machines and then when the full supply of British coal came into the country, which under our successive trade agreements cannot be tariffed, the machines became out-dated. They were not fully mechanised and there was absolutely no hope of making use of them for any modern form of peat production. That explains why they had to be disposed of.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator McDonald made references to the management of Bord na Móna and the management was referred to indirectly or directly by other speakers. I have known all the people in Bord na Móna and have been many times with the Board and have sat many times at meetings, not only with the Board, the chairman and the manager, but also with what might be described as informal meetings on the bog with the staff. I do not know of any more dedicated staff in the whole of this country. Every aspect of their operation has been examined by themselves and, in consultation with world famous consultants of the very highest order, such matters as the entire structure of the sales policy, market research into the likely demand for their various products and the examination of the whole of the maintenance of the machines. The footing machines, without which the cost of turf would be absolutely prohibitive, were invented by one of the engineers of Bord na Móna. The examination of the costings of the introduction of polythene, whether there would be a net saving after allowance for cost of material and implementation on the bog has been part of one of their many investigations. <Col N="1543" /> They have a complete research department which has been working for many years under a very practical scientific adviser who has now left for another post but he did very good work for Bord na Móna in his time.</P>
    <P>Every machine used by Bord na Móna was partly the result of examination of the results obtained abroad, in Germany and Denmark. The equipment either had to be completely designed here or else had to be adapted to allow for the surface of the Irish bogs being very, very soft. Members of the Seanad should read some of the documents of the research into the machines&mdash;the size, the shape of the channels through which the peat has to pass, the optimum speed of the machines, the difficulty involved in the generation of dust and moisture and the relation of the machines to the many different types of peat on the bog &mdash;because peat varies enormously in quality as everyone who comes from a peat area knows. The peat, for example, in the blanket bog of Mayo is different from some of the very light peats in the midlands. Quality of peat varies as bog is cut out and the peat at the top of the bog is quite different from the peat at the bottom of a bog 20 feet deep.</P>
    <P>The Seanad can be assured that Bord na Móna will not object to examination by a firm of consultants because they are confident that they have a splendid record with good management up to now, as I am also.</P>
    <P>Next about the question of peat moss litter. Peat moss is used for tomato production in this country. Peat moss exports and briquettes were valued at £727,000 in 1967 and peat moss exports increased by 15 per cent. A lot of the peat moss litter goes to Great Britain and the Channel Islands.</P>
    <P>The expected life of the bogs is 25-30 years. An Foras Talúntais is experimenting in the use of bog, in fertilisation, and the drainage and growing of crops. At Lullymore and Timahoe experiments are being undertaken. One of the likely crops will be, possibly, grass-meal. The improvement of soil which was mentioned by one Senator is being undertaken by research <Col N="1544" /> carried out by An Foras Talúntais in association with University College, Dublin and Trinity College. I myself doubt whether it will ever be economic to try to break up heavy clays by the admixture of peat. Maybe I am too pessimistic about it.</P>
    <P>There is also the question of using the lands of Bord na Móna that have ceased to produce peat for forestry and 550 acres have been taken over by the Department of Lands in Lyracrompane in Kerry. Senators may be interested to know, from the point of view of their descendants, that 100,000 acres of peat when fully exhausted, if entirely planted with trees at a cost of some £60 to £80 an acre, would yield eventually to our descendants £100 million in the value of the trees when they finally mature at the end of 50 years. We cannot take that into account in working out the finances in relation to Bord na Móna's present difficulties. It would be impossible.</P>
    <P>There is a suggestion box in Bord na Móna. A Senator asked about that. The task of the consultants will be to do a complete investigation into all aspects of the Board's operations&mdash;engineering, management and financial. The final terms of reference have not been decided and the firm have not yet been chosen but they will be definitely an efficient firm of consultants. Senator Miss Davidson asked why we did not initiate this Bill earlier. The reason is that we always hope for better weather and being in charge of the Meteorological Division I have read something about the history of weather.</P>
    <P>Weather information statistics were unreliable from before 1815 and much more reliable from 1880 but there have been cold weather cycles in Europe. In previous eras information was derived from logs of seamen and of ships' captains and from the naturalistic paintings of artists. The true statistical analyses have been since 1880, and there was a cold summer period for years after 1912. We have colder summers now. It is mostly a matter of cold summers, which do not affect tourism as much as wet summers, but slightly colder summers combined can make all the difference between a profit and a loss for Bord na Móna.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1545" /> Bord na Móna, in looking back on whatever reports they could have got from the Meteorological Office, were not rash in assuming that the weather cycle through which we were passing when they commenced operations was an unusually good one. We are introducing the Bill at the point which we think is essential. Senator Quinlan referred to the relationship between peat production for thermal power stations and the coming of nuclear energy. The milled peat and sod peat production will be declining in relation to thermally produced power in the next ten years and it will be of far less importance relative to the use of oil and nuclear energy by 1980. Therefore there is not any reason why we should not take the attitude that we should want to preserve employment on the bogs, as Senator Quinlan suggested, to avoid unnecessary payments outside for our fuel requirements and at the same time for Bord na Móna to be as efficient as possible in relation to weather conditions. It does not require any great philosophical analysis to produce a policy which is right in relation to the nation's needs.</P>
    <P>If the reverse were the situation, if peat were to have an increasingly greater part in the matter of our electricity supply, we would be in a very serious position because the cost of electricity here is reasonable, comparatively, in relation to other countries and it is very important that we should keep it so. The suggestion made that workers might invest in Bord na Móna shares would not be a suitable one to adopt because Bord na Móna operate a business like a copper mine or a coal mine which has a limited life and the money lent would be subject to redemption and repayment. I do not think Bord na Móna represent a suitable industry for investment of equity capital.</P>
    <P>Many references were made to the labour situation. I do not propose to enter that field because the causes of the strike are being investigated by the Minister for Labour. At the present time, as far as I can ascertain from the Minister for Labour, the wage levels there are comparable to those in similar industries. That is the position. <Col N="1546" /> My only comment on the whole matter is a very simple and human one&mdash;that in a great many cases if the decisions of the Labour Court were accepted by trade unions, in the long term of five years the effect in total employment or in family employment within the industry might be more advantageous than would sometimes be the case when Labour Court decisions are rejected. I do not think that that can be regarded as an unfair comment even by representatives of the trade unions who, I think, would also like to see the Labour Court regarded as the final court of appeal. We shall have the report of the Minister for Labour, and Bord na Móna are not worried that such an inquiry is being made.</P>
    <P>I wish to emphasise that the question of what the level of wages should be in Bord na Móna was not in any way related to the deficit, to the immediate disability of Bord na Móna to pay their way, and the fact that this Bill was not initiated when the strike took place had nothing whatever to do with the basic offer of Bord na Móna or with the decision of the Labour Court. I want to make that clear. There was no question of Bord na Móna being in a desperate position for money.</P>
    <P>Mention was made of briquettes by Senator McDonald. Briquettes were in short supply for many years. The price of loose briquettes for domestic use was increased by 10/- per ton from July, 1967. The price of baled briquettes remained unchanged during the past year. There is a fall-off in demand for solid fuel and Bord na Móna have initiated a sales campaign to sell the available supplies.</P>
    <P>Senator Miss Davidson and others asked whether four years is the maximum period of interest remission. This depends on the report of the firm of consultants and our attitude to the report and on the success Bord na Móna will have from the point of view of better weather. Senator Miss Davidson asked whether Bord na Móna should not sell milled peat to the ESB at the full cost of production. Oil prices have declined and I do not think it is a good idea for Bord na Móna to get the full cost of production in relation to the ESB because if they were <Col N="1547" /> allowed automatically to do so, simply because of poor weather conditions this might be a disincentive to the maintenance of the high productivity of the organisation.</P>
    <P>Senator Miss Davidson spoke about superannuation for workers. If the trade unions are prepared to increase the contributions to the superannuation fund it will be possible to increase the pensions. This is now under discussion between the unions and the Board and it is hoped that an equitable distribution of payments between the Board and the unions can be agreed on.</P>
    <P>The Russians came here in order to exchange views on processes and methods but some of the conditions applicable here would not apply to Russia because the climate is different and there are bogs in Russia which are the size of the whole of Ireland. Whereas they could learn from us and we from them, it is a matter of which particular factors apply to both countries. I believe myself there is no intrinsic built-in factor which will result in a perpetual deficit to Bord na Móna. I hope they will be able to get back to a profitable basis. The Fóidín experiment has not concluded, but so far has been reasonably successful. I have been informed of that very definitely by the Board and the area of bog cut each year is being extended.</P>
    <P>I am hopeful that the weather cycle will change. No one will notice this to any great extent. The ordinary people will not notice it unless they remember that they had a very slightly warmer summer feeling in the period before 1950. But it could make all the difference to the actual state of humidity on the bog surface. I might add that this actual state of humidity on the bog surface is a particular condition&mdash;the actual state of humidity of the particular particles on the bog in relation to changing weather.</P>
    <P>I thank the House for their reception of the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister give me any guarantee that the Board will pay farmers for land acquired?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1548" />
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry. I overlooked that question in my notes. My advice is that delay in payment for land is mostly due to title difficulties. If the Senator has any particular case in mind I will see to it that the managing director specially examines that case. I have had letters about this myself. In nearly every case it was quite clear that difficulties in ascertaining title were the cause of the delay in payment. Certainly, it had no relation to the Board's financial position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister look upon the broad future of Bord na Móna, not so much as that of running down a national asset but as a centre for group development and corporations within those areas and consequently something dynamic and vital for the time ahead, something people could invest in rather than a negative thing like a coppermine?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. O'Sullivan) Acting Chairman (Mr. O'Sullivan)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. O'Sullivan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot allow that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot accept the Minister's explanation in reply to my question. If the title was not in order the Board would not be able to acquire the property. If it was under a compulsory purchase order the title would not enter into it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Senator send me the case?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I will do that.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Turf Development Bill, 1968 (Certified" RHead="Money Bill): Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Turf Development Bill, 1968    (Certified Money Bill):    Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Bill put through Committee without recommendation and received for final consideration.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be returned to the Dáil&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to wish Bord na Móna well, now that they are getting this opportunity of a new <Col N="1549" /> lease of life. Despite what the Minister said I would appeal to the higher executives of the Board to listen a little more to people who are actively on the job. The Minister said there was a suggestion box in Bord na Móna, but unfortunately I find, from speaking to people employed by the Board, that if they make suggestions, they are liable to be out of employment. With more co-operation and a concerted effort, I believe Bord na Móna will be able to forge ahead as we would all wish it to.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Electricity (Supply) (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1968: Second Stage">
    <Title>Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Bill, 1968: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Minister for Transport and Power (Mr. Childers) Erskine Hamilton Childers">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Transport and Power (Mr. Childers)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the Bill is to authorise the increase to £50 million of the existing statutory limit of £42 million on the expenditure which the Electricity Supply Board may incur on the electrification of rural areas.</P>
      <P>Expenditure on the rural electrification scheme at 31st March, 1968 was nearly £41½ million and the Board will soon reach the existing statutory limit of £42 million. The Board is at present doing a systematic post-development scheme in the course of which all unconnected householders will have a further opportunity of taking supply. The increase of the limit to £50 million should enable the Board to complete the scheme. This will take another five years as the Board will have to go back over the areas already covered by the post-development scheme so that all householders will have an opportunity of taking supply at the improved terms recently announced. I shall refer to these improved terms later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The number of rural houses connected at 31st March, 1968 was 334,000, which is about 87 per cent of the estimated total of 384,000. By the time the scheme is completed, electricity at a reasonable cost will be available to 97½ per cent of rural homes and, on the ESB estimates, approximately 92 per cent of the existing total of rural houses will have <Col N="1550" /> accepted the terms offered. I may mention that, of the number not expected to take supply, nearly half could have it at the normal standard charges, that is to say, without any special service charges, and a great many others at very little more than the standard charges.</P>
    <P>The Government have been concerned to arrange that, within practical limits, electricity is available to the maximum number at reasonable charges. The ESB system of charges consists of a fixed charge, to meet the costs which arise from connecting the consumer to the supply, and a unit charge, which is the charge for the actual current used. The charge per unit is the same for all rural consumers. In some cases, because of the high cost of connection, the normal fixed charge, related to the size of the premises, is not sufficient to meet the annual fixed costs to the ESB and the ESB find it necessary to impose special service charges. The Government considered the question of these charges.</P>
    <P>It has been argued that special service charges should be abolished and that everyone in the country should be entitled to electricity at the same cost &mdash;on the analogy that letters are delivered at a flat rate to all rural as well as urban areas. However, this is not a valid comparison. The delivery of letters to isolated areas does not involve heavy capital outlay and substantial annual maintenance costs, irrespective of the use made of the service. A flat rate is therefore possible. In the case of the telephone service, however, which is comparable to electricity, in that it involves heavy capital costs, the customer in an isolated position has to pay an additional charge because of the extra costs involved in providing the service and then pays the standard rental and rate for calls made.</P>
    <P>Similarly an electricity consumer in an isolated position, who receives current at the standard rate, must expect to contribute to the extra high cost of connecting him to the electricity distribution system.</P>
    <P>If there were no special service charges the ESB would have to incur heavy capital expenditure in bringing <Col N="1551" /> supply to very isolated houses&mdash;in some cases the capital cost could be £1,000&mdash;and then receive an utterly inadequate revenue from the connection. In these areas the very substantial subsidy from taxpayers and consumers which would be incurred would be out of all proportion to the benefits received. Indeed the ESB have found that many of the isolated houses seem likely to be abandoned when the present occupancy ceases. The heavy capital expenditure involved in providing supply would in such cases be wasted. I may say that in one form or another special service charges are to be found in electricity tariffs the world over.</P>
    <P>Nevertheless, the Government are very conscious of the fact that the special service charges payable by some rural consumers were very high. It was estimated that at 31st March, 1967 there were about 22,500 unconnected houses the special service charges for which would add 50 per cent or more to their two-monthly fixed charges. I do not know what the upper limit might be, but over the 22,500 houses the average two-monthly fixed charge would amount to about five times the normal charge based on the size of the premises. The Government, therefore, have decided to reduce the level of special service charges. Where special service charges, as previously calculated, are over half the normal charges, reductions are being granted. The consumers who will gain most benefit are those who would have to pay the highest special service charges; in many cases these charges will be reduced by a half to two-thirds and even more in some cases. Those whose charges, as previously calculated, were only slightly over half the normal charges will gain small reductions; special service charges which are half or less of the normal fixed charges remain unchanged.</P>
    <P>To show clearly how much rural consumers are going to benefit, I think I should give the House some typical examples of the reductions which will result. The occupant of a county council cottage paying, two-monthly, 14/-fixed charge and £1 15s 6d special service <Col N="1552" /> charge will have his special service charge reduced to 11/5d. A consumer, similarly housed, but who because of higher connection costs, was previously liable for a special service charge of £2 12s will have it reduced to 16/-. A consumer with a medium-sized farm paying, two-monthly, £1 5s fixed charge and £2 14s special service charge will now pay a reduced special service charge of £1. A large farmer, with a fixed charge of £2 5s and a special service charge of £2 18s 4d will now pay a special service charge of £1 9s 11d. The House will see, therefore, that the reductions are quite substantial.</P>
    <P>These reductions are being introduced by agreement with the ESB and do not require amending legislation. It was therefore decided to introduce the revised terms immediately&mdash;as from 1st June, 1968, for new customers. Existing consumers will benefit from and including their accounts for the September/October and October/November billing periods. These are the earliest dates from which it is practical for the ESB to introduce the modified charges. By the end of the post-de velopment scheme, the reductions will add about £300,000 to the Board's annual loss on rural electrification. This will have to be borne by the Board's consumers generally and no increase in the statutory State subsidy payable to the ESB is contemplated.</P>
    <P>The ESB, while they are forbidden by law to make profits, are, also by law, required to avoid losses and the additional loss expected on the extension of rural electrification will require to be met by surplus revenue from existing consumers.</P>
    <P>Any householders who did not accept supply because of the high special service charges when the ESB were recanvassing their areas and who now wish to obtain connection, may get in touch with their local ESB offices. I think I should stress, however, that while some householders may be able to get supply at the revised terms without delay, people in general will find that they will have to wait until the ESB come to do their areas. In carrying out the post-development scheme, the ESB are recanvassing the country in a planned sequence of areas so as to <Col N="1553" /> ensure orderly development and to keep costs to a minimum. Any departure from the planned arrangements upsets the Board's programme and increases the costs involved. Preference for any area can be arranged only by delaying supply to other areas. It is clearly impossible for the ESB to connect immediately all who will now seek supply. The Board expect that it will take them nearly five years to give all unconnected householders in the country an opportunity to take supply at the revised terms.</P>
    <P>As I have explained, the new arrangements for rural electrification are going to mean substantial reductions for those who would have to pay high special service charges. There may be some householders, however, in areas isolated from the Board's network, who will consider even the reduced charges still too high. For these people we are increasing the subsidy for the installation of bottled gas to £35. The former subsidy of £10 was intended to provide only a basic installation. In this way it was the equivalent of the rural electrification subsidy which provides only for the connection of a premises as far as the meter, leaving wiring and fittings on the consumer's side of the meter to be provided by the consumer himself. The higher subsidy of £35 will pay for a more complete bottled gas installation. It should cover the basic equipment and three, or perhaps more, consumption points, depending on the circumstances, which may be used for lighting, heating, cooking or other appliances. This grant will be available to all rural householders whose special service charges for electricity, under the revised terms, would still be more than 100 per cent of the normal charges. Enquiries about the increased grant, which does not require amending legislation, should be addressed to my Department.</P>
    <P>While the cost of rural electrification is high, the benefits to the rural population are considerable. It has spread the amenities of modern living all over the country. This is clearly illustrated by the fact that there are now 140,000 television sets, 240,000 electric irons, 160,000 electric kettles as well as many thousand washing machines, electric <Col N="1554" /> cookers, refrigerators and storage heaters in rural homes. On the other hand, electricity has provided the rural population with greater opportunities for relaxation to enjoy these benefits, with the aids which it has made available for easier farming and simultaneous increased farm productivity. In milking, for instance, the use of electrical milking machines has increased from about 18,000 in 1963-64 to nearly 30,000 at present. There has also been an increase in the use of electric milk coolers. Piped water is, of course, essential for efficient farming operations and this is easily provided by electricity; about 60,000 electric water pumps have now been installed.</P>
    <P>I think I need say no more about the benefits of rural electrification. As I have said, the purpose of the Bill is to authorise the ESB to incur the capital expenditure necessary to complete the current post-development scheme. The present proportion of rural households connected, 87 per cent, must be considered very good when one has regard to the fact that our farmhouses tend to be isolated and not sited in groups as in some countries. Over the next five years we expect to raise the proportion to about 92 per cent, with connection available to many other houses which could bring the total even closer to 100 per cent. At that stage we should be among the most advanced countries in the matter of rural electrification. In fact with the revised charges and the continuation of the subsidy, the Government is seeing to it that practically every unconnected householder in the country will now be able to enjoy the benefits of electricity on reasonable terms.</P>
    <P>I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I certainly welcome this Bill, as it deals with matters that have interested me for quite a number of years. I congratulate the Minister on at last bringing the benefits of the rural electrification network and the modern aids that come in its wake to the last remaining few people deemed, up to now, to be uneconomic electricity consumers. I want to pay a special tribute to the ESB as a body <Col N="1555" /> since they have been so eminently successful. Looking at them from my own county, it is nice to see them comprised of public-spirited men, with officials and employees taking a very active interest in the community in which they live.</P>
      <P>Apart from this Bill, I want to compliment the ESB on their initiative in organising a special junior effort in regard to the Tidy Towns competition. This may be far removed from the Bill but it indicates the spirit of the ESB employees, people who have their work at heart and are so helpful to the public. It is this spirit of co-operation and goodwill that one meets in an ESB office that means so much to their success. One can only wish that other semi-State organisations would take a leaf out of the book of the ESB; it would be bound to achieve the same result.</P>
      <P>I welcome especially the provisions in the Bill whereby the supplementary charges for rural electrification are being met to some extent. I am not clear as to whether this includes the odd case where a Land Commission estate is divided and you have an unfortunate farmer saddled with a huge mansion and a correspondingly huge bimensal charge. In many cases I know that the ESB officials have agreed to accept the sealing of one or two floors of a big Georgian dwelling and not take other floor area into account. Perhaps the Minister would be good enough to let me know whether or not that will be included in his revised charges in the October-November period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like to avail of this opportunity to compliment the ESB and the staff in Portlaoise on the great work in the new techniques they have developed down there in handling and working on live lines. These things do not get sufficient acknowledgment, but they show the progressive attitude and the strides that are being made. The one thing on which the ESB might go a little easy is the large sums of money they spend each year on advertising. One would think the ESB had not a monopoly of electrification to judge by the vast sums of money they spend on <Col N="1556" /> both television and other advertising. I wonder if this money could not be spent on other methods of helping to provide a cheaper service.</P>
    <P>I should like the Minister to be a little more explicit on the ceiling he envisages for the new special service charge. It was not too clear as he was reading his statement. He also mentioned, and has given some examples of the new charges, and I wonder if he could lay before the House fuller details of the scheme which he seems to have fully worked out at this time.</P>
    <P>The increase in the bottled gas subsidy is a little more realistic. The old scheme whereby £10 was made available was not very attractive, and it was availed of very little by the public. The subsidy of £35 should be a greater inducement because it would be possible to have, perhaps, a cooking point and a few lights installed for the £35, and the more remote areas may find it easier to avail of it.</P>
    <P>One of the better points in this Bill is the fact that people who have been paying very high special service charges in order to avail of the ESB network can expect some easement of the situation in the autumn. The number of branches in which the ESB are now operating in rural Ireland is certainly something to be admired. Their work in the field of rural electrification and the service they give to promoters of group water schemes in providing free of charge the plans of operations on different charts is something that to a great extent goes unnoticed. The public relations in the Board must not be really on the job because the good work they have been doing over the past few years for the rural community has got scant recognition whereas the decision on their new office block in Dublin seems to have got a whole lot of adverse publicity.</P>
    <P>We have in the ESB a body of dedicated men, especially the linesmen whom I marvel at in the winter time, attending to breakdowns so very efficiently and in all weathers. These people are certainly not in the higher income brackets. I am certainly not in the labour relations movement but I do know there is there a great sense of dedication in regard to the 24-hour <Col N="1557" /> breakdown service the ESB give. The fact that one very seldom meets a bad humoured ESB man when he comes out&mdash;at least I do not meet any down my way&mdash;and the promptness with which breakdowns are undertaken are things I have always admired. It goes to show that the ESB must have a contented staff, and I sincerely hope that the Board will do all they can to keep them in that happy condition.</P>
    <P>There were a few other points I meant to mention, one of them being the principle of the Turf Development Bill relating to the transfer of the burden of the special charges from the user of electricity to the taxpayer. In the case of rural electrification the Minister proposes to increase the burden on the electricity users outside the rural areas, and I should like to know why the Government should not provide the subsidy directly from the Exchequer rather than in the way the Minister proposes to do it.</P>
    <P>I should like again to underline the very great social service the ESB are engaged on and the great service they are rendering to the community. Because so much of the economics of Irish agriculture are tied up with the cost of electricity, and having regard to the fact that the price structure of so many farm crops has not changed or improved in the past 12 months, it is to be hoped that the Minister or the Board do not contemplate an increase this year in the price of the unit of electricity.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyMcAuliffe" hpid="Mr. McAuliffe Mr. McAuliffe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McAuliffe</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to welcome the Bill. Anyone who comes from a rural area knows the advantages of rural electrification, and I was not one bit surprised that the Minister gave us a fairly detailed account of those advantages. Everything he said about it was quite true. Anyone who gets electricity, no matter how poor he is, will tell you he would prefer to do without a couple of meals a day than have the electricity cut off. That in itself shows the advantage of having proper light in a house.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister is aware that most of the people who have not got electricity in those areas are poor people. He has gone a good way towards meeting <Col N="1558" /> them, and I am sure the demand from the people in those areas who have not the advantage of electricity will be very great. It is a bit disappointing that it will take five years to supply electricity to all who are likely to apply for it. We know there is quite an amount of development going on at present in areas which did not look economic at one time but which are now considered to be economic.</P>
    <P>The Minister said it will cost about £300,000, and in the next sentence, he said it will have to be borne by the Board's consumers. That gave us a slight fright but in the next sentence he said the ESB are required to avoid losses and that the additional loss expected on the extension of rural electrification will require to be met by surplus revenue from existing customers. I consider it a great concession that there is to be no increase in the present rate of electricity to provide electricity for these other areas.</P>
    <P>I certainly welcome the Bill and I am sure there is no one in the country who will not welcome its provisions. I entirely agree with everything in it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to welcome the Bill briefly and to pay tribute to the great benefit which rural electrification has been to the countryside. It is almost impossible to think back now to less than 20 years ago when the greater part of the countryside was without electricity. There has been a great achievement in that period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I suggest that a five years delay seems rather long. I know it is in keeping with the systematic approach to these areas. I would suggest to the Minister that he could make it easy for the people in those areas during the five years while they are awaiting electricity, if they could avail in some way of the bottled gas scheme. Until these remote areas are connected, it is highly desirable that they should have some stand-by scheme. This is not possible under the present Bill, but if the Minister saw fit he could encourage the giving of a gas scheme prior to connection, and when the connection is made, perhaps half of the cost of the gas scheme could be recouped. It might be possible to work out some compromise <Col N="1559" /> for the future. It is rather difficult for those in the remote areas to have to wait five years for connection. There may be a tourist potential which could be profitably developed over the next five years.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the House for their enthusiastic reception of the Bill. Senator McDonald asked about the effect of the provisions of the Bill on farmers owning very large houses. The fixed charge will not be affected in any way. It will remain the same. It is the special service charges only that will be altered, and reduced in the circumstances which I have indicated. The reduction will apply in all cases where the special service charges are more than 50 per cent of the basic fixed charges as previously calculated. There is no upper limit or ceiling in relation to this charge which can be reduced to one-third of the previous charges.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Having regard to the fact that the ESB loss on rural consumption will increase, perhaps the Seanad would like to have some figures. If the Government provided all the extra capital required to facilitate these additional fixed charges, the extra loss to the ESB to instal electricity in the rural dwellings we estimate to be £205,000 at the end of five years. As we are not providing the extra capital, the loss would be £305,000, so the difference is £100,000 in connection with loss on rural consumption. This extra loss of £305,000 represents over a five-year period 1.13 per cent of the total value of sales of electricity, so it is not very much. There is already a loss of £1½ million on rural electricity which is subsidised by urban consumption. Again in relation to total revenue of £30 million that is not an excessive figure. If by any chance we find at the end of two years that even this slight total additional annual loss might affect the ESB in any way, I will be prepared to go back to the Government and ask them to make some contribution additional to the present one of 75 per cent of the cost or £75, whichever is less, for any single rural connection. That subsidy is also applied to system improvement, an improvement of the <Col N="1560" /> system in general as consumption increases and long lines have to be erected in order to supply rural consumption.</P>
    <P>I think I have answered all the questions except one. I am afraid we do not make bottled gas available for a temporary period. As in the case of many other things, we do our best about social and economic improvements, but a bottled gas subsidy would apply only to those whose special service charges are over 100 per cent of the fixed charges.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that by excluding these people who have Land Commission houses, he is leaving them with no hope? The houses I am thinking of normally have £7, £8 or £11 bimensal charges. They are 30 to 50 acre Land Commission houses, but the Minister must know that you cannot farm unless you have electricity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to do a lot of things like that but I have discovered by long experience of comparing electricity charges here and in other countries that it is terribly important to have mathematically exact calculations made in relation to fees and charges for electricity. The system must be worked out exactly and it is too complicated to take the House into it now. Even the charges that are being made in this Bill must be absolutely fair and equitable with no exception of any particular class of person.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Bill," RHead="1968: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Bill, 1968: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I should still like to press the Minister on this point of the farmers, even where estates are divided. Surely, out of this additional money being provided under section 2, it would be possible to include the <Col N="1561" /> minority of people who, in the first instance, thought they were lucky in being allocated farms by the Land Commission but subsequently found it uneconomic to pay £11 and £12 bimensal electrical charge. Surely, with this additional allocation, the Minister should find it possible to give these people at least some hope that they can connect their premises to the network?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>It cannot be done under this Bill. The ESB is forbidden by law to make preferential charges to anybody in the community. I think it is just as well. I am very sorry I cannot accede to the Senator's request.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 3 and 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>As we have now reached 10 p.m. and have not yet started on another Bill perhaps the House would agree to adjourn at its usual hour?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We fixed on 11 p.m. today on the Order of Business. As I explained to the Seanad, the reason is to enable us to finish this programme so that, in due course, we can go into recess not later than 1st August.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>It is coming to a very late hour, you will agree, to start into a new and quite important Bill&mdash; the Tourist Traffic Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan) Acting Chairman (Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The decision of the House was taken on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>Who agreed to that on the Order of Business?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we to sit beyond 11 p.m.?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Until 11 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1562" />
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>Who made the agreement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot help it if the Senator was not here. The House agreed to it on the Order of Business. There was no objection.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Tourist Traffic Bill, 1968 (Certified" RHead="Money Bill): Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Tourist Traffic Bill, 1968    (Certified Money Bill):    Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Minister for Transport and Power (Mr. Childers) Erskine Hamilton Childers">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Transport and Power (Mr. Childers)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the Bill is, firstly, to authorise an increase in the existing statutory limit on the aggregate amount which may be paid to Bord Fáilte for the giving of grants for the development of holiday accommodation and, secondly, to repeal the provision in the Tourist Traffic Act, 1959, which restricted payments to Bord Fáilte for grants for the development of holiday accommodation and major tourist resorts to a period of ten years from the date of the passing of that Act.</P>
      <P>Provision was made in the Tourist Traffic Act, 1959, for the payment to Bord Fáilte of such sums not exceeding in the aggregate £500,000, as the Board might require for the giving of grants for the development of holiday accommodation. The limit of £500,000 was raised to £1.5 million by the Tourist Traffic Act, 1963, and to £3 million by the Tourist Traffic Act, 1966. The total amount issued to Bord Fáilte at 31st March, 1968, was £2,630,000 which left a balance of £370,000 in the authorised amount of £3 million. The amount to be voted in the present financial year is £800,000 and amending legislation is necessary to authorise payments in excess of £370,000 in the present financial year and to provide for payments in future years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>From the funds provided for the development of holiday accommodation, Bord Fáilte operate a scheme of grants to encourage the provision of additional holiday accommodation and the improvement of existing accommodation. Although reasonably good progress had been made in the provision of accommodation since the 1959 Act <Col N="1563" /> was passed, an investigation of accommodation requirements carried out by Bord Fáilte in 1965 revealed that a much quicker rate of growth was required to cater for the increase in tourist traffic. The Board calculated that it would be necessary to provide 2,000 additional bedrooms each year up to and including 1970 of which 1,500 should be provided in registered hotels and guesthouses and 500 in supplementary accommodation.</P>
    <P>As it was clear that the required rate of growth could not be achieved on the basis of the existing incentives, I authorised Bord Fáilte in April, 1967, to provide substantially increased incentives for the development of holiday accommodation. Prior to that date the general level of grants was of the order of 20 per cent. Apart from the fact that the level of the grants has been generally increased the scheme has been modified in the light of experience to provide for greater flexibility in the provision of financial assistance. Accordingly, Bord Fáilte are now authorised to determine, within certain specified maxima, the level of grant appropriate to each case taking account of all relevant factors including the location of the premises and the adequacy of existing accommodation in the area, the type of accommodation being provided, the price level, the market demand, the prospects of off-season business, the estimated cost of development and the background of the developer.</P>
    <P>The current scheme of grants provides for the payment of up to 35 per cent of the total construction cost of new hotels in the western counties. In other remote areas the maximum grant is 25 per cent of total construction cost.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Notice taken that 12 Members were not present; House counted and 12 Members being present,</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator McDonald should consult his superiors before he starts a filibuster like this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not saying anything at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1564" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator McDonald is quite entitled to call for a quorum. A quorum is now present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrowne2" hpid="Mr. Browne Mr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>We would not let him away that easily.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>If he wants to play it that way, we can play it, too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>Where the total construction grants do not apply, grants up to a maximum of 50 per cent of the cost of new hotel bedrooms are provided in the western counties and 40 per cent elsewhere. Grants up to 30 per cent are provided for dining areas, kitchens and stores in hotels in the West and 20 per cent elsewhere. There are also grants for hotel staff accommodation and for the provision of recreational facilities for hotel guests. Guesthouses in all areas are eligible for grants up to 20 per cent of the cost of new bedrooms, provided at least five guest bedrooms are available on completion of the project. Caravan and camping sites are eligible for grants up to a maximum of 50 per cent of the cost of site development and amenity works subject to a maximum grant of £20,000 per site. There are grants also for the provision and improvement of youth hostels and for improvement works in colleges and similar institutions providing accommodation for visitors during vacation periods.</P>
      <P>The increase in the level of grants has resulted in an increase in the amount which has to be provided each year to Bord Fáilte for the purposes of the scheme. For instance, the amount provided in 1965-66 was £255,000; in 1966-67 it was £500,000; in 1967-68 it was £700,000; and in the present financial year the amount required to finance the scheme is £800,000.</P>
      <P>Since the scheme was introduced in 1959 it has stimulated an investment of £15 million by private enterprise in holiday accommodation. The number of bedrooms in registered hotels and guesthouses has increased from 17,200 in 1960 to 24,000 in the present year, an increase of almost 40 per cent. There has also been a significant improvement in the standards of accommodation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The increased incentives introduced <Col N="1565" /> in April, 1967, have had an immediate response from promoters. Figures available for the 1st January, 1968, showed that there was a net increase of almost 1,300 bedrooms in hotels and guesthouses in 1967 although the increased grants were available for less than nine months of the year. Continued expansion and improvement of accommodation will be necessary to cater for the increasing number of tourists and there will be a particular need to cater for motoring visitors. The number of passenger accompanied cars brought directly to ports in the State increased from 10,000 in 1959 to 68,000 in 1967. Bord Fáilte estimate that by 1970 about 150,000 cars will arrive directly and a further 100,000 through Six County ports.</P>
    <P>The present range of grants will fall due for review in 1969 but there is no doubt that a continuation of financial assistance will be necessary to secure the required rate of expansion. Already a large number of projects are being planned for the coming years and Bord Fáilte anticipate that the target of 1,500 additional bedrooms in registered hotels and guesthouses will be achieved in each of the next three years.</P>
    <P>I am, accordingly, proposing that the present statutory limit of £3 million for the giving of grants for the development of holiday accommodation should be increased by £2.5 million to £5.5 million. On the basis of information at present available this increase should be sufficient to provide for accommodation grants up to 31st March, 1971. I should explain that the purpose of this provision is to obtain the general approval of the Oireachtas for the financing of the accommodation development scheme. The amount to be provided each year will fall to be voted by the Dáil in the normal way under the Vote for the Department of Transport and Power.</P>
    <P>Although there has been a substantial increase in registered hotel and guesthouse accommodation since 1960 &mdash;from 17,200 bedrooms in 1960 to 24,000 in the present year&mdash;the increase in supplementary accommodation has been more significant. The number of bedrooms in supplementary accommodation included in Bord Fáilte lists increased from 815 in 1960 <Col N="1566" /> to 8,400 in the present year. The increase in A star and A hotel bedrooms has been 68 per cent in this period; in other accommodation the increase has amounted to 82 per cent.</P>
    <P>In addition to providing for an increase in the statutory limit on the amount to be provided for the development of holiday accommodation, the Bill also contains a provision to repeal a restriction contained in the Tourist Traffic Act, 1959, which limited the payment of funds for the development of holiday accommodation and major tourist resorts to a period of ten years from the date of passing of that Act. I consider that the annual debate on the Vote for my Department and the fact that legislation is required every two or three years to authorise an increase in the aggregate amount provides sufficient control over the administration of the scheme without imposing a specific time limit.</P>
    <P>The ten year limitation applies not only to payments for the development of holiday accommodation but also to payments for the development of major tourist resorts. The aggregate amount to be provided for the development of major tourist resorts was increased to £3.25 million by the Tourist Traffic Act, 1966. The total amount issued at 31st March, 1968, was just over £1.5 million. As the amount being provided in the current financial year is £400,000 it is now clear that there will be a considerable balance remaining in the authorised amount of £3.25 million at the expiration of the ten year period in August, 1969. It is intended to undertake a second programme for the development of major tourist resorts when the works at present in hands have been completed, and, in the circumstances, I have no doubt that Senators will agree to the removal of the time limitation so that the major resort development scheme can be continued after August, 1969.</P>
    <P>The further development of the tourist industry depends to a very great extent on the availability of an adequate supply of holiday accommodation. There are good grounds for believing that the incentive scheme now in operation will achieve the rate of growth required to cater for the anticipated increase in demand. It is <Col N="1567" /> equally important that the major resort development scheme should be continued. Bord Fáilte are at present embarking on a policy of promoting year-round tourism and the development of this policy will give rise to an increasing demand for entertainment and recreation facilities.</P>
    <P>There is no need for me to remind Senators of the importance of the tourist industry to the national economy. Since 1959 the income from tourism and travel has risen from £39.4 million to £84.3 million in 1967. During the period of the Second Programme for Economic Expansion tourist income at constant money values rose at a rate of 5.5 per cent a year. I am confident that this rate of growth can be maintained and possibly increased provided the necessary resources and facilities are made available. The purpose of this Bill is to enable these resources to be made available and I, accordingly, confidently recommend the Bill for the approval of the Seanad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill but perhaps the Minister would explain what appears to me to be an inconsistency. He said that the number of bedrooms had increased from 17,200 in 1960 to 24,000 in the present year, an increase of almost 40 per cent, and later on he said that the number of bedrooms in supplementary accommodation included in Bord Fáilte lists show that the increase in A star and A hotel bedrooms had been 68 per cent in this period, and in other accommodation the increase amounted to 82 per cent. There appears to be some inconsistency there. This is a very important piece of legislation because the tourist industry accounts for a considerable portion of our national income, and I still think that it is regrettable that we should rush this measure through, almost burning the midnight oil to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are many small points which are annoying people engaged in the industry as well as tourists and the Minister should use his good offices to try to effect an improvement. A common complaint is that restaurants with wine <Col N="1568" /> licences are unable to serve Gaelic coffee with a meal. There must be some alteration in the regulations to enable this to be done. Tourists regard Gaelic coffee as a feature of our meals and sometimes they cannot understand why it cannot be served and they are inclined to look down on the establishment which is unable to serve Irish coffee. Surely it should be possible to introduce an amendment to the licensing laws so that a restaurant owner would be enabled to serve Irish coffee as part of a full meal? There should also be dispensing licences available to all restaurants that need them.</P>
    <P>Again and again we are told that the tourist industry is our second major industry. Yet, we find small matters like this which seem to be insurmountable obstacles. Surely it should be possible for the Government to introduce legislation to make the situation easier for all concerned? It is ludicrous that people should not be allowed to serve a drink to those waiting for a meal.</P>
    <P>I hope the moneys being provided under this Bill, or some part of them, will be earmarked for farm guesthouses which have provided a tremendous amount of supplementary accommodation over the past few years. Latterly it appears to me that these guesthouses are being frowned on in some quarters. I think that is a pity.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>We are getting somewhat away from the Bill. Farmhouse accommodation comes under a separate heading. It has nothing to do with this Bill at all. Neither have the licensing laws anything to do with the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely they are matters related to tourism?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>It was agreed two years ago, when changes were made in relation to the Appropriation Bill and the Finance Bill, that Senators would have an opportunity of discussing legislation before the House a little more fully. That was, I think, understood. If there is to be a change now, we should, I think, have notice of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nothing to stop the Senator on the Appropriation Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1569" />
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>But this is not the Appropriation Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It will come in due course.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>But we will not have the Minister in charge of the tourist industry here on that Bill.</P>
      <P>There is one thing I find it rather difficult to understand as a member of the regional midland tourist board. Some counties seem to benefit more than other counties from the various grants given by Bord Fáilte. The counties that benefit most are those west of the Shannon. I find this a little inconsistent. One can have two guesthouses, one in Offaly and one in Roscommon, with a completely different scale of grants. Surely it should have been possible initially to have rules and regulations applying all round? I should like the Minister to ensure that regional boards will have a little more autonomy from the point of view of being allowed a little more flexibility in the expenditure of their annual budget. The scope of the directors, in my experience, is curbed somewhat when it comes to spending money in any particular direction. I think that is bad, particularly when one remembers that these directors are expected to travel 50 and 60 miles to meetings and get no subsistence or travelling expenses. Possibly too much is being asked of these people and the day may come when these regional tourist boards will be comprised solely of people actively engaged in the industry itself, people who will have a self-interest in the industry. I think that would be bad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Laois, my own county, seems to be the Cinderella of the tourist industry. We have got very little from Bord Fáilte. The only grant Bord Fáilte ever gave to Laois was the grant of £1,100 this year towards the museum for old steam engines at Stradbally opened by the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister some weeks back. I think the Parliamentary Secretary was not aware of the fact that the occasion was unique. Laois has fared very badly. Every county should have a reasonable share of whatever is going. We should, in Laois, get special grants to provide <Col N="1570" /> hotel accommodation. We need some boost to the industrial life of the county. We should qualify for grants on the same generous scale as do the counties west of the Shannon. I think regional tourist boards should get a better allocation of grants. Is that possible under this measure?</P>
    <P>One thing that worries me is the fact that Bord Fáilte always send their own officers overseas on tourist promotion and these people, in my opinion, are inclined to sell the popular resorts, like Killarney, Connemara and Donegal. Other regions receive scant mention by these people when they go abroad. It is in the interests of the less popular tourist areas that these regions should be allowed to send one of their officials overseas on tourist promotion. The manager of the midlands regional tourist organisation should be seconded to Bord Fáilte and should represent the area on these promotional tours, especially tours to Britain, in order to highlight the excellent facilities available in the area for holidaymakers.</P>
    <P>This is something that perhaps may not seem important but I defy contradiction when I state that the people whom we send out from Bord Fáilte to Europe and America for the purpose of attracting tourists to this country endeavour to sell only the well-known holiday resorts I have mentioned. This is a wrong approach and I would ask the Minister to ensure that every part of the country gets fair representation. The various local authorities endeavour to pay the annual subscriptions in respect of tourism and unless there is a reasonable opportunity of a return on their investment, justice is not done.</P>
    <P>I would ask the Minister to ensure that at the end of this season, when programmes for promotional tours are recommencing for the autumn and winter months, managers or, perhaps, some of the officials from the various regions should be given an opportunity of selling their own regions as tourist areas.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has been repeating that statement very frequently. Repetition is not in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1571" />
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I was only endeavouring to stress the point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Repetition is still not in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>With the introduction of the car ferry service we are, apparently, getting a greater percentage of English tourists, the majority of whom are not so very interested in expensive A star and Grade A hotel accommodation and perhaps we have sufficient of this type of accommodation for the time being. Bord Fáilte should for a few years emphasise the necessity of providing adequate B and C type accommodation which tourist class people from the British midlands would appear to favour. A change of policy on the part of Bord Fáilte would have this effect.</P>
      <P>There is the problem of the shortness of the tourist season. If too much Grade A accommodation is provided, it will only aggravate redundancy or unemployment during the winter months, which is not a very good result.</P>
      <P>In regard to the hotel apprenticeship scheme, there has been some disquiet and a suggestion that boys and girls training for positions in the hotel industry were being to some degree exploited. I have heard this mentioned in more than one place. I should like the Board and the Minister to investigate the matter so that the House and those concerned can be reassured that these trainees are receiving adequate training and that their hours of work are reasonable.</P>
      <P>Most of the points I had prepared would not appear to meet with the approval of the Minister at this hour of the night and so I shall leave them over for the Appropriation Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>In this Bill we are authorising the increase in the money that will be allocated to Bord Fáilte from £3 million to £5½ million. We are therefore entitled to discuss in this House the whole policy of Bord Fáilte which means, in effect, the whole national policy in regard to tourist promotion. However, I can assure the <Col N="1572" /> House that I do not intend to do that.</P>
      <P>We have had a special plug for County Laois. There are some other 25 counties and I hope we are not going to have special plugs for each of them. My own county of Cork has so many natural beauties that it does not need any special plug.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>What is that but a special plug?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>What I want to say very quickly is that Bord Fáilte are to be congratulated on the work they have been doing and associated with that would be the efforts of Aer Lingus and CIE to help in the promotion of the tourist industry. The need now is to get across to the ordinary people of the country that tourism is something that affects them individually. It is not something that affects the Grade A hotels solely; it is a major industry which affects the standard of living of all of us. I should like to see greater appreciation of that fact throughout the country. Bord Fáilte have already taken steps by the promotion of regional tourist development areas and the appointment of regional officers to bring the importance of tourism to the notice of local people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I hope that Bord Fáilte will continue in their efforts. It is very easy to pick up small points of criticism. We can all crib about something or other. My crib at the moment is the dirt of Dublin streets, which are a disgrace to the capital city. This affects tourism. We can all have a particular crib about some service or other, about what Bord Fáilte should do about this, that or the other thing, but it is fair to say that, overall, they have been reasonably successful. From what I know of them, they are an enterprising, energetic group of people and they certainly need to be because tourism is a very competitive industry. We like to assume that we are very busy promoting the development of the tourist industry here and that no other country is thinking of tourism. In fact, that is not the case. Every country attaches particular importance to its tourist industry. We are in a very competitive field. In the competitive field in which we have <Col N="1573" /> been engaged we have been reasonably successful and in approving of the Bill, I wish to convey that and to express the hope that Bord Fáilte will be as successful and as energetic in future as they have been in the past.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, wish to commend the Bill, which represents a substantial investment in an industry which is of vital importance to the economic future of the country. There is no doubt that there has been a very dramatic growth in the tourist industry in recent years, and that the availability of more hotel accommodation has been quite a factor in this. However, there are other developments which have also played a part. For instance, in my part of the country we have had considerable development of horse caravan tours which have been distinctly successful. Advertising of this form of holiday transport in European newspapers last year seems to have paid off considerable dividends. The people who visited were extremely pleased with this unique method of transport. The comfort of this was appreciated as well as which this mode of travel gave these people an opportunity of meeting our people and the friendliness of our people in city, town and country is one of the great assets we have. It was appreciated very much by foreign visitors especially.</P>
      <P>Bord Fáilte have assisted to a great extent in the development of the Tidy Towns competition and I am glad to see that some points I have made here in previous years have reached fruition&mdash;certain ideas I put forward in the matter of the allocation of the prizes in this competition. However, there is need for a better liaison between the Minister for Transport and Power and the Minister for Local Government in these matters; in the provision of better amenities, particularly water supplies and sewerage schemes, some of which are still extremely primitive in many of our important resorts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There has been, for instance, abandonment of many regional schemes, though the local authorities were diverted from the provision of smaller water supply schemes which might have sufficed, pending the implementation <Col N="1574" /> of the regional projects. The virtual abandonment of these schemes means there is a backlog to be made up and there is serious concern about the lack of such civilised amenities. This has been commented on adversely by visitors to certain areas in my county and elsewhere. There is therefore an urgent need for the Minister for Local Government to announce the promotion of substantial investment in the provision of these essential amenities because their lack leaves a very poor impression on visitors.</P>
    <P>Some time ago I appealed to the Minister to provide us with a tourist office in Bandon. This was not done, and locally we formed an organisation and entirely from our own resources this year we provided an office and staffed it. The results have proved the necessity for such an office in Bandon and we have now been assured that next year Bord Fáilte will staff a permanent tourist office in the town. I hope that promise will be honoured.</P>
    <P>Another development by Bord Fáilte has been the introduction of a scheme for students from abroad who wish to learn English here. They are to be accommodated in homes in this country. My town has been successful this year in getting a group of these students and I consider it an excellent acquisition. In most of those homes there are children of similar age groups and it gives them an opportunity to converse in the language of the students and vice versa. When these foreign children return to their homes, I hope they will carry happy memories of their association with Irish people and that in consequence not only will they return but that their parents and relatives will also be encouraged to visit us.</P>
    <P>Tourist traffic has been considerably increased by the introduction of car ferries and this has been to the benefit of areas not heretofore regarded as having tourist interest. They are now being acknowledged as being good places in which to spend holidays.</P>
    <P>In the past we have been directing attention to the luxury type hotel accommodation, losing sight of the fact that the most important type of tourist we get is the ordinary working person from England. Such people are happy <Col N="1575" /> to come here and they are of more benefit to us, from the point of view of the money spent, than tourists who come from further afield. Therefore, we should concentrate more on providing more accommodation for that class of tourist.</P>
    <P>I was happy to be associated, with Dr. Beere and the Taoiseach, in the opening of a new An Óige hostel in Kinsale. It is a credit to all concerned and it emphasises the need for more such accommodation for that type of traveller. I have not much more to add except to commend this expenditure and to say how happy we have been in our experience as members of the Cork County Vocational Education Committee in being associated with the organisation of the hotel training school in the county. It has produced some excellently trained personnel to staff our hotels. I have expressed some concern at the treatment meted out to many of these boys and girls quite frequently in the employment they receive afterwards. I hope this is transitory and that the conditions of employment afforded them will be commensurate with the excellent training they have received.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DermotHonan" hpid="Mr. Honan Mr. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>There are just a few points I wish to make on this measure. Whether it is oriented towards the expansion of the number of hotel bedrooms or not&mdash;I assume that under its provisions new hotels will be constructed&mdash;there has been a precedent that a lot of new hotels make no provision for residents' lounges, most of the effort being concentrated on the construction of massive bars which take up the space that should have been given to the provision of residents' lounges. English people, particularly, complain that because of lack of residents' lounges, they have to sit in their bedrooms. It is essential, therefore, that provision be made for such lounges so that residents can enjoy the comfort for which they pay and which they expect. This is a matter affecting seaside places in particular.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the question of festival promotion, attention has been directed recently in seaside places to public house entertainment. The first point to <Col N="1576" /> be considered here is that public houses find themselves in competition with newly constructed hotel bars, constructed with the help of grants from Bord Fáilte. In contrast, no inducement is offered to public houses in this respect.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear. Not only that but they are mulcted in increased valuations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DermotHonan" hpid="Mr. Honan Mr. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a tendency now for visitors to object to the prices they are asked to pay in hotels. I had a case the other day of a visitor who went to an hotel and was asked to pay 6s 6d for a pint of stout and 7s 6d for a pint of lager.</P>
      <P>Over the winter period, I found it almost distressing to listen on the radio every morning to one of our State companies and other private companies publicising European countries for half an hour and trying to persuade Irish people to leave Ireland and go to these countries on holiday. I have not heard any company suggesting to anybody that Ireland is a good place for the Irish people to spend their holidays. Whatever currency we earn from our tourist traffic will be whittled away by Irish people going abroad and exporting the currency we need so much.</P>
      <P>I would like to join with the other speakers in congratulating Bord Fáilte on the work they are doing. If we are to keep in the tourist industry, we must have these amenities for which the Bill provides. I hope the complaints we hear so much of at present will gradually disappear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErskineHamiltonChild" hpid="Mr. Childers Mr. Childers">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Childers</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to thank the House for their reception of the Bill. There is not very much I need say at this point. The tourist potential of each area relates to some extent to the amount of facilities available from Bord Fáilte or in the form of any other grants. There are priorities in the form of lists of potential attractions to tourists which affect the amount of income which can be provided for any area, including certain regions of areas classified as of very high potential. For example, not everywhere in Kerry is regarded as completely high scenic value and so forth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The managers of the regional tourist <Col N="1577" /> boards can deal with the questions raised by Senator McDonald. There are meetings with Bord Fáilte in relation to the fairness of allocations. Regional tourist board directors do not go out to Europe: Bord Fáilte representatives go there. There are familiarisation courses in the country to which tourist agents come from abroad to Ireland. The value of any regional board is judged by the local enthusiasm generated and its tourist expenditure over the past six years. I have not had any complaints of unfair allocations.</P>
    <P>Senators raised the question of moderately - priced accommodation. This is consistently increasing. The increase in supplementary accommodation from 815 rooms a few years ago to 8,940 is, I think, supplying this demand adequately. I am glad to say that the farmhouse grants referred to by Senator McDonald, although not the subject of this Bill because they are given under another subhead, are being taken up very well. There are between 1,500 and 2,000 farmhouse bedrooms available this year. It was an idea I had which I always hoped to see eventuate. It is going very well. They are enormously popular among tourists of all classes of income.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Sullivan referred to the establishment of an information office in his area. As he knows, the Regional Tourist Board operates an information office, and I am glad to hear that the cost is being paid for by next year. He might be interested to learn also that one of the first detailed development reports of a particular tourist area is the Foras Forbartha Report on the tourist potential and rules for the preservation of amenities in the Beara peninsula. It is one of the first examples of how you can plan the development of an area and preserve its beauty.</P>
    <P>Senator McDonald suggested that in some areas staff in hotels might be exploited. I think the treatment of staff is important everywhere. Staff accommodation grants are offered by Bord Fáilte. I do not think it is sufficiently easy to get staff so that there could be any great exploitation of them, <Col N="1578" /> although I know there can be improvements still, particularly in regard to the conditions under which they work. I hope the improvement will continue.</P>
    <P>Bord Fáilte do insist on proper residential lounge areas in hotels for which they give grants. In reply to Senator Honan, I am aware it is a very important factor. There are no grants for bars offered by Bord Fáilte, only for extensions or reconstruction of dining room areas in the case of an existing hotel.</P>
    <P>I think that covers all the points. I do not know whether Senator O'Sullivan appreciates the fact that Bord Fáilte are authorised to give grants to hostels&mdash;50 per cent up to a maximum of £5,000 in western counties and 25 per cent in other areas.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    <P>Bill put through Committee, reported without recommendation, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>No. 6, Broadcasting (Offences) Bill, 1967&mdash;Second Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>As it is now just three minutes to eleven, surely we could leave this matter over until tomorrow? We agreed to adjourn at 11 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The position is that I ordered all these Bills for today so that we could clear the table for the matters which will concern the Seanad for the next period. I asked at the start of Business today that we sit late to complete this programme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a very ambitious programme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not see any reason why we should not finish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>We agreed to adjourn at 11 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1579" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>You could not remember the Order of Business a few minutes ago. I cannot be responsible for the fact that you have no support there. We want to get the business done and we are here to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is an unreasonable hour to start into a new Bill. It is now one minute to eleven. <Col N="1580" /> Surely we can adjourn until tomorrow?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I can see Senator McDonald's point inasmuch as there are a number of sections in the Bill which might require discussion.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 11 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 17th July, 1968.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>