<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="6" Month="Mar" Year="1968" Vol="64" No="11" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 6 Márta 1968" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 6 March 1968" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="907">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="907" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 2 to 7 inclusive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>If item No. 7 is not finished by tonight, is it intended to sit tomorrow?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, we could do that if it is not finished.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Smelting Bill, 1966:" RHead="Committee Stage">
    <Title>Smelting Bill, 1966: Committee Stage.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask the Minister for my information what is the situation or in what circumstances would a person be liable on conviction on indictment.  How is it intended to bring such a person to court on an indictment?  The reason I ask this is that I have seen quite a number of Bills recently where those fines are imposed and a person gets tried summarily or on indictment but there does not seem to me to be any difference between the offence that is being committed.  It is the one offence, a breach of a particular section in each case and here we have a case where a person on conviction on indictment will be fined so much.  The same thing occurs elsewhere in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>The section provides for conviction only on indictment which means that the procedure envisaged in connection with offences under the Act is to provide by way of indictment and not summary conviction.  Therefore, I think, if I understand the Senator <Col N="908" /> correctly, the point he has in mind does not arise on this section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>It probably arises on section 6.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 3 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>Before section 4 to insert a new section as follows:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(1)  Every licence made under this Act shall specify&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  the metal or metals and</P>
      <P>(b)  the pyrometallurgical or chemical or leaching or electrolytic or other process in respect of which the licence is granted.</P>
      <P>(2)  In the case of a licence granted under this Act within two years of the passing of this Act and not subsequently revoked under this Act, no second licence shall be granted in respect of the same or similar process of smelting the same metal or metals as specified in the said licence within ten years of the granting of the said licence.</P>
      <P>(3)  Notwithstanding anything contained in subsection (2) of this section the Minister may grant to a mining company or to any company associated with a mining company a licence to smelt any quantity of ore or ore concentrates produced by the said mining company.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On Second Stage the Minister indicated the circumstances in which this Bill came to be required.  Among other things, he indicated that a certain interest had been in touch with him and that he had given certain undertakings to that particular interest as to the granting of what amounts to a monopoly for the purpose of smelting and so on.  The Minister indicated in his Second Reading speech that it was proposed to grant these licences for ten years and on Second Stage Senator Dooge commented on the lack of definition, the lack of clarity in certain features of the Bill.  It seems to me right and proper that there <Col N="909" /> should be a definite period for the granting of a licence and that there should be an assurance that the licence would continue for a particular period. It seems to me to be necessary in a case where there will be, I rather think, quite a heavy capital investment that we should spell out in the Bill that the minimum period for the grant of the licence will be a period of ten years and that we should also spell out, as is provided in the section, the particular process and particular metals in respect of which this licence will be granted.  It is for that purpose that the amendment has been brought and in order, I think, to give the Minister as well as the interest concerned and the interests that may be concerned in the future a statutory basis on which they can act.  I grant that the Bill is so framed that the Minister can in his licence limit what time he likes.</P>
    <P>At the same time, I think the House and the country are entitled to know by looking at this piece of legislation in what way, for what purpose and for what period of time those licences are authorised to be granted by law.  It is to make that apparent on the face of the Bill that I move this amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to make clear as I tried to make it clear when replying to the debate on Second Stage what is being done under the Bill and the giving of a monopoly is true only in a very limited sense.  I say that because I made it clear to the House that it was proposed on the one hand to allow any individual or company owning a mine to erect a smelter for the purpose of smelting ore coming from the mine of that person or company here in Ireland and on the other hand to allow mine owners to export the produce of their mine if they wish to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Neither of those cases is affected by the proposals brought forward under this Bill.  Therefore, it is somewhat of a misnomer to describe what is being done here as giving a monopoly. Secondly, I find myself unable to accept this amendment for a number of reasons but basically because the ten year period, which I mentioned and which incidentally, perhaps, <Col N="910" /> might not have been made clear on the last occasion, would run from the date of commencement of the operation of the smelter.  This is a particular proposition in relation to the particular proposal put forward to me but it is certainly conceivable that the group concerned, having found that the proposal was not feasible, might for one reason or another not proceed with it in which case I might find myself in the position of making arrangements with some other group.</P>
    <P>In those circumstances I do not think it would be in the national interest that in any negotiation with such a group I should be tied down as I would be if this amendment were accepted.  It would be in the national interest that I should have sufficient room to manoeuvre to make what appears to be the best possible arrangement with any such group.  I think the objective which I can see as conceivable behind this amendment can be achieved in any event without it but if the amendment were accepted the freedom to negotiate, which I feel is essential and which might well be vital in the kind of circumstances I have outlined, would not be available and that it should be available.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister's argument on the question of whether this is a monopoly is not very convincing.  It is a limited monopoly certainly and as proposed in our amendment it would not be but as the Bill stands power is given to the Government to give any group a monopoly of smelting ores on behalf of other people. You do not hear people saying that CIE has not a monopoly on road freight because of the fact that people can carry goods in their own lorries or that CIE have not a monopoly in Dublin because people travel in their own cars.  It is a monopoly and this is also a monopoly.  What is proposed is that we give the Minister the right without any limitation whatever to grant a private group a monopoly for any period of years they wish and that no limit of any kind is imposed on this particular activity.  It is contrary to good practice in any democratic <Col N="911" /> country to give a power of such far-reaching character to a Government. We must be suspicious of any private monopolies.  There may be special circumstances in which a private monopoly is justified, a monopoly of a limited kind, for a period. Concession, where the Government give a concession for a limited period to carry on a commercial activity, is an established practice, but it is one which is regarded with suspicion by the Houses of Parliament and by the public and there must in such matters be limits on the Government's freedom of action.</P>
      <P>We were assured on Second Reading that this concession will be for a ten year period and this seems a proper thing to do, but if that is the intention we should incorporate this amendment in the legislation.  The Minister made several objections to our amendment which do not hold water.  First of all, his objection is that this group want a licence for ten years from the date of operation.  It is provided in the amendment that the licence should run for ten years from the time it is granted and that it can be granted at any time within two years of the enactment of the Bill, thereby giving time for the smelter to be brought into operation.</P>
      <P>If the Minister feels this is inadequate, then it can be modified.  It may be that two years is too short a time and it can, of course, be extended so as to give a ten year monopoly of smelting for hire or reward from the time the smelter goes into operation. If inadequate time is given here, it can be modified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister has said he must have freedom to negotiate.  This seems an extraordinary statement.  The Minister and his predecessors have been negotiating an agreement for some time past to give this group a monopoly, without any legislative authority.  How the Minister can say the introduction of this reduces his freedom to negotiate, I cannot understand.  The fact is that with this Bill, he can go to any group and say: &ldquo;I have legislative authority for negotiating this arrangement for a ten year period.&rdquo;  If the group made a <Col N="912" /> case that this was not sufficient&mdash;and I would hope the Minister would regard any case with suspicion&mdash;if that case were made, the Minister would do exactly what he had to do in this case: he would go to the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>He could hardly have promised them a monopoly of ten years in the recent negotiations without pointing out that this present legislation has to be passed by the Houses of the Oireachtas.  He would not be in any worse position than he is in now, but rather a better position, because he would have the evidence of the Oireachtas that he is willing to consider ten years as reasonable and having this evidence he could hold out as good a prospect as he is enabled to hold out to these people in this Bill of getting the Oireachtas to accept any agreement reached.  Therefore, it seems there are no grounds for refusing the amendment.</P>
    <P>The amendment is important because I could not conceive myself as agreeing to give the Government power to give monopoly which a Government could not revoke without a breach of an agreement, which would redound to the discredit of the Government of this country and would undermine confidence in the honesty of the Irish Government and their willingness to keep their word.  I do not want to get into the position where a monopoly of this kind can be given to a private group and we could not remedy that situation and take that back into our hands, except with detrimental effects to the integrity of the Government.</P>
    <P>I would be prepared to consider a proposal from the Minister to modiy the amendment in order to give him greater leeway if he feels greater leeway is required, but in no circumstances can we give him unlimited power of this kind to give this sort of monopoly with no limitation.  Therefore, I ask him to reconsider this matter between now and Report Stage and come back with an amendment, if he finds our amendment undesirable.</P>
    <P>The amendment here is designed to meet the case as he stated it.  There was <Col N="913" /> nothing in his Second Stage speech to indicate that he contemplated any possible arrangement where the period of the concession would be other than the ten years.  He says:</P>
    <P>. . . . it was my intention, upon the enactment of this legislation, to give this company a licence and to arrange that for a period of 10 years from the commencement of operation of their smelter no other licences for the smelting of lead and zinc would be issued.</P>
    <P>This is a clear statement of his intention. This amendment has been drafted having regard to his stated intention. He has now modified this intention and says he is not at all certain that this proposal will go ahead on the basis on which he sought agreement to this legislation.  I am disturbed by the fact of the grant of a monopoly in any event, which I think in its own right is objectionable, and I am not prepared, on the grounds that the Minister has changed his intention since Second Stage, to concede the right to give an indefinite and private monopoly of this kind.</P>
    <P>I would ask the Minister to reconsider this and to take it away between now and Report Stage and come back with some proposal to give him whatever leeway he requires which would avoid putting this country into a position which would be objectionable with a Government of any complexion, giving this kind of monopoly of unrestricted character.  I would ask him to reconsider the matter between now and Report Stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps I ought to say another word on this.  First of all, the only reason I mentioned the question of ten years from the commencement of smelting was that I was not sure whether it would be agreed on Second Stage that it would be dated for ten years.  Secondly, I think Senator FitzGerald has missed the point I was trying to make, which was not that I was going to contemplate going beyond ten years, although this was conceivable, but that if I wanted to make it shorter this amendment would oblige me to give a ten year period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="914" /> Also, I did say to the House that there was a proposal and I explained what it was.  I explained that an undertaking had been given and how I proposed to operate this Bill if enacted. I said, in addition, that the idea of giving that undertaking was to enable a feasibility study to be carried out and that an important aspect of that was the obtaining of the necessary and substantial capital that would be involved.</P>
    <P>Clearly, when I talked about a feasibility study and the difficulties involved any reasonable man would contemplate the possibility that this arrangement might not go ahead.  I think it will. I hope it will.  It would be unreasonable to assume that because a person decides to engage in a certain business there would be no necessity for a feasibility study.  Therefore, I think Senator FitzGerald is wrong in suggesting there would be any change of ground here at all.  There is no change on that ground.</P>
    <P>Furthermore, I wish to point out that in the proposed amendment, in subsection (3), there is something put in which strikes at the very root of the undertaking I gave, and reference has not been made to it.  This would enable a company not alone to erect a smelter for the smelting of their own ore, produced here, but it would enable them also, by loose phrasing, to associate in some way with companies around the world and to bring in ore from outside to be smelted here.  This strikes at the whole root of the arrangement made.  For all these reasons I find myself still unable to accept the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>There are one or two points of which I should like explanation.  Am I to understand it to be the Minister's intention that he will grant the licence before the feasibility study has been completed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not said that. What I intend to do when the legislation is enacted is to grant a licence subject to conditions.  If, in fact, this is before the feasibility study has been completed, the conditions will take account of that fact.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="915" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>I was under the impression from what was said on Second Stage that it was the Minister's intention to grant the licence at the close of the feasibility study.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>It depends on time.  If the licence were being granted before the feasibility study had been completed, the terms of the licence would have to take account of it.  The Bill itself indicates the kind of conditions that might be imposed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>I certainly had the impression when I drafted the amendment that the position would be that the licence would be given at the point when the smelter was about to be constructed.  It is probable it might be better to re-word subsection (2) in regard to the provisions of subsection (3) because the point the Minister has made in regard to drafting is a valid one.  As drafted, the amendment certainly would allow the importation, or not prohibit the importation, of ore or ore concentrates for smelting in this country.  That could be met by amending the wording to provide for the smelting of ore &ldquo;produced in this country by the said mining company&rdquo;. That would meet the point.  On the question of association, I mentioned that point on Second Stage and there is a difficulty about drafting it here. The intention in putting down the amendment was not to produce a final, polished amendment but to carry out the intention I indicated on Second Stage&mdash;to put the guarantee in statutory form.  That is the purpose of this amendment and it is the principle which must be decided at this stage.  If it is a matter of carrying that purpose into effect, the wording can be made a matter for discussion and agreement on Report Stage.  The issue here now is whether a guarantee in regard to something which is monopolistic in character should be given as a private executive act by the Minister or by public Act of the Oireachtas. That is the net issue here and I ask the Minister to consider it carefully.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I have given it a good deal of consideration and I should prefer to do it in the way Senator <Col N="916" /> Dooge suggests but I do not think it is feasible in the circumstances.  One must remember again when talking about monopolies&mdash;I have already dealt with the point&mdash;that we are dealing with something which does not exist in this country and that the primary objective of the Bill is to enable us to get a smelter in this country and I have approached it on the basis of which is the most feasible way of doing that. The objectives Senator Dooge has outlined are being met because the conditions of the undertaking given have been made public and have appeared in the records of both Houses of the Oireachtas&mdash;there is public knowledge of it.  On the other hand, I wish to maintain freedom to manoeuvre.  One possibility is that the feasibility study might be favourable but that the people concerned might decide not to go ahead and I would find it necessary to negotiate with another group.  I should want to negotiate on the best possible terms and under this amendment I would not be free to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>Up to two years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I would have to get ten years, not up to ten years.  The objective is being met by the way we have handled this.  At the same time, I would have freedom to manoeuvre and that is in the national interest.  I would not have it under the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>There does not seem to be too much between us&mdash;it is a matter of feasibility.  With the same objectives, it might be possible in some way to meet this.  The Minister has been harping on the question of ten years and of being tied to ten years.  Subsection (2) could be redrafted to allow this degree of flexibility. The Minister has been putting the case that if, having dealt with a first company who found they did not want to go ahead, he might have to negotiate with another company.  Even in that eventuality, a one page Act could remedy it.  What we are talking about is not so unfeasible.  If we redraft it, will the Minister consider the entire matter between now and Report Stage or is it the position that he has set his mind adamantly against any such amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="917" />
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it is possible to devise the kind of amendment the Senator has in mind to meet the conditions which must be given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment was drafted late one night after two days campaigning in County Clare and, therefore, it might not have been drafted in the best circumstances.  I ask the indulgence of the House to withdraw the amendment with a view to having a look at it between now and Report Stage.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 4 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I note that there can be a substitution of one licensee for another and the manner in which it is proposed to effect the transfer is by the Minister substituting the name of the new licensee for the old licensee. On that kind of transfer of the interest of A to B will there be stamp duty payable or is this method being adopted for the avoidance of stamp duty?  I take it the licence will be a valuable commodity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I must confess I have not given any thought to the question of stamp duty.  The reason for the manner proposed is twofold.  First, if we grant the licence prior to the completion of the feasibility study we should be granting it to the company carrying out the feasibility study.  It is very likely that if that feasibility study is favourable and if another company is formed to take into account the various interests involved, financial and otherwise, it would be necessary in these circumstances to transfer the licence to that company. In the second place, there is the possibility that the smelter operating for some years might be sold to another company.  To allow for that situation, it is proposed to make the transfer of the licence as reasonably straightforward as possible.  No thought, that I am aware of, has been given to the question of stamp duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>As well as other matters, it looks as if the financiers <Col N="918" /> will not come into it, too.  I take it that the licence will be transferred?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>The licence could not carry that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a matter for the Minister for Finance.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 5.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 5 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>This raises a matter of considerable principle.  I do not know if the matter was adverted to when the Bill was going through the Dáil.  It seems to me that, here again, we are faced with the position where a Minister of State grants a licence which will turn out to be a valuable asset and, on the strength of it, there may be a considerable expenditure&mdash; running, perhaps, into millions of pounds&mdash;on the part of the licence holder.  What is being provided for here&mdash;and it is quite right so to provide&mdash;is that the licence may be revoked if the licence holder does not comply with certain conditions.</P>
      <P>This is another instance of sections being slipped into a Bill providing that the Minister who grants the licence is again the person who says &ldquo;I shall withdraw it&rdquo; with no inquiry, nobody to say whether or not the person is in default.  The Minister is again judge and jury in this kind of case.  As I understand the position, there may be hundreds of thousands, perhaps millions, of pounds involved in the decision of the Minister to withdraw a licence from somebody because, in his view, they are not complying with the conditions with which he will have required them, in writing, to comply.  There may be circumstances which make it difficult to comply with the conditions or there may be circumstances where there could be two views on whether the conditions have substantially been complied with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think it is wrong that, merely upon the say-so of the Minister, the licence can be withdrawn.  Presumably this will be a private company and its <Col N="919" /> accounts certainly will not be open to public scrutiny in the same way as those of semi-State bodies.  A company in that kind of situation and, in order to &ldquo;keep in&rdquo;, as one might say, with the Minister for the time being&mdash;it may well be another Minister for Industry and Commerce and another Minister of a different Party&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>What a hope you have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I understood the Fianna Fáil Party were out to try to ensure that the people would get a change, at some time in the future&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;that the people would get an opportunity&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I can tell one way to get a decision in a very short time and you do not have to change the voting system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Will Senator O'Quigley please keep to the section?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ó Donnabháin's interruptions are always unhelpful.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanAlton" hpid="Dr. Alton Dr. Alton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Alton</NameTxt>
      <P>They are revealing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, they are revealing. I think it is wrong a company which may, perhaps, have millions of pounds involved in a particular venture&mdash;the continuance of that venture depending upon the continuance of their licence&mdash;should be beholden to a Minister of State.  I think that is wrong.  There are so many temptations to which the company may be subject and there are so many pressures which may be applied to the company that I think it is absolutely wrong to say that it is the Minister who can decide, in certain circumstances, that he will withdraw the licence and, in other circumstances, that he will not withdraw it.  A lot of that gives rise to a great deal of the disquiet one currently hears about in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is absolutely wrong that a Minister will be entitled to withdraw the licence without any inquiry by any outside body, without even the limited inquiry we have at the present <Col N="920" /> time under the Local Government Planning Act by an inspector of the Minister, with no opportunity necessarily given or which must be given to the holder of the licence to state his case and to have it heard even by somebody appointed by the Minister. With no such opportunity in that kind of situation, I think it is absolutely wrong that the power to revoke the licence should be vested in the Minister. I am not saying that the Minister should not supervise&mdash;I think he must&mdash;the operations of the company and see that the conditions are properly carried out and should not be in a position to serve notice on them in writing if he is of opinion that the conditions are not being carried out. I am not saying he should not have that power.  However, if it is necessary to revoke the licence, it is not the Minister who should have the power to revoke it.</P>
    <P>All of this brings us back again to the need in this country&mdash;where one has so many powers which are vested in Ministers to grant things&mdash;to have some kind of body&mdash;I do not say necessarily the courts&mdash;some kind of administrative tribunal that will be independent of a Minister of State, that will do justice and, when a decision is taken by that tribunal, everybody will be quite satisfied that justice has been done.  If the Minister wanted to revoke the licence and came into Parliament and said: &ldquo;Such and such has happened; certain things were not done; the position now is that this licence must be revoked; I want to give this licence to somebody else&rdquo;, and maybe a motion is passed by one or both Houses of the Oireachtas, at any rate, it is done openly and it is not the Minister alone who is doing it in the secrecy and privacy of his Department. That situation perhaps would meet the principle I am speaking about.  But nothing like that will be done.  I cannot see how any Minister can justify his revocation of a licence upon which hinges an investment of hundreds of thousands of pounds.</P>
    <P>I think the Minister should indicate that he will be prepared to go even farther than the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries went on the Marts <Col N="921" /> Bill when he provided for a limited inquiry by a person outside himself when he proposed to revoke a marts licence for breaches of certain conditions specified in the Bill.  The Minister should go the further distance of agreeing to make the revocation of this licence the duty of some person who will be independent&mdash;not necessarily a judge or a barrister: you can make it a mining engineer or anybody else you like so long as it is somebody who would be outside the Minister and who would not be subject to any pressures either for or against its revocation. I must say that I am at fault, indeed, in not having put down an amendment on this earlier, but it goes to show the kind of mood we get into. Once we realise that the whole business of licensing is necessary we are inclined to accept the rest of the Bill. It is only when one comes to examine it, perhaps after the fresh air of Wicklow, like Senator Dooge, that one gets a clearer picture.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Quigley is correct in saying that the amount of money involved in a smelter is substantial; in fact, it would run into millions rather than hundreds of thousands.  But he is wrong, in my opinion, in suggesting that this section provides in effect that a smelting licence may be revoked more or less at the whim of the Minister.  It sets out the conditions under which a licence may be revoked.  They are set out as criteria which may be determined objectively.  We may take it as quite certain that when an investment of that nature is involved any unlawful or frivolous revocation of a licence by any Minister in those circumstances would certainly result in an application to the courts to determine whether or not the Minister had acted in accordance with this section in revoking the licence.  If he had failed to do so he would, of course, have acted <i>ultra vires</i> and the licence would not be revoked. I think that there is adequate protection here.  I do not see that there is any necessity for anything more, having laid down the criteria objectively and not making them subject to the opinion of the Minister but matters to be determined objectively.  I think that there <Col N="922" /> is quite sufficient there to protect the interests involved in the event of any misuse of the powers vested in the Minister under this section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, I am sure, trusts himself not to act capriciously and not to act in any way which would be unfair.  I am sure that many of us would trust this Minister who, I am sure, has very high standards, but there is always a question not alone of principle involved in these matters&mdash;and it seems unpopular nowadays to talk about principle&mdash;but also a question of what I might call practical politics involved.  This Minister might well, having granted this licence, if the conditions were not being complied with, adopt a somewhat different attitude to another Minister. The question does arise whether we are going to vest the power to destroy an investment of several million pounds in a Minister without any inquiry.</P>
      <P>The Minister makes what appears on the surface to be a very good case by saying that the revocation of a licence would be determined on the basis of objective standards set out in the section, but of course objective standards have to be interpreted in a subjective manner, and when it comes to determining whether a licence holder has failed to comply with the conditions that is a very difficult thing to decide.  He might not have neglected to comply with the conditions, and he might very well have done his best but for lack of technical skill or some breakdown be unable to comply with it, and require more time.  These are all highly subjective judgments.  There is no use in the Minister saying that there are objective standards laid down in the section.  I do not see any of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the last resort what will determine whether a licence is revoked or not is the opinion of the Minister. I am surprised at the Minister saying that if the Minister fails to comply with the provisions of this section the company or licence holder concerned can apply to the courts and get a declaration that he has acted <i>ultra vires</i> and that, therefore, the licence would <Col N="923" /> not be revoked.  Consider that for a moment.  First of all, by the time the licence is revoked the person is out of business.  Even if he could go to the courts his business is closed down. Probably the company would have had to go into liquidation because of pressure from creditors to pay off debts, and so on.  So that the idea of going to the court is really closing the door after the horse has escaped.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>What about an interim injunction?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I will deal with that too.  First of all, the Minister's suggestion is absolutely impracticable. Secondly, the Minister, who is a lawyer, like myself, must be absolutely aware and highly conscious of the fact that in any of these cases where a Minister has discretion and where it is the Minister's opinion that is provided for as the determining factor in any enactment, the courts will run a thousand miles before interfering with the exercise by the Minister of the discretion given to him by legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>The point I was trying to make is that this section does not provide for anything in the opinion of the Minister.  It says that a licence is to be revoked if certain conditions are not met, and it sets them out.  It does not say anything about the Minister's opinion and, therefore, the case that the Senator is making does not apply in this case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is talking like a lawyer now.  One must always be very careful about how one talks in this House.  What else can it be but the opinion of the Minister? He must be satisfied that the conditions have been broken, otherwise he would not revoke the licence.  Or he does not have to be as strongly convinced as that, but he must be of the opinion that the conditions have been broken and, therefore, he revokes the licence.  The section does not even say that.  It says that if the conditions have not been complied with the Minister may revoke the licence.  There is no doubt at all about it but that this section will <Col N="924" /> be considered by the courts in the way many other sections giving power to a Minister to exercise a ministerial function have been interpreted.  When a Minister has been given power by the Legislature our courts run a thousand miles away from any interference with the Minister in the exercise of his discretion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>They did not always do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like if the Leader of the House would tell me what he has in mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a lot of talk in the other House at the moment about certain Ministers and the way that they did not worry about interfering with the opinion of the Oireachtas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The trouble about people like the Leader of the House speaking in relation to a section of this kind is that they can never understand what it is that the courts do when they give a decision.  The courts in considering that section would merely say &ldquo;Reading that section it means this&mdash;&rdquo;, and they give effect to it.  Interpreting the Constitution, for instance, they say &ldquo;This is what the people said in their Constitution&rdquo;, and if the decision falls one way that is it, and if the decision falls the other way that is it too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator says that the court would run a mile from interfering with the decision of any Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>What I am saying is that if the courts say that this section gives the Minister power to revoke a licence and he does not have to hold any inquiry, then if the Minister revokes the licence there is nothing the court can do about it because that is the Minister's power under the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is refreshing to hear Senator O'Quigley on that line now because on every Bill that has ever come before the Seanad he has insisted on clauses going in to take the power out of the hands of the Minister and <Col N="925" /> give it to the courts.  Now we find that the courts are no good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair would like to remind the House that undue repetition is not in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Question and answer is very often instructive.  I am not asking the questions but I am providing the answers.  The truth of the matter is that the Minister under this section has absolute power, unfettered power to revoke a licence dependent upon nothing except his own opinion and assessment of the situation.  Consequently, this is a section which I find quite unacceptable and I feel that we will have to make some provision at a later stage for amending it.  I hope that the Minister will have an open mind, at least as open as the Minister for Agriculture had on the Marts Bill.  He ought to have it even more so on this Bill because the amount of money at stake is immeasurably greater and, therefore, his responsibility is correspondingly higher than was the case under the Marts Bill.  If there was a case under the Marts Bill for providing some kind of limited appeal from the Minister's decision to revoke a licence, there certainly is an even greater and stronger case under this section for the provision of some form of appeal outside of the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Quigley would have&mdash;I was going to say a much stronger case&mdash;let me say a case if this section read: &ldquo;If in the opinion of the Minister a holder of a smelting licence. . . . &rdquo; But it does not read that way.  What it says is:</P>
      <P>If a holder of a smelting licence fails, neglects or refuses to comply with a condition. . . .</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator O'Quigley knows as well as I do that there is all the difference in the world between that section and the kind of section that it might have been and which appears in other statutes&mdash;&ldquo;If in the opinion of the Minister&rdquo;, and the manner in which the courts approach a section like this and a section which says &ldquo;If in the opinion of the Minister. . . &rdquo; is quite different <Col N="926" /> because in the case where it says it is depending on the opinion of the Minister it has to take a very unusual set of circumstances to enable a court to interfere at all but here there is no question of the opinion of the Minister. The criteria are laid down objectively and if the Minister does not act in accordance with these provisions it is open to the courts to set aside the action he takes and to set it aside quickly and it seems to me that any precaution that could reasonably be requested is obtained under this section as it is worded.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No.2:</P>
      <P>Before section 6 to insert a new section as follows:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(1)  In the case of the granting or transfer of a smelting licence the Minister shall lay before each House of the Oireachtas a statement showing-</P>
      <P>(a)  the name of the person to whom the licence is granted or transferred,</P>
      <P>(b)  the metal or metals specified in the licence,</P>
      <P>(c)  the pyrometallurgical or chemical or leaching or electrolytic or other process in respect of which the licence is granted, and</P>
      <P>(d)  whether the licence is a general one or is restricted to ore or ore concentrates produced by a specified mining company.</P>
      <P>
      </P>
      <P>(2)  In the case of a revocation under this Act of a smelting licence, the Minister shall lay before each House of the Oireachtas a statement showing particulars of such revocation.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I feel that this particular amendment gives effect to much of what the Minister said on amendment No. 1.  What we are trying to do is to make provision here for the laying before each House of the Oireachtas of the name of the person to whom the licence is granted.  There does not seem to me to be any reason in principle why this <Col N="927" /> should be objected to.  Secondly, we suggest that the metal or metals specified in the licence and, thirdly, that the pyrometallurgical or chemical or leaching or electrolytic or other process in respect of which the licence is granted should be laid before each House.  That seems to me to be information which cannot affect anybody but which should be made known publicly because a monopoly of a limited kind is being granted and the fourth thing we want is a statement showing whether the licence is a general one or is restricted to ore or ore concentrates produced by a specified mining company should be laid before each House.  It is also being provided in sub-section (2) that in the case of a revocation under this Act of a smelting licence the Minister shall lay before each House of the Oireachtas a statement showing particulars of such revocation.</P>
    <P>Whenever we establish a semi-State body&mdash;and we have quite a number of them in this country&mdash;we are quite prepared to lay down the various conditions under which they will operate. These are either embodied in statutes or in some cases are contained in the Articles of Association of public companies. I feel that it is only right and proper in a case of this kind and there are precedents for this kind of enactment, that we should, when we are dealing with a matter which is of public concern, lay all the facts before the public.  If there is nothing to hide there is no reason why they should be hidden.  Accordingly, I hope the Minister will see his way to accept this amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I cannot see my way to accept the amendment, not because there is anything to hide because there is not but, first of all, because the procedure suggested in this amendment is quite unusual in relation to licences and acceptance of it might have much wider repercussions than would be envisaged in this amendment.  Secondly, as drafted, the amendment would require to be a good deal more specific in regard to the form of the licence than I am in a position <Col N="928" /> to be at the moment.  Thirdly, and most important, it seems to me that the information which it is sought to have made public under this amendment is information which can be made public quite easily without this amendment at all.</P>
      <P>I can conceive of no reason why the Minister for Industry and Commerce at any time would not be prepared to give the kind of information sought here and there are various methods, including Parliamentary Questions in Dáil Éireann, which would elicit this information without difficulty and since the implications of accepting the amendment here could be very much wider than are envisaged and since the objective required which is to make the information available to the public can be and will be I believe achieved without this, I must resist the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>We are in an extraordinary position in that even when the Minister agrees with us he chooses to disagree with us.  He says that all this information we are seeking here can be made public and the only reason that he will not accept it is that he says we would want to be a little more specific.  I readily concede that.  The Minister is in a much better position to be specific on these matters because he has very skilled people to advise him than people like myself and Senator Dooge could possibly be.  Therefore, I would have thought that if the Minister were prepared to accept in principle or at any rate not to disagree in principle with the objective of the amendment he would accept it and get his parliamentary draftsman and his own advisers to make it into the kind of amendment that would be closer to his heart.  As regards the other objection that the Minister has that this would be unusual in relation to licences, I think it is also correct to say that this particular licence is very unusual in that it is a licence for a limited form of monopoly.  Therefore, the public are being debarred from a particular activity and that particular activity which up to now would have been lawful to engage in will now be an offence.  I feel that the public are entitled in a democracy <Col N="929" /> which I believe we live in in their legislation to say exactly what the Minister shall reveal and to say that by law. The Minister says this information can be got by Parliamentary Question.  I have not a great deal of faith in the Parliamentary Question for eliciting information of this kind because I have seen time and again where questions have been put down in the Dáil and the answer is that this disclosure would interfere in the private affairs of the company.</P>
      <P>This is the fine argument which it is difficult to penetrate that the Minister could not, without the consent of the other party to the licence, disclose this information.  This is the kind of excuse we have seen from time to time and that is the answer that would be given. Although he would not have bothered his head to have sought the information it would be said that he could not, without the consent of the other party to the licence and whose private property the licence would by then have become, divulge this information and that it would be contrary to established practice to do so.  We know that the reply to the Parliamentary Question straight away is &ldquo;contrary to established practice&rdquo;.  For that reason I think it is highly desirable, as I say if there is nothing to hide, that we lay it before Dáil Éireann or Seanad Éireann so that everybody can see it. I see no reason for the Minister refusing to accept this and, accordingly, I press this amendment.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the new section be there inserted&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Will Senators seeking a Division stand in their places?</P>
      <P>
        <i>Senators O'Quigley, Dooge, Garret FitzGerald and Murphy rose.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The names of the Senators will be recorded in the proceedings.</P>
      <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Quigley should be cashiered for wasting the time of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought some of <Col N="930" /> the independent people on that side of the House might have voted with me.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 6 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>What I want to point out is that I see here that if a holder of a smelting licence fails, neglects or refuses to comply with a condition attached to a licence he shall be guilty of an offence and shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding £100 or on conviction on indictment to a fine not exceeding £1,000.  In what circumstances will there be a summary conviction, and in what circumstances will the offence warrant trial on indictment?  I, frankly, do not understand the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>The position is that, as I think the Senator pointed out earlier, this kind of provision occurs in many Bills, the objective being to ensure that, where an offence does not appear to be of too serious a nature, the whole paraphernalia of an indictment need not necessarily be invoked, and this is not only in the interest of the State but also in the interest of the person accused.  In effect, the procedure by way of summary conviction or indictment depends on the nature and gravity of the offence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I find it extremely difficult to understand how the Attorney General will decide whether the particular offence is one which warrants summary trial in the district court or return for trial either to the circuit court or to the criminal court.  However, that is a problem for the future Attorney General.  I do not see any logic in the situation.  I will leave that aside.  I do not understand it even after what the Minister has said.  I divine that is what is in mind but how that will be operated I do not understand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to refer to the new situation we are creating in this Bill.  It is to be observed that apparently a minor infraction of a smelting licence, according to the Minister, will warrant a criminal prosecution in the courts. The Minister says that for a minor <Col N="931" /> infraction we will have a summary trial and these minor infractions&mdash;is if he fails, refuses or neglects to comply with the condition attached to a licence&mdash;are related to the fact which I stated a few minutes ago.  Observe what the Legislature is doing.  They are enacting legislation which will be a precedent for future legislators.  The House rejected an amendment on which a division was challenged a few minutes ago.  Observe what the Minister and the House are doing.  Under section 5 we use the exact same phraseology&mdash;fails, neglects or refuses to comply with the condition attached to the licence.  The Minister may revoke the licence.  It may be only a minor infraction and yet this House is saying the Minister may then withdraw the licence because of a minor infraction and upset the whole investment involving millions of pounds.</P>
    <P>If the Fianna Fáil Party think that is good law and good policy, there is nothing I can do to dissuade them but I want to say that to invest those powers in a Minister and do it in written form in legislation is bad public policy and bad for democracy.  I can never understand how 11 members nominated by the Taoiseach to serve in this House so frequently swallow the Fianna Fáil line.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Senator will concern himself with the section before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Now and again a section of this kind&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The conduct of other Senators is not in question on this section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Can he accuse the Fianna Fáil Government of being guilty of what the Senator's Government was guilty of when they closed down on the constellations and closed down the chassis factory?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>We wiped out TB.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will continue on the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I regard it as less of an offence to substitute TB beds <Col N="932" /> for constellations than an infraction of a smelting licence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>You did not even do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I deplore the failure of the House to appreciate what is being done in this section and what has been done in the previous section and in the Bill as a whole.  I cannot understand why people will accept day in day out this gradual and studied encroachment on the liberty of the people of this country.</P>
      <P>In time there will have grown up a sufficient body of precedents for any Minister at any time for more repressive measures than are on the Statute Book at the present time.  This is one at this time.  We are making a minor infraction of a smelting licence an offence on summary conviction or on conviction on indictment.  If I were to judge even on a minor infraction, I would choose trial on indictment because I would think I would have a better chance of getting a fairer view of my operations from 12 men from the street, 12 of the decent citizens of this country, than I would have from one person on a summary trial.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>You are going back to the courts now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>What the Minister has had to say about the section highlights what I had to say about another part of the Bill and I suppose I will not be allowed to reply to it again because it would be repetitious.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 7 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 8.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 8 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>In section 8 there is a further penal provision contained in this Bill.  There are so many penal sections contained in this Bill and the punishments are so great, including the punishment under section 2 of a fine of £500 a day for every day an offence is committed, that they are almost <Col N="933" /> calculated to frighten off anybody coming in and looking for what we call this monopoly.  What is extraordinary about section 8 is that not alone will the company be fined, or an incorporated body be fined, presumably on indictment or after conviction on indictment on an offence but we will fine officers or servants of the company as well.  It is here that we find &ldquo;Where an offence under this Act is committed by a body corporate or by a person purporting to act on behalf of a body corporate or an unincorporated body of persons, and is proved to have been so committed with the consent or approval of, or to have been facilitated by any default on the part of any person. . . &rdquo; It is the wording &ldquo;to have been facilitated by any default on the part of any person&rdquo; which I think is going a step too far.  The Minister will be well aware that in many statutes mere default is not sufficient to create an offence even in the case of the administration of an asset which is purely a matter on the civil side.  An administrator or an executor will not be penalised to get in the assets unless it is due to his wilful default.  In this section we ought to say that the director or secretary of a company should not be liable to conviction for mere neglect alone&mdash;that mere neglect is not sufficient to constitute an offence, that there should be actual lawful and palpable neglect, such neglect to amount to a criminal offence.  To say that an offence has been &ldquo;facilitated by any default by any person. . . &rdquo; is going much too far.</P>
      <P>I accept that directors and secretaries of companies are very often the villains of the piece rather than the body corporate but the mere facilitating, by default, of the commission of an offence on the part of a servant, which a director is <i>vis-á-vis</i> the company, is going too far.  The Minister might indicate that he will accept an amendment on Report Stage to make it a punishable offence only if it has been proved that the default is wilful on the part of the person concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Quigley has referred to the relatively heavy penalties provided in this Bill.  I said <Col N="934" />&ldquo;relatively&rdquo; because one must relate what we are dealing with, which is a smelting operation, which could entail many millions of £ as a capital investment, to what the Senator said earlier could lead to fairly substantial profits.  That being so, and in the circumstances in which we are proposing to give a licence in the national interest, with certain conditions attached, it is not unreasonable that we should insist that those conditions will be fully complied with in return for the benefit which is being conferred on the licensee.</P>
      <P>The Senator accepts the principle that the officers, the directors of the company, could very well be liable, and I am sure he accepts that where the penalty can be applied only to the company and not to the officers it might be ineffective.  It seems, therefore, that it is not unreasonable we should provide for relatively heavy penalties&mdash;not so heavy in relation to the size of the undertaking, of the amount of money involved, and that the penalties should be applied to the officers, the directors, where they are guilty, as it says here, &ldquo;with their consent or approval or was facilitated by default on the part of that person&rdquo;. The conditions involved are important from the point of view of the national interest.  It is possible that quite a valuable concession is being given and it is not unreasonable, therefore, that any failure to comply with the conditions or any attempt to avoid the obligations imposed in the conditions should be dealt with fairly clearly.  That, in effect, is what this section provides.</P>
      <P>The arguments which the Senator made earlier in regard to a monopoly or kind of monopoly being given under this Bill are the strongest arguments in favour of the approach we are adopting here in regard to the penalty sections, particularly section 8.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister give some indication of the kind of conditions which will be attached to the licence?  We have no idea what the conditions are likely to be.  Would the Minister like to do that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="935" />
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I have given a general idea of the kind of conditions that will apply.  I do not think I can give any further idea until there is a specific case before us.  I have given a general idea of the kind of conditions that will apply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not saying that where we are granting a monopoly we ought not to insist that the conditions should be fulfilled&mdash;I made that clear earlier&mdash;nor do I take exception to the conditions in this section which provide that, where an offence is committed with the consent or approval of the directors, the person concerned should not be found liable. What I take exception to is the other set of circumstances in which it is proved to have been merely facilitated by default of a director or servant.  I insist that it should be made clear it is not mere oversight or neglect involving the director.</P>
      <P>For instance, I had experience recently of a servant of a public body taking a running dive at a particular matter.  With the best will and in the most honourable way, he made a ghastly error of judgment which might not have happened.  I should hate to think that a decent person like him who, because his default was not wilful&mdash;it was culpable but not wilful&mdash; in a company, by an error of judgment, and who is guilty of facilitating an offence or breach of conditions simply by this error of judgment, should have extended to him the rigours of criminal law.  That is going a bit too far.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>The circumstances in which the default occurs would be investigated in any prosecution and if the circumstances warrant it I have no doubt the court would take account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>And find him guilty.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 9 and 10 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="936" />
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We should like the remaining Stages now.  I explained the circumstances to the Members of the Opposition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the provisions of section 5, which it is necessary to state on Report Stage&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I understood we would be facilitated in regard to this matter because of the impending departure of the Minister.  I took it we would get all Stages this evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Shall we take the Final Stages?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  The Leader of the House must have misunderstood the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not misunderstand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the wish of the House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator insists on refusing to facilitate us, we will take the Report Stage in the morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not be steam-rolled or browbeaten in this fashion. We are dealing with a Bill which, according to its Title, was introduced on 13th December, 1967 but which was ordered by Dáil Éireann in December, 1966.  We are now in 1968 and we will not be browbeaten or bullied in this fashion.  If the Government want to have a vote on this, and do not want to give the Opposition an opportunity to put down considered amendments on this, they can do so and illustrate to the public their mentality, where they have the power and the numbers, and how they will deal with people who want to do their job.  I shall be delighted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We had the power and the numbers on the Marts Bill.  We gave them ample time to talk.  We let them talk until they were <Col N="937" /> worn out talking.  I made it clear to the Senator and to Senator FitzGerald that the Minister had an arrangement which made it necessary for him to leave on Friday, that he would not be here for some time and was anxious that this Bill should be put into operation as soon as possible.  I ask that the Minister be facilitated in this matter. I understood from both Senators that that would be agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>In the event, we can either take a vote and take the remaining Stages now, or, in order to facilitate Senators, give them until tomorrow morning for the amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The last thing I want is to appear to walk out of any undertaking I have given.  I understood the Minister wanted to be in the Dáil at 4 o'clock this afternoon to deal with an Estimate.  I certainly agreed that we would facilitate him in that way and was agreeable to an adjournment of a discussion on this matter until the Minister&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>You did not even facilitate him in that respect.  You kept the debate going.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>There was nothing to prevent the Minister from doing so.  He could have taken this at 9 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Leader of the House wants this tomorrow, he will have to have a vote on it.  I do not want it earlier than next Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senator O'Quigley does not wish to put down any amendment for tomorrow morning, we might as well take it now.  I <Col N="938" /> am doing it to facilitate Senator O'Quigley to put down an amendment or amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>We have a very long Order Paper to deal with today. I have no civil servants to deal with this matter for me.  I shall not have the time, between now and tomorrow morning, for this purpose.  We meet sufficiently infrequently to be given the opportunity of considering Bills properly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When will the next Stage be taken?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose that the next Stage be taken next Wednesday, 13th March, 1968.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  Does Senator O'Quigley intend to put down an amendment if we schedule it for tomorrow morning?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall not have time to draft the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the decision of the House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall take it tomorrow morning in the hope that he will have time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall not agree to that, either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>In that case I suggest we waste no more time.  The Senator understands why we were anxious to get this thing done.  I suggest we take it now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that a motion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am opposed to that.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the remaining Stages be taken today&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="939" />
      <Col N="940" /> The Seanad divided: Tá, 25; Níl, 6.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Ahern, Liam.<br />Boland, Gerald.<br />Brennan, John L.<br />Browne, Seán.<br />Cole, John C.<br />Connolly O'Brien, Nora.<br />Dolan, Séamus.<br />Eachthéirn, Cáit Uí.<br />Egan, Kieran P.<br />Farrell, Joseph.<br />Fitzsimons, Patrick.<br />Flanagan, Thomas P.<br />Honan, Dermot P.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Killilea, Mark.<br />McGlinchey, Bernard.<br />McGowan, Patrick.<br />Martin, James J.<br />Nash, John Joseph.<br />Ó Donnabháin, Seán.<br />O'Kennedy, Michael.<br />Ó Maoláin, Tomás.<br />Ryan, James.<br />Ryan, Patrick W.<br />Ryan, William.<br />Teehan, Patrick J.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Davidson, Mary F.<br />Dooge, James C.I.<br />FitzGerald, Garret M.D.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">McAuliffe, Timothy.<br />Murphy, Dominick F.<br />O'Quigley, John B.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers.&mdash;Tá: Senators Farrell and Ó Donnabháin; Níl: Senators Murphy and Garret FitzGerald.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>On Report Stage, I want to ascertain under the Standing Orders what are we to do when we have not had an opportunity of putting down amendments on Report Stage. Are we to be asked to go through the solemn farce in the Parliament of Ireland of having a Report Stage when we have not been given an opportunity through the weight of numbers of the Fianna Fáil Party and the 11 independent persons nominated by the Taoiseach&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Cut it out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;of putting down amendments?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator knows very well that he was given an opportunity of putting down amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>We have here the attitude and the mentality of the Fianna Fáil Party, that if they have the power of numbers it does not matter a damn about anybody else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We had it on the Marts Bill when you kept us here for a fortnight.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any possibility of holding the Bill over briefly to give us an opportunity of drafting amendments, because it had been our intention to draft amendments?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a pity that you were not here.  You would have seen the behaviour of Senator O'Quigley.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say that I am taken aback, because it was my understanding that there would be ample opportunity of drafting amendments and I had no idea that there would be an attempt to rush the Bill through like this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the decision of the House to take the Report Stage now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we not at liberty to change the Order of Business by agreement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the order of the House in regard to its own business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the House not at liberty to change the Order of Business?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It can change it, but I do not intend to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="941" />
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I was assuming a certain amount of goodwill on the other side, and I was going to suggest that this could be left over for a brief period, and that we would move on to other business to allow us to draft amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Senator is not aware of the offer that was made to meet tomorrow morning to have the amendments on Report Stage and that this offer was contemptuously rejected by Senator O'Quigley.  I have no intention now of changing the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be engaged in the business of the House from now until the House rises at 10 o'clock to-night&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>So will we all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;so I will not have time to draft amendments for tomorrow morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It had not been proposed that we should meet tomorrow morning.  The clear understanding was that we were not and, accordingly, a number of us have made arrangements and have other commitments, not all of them of a by-election character, and to suggest that we should meet tomorrow without notice in this way and that this is the only way we could put down amendments is an unreasonable proposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Dear Senator FitzGerald, this dalladh phúichín you are trying to put across now will not work.  At the very start of business we were asked about the Dumping Bill and we volunteered to meet tomorrow morning if necessary in answer to Senator O'Quigley.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>That is to dispose of the Second Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The suggestion that there was no notice given that we were to meet tomorrow morning is nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We did not understand we were to meet tomorrow <Col N="942" /> and we made arrangements accordingly and I do not think the Report Stage can be taken just like that.  We suggest we should be given an opportunity to draft amendments so as not to make complete nonsense of the whole affair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We decided to take the remaining Stages now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The dictators have decided, so that is that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is &ldquo;That the Bill be received for Final Consideration&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Is my proposal on this matter then rejected?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not heard a proposal.  I do not think that I can, immediately after the House has decided to do something, entertain a motion to some other effect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I understood we decided to take the Report Stage today but any business can be adjourned by agreement of the House and I would point out that I myself approached the Minister a short time ago to ask him if we could help him in any way in regard to the dumping Bill and I would expect that we would be given the courtesy of an opportunity to draft amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The House has decided that the Report and Fifth Stages be taken now.  The Chair is endeavouring to have the Report Stage taken now by putting the question &ldquo;That the Bill be received for Final Consideration&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is in order for the House to change its business at any time by agreement.  May I suggest a compromise here if I may stick my neck out?  We have decided anyway that it will be taken now but would it meet the wishes of the Leader of the House if we took it after tea so that Fine Gael Senators can put down amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am concerned with two things: one is to get the Smelting Bill passed and the other is to get the dumping Bill passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="943" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>All Stages of the dumping Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I explained to Senators that the Minister would not be available and that we were anxious to be facilitated in these two matters. If it is an understanding that we can do business on that basis, then I am prepared to change the Order of Business or change the arrangement which was made here now but otherwise I do not think there is any point in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we be clear on this?  It is not presumed to take all Stages of the dumping Bill. What we contemplated was the Second Stage.  I was trying to help the Minister. If this could be deferred until after tea and if we could at the Minister's convenience arrange to take the Dumping Bill now or at some other time, we would be willing to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We have ordered these other Bills and made arrangements with Ministers concerning them and if we are going to upset that arrangement now, the whole time table will be in a state of flux and chaos.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry. I was endeavouring to facilitate this Minister and that is why I suggested to him that we might take the dumping Bill out of order.  If that is convenient, we will do it but if it does not help him there is no point in doing it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>How long does the Senator visualise it will take to deal with this amendment or amendments he proposes?  Knowing the capacity of Senator O'Quigley to waste time, I dread the idea of making any arrangements about the Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Quigley's or any other Senator's ability to waste time is restricted on Report Stage by being able to speak only once.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>When he starts he can keep going for a long time.  If by giving time for amendments and taking the Report Stage, say, for half an hour tonight it would facilitate the completion of the debate on the <Col N="944" /> dumping Bill, I would be quite prepared to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Another package deal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the proposition then that the House proceed to the Second Stage of the dumping Bill, that to be followed by the Report and Final Stages of the Smelting Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Senators Senators">
      <NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>No, because we have other items ordered here which I want to get done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I think a solution would be to take the Report Stage of this Bill at 9.30 or 10 o'clock and sit to 10.30.  That will meet Senator Garret FitzGerald but I cannot see myself being in a position to propose any amendments at that stage.  That is the obvious course to adopt.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Or earlier if the dumping Bill were completed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>What does that mean?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am being more than reasonable and unusually helpful.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps in that case if we change the order to put the Report and Final Stages to follow the dumping Bill on the understanding that they will be completed tonight, how will that go?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>And not to be taken later than 9.45.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, that is my suggestion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The proposal is that the Report and Final Stages of the Smelting Bill be postponed until after the dumping Bill but otherwise the Order of Business stands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>We agree to that but it is to be understood that it is under protest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="945" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The order which the House has made in regard to the taking of the Report Stage now will have to be discharged and the new Order substituted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  I so move.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The motion is agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Defence Forces (Pensions) (Amendment) Bill, 1968" RHead="(Certified Money Bill): Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Defence Forces (Pensions) (Amendment) Bill, 1968    (Certified Money Bill):    Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I suppose it is correct to say, and I am sure the House will readily agree, that there is nothing more complicated to draft and few things more difficult to understand than the statutory provisions with regard to superannuation.  We had here on the last occasion Senator Ó Maoláin explaining to us with admirable clarity the provisions of an amending scheme to the Deputies pension scheme.  We all understood, of course, the difficulty of understanding, interpreting and putting in clear language what was intended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The new regulations which will be made under this section or which will be laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas under this section are, as laid down, as complicated, as rigmarole and as badly drafted as the regulations we have laid before us in many other cases up to the present time.  Therefore, I should like to ask the Minister, in relation to all Statutory Instruments that will be laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas under this section, whether there will be a comprehensive explanatory memorandum submitted which should accompany it in the same way as an explanatory memorandum would accompany a Bill.  I claim, as a result of the recommendations of the Statutory Instruments Committee some years ago, that we have an explanatory memorandum at the foot of every Statutory Instrument <Col N="946" /> but I want to go much further than that.</P>
    <P>I want not merely the general effect of the Statutory Instruments to be specified in this memorandum but some details as to what the different articles of the Statutory Instruments mean.  If Deputies and Senators are to study those things with any effect they must have an explanatory memorandum. Now, when one goes to most Statutory Instruments that are made under this particular code of pensions, of which there are in all 15 or 16 I understand, and when you also consider the fact that there is nothing equivalent to the index to the statutes available for Statutory Instruments showing what articles have been amended and in what way it becomes absolutely essential if the Members of the Oireachtas are not to be mere cyphers that they should be given an explanatory memorandum setting out what is contained in the instruments to be laid under this section.  I would ask the Minister to undertake to the House that this will be done so as to make a reality of the procedure of laying those before the Houses of the Oireachtas and in that way enabling Members of the Oireachtas to make an intelligent assessment of what is contained in those instruments which at the present time it is impossible for them to do.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. Hilliard) Michael Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. Hilliard)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the usual practice to circulate an explanatory memorandum setting out the details of pensions schemes and amendments thereto and I propose to continue that practice.  When any scheme envisaged in this section is being laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas an explanatory memorandum will be issued.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 3 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I move recommendation No. 1:</P>
      <P>Before section 4 to insert a new section as follows:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;This Act shall come into force on a day to be fixed by the Minister, such day to be not earlier than the <Col N="947" /> seventh day following the laying before each House of the Oireachtas of a copy of the consolidated version of the Defence Forces (Pensions) Scheme.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>On Second Stage Senator Dooge raised the point with regard to the condition in which the Statutory Instruments are at the present time.  There are, as I say, something of the order of 15 or 16 such instruments dealing with pensions under this particular Act, the Act of 1932 and its amending Acts.  In 1958 the Statutory Instruments Committee made a recommendation to the Department of Defence and the Minister for Defence that those instruments be codified into one instruments.  I do not know to what extent that work has progressed but it certainly was the view of the Statutory Instruments Committee that that work should be undertaken and completed.  I remember being on that Committee myself at that time.  They were people who had waded through hundreds of statutory instruments every year and they knew exactly the difficulty in interpreting and following what was contained in a variety of statutory instruments.  This was particularly difficult in regard to the statutory instruments relating to pensions of the Defence Forces</P>
    <P>In modern times it has become necessary to give power to Ministers to make regulations but the stage has now been reached, and we better face up to it, that for most regulations, whether they are under the Social Welfare code, the Defence Forces code or any other code, where it is quite impossible to know at any time what the law is.  If one wants to find out what the law is in relation to an Act of Parliament one can find that in the statutes and one is aided in tracing it in various amendments that have been made by looking up the index to the statutes published periodically and the index published at the end of every year to the statutes passed in any particular year.  There is no similar facility available to anybody to try to trace what amendments have been made by one statutory instruments to another.</P>
    <P>It is quite obvious that when you have a specific recommendation made <Col N="948" /> by a Statutory Instruments Committee established by this House those regulations should be codified it should be done in view of the fact that in this Bill we are now giving authority to the Minister to make regulations and lay them before the Houses of the Oireachtas. The purpose of this amendment is to force the Minister, I franckly admit, and his Department, into codifying this complex and scattered body of regulations and to provide that this Act will not come into force until a date to be fixed by the Minister, which will not be earlier than the seventh day following the laying before each House of the Oireachtas of the codified regulations.</P>
    <P>I consider that is an eminently sensible thing.  It should not be necessary at all in the ordinary course of events to provide for this because the administrators would have enough sense to see to it that the statutory instruments would be clearly available to the public at all times and not available only to officers and servants of the Minister.  When that has not been done after a specific recommendation of the Statutory Instruments Committee, I am inviting the House now to see that they endorse what the Statutory Instruments Committee did in 1958.  They can do that most effectively by accepting this amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to support a good deal of what Senator O'Quigley has said.  I am not quite sure I will go as far as laying this before the Houses of the Oireachtas in order to force the hands of the Minister although I know there has been very great difficulty in finding out in the Department of Defence what exactly the position is in regard to this matter. You find the amendment to an amendment of an amendment.  It is very difficult and very troublesome to discover what the position is.  On the position generally, I think there should be some recommendation whereby a statutory instrument could not be amended more often than so many times and then it must be reprinted with the new amendments and brought up to date even though you might find that in many of these army regulations it is on <Col N="949" /> amendments of substituting a figure of two-thirds or three-thirds or something like that.  It is sometimes a very slight amendment but it seems to me that by reprinting the whole thing after a certain length of time the Departments would facilitate their own staff as well as facilitating members of the Bar and Members of this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>And members of the Defence Forces particularly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>The Defence Forces must want to know what the wording of the Departments is to secure these regulations and find out the conditions.  That is what appeared to us the previous time this came before the Statutory Instruments Committee.  Whereas we understood a great deal had been done there had been nothing near completion on discussion of the matter.  I would not go so far as to delay the regulations under the Bill for this purpose but otherwise I have full sympathy with what Senator O'Quigley has said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>I sympathise very much with the idea underlying the proposal contained in this recommendation because it would be a great convenience for everyone including me as Minister, the Department and the Army to have a consolidated pension scheme.  Actually, a considerable amount of work, preparatory work, was done but the difficulty is that in order to finalise a consolidated measure it is desirable to have what can be described as a valley period&mdash; that is a period free from current amendments and in point of fact we have had no such experience.</P>
      <P>Senator O'Quigley, speaking on section 2, admitted that the preparation of pension schemes is a very complex business, a very difficult business to undertake.  So also is a consolidation measure as Senator O'Quigley knows very well.  There has been no time in recent years at which amendments to the pension schemes have not been on the stocks as a result of pay increases and budgetary increases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>These are factors which prevented the Department from pursuing the <Col N="950" /> matter of condification to finality.  There is also the point that in a number of respects simple consolidation would not be satisfactory.  There are things which could well be changed, provisions which we should like to improve, and so on.  Even if the codification were done it would not mean an end to amendments to pension schemes.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>We should hope so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>As I said on the Second Reading this Bill has been prepared in order to save the time of both Houses of the Oireachtas.  Under the present system requiring confirmation of amending schemes by resolution of each House retired members of the Forces have to wait some time for benefits to which they are entitled.  At present there are ex-members who are waiting increases based on the tenth round pay increase which took place in 1966.  Once this Bill becomes law amending schemes can be made quickly and in the future there need be no great delay since increases would be automatic.  I would, therefore, ask the House to give me this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Defence has, of course, put up the best defence possible for himself and his Department and he has done it in a manly way but I am quite sure that the Minister is not at all happy with the defence he put up.  He was given very few weapons to fight off the charges levelled against him and his Department.</P>
      <P>This, of course, is the usual kind of excuse and answer that one always gets from a Government Department when they have not done their job. The Statutory Instruments Committee which sits here regularly&mdash;and I know the work they do because they are conscious of the frightful mess into which a variety of codes and regulactions get&mdash;made this regulation.  I remember correspondence with the Department of Defence on this matter and then they made this very gentlemanly courteous recommendation in the last part of their report.  It is in the First Report of the Statutory Instruments Committee and it states:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="951" /> In the case of instruments which have been subject to amendments over a period of years such as the Defence Forces (Pensions) Scheme, 1937, the Select Committee is of the opinion that there is a need for consolidation and it would be glad to see this work undertaken at a convenient opportunity.</P>
    <P>This was a very nice polite way for the Members of the Oireachtas to tell the Department of Defence that they failed hopelessly to do their jobs.  I recollect quite distinctly that the correspondence with the Department of Defence at that time did contain a promise somewhat like what the Minister gave now, that the work was under way and it was because we believed at that time that the work was under way that we made this gentlemanly recommendation to the Minister for Defence.</P>
    <P>The present Minister is not to blame for this.  They had another Minister since 1958.  The grounds which the Minister gives of doing it now will always apply.  I can never see stability in money values or, alternatively, whether a stage will be reached where there will be no improvement in pensions for the Defence Forces.  I hope the latter will never arise and, therefore, we expect there will always be amendments to the statutory instruments. If it were not possible to do it in ten years from July 1958 to March 1968, is there any prospect whatever that these regulations will be amended for the next ten years?  I do not see any change from 1968 to 1978 and I do not see that there is any real intention by the Minister or his Department to get down to the work which they can do in a matter of weeks.</P>
    <P>I have here with me to use later this evening the whole difficult code of income tax law.  I do not know how many enactments are involved in this. The difficulty about consolidated statutes is that you have to make recommendation in modern dress to old legislation.  When it comes to consolidated regulations it is freer because not alone can you consolidate the regulations but you can amend them as you go along.  If the Minister wants to <Col N="952" /> incorporate amendments here or there, nobody will find fault with it because these regulations will revoke all the old ones and the new ones will come into effect when presented to the Oireachtas or, rather, when signed by the Minister.  Neither is there any argument for not amending them, based on the proposition that amendments are necessary from time to time.</P>
    <P>If I seek to find out tomorrow which regulations govern Army pensions, with all my experience I could not say with certainly &ldquo;these are the regulation&rdquo;. There is no way of finding out.  I would have to ring the Department.  If any officer or soldier wanted to find out, he should be able to take a single book of regulations.  That is the situation the amendment seeks to bring about &mdash;to force the hand of the Minister to codify the regulations in a way that will make them intelligible to people outside the Department.  I am satisfied nobody outside the Department knows what is contained in the regulations, that nobody can say with any degree of certainty that such and such is what a particular person is entitled to.</P>
    <P>I regret to say the Minister has pleaded a defence which can be pleaded again in 1978 if this matter arises.  He has shown no indication of willingness to tackle the problem.  I regret that the Minister has not faced up to the difficulty and given the House an undertaking that within a year or two years this work will be completed.  The Minister should be in a position to do that.  If he has the will it certainly can be done.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope our Defence Forces are more efficient and up-to-date than the Department who administer their pensions.  It should be stressed that the recommendation of the Statutory Instruments Committee is ten years old.  I do not accept the Minister's defence&mdash;I do not think he believes it himself&mdash;that a valley period is needed to deal with this problem. The Department must know what is the up-to-date position.  They must know in order to administer the pension. All that is required, therefore, is to bring the position into one up-to-date document.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="953" /> A trade union might as well say, instead of looking for improvements in conditions, that it would bring the printed agreement up to date.  We do not do that.  We bring it up to date anyway and at the same time continue to get improvements for members as far as we can.  We do not say we should wait during a valley period.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>A truce is what they want.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is plain silly.  I have more respect for the Minister than to think he believes this himself.  I was shocked, and I underlined it, when we were told during the last sitting that we are now dealing with pension improvements arising out of the 10th round which, as the Minister reminded us, occurred in 1966.  Members of the forces have been waiting to get an increase in pension&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>I told you last week that they were automatic increases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not the Defence Forces (Pensions) (Amendment) Bill, 1966 but the Defence Forces (Pensions) (Amendment) Bill, 1968.  We have had to wait two years before a Bill dealing with adjustments in pensions arising out of the 10th round increases saw the light of day.  This is fantastic.  None of us wants to hold up the measures but even the silent Members condemn this situation and would like to have a firm assurance from the Minister that he will take a bayonet or gun or whatever is necessary to have this straightened out without delay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>The idea in introducing the Bill is to eliminate delay in the payment of automatic increases of the type specified in section 3 of the Bill.  There are very few people who fully understand army pension schemes. The schemes involve instruments which are most difficult to frame and put into legal language.  The same applies in other countries.  It is not as simple as one would think to have these measures consolidated.  There is a reason for the delay.  I have assured the Seanad that I should like to see consolidation brought to finality and I <Col N="954" /> will do everything I can to have that done.  I do not wish to be bound to a period of time in which to complete the work.  I have nothing further to say&mdash; there is nothing further I can say&mdash; beyond the assurance that I will do everything I possibly can.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course, I have no intention of pressing the recommendation because the situation is already bad without making it worse. It was necessary to put down the recommendation to highlight two things &mdash;the neglect to carry out a recommendation of the Statutory Instruments Committee and the appalling delay and callous indifference of the Minister and the Department to frame regulations to give effect to increases which should have been applicable two years ago. These are increases which pensioners should have got two years ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of the £1 a week pay increase.  Pensioners may not have finished their Army service two years ago.  I do not know if there are many who have been waiting two years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Will they get interest?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>No, but if they were liable for income tax they would be paying interest on it.  It is outrageous that this has continued and if the Bill will do anything to avoid that kind of delay it will do something good.  However, I am satisfied nothing will be done about consolidating the Statutory Instruments until some new Minister gets in and gets a bayonet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>You are mistaken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Minister has sufficient steel in him to do it.</P>
      <P>Recommendation, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">TITLE.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Title be the Title to the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to say again that I object vigorously and that I will continue to object to this piece of absurd nonsense of giving to a Bill a <Col N="955" /> title like &ldquo;Defence Forces (Pensions) (Amendment) Bill, 1968.&rdquo;  If we wish to pass a Defence Forces Pensions Bill we should call it that.  We all know that in cases like this one piece of legislation amends another.  It is unnecessary, therefore, to have this sort of title typed across every document, written across every pay cheque.  On this, might I draw your attention to the fact that section 4 of the Act says&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We can hardly go back to that now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there not a mistake in the Title?  In the Bill, we call it &ldquo;An Act to amend the Defence Forces (Pensions) Act, 1932&rdquo; and, in the Title of the Bill, we call it &ldquo;Defence Forces (Pensions) (Amendment) Bill, 1968.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Long Title is before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>Under section 4(2) we read that the Defence Forces (Pensions) Acts, 1932 to 1957, and this Bill when enacted may be cited together as the &ldquo;Defence Forces (Pensions) Acts, 1932 to 1968&rdquo; and shall be construed together as one Act.  The Title of the Bill accords with what was drafted by the Parliamentary draftsman.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without recommendation.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be returned to the Dáil&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>When will the new regulations to give effect to the 10th round increase be made?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>They will be made as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall be keeping an eye out for the Statutory Instruments when it is laid.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Finance (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill," RHead="1967 (Certified Money Bill): Second Stage">
    <Title>Finance (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill, 1967    (Certified Money Bill):    Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="956" /> Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. Haughey) Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. Haughey)</NameTxt>
      <P>The main purpose of this Bill is to provide a new and more precise legislative basis for the taxation of profits from dealing in or developing land.  The existing legislation, which was originally enacted as Part VII of the Finance Act, 1965, and is now contained in Chapter VII of Part IV of the Income Tax Act, 1967, starts off by imposing a very wide charge and then excludes from the charge specific types of transactions which could not be regarded as profits-making ventures of a trading nature.  There has been criticism of the legislation on the grounds that the exclusions do not cover all the appropriate cases.</P>
      <P>Part IV of the Bill approaches the problem in a new way.  It confines liability to cases in which a business of dealing in or developing land is carried on.  The main provision to this effect is contained in section 17.  Briefly, the object of that section is to impose tax on profits on disposals of interests in land in the course of activities which constitute trading but which cannot be regarded as trading under general income tax law because of either or both of two circumstances, namely, that the interest disposed of was not the full interest held by the disponor or that he did not acquire his interest with a view to turning it over at a profit.</P>
      <P>I might mention that the new provisions will be fully retrospective in so far as they give relief but they will operate only as from 6th April, 1968, in so far as they may impose an additional charge.</P>
      <P>The other provisions contained in Part IV deal, <i>inter alia,</i> with the principles for computing the profits of a business of dealing in or developing land and with the avoidance of liability by devices such as buying land at an artifically high price or selling it at an artificially low price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I have said.  Part IV is the <i>raison <Col N="957" /> d'etre</i> of the Bill.  The other parts of the Bill, however, contain a number of important provisions relating to income tax, surtax, corporation profits tax and stamp duties.  I will now deal briefly with the more important of these measures.</P>
    <P>Part I is concerned with income tax. In line with the recommendation of the Commission on Income Taxation, sections 1 and 3 provide for the appointment of Appeal Commissioners to carry out functions under the Income Tax Acts at present performed by the Special Commissioners as well as for the transfer of their administrative functions to the Revenue Commissioners. The Appeal Commissioners will, therefore, be an appellate body only.</P>
    <P>Section 4 provides for a new time-limit of ten years within which income tax and surtax assessments may be made, subject to the qualification that assessments may not be made for a year earlier than 1961-62.  However, these time-limits would not apply in cases involving fraud for neglect and in these cases assessments may be made at any time.  Corresponding time-limits for making claims for repayments of income tax and surtax are provided for in section 4.</P>
    <P>Another important provision of Part I is contained in section 9 which exempts from Irish tax any foreign pension which is not regarded as income for tax purposes in its country of origin.</P>
    <P>Part II of the Bill is concerned with reducing the stamp duties on certain instruments.  The duty on a short-term life insurance policy is being reduced to bring it into line with the duty of 6d on an accident policy.  The duty on agreements for hire of goods, plant and machinery is being reduced to the fixed rates of 6d and 10s which apply in the case of hire-purchase and credit-sales agreements.  The incidence of duty on foreign loan issues by Irish concerns is also being reduced and these will only be chargedable with a duty of 2s 6d per cent on issue.</P>
    <P>Part III extends to corporation profits tax the new time-limits for <Col N="958" /> assessments and claims provided in Part I in relation to income tax.  It also makes the necessary adjustments arising out of the changes made in the title and functions of the Special Commissioners.</P>
    <P>Finally, Part V is a miscellaneous Part which includes provisions in regard to the appointment of and superannuation terms for Appeal Commissioners as well as their replacement of the Special Commissioners for the purpose of the enactments relating to turnover tax and wholesale tax.</P>
    <P>If Members wish to have further explanation of any of the Bill's provisions I will be glad to deal with their questions at the Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>I recommend the Bill to the House for a Second Reading.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the Members of the House would wish the Minister to give a great deal of explanation so that we would get a proper understanding of what this piece of legislation is all about.  I am afraid that the kind of education in tax law that we would require would be such as we could not properly and reasonably request the Minister to give us when the Bill is passing through the House.  I think the new position of dealing with these technical amendments to the various taxation codes is very laudable.  It provides an opportunity for getting down to the detail of income tax and stamp duty legislation, and so on, in a way that was not possible when we had more lengthy debates on the Finance Bill, when it was introduced, to implement the Budget Resolutions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There has been a good deal of debate on this Bill in the Dáil.  From what I can gather from my colleagues in the Law Library, it has been the subject of much scrutiny and examination by a variety of concerns, assisted by various legal advisers.  I rather gather that the Minister and the Revenue Commissioners have gone a good distance to meet a variety of perhaps not objections but fears and to clarify a number of matters in various ways.  That is very much to the good.  One hopes that the end <Col N="959" /> result of all of that will be that the income tax law will be somewhat more intelligible not alone to the ordinary man in the street but to the ordinary run of the mill lawyers than it has been up to the present time.</P>
    <P>Codification of the income tax law in this volume was a great step forward in making income tax legislation somewhat more intelligible, though I have heard one person, who is rather an expert on income tax legislation, saying that he knew the old sections so well that he now found it difficult to translate his mind into the new sections contained in the Bill.  One can sympathise with that kind of attitude and see how it arises.  In that context, I want to congratulate the Minister and the Revenue Commissioners on the new loose-leaf volume of the Income Tax Act of 1967 and the splendid index which has been provided with it.  It certainly will make it a great deal easier now to find the various sections of the legislation which pertain to a particular problem, and the new loose-leaf income tax volume with the index has already received widespread commendation among income tax lawyers.</P>
    <P>The same thing has already been done in relation to stamp duty, and I hope that with the passage of time, it may be possible to do that in relation to death duties and corporation profits tax.  Somebody asked me to inquire from the Minister if there is any word of the codification of the law relating to corporation profits tax, and he might be able to deal with that. I am quite sure that such codification would be welcome.</P>
    <P>This Bill, of course, makes redundant almost immediately the new Income Tax Act of 1967, or certainly throws it back into the melting pot.  I am wondering whether it would be possible for the Minister to issue as a White Paper, or as an explanatory memorandum to this Bill, those sections of the Income Tax Act 1967 which are amended in a substantial way by this Bill.  I readily agree that it would be laborious, and perhaps unduly costly, to take all the amendments <Col N="960" /> made in the Schedule and to weld those into the Income Tax Act 1967, certainly the amendments contained in Part I and Part II, but I wonder whether it would be very costly to take the substantial amendments to section 7 of the 1967 Act and, as happened in the case of the Criminal Procedure Act 1967, and the Rent Restrictions (Amendment) Act 1967, to weld the amendments being made by this Bill into the existing sections of the 1967 Act.  I have no doubt that if the Minister were to undertake that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>That will be done in the loose-leaf edition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister will earn the gratitude of many a harassed accountant and lawyer and, I suppose, taxpayer, when that operation has been completed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>In the present Bill we also repeal a whole Part of the 1965 Act and put in a new Part for consistency purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I see that, in relation to Part IV, that it is a replacement of what we call Part VII of the 1965 Finance Act.  That is easy enough and it stands by itself, but then the amendments in Part I and in Part V&mdash; if it were possible to do it without any great expense, it would make for a much readier appreciation of income tax law.</P>
      <P>The Minister has referred to a number of amendments being made in relation to the re-opening of assessments. I wonder if I am correct in this, that while the limitation of ten years placed upon the re-opening of assessments which have already been made applies in relation to income tax, the period has been extended from six to ten years in the case of surtax assessments?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>No. The same has been done in both cases.  What has happened is that up to now, it was a practice of the Revenue Commissioners, not to go back beyond six years.  Now we are setting the statutory limits and making the period ten years.  Subject <Col N="961" /> to the qualification that assessments may not be made for a year earlier than 1961-62.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I see that.  To an extent the new statutory provision is continuing the practice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Except that it is now statutory.  The big complaint in the Dáil was that only a practice of the Revenue Commissioners.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>To that extent, it gives a degree of security, but it would not, in fact, affect anybody who has had an assessment made for surtax up to the present time.  Further, the Minister takes power in the Bill, in giving this concession to limit the re-opening of the assessment to a period of ten years back from any particular year.  At the same time, when one looks at the definition of neglect, one sees that if it exists in relation to making a return or a statement, the concession almost vanishes.  Neglect is defined as negligence or failure to give any notice or make any return, statement or particulars.  I can well understand a person being negligent and not giving notice, and their saying: &ldquo;We will re-open our assessment and have a look at what you were liable for&rdquo;, but if it refers to mere failure or to the case of a person at a particular time being unwell or being bothered by adverse business affairs, that individual kind of case will be caught as if it were guilty of fraud.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a proviso for a reasonable excuse.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>In that context, I suppose it does provide that where a person had a reasonable excuse for not doing anything, he shall be deemed not to have failed.  I can only hope in the interests of the taxpayer concerned that the Revenue Commissioners will be reasonably reasonable in their interpretation of &ldquo;a reasonable excuse&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the repeal of Part VII of the 1965 Act, which is in effect being done in Part IV, I think that the general view is that the Minister has <Col N="962" /> now succeeded in really getting at the kind of profits from the business of dealing in land that was originally intended.  For my part, I commend the attitude that lays down a particular line at a particular time, on the understanding that if it does not work out well, the Minister concerned will have no hesitation in coming back to the Legislature with amending legislation in the light of experience.  I have oftentimes in the House suggested that certain amendments be adopted on that basis and that legislation be enacted, particularly where new fields have been gone into.  I think it entirely praiseworthy on the part of the previous Minister for Finance, who is now the present Taoiseach, and the present Minister, to have faced up to the real difficulties, some of which might not have existed if more consideration had been given to them, which were shown to arise in the course of the application of the Acts by the Revenue Commissioners.</P>
    <P>I am still not satisfied, nor do I think a lot of people are satisfied, that Part II of this Bill gives the security that one would wish.  There was a good deal of discussion on section 16 in the Dáil and the Minister now in his own statement says that the object of the section is to impose tax on profits on disposals of interests of land in the course of activities which constitutes trading but which cannot be regarded as trading under general income tax law and I feel that part of the difficulty that has arisen in relation to the taxation of profits arising out of dealing in and developing of land arises from the fact that it was sought to fit this new kind of activity which it was desired to capture into a code which was not really suitable to receive the amendment and it might have been better to face boldly up to the situation and set up a new set of rules analogous to the rules under which it was sought to make this income liable and deal with it in that way.  I feel that if that had been done it might be clearer and easier to understand what was being got at but that, in fact, has not been done and I suppose there will still be a <Col N="963" /> good deal of debate and discussion as to what various provisions of this part of the Act means.  However, the general opinion does seem to be that the more objectionable, from the point of view of the taxpayer, features of the 1965 Act have been got rid of in sections 16 and 17.</P>
    <P>There are a few other matters I should like to refer to and, perhaps, the Minister might be able to deal with them in his reply.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Business suspended at 6.5 p.m. and resumed at 7.15 p.m.</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Before business was suspended I was about to ask the Minister what the position was in relation to friendly societies.  As I understand the position under the Friendly Societies Act of 1898, I think it was, friendly societies are limited certainly for insurance purposes to issuing policies, not exceeding £300.  I think it was £200 under the 1898 Act and then that was amended subsequently to £300 in an Act amending that. Under the Credit Union Act, 1966, there was an extension of the maximum amount for which those societies could insure from £300 to £1,000. When the Income Tax Act, 1918, was enacted certain exemptions under various schedules were given to friendly societies which were either limited by their own articles or by statute to this limit of £300 of which I speak.</P>
      <P>The purpose of that I take it was to encourage the development of friendly societies and to encourage an expansion of their activities.  The £300, of course, is long since out of date.  The Credit Union Act, 1966, brought in a more realistic figure.  As I understand it, the position now is that the friendly societies are either prevented from extending themselves to the £1,000 limit or if they do extend themselves to that limit the exemptions provided for them under the 1967 Income Tax Act will no longer be available to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is not anything in this Bill dealing with that kind of situation.  It seems to me that it is desirable in view of the extensions contained in the <Col N="964" /> Credit Union Act, 1966, to modify the provisions of the Income Tax Act to enable those friendly societies to avail themselves at the same time of the extensions provided by the amendment contained in the Credit Union Act, 1966 and at the same time of the valuable exemptions which were provided for them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>That has been done. The £300 has been increased to £1,000 in the case of the friendly societies under the 1967 Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>In the Finance Act? Those who should know advise me it has not been done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>There may be confusion. In the case of the trade unions it has not been done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>It was not the trade unions that my informant was concerned about but, in fact, the ordinary friendly societies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>The increase in the case of the friendly societies was provided by section 7 of the Finance Act, 1967.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>That is section 7.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not the Consolidation Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate it is the ordinary Finance Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 7 says:</P>
      <P>Section 335 of the Income Tax Act, 1967, is hereby amended by the substitution of &ldquo;£1,000&rdquo; for &ldquo;£300.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I was surprised that the exemption provisions in the Income Tax Act were not up to date with the limit provided in the Credit Union Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to refer to the stamp duty provisions in this particular Act.  I do not understand why in modern times, when we are dealing in terms of millions of pounds, stamp duty at the rate of 6d. on a short-term life insurance policy should be worth bothering about at all.  I do not know that the actual stamping of a particular document gives it any greater validity or <Col N="965" /> sanctity except unless it is stamped that it is not admissible as evidence in a court of justice.</P>
    <P>What I am trying to get at it is that small amounts such as 6d and 1s cost more in terms of man-hours on a national scale in paying and collecting them than is really worthwhile as a contribution to the Exchequer.  I would rather we did this in the way we got rid of the 2d stamp a few years ago and that all 6d stamps at present required which give no added validity or sanction to agreements and so on should be abolished altogether.</P>
    <P>I am also mindful of the position in regard to the number of stamps that have to be affixed to various court documents.  Somebody in the Minister's Department or in Revenue should carry out an investigation as to the amount of wholly paid time that is wasted daily and weekly in the stamping of affidavits, motions, and so on in our courts.  For instance, one has to get an attested copy of an affidavit, which is an antediluvian process. One has to get an affidavit read over to ensure that the affidavit handed to the judge corresponds with the affidavit originally filed and that affidavit has to be stamped.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Senator is addressing those remarks to the wrong Minister; they come more within the purview of my colleague, the Minister for Justice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The present Minister gets a rake off in the stamp of the attested copy.  It is either 2/6 or 3/6.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Any action on this line would have to be initiated by the Minister for Justice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to put to the Minister with regard to the amount of money collected in these footling payments of duties that if he insisted on the courts paying them they could easily be collected by levying on successful plaintiffs&mdash;or unsuccessful defendants as the case may be&mdash;a stamp duty to be paid once and for all. In the case of a High Court action <Col N="966" /> where one has to get 14 documents stamped on 14 different occasions time is wasted getting these things done and the total amount of stamp duty on this is say, £3; it might be more when you have a stamp on a plenary summons.  It should be possible to average out over a year what the amount is and then when an order is made the stamp duty should be levied and collected.  But the provision in relation to the 6d stamps in Part II seems to me to be ludicrous in modern times.</P>
      <P>When one considers that all of these documents have to be stamped by somebody and taken to the stamping office and waited on and collected, the loss in man-hours is disproportionate to the amount of revenue collected by this means.  The Minister for Finance the Revenue Commissioners and the Minister for Justice and the rules-making committees of the courts in relation to court work should consider the abolition of these stamp duties altogether or, alternatively, substitution of a single stamp.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In relation to duties dealt with in Part II of the Bill, the Minister should consider seriously getting rid of trifling duties in the same way as the 2d stamp was got rid of in the past ten years. There is another matter in relation to stamp duties which I had hoped to see included in a Bill of this kind.  Everybody will agree that the cost of a house at present is sufficiently high for young married couples, or, indeed, single people if they want to buy it, to suggest that when a person is buying a house for the first time or, for employment reasons is transferring from one house to another, he should not have to pay for one of the necessaries of life, a home in which to live, any contribution to the State.  It might have been all right in the old days when the Stamp Acts were first introduced and when big wealthy owners had to pay to transfer interest in properties, but it seems to be socially wrong to require people who are put to the pin of their collars to buy houses in order to found families to have to pay this kind of contribution to the State.  The Minister for Finance should consider abolishing altogether stamp duty on transfers of <Col N="967" /> properties which are intended to be used and designed to be used as dwellings. That would be a small help to prospective house buyers and I do not think the amount of money lost would be enormous.  Perhaps the rate of duty on other property activities could be increased to offset the losses the Minister might have.</P>
    <P>There is one further matter which I should be obliged if the Minister clarified.  It is contained in section 6. I am not quite certain what is the effect of the section.  The explanatory memorandum, I regret to say, is as mean in its information on this section and other sections as one might expect the Revenue Commissioners to be.  Of course, this was issued by the Department of Finance who are not giving very much away.  The memorandum on section 6 says that subsection (1) repeals sections 167, 168, 171 (3) and 179.  It seems to me that what is being done in this case by this section amounts to a worsening of the position of income tax and surtax payers.  It appears that where previously a notice to furnish a return was given by the Revenue Commissioners to individual taxpayers, that will not be done any more.  I do not know if I am correct in that interpretation.  If that be so, I wonder what is the reason for it and what purpose it is intended to serve.  I should like to know why it is being done.</P>
    <P>Finally, in connection with a Bill of this kind, while it is not easy to spell out in a clear way what is intended to be done by the different Acts, it would be of considerable help to Members of the House, who always have a short time to study the final provisions of the Bill, if we had an explanatory memorandum in a form a lot more ample than the one which accompanied this Bill as introduced.  There was no explanatory memorandum with the Bill as passed by Dáil Éireann.  I can readily agree that arises because of the brief interval between its passage in the Dáil and the discussion in this House.  Our discussion here is limited and it is important, therefore, that the provisions of the more complicated sections should be amplified more <Col N="968" /> fully.  In the circumstances of the short time we have to discuss the Bill that would be very welcome.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful to Senator O'Quigley for what I might describe as the guarded welcome he has given the measure.  I shall deal at the outset with his query on section 6. The purpose of the section is to tidy up a number of measures which deal with the obligation to issue notices of one kind or another.  The main purpose of the section is to abolish the requirement on the Revenue Commissioners to issue a general notice which could be in conflict with some other provisions of Acts arising out of new developments in our taxation structure generally which require various people like employers to submit specific lists, specific returns, specific information.</P>
      <P>The proviso requiring a general notice is no longer appropriate to this type of situation and the main purpose of section 6 is to repeal that proviso and then to make a number of consequential provisions.  When Senator O'Quigley was speaking, I mentioned that it seemed to me the questions he raised about stamp duty on court documents were ones which, perhaps, he should raise in the first instance with the Minister for Justice because the Revenue aspects of the items he mentioned are comparatively unimportant.  It may be that the law requires stamping of some of these deeds for the purpose of giving them formality which they otherwise would not have.  The Senator might raise it on some other occasion with the Minister for Justice.  Offhand, I cannot recall if any other point was raised by Senator O'Quigley which I have not dealt with already by way of question and answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad the Minister is saying that the revenue implications and the stamp duties are very small.  I raised the matter with the Minister for Justice on another occasion and was told it was one for the Minister for Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall undertake to discuss it.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="969" />
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>In deference to representations made to me that a number of matters arise on various sections on the Committee Stage, it seems to me that the Bill would require a somewhat longer study than I have been able to give it in the time I have had it.  I should be obliged if we could have it this day week.  The Minister for Finance will be aware of the widespread interest in his proposals and, notwithstanding the clarification of them in the Dáil, there are still some matters that require elucidation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator might agree to give the Committee Stage and all Stages on Tuesday, 19th March, 1968.  This is a Money Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are limited in time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We must dispose of it on or before 20th March.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>There are technical difficulties if the House sits on the day following a bank holiday&mdash;printing, and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any objection to Wednesday next, 13th March?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is inconvenient for a number of Senators to be here next Wednesday.  The Senator will appreciate the difficulties.  If we could be assured of the completion of the Committee and remaining Stages on Wednesday, 20th March, 1968, that would be satisfactory.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Fair enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it agreed to take all Stages on Wednesday 20th March, 1968?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot forecast what the House will do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The House must come to a decision.  The Chair understands that the Bill will be taken on Wednesday, 20th March, 1968, and <Col N="970" /> that all Stages of the Bill will be agreed to on that day.</P>
      <P>Agreed and ordered accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Courts (Supplemental Provisions) (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1967&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Courts (Supplemental Provisions) (Amendment) Bill, 1967&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. B. Lenihan) Brian (Snr.) Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. B. Lenihan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill may be stated very briefly.  It is to provide that a judge of the Supreme Court, Judge W. O'B. Fitzgerald, who was appointed to the Bench in October, 1966, will qualify for full pension, that is, one-half of salary, when he reaches the retiring age in 1978, notwithstanding that he will have only eleven years service on retiring age, as against the standard fifteen years' service required for full pension.</P>
      <P>I wish to emphasise that the new provision applies only to the Supreme Court and only to one judge of that Court.  The question of extending the new provision to the other serving judges of the Supreme Court does not arise, because their ages and lengths of service on the Bench are such that it would confer no benefit on them.</P>
      <P>In view of the very special importance of the Supreme Court in our judicial system, it will, I feel sure, be widely accepted that the Government, in considering appointments to that Court, should have open to it the widest possible field of selection.  It follows that a minor obstacle in the way of a particular appointment should be capable of being removed, so as to put outstanding Senior Counsel, as in this instance with no previous service on the Bench, in a position to accept an offer of appointment made to him by the Government.  In the present instance, acceptance of appointment as Supreme Court judge involved the person concerned in a very substantial reduction in income, and the Government did not hesitate to accept the view that steps should be taken to enable him to qualify for full pension on reaching retiring age after eleven years' service instead of the usual fifteen years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="971" /> This proposed measure arises from the Government's consideration of an individual case in the Supreme Court. As I have mentioned already, the other Supreme Court judges are not involved.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The House will have little difficulty in accepting this Bill because of the reasons advanced by the Minister.  It is right and proper that persons of maturity as well as of great skill and experience should be available, especially in the Supreme Court.  As the Government found themselves in the position of wanting to appoint somebody who would not qualify for full pension, they acted very prudently in offering the appointment upon the basis that legislation like this would be enacted.  In the last resort, from the point of view of the individual citizen and taxpayer, what is important in a country such as ours is that the High Court and the Supreme Court Bench should be peopled by judges of the highest possible calibre. It is a small price to pay for getting people of that calibre to provide that, when their normal way of life is interrupted with a tempting invitation to accept a nomination to the High Court or the Supreme Court, they should be in a position to do so without undue loss of income.</P>
      <P>The position for many lawyers is that even after the age of 72, which is the retiring age for judges of the High Court and the Supreme Court, they can continue in their own way to earn quite a good livelihood.  Once a man goes on the Bench and reaches the age of 72 he does not earn and he cannot go back to practice.  I suppose that he could, there is no law against it, but the convention is the other way.  Therefore, it means that in cases such as here the earning life of a judge is shortened, and I think it is right and proper that due account should be taken of that.  I am glad to be in a position to support the Bill most wholeheartedly.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="972" /> Bill considered in Committee.</P>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I have heard the Minister for Justice from time to time asking the House to accept certain amendments on the basis that his amendment and his drafting was clean drafting and perfectly clearcut.  I do not think the Minister would for a moment suggest that subsection (2) is clean drafting, with this rigmarole &ldquo;The Courts (Supplemental Provisions) Act, 1961, the Courts (Supplemental Provisions) (Amendment) Act, 1962, the Courts (Supplemental Provisions) (Amendment) Act, 1964, the Courts Act, 1964, and this Act shall be construed together as one Act and may be cited together as the Courts (Supplemental Provisions) Acts, 1961 to 1967&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Very clean, excellent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I think this is the greatest form of gibberish, and the sooner we get away from this business of brackets and simply saying the Courts Acts, 1961 to 1967 and leaving it at that the better.  There is no necessity, and never was, to refer to it as the Courts (Supplemental Provisions) Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Now we have bulked them all in one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>It reminds me of the wasp's nest that was found in the attic of my house this morning.  It was a pile upon pile of wax.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>All the verbiage is finished now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not wish the Minister to believe what he says he does believe.  I would hope that he does not.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without recommendation, received for final consideration and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Local Government (Buncrana) Bill, 1968:" RHead="Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Local Government (Buncrana) Bill, 1968: Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="973" /> Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Minister for Local Government (Mr. Boland) Kevin Boland">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government (Mr. Boland)</NameTxt>
      <P>This short Bill proposes to alter the present statutory basis of assessing the annual rate demand by Donegal County Council on the urban district of Buncrana.</P>
      <P>The cost of services carried out by a county council for the whole county, including any urban districts in the county, is apportioned between the county health district and the urban districts by reference to the effective valuation of each area.  The share of each urban district is levied by way of an annual demand made by the county council on the district.  A general revision of all rateable property in Buncrana was carried out in 1950 at the request of the Urban District Council. As a result the total valuation of the urban district increased from £7,563 at the 1st March, 1950, to £11,445 at the 1st March, 1951.  As no request had been made to the Commissioner of Valuation to have the valuations of property in the rest of County Donegal comprehensively revised, the valuation revision in Buncrana resulted in a disproportionate increase in the county demand on that urban district.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Local Government (Temporary Reduction of Valuation) Acts, 1954 and 1960, contained provisions designed to ease the effect of the valuation revision on Buncrana.  The 1954 Act provided that the 1954/55 county demand would be calculated on the estimated valuation of the town in that year if the general revision had not taken place and only normal increases in valuation had occurred since 1951. This notional valuation was then to be increased each year for county demand purposes by a fixed amount of £330 annually over a ten-year period, at the end of which the normal method of calculating the county demand by reference to the actual valuation would apply.  In fact, however, the normal annual increase in valuation between 1954 and 1960 fell substantially below the estimates on which the 1954 Act formula had been devised.  To meet the resultant situation, the 1960 Act provided <Col N="974" /> that the county demand on Buncrana was to be calculated in respect of the year 1960/61 on the basis of 70 per cent of the net produce of a rate of one penny in the £ in the urban area.  This proportion was to increase by 1 per cent of a penny in each subsequent year until, in 1990/91, the county demand would, as elsewhere, fall to be calculated on the net produce of a rate of one penny in the £.</P>
    <P>The present Bill provides for the stabilisation of the basis of assessment of the county demand at 70 per cent of the net produce of a rate of 1d in the £ until such time as there is a general revision of the valuation of the rest of County Donegal.  The effect will be to reduce Buncrana's share of the cost of the services carried out by the county council on behalf of the entire county, including the urban areas, to what it would have been if a general revision of valuation had not taken place in Buncrana and to maintain an equitable financial relationship in the future between the various contributing areas in the county.</P>
    <P>It is proposed that the new arrangements will come into effect in relation to the year beginning on the 1st April, 1968.  The statutory period for the estimates meetings of county councils expires at the end of the present month.  It is essential, therefore, for legal reasons, that the Bill should be enacted without delay if the revised arrangements are to apply in respect of 1968-69.  The Bill has been promoted at the request of the parties most directly affected&mdash;Buncrana Urban District Council and Donegal County Council&mdash;and because the legislation is necessary to rectify an inequitable situation.  On that basis, I commend it to the Seanad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister can be assured straight away of getting this Bill as far as I am concerned and all Stages of it this evening.  However, the Bill highlights a matter to which I have already referred in this House and that is the obsolescence, if not the complete obsoleteness, of the present method of valuation.  This Bill highlights it in a very particular way because the law at the present time enacts that there shall <Col N="975" /> be annual valuations of property and every property is valued annually and anybody can in any year&mdash;and the notices are going out at the present time&mdash;object to a valuation of his property because there is a notional valuation of that property every year.  What has happened here, as I understand the Minister's speech, which is a good deal more enlightening, indeed, than anything contained in the Bill, is that Buncrana town was revalued in 1950.  If the mechanism for valuing property and carrying out valuations were operated correctly then it did not matter if Buncrana was valued because equally so it is correct to say that all other properties in the county are, according to law, valued in every year and as I have said the mechanism for valuing properties is such that whatever valuation is made in strict accordance with the Valuation Acts is divided by three and that is the way you get the valuation of a particular property at a particular time.  It is quite clear that the present system of carrying out valuations is not suitable and this particular Bill indicates that quite clearly.  I have little doubt that it would be a great inequity and a great injustice to the ratepayers of Buncrana if they were, because of this revaluation, required to pay more than their share of the county at large charges being made by Donegal County Council.  I entirely agree that they should not have to bear more than their proportionate share of local taxation.  I suppose it would be irrelevant to say that the whole system of rating both in Buncrana and the rest of Donegal is quite out of date and the idea of imposing rates on the valuation of properties which have to be paid irrespective of the capacity of the ratepayer to pay it is to my mind socially unacceptable in modern times. I could only wish that the Minister, instead of bringing in a Bill confined to relief for Buncrana, was bringing in a Bill that would provide relief for all the ratepayers of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBoland" hpid="Mr. Boland Mr. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>Many people would agree with what Senator O'Quigley has said and it is generally agreed that the present system is not satisfactory but the problem, of course, is what to substitute <Col N="976" /> for it.  In this respect an interDepartmental committee has been sitting, has already published two reports, the third report is just ready for publication and the fourth is being prepared.  I think that will practically complete their consideration of the matter.  The Government have made it clear that they are not committed to the views expressed in these reports that have been published but they are published in order that interested people and interested organisations will submit their comments on them. The intention is that when these are all available the Government will see what can be done to provide a more satisfactory system.</P>
      <P>In their first report the interDepartmental committee dealt with the question of valuation for rating purposes and made a number of recommendations on the matter.  The committee, in fact, concluded that the position in regard to rateable valuation is unsatisfactory and should be remedied by a general revaluation of all property excluding agricultural lands situated outside the county boroughs and Dún Laoghaire Borough.  A summary of this report has been published with a view to evoking suggestions for the improvement of or providing alternatives to the present system.  The other two reports of the committee should be available to the public fairly soon and as soon as they have been published and there has been some time to comment on them it is the Government's intention to formulate proposals for any necessary changes in the system of local finance and taxation.</P>
      <P>In the meantime I might point out that action is being taken all the time to lessen the burden of ratepayers by increasing State aid to local authorities. A striking feature of local authority finance in recent years has been the huge increase in such State aid which in the current year meets an estimated 52 per cent of local authority revenue expenditure and the proportion of local authority revenue expenditure which is met by rates at present is 32 per cent so that something is being done in the meantime to lessen the burden on ratepayers generally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="977" /> I thank the House for the manner in which they received the Bill.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Bill considered in Committee.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 1.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I say what I have been saying on other sections of Bills like this?  I think the Minister would agree, from his experience of local government law, that there are few branches, apart I suppose from taxation laws, that are so difficult to find your way round than local government law.  I do not know that it would be possible at any time to do very much to clarify the position by way of codification.  What I would suggest to the Minister to bear in mind with a view to not allowing the position to get out of hand entirely is to endeavour, when sections are being amended, to take a whole section and amend it. The Minister will see from section 1 here that the Principal Act means section 10 of the Local Government Act, 1946 which has already been amended in 1954, amended again in 1955 and in 1960.  The Local Government (Temporary Reduction of Valuation) Act, 1960 might be an amendment in relation to a figure but those things are becoming more confusing.  I would ask the Minister, when those amendments are being made in future legislation, to try as far as possible to amend a whole section at once and not allow reference back to previous statutes and amending them.  When people get down to probe one section they have to go back to sections in another Act which has already been amended.  If one whole section is completely amended it would be more clear to the Minister, his officials, and the public at large.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBoland" hpid="Mr. Boland Mr. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>This seems desirable. I do not know if there is any difficulty from the drafting point of view but it certainly seems to me to be agreeable.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 2 and 3 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Bill reported without amendment, <Col N="978" /> received for final consideration and passed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Imposition of Duties (Dumping and" RHead="Subsidies) Bill, 1967: Second Stage">
    <Title>Imposition of Duties (Dumping and Subsidies) Bill, 1967: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley) George Colley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Colley)</NameTxt>
      <P>The object of this Bill is to provide legislation to safeguard both our manufacturing and agricultural industries against injury, or even destruction, by dumped or subsidised imports from other countries.</P>
      <P>It is not the object of the Bill to provide further protection for Irish producers, as the word protection is ordinarily used.  To counteract dumping is the more important object of the Bill, since the danger from subsidisation is more remote.</P>
      <P>Neither dumping nor subsidisation may be wrong in itself, but may justly be objected to when it injures a manufacturing or agricultural industry by infiltration into the home market.  The home market may also be threatened by fair competition or by imports from low cost countries.  From the point of view of the Irish producer it is all the same whether he loses his market because of fair competition, low cost imports, dumping or subsidisation, and for this reason producers are apt to complain of dumping when they find that imported goods of the kind they produce themselves are being offered at prices which are lower than their own. Most of the complaints of dumping which my Department has received in recent years have been of this kind, and investigation has shown that the charge of dumping could not be substantiated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There has been little danger of dumping, so far, in this country, because of the high tariff protection.  The exporter of dumped goods has to lower his prices so as to absorb these tariffs and, for this reason, dumping in Ireland is not in general an attractive proposition.  If, however, prices of Irish goods are unnecessarily inflated to take advantage of the tariff protection, the producers concerned run the risk of losing the home market, either through fair competition or through <Col N="979" /> dumping.  Apart from this, as our tariff protection is reduced because of international agreements, the danger of dumping will increase and so, in order to make provision for the years ahead, it is necessary now to introduce effective, flexible and acceptable anti-dumping legislation.  The powers which the Government already have under the Imposition of Duties Acts can be and have been used to counter dumping. These Acts, however, were designed to facilitate the imposition of protective tariffs and are not ideally suitable as anti-dumping measures. Duties imposed under these Acts do not bear on their face any indication that they are anti-dumping duties.  The Acts, moreover, are not sufficiently flexible and were not designed to conform with the accepted methods of dealing with dumping or subsidisation.</P>
    <P>It is internationally agreed that countries are entitled to take action against dumping or subsidisation and there is also a fair measure of agreement about the kind of action which may be taken.  Of particular concern to this country are the principles contained in Article VI of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, the GATT, and the agreement circulated in June, 1967 on its implementation. Member States may sign this agreement if they wish to do so.  A number of them, including Britain, has already done so and it is probable that Ireland will also wish to sign it.  This anti-dumping code of the GATT is of importance to us, first of all, because we have now acceded to the GATT and, secondly, because it is provided in the Free Trade Area Agreement with Britain that both countries will observe Article VI in their anti-dumping measures.</P>
    <P>Dumping may take place for different reasons.  A manufacturer may overproduce and find himself with large stocks.  He does not wish to tie up his capital in holding these and so he has to sell them, even at a loss.  He cannot afford to damage his home market by unloading the goods there and for this reason he dumps them in another country.  A manufacturer may also dump for the purpose of destroying an <Col N="980" /> industry in another country, by taking away its market.  He calculates that he will then have the market to himself and can recoup himself by stepping up his prices.  Dumping may also be motivated by political purposes.  A country may not be able to attack industry in another country by direct dumping, because the country is protected by anti-dumping legislation, but it may be able to attack that country's markets in third countries.  The kind of dumping most difficult to counter is sporadic dumping, the sudden unforeseeable and massive importation of goods at dumped prices.  The peculiar difficulty of dealing with this kind of dumping is that the damage has been done before action can be taken.</P>
    <P>The fact of dumping is determined by setting the prices at which goods are offered for sale in the exporting country, at any point in the chain of distribution between factory and consumer, against the comparable prices at which these or similar goods are offered, at the same point, for importation into the importing country.  The prices at which local producers offer their goods for sale are not relevant to the question of dumping.  Accordingly, in the Bill two prices are defined, the fair market price, in section 3, which is, in effect, the home market price in the exporting country and the export price, in section 2, which is in effect the comparable price at which the goods are offered for export to this country.  If the fair market price is greater than the export price then there is dumping, and the difference between the two prices is the margin of dumping.</P>
    <P>The Bill provides for the setting up of a commission whose members will be appointed by the Minister for Industry and Commerce and by the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries. This commission will investigate all complaints of dumping and will make a report to the appropriate Minister. It will be the task of the commission to establish whether there has been dumping and, if there has been, to ascertain the fair market price and export price and, then, the margin of dumping.  The commission will also investigate whether any dumping which has taken place <Col N="981" /> has caused material injury to an Irish industry and this aspect of the dumping will be considered at the same time as the dumping itself.  It is not enough that there should have been dumping. It must also be established that this dumping was injurious.  This is a very important principle in the GATT code on anti-dumping legislation.</P>
    <P>What I have just said needs some modification with respect to third country dumping.  It is in accordance with the GATT code that anti-dumping measures may be applied if dumping attacks the market of another country in this country, even though it does not injure a domestic industry.  Provision is made for this in section 14.</P>
    <P>It is only in the case of certain evidence to be provided by the Revenue Commissioners that the commission will have power to require the production of evidence.  In general there is no compulsion on any person or firm to give evidence to the commission or to appear before it.  This also is in accordance with the international code. At the same time, the decision as to the fair market price and the export price will be made by the commission, though provision is made for an appeal to the Minister.</P>
    <P>A distinctive feature of the commission is that it will have power to effect the refund of any duty which has been paid in excess of the margin of dumping. Governments and Ministers of State are liable to be suspected abroad of using anti-dumping legislation for the purpose of concealed protection.  It is desirable, therefore, that the Government's intention, which is also a principle of the international code, that anti-dumping duties in any particular case should not exceed the margin of dumping, will be carried out by an independent body.</P>
    <P>Power is also provided whereby the appropriate Minister may impose provisional duties on the recommendation of the commission.  These duties are provisional in the sense that they have later to be confirmed by the Government. If they are not confirmed, any duties collected will have to be refunded.  The purpose of these provisional duties is to guard the market <Col N="982" /> while the commission is carrying out its investigation into a complaint of dumping, and such duties would not be recommended by the commission nor imposed by the Minister unless this action was considered necessary.</P>
    <P>Power is also provided whereby the Government can impose anti-dumping duties, which will be effective from the date of their imposition, or can confirm provisional duties, so that such duties will, in effect, be retroactive to the date of the imposition of the provisional duties.</P>
    <P>All duties imposed under the Bill will be duties of customs and will be administered by the Revenue Commissioners.</P>
    <P>Another important feature of the commission is that its deliberations will be carried out in private and that information given to it will be treated as confidential, if those who give the information so desire.  This provision, which is contrary to the practice in some countries, is designed to protect the interests of those who have to meet an allegation of dumping, and to encourage them to lay all the facts before the commission.</P>
    <P>It will be noted that there is special provision in the Bill, section 17, to safeguard the Glass Bottle industry against dumping.  The reason for this is that this industry is peculiarly exposed to the danger of being very greatly injured or destroyed by sporadic dumping. A single consignment of goods could cause the industry to close down its furnaces and this in turn might force the one firm engaged in the industry into liquidation.  It is not the intention that the safeguards provided in this section, for this one industry, will be extended to any other industry.</P>
    <P>The duties which are imposed for the purposes of counteracting the effects of subsidies given in other countries are known as countervailing duties, and these duties will be imposed by the Government.  It will not be part of the function of the commission to make recommendations in respect of countervailing duties or to examine matters relating to subsidisation as these are more appropriate to the Government.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="983" /> The Minister, however, will be able to consult the commission.  It should be noted that anti-dumping and countervailing duties are not additive, so that if an anti-dumping duty is imposed to counter dumping, the same element of dumping may not, at the same time, be countered by a countervailing duty, even though the dumping is the result of subsidisation.  There are provisions, also, parallel to those for anti-dumping duties, for the refund of countervailing duties to the extent that these exceed the amount of the subsidy.</P>
    <P>The Bill also provides for the imposition by the Government of a retroactive levy.  This levy, which is not a customs duty, may be imposed only on goods to which a provisional duty applies, but may be charged on any such goods which were imported during a period of 90 days before the date on which the provisional duty was imposed.  The purpose of this provision, which is in accordance with the international code which was circulated in June, 1967, is to deal with sporadic dumping, and certain conditions have to be fulfilled before the Government can impose such a levy.  Senators will, I think, agree that this rather severe provision should be an effective deterrent against the kind of dumping which is most likely to endanger an Irish industry, and most difficult to prevent.</P>
    <P>The Bill also provides for penalties for giving false information, for the making of regulations by the Minister and for the power of the Revenue Commissioners to require information. These and other provisions of the Bill require no comment at this stage.</P>
    <P>I hope that Senators will agree that this Bill framed as it is in accordance with the most up-to-date thinking upon the matters with which it deals, will provide us with a satisfactory means of countering injurious dumping and subsidisation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to welcome the Bill first of all and then to say that that welcome might be shared in industry now in waiting for it for a long time.  It is one of the disturbing features of our preparation <Col N="984" /> for the freedom of trade that in so many cases, although the need for action was pinpointed at an early stage, action has been taken only after a long period.  While this may in part be explicable by the need for consultation, as, for example, in the case of the long delay with the introduction of facilities for training, in other cases consultations with industry and trade unions are not the explanation, and one must be concerned that it has taken so long for such legislation, including this legislation, to come before the House.</P>
      <P>As was pointed out by the NIEC in its 1966 industrial review, the need for anti-dumping legislation was pinpointed in 17 of 22 CIO reports summarised in Miss Brock's summary report or synthesis.  It was pointed out in that synthesis, summarising what had been said in these reports produced from the end of 1961 onwards, that the small size of Irish industry, and, therefore, of firms within it, makes it very vulnerable to dumping, and this matter of considerable vigilance and speedy action by the Government would seem the only way of mitigating the severity of the problem.</P>
      <P>The matter was referred to again in the first review on industrial progress of the NIEC in the spring of 1965 when it was said that in many industries they were anxious to have adequate protection against dumping and low-cost imports.</P>
      <P>In the final report of the CIO the matter was dealt with at some length.</P>
      <P>The real need for anti-dumping legislation was referred to and again pressure was put on the Government to do something about it in the spring of 1965.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the NIEC report on the Free Trade Area Agreement, which was published in February, 1966, the matter was again taken up because of the fresh urgency given to it by the introduction of this Free Trade Area Agreement.  It was pointed out that in virtually all discussions held with industry in regard to the Second Programme, the importance of effective protection against dumping <Col N="985" /> was emphasised.  This emphasis is understandable because the small size of the Irish market renders it particutarly vulnerable to dumping from highly industrialised countries.  These proposals were put forward shortly after the First Industrial Review, three to four years ago.  In the 1965 Review of Industrial Progress by the NIEC the matter was again mentioned.  This was published in the spring of 1966, two years ago.  In the 1966 Review of Industrial Progress, the refrain was taken up again.</P>
    <P>It is not a very satisfactory picture and no adequate explanation has been given as to why it took four years to introduce this legislation.  Fortunately, no serious damage has been done and where problems have arisen it has been possible to deal with them.  However, I do not think that is an excuse for this kind of dilatoriness.  When the urgency was pointed out, action should have been taken very quickly, much more quickly than in fact happened.</P>
    <P>The need for this legislation has been explained by the Minister.  That until now we have not needed anti-dumping legislation has been due to the fact that our tariffs have been at a high level, very much higher than was needed to protect adequately our industries. We have had a degree of protection so great as to protect our industries not only against the normal problems of unfair imports but against unfair competition as well.  Of course, the need in Ireland is likely to be greater because of the overspill of advertising in Britain&mdash;the fact that many British manufacturers, in press advertisements in British magazines and newspapers and on Independent Television, are inadvertently and without any cost to themselves, apart from what it takes them to advertise their goods on the British market, reaping the very rich benefit of having their advertisements seen here.  In that way they are getting a free bonus&mdash;it does not cost them a pound&mdash;and they are already making an effective impact on this country's market as a by-product of their advertising campaigns in Britain.  This puts them in a very favourable&mdash;I do not <Col N="986" /> use the word &ldquo;unfair&rdquo;&mdash;position <i>vis-á-vis</i> Irish manufacturers.</P>
    <P>Then there is the diminutive size of the Irish market beside the British one. We are peripheral to Europe and there is a tendency to dump goods in peripheral markets from which they are not liable to leak back again to the main market.  Again, this is an important consideration, the significance of which I do not think is appreciated in the European Economic Community. There is the fact that we are separated from all neighbouring markets by a sea channel and not a land frontier.  As I have said, the significance of this is not appreciated fully.</P>
    <P>I have visited the Community in Brussels on several occasions since 1961 and I have taken every possible opportunity to raise this question of dumping and its significance to Ireland because the Community's legislation, the Treaty of Rome and its provisions, are inadequate in this respect.  The countries in the Community are joined together in a land mass with contiguous frontiers and if a German firm dumped goods into France, from Baden Baden to Strasbourg, the dumping would not be altogether into a separate market because the dumped goods could be so easily dumped back that the German manufacturer could be undercut by his own goods being dumped back.  We do not have the same situation with a sea channel.  An English manufacturer selling goods in England, dishwashers for instance, at £100 could sell these at £80, after dumping, in Ireland, pay £10 transport to have them dumped here and nobody in Ireland could afford to send them back to undercut that manufacturer in his own market because with the £10 transport charge it would not be possible to do so economically. Therefore, the remedy of anti-dumping legislation is much less likely to be available in conditions of an area cut off by a sea channel than in countries separated only by a land frontier.  This distinction has not been appreciated and the fact is that EEC countries have, therefore, not seen the need for anti-dumping protection which we feel so acutely.</P>
    <P>I should like to press on the Minister the need to explore this matter further <Col N="987" /> with the EEC.  The Minister should tell us what progress has been made in talks on this matter.  There were talks of a preliminary character in 1962 and since then there have been exploratory discussions, not dignified with the name of negotiations, dealing with the kind of problems to be met.  I should like the Minister to tell us what reaction he has found in Brussels to the Irish situation on this subject because it is a matter which the Irish Government would naturally press with the Community.</P>
    <P>The reactions I have found have on the whole been understanding up to a point, without showing, however, any full appreciation of the problem.  There is a tendency for them to say: &ldquo;We do not have any problems in this respect, why should you?&rdquo; There is a tendency to adopt a doctrinaire attitude because a common market, it is said, cannot have trouble of that kind&mdash;this doctrinaire attitude which fails to recognise the fact that they are together within what is by law a common market but which is, in fact, a series of separate markets for the purpose of competition.  I am not happy that I have made the desired impact on the countries concerned and I ask the Minister to keep up the pressure.  I ask him also to tell us if he has detected any willingness in this respect.</P>
    <P>One answer would be to seek a solution, not within the framework of anti-dumping legislation because of the doctrinaire attitude I have described, but under the terms of Article 86 of the Treaty of Rome which deals with the dominant position.  For instance, if a German or French or English firm were dumping goods on the Irish market with the effect inadvertent or deliberate, of damaging Irish firms through unfair competition, this would represent an abuse of a dominant position, which is more or less the terminology of Article 86.  I wonder whether the Minister is speaking in terms of a solution within the framework of Article 86 and, if so, if it can be sufficiently speedy against the damage which may be done by dumping in putting firms here out of business.  If the answer is not Article 86, how then can the problem best be tackled?  It may be necessary to consider <Col N="988" /> a special protocol on this matter. Just as the accepting members of EEC not only subscribe to the Articles of the Treaty but add protocols to meet their special problems, I believe we would be entitled to seek a protocol where we have a special problem requiring special treatment.  Perhaps the answer may lie there.</P>
    <P>In any such negotiations, it would be important that we should show not only our genuine desire to protect ourselves against dumping but that we are not seeking to re-introduce protection in another form.  The solution in this Bill on the question of refunding duties seems to me to be along the lines on which we could perhaps talk to EEC because if, in any arrangement we had about dumping with the Community, it was established in any instance by the commission substantially, rather than by us&mdash;because the power would rest with the commission&mdash;that dumping had not occurred and a special emergency procedure we would seek had been applied in error, then we would be prepared to refund the losses. I would be prepared to agree to compensating any firm for any losses of profits they have incurred.  It would be no harm for us to show we are absolutely genuine on this and that this is not an attempt by the back door to re-introduce protection.</P>
    <P>Our only concern is genuine cases of dumping.  We do not wish to damage any firm that is not dumping.  We want quick emergency action to prevent serious damage to our industries and, if it is done in error, we should be prepared to bear the full consequences by ensuring that any firm would not be put at a disadvantage by our action. If we are prepared to go that far to show how genuine we are, suspicions might be alleviated and our chances of securing a special provision under either Article 86 or a special protocol would be enhanced.</P>
    <P>I press the Minister to tell us about discussions to date with the EEC and how he sees them evolving.  There is a genuine fear at this stage in this country. Many of the fears of Irish people are exaggerated about the EEC, and will be shown to be so when we become members, but they are not all <Col N="989" /> exaggerated.  People here remember cases of dumping in the past which had serious effects on Irish industry.  They fear that, if we join the Common Market and we have no effective provision against dumping, serious damage could be done to this country.  This is a very important issue, an issue to which this Bill offers no answer at all.</P>
    <P>I have been concerned that the Government, in one or two instances, have brought forward measures to deal with current industrial problems without making it clear that these are only temporary measures pending our entry to the EEC.  This Bill is one example. The other serious one is the arrangement with regard to the motor assembly industry with Great Britain.  It modifies the terms of the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Area Agreement in such a way as to protect our motor assembly industry from being wiped out by British competition under this Agreement.  The Government are to be commended on negotiating this Agreement and on preserving, for the time being, the motor assembly industry here by an ingenious solution to this problem.  In all the pronouncements and preliminary leaks that occurred, nothing was said to the effect that it was a purely temporary solution to the problem.</P>
    <P>There were headlines in the papers, which must have come from some inspired source, saying that the motor assembly industry would be saved for 25 years.  Unless that represented the Government's expectation of how long it would take us to get into the EEC, it was misleading and, if it was misleading, then the Government should come clean.  The statement was never contradicted. From the manner in which it appeared, the timing and the fact that it appeared in a number of papers simultaneously, quite evidently it came from an informed source.  In all that, nothing was said about the temporary character of these measures.  At no stage did the Minister warn, as he should have warned, that the motor assembly industry got a reprieve until we joined the EEC and that the Agreement he signed is quite obviously illegal under the terms of the Rome Treaty and would cease to be operative when we joined the EEC.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="990" /> It is wrong that the people should be lulled into a belief of security for a period of 25 years when, in fact, all that has happened is a temporary and useful reprieve.  I congratulate the Government on negotiating it but not on the way the information was leaked out, the timing and manner of the inspired comments associated with it, the failure to clarify the position and the fact that the workers in the industry have been misled by the Government as to their prospects.</P>
    <P>Similarly here, this Bill is extremely useful and urgent.  It will help to preserve Irish industry against unfair competition and dumping from Britain during the period of the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Area Agreement until we join the EEC, when this Bill becomes a dead letter.  It has no value or importance as far as the EEC is concerned. It can continue to be used against dumping but, if Britain and ourselves are in the EEC, then, so far as Western Europe is concerned, the Bill will be ineffective.  It is surprising that the Minister did not find it appropriate to make that point.</P>
    <P>We are supposed to be preparing for EEC membership.  All kinds of generalities are spoken about the need to prepare and not to be complacent. With the motor vehicle agreement, or this Bill, further encouragement to complacency is given by the failure to say that this or the other particular measure has no relevance to the EEC and will offer no answer to the problems arising under EEC conditions. As the Government have not seen fit to do so, it is appropriate, therefore, that the real position should be made clear from the Opposition benches and that this encouragement to complacency should not be allowed.</P>
    <P>Coming more closely to the Bill, a number of queries come to mind.  I should like to ask the Minister to tell us generally something about how this compares with the United Kingdom Act of 1957 in relation to dumping.  I have merely glanced at the British Act.  I note dissimilarities in the construction of the Act, in the order in which things are dealt with and in the manner of approach.  My first impression&mdash;which <Col N="991" /> I might not stand over if I had time to examine it closely&mdash; is that our Bill represents improvements on the British Act.  That statement would require more careful study before it could be validated.  Have we, as I suspect, approached this problem somewhat differently from the British and, if so, why?  Am I right in thinking that, by so doing, we may have produced a more satisfactory answer? I should like the Minister to say also how this Bill, in its present form, compares with the proposals put to him by the Federation of Irish Industries.  The Federation as long as four years ago, as we have been told by the NIEC, put forward proposals of a detailed character after having carefully considered legislation in other countries, including particularly Canada.  These proposals were worked out very fully and I would like to know to what extent they were found useful in the preparation of this Bill and to what extent the Bill conforms to these proposals.</P>
    <P>I would also like to ask the Minister to say a little about the speed with which the Government will be able to act under this Bill.  There is this system of provisional duties, but they can only be applied when something is under consideration by the commission and it must make a recommendation to the Government which must then take action of the kind which is envisaged. It is vital that where goods are dumped and come into this country and are in the docks immediate and urgent action should be taken to hold up what could lead to a disastrous position.  We must be clear that for certain products a slight error in the calculations of the British producers leading to an over production of three per cent in a particular year would yield a surplus which if dumped in Ireland would be equal to the whole production of the Irish industry for a year and could totally wipe out the Irish industry.  In many cases one boatload or even a part load will be enough to do the job.  There is no use shutting this stable door after the horse is gone.  This is one of the points made in the recommendations of the NIEC.  I am not so happy that the <Col N="992" /> procedure provided in this Bill which involves a complaint and the making of an inquiry, with four stages altogether.  I am not happy that this could give speedy enough action to ensure that if a cargo of goods were dumped in this way, before it could leave the docks and get through customs it could be dealt with by this procedure.  I should like the Minister to tell us something about that, because this is a very sensitive point as far as Irish industry is concerned, and the NIEC were right to stress its significance.</P>
    <P>As regards particular points, I shall run through them quickly as I go because I want to leave time for others to contribute to the debate and also to give the Minister time to reply.  In section 1 dealing with definitions the third word defined is &ldquo;country&rdquo; which is said to include &ldquo;territory, area and place&rdquo;.  This is an extraordinarily wide definition of a country.  One wonders what is intended by it.  I would see no particular difficulty about including &ldquo;territory&rdquo; because you can get some place like Hong Kong which is just a dependent territory of the British Commonwealth or Empire or whatever its appropriate name is now.  Although this dependent territory has its own form of subordinate government it is easily identified as a place of origin for goods and, therefore, it should be included in territory, but &ldquo;country&rdquo; is simply not a sovereign state, and &ldquo;area&rdquo; and &ldquo;place&rdquo; are not sovereign.  A place can be anywhere, any particular town or port.  I would have thought that you should have country or territory of some kind defined as having some kind of status and identity for purposes of international trade, not just somewhere within any country.  I wonder what is the purpose of &ldquo;area&rdquo; and &ldquo;place&rdquo; and why they have been introduced into the definition.</P>
    <P>Indeed, the Minister is defined in section 1 in a rather odd way, as being the Minister for Industry and Commerce except when he is the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries.  This procedure of bringing in the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries is further developed to a point of utter absurdity in section 4 subsections (2) and (3) <Col N="993" /> where it transpires that the commission shall consist of three people appointed by the Minister for Industry and Commerce and two by the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries, but that when a particular topic is being discussed this Box and Cox effort is indicated of them changing status so that one of the agricultural people becomes chairman, instead of appointing as chairman a nominee of the Minister for Industry and Commerce. If the civil servants want to play games of that kind between Departments it is their own affair, but they should do it in the privacy of their offices.  That they should do it in a public Bill is offensive. It introduces a most clumsy mechanism into the Bill and it shows up an attitude of mind which we must deplore.  This human feeling we know exists, but to put it in a Bill wastes everybody's time, with this complicated provision to ensure that when something is being discussed which happens to be for some reason under the auspices of the Minister for Agriculture the representative of the Department of Agriculture sits in the chair and the representative of the Department of Industry and Commerce sits under him.  This is nonsense.  The Minister quite frankly should have refused to submit to this practice from the Department of Agriculture, which was founded 25 years before this State was established; and there is a lot of evidence that it is still reluctant to recognise that there is a State superior to it.  It seems to think it is a separate and superior State.  This is a performance we should not allow them to get away with, and I am surprised that the Minister allowed this to be put down.  It seems to me to be an entirely improper procedure.  This commission should have a chairman, and after he is appointed by some defined procedure he should sit in the chair and run the meetings regardless of what the topic is for discussion, and not be pushed out by somebody from the Department of Agriculture just because the produce is flour instead of textiles.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not forget that the Minister for Agriculture likes being chairman of the National Agricultural Committee and things like that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="994" />
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>This goes back a long way, even before the present Minister for Agriculture.  It goes back to 1890 before the Minister for Agriculture was born.</P>
      <P>The next point I want to make is in relation to section 1, line 5 at the top of page 3.  The word &ldquo;produced&rdquo; here is defined as including &ldquo;grown and manufactured&rdquo; and the Bill says that &ldquo;cognate words shall be construed accordingly&rdquo;.  I am unhappy about the word &ldquo;produced&rdquo;.  Any international trade, and, indeed, any economic consideration of industrial production is not simply a single process.  Everything we buy that is manufactured has gone through many different processes in different places.  Value has been added in different countries at different times, getting materials, processing them, assembling them, putting them in final form, painting them perhaps, and all these processes can be carried out in different places at different times, so that you cannot say that an article is the produce of a particular country. Value is added, and this is recognised in the whole system of certificates of origin in free trade areas, where in order that it might be considered that a thing is substantially produced in a country a certain percentage of the value has to be added or a certain number of processes carried out in that country.  Therefore, to use the word &ldquo;produced&rdquo; as being equal to the word &ldquo;produce&rdquo; of any one country instead of being put through all these various processes is a bit misleading, and it is dangerous.  One would have to go right through the Bill to see whether the word is used so as to be dangerous.</P>
      <P>I may say that I am raising these points now, and going into some detail, instead of waiting for Committee Stage so that the Minister can reply, and thus enable us to see whether we should put down amendments on Committee Stage.  If the Minister is able to answer these points satisfactorily perhaps we will not need to put down amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to section 2, the last two lines of subsection (1), I know why they are there; they are there because somebody put them into the British <Col N="995" /> Act, or words almost identical, on page 76 of the relevant 1957 statute in England.  But that does not explain what they mean.  I have tried to think of any possible reason for these words being put in in our circumstances, but I cannot visualise any reason for including them and I have been unable to make sense out of them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I have the reference, please?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The last two lines of section 2 (1):</P>
      <P>except so far as any such costs, charges or expenses are required to be met separately by the buyer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I will explain that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I shall not labour it any further if the Minister has a good explanation.  I should like a little explanation of section 3 (3) as I could not quite understand the purpose of this.  I am sure it has some good purpose which the Minister can explain.</P>
      <P>Section 4 (1) has been amended in the Dáil.  I would like to take issue with the Minister on this amendment. The Minister is a much better scholar of the Irish language than I am and, therefore, I am slow to join issue with him on this subject but the form we had here seemed to me to be a reasonably respectable form that you could stand over and that did not make nonsense of the thing but now it has been changed to this incredible phrase &ldquo;An Coimisiún Dumpála&rdquo;.  I really must protest.  The reason given by the Minister for this terrible word is, in fact, a reason for not using it.  He said he discovered after having introduced this phrase here that in many countries the word &ldquo;dumping&rdquo; has an international usage and it is used, for instance, by Scandinavian countries, just taken from the English.  Therefore, I should think that the thing to do would be to call it &ldquo;An Coimisiún Dumping&rdquo; but it becomes &ldquo;An Coimisiún Dumpála&rdquo;. The logic of this appals me.  It is a &ldquo;dumpáling&rdquo; proposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>The structure of other <Col N="996" /> languages is, of course, somewhat different from Irish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>That is true no doubt but the fact remains that they did not take the word dumping and give it a Danish or a Scandinavian ending.  They took the word &ldquo;dumping&rdquo; from English and used it and the same procedure should operate here rather than to invent Irish words of this kind because the ending &ldquo;ála&rdquo; used in this country is one which is a subject of considerable jocosity and it does not do the Irish language any good because it sounds so odd it makes people poke fun at the language in a way that is inappropriate.  I do not think the Minister should lend himself to this procedure.  He should leave it &ldquo;An Coimisiún um Mí-allmhairiú&rdquo; or call it &ldquo;An Coimisiún Dumping&rdquo; or &mdash;and this seems to me in this instance to be the best way&mdash;call it &ldquo;The Dumping Commission&rdquo; because I am not convinced that in all these things the translation of titles to Irish is a good thing.  It is in some cases.  Some of them have been a great success.  An Foras Forbartha, although a little bit difficult to say, has caught on for the very good reason that it is so much shorter and easier than the National Building Construction and Physical Planning Institute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>And a lot more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not got it right but it is something like that.  Where you can use a brief Irish phrase it catches on and there are cases where it is appropriate to use the Irish title but I am not convinced that this is a case for using the Irish name. If it is to be used let us have it in the form it was originally or &ldquo;The Dumping Commission&rdquo; but let us dump this &ldquo;Dumpála&rdquo;.  If the Minister does not agree, I shall put down an amendment on this anyway.</P>
      <P>In section 4 (11) provision is made for remuneration for members of the commission.  I would only make the point that if members of the commission are civil servants I do not think there should be extra remuneration.  I do not say this with any animus against civil servants but as a general principle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="997" /> We have introduced this system here where when civil servants are appointed as directors of public bodies additional remuneration is payable.  I think this is a bad system.  I think it would be better if civil servants, if they are not adequately paid, should be paid adequately but a system where if outside bodies are set up and if they are appointed to them they get extra remuneration seems to me to be bad because it does, in fact, create an incentive to establish such bodies, to establish bodies with directorships to which civil servants are appointed.  I do not think there should be such an incentive and I do not think this should be done.  This is something which has concerned me a good while and, indeed, I am not alone in this.  There has been a good deal of concern expressed privately at any rate on this point.  It seems to me to run contrary to any reasonable principles of public administration.</P>
    <P>I should also like the Minister to say whether he visualises the members of this commission in fact as including civil servants or not.  I would think they should not be civil servants in this instance and this is, indeed, a general principle although there are exceptions to it and I have defended these exceptions even when these have come under heavy fire.  I think, on the whole, they should not be but I should like to hear the Minister's point of view and what his intentions are.  I think we have a right to know this before such a commission is set up.</P>
    <P>I come now to section 7 (1) (b).  I am not happy with the wording here because it says that whenever various things happen</P>
    <P>and the Commission is of opinion that the goods to which the request under paragraph (a) of this subsection relates have been or are being dumped. . . the Commission shall carry out an investigation of the matter. . .</P>
    <P>This seems to me to be unsatisfactory. The commission should not be in the position of, first of all, making up its mind about something and then investigating the thing about which it has made up its mind.  I do not think <Col N="998" /> this is appropriate.  If the Minister wishes here to make provision for a case where there is <i>prima facie</i> evidence of dumping, then he should say that where there is <i>prima facie</i> evidence of dumping the Commission shall. . . but I do not think the commission should be carrying out an investigation into something on which they have already expressed an opinion because if they had not there would not be an investigation. This seems to me to be inappropriate procedure.</P>
    <P>In section 7 (2) I would ask why only the Minister can raise this issue of subsidisation and why is it not open, as in the case of dumping, to an interested party to raise the question of subsidisation.  In this case of dumping either the Minister or an interested party producing evidence of the dumping can raise this question but in the case of subsidisation under subsection (2) only the Minister can do so.  I should like to know why.</P>
    <P>Section 7 (3) reads:</P>
    <P>The Commission shall have regard to any international agreements or conventions to which the State is a party.</P>
    <P>I should like to know why the comthese agreements.  I feel that in so far as they could limit the action of the commission and in so far as they may have limited the drafting of this Bill we ought to be told something about them.  The Minister has, in fact, referred in his opening remarks to Article 6 of the GATT.  In this connection I would suggest perhaps that he could table the relevant articles of GATT and any other agreements&mdash;OECD perhaps&mdash;to which we are parties.  I feel we should know what international obligations we have entered into at this point in time before we pass this legislation.  Perhaps, he could make this available to us in some appropriate manner.  Incidentally, the British Act does, in fact, mention GATT specifically in this connection, whereas we have not done so.  Is there any reason for not coming clean and putting it into the Act rather than leaving it open in this way?  If there are international agreements, I feel we should be told what they are and they <Col N="999" /> should be put into the Act as was done in the UK Act.</P>
    <P>Section 8 requires publication in <i>Iris Oifigiúil</i> and in such national daily newspaper or newspapers as is thought fit.  I trust the commission will not adopt the practice of the Minister for Agriculture in using this power to advertise for political purposes by withholding advertising from particular journals.  I shall not take that point any further tonight.</P>
    <P>Section 9 reads:</P>
    <P>If a member of the commission is personally interested in a particular matter with which the commission is dealing, he shall inform the Minister of State who appointed him to the commission accordingly and shall not act as a member during the consideration of the matter, unless that Minister, being of opinion that his interest is not such as to interfere with the impartial performance of his duties, authorises him to act.</P>
    <P>I think this is reasonable but this should be publicly stated.  There should be a requirement that in such a case the Minister should advertise the fact publicly that this interest has been declared and that he has, nevertheless, authorised the person to act.  It will not help public confidence in this body if it is thought that the Minister may behind the scenes be giving authority for people to act where they have an interest and this is not publicly known. I think the section is perfectly all right as long as there is the requirement to publish the fact.</P>
    <P>Section 10 (1) reads:</P>
    <P>The commission may for the purposes of its functions:</P>
    <P>(a) request witnesses &ldquo;other than the Revenue Commissioners and their officers&rdquo; to attend before it,</P>
    <P>I should like to know why the commission will not have the Revenue Commissioners appearing before it as witnesses, although, in fact, the Revenue Commissioners can be required to produce information for the commission.  I would have thought that <Col N="1000" /> if the Revenue Commissioners are required to produce information it would be not only desirable but essential that they should be available as witnesses in relation to such documents. That they should be accepted specifically and excluded as witnesses seems to be nonsensical in relation to subsection (3) of section 10 which requires them to furnish information. Section 13 deals with provisional duties.  As I have already asked the Minister to give an indication of how speedily this operates, I will not say anything further on it.  In section 14 (2) (a) it is stated:</P>
    <P>Whenever the commission makes a recommendation to the Minister under subsection (1) of this section in relation to goods of any kind and the Minister is satisfied that there has been injurious dumping of goods of that kind.</P>
    <P>Why put in those words about the Minister being satisfied.  It seems to me that if the commission make a recommendation to the Minister they should be satisfied to give the Government power.  I could understand if the clause implied that the Government &ldquo;must&rdquo; because then it might be necessary to put in a qualification that the Minister must be satisfied with the qualification. I cannot see why the Government should be prevented in this section when the commission make a recommendation from having that power unless it is backed up by something else. I should like to see this deleted altogether so that whenever the commission make a recommendation the Government may if they are satisfied impose a duty.</P>
    <P>The second leg of that particular double &ldquo;whenever the commission makes a recommendation to the Minister&rdquo; or &ldquo;whenever goods of any kind have been dumped the Government may if they so think fit by order impose a duty&rdquo; seems to undermine the whole procedure here in this Bill, which is designed to identify dumping by this commission procedure so that whatever action is taken is as a result of a decision of the commission or where the commission recommends a provisional duty to avoid dumping while it is carrying <Col N="1001" /> out its investigation, yet here we have a case where the Government can impose a duty and are by-passing the commission altogether.  This seems to me to be quite unsatisfactory.</P>
    <P>In subsection (3) of section 14 there is a phrase in line 54 &ldquo;whichever is the lesser&rdquo; and without going into detail, I should like that explained.  I should like to commend section 17 because I am aware of this particular problem in regard to glass containers. It is important that it should be dealt with and that it should be given particular treatment here.  I welcome this particular provision.</P>
    <P>In section 19, line 43, I should like some guidance on what is the purpose of the words &ldquo;something else&rdquo;.  It says &ldquo;references to a subsidy are references to a bounty given directly or indirectly by way of grant, loan or tax relief or in any other way and whether related directly to the goods themselves, to materials of the goods or to something else&rdquo;.  A subsidy or bounty relating to something else other than goods or materials seems quite impossible. &ldquo;Something else&rdquo; seems an extraordinarily vague phrase to put into this Bill.  I wonder if we could get something more precise than this.</P>
    <P>Section 20 refers to this question of ninety days.  This was something which came up in the Dáil.  I do not think this is adequate and the view of industry is that it is not.  Again, the Minister has said in a vague way that it is a GATT provision but it is one to which we have not adhered and one to which we should not adhere if it involves a limit of up to a period of ninety days for this.  I would urge the Minister to look at this.  I think an amendment on this was ruled out of order in the Dáil but that does not mean the Minister might not amend it. I think industry is happy with this Bill but one point about it with which it is not happy concerns this particular point.  I should like the Minister to have another look at it and to tell us why he felt obliged to accept this ninety days period when it arises under a provision of GATT, which we have not adhered to.</P>
    <P>Finally, in section 23 there are words <Col N="1002" /> which require explanation such as in line 36 &ldquo;from any country&rdquo;.  Subsection (1) states:</P>
    <P>The Revenue Commissioners may require a person who imports goods to state such facts concerning the goods and their history as they may think necessary to determine whether the goods are goods produced in a country specified under this Act or are goods exported from any country.</P>
    <P>Goods must be exported from some country if they are imported here.  If they are not, why worry about dumping? It seems to me that the draftsman has gone a bit wild here.  I am bothered about the second clause of subsection (1) of section 23 which states:</P>
    <P>Provided that the Revenue Commissioners shall require proof of the country in which goods were produced in relation to any duty under this Act in the case only of goods exported from such countries as the Minister may direct in relation to that duty.</P>
    <P>I cannot follow that or how that would work.  Perhaps the Minister could explain that to us because it does seem to me to be unworkable.</P>
    <P>Those are points of detail and I apologise to the Minister for keeping him and the House on this but this is the only way we can raise those points and decide whether we should put down amendments on Committee Stage.  I thought I had a further point arising out of the Minister's introductory speech but as I cannot trace it at the moment I will leave it at that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I note the Minister's concern about Irish producers, which I share, in relation to dumping on the market here but if I am a little bit more concerned about the workers employed in industry, I am sure he will understand it.  The Minister describes this legislation as being flexible and acceptable.  &ldquo;Acceptable&rdquo; is the word that worries me because I do not think legislation is acceptable whatever about it being flexible.  I think really what governs it all is what is acceptable and acceptable to whom?  Acceptable to <Col N="1003" /> GATT or other countries?  We seem to be operating this scheme under a very constrained position.  I am quite frankly worried as to whether this will be effective because from what little I know of customs procedure it seems to me that the customs people will have no function to hold up or examine critically imports coming in, whether they would be likely to be products which are dumped or not.  If they are all right under customs procedure they pass in and if they are being dumped I think a lot would depend on the flow of goods and possibly the nature of the goods themselves.  For example, if cars started to flow in as being dumped it probably would be spotted by the people affected, by the producers here and they would be howling about it before many cars were dumped.</P>
      <P>But, supposing something small like a few crates, half a cargo of, say, soup was dumped this would pass through the customs without comment if the customs papers were OK and until this appeared on the market the people who would be affected by the dumping would possibly not know anything about it until it had an effect on their sales.  At that time it seems to me that it would be too late to take any action.</P>
      <P>The Minister made a point that the Bill is providing for retroactive levy. He said that it may be imposed only on goods to which a provisional duty applies, but may be charged on any such goods which were imported during a period of 90 days before the date on which the provisional duty was imposed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Before the provisional duty is applied at all the commission have to make representations or advise the Minister.  The Minister then asks a provisional duty to be imposed and this may be retroactive to the extent of 90 days.  We could have a situation in which the stuff which has been dumped has been coming in over a period and nobody spotted it in the sense that it is dumped.  It is coming in and suddenly it appears on the market and the home manufacturer becomes alarmed and he makes representations to the commission.  The commission make representations to <Col N="1004" /> the Minister to impose a provisional duty and that provisional duty may be retroactive for 90 days but the most of the goods which are, in effect, doing injury to the home producer may have come in long before the 90 days and nothing can be done in that situation and the home manufacturer could quite well be ruined and his workers put out of employment as a result.</P>
    <P>I am reading what the Minister said and this seems to me to be a definite shortcoming in the Bill.  I am wondering are we, in fact, being caught here by the terms of the GATT agreement. In other words, are our hands being tied and cannot we take action which might be necessary in our peculiar circumstances, which might be necessary to protect our home manufacturer against dumping?  That is what makes me unhappy in regard to this Bill and I will be glad to hear the Minister's reply when I hope he will assure us that my fears in this respect are groundless.</P>
    <P>It seems that the 90 days are relatively short and I hope the Minister is not prevented by any international agreement from extending this period in so far as it might be necessary to protect our home industries.  The Minister also points out that the Bill provides against dumping with respect to third countries.  He says that if dumping attacks the markets of another country in this country, even though it does not injure a domestic industry, he has provision to act in those circumstances.</P>
    <P>What I am concerned about is dumping in another country which injures our producers and exporters here and understandably the Bill does not deal with that.  Can the Minister give us an assurance that parallel provisions in other countries would protect our exporters here?  For example, if an exporter has built up a remunerative market in Britain, as some industries have done and is giving good employment here and somebody from Japan dumps into the British market it does not injure the British producer but puts out of business a producer or a factory in this country.  There is nothing in this Bill to enable us to do <Col N="1005" /> anything about it which is understandable because we cannot deal with the position in the British market.</P>
    <P>I would like to have assurances, in so far as we are making provision in this Bill to help exporters in this country against the adverse effects of dumping into this market, that parallel provisions would be made in other countries.  That is a long sentence but I hope the Minister understands the points I am making.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to delay on this Bill.  I know the Minister wants to get in with another Bill at 9.45 and I am sure we are all anxious to hear what he has to say on the points made by Senator FitzGerald. The House must be grateful to Senator FitzGerald for the lucid manner in which he dealt with all the problems associated with dumping and, indeed, with regard to this Bill.  When reading the Bill &ldquo;dumping&rdquo; and &ldquo;anti-dumping&rdquo; occurred in every second sentence and, in fact, the words &ldquo;dumping&rdquo; and &ldquo;anti-dumping&rdquo; occurred 60 times.  I must say we were not much wiser until Senator FitzGerald gave a masterly explanation of the situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is obvious that this is a case of mutual admiration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>It is time somebody recognised merit when it makes its appearance in this House.  I think what I say about Senator FitzGerald is well merited.</P>
      <P>What perturbs me about this Bill&mdash; Senator FitzGerald said this also&mdash;is that it is only temporary in so far as we and Common Market countries are concerned.  I thought from what the Minister had to say and from all that is contained in the GATT agreement that this was the first shot in the locker for Common Market membership; that is, if Senator FitzGerald is correct.  I take it he is.  For that reason, I am somewhat disappointed to find what I thought was legislation with a real future turns out not to be so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The point that concerns me and also Senator Murphy is that the machinery for bringing this Bill into effective operation when we are threatened with <Col N="1006" /> dumping of a particular commodity seems to be altogether too lugubrious, the very fact that the Minister for Industry and Commerce will be able to impose a provisional duty and salve the consciences of the commission and everybody else.  The duty will last for only a limited period but all the damage will have been done by that time and I can see this slow-moving body providing excuses but not delivering the goods that Irish workers and Irish industry require them to deliver.  Indeed, it is deplorable in a Bill of this kind to realise that when we appoint five members of a commission only two of them will constitute a quorum.  It is deplorable to say that people who are paid good salaries out of public funds will be absent from private deliberations of the commission.  I could understand one having a cold or being away but to say that two out of five will be a quorum&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>There might be a by-election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Or a trade union congress.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>That may be so but it is wrong that the board should be limited to that number.  I entirely agree with Senator FitzGerald on the use of the term &ldquo;Coimisiún Dumpála&rdquo;. Immediately I saw it I thought it was daft.  The Bord Traenála was another by-product of the Department of Industry and Commerce, given birth to by the Department of Labour.  I do not think it helps the Irish language cause one whit to concoct words of that kind.  As has been said, it makes it a cockshot, makes people laugh at it and say: &ldquo;Sure, it is not a language at all, it is all a made-up business&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>They do not laugh at the phrase &ldquo;Aer Lingus&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>There are some successful instances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think I have a lot of time at my disposal but within it I hope to deal with most of the points raised.  I should make it clear, first of all, that the provision in this Bill for the imposition of retroactive levies is a very wide power to confer, <Col N="1007" /> one that could, indeed, put importers into this country out of business.  I also think its main effect will be as a form of insurance.  Senators Murphy and O'Quigley did not advert to this provision as a form of insurance.  If you put yourself in the position of a man importing dumped goods into this country, you will know there is a risk that by doing this you may find that for 90 days back there will be a levy imposed which could be at such a level as to put you out of business.  You will think twice before doing it knowingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is limited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Limited?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Limited by what is the fair price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>A levy is limited only to the margin at which dumping is authorised.  It means there is no dumping but that if a man imports goods at a dumped price, sells them, has got his price, and the levies imposed, he takes the rap.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>If he holds them for three months?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>If he does that he is taking the risk that the provisional levy will be applied straight away and in due course an anti-dumping levy.  The suggestion that he is bringing them in, disposing of them and that the damage is done before anything can be done about it must be considered in the light of the fact that he is running a risk and that he must calculate the risk before he takes it.  Another thing which is basic to our approach to the Bill is that we are conforming to international agreements in this matter and in particular to the Free Trade Area Agreement with Britain in which each country agreed to operate dumping legislation in accordance with the GATT regulations.  It may be thought that is a limitation on us.  That is true on the basis that no goods could be dumped in any circumstances but we must remember that similar legislation could be operated against us in other countries. We would have no protection in <Col N="1008" /> other countries and it must be remembered that our dependence on exports becomes increasingly important.  Therefore, unless there is international agreement on what can and cannot be done about dumping, small countries like this will be in serious difficulties. On balance, the existence of an international code is to our advantage rather than against us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>We are hardly potential dumpers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think I should like to comment on that.  I do not hope to be able to deal with all the points raised by Senator FitzGerald at this stage.  Many of them can be dealt with more appropriately on Committee Stage and if the Senator wishes to put down amendments he can do so.  On the point he raised about the delay in introducing this legislation, I wish to say it is not valid and I do not care how many reports of the FII and the NIEC he quotes.  First of all, it is clearly demonstrated that the machinery we now have of ordinary tariff protection and quotas is more effective than this could ever be, and on the basis of what has happened there is no evidence that there has been serious dumping up to now.  The reason is that we have had that legislation in operation and that our tariffs have been at a level that would not allow substantial damage&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I made that point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Therefore, it is not a case of the long delays and negligence implied by Senator FitzGerald.  Perhaps, that is not what he wished to convey.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator FitzGerald knows that this legislation was drafted and was about to be introduced after a good deal of consultation with the British as we were obliged to do under our Free Trade Area Agreement.  He also knows there was long and protracted negotiation within GATT in relation to the GATT code and that ultimately when the GATT code was circulated in June of last year it provided for <Col N="1009" /> retroactive legislation which was vital to what we wanted and it was well worth our while recasting our legislation on that basis.  It is something we and our manufacturers wanted and to misrepresent our position, to suggest that the Government were sitting on this problem for years until urged on by the NIEC and FII does not present an accurate picture of what really happened.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I was unaware of that.  This offers some explanation of the delay.  I was not misrepresenting the position.  I was quite unaware that that was the reason for the delay.  I accept it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I mentioned it before.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister emphasised the other point repeatedly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I have made my point. I shall not dwell on it.  I think Senator FitzGerald said the motor vehicle arrangement is temporary and will have no effect once we go into the EEC.  Again, this is not an accurate picture of the position, in my opinion. When we go into the EEC, the position depends on what we negotiate with the EEC.  Therefore, it would not be possible to say that this will not operate nor would it be possible to say it would operate fully in the EEC.  From our point of view at the moment, all we can do is to legislate for the position as it is now&mdash;not for a position which is dependent on negotiations which have not yet taken place.  I can say that we have discussed this matter with the EEC.  I myself have discussed it with Monsieur Rey some time ago and I have indicated to him our special problems in this regard&mdash;particularly the danger of sporadic dumping in a small market like ours and the danger arising from the sea frontier, as Senator FitzGerald pointed out.  I made it clear that we would expect, in negotiations with the EEC, to have special provisions which would cover this very real danger for us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I feel, from the reaction I got, that these problems are understood in Brussels.  Certainly, it was indicated to <Col N="1010" /> me that there was no objection in principle to the idea of special provisions to deal with the special difficulties we have, although Senator FitzGerald was quite correct in saying that the general attitude in the commission, certainly, is one of the doctrinaire theory that there cannot be dumping within the Common Market.  I think even the people who say this admit it is doctrinaire and is not very realistic.</P>
    <P>As to how this compares with the British Act, it compares to some extent rather closely while in other respects it differs.  In the main, I think it differs to our benefit.  One example of this is that there is no commission under the British Act.  It is administered by a Government Department&mdash;the Board of Trade.  This, of course, reduces the credibility of the whole dumping procedure internationally.  In addition, I think our legislation is more effective in regard to the provisional duties, to the levy and to the commission&mdash;as I mentioned, there is a Government Department there&mdash;in the power of the commission to refund excessive payment and in the provisions for confidentiality. Under the British Act, I understand action can be taken only after examination of the complaint.</P>
    <P>Representation on the commission and, in particular, the question of the chairmanship changing in the event of agricultural grants being dealt with, are not there simply to assuage the vanities of civil servants or anybody else.  If the commission is dealing with agricultural produce, it is very important that the people dealing with it should have as good a knowledge as possible of the produce concerned and of the markets for it in circumstances in which it may be necessary to determine very quickly whether provisional duties should be imposed.  That the people dealing with this are people who know what the whole problem is about and who have to refer back as little as possible to find out about the position is a matter of importance to us if the legislation is to be effective.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister proposes to change only the chairmanship when these are discussed and not the personnel.  How is that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1011" />
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Senator knows, it could happen that the approach of industrialists may be different from that of agriculturists especially if there is a question of a raw material for industry involved.  The people who are concerned with the particular product about which the complaint is made&mdash; where it is agricultural&mdash;should be the people who would have the dominant position in that kind of investigation.</P>
      <P>With regard to the provision for 90 days application of the levy, it is true that there was a suggestion that this should be made 180 days.  As I mentioned in Dáil Éireann, this would not be in accordance with the GATT code to which I have referred which provides only for 90 days.  Under our Free Trade Area Agreement with Great Britain, we must give Britain GATT treatment so that, even if we were to ignore the GATT code and make this 180 days instead of 90 days, we should have to make an exception in the case of Britain but I think we would be very severely attacked in GATT if we were to do this and eventually it might bring retaliation against us in GATT.</P>
      <P>I think the question of having this Bill will improve our position in the event of negotiations with the Common Market for membership and, indeed, in this regard, we shall be in a stronger position than the British because, as I have said, our Bill is more effective than theirs.  It is not the position that this legislation will just come to an end when we join the Common Market but, rather, the position obtaining when we conduct our negotiations will be important from the point of view that, negotiating from the position which we shall occupy, this Bill will put us, I think, in a stronger position than the British.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the use of the word &ldquo;dumping&rdquo;, I am sure the House is aware that the Government, for a long time have been operating a policy that, where possible, in the event of setting up any State Boards, the title should be in Irish and should be one that can easily be used and remembered. I think there is some misunderstanding about the word &ldquo;dumping&rdquo;. The word &ldquo;dumping&rdquo; is used in French and in German.  I said a <Col N="1012" /> similar word was used in Scandinavia. In one case it is &ldquo;dompe&rdquo; and in another case another word is used which sounds the same.  People get the sound &ldquo;dump&rdquo;, which we have in Irish&mdash;&ldquo;dompála&rdquo;.  It is merely to conform with the structure of the language it is in.  I do not know why anybody should say it is a made-up word and that this is bringing the Irish language into disrepute.  In similar circumstances, they do not say that about the French and German languages.</P>
    <P>I agree with Senator FitzGerald in his discussion of the principle of civil servants being paid extra for serving on State boards or otherwise: I quite agree with the principle involved.  The practice that has grown up in the past is, I think, unfortunate.  I have not considered the question of the membership of this commission, as yet.  It seems to me <i>prima facie</i> that civil servants would not be the right people to be members of this because we want to make it clear that this commission will act independent of the Government and of the Minister.  It might be more difficult to do this if we had civil servants. I am saying this off the cuff.  I have not given any consideration to it, but this is the way it strikes me at the moment.</P>
    <P>I think I am running over the time that was set earlier.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>You are only holding yourself up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not mind if it is the wish of the House.  There was a point raised on subsection (2), subsection (1).  Senator Garret FitzGerald said that he did not know why the additional words &ldquo;any such costs, charges or expenses are required to be met separately by the buyer&rdquo; are in.  The reason for these words is that it is quite likely that the price in the contract of sale will be such that certain deductions from or additions to the price will be necessary to arrive at the export price.  For example if the invoice shows the price for goods delivered at an Irish port, demands will have to be met for any charges at the port unless it is clear from the contract that this would be met separately by the buyer.  To arrive at a comparable figure between <Col N="1013" /> the prices on the home and the export market one must compare like with like at the same point of sale.  If there are port charges and so on one must ensure in making a comparison that if the buyer has to pay the charges an adjustment has to be made, and if the seller has to pay these charges a corresponding adjustment has to be made, in order to compare like with like. That is the only reason why these words are in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to be the opposite to the wording that would be needed for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>We can deal with that on Committee Stage.  The question was asked as to whether we had adopted the FII proposals.  It was not possible to adopt those proposals in particular in relation to the control by customs officers.  It is true that this system is used in Canada but it is subject to very severe criticism in GATT and has been attacked all the time and if we had contemplated it we might have found it difficult to accede to the GATT.  The FII has been consulted at various stages in the preparation of this legislation and has not indicated dissatisfaction with the present Bill.</P>
      <P>I think that many of the points raised are more appropriate to the Committee Stage, and I do not think I can attempt to deal with any more of them.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, March 20th, 1968.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Smelting Bill, 1966:" RHead="Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Smelting Bill, 1966: Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 3 before line 1 to insert the following:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(1) Every licence made under this Act shall specify&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  the metal or metals and</P>
      <P>(b)  the pyrometallurgical or chemical or leaching or electrolytic or other process in respect of which the licence is granted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(2) In the case of any licence <Col N="1014" /> granted under this Act and not subsequently revoked, no second licence shall be granted in respect of the same or similar process of smelting the same metal or metals as specified in the said licence within a stated period of years from the commencement of smelting operations, such stated period to be specified in the said licence and not to exceed ten years.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>This amendment is concerned with the guarantee which the Minister thinks it is appropriate to make to the particular firm which has undertaken a feasibility study in regard to a smelter in this country.  During Committee Stage the Minister indicated that there was an agreement in principle in regard to this particular matter and that he agreed with the case I had made that this matter should, if possible, be the subject of a public enactment rather than a private agreement.  The issue between us on Committee Stage was whether it was possible to enact a statutory guarantee of this type and still leave enough flexibility in the matter so that the Minister's hands would not be unduly tied.  Accordingly, I have substituted for the amendment withdrawn on Committee Stage amendment No. 1 which I now propose.  Subsection (1) of this amendment is the same as subsection (1) of the earlier amendment but subsection (2) has been modified in several respects.</P>
    <P>It is difficult to draft in haste an amendment of this sort.  In the original drafting of the amendment for Committee Stage, apart from certain circumstances which I mentioned on Committee Stage, I suffered under the disability that the report of the Second Stage debate was not in my hands at the time of drafting the original amendment, so that I had to depend on my recollection of what the Minister had said in regard to this guarantee.  In drafting this particular amendment for Report Stage during the interval this evening I again suffered under the disability that I did not have before me the account of the Committee Stage debate.  This is a severe handicap, and I am not sure that the amendment now put forward suffices in this regard.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1015" /> While we are quite willing to accommodate the Minister in this, I think that it is a distinct pity that this situation should have arisen both on Report and Committee Stages in regard to a Bill which bears the announcement that it was ordered to be printed in December, 1966.  This Bill, which was introduced in Dáil Éireann 15 months ago, took 15 months to go through Dáil Éireann, and the Seanad now finds itself hampered in endeavouring to reach a formula of words on a principle on which the Minister says there is general agreement because this Bill, having taken 15 months to go through Dáil Éireann, has apparently to pass through Seanad Éireann within eight days.</P>
    <P>Nevertheless, accepting these disabilities, I do submit that this amendment in subsection (2) of amendment No. 1 is an improvement on the form of amendment which was put forward on Committee Stage and I would ask the Minister if he could not agree that it does meet many of the difficulties which he raised.</P>
    <P>I am, of course, depending on my memory in regard to those difficulties. Of the difficulties which he mentioned one was that it might well be that the firm now undertaking a feasibility study would, even if the study were favourable, not wish to go forward, and in these circumstances he might think it desirable to ask another group to undertake something in regard to the operation of a smelter and that he would wish to give a guarantee to this second group.  Such a second guarantee is perfectly feasible under this amendment because I have now omitted from the proposal the phrase &ldquo;within two years&rdquo;, so that even after two years had elapsed even if the feasibility study went on for more than this time the Minister would be able to give this guarantee because if the original firm undertaking the feasibility study either already hold a licence or if they have been given a licence before the feasibility study is completed and then decide not to go ahead, surely it is reasonable that going ahead with the operation would have been a condition of this <Col N="1016" /> licence and, therefore, the Minister would have been in a position to revoke the licence when they indicated that they were not going ahead.  Accordingly, we then have the case that there is no pre-existing licence granted under the Act and not revoked and so the Minister would be perfectly able to grant a licence to a second group of individuals whether they form one firm or a consortium and he would then be able to grant them a licence which would be the one standing unrevoked licence and could carry the same guarantee. I think the present wording removes any difficulty in regard to the possible granting of a second licence. If, of course, no licence has been granted before the feasibility study ends, then no difficulty arises.</P>
    <P>A second point on which the proposal is being amended is that in the original amendment on Committee Stage it is indicated that the period of years should run from the granting of the licence and this has now been altered in accordance with what the Minister indicated was the nature of the guarantee he was prepared to give, that is that it should run from the commencement of smelting operations so that in this second respect the proposal has been substantially altered in order to fit in with what the Minister has said is the type of guarantee which he wishes to give.</P>
    <P>The third matter in which the amendment has been altered is in regard to the period of years for which the guarantee of no second licence for the same process could hold.  I certainly had the impression from reading the early Stages of the debate in another place that the guarantee was a perpetual one.  However, it emerged at the end of the proceedings there and was quite specific in the Minister's Second Stage speech here that the period for which the guarantee would stand would be a period of ten years and this was the reason why the period of ten years was in the amendment put forward on Committee Stage.  During the Committee Stage debate the Minister indicated that that is undesirable because he would then be held to ten years and this might, indeed, be an undesirable thing.  This has been modified in the <Col N="1017" /> present amendment so that all that is required is a stated period not to exceed ten years.  All that is required here is that at the time of the granting of the licence the Minister has to state a period.  It might well be argued that this would also leave the Minister in difficulties; that he might feel that he had to grant a licence now even before the feasibility study was finished and that, therefore, he could not say now what the appropriate period of guarantee should be but actually under the terms of this Bill there is no need to grant a licence until the day before smelting commences and I think the Minister has quite some freedom in regard to that.</P>
    <P>Therefore, in regard to the omission of the limitation of the guarantee to licences issued within the first two years, this has been modified so that the guarantee can apply to a licence issued at any time provided there is no pre-existing licence in regard to the smelting of the same ores by the same process.  The second point is that a change has been made to allow the period of years to run from the commencement of smelting operations and, in addition, this period has been made more flexible in regard to ten years or less.</P>
    <P>It is a matter for regret I think that the Report Stage amendment should of necessity have to be drafted in haste and that since the period in which this amendment was drafted&mdash;the interval of today's sitting&mdash;the Minister has hardly had time to indulge in the calm reflection which one likes to expect from a Minister between Committee Stage and the Report Stage of a Bill. Nevertheless, I hope that the Minister will recognise that we have here something which should be an instrument of sufficient flexibility for his purpose and that he will find it satisfactory so that he could do what he said during Committee Stage he wished to do, namely, to act by way of public enactment rather than by way of private agreement.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I freely acknowledge that this amendment goes a considerable distance towards meeting some of the objections which I raised to the previous amendment which was <Col N="1018" /> withdrawn.  A number of points that I raised are adequately dealt with in this amendment but I must point out that the objections which I made to the previous amendment were made to that amendment.  It does not mean that they were the only possible objections and, in fact, I did say that I was very anxious to ensure that I, or whoever might be Minister for Industry and Commerce at the time that this situation would arise, should have freedom to manoeuvre and freedom to negotiate having regard all the time to the fact that whatever kind of arrangement is made and whatever kind of conditions are set out in the licence can, and no doubt will, be made public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As Senator Dooge has said, I have not had a great deal of time to consider the implications of this amendment but it does seem to me without straining the imagination too far that I can conceive of circumstances in which this amendment, as drafted, would create a difficult situation.  If, for instance, as I think is quite likely, a licence were to be granted while the feasibility study is proceeding&mdash;I say I think this is quite likely because as I mentioned earlier part of the feasibility study is not merely the technical aspect but the financial aspect and the availability or non-availability of a licence could be of crucial importance in studying the financial feasibility of the project&mdash;therefore, assuming that a licence is granted during the duration of the feasibility study it is conceivable that the company which had got the licence, which was carrying out the feasibility study and which had decided that it was a worthwhile operation might, for some reason, wish to ensure that the other company&mdash; which, no doubt, it would be another company would be operating the smelter might have a licence contemporaneously with the licence which had been granted to the company carrying out the feasibility study.  I do not say that this is something that must happen but I do say it is something which could conceivably happen.  I could conceive of certain circumstances in which this might be reasonably requested and I mention this merely as one example.  I have no doubt that <Col N="1019" /> if I gave a good deal of thought to this, other possibilities would strike me all of which would come under the heading which I made today and that was that I feel that the Minister should be in a position to negotiate what seems to be the best possible deal and that he should not have his hands tied by a too rigid definition of what should be contained in the licence in the Bill.</P>
    <P>Having regard all the time to what I have said earlier, whatever arrangement is made, whatever licence is granted, can, as I said, undoubtedly be made public by way of question to the Minister and otherwise, for those reasons, although I say I acknowledge that this amendment goes a considerable way towards meeting some of the difficulties I have mentioned, it does not in my opinion, and there could not, as I indicated, be any amendment which would meet the difficulties involved in tying the hands of the Minister in negotiating.  As I said, I do not think the House need worry unduly about that giving too much freedom to the Minister, not merely to me but to any Minister for Industry and Commerce because whatever is done can be elicited and made public.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has said if he had further time to think about this he could have raised further difficulties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think I quite put it like that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel there is possibly no limit to Ministers putting forward reasons as to why they could not accept amendments.  The reasons the Minister has given tonight are not, I feel, compelling ones.  I sympathise with the Minister's feeling that he should have freedom to negotiate but I think the Minister would be in a better position to use that argument if he had not rejected an amendment put forward on Committee Stage, that following the end of the negotiations the fruit of the negotiations under the main headings of the final negotiating settlement would be laid before this House of the Oireachtas.  If the Minister had been prepared to accept that he, having <Col N="1020" /> negotiated, would report to this House of Oireachtas the outcome of those negotiations he would be in a stronger position to argue that he should be left completely free in regard to the negotiations themselves.</P>
      <P>The Minister said the position is that the information will be public, that it will be accessible by way of Parliamentary Questions but Parliamentary Questions are not asked in this House of the Oireachtas.  We in this House of the Oireachtas would not like to feel that we are being asked to allow this monopolistic situation to develop and that this House will not be officially informed of it.</P>
      <P>The Minister instanced one particular case which he thinks would be difficult to cope with under the terms of this Act.  He has suggested that the firm carrying out the feasibility study would be a mining company, that such a firm would like to have a licence in order to be able to raise the money and that at the same time the smelting company which would be formed as a subsidiary and as an associated company might like to have a licence.  I do not think this is very likely.  If the smelting company had been floated as a subsidiary or otherwise, the obvious course here would be for the mining company, which has organised the feasibility study, to ask the Minister to transfer the licence in this particular case.</P>
      <P>The Minister has got great freedom in this Bill even if this amendment were included.  I must say I am disappointed he is not able to meet this particular amendment.  I feel if the whole passage of this Bill had not been so rushed we might by more leisurely debate on Committee Stage, followed by Report Stage, for which there would be adequate time for preparation, have reached agreement.  There is little point therefore, except to withdraw the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 3, before line 1 to insert the following:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;Notwithstanding anything contained <Col N="1021" /> in this Act, the Minister shall grant to a mining company or to any company in which the mining company holds more than 50 per cent of the issued share capital a licence to smelt any quantity of ore or ore concentrates produced in Ireland by the said mining company.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>This amendment is concerned with the right of a mining company to smelt its own ore.  Once again, I feel that this amendment goes a good deal towards meeting the objections raised on Committee Stage.  It is important that we should endeavour to reach agreement on this.  In the case of the last amendment, as I said, I could sympathise with the Minister's desire that his hands should not be tied but in this amendment we are dealing, not with something in regard to the freedom of the Minister to negotiate, but with the rights of corporations who have made heavy capital investments in this country.</P>
    <P>We should be exceedingly careful in this regard and we should in this instance give those mining companies a statutory guarantee of the right to smelt their own ores.  It may well be that there is a flaw in this Bill, which we have not seen, which the Minister and his advisers have not seen and as a result of this flaw the Minister might find, having given a licence to a particular firm, that in law certain other mining companies might be circumscribed in regard to the smelting of their own ore.  It is only reasonable, to put this beyond any doubt, that the right of a mining company to smelt their own ore should be given statutory effect.  It is for that reason that I have tabled this second amendment on Report Stage.</P>
    <P>During the course of the Committee Stage the Minister indicated that there were some objections to the form of the amendment brought forward on Committee Stage.  Once again, I must say I am under the disability of having to try to meet those objections in a rather hasty redrafting.  Nevertheless, I feel that this amendment in its present form should be more acceptable. The Minister commented on Committee Stage that the original <Col N="1022" /> phrase in relation to a mining company or an associated company was unduly loose.  That has been changed in the present amendment to a &ldquo;mining company or to any company in which the mining company holds more than 50 per cent of the issued share capital&rdquo;.  The condition here is that we are dealing with a mining company or its smelting subsidiary.  It could be a smelting or marketing subsidiary. The Minister also made a perfectly valid point on Committee Stage that the amendment put forward then would give the right to a company to associate with a company or even, indeed, through a subsidiary company, to smelt ore imported into the country.</P>
    <P>I imagine the Minister might have other powers by which he could prohibit the importation of ore but, nevertheless, I consider this a valid objection.  Accordingly, this amendment refers only to ore or ore concentrates produced in Ireland.  In regard to those two points I have endeavoured to meet the Minister's objection. In redrafting the amendment, I discovered that there was one point in relation to which I thought it would have to be stiffer.  The amendment on Committee Stage read &ldquo;that the Minster may grant a licence to a company to smelt its own ore&rdquo;.  That has now been changed to &ldquo;the Minister shall&rdquo;.  I want to say a few words in justification of that.  I thought no company should have the right to compel a Minister to give them a licence to smelt their own ore but when I read through the Bill again and realised that the Minister in his absolute discretion can attach any condition he likes to the granting of a licence, I came to the conclusion that, indeed, a company which has invested a large amount of capital in this country, which has produced ore or ore concentrates should have the right to have a licence to smelt its own ore.  But this does not say that this is an absolute right.  It will be a circumscribed right, circumscribed by the conditions the Minister can put into this particular licence when he grants it.  He can protect a public interest.  He can protect a mining interest in any way <Col N="1023" /> he likes.  I feel that while the Minister is going a long way towards meeting a particular mining group with a feasibility study for a smelter, he should go this distance to meet the other mining interests and say to them, even if one particular company introduces a smelter here: &ldquo;I will give you a statutory guarantee that you will get a licence to smelt your own ore, no guarantee as to the condition but you will have a guarantee to smelt your own ores.&rdquo;  That they have a right to expect.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret that, again, I find myself unable to accept this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is impossible to please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>It may be that some Senators are rather difficult to please too.  I find it impossible to accept this because I believe the drafting of this amendment inadvertently does the same thing as the one which we dealt with on Committee Stage.  It, in fact, provides an opportunity for the company operating here in Ireland to erect a smelter which can be used to smelt not only ore produced in Ireland but also ore produced abroad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>And concentrates in Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Exactly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>So the Minister will accept it if we delete &ldquo;concentrates&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not what I said. This, as drafted, strikes at the root of the whole basis of the undertaking which I gave.  I am accepting the fact that Senator Dooge finds that this has occurred inadvertently, that he did not intend this and that he did not intend it in the other amendments put forward today which have the same defect but I cannot contemplate any amendment which would have the effect of destroying the whole basis of the undertaking given as the basis on which this Bill was introduced</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1024" /> However, the point of this amendment, as I understand it, was not the one I have been making, that is, the suggestion that every mine-owner in this country should know that he has a statutory right to erect a smelter to smelt his own ore.  I wonder if this is not a little exaggerated.  It may be desirable but I wonder is it anything more than desirable.  After all, this Bill provides for the issue of a licence so that people can only operate a smelter with a licence, but that does not say that people will not be given licences, or that, in fact, what I have told the House in relation to this undertaking will be operated assuming the feasibility study is right and so on.  What I am anxious to do is have the machinery to implement an undertaking which I have given and, at the same time, cover a situation in which that undertaking, perhaps, is not operating for the reasons I mentioned earlier, and to have a legal framework in which we can deal with smelting in either of those circumstances.  I have made very clear&mdash;and it is on the records of both Houses of the Oireachtas&mdash;what the terms of that undertaking are.  I have made it very clear that the undertaking does not preclude a mine-owner here from having the right to smelt his own ore as produced in Ireland.</P>
    <P>It may be argued that this is not in the statute and, therefore, that it is not binding.  For this reason I say it could be argued that it would be desirable that the statutory right could be inserted but at the very best that is the most that could be said.</P>
    <P>Long years of experience have shown that in circumstances where the Minister concerned has, if you like, read into the official records of the Oireachtas the terms of an undertaking such as this they, in fact, operate as though they were in the statute without the limitations involved but being rigidly controlled, for instance, the 10 year period I referred to today. In other words, what I am saying, in effect, is that the point of this amendment as I understand it, the ensuring of the right of mine-owners to erect a smelter to smelt their own ore produced in Ireland, is being guaranteed, being secured without the benefit of <Col N="1025" /> the amendment, which, in any event, I could not accept because, as I said, it strikes at the root of the whole arrangement on which this smelting proposition is based.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>I find it hard to appreciate how this strikes at the basis of the whole situation.  The Minister has indicated that he intends to give a guarantee to one particular company and that he intends, at the same time, to give a licence to any mining company to smelt their own ore or ore concentrates.  He indicates that this is statutory because he has read it into the records of the Houses of the Oireachtas.  I cannot see that this whole situation would be in danger of being brought to the ground because of the statutory effect of its being written into the records of the Houses of the Oireachtas.  The position is that the mine-owner who for any reason has a defective licence or who in any way can be held to have smelted an ore by way of trade commits an offence which makes him liable to a fine of £5,000 and a continuing £500 a day.  The circumstances could well be such that a mine-owner would wish to try out a new method of smelting to see if this were suitable for his particular mine.  There might well be a mine-owner who wished to try this new pyrometallurgical process.  Such a person might inadvertently be held to be smelting because this is included in the definition of smelting here.  He could well find himself in contravention of the law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister said that he could, indeed, allow to be done what he thinks is most undesirable, that ores could be imported and concentrated in this country under this particular amendment and, therefore, defeat the whole purpose.  This is quite ridiculous because it is quite obvious that any Minister granting a licence to a mining company to smelt their own ores or ore concentrates would insert as a condition on this particular licence that these ores or ore concentrates have been mined in this country.  It is quite clear that this would be a condition.  The Minister has power to restrict the operation of a licence by conditions, <Col N="1026" /> and, indeed, he could ensure in this way that there would be no danger of the type he has envisaged.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>He would not have the power if we accepted the amendment. It would override any conditions in a licence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>You can fix your conditions in the licence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be met by removing the words &ldquo;ore concentrates&rdquo;. If the Minister now says he is prepared to accept the amendment without &ldquo;ore concentrates&rdquo;&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not what the Minister said.  What I said was that the case being made by the Senator is not correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be possible to operate it.  The difference that lies between us is that I feel in this instance, when a monopolistic situation is being operated in relation to one group, the least that might be done is to give statutory protection to other groups in relation to the smelting of the ore mined in their mines.  We are largely agreed in principle and we differ in detail.  When the Minister and Opposition Senators differ in that way there is no doubt what the result will be.  I, therefore, wish to withdraw the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I can only regret the bad turn which the debate on this Bill took today.  It is quite clear that if adequate time had been given to the House to debate the Bill, introduced 15 months ago in the Dáil, the Bill would leave the House in better shape and with better protection for persons engaged in ore-mining in this country. I am quite satisfied that a misunderstanding or a misinterpretation, a misunderstanding developed between the Leader of the House and me, as a result of which the House has been <Col N="1027" /> deprived of the opportunity of having the usual period in which to discuss the Minister's point of view and for the Minister to consider the points of view of Senators for the purpose of amending the Bill on Report Stage. It is a deplorable condition that in this House, which has so few meetings during the year, when we do meet we are forced to pass a Bill in a form which is not as good as it could be if we were given adequate time.</P>
      <P>I realise that the time now is late&mdash; I know I am confined to the contents of the Bill.  The Minister has said he has read certain undertakings and guarantees into the records of the House and that these bind him and future Ministers.  I should like him to read a guarantee in this instance into section 5 of the Bill.  It is wrong in principle to say that the Minister for Industry and Commerce will have an absolute right&mdash;I have no doubt that is the interpretation it bears&mdash;to revoke its smelting licence and that this revocation may result in an industry set up at a cost of millions of pounds closing down.  That is bad law and bad public policy.  The Minister was not prepared to wait for amendments to make some provision for an independent inquiry, by mine experts, engineers or the courts, outside the Minister, if it is seen there has been a breach of this section and of the conditions attached to the licence.  The only thing one can do at this stage is to ask the Minister, if that situation ever arises, to agree to have the matter referred&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not say to the courts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;to some form of independent inquiry analogous to that operated under the Town Planning Acts or to arbitration.  What the Minister and that side of the House are doing is saying that if the industry is closed down by withdrawal of licence the man can go to the court.  That will be too late and the resort to the courts at that stage will be quite useless to protect that man.  It is the Minister and those who voted for this section who are driving the person into court by preventing the provision of some form of <Col N="1028" /> inquiry.  What we have been trying to do is to provide for an independent inquiry before the withdrawal of the licence.  The Minister can do that and he should do it in fairness to people who may get licences.  It is a pity the House did not accept an amendment to that effect but the Minister may indicate that is the line he will adopt in the event of that situation ever arising. That would do something to repair the damage and to uphold the reputation of the treatment this House gives to matters of this kind which so infrequently come before us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>How could one take Senator O'Quigley seriously?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not wish to delay the House unduly but there are two things on which I wish to comment.  The first is the delay which occurred between the time the Bill was ordered by Dáil Éireann to be printed and the time it came before this House.  That delay was not entirely due to the Minister and his Department.  I am not saying some of the delay was not but it was not entirely due to the Minister and the Department and Senator Dooge may know something of what I am referring to.  The other matter is the point made by Senator O'Quigley in regard to section 5 which was discussed at length.  I shall not say anything more on it except to reiterate my belief that I do not think Senator O'Quigley seriously meant the argument he put forward.  I do not think he could possibly mean that this section is to be read as though, in the Minister's opinion&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>It is even worse.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeColley" hpid="Mr. Colley Mr. Colley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colley</NameTxt>
      <P>Anyone who can conceive of a business in which there are millions of pounds invested likely consenting to a Minister taking away his licence without doing anything about it is not living on the ground.  Such a man can go to the courts, get an interim injunction and if the Minister has not complied with the section there is nothing the Minister can do.  We have been over all this today and I doubt if Senator O'Quigley really means the arguments he has put forward.  We <Col N="1029" /> shall, of course, act in accordance with the kind of practice and procedure which have grown up during the years but I do not undertake to set up any tribunal to operate something like this. I believe the procedure to be adopted would be as fair as we could make it. Furthermore, and most important, the <Col N="1030" /> person concerned has a right of appeal to the courts which he will certainly use if his rights are being taken away.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 10.40 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 20th March, 1968.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>