<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Tue" Date="16" Month="Jun" Year="1998" Vol="155" No="24" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 16 Meitheamh 1998" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 16 June 1998" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1441" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Quinn that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Environment and Local Government to consider the co-funding of public works projects on a basis that would allow the tendering process to take into account the full cost of the project to the community.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Tom Hayes of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for the Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands to make funding available on a once off basis to allow for the restoration of Fethard Abbey, County Tipperary.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Chambers of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for the Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands to ask Údarás na Gaeltachta to make a specific effort to encourage the creation of new jobs in the Achill area to undo the continuous trend of job loss that is happening in that particular part of County Mayo.</P>
      <P>I have also received notice from Senator Finneran of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Education and Science to provide a second teacher at Curraghroe national school, County Roscommon.</P>
      <P>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected Senator Quinn's and Hayes's matters and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.  Senators Chambers and Finneran may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Col N="1442" />
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Today's Order of Business is items 1 and 2.  Committee and Remaining Stages of item 1 are to be taken today.  Committee and Remaining Stages of item 2 are also to be taken today but are not to commence before 5 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order of Business is agreed. Does the Leader propose to have a debate between now and the recess on the future role of the Seanad?  Will he leave it over until the autumn? Will he arrange a debate for the next session on the recent report of the Oireachtas review group on the electoral system?  It is interesting that the report has become available and it is worth discussing.  A debate would provide an opportunity to review some aspects of the Seanad electoral system and the way it works.  There were a number of problems in the last elections.  The system takes a great length of time and there may be ways of streamlining the process, something which the Leader might examine.</P>
      <P>I have had almost a lifetime's experience of examinations and students.  At present in a number of instances students are experiencing great difficulties.  The horrendous tragedy in Laois has, among other things, put enormous stress on the students involved.  Our sympathy goes to the families. It is difficult to imagine the stress the students are facing as they sit the examinations. There is another problem in Cork.  I appeal to the Minister and his Department to be as flexible as possible.  It is possible to be flexible and fair and people will understand in these cases if the normally rigid procedures are departed from in an effort to prevent the students having to resit the examination thereby losing a year or having to do them in the autumn.  The Minister should have an open mind and will have the support of all fair minded people if he exercises flexibility in these matters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order of Business is agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The loss of low skilled jobs in different parts of the country, for example, at Apple in Cork, through their transfer elsewhere has recently been making the headlines.  This is relevant to a recent request made in the House for a discussion on literacy and numeracy at primary and postprimary school level.  This is a very important issue which could be dealt with in the context of item 14 on the Order Paper which concerns the report of the Joint Committee on Education and Science on literacy levels.  The Leader previously indicated he was prepared to examine the issue. I would like this to be tied in with the commitment he gave last week for a discussion on educational resources and their application.  The Minister is currently examining these issues.  We cannot get jobs for people who are not qualified and there will be an absence of qualified people if support is not provided in the schools.  It is a vicious circle and the issues must be considered together in the context of employment.  I ask the <Col N="1443" /> Leader to ensure a debate takes place before the end of session as he promised last week.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I fully support what Senator Manning said about the tragedy in Laois and ask that the Leader bring to the attention of the Minister our concern that flexibility be exercised in the context of examinations where it is impossible for students to continue.  Some alternative procedure must be put in place to ensure those young people doing their leaving certificate do not lose out because of the huge personal tragedy they have experienced.</P>
      <P>Today is Bloomsday and the House should mark it in some fashion.  Unfortunately, the famous Senator Norris is not present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>That is our contribution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps we should join him for breakfast in North Great George's Street or go to the Martello Tower in Sandycove.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Davy Byrnes would be much better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>We might head in that direction later.  This is the most cultural and literary of days.  Following on what Senator O'Toole said, there are a large number of people who will never have the opportunity of reading the works of James Joyce.  They will understand the language in which <i>Ulysses</i> is written but will never understand the work itself.  In this context I refer to motions 5 and 15 on the Order Paper.  Motion 5 states: &ldquo;That Seanad Éireann expresses its deep concern at the findings of an OECD report which reveals that 25% of Irish adults have serious literacy difficulties; and calls on the Government to take urgent action to improve the situation.&rdquo;.  If we could fulfil that one project I am sure we could deal with the literacy levels.  That would be the best way to mark Bloomsday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>Apparently the Government proposes to bring in emergency legislation on illegal immigrants and penalties for those who employ them.  Before we discuss this legislation, will the Leader organise a debate on the treatment of illegal emigrants to the United States of America over the past 20 to 30 years and the penalties imposed on those who employed them?  I am thinking in particular of those who went to America as economic emigrants because I am sure we would not want to treat anyone who enters this country illegally in a manner worse than the Irish population were treated in the United States.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to raise a point similar to that raised by Senator Henry.  I asked before for a debate on immigration which is an escalating problem and I was concerned by reports on the radio this morning.  I believe accounts suggesting a degree of Mafia control in bringing illegal immigrants to this country are truthful.  I am concerned <Col N="1444" /> about this important issue and escalating problem which we have not had the opportunity to address.  I am sure the Leader will oblige because he has voiced his concerns as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Leader arrange for the Minister for the Environment and Local Government to come to the House to discuss a problem facing the farming community which is almost being forced to work at night transporting silage, etc.  ?  Will the Minister ensure all farm vehicles and farm machinery using the roads during darkness are equipped with a flashing light, which is essential?  As somebody with a hands on knowledge of farming, I appreciate the difficulty facing farmers and I am not inferring or implying responsibility for the serious accident in County Laois.  It is part of an ongoing problem facing the farming community which is forced to work and have vehicles on the road at night.  Will the Minister consider imposing a condition that all farm vehicles must have a flashing light when travelling on roads and will he impose stiff penalties if they are found without them?  Perhaps the Leader will arrange for the Minister to come to the House to consider this serious matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomHayes" hpid="Mr. T. Hayes Mr. T. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the ongoing Garda dispute and the serious concerns citizens, particularly old people, have about it, it is time for leadership.  Will the Leader convey that point not only to the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform but also the Taoiseach?  Some of the tutors or lecturers from the Garda training college in Templemore are outside the House today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot debate this matter now.  I have ruled on it on a number of occasions on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomHayes" hpid="Mr. T. Hayes Mr. T. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to bring it to the attention of the House that the lecturers and tutors from the college in Templemore are outside the gates of Leinster House today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Leader draw the attention of the Minister for Finance to a concern of the EBU, the European Blind Union, which represents 7.5 million people who are partially sighted or blind?  The organisation is concerned about the design of the new euro 20 and 50 cent coins.  Will the Leader ask the Minister to take these concerns into account when decisions are being made at European level?</P>
      <P>I congratulate the National College of Ireland, formerly the National College of Industrial Relations, which has reopened with a bright new college and logo.  I wish it well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Manning inquired about a debate on the future role of the Seanad.  I am pleased to inform the House that Seanad review statements are listed for Wednesday, 24 June.  I will be flexible in regard to time limits and Members will be facilitated in contributing for as long as they wish in the afternoon and evening. <Col N="1445" /> Senators Manning and Costello called on the Minister for Education and Science to display some flexibility in light of the horrific tragedy which occurred in County Laois.  I join in the sentiments expressed by the Senators and, on behalf of the House, offer our condolences to those who have been bereaved.  This was a horrific and terrible accident and I know the Government, the Minister and the Taoiseach would concur with the request for flexibility.</P>
      <P>Senators O'Toole and Costello asked that the Minister for Education and Science come into the House for a debate on literacy.  I have agreed to such a debate taking place prior to the end of this session and will discuss it at the weekly meeting of the Leaders and Whips immediately after the Order of Business.</P>
      <P>Senators Henry and Ridge requested a further debate on illegal immigrants.  Senator Keogh raised this matter in an Adjournment debate last week.  It is expected that the Illegal Immigrants (Trafficking and Employment) Bill will come before the House in the next session.  The Bill would serve to criminalise trafficking in illegal immigrants.  The Government is treating this serious matter as one of urgency.</P>
      <P>Senator McGowan called on the Minister for the Environment and Local Government to come into the House to discuss problems facing the farming community.  I will pass on the Senator's concerns to the Minister and I will afford him time to highlight these issues in the last Fianna Fáil Private Members' time in the last week of the session should he so wish.</P>
      <P>Senator Tom Hayes expressed concern about the GRA dispute.  I welcome the Taoiseach's intervention in the dispute, particularly as he is known for his negotiating skills.  I look forward to a speedy conclusion to the dispute and I join in the concerns expressed by the Senator.  The entire country would like to see the matter brought to a conclusion at an early date.</P>
      <P>Senator Quinn raised a very valuable point in regard to the new euro coins.  There is a great deal of merit in the Senator's comments and I will pass on his concerns to the Minister for Finance later today.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Industrial Development (Enterprise Ireland)" RHead="Bill, 1998: Committee and Remaining Stages">
    <Title>Industrial Development (Enterprise Ireland) Bill, 1998: Committee and Remaining Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 1:</P>
    <P>In page 6, subsection (1) to delete line 10.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Tánaiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment (Miss Harney) Tánaiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment (Miss Harney)">
      <NameTxt>Tánaiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment (Miss Harney)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the amendment is to improve the drafting of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1446" /> Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P>Section 2, as amended, agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 3 to 5, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 2 and 44 are related and may be discussed together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 7, subsection (1), line 16, after &ldquo;as&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;Fiontraíocht Éireann or in the English language&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This simple amendment seeks the insertion of the term &ldquo;Fiontraíocht Éireann&rdquo;.  The Minister proposes to abolish two titles, Forbairt and An Bord Tráchtála.  These bodies are known by their names in the Irish language and it is appropriate to replace them with the Irish language version of the name of the new body.  It appears the new body will be known only as Enterprise Ireland.  It will perform the functions of two bodies which were known by their Irish language titles and I ask the Minister to consider the insertion of the Irish language version of Enterprise Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not table any amendments because we should work in a constructive rather than confrontational manner in this area.  I do not suggest the amendment is confrontational but I hope constructive views will be expressed.</P>
      <P>The name Enterprise Ireland is marvellous and I congratulate the Minister for devising it.  My experience is that the use of Irish language names is powerful and they should be used whenever possible.  However, there are occasions when they work the wrong way and we should try to find a term which is effective.  I was involved in An Bord Poist.  Nobody could pronounce the name and everybody spelt it with a &ldquo;h&rdquo; because they mistook it for a genitive term rather than as an adjective. An Bord Poist was not a good name for the postal board and it was decided that the new organisation should be called An Post to ensure it would be understood and easily translated.  The Minister at the time accepted the term.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are some occasions when the use of the Irish language works well.  However, it would not work well in terms of export business and attempts to attract foreign investors if an unsuitable name is used.  The Industrial Development Authority does not mean anything to a person in San Francisco because the word Ireland, the one word which is necessary, is not mentioned.  In many other cases words which are not suitable are used.  Enterprise Ireland is one case where we should use the word &ldquo;enterprise&rdquo;.  If we were speaking in Irish we would automatically translate the title into its Irish equivalent, but this is an occasion where we need the English language <Col N="1447" /> version because it says more to those who will use the services of this agency.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Quinn that Enterprise Ireland is an excellent name for this important body but, in keeping with tradition, we should not omit the opportunity to apply the correct Irish title.  I like the translation Fiontraíocht Éireann given here.  As the State has always used the first official language in all its publications and laws, it would do no harm to have the correct Irish title inserted into the Bill.  Obviously Enterprise Ireland will be known by the English title but I ask the Minister to consider allowing the correct Irish title to be inserted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot accept this amendment. We are keen to ensure that this agency has a clear focus and that everyone who deals with the agency knows what it is supposed to do.  I have seen a number of examples in the last 12 months of where the agencies which use Irish names have not had that clear focus and, for that reason, they have not been as clearly understood.</P>
      <P>I was visited by the Honorary Irish Consul in western Canada.  With him was a business person who wants to invest in Ireland.  I was discussing the opportunities available with him and he told me that he was going to see An Córas Tráchtála and An Bord Tráchtála.  He did not realise that An Córas Tráchtála had been replaced by An Bord Tráchtála.</P>
      <P>An executive in the IDA tells a story about an American business person who went to Wilton House to visit the home of the agency.  Wilton House is also shared by Forfás and Forbairt. There is a sign in the building which reads Forfás, Forbairt and IDA.  The American asked what this meant and the executive joked that it translated as one hundred thousand welcomes to the IDA. That may be amusing but the reality is that the people who deal with our agencies must know with what they are dealing.</P>
      <P>I do not believe it is sensible to put an agency's name in Irish in a State which exports 84 per cent of what it produces.  Much of the work of this agency will be the overseas marketing of the products of Irish companies.  As I said last week on Second Stage, the purpose of this agency is to help to create sustainable competitive advantage in all our companies.  They will do that by increasing their business and profits through export and employment.  As the focus will be on exports, and because our own market is small, the dealings of this agency with overseas promoters is crucial to its work.  Almost all the work carried out overseas by An Bord Tráchtála, The Trade Board, is done under its English title.</P>
      <P>I do not want to get into a debate about the Irish language.  I am very supportive of it but support should be meaningful.  We should not become involved in tokenism.  I do not suggest that is the motivation behind Senator Costello's amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1448" /> The draftsperson has advised me that if there is both the Irish and English titles it will lead to legal confusion about the precise title of the agency and none of us would want that to happen.</P>
    <P>For those reasons, and I welcome the support of Senator Quinn in this matter, I cannot accede to the amendment.  I hope to be in a position to accept some of the Senator's other amendments later this afternoon.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Due to the sympathetic remark at the end of the Minister's reply, I will not press the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 6 agreed to.</P>
      <P>SECTION 7.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 7 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to raise the definition of &ldquo;service industries&rdquo; in section 7(1) (c).  It is too limited and will make the legislation restrictive rather than enabling.  For many years it was believed that the only real jobs were in manufacturing. In the last decade we created 255,000 jobs in service industries and only 15,000 in manufacturing. These figure may be out of date.  The jobs of the future are going to be in services.  However, manufacturing gets all the State's attention &mdash; tax breaks, grants and the panoply of support.  I am not suggesting that we should be looking for grants for the services sector but there is a bias.</P>
      <P>Ten or 15 years ago the potential of the services sector began to be realised and the Minister was involved at that stage.  However, there was a reluctant acceptance of the potential of the sector.  State support was restricted by legislation to a small number of specialised industries, particularly in internationally traded services.  As we enter the next millennium we are beginning to realise the real potential of the services sector as a job creator and that services do not have to be traded internationally to create good jobs.  This realisation will further develop in the years ahead.  In this context the subsection is too restrictive.  We are perpetuating the cautious attitude of the 1960s rather than reflecting the realities of today.  We should take a different approach.  I am not suggesting that we extend the remit of Enterprise Ireland to cover all services all of the time.  That would be too blunt and would dilute the effectiveness of what we hope to achieve with this agency. However, we should extend its activities to services in stages as demanded by the marketplace.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We should place an onus on the agency to guide the State on which services it believes are appropriate to support at any given time. Enterprise Ireland should be required by legislation to keep under constant review the question of which services it believes we could usefully <Col N="1449" /> support and apply to the Minister on a regular basis for an extension of its remit.  The Minister could be empowered to do so by ministerial order.</P>
    <P>The Minister may tell me that this is already the case.  This moves the decision making closest to the marketplace where it is best laid while maintaining ministerial control.  If the Minister rewords section 7(1)(c) the Bill will cater for the needs of the future rather than being perceived as bound by the shackles of the past.  We have lived for too long with a different attitude.  We need a change of mind and the Minister should consider how this could be achieved.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill brings about a fundamental change to the mindset of supports to business. Section 7 will contain that spirit and a clear direction that the mindset of those providing the service must become client focused.  The Minister intends this as one of the major aims of the legislation and she has my support.  Change of this magnitude must be provided for by the training and retraining of staff.  People must be educated on the change of focus.  I welcome the fact that this focus will be user driven and user friendly and this is one of the key elements of the legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Quinn has expressed many of my concerns.  Staff in these agencies must become very demoralised because the focus of their efforts is often too wide.  The priorities of such agencies should be identified first. Enterprise Ireland seems to have an enormous task ahead of it so perhaps priorities could be set for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I have reservations about combining the functions of the two bodies, replacing them by &ldquo;Enterprise Ireland&rdquo; and the manner in which the Minister proposes to direct the agency to operate.  There is an imbalance in that this seems to be more a Forbairt agency than a marketing agency and that is reflected in the title &mdash; it is an enterprise agency.  I am not happy with the title &ldquo;Enterprise Ireland&rdquo; because it does not reflect the marketing of Ireland or the fact that it will be involved in the export of goods.  While enterprise is involved in both functions, their legal definitions are different.  In the functions outlined in the Bill, a limited number of subsections are devoted to marketing while a considerable number are devoted to enterprise.  The importance of underpinning entrepreneurs, industry and business is well known but the last thing needed is the creation of a new agency which is unbalanced and undermines the role and morale of staff who worked in An Bord Tráchtála. That is one of my concerns and it is continued throughout the Bill, especially in sections 18 and 19 concerning the redeployment of staff.  There seems to be a bias towards the major agency of Forbairt and less consideration given to the importance of either the staff or functions of An <Col N="1450" /> Bord Tráchtála.  Will the Minister address that? How does she envisage that equal emphasis and importance would be given and that the morale of both staff which will comprise Enterprise Ireland would be underpinned?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I share the views of Senator Quinn.  In the past, it was the traditional, old fashioned approach that, if something was not physically made, an enterprise was not created.  It is only in recent years we have been more imaginative in the manner we have sought to support Irish industry.  The International Financial Services Centre is a case in point.  There was much criticism of it when it was first mooted but it has generated a great deal of income for the Revenue and additional employment.  It has been good for Ireland.</P>
      <P>The Industrial Development Act, 1981, specifies that the Minister may, by order, decide what sectors the industrial development agencies support and that was amended in the Industrial Development Act, 1986, to specify designated services.  Which services should be assisted and which should not is clearly a matter for ministerial order because it is accepted that there are many services which would not be considered appropriate for grant aiding by industrial development agencies.  It may be the case that a training agency would support the training of employees in the sector but that it would not be appropriate to give grant aid, for example, hairdressing. FÁS provides a great deal of training for hairdressers to support the hairdressing industry but I do not believe it would be appropriate for it to be grant aided by Enterprise Ireland.  The most effective way to deal with the issue is to take on board what is in the 1981 and 1986 Industrial Development Acts to ensure designation occurs in accordance with new norms and practices.</P>
      <P>The purpose of the agency is to help indigenous Irish companies to grow and develop, particularly in the export sector because the Irish market of 3.5 million people is extremely small.  At present, three different agencies are helping industry through 45 measures for this purpose.  Businesses are currently helped on the basis of an agency's perception of their needs and the objective of this legislation is to look at the needs of Irish industry and to help it accordingly.</P>
      <P>It is intended that industry will be assisted under six categories.  The functions of the agency are to promote, assist and develop the marketing of Irish industry's goods and to promote, assist and develop the marketing of service industries. These functions will be carried out in relation to research and development, human resource development, finance and strategy assessment. This will be done through the business development model we discussed on Second Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I assure Senator Costello that this is not a reinvention of Forbairt.  The purpose of the agency is to bring together the different supports which are available to indigenous industry at present and to ensure that they are integrated into one package <Col N="1451" /> and delivered in a clear, focused and comprehensive manner.  At present, some companies receive support from all three agencies because they have the wherewithal and the competence to access many of the 45 measures that are available to help industry.  Other smaller or peripheral companies or companies at an earlier stage of development which might be in greater need of the support do not have the wherewithal to access the type of support they need.  This agency will help them in that regard.</P>
    <P>With regard to Senator Ross' comments, unless there is a completely free market where all agencies are abolished, I see no other way of proceeding. Senator Ross and others might desire such a free market but we had three options: to get rid of all agencies, to keep things as they are or to take the route outlined in the Bill.  The last is the way to help industry to grow, particularly indigenous industry whose potential has not been realised.  In future this might not be a function of the State but for as long as the State supports the growth and development of industry, as it currently does in many ways, it must do so in a focused and streamlined way.  That is the aim of the Bill.</P>
    <P>Later we will deal with the functions being assigned to the agency.  All functions of An Bord Tráchtála will be assigned to the agency and An Bord Tráchtála will be dissolved.  The same will also happen in the case of Forbairt.  The two agencies will be combined in one and its focus will be on developing business through exports. The potential to develop business otherwise is extremely limited.</P>
    <P>If Senator Quinn can give me examples of services which should be designated, we can discuss it on another occasion.  Anything that has the potential to grow and develop and create employment, particularly in an export context, should be supported.  However, I am anxious that there should be a flexible approach to ensure that we do not exclude anything that might have great potential.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Lest my comments are misunderstood, Enterprise Ireland should be required by the legislation to constantly review which industries should be supported so the onus of reponsibility is on the agency.  If the agency is not told that it is part of its function, it might fail to do it.</P>
      <P>I agree that the Minister should have responsibility to make the order but I was seeking a way to encourage, if not force, the agency to keep this issue under constant review and to continue to come up with ideas.  The agency might just decide to do what it is asked to do and not continue to seek new and better ways if it is not asked to so do.  I accept the Minister's point but I ask her to consider mine in case there is a better way of doing it.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1452" /> SECTION 8.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 8 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 8(1) states:</P>
      <P>The Minister may give the Agency such general policy directives as he or she considers appropriate to be followed by the Agency in the exercise of its functions.</P>
      <P>However, subsection (2) appears to remove that power.  Galway lost a number of jobs following the closure of Digital and the focus of the IDA on the Galway area after that loss was most important for the continued economic growth of the region.  Can the Minister clarify if that power will be removed from the agency should a similar circumstance require it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>On Second Stage I commented on section 8 and I welcomed these two subsections. It is appropriate that the powers of the Minister which are outlined in section 8(1) are circumscribed by subsection 2.  This does not diminish in any way the capacity to ensure that inward or indigenous investment is directed to where it is most needed.  It is appropriate that some restriction is placed on the Minister's powers in order to avoid any inference that a project was directed to a particular place by a Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I can fulfil the requests of both Senators.  The purpose of the general directive is to allow a Minister to give general policy directives to an agency.  For example, the Minister could decide that, if resources were limited, support should be directed to particular sectors or regions in line with Government policy.  Ministers should not intervene in relation to particular companies or projects.  That would be a recipe for disaster.  We had Fóir Teoranta but that body no longer exists.  We do not want to see a Minister or a vulnerable Government being tempted to support a company in one location while a similar company in another location is not supported. Officials in my Department spent much time recently going through files trying to find out if a Minister had intervened in relation to a particular company a number of years ago.  I do not want to see a Minister or a Government in the future being able to decide to give a specific direction. On one occasion in the past such a direction was given to the IDA.  It is wrong that a Minister or a Government should interfere in relation to a particular company.  These decisions must be made on the basis of clearly laid down criteria.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Government in its Programme for Government has declared its commitment to balanced regional development.  I have spoken to the chief executives to ensure that a favourable bias is shown towards areas outside the greater Dublin area and particularly outside the cities.  It is relatively easy to generate economic activity in urban areas but we must ensure that the peripheral areas get industrial support.  That directive is of <Col N="1453" /> a general nature and does not apply to specific companies.</P>
    <P>I share the Senator's concern.  Large regions of the country have virtually no industrial development. People will not live in these regions if they cannot find employment.  Companies will not locate there because there is no available workforce. The agencies must marry all elements together and present attractive packages for these locations.</P>
    <P>Current policy is to give more grant aid to peripheral locations and it has had some effect.  We need to do more to support regional industrial development.  The Government is examining the best way to ensure, for example, that the Border counties do not suffer from development on the other side of the Border.  The Border counties have suffered from low investment in recent years because of violence in Northern Ireland and from being cut off from their natural economic hinterland. Our policy for those regions must encourage, in so far as it can, the growth of industrial projects there.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister's statement. In addition to the restrictions which are imposed on the Minister by section 8(2), there is an additional onus of transparency in that the directive must first be placed before each House of the Oireachtas and that the actions relating to any directive must be outlined in the annual report.  These additional mechanisms provide adequate safeguards.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 9.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 8a, on the additional list, is an alternative to amendment No. 3.  Both amendments may be discussed together, by agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 3:</P>
      <P>In page 8, subsection (2), line 41, after &ldquo;members&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;not less than 4 of whom shall be women&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This amendment proposes that not less than four of the 12 board members shall be women. Women will not have the majority but rather one third of the board membership.  It is not unreasonable that this should be stated in the legislation as we are establishing a State body.  In the previous Government there was definite and deliberate practice that new and existing State bodies would have a strong element of gender proofing.  I would have thought that the Minister, introducing her first legislation, would take the opportunity to follow in those footsteps, in accordance with clear Progressive Democrats' policy in terms of gender equity, and that she would have ensured that women are represented on State boards.  This is the recommendation of the Commission for the Status of Women.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1454" /> It is not good enough for the Minister to provide an alternative whereby she shall &ldquo;in so far as is practicable and having regard to relevant experience, ensure an equitable balance between men and women in the composition of the Board&rdquo;.  That is wishful thinking.  Deputy Harney will not be the Minister forever.  Perhaps she is well disposed to ensuring a reasonable balance. However, I am not sure her colleagues in coalition would be.  This is a sop.  The Minister should have proceeded with the Progressive Democrats' policy, which coincides with the views of the majority of Members of both Houses.</P>
    <P>This should be one of the central features of membership of not just the main board, but subsidiary boards and sub-committees which may be established under this legislation.  I am disappointed that the Minister did not take advantage of the first opportunity she had to assert her concerns in this matter on a statutory basis.  When she indicated she would accept some amendments, I thought this would be one of them.  It is a reasonable and modest proposal and the Bill would benefit substantially from its inclusion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I am disappointed that Senator Costello said that the other Coalition parties would not ensure equity between men and women in the composition of the board.  Perhaps he is talking about other parties that may be coalition partners in the future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not include Senator Cox.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Costello's amendment proposes that four out of 12 members of the board should be women, which is 33 per cent.  This is not equitable.  I commend the Minister's amendment which proposes that in so far as is practicable and having regard to the relevant experience, the Minister shall ensure an equitable balance.  The days of women looking for tokenism on any board are over.  We can stand on our own and we are proud of our ability to be equal to any man. Enough women have relevant experience and have major contributions to make in this area. The Government amendment goes further than the amendment proposed by the Labour Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator Costello's amendment.  I appreciate what the Minister is trying to do with her own amendment No. 8a.  We might not always have a lady Minister, so we might then be trying to protect the men.</P>
      <P>The term &ldquo;having regard to relevant experience&rdquo; in amendment No. 8a might be taken to imply that a sufficient number of women are not qualified.  I reject what Senator Cox said; we are not interested in seeking tokenism.  The truth is that in this day and age the contrary is the case. There is more than an abundant number of women who are well qualified to fill spaces on any such board, including this one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I understood, however, that regardless of who was in office, the State had established a way of <Col N="1455" /> dealing with matters like this.  We have a gender quota subsidy built in, although I do not know what the convention is.  However, I am sure that what Senator Costello has tabled regarding one third is not unreasonable.  I support his amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister should be assured that no one is looking for tokenism.  Having served on boards which in recent times have had a better gender equity, for example, Comhairle na nOspidéal, I do not think anyone could but say that the boards were improved.  What concerns me is that if we do not insert something such as suggested by Senator Costello's amendment, a very large number of those who represent smaller industries and the service industries, where women have been extremely important in the establishment of new industries, will not be represented.</P>
      <P>This board could all too easily have the great and the good and, with all due respects to Senator Quinn, the most senior business people, but that is not necessarily the best way of setting up the board.  If the legislation specified that at least a certain number of board members would be women, we would all think it very odd if we had to say that a certain number would be men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Why does the Senator not do so?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it is necessary because we know that it will be a mainly male board as most State boards have been in the past. Until very recently I have seen this happen in medical, academic and business boards.  I have not heard anyone argue, although they may start today, that the value of these boards has been diminished by the fact that women are now represented on them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>It should be made clear that one of the important parts of amendment No. 8a is where it states that:</P>
      <P>The Minister shall, in so far as is practicable and having regard to relevant experience.</P>
      <P>We are now introducing the idea of relevant experience both for men and women.  In the past a number of men were appointed to State boards who did not have any relevant experience.</P>
      <P>I totally reject Senator Coghlan's assertion that there are not enough women with relevant experience.  There are more than enough women with relevant experience.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>That was precisely my point.  The Senator has misinterpreted what I said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I apologise if I misinterpreted the Senator's point.  I welcome the fact that we will now have regard to relevant experience.  The equitable balance is certainly much stronger than four out of 12.  I would be afraid that in future, with a change of Government or of Minister, a new Minister might be happy with only four out <Col N="1456" /> of 12 instead of having eight out of 12, which is what in my opinion would be equitable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not intend to contribute on this amendment but, as so often happens, the contributions from the Labour Party inspired me to say something.  I think we are fighting the battles of yesterday and I cannot believe this amendment is serious.  This battle was won and lost ten or 20 years ago.  It is no longer necessary to specify in exact numbers and figures how many women or men must be on a particular board.  There is some blatant political opportunism involved in this.  To say that we need women for these boards is to appeal to the women's vote.  We should do what the Government amendment suggests and take a mature view on this, saying that we will have an equitable number of men and women if that is necessary.  This battle is won and we should not have to fight the gender battle every time a Bill like this comes before the House.  That battle ended ten years ago and most women like to be educated, to compete and to get jobs on merit. This is a middle aged, middle class argument which should not be entered into.</P>
      <P>This amendment is flawed in any case because it does not seek to have at least four men and four women; according to Senator Costello's interpretation, one could have 12 women but not 12 men.  This seems to be biased the other way, and if the Senator is to be consistent he should have at least four of each.  Here one could have 12 women and no men, but not 12 men and no women.  There should be a free for all debate on this matter, once and for all, and then we would never hear of it again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is difficult to deal with this issue without being misunderstood, but if someone suggested that 40 per cent of the Cabinet, 40 per cent of Senators or 40 per cent of Labour Senators should be female, Senator Costello might be the first to say it was not democratic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Due to a Labour Party regulation, 40 per cent of our Ministers in the last Government were female.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>They were not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>They were; that is correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator mean 40 per cent of Labour Ministers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Labour Party had one full Minister, Ms Niamh Bhreathnach, out of six Cabinet posts, and one out of six is not 40 per cent, at least it was not when I was going to school.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The new mathematics.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1457" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I am counting Ministers of State as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>As someone once prevented from joining a club not because I was a woman, as I was told, but because I was not a man, nobody is more conscious of the need for equality than I. However, we must also be practical.  I want the best people on this board to help indigenous Irish industry to grow.  I want people of experience and high calibre.  I am not suggesting there are no such women, but in 1997 only 2 per cent of the chief executives of companies in Ireland were women.  The reality is that one is drawing from a pool of 2 per cent.</P>
      <P>If 40 per cent of the board was female and one woman retired, there might be a gap on the board in the technology area and one would need a replacement from that field.  If a woman with the necessary experience could not be found, is the Senator suggesting that a man should not be appointed to the board?</P>
      <P>To some extent this debate is over.  If Senator Costello was being consistent he would suggest that a certain percentage should be under 30 or 35.  That is an equally valid argument.  My amendment seeks to be practical and the emphasis is on relevant experience.  I want a board of experienced people, many of whom should have developed their own businesses.  That is the key. Board appointments from recent Governments have, in general, improved enormously from what they were years ago.</P>
      <P>The last Government had a general policy of appointing boards with 40 per cent female representation, but that is proving extremely difficult. Many boards are representational and the social partners make nominations for them.  The partners on both sides &mdash; not just the employers - frequently present exclusively male panels for appointment.  That is because it is difficult to find relevant women in particular sectors.  It is important that Enterprise Ireland has a board of talented, experienced people who can contribute to the growth and development of indigenous Irish business because of their experience.  I will be conscious of the need for women to be involved.  There are women who have started their own businesses, particularly in the services sector, as Senator Henry said.  Women in the United States are starting businesses at twice the rate of men now, but the pool from which we draw means it will not always be possible to achieve Senator Costello's aim.</P>
      <P>For example, one board member will be the chief executive, who is male.  The chairperson designate has been announced and is also male. Traditionally an official from my Department and an official from the Department of Agriculture and Food &mdash; because Forbairt deals with the food sector &mdash; are on the board.  That leaves eight places and Senator Costello proposes that four of those eight people or 50 per cent should be female.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1458" /> I will endeavour as far as I can to have good women on the board.  I have a good record since coming to office for appointing good people, both male and female, and for retaining those appointed by my predecessor where I felt it important to do so.  However, it would be wrong to have a statutory requirement for this board which does not exist in relation to any other private sector board or to membership of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>The Constitution has a lot of pious aspirations for the role of women such as not forcing women to work because of economic necessity and neglecting their duties in the home as a result.  We must understand that words alone do not achieve equality.  They have not achieved equality in the public sector where women have not made it to key senior positions.  There are wider issues to discuss here, and they will not be dealt with by a statutory requirement for this board to have 40 per cent female membership.  I want an experienced board that is regionally balanced and of mixed age, if possible.  There are many young dynamic businesspeople I would like to see involved, but it is neither right nor fair to tie my hands and those of my successors on female representation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand the concerns expressed on where the women will come from if the search is limited to chief executives.  I asked people who set up small businesses about the sort of person they wanted for this board and their suggestions were interesting.  We have had great success in science and technology, particularly the telecommunications, pharmaceutical and computer industries.  The people I spoke to felt that bodies like the Science Council should advise the board.</P>
      <P>Another suggestion relates to section 7(1)(i), which states:</P>
      <P>to administer such schemes, grants and other financial facilities requiring the disbursement of European Union and such other funds as may from time to time be authorised by the Minister with the concurrence of the Minister for Finance,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The need for people with experience of the environmental impact area or the ecology of enterprise was also mentioned to me.  The Department of the Environment and Local Government is setting up a new council, the National Developmental Council, which is to work in parallel with the National Social and Economic Council.  Several people said we would face trouble unless the developments were sustainable and the environmental impact of whatever industries were set up was taken into account.  The new structure of funds we hope to get means that environmental impact must be taken into account before those funds are disbursed. Accordingly, people with environmental knowledge on the board would be important so <Col N="1459" /> that areas of sustainable development could be considered.</P>
    <P>Those appear to be two areas where one would find plenty of women.  Women have also been involved in university innovation.  Chief executives are very important, because if one has not had experience of getting one's fingers burnt one is not in a position to give advice.  We will miss out on a huge number of people who could be extremely important to the board if, as I suspect, only chief executive officers or chairpersons of companies are appointed.  I hope the Minister will look to other areas for suitable members apart from chief executive officers, 2 per cent of whom are female.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I am disappointed by the Minister's response and the fact that she did not give some indication in the legislation of equity in the membership of the board.  She said the pool of qualified women is small, amounting to about 2 per cent in industry.  She is effectively admitting that it is very unlikely that women will be represented on the board.  She has chosen four males and, showing her attitude to this issue, is asking if we are expecting her to choose females for four of the remaining eight places.</P>
      <P>I respect what the Minister says regarding the macho ethos of industry and big business, but this is something we are trying to change.  The Minister is speaking about a new body which will lead us into the future, not one which will dredge up the residue of the past.  We are talking about a new culture and a new approach to indigenous industry where many women are coming on board, particularly in the services area.  Senator Quinn spoke eloquently about the emphasis on services and the marketing of service industries under section 7.</P>
      <P>A free for all along the lines described by Senator Ross will result in a male dominated system. We have no choice but to build in some gender proofing.  I am proposing a minimalist approach, namely, the appointment of four females thereby leaving the remaining eight positions to be filled by males.  My wording may not be absolutely correct &mdash; the phrase &ldquo;a minimum of four should be of either sex&rdquo; might be better. However, there should be some support for female representation.  The simple fact is if there is a free for all in the context of a board of this nature, it will be totally male dominated.</P>
      <P>I also take on board what Senator Henry said, namely, that we should be looking at some of the other areas from which women can be recruited, including the environmental sector and small innovative businesses which are being developed. There is no reason we should not look for female representation in these sectors.  In addition to specific expertise, a range of expertise, acumen and thought processes is necessary.  It is also necessary to have people with different logical processes on such a board, something which cannot be represented if it is 100 per cent male.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1460" /> Arguments can be made for a broader range of skills in addition to those which are relevant.</P>
    <P>In this context I find it difficult to accept the Minister's amendment which states &ldquo;as far as is practicable and having regard to relevant experience&rdquo;. &ldquo;Relevant experience&rdquo; seems to be defined in a very narrow fashion.  If the Minister's amendment simply said &ldquo;The Minister shall ensure an equitable balance between men and women in the composition of the board&rdquo; I would gladly accept it.  However, we are talking about a State board and if we continue along the lines being proposed I have no doubt there will be a token woman appointed and that the Minister will have added to the approach of tokenism in legislation.  The chairperson is already being referred to as a chairman.  By implication, a male chairman has already been selected.  There is a presumption that a male will run the show.  My amendment is reasonable and very desirable.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Costello seems to be saying that he would happily accept the Minister's amendment if she removed the term &ldquo;relevant experience&rdquo;.  I do not understand why this would satisfy him.  Members and the Minister want to ensure the board has the best people on it wherever they come from.  Ensuring &ldquo;an equitable balance between men and women in the composition of the board&rdquo; is the correct wording.  Perhaps Senator Costello has explained his wish to remove the words &ldquo;having regard to relevant experience&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Senator Henry made some very pertinent points regarding relevant experience which may not necessarily be found among chief executive officers of big companies but rather among people who, for example, solve the difficulty of paying wages every Friday night.  Such a person might be very useful on the board, a point made very well by Senator Henry.  The Minister's words cover this issue adequately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Costello seems to think we have made up our minds regarding membership of the board.  The chief executive designate is male but I was not involved in choosing him. The process was completely independent and I understand no woman applied for the job.  It is hard to pick a woman when none applies.  I picked Pat Molloy, the retiring chief executive of the Bank of Ireland, as he is an outstanding business person who will make an enormous contribution to establishing the new agency.  He has a good track record of dealing with businesses at all levels.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I recently appointed a woman to chair the small business forum, the group which advises Government about small business issues.  I appointed the first ever female rights commissioner attached to the Labour Court.  Three of the five members of the minimum wage commission were female as was the chairperson.  I have appointed umpteen women since coming to office.  Recently, there was a joint meeting between Industry Ministers <Col N="1461" /> of OECD countries regarding business.  Each Minister was invited to bring two business persons with them to attend and I took two women. I have a good track record in this area and for political parties which do not have quotas to tell everybody else they must have a quota is a bit much.</P>
    <P>I take on board the comments of Senator Henry.  I may not have explained myself so well. I do not intend only having chief executives, many of whom may not have time to participate in a State board.  I was simply making the point that, relatively speaking, there are very few women who have advanced in the world of business and I want people with business experience on the board.  This does not necessarily mean people who run a business and I accept the point about those who may have established a business and women involved in innovation.  The board must include people with ideas, competence and relevant experience.  To delete the reference to relevant experience as suggested by Senator Costello would weaken the position.  It applies as much to males as females in terms of appointment to the board.</P>
    <P>Later we will discuss those eliminated from membership of the board.  County councillors, for example, cannot be involved in the board, something which is to be welcomed.  Among other considerations, this provision is for good political reasons; we do not want political decisions being made or any inference of there being such. Members of the Oireachtas, the European Parliament and local authorities are excluded from membership of the board.  In the past there has been a tendency to make appointments from these groups and I am not sure doing so is appropriate.</P>
    <P>None of the four people I spoke about has been chosen except for the chief executive designate. I recently appointed an official to An Bord Tráchtála which did not have an official in the past.  Such appointments are good for the boards, the Department and the officials involved.  I went down a rank to find a woman to appoint because the person I would have appointed if I had appointed the person in charge of the sector would have been a male.  To ensure I gave an opportunity to a female official to participate, I went down a rank and appointed a female principal officer.  My record stands for itself and I will be happy to come back to the House when Enterprise Ireland is established to defend the appointees.  I may be leaving myself open to problems down the line but I have no doubt the board will win widespread acceptability from, I hope, all Members of the House.  I would like the board to get off to a good positive start and would like its members to be seen as people of experience and with the competency to do the job the Oireachtas will require them to do.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Dardis) Acting Chairman (Mr. Dardis)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Dardis)</NameTxt>
      <P>We have fully discussed this matter and we should put the question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1462" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask Senator Costello to accept the words &ldquo;relevant experience&rdquo; because they apply to men and women.  We all have ideas on relevant experience.  For example, I hope the Minister will look for people with experience of working abroad and perhaps experience of languages.  The board needs to be broader than simply 12 chief executive officers sitting around a table and who, as Senator Quinn and I believe, would not have the time do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to clarify what I said. The Minister proposes that the Minister shall in so far as is practicable and having regard to relevant experience ensure an equitable balance between men and women in the composition of the board.  We are inserting two conditions.  The first condition is &ldquo;in so far as is practicable&rdquo;, which is open ended.  What does &ldquo;in so far as is practicable&rdquo; mean?  On having regard to relevant experience, the Minister made much of the fact that 2 per cent of women have the experience and are of the required calibre.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say that.  I said 2 per cent of chief executives running private enterprise are female.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>She went on to say that this was a small pool from which to draw.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to imply they will be chief executives because there may not be any on the board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>If this is how the Minister determines relevant experience, we should not include conditions in her amendment.  I would be happy to accept the Minister's amendment if she removed both conditions and if it read as follows: &ldquo;The Minister shall ensure an equitable balance between men and women in the composition of the board.&rdquo; The Minister may include a condition but once we do so, we distort the situation. I interpreted what the Minister meant by &ldquo;relevant experience&rdquo; in the way she described it.</P>
      <P>The Minister has a good track record and I am not attacking her in that regard.  However, I do not see why she cannot continue that record into this area.  Four of the 12 appointed to the board should be women, which is a modest proposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>The use of the words &ldquo;in so far as is practicable&rdquo; and &ldquo;having regard to relevant experience&rdquo; ensures that we treat men and women equally in relation to appointments to this board.  There is no longer a need for Senator Costello to push out this boat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>That would make sense if we removed the words &ldquo;in so far as is practicable&rdquo; and &ldquo;having regard to relevant experience&rdquo;.  Having regard to relevant experience would mitigate against women.  If these words were removed it would mean what the Minister intends, Senator <Col N="1463" /> Costello would be happy and we would avoid a vote.  The section is better without those words.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>We either leave the Bill as it stands or we write in my amendment which strengthens it.  I am trying to take on board some of the suggestions made by Senator Costello.  The words &ldquo;relevant experience&rdquo; and &ldquo;in so far as is practicable&rdquo; refer to men and women.  By removing the words &ldquo;relevant experience&rdquo;, we are saying it does not matter what women or men we get and that anybody may be appointed to the board. That would be a pity.  &ldquo;Relevant experience&rdquo; will be defined in its broadest sense and does not refer only to people who have been chief executives but to people who have started their own <Col N="1464" /> business, people who have been involved in innovation or, as Senator Henry said, people who have worked abroad.</P>
      <P>I would like to think we will take a wide definition of &ldquo;relevant experience&rdquo;.  The key issue is to have people of quality who can help indigenous industry to grow because of the perspective they will bring to decisions which will be taken by the board.  All the grant aid packages going to companies will have to be approved at some level by the board and many will be assessed by subcommittees of the board.  It is important, therefore, the board is composed of people who have relevant experience and a competency to bring to this issue.</P>
      <P>Amendment put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Committee divided: Tá, 10; Níl, 22.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Burke, Paddy.<br />Coghlan, Paul.<br />Connor, John.<br />Costello, Joe.<br />Doyle, Avril.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Hayes, Maurice.<br />Hayes, Tom.<br />Henry, Mary.<br />Manning, Maurice.<br />Ridge, Thére se.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bohan, Eddie.<br />Bonner, Enda.<br />Callanan, Peter.<br />Chambers, Frank.<br />Cox, Margaret.<br />Dardis, John.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Finneran, Michael.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Gibbons, Jim.<br />Keogh, Helen.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kett, Tony.<br />Kiely, Daniel.<br />Lanigan, Mick.<br />McGowan, Patrick.<br />Mooney, Paschal.<br />Moylan, Pat.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />O'Donovan, Denis.<br />Ó Murchú, Labhrás.<br />Quinn, Feargal.<br />Ross, Shane.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Tellers: Tá, Senators Coghlan and Costello; Níl, Senators T. Fitzgerald and Keogh.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 4, 5, 9 to 16, inclusive, 18 to 25, inclusive, 30, 32 and 38 form a composite proposal while amendment No. 17 is an alternative and all may be discussed together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 4:</P>
      <P>In page 9, subsection (5), line 2, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This is a straightforward amendment which seeks to replace the term &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; with the term &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.  This precedent has been established and is enunciated particularly in employment equality legislation where the term &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo; is used in all references to the chair of bodies.  It is a simple but important approach because it is now normal practice that the term &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo; is used to describe the person chairing a meeting or a board.  This should be reflected in this legislation.</P>
      <P>The former Minister for Equality and Law Reform established that precedent under the previous Government and it is appropriate to maintain it because it is part of equality and law reform matters.  The Statute Book should reflect that position.  I was surprised that the Minister was not prepared to accept that a number of posts should be specifically set aside for women in the composition of the board.  I will also be surprised if she is not prepared to accept the term &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo; as the proper designation of the person chairing the board or meetings of committees.</P>
      <P>The Minister has suggested an alternative in amendment No. 17 which states:</P>
      <P>A person appointed to be chairman of the Board may be referred to (including in any document relating to appointment) by that title or by such other title as the Board considers, with the concurrence of the Minister, appropriate.</P>
      <P>It would be easier to use the term &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo; in the legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister said earlier that words alone do not achieve equality.  It is important to note this point, but I ask the Minister to accept the amendment.  A precedent has been set and it is important to recognise in the legislation that it is a time of change and women are becoming more involved in an increasing number of areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1465" />
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I usually favour tradition and precedent.  However, in light of new age developments, I also plead with the Minister to accede to this and other appropriate amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted to welcome Fine Gael into new age developments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am happy to oblige.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I recall debates in this House and elsewhere when Senator Avril Doyle referred to tokenism.  Given Senator Costello's unreasonableness regarding the previous amendment, I am tempted not to accept this amendment.  However, given that Senator Cox has been more than reasonable, I am prepared to accept it and not to proceed with amendment No. 17 which would have allowed the chairperson to be called whatever he or she wished.</P>
      <P>Chairpersons are probably similar to angels in that they are genderless.  There are many consequential amendments which must be accepted if amendment No. 4 is agreed to but the Senator is correct that the term &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo; is more acceptable nowadays.  The Irish language term, &ldquo;Cathaoirleach&rdquo;, is also gender neutral so the term &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo; is appropriate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>That was graciously put by the Tánaiste.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Does Senator Costello wish to comment?  Does he think he should speak at this point?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I am overwhelmed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator was taken by surprise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>If I had known the Minister intended to accept these amendments, I would have reconsidered calling a division on the previous amendment.  I thank the Minister and I appreciate her acceptance of the amendments.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 5:</P>
      <P>In page 9, subsection (8), line 13, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 7 is consequential on amendment No. 6 and may be discussed together.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 6:</P>
      <P>In page 9, subsection (9), line 18, to delete &ldquo;one of whom is&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;who are&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the amendment is grammatical.  It involves two members standing <Col N="1466" /> down from the board on a rota basis after three years.  The provision should, therefore, state &ldquo;who are&rdquo; rather than &ldquo;one of whom is&rdquo;.  They are technical amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I disagree with the approach in this area because it will produce a board which will not change often enough.  If there are 12 members and only two retire at three yearly intervals, the section provides for a cycle which could continue for 18 years.  This is too long.  Under subsection (14) a board member could then be reappointed for a further 18 years.  It is almost absurd to consider such a provision.</P>
      <P>The ideal is that a board constantly refreshes itself through the input of new people.  This avoids the mistake of throwing people off the board when they are getting up to speed and starting to make a contribution.  Everybody should come up for reappointment at intervals not longer than five years and they should not serve more than two terms, giving a total service of ten years.  The section allows for a position where people could become fixed on the board for too long.  They could serve as long as 18 years.  Everybody with experience of this matter will agree that the usefulness of any board member begins to diminish after some time.</P>
      <P>I ask the Minister to consider this matter. There must be a better way because the method used in the section is incorrect.  I do not disagree with the amendment but I disagree with the principle behind it.  There are benefits in having people with experience on a board and not changing its construction at one time.  Changing elements of the board at different times makes sense.  However, this provision is wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>There is merit in Senator Quinn's comments.  I will reflect on the position between now and the debate on the Bill in the other House, but if amendments are made in the Dáil the Bill must be returned to the Seanad.</P>
      <P>Traditionally, boards were put in place for five years and at the end of that time everybody stood down.  This caused many difficulties because there tended to be a new board every time a new Government came into office.  There was no continuity and this is not good for agencies and their senior executive staff.  The previous Government when it introduced the Industrial Development Act, 1993, to implement some of the recommendations of the Culliton report brought in the new procedure.  It works well and means in the case of Enterprise Ireland that after three years, two board members will stand down.  Another two will stand down in the fourth year and a further two in the fifth year.</P>
      <P>However, Senator Quinn made a valid point.  I agree nobody should serve on the same board for more than ten years.  I will consider the matter and, if necessary, I will introduce an amendment. However, I wish to discuss its implications for other boards before I return to the House with an amendment at a later stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1467" />
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister.  I did not expect her to do anything more than consider whether there is a better way.  I did not table an amendment because I considered that the Minister might make suggestions which may be suitable.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 7:</P>
      <P>In page 9, subsection (9), line 19, to delete &ldquo;member&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;members&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 8 is in the name of Senator Costello.  Amendments Nos. 29 and 37 are related.  Amendments Nos. 8, 29 and 37 will be taken together by agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 8:</P>
      <P>In page 9, subsection (12), line 35, after &ldquo;time&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;for stated reasons&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I propose that we insert the words &ldquo;for stated reasons&rdquo; so the Bill reads &ldquo;A member of the Board may at any time for stated reasons be removed from membership of the Board&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The purpose of this is to ensure that members are not removed unilaterally or due to the opinion of the Minister, that natural justice would operate and there would be no form of diktat or interference.  In the text of the subsection the Minister specifies certain conditions: &ldquo;if, in the Minister's opinion the Member has become, incapable&rdquo; or &ldquo;has committed stated misbehaviour&rdquo;. Those are the areas which have been covered.  It continues that a member can be removed if the Minister deems it &ldquo;to be necessary for the effective performance by the Agency&rdquo;.  It is uncertain how someone can be removed from the board.  We need to specify that there must be a stated reason before the Minister would take any action.</P>
      <P>This Bill gives the Minister inordinate powers and here it goes beyond what could be considered appropriate.  It leaves it to what the Minister regards as necessary in his or her opinion.  We should include the clause &ldquo;for stated reasons&rdquo; to ensure that board members receive full protection and that there is transparency in the decisions and actions of the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I know Senator Costello will be surprised to find me supporting one of his amendments. I have no problem with the Minister having the complete power to remove a board member but such power should bring its own measure of responsibility and accountability.  I suggest that after any exercise of this power the Minister be required to make a statement to both Houses of the Oireachtas explaining the reason for the removal.  Officials may find some legal difficulties with this, but it reduces the possibility of legal action which could take place after the <Col N="1468" /> removal of a board member.  It would ensure a removal took place only when it could be openly defended.  I support the intention of Senator Costello's amendment and believe that the Minister should give serious thought to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is an excellent amendment.</P>
      <P>I thought we had moved on in our democracy from the practice of something occurring at the whim of the Minister, although that is not the intention here.  We need to be proactive in ending that culture.  As Senator Quinn said, if we are to avoid court action there must be accountability and responsibility.  Senator Costello's proposal that the phrase &ldquo;for stated reasons&rdquo; be inserted implies all that is necessary regarding equity and natural justice.  I strongly support this amendment. The removal of a member on a whim would have nothing to do with policy and, in the past, would have had everything to do with subverting proper procedures.  I know the Minister, in her projected role as guardian of the highest standards in Government, would see good reasons to accept this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate Senator Costello on this amendment.  I have a problem with political appointments.  On the basis that this section will not be withdrawn, I am totally supportive of the principle that if people are going to be removed, having been appointed politically, the political process should require a reason to be given.  That is common sense.</P>
      <P>The provisions here are completely inadequate. It reads &ldquo;if, in the Minister's opinion, the member has become incapable through ill-health of performing his or her functions&rdquo;.  The director would be aware of his or her own health and a Minister would not be in any better position to tell, unless the Minister anticipates a situation where someone has gone off their head, a situation open to subjective judgment.  Indeed it could be interpreted that a person has gone off their head when they do something the Minister does not like.</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Stated misbehaviour&rdquo; is also inadequate.  It is the minimum we should require that any Minister who summarily removes someone from the State board to which they have been appointed politically should answer to the political process for that removal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I request that the Minister accept this amendment given the experience of the lady from Galway, who although very capable, was removed at the whim of a Minister in a previous administration.  In recognising that these situations have arisen in the past, perhaps the Minister will consider accepting this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I am advised that this amendment is unnecessary but the Senators have made a case for it.  The recent court judgment in the CIE case, to which Senator Cox referred, when the then Minister removed certain members from <Col N="1469" /> the CIE Board, held that the Minister was wrong. It is right that if a Minister removes someone from a board for extraordinary reasons, he or she should have to state those reasons.</P>
      <P>In stating the reasons one would have to be precise because it could open a Pandora's box of litigation, but a person's name is blackened if they are removed from a board.  If a Minister does not like someone for political reasons, that is not a good enough reason for removing that person from the board of a State company.  I am happy to accept the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank all the Senators for their support and the Minister, who is showing herself as a reasonable Minister.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 8a:</P>
      <P>In page 9, after line 49, to insert the following subsection:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(15) The Minister shall, in so far as is practicable and having regard to relevant experience, ensure an equitable balance between men and women in the composition of the Board.&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 9, as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not approve of this section.  I do not approve of the political control of State agencies or boards.  We have touched on this by accepting an amendment in which the Minister must state reasons for removing someone.  We should do the reverse and have the Minister state why he or she appointed a person.  The record of successive Governments on appointments to State boards is disgraceful.  We have witnessed political appointments to these bodies where people's credentials are dubious but they can be visibly identified as belonging to a political party and that is the primary reason for their appointment. I will not be invidious and name people, but one could see that on some of the boards appointed by the last Government one member was appointed by each of the three parties.  That is dangerous and a perversion of the system to which at some stage we should call a halt.</P>
      <P>The Minister devised a different system for appointing members to the EPA and I would be interested to hear how she feels that has worked. She devised a system of appointing people to a State agency which removed the Minister from direct involvement.  As far as I know that has worked reasonable well and there have been few accusations of political influence on the EPA.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would prefer if there were no State agencies but if we have them it is important that they are removed from the accusation that it is the same faces and names on boards time and again.  There is an overlap of people appointed to State agencies <Col N="1470" /> and it is obvious that they are appointed for political reasons and not because they are experts.  Some of those appointed are not experts in the relevant fields, ranging from communications, training, exports and so on.  However, because of their loyalty to a party, they are considered worthy of appointment.</P>
    <P>This issue is particularly important with this new agency as it will be disbursing grants.  The statutory requirement for the agency will rise from £750 million to £2 billion.  That is not the amount it will disburse in grants but the amount it will receive.  However, this superagency will be disbursing grants; and if ever there was an area prone to political pressure, it is the allocation of money.  Human nature being what it is, there is no doubt that whoever is appointed to the board of this quango will be subjected to people telephoning them day and night asking for grants or assistance in obtaining grants.  That will be part of their function.</P>
    <P>It has been claimed that board members will have no day to day influence on the disbursement of grants, but they will have a great influence as they will be in charge of making appointments and policy decisions.  These people will be vulnerable to political pressure if appointed by a politician. They will be even more vulnerable to political pressure if they are members of a political party, because loyalty is one of the requirements of membership.  I am not making any accusations against particular people, but Irish political life is studded with occasions on which political patronage to State boards has had unfortunate results.</P>
    <P>The Minister rightly mentioned the importance of continuity on State boards.  I apologise if I am paraphrasing her pejoratively, but she stated that boards always changed every five years when a new Government appointed its own people.  No further evidence is needed that political appointments are made because the appointees are friends of Ministers, politicians or have worked for or donated money to a political party.  No one argues about this.  In an agency such as Enterprise Ireland in which people will be awarded for service to a political party by being appointed to the board, there is no doubt that they will be subjected to political pressures in doing a job which should be utterly independent and impartial.</P>
    <P>The Minister does not intend this to happen and she is not guilty of such practice.  However, we are legislating for her successors.  This Bill will not be changed in five years to facilitate another Minister.  We are legislating for the Minister's successors over the next 20, 30 and 40 years and for potential abuse.  We should be setting out principles which will be established for other semiState bodies.  Unfortunately, we are not doing so. We are adopting the same pattern as before &mdash; giving to political parties the right of patronage, which will be abused.</P>
    <P>I have been in this House quite a long time and I apologise for repeating things I have said over the years.  However, Ministers of all parties have repeatedly come into the House and said that <Col N="1471" /> they understand what we are saying about political patronage but it is not going to happen this time.  Invariably, on the occasions when Ministers protest the loudest that it will not happen in a particular agency, the most obvious political nominee is appointed.  That is not satisfactory, nor is it satisfactory to say that it is not the intention. I hope the Minister will take an initiative to remove agencies such as this from political control and consider a model such as the EPA, which she ably introduced some years ago.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator makes many valid points.  The difference between this board and the EPA board is that the latter was an executive board &mdash; it comprised full-time executives.  I put a mechanism in place which removed the Minister. The Minister had to approve the appointments but that was after an independent selection procedure, three names being proposed for each position.  Having left office, I regretted that all five appointees to the first EPA board came from the public sector.  That is not to take from any of the outstanding individuals appointed but I thought it a bad precedent that when establishing the Environmental Protection Agency and trying to get the private sector to focus on the need to care for the environment, all of the EPA's executives came from the public sector.  There may have been reasons for that other than the Minister of the day making such a decision.  Many private sector people are not interested in these positions because of the remuneration.  That is the difference.</P>
      <P>I would like to find a procedure which comes between our system and the American system. Not many people would subject themselves to an American style process whereby every nominee had to go before an Oireachtas committee and was only paid £3,000, £4,000 or £5,000 per year. In the case of an appointment I was making I tried to choose someone identified with another party, not Fianna Fáil, who I thought would make an outstanding board member.  I spent four weeks trying to persuade this person to accept the nomination, but the answer was no. It is difficult to get people from the private sector to accept these nominations because of the time factor, the invasion of privacy and all of the matters in the public domain for many years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a limited capacity to lobby because of the evaluation process in all these agencies.  They must carry out cost-benefit analyses before putting proposals to the board.  That is an independent procedure which, in the case of IDA Ireland, is often carried out by outside people.  There is an IDA Ireland evaluation sub-committee which includes the executives dealing with the project. Then there is the board, my Department and the Department of Finance.  That is only when the threshold is over £4 million, but we cannot legislate for honesty.  This is one of the difficulties in the public domain.  No matter how many rules and regulations are inserted there is nothing to <Col N="1472" /> stop a member or a number of board members from being dishonest, although they would require considerable influence as the consent of a large number of members would be needed to have a suspect matter ratified.</P>
    <P>Board appointments have improved in recent years.  The vast majority of appointments made by my predecessor, Deputy Richard Bruton, and the ones I have examined as the need for replacements arose, were very good, by and large.  I do not know if the system the Senator suggested worked.  It did in some Departments but I am not certain it operated in the then Department of Enterprise and Employment.  The politics of many of the people appointed by my predecessor would not be known to me.</P>
    <P>The Government is determined to privatise as many State companies as possible.  A number of boards under the aegis of my Department will soon be obsolete because the activities they oversee will no longer be in State control.  That is my ambition and it is well known.  The capacity for board appointments will be drastically restricted in the life of this Government.  It has already decided to privatise ACC, ICC, Cablelink and Telecom Éireann and there are a number of other matters the Government has discussed recently. When the Government finishes its term of office, there will probably be so few boards left that the issue might not even arise.</P>
    <P>The Senator made a valid point about ensuring people of high calibre are appointed.  On the other hand, people should not be excluded because they have been involved in politics.  The Government recently decided to appoint the former Tánaiste, John Wilson, to chair the new commission to examine the concerns of victims of violence.  He was an outstanding choice.  He has never been ambivalent as regards violence and he also has a great deal of political experience. There are other people who have served in politics, such as Senator Ross and Senator Quinn &mdash; who has vast experience of business &mdash; who would make fantastic members of boards.  I would not like for them to be excluded because their politics were Independent, Fine Gael or whatever. That would be unfair.  It is a question of trying to obtain people with experience.  Amendment No. 8a assists in this in that it attempts to bring people with experience to Enterprise Ireland.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister seems to say that there will be fewer State bodies in future and that, while the problem may not be solved, Senator Ross's concerns will be taken into account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Regarding section 9(3), I congratulate the Minister on what I regard as good management practice in insisting that the chief executive be a member of the board.  That is correct.  I believe legislation will shortly come before the House which plans to debar the chief executive from being on the board.  I hope the Minister's action will set a precedent to ensure that does not happen <Col N="1473" /> in future.  Perhaps we might discuss this on a future occasion.</P>
    <P>I have another suggestion to make under section 9(10) where there is room for one more provision.  There would be widespread public support for a provision to ensure board members of State companies were required to provide a tax clearance certificate.  I do not believe it has been suggested before.  It would be a reassurance as to the suitability of board members and one which is regrettably necessary in current circumstances. There is an opportunity to do it under this section by adding to the causes for disqualification as a board member the failure to supply a tax clearance certificate.  There are other places in the Bill where it could be done but the important thing is that it be done somewhere in the Bill.  The underlying principle behind the suggestion is well established.  People supplying goods or services to the State must do it, so why should it not also be required of board members?  It might hasten the day when Deputies and Senators must provide tax clearance certificates but I do not believe anyone could object.  It is the least the public could expect from us and I put it as a suggestion to the Minister for it to be added to section 9(10).</P>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>While I accept some of the points made by Senator Ross about practices in the past, people who serve on State boards do so as a public service.  It must be recognised that the service they provide is very good.  I do not know if the Senator has served on State boards but I served one term on Galway County Enterprise Board.  It surprised me how much the board worked together regardless of political considerations or leanings.  I am not aware that any political pressure was brought to bear on any member of the board in terms of making decisions.  The majority of people who serve on boards are hard working, take their appointments seriously and do their best for the people they serve.</P>
      <P>I commend Senator Quinn's suggestion about tax clearance certificates.  However, it can often happen that a person may not be able to provide a tax clearance certificate in the short time between accepting an appointment and taking it up.  For example, if a person paying tax under the PAYE system or a person making a reconciliation at the end of the year is in dispute with the Revenue Commissioners about medical or other expenses, it may prevent them obtaining a tax clearance certificate.  While I support the spirit of Senator Quinn's suggestion, good people may be unable to accept State appointments because of administrative difficulties with their tax returns.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Quinn's suggestion is excellent and I am sure the Minister would readily agree to it because it is in keeping with her ethos and general political beliefs.  If politicians and others in the service of the State are required to have a tax clearance certificate, it should also be required of people who serve on State boards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I agree with what the Minister said about not <Col N="1474" /> excluding political people.  Some excellent people have served and are still serving in political life.  I am sure the former Tánaiste and Deputy, John Wilson, will prove to be an excellent choice in the capacity for which he has been chosen.  I know Deputy John Bruton, in making appointments in the past, appointed a member of the majority party in the current Government to a certain board, as well as one or two others known to be non-political or whose politics would not have been known.</P>
    <P>I thank the Minister for accepting Senator Costello's excellent amendment because for the first time something proper and definite is being done.  While none of us wishes to delve into the past, given all that is alleged to have happened regarding passports, licences and planning permissions, the Minister has started out on a correct road and I compliment her for doing so.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Many good suggestions have been made by Senators Quinn and Ross concerning this section.  It is appropriate that standards be set in the public sector and in public office, regardless of whether it be the Oireachtas, local authorities or boards established by statute.  The principle should be extended to all those bodies as far as is practicable.  I support the idea of a tax clearance certificate as a requirement of appointment to the 12 places on the board of the new agency.</P>
      <P>I notice that politicians are specifically disqualified. In fact, two categories of people are disqualified. Section 9 disqualifies people who make a composition or arrangement with creditors, who are adjudged bankrupt, who are convicted of an indictable offence, or who are convicted of an offence involving fraud or dishonesty.  Section 12 refers to elected politicians.  An elected politician is deemed suspect with regard to serving on any body.  A Member of the Seanad, therefore, is not allowed to serve on these boards.  The same applies to a member of a local authority, although we are not discussing that section.  Legislation now disqualifies members of one profession, politicians, from serving on State bodies.  The only other category accorded the same treatment is that of fraudsters and criminals.  That is an unusual anomaly.</P>
      <P>We are gradually moving towards greater transparency in public office.  Politicians are obliged to declare gifts, donations and so forth. The public sector is the only sector where there is a degree of transparency although there are many areas in the private sector where such transparency would be desirable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Members of the board are accountable to the Minister and to the Oireachtas.  It is important that there is accountability in the system and that when a board is established the relevant Minister is responsible for it.  Under this legislation, the Minister will be obliged to make an annual report and to account for the activities of the board.  The Minister has also accepted, on the basis of my amendment, that the board, once established, <Col N="1475" /> cannot be interfered with unless objective reasons are put forward.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a possibility that this discussion could go in the wrong direction.  We must acknowledge that many people in society, who are members of political parties in many instances, are prepared to give outstanding service to the State for no reward and for no other reason than they wish to improve the lot of their fellow citizens.  It is now difficult to find people who are prepared to serve even though Ireland has a proud tradition of producing such people. There is nothing wrong with appointing members of political parties to State boards.  Every party has members who are people of quality and experience, people who would be regarded as desirable for appointment to such boards.</P>
      <P>County councillors are referred to in section 12 but the issue is relevant to this section.  I have always held the view that county councillors should not be precluded from membership of State boards; I even successfully moved an amendment to that effect in the context of other legislation.  However, in this instance and in instances where large sums of money are disbursed and where key strategic decisions are made as to where industries will be located, it is appropriate that county councillors should not be involved.  There is a clear potential conflict of interest between what would be the county councillor's local interest and the national interest to be served by the board.  In that context, it is right that such an exclusion operates.</P>
      <P>In previous legislation to establish the National Heritage Council such an exclusion was proposed but it was amended to permit the selection of county councillors.  There is a great deal of expertise and experience among county councillors and many of them are good people who can serve the State at that level.</P>
      <P>Recent controversies could lead to concern on the part of private citizens who have built successful businesses and who choose to serve the State that they might find their names in newspapers. While this might sometimes be appropriate in certain instances because of improper activities, the exposure private citizens leave themselves and their families open to when they become members of State boards can be worrying.</P>
      <P>It would be wrong to limit legislation to the extent that people who are members of political parties or who have other affiliations should be disqualified from participation on State boards by virtue of those affiliations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Quinn made a valid point about tax clearance certificates.  Ideally, everybody who is appointed to a State board, every Member of the Oireachtas and every member of a local authority should have their tax affairs in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Government has already said, in the context of the proposed permanent public ethics commission, that every Member of the <Col N="1476" /> Oireachtas should be required to have a tax clearance certificate.  However, we have encountered legal difficulties with that requirement and we are taking legal advice on its constitutionality and when it should come into effect, pre-election or at some time after an election.  There are many difficulties in relation to this issue.  For that and other reasons it can best be dealt with in the context of the proposed legislation.</P>
    <P>It is the Government's intention that when it has finalised its preliminary view on this matter, it will be sent to an all-party forum.  Clearly we must proceed in this area on an all-party basis. The appointment of persons to public bodies and State boards should probably be dealt with on the same basis.  We cannot impose a requirement on people appointed to State boards which we do not impose on ourselves as Members of the Oireachtas.  The Taoiseach required all Members of the Cabinet to show him that their tax affairs were in order.  That was a good precedent and it should be widened.  However, there are constitutional aspects with regard to who can and cannot stand for office which must be resolved.</P>
    <P>Perhaps Senator Quinn's objective could be dealt with in the context of the public ethics legislation, which could also deal with members of State boards.  I will consider the Senator's suggestion before introducing the legislation in the Dáil but I wish to take legal advice on how it might work.</P>
    <P>Senator Cox made a number of valid points. One might be a compliant taxpayer, whether one is a PAYE worker or self-employed &mdash; although there is an assumption that if one is self-employed one is not compliant, which is unfair &mdash; and be in dispute with the Revenue Commissioners over medical expenses or other such matters.  I do not wish to be unreasonable but I accept Senator Quinn's point and I will examine it before the Bill is brought before the Dáil.  In any event, it probably can be dealt with in the context of the proposed new ethics requirements for public office.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 10.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 9:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (1), line 1, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 10:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (2), line 3, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 11:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (2), line 4, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1477" /> Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 12:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (3), line 6, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 13:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (3), line 7, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 14:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (4), line 11, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 15:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (4), line 12, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 16:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (4), line 15, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 17 not moved.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 10, as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister gave a fair answer to the point I raised with regard to tax clearance certificates.</P>
      <P>I am concerned about section 10(4) which provides that the chairman can be reappointed indefinitely at five year intervals.  That is not a good idea.  The Minister said earlier that the term of a member of a board should probably be limited to ten years.  The term of office of chairman should also be limited to ten years or two terms of five years.  It is true that a chairman could be so excellent that there would be a great temptation to continue to reappoint her or him.  However, this temptation should be resisted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When I was young the priests used to warn us to stay away from occasions of sin.  I wish to remove a future Minister from such an occasion of sin by removing his or her power to continue to reappoint a chairman simply because the chairman has been there for a long time.  However excellent a chairperson, after a certain length of time, the chair comes to be seen as a personal fiefdom.  By the end of ten years the chairperson will have made all the contribution he or she is likely to make.  It is then time for the organisation to have new blood at the top and for the chairperson to move <Col N="1478" /> on to new challenges.  The chairperson's tenure should be limited to two terms of five years.  Perhaps the Minister would consider that at the next Stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>In order to expedite matters I will consider this.  The Senator makes a valid case. Any Minister who lasts for ten continuous years deserves a few occasions of sin.  I do not know of any Minister who held the same portfolio for ten years.  The Senator is right.  Ten years is sufficient. If the chairperson has been outstanding many other bodies will require his or her services.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 11.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 18:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (2), line 19, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 19:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (4)(<i>a</i>), line 23, to delete &ldquo;the chairman of&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;the chairperson of&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 20:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (4)<i>(a),</i> line 23, to delete &ldquo;be the chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;be the chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 21:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (4)<i>(b),</i> line 25, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 22:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (4)<i>(b),</i> line 26, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 23:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (4)<i>(b),</i> line 28, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1479" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 24:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (5), line 30, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 25:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (5), line 34, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 11, as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the vigilance of the Cathaoirleach will prevent anything being slipped through.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Dardis can be assured of that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I draw the Minister's attention to section 11(3) which refers to the proposed quorum for the board.  On a board of 12 members the proposed quorum of three is too small.  Although I have not experienced it myself, some State boards have had difficulties in this regard.  A quorum of three could consist of the chairperson, the chief executive and just one other member.  The minimum for a quorum should be four.  The difficulty in providing a quorum stems from the problem of physically assembling the required number. So, I suggest a virtual meeting.  I believe a Cabinet decision can be taken following discussions by telephone.  Such an approach is sometimes necessary and I would like to see a provision to allow for decisions to be taken in this way written into the Bill.  I am sure a method could be found to legislate for such virtual meetings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Quinn.  Five might be a better number for a quorum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator Quinn.  A quorum should be, at a minimum, a third rather than a quarter of the board.  The number for a quorum should be four.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senators have made valid suggestions.  As a matter of interest, there is no quorum for a Cabinet meeting.  Telephone, or <i>in corporeal</i> meetings are provided for in the Bill.  I agree that five is a reasonable number for a quorum, particularly as emergency decisions can be taken at an <i>in corporeal,</i> or telephone, meeting. I will bring forward an amendment to that effect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree that a quorum should consist of at least a third of the board but five would in fact be better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>Otherwise it might be all women.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1480" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Indeed, a larger quorum will ensure an more equitable balance.  The board will do important work and will spend large amounts of money.  It is advisable that a reasonable number of members attend each meeting.</P>
      <P>Section 11(1) states that &ldquo;The Board shall hold such and as many meetings as may be necessary for the performance of its functions.&rdquo;.  It would be useful for the Minister to indicate a minimum number of meetings.  A monthly meeting would be normal and others would be called where necessary.  The board would obviously determine the number of meetings held but the Minister might set a minimum number.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>In the case of some State boards it is necessary to limit the number of their meetings. They often tend to meet too frequently in my opinion.  I might be tempted to set a maximum number of meetings.  However, that would not be a good idea.  A good board with an effective chairperson will call meetings when necessary.  I would not like the legislation to interfere with the board unduly.  It should be given as much freedom as possible in operational matters and I am not inclined to set down a requisite number of meetings.</P>
      <P>My officials have corrected something I said earlier.  I am told that <i>in corporeal</i> meetings are not excluded but they must check legally if they are specifically included.  I will have that matter clarified before I come back to the House.</P>
      <P>The board must approve all decisions relating to grant aid and so on, even those which come below the threshold which requires Government approval.  That would require, in times of economic boom, frequent meetings.  The existing board meets on average 11 times a year.  Boards of that kind generally meet once a month except for the month of August.  I presume that the people appointed to the board will be busy and businesslike and will hold the necessary number of meetings and no more.</P>
      <P>I ask the Seanad to accept section 11 with the change: that the quorum shall be five.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the principle is not applied to the Seanad because it might create difficulties.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 12.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 26, 27 and 34 are related and may be discussed together.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 26:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (1)(b), line 42, to delete &ldquo;a House&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;either House&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>These amendments substitute &ldquo;either House&rdquo; which is the appropriate phrase.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1481" /> Government amendment No. 27:</P>
    <P>In page 11, subsection (2), line 7, to delete &ldquo;a House&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;either House&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: That section 12, as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>You raised the point, a Chathaoirligh, of county councillors and membership of the board.  The Minister indicated at an earlier stage that she might have something to say about that. Section 12(3) provides that a member of a local authority shall be disqualified from becoming a member of the board.  This is appropriate in this instance because there is a potential conflict of interest.  However, as a general principle, it is desirable that members of local authorities should not be excluded.  There is a precedent for the amendment of legislation to specifically allow members of local authorities to sit on the boards of several State owned companies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator Dardis.  There is potential for conflict in this instance but, as a general principle, it is not constitutional to automatically exclude someone because of membership of any group.  The Minister said earlier that people with political experience should not necessarily be excluded.  We concurred with that and it should be borne in mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree that serving politicians should not be automatically excluded where appropriate, particularly in policy related areas. It is the job of a politician to decide policy. However, in relation to the daily running of State organisations and operational matters, with which this board will be charged, it would be wrong to appoint a politician who would clearly have a conflict of interest because of duality of responsibility to those who elect us &mdash; in the case of Members of this House, councillors or university graduates, and in the case of the Members of the other House, the people who directly elect them on a constituency basis.</P>
      <P>For example, if a company in a certain constituency is about to close and should not be supported because it will never be commercially viable, it would be hard for a politician on the board of this agency to distinguish between their representational role and their national responsibility to an organisation with a responsibility to disperse public money.  This would put a politician in a difficult and unfair position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is important that people overseas who deal with these agencies and ask whether matters are conducted on a political basis know that the decisions of our industrial development agencies to give substantial amounts of taxpayers' money are made on a purely independent basis and that there is no taint of party or independent politics attached.  It is a difficult position for a politician to be in and therefore it is better to exclude not just Members of the Oireachtas but also members <Col N="1482" /> of local authorities.  It would be wrong to include one category of politician and exclude another.  It is better to treat politicians at local and national level on the same basis as far as this agency is concerned.</P>
    <P>I accept the need to involve local politicians more in national affairs.  Government is over-centralised and there should be more decentralisation. Politicians are involved at a local level in regional authorities, health boards and other bodies. We need to find a more fulfilling role at local government level for members of local authorities. However, this is not the appropriate agency for local authority membership.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 13.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 28, 35 and 36 are related and may be discussed together. Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 28:</P>
      <P>In page 11, subsection (4), line 21, after &ldquo;Board&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;and the board of Forfás&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment ensures that the chief executive of Enterprise Ireland, like the chief executive of the IDA is an <i>ex officio</i> member of the board of Forfás.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 13, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 14.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 29:</P>
      <P>In page 11, subsection (7), line 41, after &ldquo;time&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;for stated reasons&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 30:</P>
      <P>In page 12, subsection (9), line 1, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 14, as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 14(6) states &ldquo;A committee may include persons who are not members of the Board or staff of the Agency&rdquo;.  What type of person is envisaged under this subsection?  What type of functions will they carry out and will they be remunerated?  Will there be a proliferation of committees with or without personnel from the agency or board?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>This provision could include outside consultants or experts who are drafted in to help the agency with a particular task.  The person <Col N="1483" /> may not necessarily be a member of the board or the staff of the agency.  Agencies frequently use outside expertise to deal with issues.  I know of one agency which recently drafted in expertise from abroad to advise them on a certain matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the establishment of a committee be necessary in such circumstances?  Normally consultants are drafted in to compile reports or give advice.  However, if committees are established using outside personnel presumably they will use staff from the agency.  Will these be standing committees which perform specific functions or are they intended for a remote contingency?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 14 provides that the board may establish committees to assist it in carrying out its functions.  However, in the IDA projects are decided on by an evaluation committee. The board of Enterprise Ireland may decide to support companies in new or changing sectors and it may need some expertise to help it evaluate projects.  There may be a gap in the board's competency or it may need just one person to sit on a committee rather than a team of consultants. That person may be paid.  We must give the board flexibility.</P>
      <P>This section ensures the board organises its affairs so that it is not debarred from acquiring expertise to allow it to make the appropriate decisions.  For example, if the agency is helping a company in a new sector of which it has little or no experience, it may be necessary to draft in someone with experience of the research and development area in other countries.  The board does not have to establish committees &mdash; the section states that the board &ldquo;may&rdquo; establish committees, not &ldquo;shall&rdquo;.  The agency will establish them on the basis of the need to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I just had the mischievous thought that it might be possible to have a county councillor on the committee because they would not be precluded by the legislation.  It is appropriate that the board should go outside its confines to find expertise that otherwise might not be available to it.  In a rapidly changing business environment, that is desirable.  Section 21 allows the board to appoint consultants as it considers necessary for the performance of its functions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a useful and necessary inclusion in the Bill.  We should certainly allow the board to have that flexibility, for whatever reason.  It may be that the board feels it is short of expertise; it may concern a specific subject area or it may be to bring a group of industrialists together to advise the board.  I have seen a case in the past where the IDA, on an <i>ad hoc</i> basis, brought together a group of industrialists and it was very useful.  We should not tie the board; I agree with this inclusion.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1484" /> SECTION 15.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 15 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am in full agreement about the need to legislate concerning conflicts of interest, and it is right to do so here.  However, I am concerned about some of the terms used, in particular, the term &ldquo;household&rdquo; in section 15(2)(a), (b), (c) and (d).  I am sorry Senator Norris is not here - and if it was not Bloomsday I am sure he would have been &mdash; because he would have raised some humour from this section.  In the old days the term was used to include even the domestic servants in a household but I suspect that something more modern is envisaged here.</P>
      <P>In this case we are, no doubt, contemplating the establishment of couples who are living together outside marriage.  That is the reason we are using the word &ldquo;household&rdquo;.  I have no problem with legislation for that but I wonder if we are not approaching the matter in a sloppy manner.</P>
      <P>Shortly after I was elected to the House I tabled an amendment to the Unfair Dismissals Bill seeking that age should be included as a reason for regarding a dismissal as unfair.  A number of other amendments were tabled at the same time.  The Minister of the day was not able to accept the other amendments but said that the word &ldquo;age&rdquo; could easily be defined.  Someone is an exact age because we know the day they were born, but other terms were not easily accepted at that stage.</P>
      <P>I have great difficulty with the word &ldquo;household&rdquo;. How will it be defined?  Marriage is a certified fact and is a black and white matter but at what point are two people judged to be part of one household?  It could well be that two people are living together most of the time, but one of them might keep a home of his or her own.  In such a situation that person is likely to have a considerable amount of money and might be the very sort of person who would be involved in the kind of conflict of interest we are concerned about.</P>
      <P>While I can see the problem I do not have an answer to it.  Are we to have special household police who will go around trying to see if people are actually living together within the meaning of the Bill?  Obviously not, but what are we trying to achieve by putting in a term that may be contentious and may pose legal difficulty in the future?  If we want to make sure the Bill is tight and will avoid problems in the future, perhaps the Minister could consider whether &ldquo;household&rdquo; is the correct term to use.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I share Senator Quinn's concern.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In fact, this concern was expressed on our behalf to the parliamentary draftsman who could not come up with a better form of words.  I would be open to any suggestion that would be more appropriate.  The term &ldquo;household&rdquo; is used to cover what the Senator said, people living <Col N="1485" /> together who are not what could be described as a family under the meaning of family as we understand it legally.  That is one of the difficulties. If the Senator had a better word I might be prepared to accept it, but he has the same difficulty and the parliamentary draftsman had no alternative word either.</P>
    <P>It is important, however, that we do not exclude cases where two people are living together.  It would clearly be unfair to treat them on a different basis to people who are married to each other.  That is why the wording is in this form.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 16.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 31:</P>
    <P>In page 13, subsection (1), line 25, to delete &ldquo;paragraph&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;subsection&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a purely technical amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 16, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 17.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that amendment No. 32 is being accepted.  It has already been discussed with amendment No. 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 32:</P>
      <P>In page 14, subsection (2)(a), line 5, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Senator spotted all of them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the first amendment I have accepted from Senator Costello.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>It is like the cuckoo; is this a record?</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 17, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 18.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 33 is in the name of Senator Costello.  The Government has also tabled this amendment.  I call on Senator Costello to move this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 33:</P>
      <P>In page 14, subsection (4)(c), line 31, to delete &ldquo;the said&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I was not aware that the Government had also tabled this amendment.  As we are all in agreement shall we leave it at that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1486" /> Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 34:</P>
    <P>In page 14, subsection (5), line 42, to delete &ldquo;a House&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;either House&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 18, as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to make a point that applies not only to the appointment of staff as provided for in this section but also to the holding of property as referred to in section 24.  Forfás was established in 1993 and it included what I think was quite an innovative and useful idea; Forfás would be the employer of record and would second staff as necessary to the different agencies under its aegis.  This ensured a certain consistency of approach and also made possible a flow of talent between the different agencies involved.  It was very worthwhile.</P>
      <P>There were advantages in Forbairt's holding property rather than the individual agencies doing so.  Nowadays, managing property involves highly specialised expertise.  It makes sense &mdash; and it made sense in 1993 &mdash; to concentrate that expertise in one agency rather than in several.  It also allowed the subsidiary agencies to concentrate on their real jobs rather than becoming too involved with housekeeping.</P>
      <P>However, the ink was hardly dry on that legislation before the subsidiary agencies began lobbying to undo it.  Within one year amending legislation was passed allowing the IDA to hold property directly.  I suggest this Bill is continuing the process.  In my view the original approach was right and the successful attempts to undermine it are nothing more than empire building by each agency.  We should resist that sort of empire building.  I am critical of these sections of the Bill and I urge the Minister to reconsider them.</P>
      <P>We should do anything that encourages State agencies to stick to their knitting.  They should concentrate on the job they are supposed to do. We should view with suspicion any wishes they express to indulge in empire building.  Above all, we should avoid any situation which gives us half of one and half of the other.  That is effectively what is happening here.  I would like the Minister to consider that and see if we can find a solution to avoid the problems that have been created in the past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I support what Senator Quinn said.  Sections 18 and 19 seem to be, as he said, giving scope for an element of empire building. Section 18, by its terms, would seem to allow for selective recruitment.  An initial bias would appear to have been given to one of the agencies in relation to the secondment of staff.  If all staff are seconded on an equal basis that is good. However, if there is an imbalance, which seems to be the case according to sections 18 and 19, a new agency will reflect that imbalance.  The new <Col N="1487" /> roles of An Bord Tráchtála and Forbairt will not be reflected in the degree of integration the Minister wants.  Staff will be seconded to reflect the development side of indigenous industry and to reflect the export side of the same indigenous industry.  These sections need reworking to ensure that we get fair secondment of staff to the new agency and that we get a definite date from which the agency will operate.  The Minister should include a date for the establishment of the agency in the legislation.  I am concerned about seconding and recruitment of staff as there may be a bias in the representation of one of the two agencies in the secondment process.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>When Forfás and Forbairt were being established after the Culliton report there were negotiations on where staff and property would go.  In order to get on with the work of establishing agencies and to leave the property and staff issues to be dealt with by negotiation, Forfás was put in charge of the whole operation because it was an umbrella organisation.  Forfás's role is a policy one and it remains the employer of the staff of An Bord Tráchtála and Forbairt to this day, which may continue.  The staff of those two bodies which belong to the staff of Forfás will be seconded to the new agency, Enterprise Ireland, just as IDA staff are on secondment from Forfás.  Of Forfás's £10.5 million budget, £9.5 million goes on staff pay, superannuation and so on.</P>
      <P>We may not change that arrangement but this Bill provides that the Minister can allocate staff to the agencies by ministerial order but that will only be done after negotiation and in agreement with staff associations.  We have not reached agreement yet because there are ongoing issues to be resolved.  Sensitive matters must be handled delicately and, as I said in the Dáil, there will be no forced redundancies.  If there is staff superfluous to the requirements of Enterprise Ireland, a voluntary redundancy package will be set up and that will all be agreed with the staff associations. I will only bring in a ministerial order transferring staff if I feel that is the most effective way forward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Regarding property, when Forfás, Forbairt and IDA Ireland were established, Forbairt and the IDA were one organisation.  Property belonged to that organisation but it was being divided.  It was felt that the property could not be divided and the majority of it was subsequently allocated to IDA Ireland.  Use of the property portfolio is an important function of the agencies.  That is not to say I want them to have a host of properties around the country.  I want them to keep their property interests to a minimum.  The IDA has made substantial money from disposing of property in recent years.  We do not want taxpayers' money tied up in properties and I am always happy to hear of an inward investor buying property as opposed to leasing it.  That indicates that taxpayers' money will be released for other projects and it beds the enterprise down in Ireland.  If <Col N="1488" /> the property is bought it means the organisation intends to stay.</P>
    <P>The property interests of Enterprise Ireland and the IDA are minimalist.  Many advance factories are now being provided through private funding through BES schemes under Finance Act designations, though with IDA approval, and that will continue.  Those agencies hold property for an undue length of time only in exceptional cases. It is important that those agencies allocating the grants and supporting enterprises have the power to make decisions about the properties they own.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 19.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 19 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>What discussions has the Minister had with the staff associations of An Bord Tráchtála and Forbairt?  FÁS will also be affected, though it has not been mentioned yet in the debate, because part of its functions will be taken over by the new agency.  What discussions has the Minister had regarding secondment, recruitment and remuneration of new employees?  What discussions has she had regarding the functions of these organisations?  The Bill seems to be biased in favour of Forbairt and the developmental aspect, which is reflected in the title Enterprise Ireland.  This is intended to develop industry and business, not export and marketing.</P>
      <P>Section 19 states:</P>
      <P>A person seconded from Forfás . to the Agency who is on such secondment immediately before the commencement of this section, shall cease to be a member of the staff of Forfás and shall become a member of the staff of the Agency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am not suggesting that the new chief executive officer, who will be an ex-member of one of the organisations, will be in a position to second as many staff as he thinks appropriate prior to a commencement date.  This could go on for a period of time.  If the chief executive officer was a member of Forbairt we could find that he seconds staff from that body because he knows them. Before the new agency commences operation as an employment agency it could have an imbalance of Forbairt staff who are trained for a particular area of industry and not for the export market.  There is a perceived danger that this section has the potential to reflect a bias, and that is why I want to know what talks the Minister has had with staff representatives in both bodies to assuage their fears about transfers, secondment and recruitment.  The Minister said she wants to see this grow organically and that there may be a transfer of powers and staff to this agency.  If a date is not specified the issue will be left in the air and staff in both organisations will not know what is happening.  Will the Minister reconsider this issue by giving of a reasonable date, for <Col N="1489" /> example, one near the end of the year or in a number of months time, for the commencement of section 19(4)?</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I had meetings with all representatives of staff in Forbairt, An Bord Tráchtála and FÁS.  The restructuring task force established to bring about the new structures consisted of representatives of Forbairt, FÁS, Forfás and An Bord Tráchtála and meetings were held between it and the staff every three weeks over the past number of months.</P>
      <P>This will not come into effect until all the pieces are put in place.  We want to continue consulting with the staff.  Nobody's conditions of employment will be worsened and there will be no forced redundancies.  The staff will continue as staff of Forfás and be seconded to the agency which will hopefully be established in early July subsequent to the Oireachtas passing the legislation - I want it established as quickly as possible. Regarding the day to day issues about which Senator Costello spoke, it is not a matter for a Minister to decide the level of remuneration X or Y will receive.  This is a matter for the chief executive.  I was anxious to have the chief executive designate in place at this stage so that he can prepare and discuss with staff associations the implications of the change.  I did not want to leave this until the legislation was passed.  There is also a chairman designate who with the chief executive designate is working closely with staff to put the structures in place so that when Enterprise Ireland comes into effect as much work as possible will have been done.  The day to day negotiations regarding who goes where and who is in charge of different areas will be a matter for the person charged with running the agency, its new board and its chief executive.</P>
      <P>The focus on company development, previously undertaken by Forbairt, is in the context of exports.  Companies cannot be assisted unless they are assisted in an export context as we have a very small market of 3.5 million people.  We must trade 140 per cent of GNP and export up to 85 per cent of what we produce.  There is no point in helping companies unless we assist them in an export context and compete in the very large and competitive global marketplace.</P>
      <P>The purpose of establishing Enterprise Ireland is to co-ordinate the structures so as to allow a clearer focus.  Enterprise Ireland is about helping companies compete in the global marketplace, nothing else.  I want the new structure to focus on the needs of Irish industry, encourage more companies to diversify and get out of traditional sectors where they are no longer competitive, encourage them into other export markets and not be so dependent in particular on the UK. Dependence on the UK is not good, particularly as the UK will not be joining EMU on 1 January 1999.  At least 40 per cent of exports from SMEs go to the UK market, the figure being much higher in some sectors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We want to encourage Irish companies to invest in research and development.  Last week in <Col N="1490" /> the House I said nearly half of Irish companies invest nothing in research and development. Senator Quinn more than any other Member is aware that failure to get involved in research, development and innovation means a company will not do business or survive.  Research and development is crucial if Irish companies are to produce new products and ideas that are marketable.</P>
    <P>I also want companies to get involved in human resource development.  Irish companies are very bad at investing in staff training.  Time and again I visit multinational companies and have not yet come across one which does not have a human resources manager and a large human resource division relative to the size of the operation.  Why is this the case?  These companies recognise that part of their success results from investing in training and retraining their staff.  Half of those at work today will still be at work in 2020. However, they certainly will not be doing the same job and if they are they will not be doing it in the same way.</P>
    <P>Investment in research, training of the workforce and the financial strategy of companies are areas I want the agency to examine when it decides to support particular companies.  Exports will be central to these issues which is why I integrated the structures.  It does not make sense for Forbairt to be supporting the development of a company, An Bord Tráchtála to be helping it sell its exports, FÁS to be helping with training and other help being provided here and there in the context of research and development.  It is a waste of public resources and taxpayers' money.  It means there is no clear focus on the company with every agency claiming its package achieved success.  Alternatively, if a company fails each agency can blame the others.  Even from the point of view of performance it is better to have a structured approach.</P>
    <P>I know Senator Costello is as concerned about the staff as I am.  The staff in these agencies have worked extremely hard.  In the overseas context in particular we can be very proud of the staff of An Bord Tráchtála who are highly professional and who work by and large with very poor resources in comparison to their counterparts from other countries.  Our diplomatic service alone is smaller than the British Embassy in Washington and the same applies to our agencies abroad.  We have a very, very small highly committed staff working on behalf of Ireland.  They do a terrific job and I want to motivate rather than demotivate them.  My dealings and those of my officials with the staff have been from the perspective of motivation rather than seeking to undermine their position or lessen their conditions of employment, something I do not want to happen and which will not happen.  I have given assurances in relation to these issues both here and elsewhere.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 20 to 43, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1491" /> SECTION 44.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 35:</P>
    <P>In page 25, subsection (2), line 32, after &ldquo;other than&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;section 9(3) thereof and&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 36:</P>
    <P>In page 25, between lines 36 and 37, to insert the following subsection:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(4) Section 9(3) of the Act of 1993 is hereby amended by the substitution for &lsquo;and each Agency&rsquo; of &lsquo;, Enterprise Ireland and IDA.&rsquo;.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P>Section 44, as amended, agreed to.</P>
    <P>Section 45 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 46.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 37:</P>
      <P>In page 26, subsection (8), line 43, after &ldquo;time&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;for stated reason&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be useful to clarify this amendment.  Although taken with another amendment which has been accepted, it relates to a different aspect of the board's activity.  It concerns members of committees of the board and not the board itself.  It is not a matter for ministerial sanction but for the sanction of the board. The context of this amendment is somewhat different.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Dardis has made a valid point.  If a board has a member which it does not need and requires somebody from a different sector, one should state the reason.  It is not unacceptable to keep this continuity.  I take the Senator's point that it is not a matter for a Minister. We accepted Senator Costello's earlier amendment in relation to committees so it is right that we keep this continuity and accept this amendment.  I am sorry to disagree with Senator Dardis who is so reasonable.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Finneran) Acting Chairman (Mr. Finneran)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Finneran)</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a correction to the text of amendment No. 38; &ldquo;subsection (10)&rdquo; should read &ldquo;subsection (1)&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 38:</P>
      <P>In page 27, subsection (1), line 1, to delete &ldquo;chairman&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;chairperson&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 46, as amended, agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1492" /> Sections 47 to 49, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 50.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 39:</P>
    <P>In page 29, subsection (1), line 25, to delete &ldquo;, as the case may be,&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>The parliamentary draftsman has advised us to delete the words &ldquo;, as the case may be,&rdquo; as it is completely superfluous to the legislative requirements.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 50, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 51.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a correction to the text of amendment No. 40 and a comma should appear at the end of paragraph (b).</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 40:</P>
      <P>In page 30, to delete lines 7 and 8 and substitute the following paragraph:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(b) in section 31, by the insertion after &lsquo;under&rsquo; of &lsquo;Part III of,&rsquo;&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 40 to 43, inclusive, correct errors in the Bill as printed, although I do not wish to blame the printers.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 41:</P>
      <P>In page 30, paragraph (c), line 10, to delete &ldquo;, 5(2)&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 42:</P>
      <P>In page 30, paragraph (c), line 10, to delete &ldquo;6.&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;6, and&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 43:</P>
      <P>In page 30, between lines 10 and 11, to insert the following paragraph:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(d) in paragraph 5(2) of the Second Schedule, by the insertion after &lsquo;offence&rsquo; of &lsquo;and shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding £1,500,&rsquo;.&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 51, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Schedule agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">TITLE.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 44 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1493" /> Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Title be the Title to the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a sad day that the official language is being removed from the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Title refers to the setting up of the agency to be known as Enterprise Ireland and defines its functions.  Will the Minister assure me that the influence of Enterprise Ireland will be greater than the current set up in seeking to establish industries in areas of greatest need?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I can give an assurance to Senator Mooney.  Since the Government took office we have announced 23,000 new jobs.  Over 70 per cent of those jobs have been in regions outside the Dublin region.  I am particularly keen to ensure the Border counties, including counties Sligo and Leitrim, which are of particular concern to Senator Mooney, get their fair share of investment. In that regard, the visit to Sligo last week by the US Secretary of Commerce, Mr. Daly, to Sligo will be very helpful.</P>
      <P>The Senator may be assured that the priority of the agencies, in accordance with Government policy, is to develop the regions, particularly the more peripheral ones.  We must give people reason to live in the regions because they will not live there if there are no employment and economic possibilities.  This is of great concern to Senator Mooney but we must ensure the companies which are supported are sustainable and viable.  It is a question of marrying the two and trying to achieve the maximum amount of activity throughout Ireland, particularly the regions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister ensure Enterprise Ireland liaises with other Departments, such as the Department of the Environment and Local Government and the Department of Public Enterprise, to ensure a proper infrastructure is put in place in the areas to which she referred in her response?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>The issue of infrastructural development has been on the Cabinet agenda on a number of occasions in recent years.  As the Senator clearly knows, one of the handicaps or obstacles to regional development is access and the infrastructure generally.  I asked my Department to carry out an assessment of each region, to look at their strengths and deficiencies and examine what activities we can promote in the different regions.</P>
      <P>In particular, I am anxious to ensure industries based on technology and telecommunications are located outside the cities because it does not matter where an activity occurs if it is dependent on telecommunications.  An activity which occurs in the most peripheral part of Ireland can be transmitted or transferred to another part of the world in seconds.  Clearly, there are sectors which could be located in peripheral regions and we will try to exploit that as much as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1494" /> The Senator can be assured that the infrastructural deficit is being addressed by the Government and I hope there will be big changes in that areas over the next number of months.  In the context of new EU funding and so on, it is important to promote the deficiencies in the regions.  Senator Costello, like Deputy Broughan, makes the case for Dublin and I represent a Dublin constituency.  It is bad for Ireland and Dublin that so much happens in the capital.  The services in Dublin cannot cope and house prices have risen beyond the reach of most people.  Houses are cheaper in other regions and there is overcapacity in terms of services which are cheaper.  It does not make sense from a demographic point of view that Dublin should act as a hoover.</P>
    <P>It has not been good for unemployment in Dublin.  Notwithstanding all the investment in Dublin, unemployment remains high and it requires a concentrated effort in the unemployment blackspots which I hope to address shortly through the changes coming into effect in September &mdash; the implementation of the employment action plan.</P>
    <P>A different strategy is required for unemployment in Dublin than that which was adopted in the past.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Bill reported with amendments and received for final consideration.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I was under the impression we had only passed Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>We are on Fifth Stage now.</P>
      <P>Discussion can only be held on Report Stage if amendments have been tabled.  However, the contents of the Bill can be discussed on Fifth Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill's establishment of a streamlined approach to business and exports.  The Minister acknowledged we must focus on the fact that Ireland is very exportoriented.</P>
      <P>I took on board the Minister's comments in regard to staff and staff consultation which I consider to be the key to getting Enterprise Ireland up and running.  If that issue is not sensitively dealt with, serious problems could be encountered. The Minister is seeking to unite two important enterprises and professional staff and it is extremely important that all staff recognise they are all getting a fair crack of the whip in terms of appointment, promotion, secondment and the ethos of the new organisation.  I would dread the consequences if the ethos of the new body were to be dominated by one agency over the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1495" /> I hope the Bill does not simply represent a moving around of the deck chairs.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not mention the <i>Titanic.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>It is pointless to move things around unless some function is served by that.  I thank the Minister for accepting my amendments and hope they will improve the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Tánaiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment (Miss Harney) Tánaiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment (Miss Harney)">
      <NameTxt>Tánaiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment (Miss Harney)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Members for their considered contributions and general goodwill towards the establishment of Enterprise Ireland.  I congratulate Senator Costello on having all but three of his amendments accepted, something I may live to regret. Of the 45 amendments tabled on Committee Stage, 16 were in my name and the balance were in Senator Costello's.</P>
      <P>I thank all Members of the House, particularly Members of the Opposition and the Independent Members, for their contributions.  I assure Senator Costello the purpose of the Bill is to create a new dynamic agency with a different approach to industrial policy.  It is hoped that the marriage of the activities of An Bord Tráchtála, the company development activities of Forbairt and much of the services to business aspect of FÁS will be greater than the individual parts of all three.  I do not want to establish a dysfunctional or de-motivated agency, which would clearly be the case if staff were de-motivated.</P>
      <P>We want to bring people together and ensure the people best suited to various tasks are given responsibility for them.  In appointing the board I will be conscious of the need to get dynamic, innovative and enterprising people who will be able to give time to the establishment of the new agency.  The next 12 to 18 months will be the most important for the board and we want to get off to a good start.  That is why I was anxious for the legislation to go through prior to the summer recess.  It is important that staff are made aware of what exactly is involved.</P>
      <P>This proposal has been in existence since the Government took office but it is unusual for a Bill of this kind to reach this stage so soon.  On the last occasion reform occurred, it took almost three years as the process is a slow one.  I appreciate the Opposition's agreement to the Government's request to deal with this Bill and I appreciate the very interesting comments made on it which I will bear in mind.  If the Bill is amended in the other House, we will return to the Seanad with it before 3 July.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate the Minister for the manner in which she dealt with this Bill and for introducing it in the Seanad.  Her acceptance of 24 of Senator Costello's amendments must be something of a record.  The Bill is a good one and is going in the right direction.  A number of points were made which were not tabled as amendments and the Minister promised to consider those.  I <Col N="1496" /> look forward to that and hope that, if they are found useful, the Bill will return to this House in the near future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan" hpid="Mr. Coghlan Mr. Coghlan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with my colleagues in complimenting the Minister on her careful and considered disposition towards the points made in the course of the Committee Stage debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I join in thanking the Minister for her continuing attendance during a prolonged Committee Stage debate this afternoon and I thank her officials for their input.  We hope the Bill will advance the case for investment in, and development of, our indigenous sector.</P>
      <P>I attended a function in Dublin Castle earlier today at which Tesco announced food awards. The evident innovation, energy and youth of the recipients was something to be marvelled at and obviously augurs well for the future.  We hope the new agency will achieve all its objectives.  I was very critical at the time of the break-up of Forbairt, the IDA and Forfás.  The Bill is a step in the right direction.</P>
      <P>I am in awe of Senator Costello's achievement. When I occupied that chair in a previous incarnation, my record was quite lamentable. However, I do not intend to return to that side of the House in the near future.  I thank the Minister for accepting the amendments and for the fact that this is the second major piece of legislation she has initiated in the Seanad, the other being the Environmental Protection Agency Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>A good afternoon's work was achieved in the House today.  I hope the Bill has been strengthened by the amendments we have made.  I thank the Minister for the very open and fair manner in which she dealt with the issues which arose.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Parental Leave Bill, 1998:" RHead="Committee and Remaining Stages">
    <Title>Parental Leave Bill, 1998: Committee and Remaining Stages.</Title>
    <P>SECTION 1.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 3, lines 15 and 16, to delete subsection (2).</P>
      <P>This amendment proposes the deletion of section 1(2) which would allow a derogation until 3 December 1998 in terms of the Bill's operation. The Government appears to claim that this type of derogation already exists but the directive makes it clear that the Commission has no power to issue a derogation of this nature to the Government.  If a member state wishes to defer implementation of the directive, it should state serious reasons for doing so.  However, the Government has not stated any reasons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I presume it is intended to have the Bill passed by the other House before the summer recess. However, it appears the extension the Government <Col N="1497" /> has decided to implement is in breach of the European directive because it has not stated any grounds for it.  No member state has been granted an extension in terms of its implementation.  It appears the operation date of 3 December has been pulled from the air and that the Minister wants another six months for no particular reason.  Serious reasons for the deferral of the implementation of the directive should be stated. The Minister has not stated any reason and, therefore, the subsection should be deleted and the Bill should become law as soon as it is passed by both Houses of the Oireachtas and signed by the President.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand Senator Costello's position but the Bill will introduce a major new scheme.  Ireland might be one of the last countries in Europe to implement the EU directive but, as an employer, I am aware that practical difficulties are involved in setting up the scheme.  The date of 3 December is only a few months away and the delay is not unreasonable from the point of view of employers who must put the structures in place.  I differ from Senator Costello on this matter.  The date of 3 December is practical.</P>
      <P>The Bill states that an employee must give notice of his or her intention to apply for parental leave and an agreement must be drawn up between him or her and the employer.  This will take time to arrange and this breathing space is necessary for employers.  Therefore, I oppose the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Miss M. Wallace) Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Miss M. Wallace)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Miss M. Wallace)</NameTxt>
      <P>The directive has a flexible aspect which means that employers cannot use the directive to prepare for parental leave in their workplaces.  Until the Bill is enacted, the details of the scheme will not be certain.</P>
      <P>The purpose of the deferral of the implementation of the scheme until December is to allow employer organisations to provide information to their members, enable systems to be put in place for the operation of the scheme and enable any regulations to be made which would allow for the reconciliation of the parental leave and <i>force majeure</i> schemes within existing non-statutory schemes of special leave.  It will generally permit the smooth introduction of the scheme.  It would be impractical to have such a new departure in working life brought into effect immediately.  The operative date of 3 December is in full compliance with the terms of the directive.  This has been confirmed to the Department by the EU Commission.</P>
      <P>Question, &ldquo;That the words and figures proposed to be deleted stand&rdquo;, put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
      <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1498" /> SECTION 2.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 4, subsection (1), line 10, after &ldquo;including&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;a member of the Garda Síochána or the Defence Forces or&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The amendment relates to the category of employees who are entitled to parental leave and seeks the specific inclusion of members of the Garda Síochána and the Defence Forces.  In the corresponding definition of employee in the employment equality legislation, members of the Garda Síochána and the Defence Forces are expressly mentioned.  In those circumstances it would be appropriate to specifically refer to them in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>I will accept the amendment.</P>
      <P>Although it may not be necessary to make explicit reference to members of the Garda Síochána and the Defence Forces, it is usual in legislation which defines an employee to make such a reference.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 2, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 3:</P>
      <P>In page 5, between lines 22 and 23, to insert the following new subsection:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(2) Before making a regulation under this Act, the Minister shall consult with persons whom he or she considers to be representative of employers generally and persons whom he or she considers to be representative of employees generally in relation to the regulation.&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment will require the Minister to consult with employer and employee representatives before making regulations under the Bill.  This is in line with the spirit of the EU Directive on Parental Leave and will be of practical use to the Minister in drawing up such regulations.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 3, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 4 and 5 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 4:</P>
      <P>In page 6, subsection (1), line 6, to delete &ldquo;14&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;18&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1499" /> The amendment relates to the entitlement to parental leave.  The Bill as it stands specifies a period extending to 14 working weeks to enable a person to take care of his or her child.  The amendment proposes a move away from the bare minimum period contained in the directive and the extension of the period to 18 weeks.  This would show generosity and is not unreasonable.</P>
    <P>The Bill includes the minimum period specified in the directive but a degree of imagination should be shown in terms of Ireland making a decision to extend the period.  An extra month of unpaid parental leave would recognise the increasingly onerous work required of parents. The Bill should not be viewed as a vehicle to implement the bare minimum of a troublesome legal obligation under a European directive.  This matter should be viewed in a generous fashion and legislators should facilitate parents to fulfil their duties to their children to the best of their ability.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the amendment and favour the inclusion of an 18 week period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senator Costello was serious about this matter, he would have been consistent in his amendments by also referring to section 7.  Perhaps the Senator does not understand what operating a business involves.  It is difficult to manage a small business in peripheral areas such as the west.  While the Bill acknowledges the need to balance family life and assist parents in spending more time with their young children, it would be impossible to manage 18 weeks of parental leave for each parent.  The Bill proposes a period of 14 weeks per parent, giving a total of 28 weeks for both parents.  It would be totally unmanageable to increase the period to 18 weeks for each parent given the current climate and skills shortages. I am the mother of three young children and I am sympathetic to the needs of family and home life but there must be balance.  It is opportunistic to suggest that we should increase the 14 week period to 18 weeks and it is an insult to the Government to suggest we are introducing minimalist legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not propose to accept this amendment.  The parental leave directive stipulates a minimum entitlement of three months parental leave and, bearing in mind the novelty of parental leave in this country, the duration of the leave is set at 14 weeks.  There is already a statutory entitlement to 14 weeks maternity leave with four additional weeks of unpaid maternity leave.  The parental leave will be added to the existing entitlement.  As Senator Cox pointed out, the entitlement is 14 weeks for each parent for each child.  Senator Cox made a further relevant point &mdash; the proposed amendment is at variance with the provision of section 7.  If accepted it would make the Bill internally inconsistent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1500" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not understand why the Minister has a problem with the fact that parental leave has just been introduced.  Could we try not to be so gloomy about it?  The great increase in the number of married women in the workforce is due to the increasing flexibility in working hours and maternity leave and, I said on Second Stage, the State has received a huge economic dividend as a result.</P>
      <P>While we would like a longer period, I congratulate the Minister on the introduction of this legislation which will not be an economic disaster for the State, like everywhere else only the women will take the leave.  We should not look at this as something which will bring the State to its knees.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I am disappointed with the Minister's reply.  This directive has been around since the summer of 1996.  While the previous Government did not have much of an opportunity to introduce it, it is a directive the Minister had to introduce and it has been introduced after most other European countries.</P>
      <P>Parental leave can be taken over a five year period; it need not be taken at the one time.  Child rearing is becoming increasingly difficult and if we examine the statistics of women in the workforce we see there has been a disproportionate number of women entering the workforce in comparison to men &mdash; the ratio is 4:1.</P>
      <P>This is an important matter and we must deal with it on the basis of parental leave, not male or female leave.  As sharing of labour becomes part and parcel of our society, why should there not be a sharing of child care?  As there is a statutory right to paid maternity leave for a 14 week period, with an extra four week period of unpaid leave, I do not see the problem with giving that notional 18 weeks to everyone rather than adopting the minimalist approach indicated in the legislation.</P>
      <P>The fact that there is no amendment to section 7 is an oversight.  I would have expected that, had the Minister accepted this amendment, it would have continued into the next amendment.  This Bill is being taken in the Seanad and the Minister has ample opportunity to deal with amendments before it goes to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>It is important to point out that the period of leave is 14 weeks per parent per child.  I have two children for whom I could take parental leave, a total of 28 weeks before both children are five years old.  If my husband or partner worked in the same business, the company would lose one worker for 14 weeks for each child and then lose the other parent for the same length of time, in addition to maternity leave and four weeks unpaid maternity leave.  This is a strong move in equality legislation and as an employer I refute the need for 18 weeks parental need.</P>
      <P>Question, &ldquo;That the figure proposed to be deleted stand&rdquo;, put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1501" /> Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 5:</P>
      <P>In page 6, lines 8 to 10, to delete subsection (2).</P>
      <P>The subsection reads:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The entitlement to parental leave shall apply only in respect of a child born on or after the 3rd day of June, 1996, or a child in whose case an adoption order has been made on or after that date.&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Deleting that subsection would let the legislation apply irrespective of when the child was born so that leave can be taken at any time up to a period of five years rather than specifying the starting date of 3 June 1996.  That is the day on which the directive was proposed.  I do not see why the operation of leave should be limited to that date. Why can it not state the parent of a child up to the age of five from the time this legislation is passed should be entitled to the provisions of the legislation?  There is a minimalist approach here. Why can it not be more generous?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>The concern shown in this regard bothers me because the last Government had over 12 months to deal with this.  Minister O'Donoghue made it clear this EU directive gave flexibility to each government to introduce legislation within certain parameters.  Backdating the operation of the scheme to 3 June 1996 indicates the flexibility of this Government.  It indicates fairness and I see no merit in the proposed amendment.  If it was so urgent, why did the last Government leave the matter for 12 months without even initiating it?  This Government has initiated it and its thrust is welcome.  I accept the date of the directive was 3 June 1996 and I see no point in going back before that date.  We are fully in compliance with the EU directive in the legislation as drafted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>There are children born in 1993 who could be eligible under this Bill.  The Government has not been generous in the time allowed because when we realise that no payments are allowed to parents on parental leave.  I appeal to the Minister to yield on this issue.  It was fine to backdate the legislation to when the directive was introduced.  If one takes it back five years, children born in 1993 would qualify and many parents would be glad to avail of that provision. I appeal to the Minister to accept the amendment on those grounds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry to pursue the same point again.  However, there must be a recognition that paternal leave will only work if there is sustainable employment.  If companies face a situation in which the parents of children up to the age of five started to take parental leave, there would be applications from parents whose children were born from June 1993 onwards.  If both parents took leave it would amount to 28 weeks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1502" /> The economy is facing tremendous challenges such as the introduction of the euro and the year 2000.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>And high inflation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>There must be a balance between what we do for the family and what we do for business.  The Opposition is incorrect in calling this a minimalist attitude.  Employers must be treated fairly and there is a need for fairness and equity.  I am not only speaking on behalf of employers, but we must run businesses as well as look after children at home.  If businesses do not exist there will be no jobs from which people can stay at home.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>If children are not reared there will be no one to work in those jobs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>This debate reflects the many submissions received by the Department regarding the concerns of employers and employees. The directive on parental leave does not specify any form of retrospection.  We have to balance employers' concerns that people would seek backdated parental leave at the same time.  I am not sure how old Senator Cox's third child is, but the Senator might immediately apply for parental leave for her eldest child and for the other two children immediately thereafter.  She would be entitled to 42 weeks as would her husband.</P>
      <P>There are small firms employing couples with two or three children.  Companies, particularly small companies, were concerned about this.  The Government decided to balance the expectation of parents, especially those referred to by Senator Connor who might expect that this legislation would apply to them, and the concerns of employers about a backlog.  It was decided that parental leave should be given to the parents of children born after 3 June 1996, the date of the adoption of the directive.</P>
      <P>The proposed amendment would create difficulties for employers.  It is not required under the directive and we took the operative date as the balance.  This legislation must apply from 3 June 1998 &mdash; the final operative date.  We are going back two years to 3 June 1996.  It is not usual to backdate legislation.  My child was born in September 1995 when there was no parental leave so I do not qualify.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>We will compromise &mdash; three years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>We are backdating it to six months beyond my child's date of birth.  There are many complications for employers concerning the implementation and the backdating of the legislation.  For those reasons we struck a balance by opting for the date of the directive &mdash; 3 June 1996.</P>
      <P>Question, &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand&rdquo;, put and declared carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1503" /> Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 6:</P>
      <P>In page 6, subsection (3)(a), line 13, to delete &ldquo;5&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;8&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Perhaps I have the Minister this time as the directive refers to eight years as the maximum period. I hope the Minister will not reduce the maximum number of years proposed by the directive.</P>
      <P>The directive states that parental leave should be available to parents up to a maximum of eight years.  In this case the Minister has decided on five years as the maximum period she is going to allow.  Will the Minister extend the period of time for which parental leave is available?  It does not go against any of the points raised by the Minister or Senator Cox on the ability of business to function if parental leave is taken.  Employers should welcome this measure along with parents as it would give them greater flexibility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Only two EU countries have gone for the age of eight, some have gone for less than five years.  Five years is a reasonable period. On Second Stage I was interested in the contribution of Senator O'Toole, who heads the INTO. He stated that five years was too much and that perhaps four was more reasonable.  I respect the views of the Senator, given his position.  Five years of age is a reasonable period and we would be more the exception than the rule in Europe if we extended it to five.  This would further complicate difficulties for employers.</P>
      <P>In Germany only 1 per cent of working men took up their right to parental leave.  The same would apply here where only a small percentage of men would opt to take their leave.  This is a startling statistic which may auger badly for men. The figure may be higher in other countries but it will still be a small percentage of the overall male working population.  Five years of age is reasonable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I am a little left out of this debate as I do not have children to whom parental leave would apply unless there will be a directive on grandparental leave.  I am not yet a grandparent but I do have an interest in this new and welcome provision.  I disagree with the minimalist approach of the Government.  Some Senators, particularly Senator O'Donovan, are being very selective when referring to what is available in Europe.  Ireland rated poorly in the list in the report on the status of women in Ireland.  I cannot see anything wrong with acknowledging the needs of children.  A child is not defined as responsible for his or her actions until seven years of age.  It would be a generous and welcome gesture to increase the age to eight.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the proposal that the age limit be raised to eight years of age.  I am not a parent so I do not have such experience and I am unlikely to be a parent in future.  Nevertheless, I had the opportunity to study sociology, the manner <Col N="1504" /> in which children are influenced and socialised and how this affects them when they become adults.  There is no greater influence on a child than that of their parents.  People who study behavioural science and sociology agree that the most formative years of a child's life are between four and eight.  The Cathaoirleach has experience from the classroom of children and their socialisation. It is important that children have maximum contact with their parents during those formative years up to age eight and it is for that reason I support the amendment.</P>
      <P>There are enormous problems in society with juvenile delinquency and the deviant behaviour of some young people, although it is in many ways no worse in this generation than in others. Much of it can be traced to a lack of contact in formative years between parents and children and a corresponding lack of influence.  We must be conscious of that because it is like making an investment.  People have argued about the economic effects on employers of extending the limit from five to eight years and of paying parents on parental leave.  There is another aspect to it.  We should think in terms of people who do not conform to the norms of society and who cause enormous problems, because these can often be traced to the fact that they did not have adequate contact with their parents.  It is a major problem which has severe economic and social consequences. The debate so far seems to have lost sight of that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I object strongly to what Senator Connor has said unless he can prove that some of our social and economic problems are as a result of children suffering a lack of parental contact.  It seems to suggest that the phenomenon of women going out to work and not being at home is one of the reasons for a higher rate of crime.  I assume that is not what he meant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not and the Senator knows that.  The Senator is trying to deliberately misrepresent me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not trying to misrepresent the Senator but his points needed clarification.</P>
      <P>On the issue of extending the age limit from five to eight, most children attend school for the first time between the ages of four and five. However, I have great sympathy for the amendment although I am not in a position to support it.  Perhaps the Minister of State might address the issue with the Minister, Deputy O'Donoghue, with a view to seeking a compromise.  Extending the limit to seven may, perhaps, make matters easier for employers.  However, it creates a problem for employers in terms of keeping records.  If a person can avail of 14 weeks' leave up to age seven for their child, it would be necessary for employers to keep more records thus potentially opening the system to greater abuse.  As a parent, I would sympathise with the extension of the limit to seven and I ask the Minister of State to consider it at a later stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1505" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>It is important to remember that the Bill gives parents more time with their children and I know that is the Minister's aim.  While the economic consequences for employers is important, so also is the economic consequences to the country of bad parenting.  Parents who are not in a position to give their children attention or who are not in a position, as Senator Cox is and I was, to have excellent child care for their children are in great difficulty.  That is one of the reasons for the repeated request for better, affordable child care for those who must work.  It is important children have good care when their parents are working outside the home.</P>
      <P>I understand the Minister of State's difficulties about the number of years for which parental leave should be allowed.  I also understand why five would be chosen as this is the age at which children go to school.  I was interested that Senator O'Toole stated that three would be a better age.  It seems the INTO has started recruiting from the ranks of those working in nursery schools and that, from now on, the right time to go to school is three.  As the Minister of State intends to review the legislation in two years, perhaps she could give her views on extending the age limit at a later date.  Children are not selfmotoring at age five and it is very difficult to organise them in terms of visits to the dentist or doctor, accompanying them on important occasions or attending parent-teacher meetings which are now generally held in the afternoon. We should not underestimate the importance of parents being present.</P>
      <P>When Senator Quinn spoke on Second Stage, he stated how careful Europe had to be to avoid having so much social legislation that it would be less able to provide jobs.  However, I suggest that he examine the social scene in America where some people need three jobs a week to support their families.  Social and economic progress always go hand in hand and this Bill is an effort to combine both sides of that progress, which is why I commended the Minister of State for introducing it.  Perhaps when it is being reviewed, she could see her way to extending it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not repeat what I said on Second Stage but I am concerned about any strengthening of the Bill which will make it less attractive for potential employers to consider employing people in future.  While I understand that the difference between three, five or eight years does not necessarily lengthen the time people take off and that it is unpaid leave, I believe five years is the right age limit as it is the age at which most children start school.  The Minister of State should be careful about making changes because she should ensure the Bill does not become a discouragement to those considering creating jobs as opposed to those who hope someone will create jobs for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>On the point of our approach being minimalist, the directive allowed the age limit to be set anywhere between two and eight.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1506" /> Two would have been a minimalist approach. Two countries set the age at eight.  We determined that five was a fair balance having examined the approach taken in other countries.  For example, in Austria, the age limit is two, in Belgium it is four, and in France and Germany it is three.  We are setting the age limit at five.  We believe it strikes a fair balance.</P>
    <P>As regards the point made by Senator Quinn, IBEC was in contact with the Department and it was anxious we opt for the lower limit as it would be easier to record and administer.  It is important to note that as parents move from one place of work to another, employers must keep records, which can become complicated.  For example, parents could in their first employment take three weeks for their first child, two for their second and a month for their third.  They could then move on to second and third employments.  These records must to be kept for five years in this country, for fewer years in other European countries and for eight years in Sweden and Denmark. The Government decided on five years as a fair and happy medium.  It is the age at which children in Ireland start school.</P>
    <P>Senator Henry asked if the age could be reviewed at the review stage.  The review stage takes place after two years and no later than three years and the legislation as passed will be reviewed at that time.  The age of five years is a fair balance in comparison with the situation in Europe and particularly in view of IBEC's concern that more than five would be too high.  Even Senator O'Toole, who struck a chord with most Members during the debate on Second Stage, was concerned that the age of five was too high.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>He was beating his own drum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>Children in Ireland start school at five years of age.  That is why the Government decided five years would be a fair balance.</P>
      <P>Question, &ldquo;That the figure proposed to be deleted stand&rdquo;, put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 7:</P>
      <P>In page 6, lines 19 to 22, to delete subsection (4).</P>
      <P>This subsection which the amendment proposes to delete provides that an employee must have completed one year's continuous service.</P>
      <P>There is nothing generous in how the Minister of State is implementing the EU directive.  There is no intention to enhance the employee's rights. There appears to be a continuous acceptance that the employer rules the roost and that the requirements of the employer are uppermost rather than taking into consideration the important role of parents in rearing children.  The requirement for one year's continuous service underpins that acceptance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1507" /> We should have greater consideration for the rights of employees as parents rather than thinking exclusively of employers, as appears to be the case in this minimalist implementation of the directive.  As Senator O'Donovan said, the take-up is so small in the countries where it is operational that we should go out of our way to facilitate it.  The subsection should be deleted or the period of continuous service should at least be reduced to six months.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>If this subsection were deleted it would be possible for an employee to join a company and after one week's service apply for 14 weeks paternal leave in respect of their first child, another 14 weeks in respect of the second child and a further 14 weeks in respect of a third child.</P>
      <P>It must be remembered that an employer appoints a person to a vacancy to do a job.  The system could not work if, after one week or even six months of service, an employer was obliged to let an employee take paternal leave for 14 weeks. I would love if it could work but in the current competitive business environment it would not, and if it would not work it would be of no benefit to either the parents or the employers.</P>
      <P>This is not a situation where the employer is king.  We are trying to strike a balance between the rights of children and the right of parents to have as much time as possible with young children on the one hand and on the other hand the rights of employers to run businesses, make profits and to maintain competitiveness and sustainability in the economy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>We appear to have lost sight of an important point I made on Second Stage. There is a vast number of decent and honourable employers.  In many instances employers readily agree to giving employees time off in certain circumstances. There is nothing in the Bill to stop an employer and an employee voluntarily agreeing that the employee can take three months off within the first year of service to take care of a child.  This legislation provides for situations where an employer might not be so decent.</P>
      <P>Members have referred to the rights of employers and of employees.  In my experience, leave is readily permitted by employers when there is good reason for taking such leave.  The objective of the Bill is to ensure that all employees get their fair share.  The period of one year's continuous service is sensible and practical. Senator Cox correctly pointed out that the absence of such a requirement could be abused. A person could start work and after one month's service demand up to 28 weeks leave.  If the amendment were accepted the employee would be entitled to make such a demand.  That would create major headaches for employers.</P>
      <P>The subsection is sensible and should remain part of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>Women can be non-consultant hospital doctors until they are well into their <Col N="1508" /> thirties and such doctors move between hospitals every six months.  How will non-consultant hospital doctors be treated?  Sometimes one might be lucky enough to get a good job which lasts for one year but most jobs last for six months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>Having worked in a hospital environment, I am familiar with the problem to which Senator Henry refers.  It is recognised that the requirement of one year's continuous service might leave some employees at a disadvantage and section 6(8) provides that an employee whose child is approaching the upper age limit but who has not a full year's service can take parental leave on a <i>pro rata</i> basis.</P>
      <P>It is reasonable that before somebody takes parental leave with all service entitlements preserved he or she should have been with the company concerned for a reasonable period.  The directive suggests that such a requirement can be included in national schemes of parental leave. It is important that an employee should have an attachment to the company and have been working with the company for this period of time.</P>
      <P>Senator Costello continues to describe the legislation as minimalist.  That is not the case.  If this was a minimalist Bill, the age of five years could have been set at two years.  The retrospection provision need not have been included and instead of setting the date at 3 June 1996, it could have been set at 3 June 1998.  The legislation also provides for flexibility.  It could have provided, as is the case in other European countries, that the parent must take the three months leave together. However, this legislation provides that the leave can be taken periodically and on a part-time basis by agreement with an employer.</P>
      <P>With regard to reckonability of service, the Bill provides that increments, annual leave, promotion and entitlements can be counted during periods of parental leave.  This was not required by the directive.  By arrangement with the Department of Social, Community and Family Affairs, credited contributions are protected for people during parental leave and no employee will lose entitlements to short term or long term social welfare benefits because he has taken parental leave. <i>Force majeure</i> leave is paid and that is not required by the directive.  It is wrong to claim that this Bill is a minimalist approach to the directive. That claim should not be repeated.</P>
      <P>Question, &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand&rdquo;, put and declared carried.</P>
      <P>Amendment decared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 8:</P>
      <P>In page 6, subsection (5), lines 25 and 26, to delete &ldquo;, but children of a multiple birth shall be deemed, for the purposes of this subsection, to be one child&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1509" /> It is an unusual provision indeed that treats two or more children as one.  I am sure a parent would see a difference between taking care of one child and taking care of twins or triplets.  This does seem to reflect the Government's minimalist approach to this legislation.  Can three children not be regarded as three and one as one?  The Government is, of course, attempting to reduce the amount of parental leave as much as possible. The wishes and needs of employers are being considered rather than those of parents.  There should be a <i>pro rata</i> extension of parental leave for multiple births.  Instead, the Government pretends that only one child has been born and forgets that the other one or two must also be taken care of.  I must repeat that the legislation has been drawn up in a minimalist fashion and is insulting to parents who have had multiple births.  I hope the Minister will reconsider.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I fully understand why the legislation may have been drafted as it was.  Only one maternity leave is given when there is a multiple birth.  I have not had twins or triplets but I realise that it is highly unlikely that twins or triplets would oblige by contracting their childhood illnesses at the same time.  It is important to recognise that children of a multiple birth are separate children with separate needs.  I ask the Minister to consider accepting this amendment, particularly as we are not implementing the Bill in a minimalist fashion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Minister to reward productivity. I will not speak of the increased productivity of Irish women, who in recent years have lower fertility rates but an increased number of successful multiple births.  The Minister might consider granting parents of multiple births one and a half times the normal parental leave.  As Senator Cox says, it is very difficult to organise twins or triplets to do things at the same time even when it is something you want them to do. I hope the Minister will increase leave for parents of multiple births just a little.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>I support what has been said.  I am happily surprised that Senator Cox supports the amendment from this side of the Houe.  The number of multiple births, as a percentage of all births, is small.  For that reason some additional weeks could be given when twins are born and in the happy and unusual event of triplets or quadruplets being born.  There has been much support for this amendment and I urge the Minister to accept it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>This case was trenchantly put by Senator O'Meara on Second Stage.  She was listened to by the Minster of State and spoke to her subsequently on the matter.  Female Senators have more knowledge of this matter than I but a strong case was made and I hope the Minister of State will show compassion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1510" />
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>The State already acknowledges the difference between single and multiple births by way of child benefit.  That should be reflected in this Bill by acknowledging that one human being cannot be two, three or four, for any purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>I am happy to be encouraged by all sides.  On Second Stage Senator O'Meara made a strong case based on her own experience as a triplet.  She was supported by Senator Ridge who frightened me by referring to the prospect of triplets getting measles on separate occasions, one after the other.  Senators Cox and O'Donovan, after the debate on Second Stage, asked me to check some legal points.  The Attorney General has advised that although the directive is silent on multiple births its wording suggests a right to parental leave for each child.  For those reasons I am happy to accept the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 9:</P>
      <P>In page 6, subsection (6), to delete lines 29 and 30 and substitute &ldquo;as a natural parent, but not as an adoptive parent, in respect of the child.&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment means that an adoptive parent who is also the natural parent of the child can only take parental leave as a natural parent and cannot choose between taking leave as a natural parent and as an adoptive parent. The present wording potentially gives a natural parent who later adopts his or her own child a longer time frame in which to take parental leave than other categories of parents.  Without this amendment someone who is both the natural and adoptive parent could have up to seven years in which to take parental leave; they could opt either to take it before the child is five or within two years of the adoption.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 6, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 7.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 10:</P>
      <P>In page 7, subsection (3), line 42, after &ldquo;child&rdquo;, to insert &ldquo;and the children concerned are not children of a multiple birth&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment follows that made to section 6(6).  It will allow parents of twins, triplets etc, to take more than 14 weeks parental leave in a 12 month period.  Without this provision, such a parent might be unable to take all his or her parental leave entitlement before the children concerned reached the age of five.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1511" /> Government amendment No. 11:</P>
    <P>In page 7, lines 45 to 51, to delete subsection (4) and substitute the following new subsection:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(4)(a) Where any holiday (other than a public holiday) to which an employee is entitled falls during a period of parental leave of the employee and on a day when (but for the leave and the holiday) the employee would be working in the employment concerned, the holiday shall be taken at such other time as may be determined by the employer concerned pursuant to section 20 of the Organisation of Working Time Act, 1997.</P>
    <P>(b) Where any public holiday to which an employee is entitled falls during a period of parental leave of the employee and on a day when (but for the leave and the holiday) the employee would be working in the employment concerned, a day shall be added to the period of parental leave that the employee is entitled to take.&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment brings the treatment of annual leave which falls during parental leave into line with the Organisation of Working Time Act, 1997.  The new wording means that while public holidays which fall during parental leave will be added to the end of parental leave, annual leave which accrues during parental leave will be granted by the employer in accordance with section 20 of the Organisation of Working Time Act, 1997.  This amendment does not mean any loss of annual leave for the employee but removes an inconsistency between the existing wording and the provisions of the Organisation of Working Time Act, 1997.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 7, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 8 to 11, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">NEW SECTION.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 12 is out of order as it involves a potential charge on the Revenue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an important issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ridge may speak on the section.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 12 not moved.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 12.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 13:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (2), line 7, after &ldquo;leave&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;and the notice shall contain a statement in summary form of the grounds for terminating the leave&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1512" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment strengthens the subsection by requiring an employer to state in writing his or her reasons for terminating leave. There is a comparable provision in section 12 (5). This is a sensible and reasonable addition to the wording of this subsection.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 14:</P>
      <P>In page 10, lines 26 to 28, to delete subsection (6) and substitute the following new subsection:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(6) A person shall retain a notice under this section given to him or her and a copy of a notice under this section given by him or her.&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not a change of substance but rather expresses the idea better.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 12, as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that my amendment is out of order.  However, there should be a child benefit payment to families who take parental leave, otherwise it will not be possible for families on low incomes to avail of it.  The Minister should consider paying a double rate of child benefit for the children of such households for the 14 weeks. This will assist parents in taking parental leave, which is a big step in terms of child care and supporting a family.  It will be impossible for most families to take parental leave without some financial help.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>A huge number of women take four weeks unpaid leave at the end of maternity leave, whether they are in high or low income jobs.  This is an indication that income will not be a barrier to people taking parental leave.  While it would be marvellous to provide paid parental leave, it would not work as we cannot afford it.  I accept the spirit of what Senator Ridge is trying to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the sentiments expressed by Senator Ridge.  It is a pity the amendment could not be discussed.  However, the rule of the House is it is out of order as it would involve additional taxation.  However, the Government Commission on the Family recommended that a payment should be made to parents who take parental leave.  The Government is flying in the face of a fundamental recommendation of a commission it established.  It is regrettable that the Government cannot provide minimal social welfare assistance rather than asking an employer to give paid leave.  Children's allowance is not an enormous payment and we are asking that this be doubled for the period of parental leave.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1513" /> Thousands of parents will be unable to avail of parental leave because they will be unable to afford it.  We should do everything we can to ensure that medium to low income families can avail of it.  For economic reasons, these parents will be unable to take 14 weeks off work without pay as they need every week's pay to make ends meet.  This matter must be looked at.  Perhaps in two or three years it will be proposed that some form of payment should be made but we should not have to wait that long.</P>
    <P>Some form of payment is made in eight of the 15 EU countries; we are in the minority of seven countries who do not make a payment.  We may say we cannot afford it but I think we can.  We have not calculated the cost of the proposal, but it would not be enormous.  We must ensure that the maximum number of families on low incomes can avail of parental leave.  Families on above average incomes will be able to avail of it.  We should not make an economic distinction between these families.  I ask the Minister to look at our proposal again.  If it is closely examined, it will be seen that it will not be a great economic burden on the country.  I assure the Minister that the social dividend will be great.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the cogent arguments of Senator Ridge and Senator Connor as to why family child benefit should be paid at double the rate during parental leave.  We must remember that this is unpaid parental leave.  It is important that we provide an incentive for people to take parental leave.  This proposal is an obvious incentive for poor families.  It will guarantee that parents are in the position to take leave and take care of their children at a crucial time.  This proposal is the most potent incentive in the legislation to ensure substantial take-up of parental leave.</P>
      <P>If this proposal is introduced it will ensure that this will not be minimalist legislation and that it will be implemented to the maximum.  No costings have been done but I would like the Minister to look at the matter.  She has time in abundance as the legislation will not be implemented until the end of the year and it has yet to go before the other House.  The Minister should consider the social importance of the proposal as a financial measure which will ensure that those entering the workforce &mdash; a large proportion of whom are women &mdash; and especially those on low incomes, are given the opportunity to avail of parental leave.  I support the proposal and I ask the Minister to look at it again under section 12.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ridge's amendment states that family child benefit shall be payable at double the rate during the period of parental leave.  If we accepted this proposal it would militate&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not discussing the amendment, which was ruled out of order.  We are discussing section 12, as amended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1514" />
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>This would militate and discriminate against that section of women who stay at home permanently to look after their children. What do they get?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to make one point in relation to what Senator Costello said.  We do not need to provide any incentives for people to take up parental leave.  People will avail of it by virtue of the fact that it is available.  Because of the flexibility that has been built into the Bill and the nonminimalist approach &mdash; I am beginning to hate that term &mdash; it is possible for people to take that leave one day a week, in agreement with the employer, until all 14 weeks are taken.  One finds that where people are looking for additional time at home they will often go onto part-time hours on a weekly basis and lose salary in order to spend more time at home.  The issue of payment is a red herring which has been thrown into the debate by the Opposition in an attempt to score political points.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>No. We are just trying to be constructive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a sad day.  We cannot cost it.  The lack of payment for parental leave will not mitigate against anybody taking it in this instance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>One can look at the general issue of payment in a number of different ways but to regard it from a child benefit point of view would not be correct.  All parents are paid child benefit; it is not related to PRSI or whether we are in the workplace.  As Senator O'Donovan pointed out, the suggestion that parents on parental leave should receive double child benefit does not apply to the parent who is on permanent parental duties in the home.  To approach it from that aspect would not be correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a grotesque rejection of a good point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister of State should be allowed to reply without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so because we look at equality from all fronts &mdash; with regard to women in the workplace, but equally in the home.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the equality between well off and not well off people in relation to their accessibility?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>The same applies with regard to Senator Connor's point because what he is saying is that regardless of one's income one should be paid double child benefit.  Therefore, he is not looking at equality with regard to income or women in the home.  We have to look at it from an equality point of view with regard to all women.  Many women would find this approach very unacceptable in their situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1515" /> Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 13.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment Nos. 15, 16 and 17 are related and may be discussed together.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 15:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (1), line 31, after &ldquo;where,&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;for urgent family reasons,&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>The overall effect of these amendments is to tighten the provision dealing with <i>force majeure</i> leave and to ensure that they are in keeping with the wording of the directive itself.  Under the directive member states must give workers <i>force majeure</i> leave for urgent family reasons in cases of sickness or accident, making the immediate presence of the worker indispensable. The revised wording will more faithfully reflect the spirit and text of the directive.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 16:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (1), line 32, after &ldquo;the&rdquo; where it firstly occurs to insert &ldquo;immediate&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 17:</P>
      <P>In page 10, subsection (1), line 34, to delete &ldquo;required&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;indispensable&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 18:</P>
      <P>In page 11, lines 1 to 6, to delete subsection (3) and substitute the following new subsection:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(3) When an employee takes <i>force majeure</i> leave, he or she shall, as soon as reasonably practicable thereafter, by notice in writing given to his or her employer, confirm that he or she has taken such leave and the notice shall specify the dates on which it was taken and contain a statement in summary form of the reasons for the leave.&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this amendment is to tighten up this section and to make it clear that <i>force majeure</i> leave is not something premeditated but something which arises suddenly. Rather than referring to proposed <i>force majeure</i> leave or to a notice given in writing before the employee takes <i>force majeure</i> leave, the amendment will require the employee to confirm the <i>force majeure</i> leave after it has been taken.  This more faithfully reflects the spirit of the directive and the whole thinking behind <i>force majeure</i> leave.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1516" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad the Minister of State is introducing this amendment because I thought we would have people taking over from my own profession, who could predict so accurately illness and accidents that will occur in future.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 19:</P>
      <P>In page 11, lines 17 to 23, to delete subsection (6).</P>
      <P>I would ask the Minister of State to accept this amendment because in relation to sickness certificates we have already decided it was wiser not to ask for a doctor's certificate for the first three days of illness.  I have to agree with Senator Quinn and Senator Leonard that there is a problem concerning the abuse of <i>force majeure</i> leave but bringing the medical profession into it will only add to the confusion.  If the employer does not agree with the employee's explanations something could be sought then, but it is not wise to make such a certificate obligatory.  For a start, there will be costs for those who have to obtain a certificate from a doctor.  If the person is a medical card holder you may be sure that the medical profession will seek some sort of reimbursement for providing these certificates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I seldom disagree with Senator Henry and I will not do so now.  I spoke with regard to this very point on Second Stage when I said that it had become a habit to abuse this sort of leave.  However, I do not think the solution is to remove subsection (6).  My concern is that since this is paid leave, if it is made too attractive and easy for somebody to be tempted to take it and then give the excuse afterwards that they had an illness, and it may not have been an illness, it is necessary for them to feel it is serious enough to do so.  I have difficulty in believing that the solution to the problem I referred to would be to remove subsection (6).  It probably has to stay if only as a disincentive for somebody who would find it so easy to take time off work and use this as an excuse afterwards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator Henry on this matter.  As I understand it, the leave that is envisaged by <i>force majeure</i> is leave that applies in emergencies and crises.  It is limited to a small number of days &mdash; perhaps five or six over a period of three years.  I do not see why we should put further obstacles for people where there are substantial family needs when parental leave is sought.  It is rather heavy handed and unwieldy to require a medical certificate in all instances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>The essential aim of subsection (6) is to place an obligation on the employee who has taken <i>force majeure</i> leave to supply to his or her employer a definitive statement, namely, a medical certificate, which confirms the basis on which the <i>force majeure</i> leave was taken. This supplements the requirement of section <Col N="1517" /> 13(3) which obliges the employee to write a summary statement of the reasons for taking the parental leave.</P>
      <P>I have listened carefully to the points that Senator Henry has made in support of her amendment.  I will certainly look at this issue from the point of view that Senator Henry is concerned about, the undesirability of having recourse to the medical certification procedure to verify <i>force majeure</i> leave.  We will see if it can be dealt with by some modification of what is already in place or by substituting an alternative mechanism.</P>
      <P>In the case of a small firm it does not really arise because, more than likely, the employer will know the emergency circumstances.  On Second Stage, Senator O'Donovan raised the point that in his workplace he would know if there was an emergency in a person's house.  It would be dealt with and the person concerned would work at different times.  It would probably cause some problems for a larger employer as to how the personnel officer can really know what the situation is in each case.  We will try to see what we can do to ensure some type of regulation or situation within the employment.  We will have another look at it based on what has been said.  We will see what we can do in terms of the question of medical certification.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister of State has not already done so, may I suggest that she should discuss the matter with the College of General Practitioners and with the Irish Medical Organisation. Has that happened already?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>Our discussions will be with the Department of Health and Children, which will deal with classifications.  That Department is making inquiries on our behalf.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be a good idea, because it could consider our discussions over three days regarding certificates for sick leave.  The medical profession is not enthusiastic about policing legislation like this and I am grateful for the Minister of State's reply.  I look forward to seeing what she can do with this.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 13, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 14.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 20 is out of order.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 20 not moved.</P>
      <P>Section 14 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 15 to 18, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1518" /> SECTION 19.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 21:</P>
      <P>In page 14, subsection (7), line 51, to delete &ldquo;that offence&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;an offence&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This is a technical amendment.  A person who gives false evidence to the tribunal cannot be found guilty of perjury because the tribunal is not a court.  He or she should be found guilty of &ldquo;an offence&rdquo; and this amendment proposes that technical adjustment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to proceedings of the Employment Appeals Tribunal, a person giving oral evidence or producing documentary evidence is deemed to be in the same position as if he or she was giving evidence before the High Court.  Such a person is conferred under the provisions of section 19(3) with the same privileges and immunities as if he or she were a witness before the High Court.  The tribunal must be duly empowered to take action if a witness tenders false evidence and this is covered in section 19(7). Under that subsection, a witness before the tribunal shall be found guilty of the offence of perjury if giving evidence before a court would mean he or she would be guilty of perjury.  Perjury is an indictable offence for which the penalty is a prison sentence of up to seven years.  Under the law as it stands, perjury is an offence when it is committed by a person who asserts upon oath the truth of some matter of fact which assertion he or she does not believe to be true.  This is the specific offence with which subsection (7) is concerned.</P>
      <P>The amendment proposed by the Senator would appear to remove the reference to perjury and substitute the words &ldquo;an offence&rdquo;.  Thus, instead of the certainty which the text of the Bill sets out, acceptance of the amendment would mean that a less certain situation would obtain and that the person giving false evidence before the tribunal would be guilty of some unspecified offence.  For these reasons I do not support the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>If that is the legal interpretation, I accept it.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 19 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 20 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 21.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 22:</P>
      <P>In page 15, subsection (3), to delete all words from and including &ldquo;but&rdquo; in line 28 down to and including &ldquo;prescribed&rdquo; in line 30.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is the area of compensation or redress for entitlements that are not adequately provided for. This amendment seeks to delete the maximum provided in the legislation, which shall not exceed <Col N="1519" /> 20 weeks remuneration in respect of the employee's employment and calculated in such a manner as may be prescribed.  I would have thought it adequate to have the text read &ldquo;. that compensation shall be as the rights commissioner or the tribunal deems just and equitable having regard to all the circumstances .&rdquo; and that we could leave it to those people who have the professional expertise to decide what is appropriate.  One can envisage circumstances where 20 weeks might not be excessive over a substantial period of time and might not reflect the degree of loss of entitlements if an employer was being deliberately negligent regarding statutory entitlements.  I suggest we leave well enough alone regarding the rights commissioner and the tribunal.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>If we did not set an upper limit on compensation we would set a strange precedent. We need only look at the difficulties insurance companies encountered in the courts' system with personal injury claims.  To be fair to employees suffering at the hands of unjust employers and to employers, the provision &ldquo;shall not exceed 20 weeks&rdquo; is a fair estimate of compensation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>The limit set here follows those of the Maternity Protection Act, 1994, and the Adoptive Leave Act, 1995.  This upper limit provides guidance to the rights commissioner in determining the amount of compensation to be paid and is set at a level I consider appropriate in the context of this legislation.  Without any statutory indication of the maximum level of compensation, the rights commissioner might feel compelled to provide low or minimal compensation or conversely may feel the sky is the limit.</P>
      <P>Question, &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand,&rdquo; put and declared carried.</P>
      <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
      <P>Section 21 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 22.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 23:</P>
      <P>In page 16, subsection (4), line 49, to delete &ldquo;relevant employer&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;respondent to the application&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This amendment proposes the deletion of &ldquo;relevant employer&rdquo; and the insertion of &ldquo;respondent to the application&rdquo; in its place.  This is intended to proceed with the normal rule of Circuit Court proceedings, which is that the action is brought in the county of the respondent.  It is a technical amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>The relevant employer in this instance would be the respondent and, without making little of the proposed amendment, it is a mixture of words that does not take from the effect of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1520" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not propose to accept this amendment.  The wording of the section is based on the equivalent provisions of the Adoptive Leave Act, 1995, section 39(4), and the Maternity Protection Act, 1994, section 37(6). The term &ldquo;relevant employer&rdquo; is clear and unambiguous and I do not see what purpose is served by making the change proposed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I bow to the Minister of State's superior legal advice.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 22 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 23 to 28, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">NEW SECTION.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 24:</P>
      <P>In page 20, after line 8, to add the following new section:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;29.  -The Employment Equality Agency shall take such steps as it considers appropriate to make available to the public information on entitlements under this Act.&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This amendment is intended to assist the Minister of State, as are all the amendments.  There is not much sense in having legislation on the Statute Book and going through the work, sweat and tears of producing and passing it unless there is a mechanism whereby its substance is made public and circulated to the widest possible audience.  In this case the audience are parents with children born after 3 June 1996.  I urge the Minister to accept the new section as one that will be valuable in progressing the legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Costello.  It is important that everybody is fully appraised of their rights and entitlements and, in particular, that fathers be fully aware that they can take 14 weeks paternal leave for each child up to the age of five years born after 3 June 1996.  It is appropriate that the Minister should consider some way of ensuring those who can benefit from the legislation, which is an important step in the equality agenda for men and women and which will make a good contribution to family life, are made aware of its provisions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree the new section should be inserted.  The legislation is complex and a new departure in employment and labour law.  Very often employers may not make available to employees all information in relation to their entitlements under such legislation.  The Employment Equality Agency is the appropriate body to charge with making the maximum amount of information available and to take all necessary steps to ensure it is disseminated.  Public representatives are aware of the dearth of information among people in relation to legislation <Col N="1521" /> and their entitlements.  The amendment includes a novel idea and I congratulate Senator Costello on bringing it forward.  Not only should it be applied to this legislation but it should be applied to earlier and future legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no real quarrel with the principle of the amendment as I accept the desirability of the Employment Equality Agency or the new equality authority having an information role regarding parental leave.  We will have to examine the matter and give further consideration to how it can best be incorporated in the Bill, bearing in mind the status of the Employment Equality Bill, 1997, which was passed by the House last Thursday and the forthcoming equality authority.  The new authority will have statutory functions regarding the Maternity Protection Act and the Adoptive Leave Act.  I will have to work out a mechanism for the incorporation of such a provision in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted by the support from all sides of the House for this measure.  Very often we pass legislation which is subsequently left on the shelf and not sufficiently promulgated. Important legislation should be attached to a body in the context of responsibility for publicising its provisions.  The Employment Equality Agency would be the relevant body in this case. I accept what the Minister has said regarding examination of it to see the best mechanism for fulfilling the spirit of the amendment.  In these circumstances I withdraw the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Miss M. Wallace Miss M. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Miss M. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree to examine the provision to see how it can be incorporated in the Bill.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported with amendments and received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWallace" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Miss M. Wallace) Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Miss M. Wallace)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Miss M. Wallace)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senators for being so helpful in passing the legislation.  Hopefully they will appreciate that we have listened to what has been said today and on Second Stage last week.  I hope people will accept we have not taken a minimalist approach but have approached the legislation in a very positive manner.  The point made by Senator Henry, namely, that this is a positive measure for parents in the workplace, is important as the Bill is another step on the road to equality.  The Bill should be seen in the context of the Employment Equality Bill, the expert group on child care established last July and which will report by the end of the year, and a number of other initiatives in which we are involved concerning family <Col N="1522" /> friendly initiatives and support of parents in the workplace.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThereseRidge" hpid="Mrs. Ridge Mrs. Ridge">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Ridge</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate the Minister.  This is my first Bill.  I have attended its delivery but I do not think I will be entitled to leave.  There is a strong sense of goodwill towards the Bill.  We are moving to a new era for parents.  The comments on all Stages have been well thought out and constructive. I appreciate we cannot deliver everything we wish but note the Minister has agreed to take on board some of the amendments and have a rethink on other aspects of the Bill.  This is something I welcome.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCox" hpid="Ms Cox Ms Cox">
      <NameTxt>Ms Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I compliment the Minister, her Department and officials on the very fine work they have done in implementing the directive on time as promised.  The commitment to review the legislation is a very important step in the context of equality as it will be important to monitor progress in the future.  I particularly welcome this section and the entire focus of the Bill in terms of equality not just for women but also for men. The Bill recognises men's distinct and important role in the upbringing of their family, looking after young children and sharing responsibilities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to be associated with the tributes to the Minister and thank her for the courteous manner in which she has dealt with the Bill and her willingness to consider amendments. I also compliment her officials for their good work.  It is key legislation in terms of making the workplace more user friendly for parents.  It is an appropriate time for such legislation in the context of our economy as more and more people are entering the workforce.  I revoke my description of the legislation as minimalist.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate the Minister and her officials for the manner in which the Bill was debated.  The aim of the Bill was to give effect to an EU directive and the Minister gave serious thought to how best this could be done.</P>
      <P>This was one of the few occasions in the House when I felt as if I was the sole voice of the right wing attitude to this legislation.  I wished to make sure the Bill did not inhibit potential employers from taking on staff and creating jobs.  The Minister has taken that balance into account and I congratulate him.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>When it is proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. -" RHead="Co-funding of Public Works">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Co-funding of Public Works.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State and would like to explain to him from where this concept <Col N="1523" /> came.  I was in Singapore at the beginning of last week and noticed how well it was run and the amount of work going on.  I was told that if public works had to be undertaken, they were done at such a speed so as not to disrupt the community. People worked nights, afternoons and weekends to get work done on time.</P>
      <P>I travelled to Naas last Saturday and on my way back at 5 o'clock in the afternoon I realised that no work was being done on the Naas dual carriageway and that it was unlikely work would be done until Monday.  There does not seem to be an urgency about getting work done quickly. That is the reason I raise this matter on the Adjournment.  I do not have an answer to this problem and am asking questions and sowing seeds.  I am grateful to the Minister for his attendance and would like to sow the seeds of an idea.</P>
      <P>I am concerned about the way we, as a community, approach projects which impinge on society.  These projects are very often paid for from the public purse and almost always involve some disruption to the everyday life of the community. They may be road or drainage projects or, perhaps, light rail projects in the future &mdash; there is a huge list of potential candidates.</P>
      <P>Let us consider how public works projects are tendered for at present.  The aim, quite rightly, is to get a project or job done at the lowest cost.  I fully subscribe to that aim, as I am sure does everyone else but I am concerned about how we define the word &ldquo;cost&rdquo;.  We operate the principle of tender by open competition, which is right.  I do not want to change that but the issue which exercises me is the basis of the tender and for what is being tendered.</P>
      <P>The centre of the town of Swords, County Dublin, is being disrupted because the main street is being dug up to lay pipes, which is worthy and necessary.  I have an interest to declare because my company operates a business in that town and that is the reason I am aware of this disruption.  I use Swords as an example because I have first hand experience of the implications.  Work on one side of the street will finish in about a month's time but it will take three months to work on the other side.  The town is devastated while that worthwhile work takes place.  I am not here to make a special case for Swords but I offer it as an example of what is a problem nationwide.</P>
      <P>A project goes out to tender and, in the fullness of time, the contractor who offers the lowest price gets the job; this is right.  However, there is an element in the overall cost which is not taken into account under the tender process &mdash; the cost of disruption to the community while the work is being carried out.  There is a cost to local business which lose custom during the period of the project. Sometimes that loss is irrevocable because business goes elsewhere and there is always a chance people may change their buying patterns and not change back.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is not only businesses which suffer.  People lose time as a result of traffic congestion and incur the cost of extra petrol.  Health problems <Col N="1524" /> and accidents may result and the environment is damaged for the duration of the works.  Other businesses apart from those in a town face added costs because of delays during that work.</P>
    <P>There is a cost to the community which is not taken into account when we plan such projects.  If we took it into account we might organise projects differently which is what I would like us to do.  Specifically, we should aim to complete projects in a shorter time.  If we reckoned in the overall cost to the community we would immediately see the benefit of putting a premium on quick completion and would encourage contractors to find ways to do the job which would reduce to a minimum the amount of disruption caused to the community.  Obviously, a contractor trying to put in the lowest price will avoid like the plague the cost which will shorten the period of disruption. If he is driven to deliver the lowest price, he will avoid night and weekend work and the costly aspects which would shorten the period of disruption. That makes perfect sense in narrow accounting terms but it makes no sense in terms of the interests of the wider community.</P>
    <P>We are spoiling the ship for a hap'orth of tar and are not looking at the big picture.  We are saving on the budget of whoever is carrying out the immediate cost but our approach means we inevitably add to the overall community costs rather than aim to mitigate them.  I hope to start a change in that attitude which will not be easy. It would, however, be a start to acknowledge that there is a problem.</P>
    <P>Our tendering process should be flexible enough to encourage contractors to propose ways of doing jobs which will reduce the cost to the community of all that disruption.  Contractors should be able to say a job will cost £0.5 million more but we will save more in the reduced cost to the community as a whole.  I would like to open up our approach to tendering so that contractors compete in a different way.  The question is, how do we find the money to make such an approach work.  Individual players will only be concerned with their own costs.  It would obviously be quite unrealistic to tell a local authority it could spend an additional 20 per cent on a particular project as long as it saved on cost to the community.  The money must come from somewhere.  I mention the issue of co-funding to acknowledge my awareness that at the end of the day, somebody must pay the community costs if they are to be factored into public works projects.</P>
    <P>I think it would be reasonable to ask businesses to pay part of the extra cost as I believe they would consider that to be the lesser of two evils but they could not be expected to make up all of the difference. It would be necessary to look more widely at how the shortfall would be overcome.  Perhaps it would be necessary to raid the budgets of Departments other than the Department of the Environment and Local Government.</P>
    <P>I am aware my proposal is untidy in bureaucratic terms but we must ultimately ask ourselves how best our communities and citizens can be <Col N="1525" /> served.  There is no simple solution.  The first step involves admitting a problem exists and then we can begin to work towards solving it.  Public works projects are being carried out in a very wasteful way because we are shackled by our perceptions of what makes economic sense and are being driven by the accountants.  Let us acknowledge a problem exists and explore whether there is some way in which the matter can be approached in order to reduce the overall cost to the community.  We must consider how it would be possible to elicit better value from these projects for the overall community.</P>
    <P>I do not expect the Minister to make a considered response at this stage; I am merely floating an idea.  However, I would like to think I have sown the seeds of an idea in the Minister's mind and that this issue would be given careful consideration. I believe a solution exists to this issue if we begin to alter our perspective on it.  Thousands of people are currently stuck in traffic jams over a three year period but it might be possible to reduce that to one year by speeding up work projects.  I thank the Minister for his attention.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanWallace" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Environment and Local Government (Mr. D. Wallace) Minister of State at the Department of the Environment and Local Government (Mr. D. Wallace)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment and Local Government (Mr. D. Wallace)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Quinn for raising this matter.  My colleague, the Minister for the Environment and Local Government, is unable to be in the House this evening to respond to this item and has asked me to do so on his behalf.</P>
      <P>Major infrastructural investment projects generally bring substantial long-term benefits to the areas they serve.  These benefits may take the form of a higher quality drinking water supply, a more environmentally friendly sewage disposal system or a better road network.  In addition, infrastructure projects frequently facilitate the construction of additional houses, factories, offices and shops, thereby generating additional business opportunities and jobs in the locality.</P>
      <P>The downside of major infrastructural projects is that they can cause significant disruption, in the short or medium term, for local residents and businesses in the vicinity of these works.  It is, therefore, essential that local authorities, together with any private contractors involved, co-operate to ensure that projects are carried out as quickly as possible.  At the same time there is a statutory duty on local authorities and contractors to ensure the construction period is adequate to ensure the safe construction of the project.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Annual guidelines issued by the Department of the Environment and Local Government and the National Roads Authority, remind local authorities to pay special attention to minimising the frequency and duration of road openings and to minimise traffic disruption and hazards to road users.  Authorities are also asked to ensure road openings are permanently reinstated as quickly as possible after the completion of the work.  The concerns expressed in the House today will be fully considered when the guidelines are next being updated.  In the meantime, any major or persistent failure to respect these guidelines <Col N="1526" /> should be brought to the attention of the elected members or manager of the relevant local authority.</P>
    <P>While owners and operators of businesses would prefer if work was executed outside shopping hours, local residents have legitimate objections to drilling and hammering going on in the early hours of the morning or at night.  Another option is for construction work to continue over weekends, but this involves unsocial working hours which may have to be negotiated with the trade unions involved and for which a premium wage rate would have to be paid.  I also understand there are statutory restrictions on night time and weekend working designed to protect worker health and safety.  In any event, many businesses now operate on both Saturday and Sunday and, like local residents, probably welcome a weekend break from the noise and nuisance caused by the construction work.</P>
    <P>Major infrastructure works are generally 100 per cent funded by the Department, often with the aid of EU Structural or Cohesion Funds. Repair and renewal work is funded wholly or partly from local revenue.  Irrespective of the method of funding, the work should be executed with optimum speed and efficiency.  Civil engineering projects are not awarded on the basis of the lowest suitable tender but on the basis of the most economically advantageous one, taking all relevant factors into account.  I am advised it would be difficult to accurately estimate and take into account the indirect costs of a project including the cost of disruption of local business and inconvenience for local residents.</P>
    <P>I assure Senator Quinn that the points raised by him in regard to this matter will be carefully considered.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Restoration of" RHead="Fethard Abbey">
    <Title>Restoration of Fethard Abbey.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TomHayes" hpid="Mr. T. Hayes Mr. T. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity to raise this matter which is of very significant interest to the people of my constituency.  I am aware other Oireachtas Members have also raised it with the Minister.</P>
      <P>The church in Fethard, known locally as Fethard Abbey, was built in 1305.  The original church is still standing and has been in use since that date with the exception of one brief period. Some alterations occurred during the past 700 years.  The monastery in which the monks resided is now a ruin, as is what was at one time the Lady Chapel.  The central area of the church has survived well although some of the alterations detract from the imposing age and structure of this medieval church.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A reputable and experienced group of consultant engineers was engaged to examine the building and prepare a report on it.  They estimated it would cost in the region of £600,000 to carry out necessary restoration and upgrading work at Fethard Abbey.  A significant sum of £150,000 has been raised in Fethard town over the past 20 months.  Left to the community, it would take in <Col N="1527" /> the region of eight years to reach the required amount, by which time costs will have increased and the generosity of local people will have been exhausted.</P>
    <P>The abbey is a jewel in the crown of the medieval walled town and is the best preserved abbey of its kind in Ireland.  Fethard is located between Cashel and Kilkenny, two important tourist locations which attract huge numbers of visitors annually.  It is imperative that necessary works are undertaken to ensure the future of this old church and that there will be no cause to lament its condition in the years ahead.</P>
    <P>As I said, a sum of £150,000 has been raised locally and, according to predictions, the total will be almost £200,000 before the end of the year.  A local businessman has pledged to contribute £100,000 as a once off donation, which is a significant gesture.  There is an urgent need for the Minister to consider this important project and to examine if a major contribution can be made to it.</P>
    <P>The tourism potential of this part of County Tipperary is totally unexploited.  If this project was completed, there would be a huge jump in the number of tourists to the locality.  The large number of tourists who visit the Rock of Cashel and Kilkenny adds to the argument in favour of a contribution to the Fethard project.  I ask the Minister to give this good community project, which would be self-sustaining for many years, a once off contribution.  This would allow tourists to enjoy this wonderful, historic and important example of medieval times.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SiledeValera" hpid="Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands (Miss de Valera) Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands (Miss de Valera)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Arts, Heritage, Gaeltacht and the Islands (Miss de Valera)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Augustinian foundation in Fethard, known as Holy Trinity Priory and locally as &ldquo;The Abbey&rdquo;, was founded around 1305.  The friars remained there until the dissolution of the monastery in 1540.  The property was granted to Edmund Butler, Baron of Dunboyne, in 1544.  The Augustinian links with Fethard continued until the 17th century and the Provincial Superior of the Order lived in the town from 1646 to 1649.  The friars returned early in the 19th century, rebuilding the church almost immediately in 1820.  The church is still in use today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As the church is in private ownership and still in use for ecclesiastical purposes, Dúchas, the Heritage Service of my Department is precluded from incurring any expenditure in relation to it. However, I am glad to inform the Senator that adequate legal protection is afforded to Fethard Abbey, County Tipperary, as it is included on the <Col N="1528" /> record of monuments and places under section 12(1) of the National Monuments (Amendment) Act, 1994, notice of which is being published in the national and local newspapers this week. Section 12(3) of the Act makes it obligatory for any individual wishing to carry out works at the site to give two months notice in writing of their proposal to Dúchas, the Heritage Service of my Department.</P>
    <P>This legislation provides the means to accelerate the statutory protection of the estimated 140,000 monuments and places which are in private ownership throughout the State.  In addition, Dúchas, the Heritage Service, has responsibility for the preservation and maintenance of approximately 700 national monuments in its direct care.</P>
    <P>It has committed approximately £1.9 million to projects at national monument sites in County Tipperary under the EU operational programme for tourism, 1994-9.  A fine example of one of these projects is the Mainguard in Clonmel.  Following extensive archaeological excavation, restoration is now underway with the provision of an exhibition on the history of the building completing the project.  Works at Roscrea Castle have been underway for a number of years, involving the conservation and restoration of the castle, round tower and friary with the provision of an exhibition in the castle and a further interpretative facility at the round tower.  The upgrading of the exhibition material at Ormonde Castle, Carrick-on-Suir, is also underway and is expected to be completed later this year.</P>
    <P>In addition to the extensive programme of works funded by the EU, Dúchas, the Heritage Service, has responsibility for the conservation and maintenance of approximately 150 national monuments in the southern national monuments maintenance region.  Extensive conservation works are merited at important sites such as Kells Priory, County Kilkenny, Athassel Abbey, County Tipperary and Nenagh Castle.  Further work is also required at a large number of other sites and, subject to the availability of resources, these works will be addressed on completion of the EU programme.</P>
    <P>I appreciate that Fethard Abbey is of architectural and historic significance and I assure the Senator that Dúchas, the Heritage Service, would be prepared to give advice on any proposed works which would ensure the preservation of the abbey.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.15 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 17 June 1998.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>