<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Fri" Date="16" Month="Feb" Year="1934" Vol="50" No="11" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 16 Feabhra 1934" DateEnglish="Friday, 16 February 1934" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1691">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1691" /> Do chuaidh An Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="PN" LHead="Private Notice Question." RHead="- Tobacco Growing">
    <Title>Private Notice Question. - Tobacco Growing.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he is aware that great uncertainty exists among prospective tobacco-growers regarding this year's crop; that many of them relying on the statement made by the Minister for Finance in his Budget speech last year have ploughed and made other arrangements, involving much capital expenditure, to deal with the crop; that statements appearing in the daily newspapers of the 6th February are however entirely at variance with the statement of the Minister for Finance; and whether in the circumstances and in view of the close proximity of the sowing date he will state if he proposes in respect of this year's crop to depart from the proposals outlined by the Minister for Finance last year and, if so, in what way he proposes to depart from them and for what reason.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan) Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to introduce a Bill at an early date for the control of the growing and sale of tobacco.  The preference for Irish-grown tobacco outlined in the Budget of last year will be replaced by a lesser rebate.  By this method the grower can be as well paid for his crop at less cost to the Exchequer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister states that it is proposed to introduce legislation at an early date in respect of this year's crop.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>In respect of the price to growers, can the Minister say if the published figures of 1/- to 1/3 per lb. is sufficient, in his opinion, to remunerate growers who have gone to <Col N="1692" /> special expense regarding grading and such rehandling machinery as they thought fit to instal?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as my inquiries have gone 1/3 per lb, on the average, would be a good remunerative price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister say at what date he proposes to introduce the legislation in question?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Probably within three weeks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that the planting of the seeds takes place about the 1st March?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, of course, is aware that provisional licences were to be made available by the Revenue Commissioners.  Can he say if any provisional licences have been issued to any growers, or if it is proposed to issue any?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Revenue Commissioners have no option but to issue licences, unless in cases of bad character. Otherwise they must issue licences.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that in his own constituency applications for these provisional licences have been presented to the Revenue Commission and that in the cases in question no such licences have been issued?  As a matter of fact, no licences at all have been issued in the Minister's constituency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not assuming that they are all bad characters in my constituency. The licences will be issued by the Revenue Commissioners, who have no other option.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked the Minister if any have been issued.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to know if the Minister is aware whether any such provisional licences have been issued in his own constituency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not responsible for the Revenue Commissioners but, as the law stands, if licences are asked for, <Col N="1693" /> for the growing of tobacco, the Revenue Commissioners must issue them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>For the full area asked for?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to take the Minister at a disadvantage. He states that this licence must be issued by them.  That is not the case because, as a matter of fact, the issuing of a provisional licence is an act of grace.  They are not bound to issue a provisional licence at all.  They may or may not.  Will the Minister, between this and the next sitting day of the Dáil, inquire into the question as to whether or not applications have been received by the Revenue Commissioners for provisional licences; whether any such licences have been granted and as to the discrimination that has been made, if any, in respect of the area applied for by those who are making the applications?  I gave the Minister very short notice about this question and I quite understand that he is not responsible for the Revenue Commissioners, but I understand also that he accepts a certain responsibility for this particular industry. I should like to know from the Minister whether he will make inquiries between this and the next sitting day of the Dáil so that he can give me an answer to the question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a question the Deputy should put to the Minister for Finance.  I cannot accept any responsibility for what has been done in the past in the issuing of licences.  But, in the Bill to be introduced, there will probably be provisions for registration by the Minister for Agriculture.  For what has been done up to this I cannot take any responsibility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, presumably, will understand that the purpose I have in mind in connection with this question is to allay growing apprehensions. I ask the Minister if, in the interval, between this and Wednesday next, he will make the necessary inquiries and not try to shelve responsibility <Col N="1694" /> in this connection because the major responsibility is his.  I ask him to make inquiries from the Revenue Commissioners as to whether or not any applications for provisional licences have been made and if any have been granted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy will put the question to the Minister for Finance on Wednesday it will be answered.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Trade Loans (Guarantee) (Amendment) Bill," RHead="1934.&mdash;Report and Final Stage">
    <Title>Trade Loans (Guarantee) (Amendment) Bill, 1934.&mdash;Report and Final Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass) Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Bill be received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that the Fifth Stage be taken now if there is no objection.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Bill do now pass.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask the Minister a question.  I do not know if it arises specifically on this Bill, but as the Bill deals with the matter of giving trade loans in respect of the building of houses, I should like to ask if the Minister is making any arrangements to get information from persons engaged in the building industry as to the number of private houses that are being built.  There has always been a great difficulty in ascertaining how many houses are being built in the country other than houses built with the assistance of Government grants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know that I have any machinery which would enable me to procure that information. It does not arise under this Bill because it is certainly not intended that the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Act should be used to further private housing operations.  If the Deputy would put down a Parliamentary question I shall try to get what information is available on the point.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Supplementary and" RHead="Additional Estimates">
    <Title>Supplementary and Additional Estimates.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1695" /> The Dáil, according to order, went into Committee on Finance and resumed consideration of Additional and Supplementary Estimates for the service of the year ending March 31st, 1934.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="In Committee on Finance. - Vote No. 3&mdash;Department" RHead="of President of the Executive Council (Resumed)">
    <Title>In Committee on Finance. - Vote No. 3&mdash;Department of President of the Executive Council (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on Vote No. 3&mdash; Department of President of the Executive Council (The President).</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>On the adjournment yesterday evening I was dealing with the high pretensions of the Minister for Industry and Commerce, who claimed that this Information Bureau, Press Bureau, Publicity Bureau, or whatever technical name may ultimately be affixed to it, was essential in order that the Fianna Fáil policy should be known in this country and outside it.  As is usual with the Minister for Industry and Commerce, he claimed that everything that is national in policy belongs to his Party and that we, in this Party, have been taking some items from it.  Deputy Norton in replying to Deputy MacDermot produced records showing that the previous Government had some kind of Publicity or Information Bureau in the years 1923-1925.  I wonder was the Minister for Industry and Commerce and the present Government practising at that period the great economic policy that they now claim to have and that they accused us of having taken up? Two great points in the economic policy laboured by the Minister for Industry and Commerce last evening were wheat and beet.  I wonder how much wheat and beet were troubling the Government Party in the years 1923-1925?  It might be information to the Minister and his Party to be told that the case was made for wheat in 1925 and for beet in 1925 and not a solitary member of the Government Party participated in these experiments or had anything to do with their promotion. The members who had to do with them are members of the United Ireland Party now and whatever credit is to <Col N="1696" /> be claimed for those two policies of wheat and beet we can claim it.  These were experiments, but the Party opposite have no information except that, regardless of expense, these two crops can be successfully grown in this country.  That is all that the experimental stage has yet taught.  The experiments have not taught that they can be grown economically, but I am not going to question the fact that they are useful crops grown in a general agricultural economy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The President, in introducing the Vote, said in effect that this country is libelled through reports getting into the foreign Press about threatened revolution here and he wants, apparently, to counter those false reports. That is a praiseworthy object, but there are other methods nearer the President's hands that he fails to adopt.  I shall give him one instance of what occurred in the streets of Dublin on last Friday evening.  I was one of four people who were beset by a mob in Duke Street and Dawson Street.  We caught two of them and offered them to the Guards but the Guards refused to take them. I am not going to give the Deputy's name, but one of them claimed to be a nephew of a Fianna Fáil Deputy.  I hope that the statement of that man is wrong for the honour of this House because we all would feel ashamed of it, no matter to what Party the Deputy belonged, if the statement were true. I intend to tell the Deputy, who is a personal friend of mine, to inquire into it but I shall pursue it no further.  I am not concerned with that aspect of it.  What I am concerned with is the fact that the Guards told us that they could not take them in charge when a mob came up saying to us: &ldquo;There are the murderers; there are the members of the murder gang.&rdquo;  When public representatives of the City of Dublin are accosted in that way and the persons are caught and handed over to the Guards and the Guards are not in a position to take them in charge I cannot understand it.  If such a condition of affairs is allowed to obtain I look upon it as the breeding ground for revolution.  I told the Guards that I <Col N="1697" /> would put down a question in the Dáil. I have been considering whether or not I should put down a question.  I think I have said enough about it now without putting down a question.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>Put down a question. If you took the numbers of the Guards let us know the numbers of the Guards who refused to do their duty.  It was their duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know their duty in a matter like that.  I am giving you the circumstances briefly as they occurred.  If in the opinion of the President or the responsible Minister they have not done their duty and the President invites me to bring it before the notice of the Government by a Parliamentary question, I certainly will put down a question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>I do invite you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure that the President and the Government will see that the Guards will do their duty and I shall facilitate them.  I shall not give the names, but as one of these persons was being examined by the Guards the other came up and said to me: &ldquo;Belton, if anything happens that man you will get a letter.&rdquo;  I caught him by the neck and brought him up to the Guards and said: &ldquo;You will go with this other fellow; whatever happens this fellow will happen you.&rdquo;  That was obviously a reference to a threatening letter, I suppose to be followed by something more stern.  It is very little use to tax the people for a Publicity Bureau to counter alleged slanders about this country being on the verge of revolution if conditions like that are allowed to obtain within sight of this House.  It was not merely within the proverbial stone's throw but within an actual stone's throw of this House that that happened within the last week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I doubt if it would redound to the credit or intelligence of this country if a Publicity Bureau were set up to announce to the world that we had decided not to make certain payments to England while in fact we are making them.  No attempt has been made to controvert that.  We are engaged in a war and we are going to send out propaganda <Col N="1698" /> about that war to the world. The first war I remember was the Spanish-American war, followed by the Boer war, the Russian-Japanese war and the little wars in the Balkans until we came to the Great War.  The countries engaged in these wars all had their agencies for the issuing of propaganda to the world.  Presumably this is intended to be a war measure and to be our propaganda agency for the world.  If we have any sense and are going to get any respect from the outside world we ought to fight this war or give it up.  There is no half-way house between cutting off all supplies from Great Britain and settling the dispute.  It is silly nonsense to be taxing the people of this country to subsidise exports to Great Britain while we are sending orators round the country telling the people that we are starving Great Britain.  We had Deputy Hugo Flinn and others yesterday chastising the Party on this side of the House for want of intelligence in claiming that tariffs on goods going into a country are paid by the country that exports the goods.  Is not that perfectly obvious?  Tariffs were put on and more goods than were wanted were sent in.  They had to curtail the quantity going in.  When tariffs are put on it is only when there is a shortage of supplies that the country to which the goods are going will pay any part of the tariff.  Notwithstanding the tariffs in Great Britain we sent Great Britain more of these goods than they actually wanted.  Therefore, the British citizens paid none of the tariffs. The returns have been published and, while a vulgar attempt, I must say, was made by Deputy Flinn and the Minister for Finance to make light of the figures published on the other side as to the book-keeping in this transaction, no attempt has been made to controvert the figures.  These figures demonstrate one thing, that in the so-called war which is going on we are losing all along the line.  The only second line of defence or alternative method of warfare that the President can conceive is to establish a Propaganda Bureau to tell the world how successful we are in the warfare when the world knows that we are fighting a losing game.</P>
    <Col N="1699" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardSidneyAnthony" hpid="Mr. Anthony Mr. Anthony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Anthony</NameTxt>
      <P>What does the world care?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Not tuppence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardSidneyAnthony" hpid="Mr. Anthony Mr. Anthony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Anthony</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not labour that point any further.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I only want to labour it because it has been laboured on the other side.  If you take up any daily paper and look at the news from any country in the world you will see that every country is preoccupied with its own business and not bothering about us here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardSidneyAnthony" hpid="Mr. Anthony Mr. Anthony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Anthony</NameTxt>
      <P>They will not know where we are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>The President laughs assent to that.  Why is he anxious to set up a Publicity Bureau then to tell them about this country?  He knows as well as, and perhaps better than, anyone in this House that the world will not bother to read his publicity stuff when sent out from 2DV.  The Minister for Industry and Commerce, in a truculent and eloquent mood last evening, said that we had stolen their wheat policy from them. He forgot, of course, that they stole it from the people, but we pass over that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Perhaps the President might tell us in some simpler fashion than by establishing this Bureau, and taxing the people in order to establish it, what the people who have thousands of acres of wheat stubble, following up his wheat policy, are to do with it.  He knows that wheat is only a preliminary to other developments in agriculture and those other branches of agriculture must be paying concerns, because human food out of the land will not be 20 per cent. of the entire production and human food cannot be economically produced unless animal food, produced directly and as a by-product of human food, is utilised at a profit.  The Government appear to want a Publicity Bureau to put over their propaganda on the country.  I submit this is urgent propaganda; but it is propaganda that the President and his Ministers are carefully side-tracking, because they are now up against the kernel of the whole problem.  I do <Col N="1700" /> not want to go into an agricultural discussion on a Vote of this kind.</P>
    <P>If this were to be used as a national Publicity Bureau I do not think there would be any division of opinion upon it.  But it is going to be used as a kind of super publicity agency, over and above the ordinary Press of the country, in order to put over the propaganda of a political Party.  I do not say that because a certain political Party is in power.  It would only be natural if another political Party came into power that they would use it in the same way.  A bad precedent will be set.  In the early days of the Sinn Féin movement, some 30 years ago, I remember being one of a deputation sent to interview the authorities connected with the Bloomsbury Town Hall in London.  Our object then was to set up a Press Bureau in order to send out our stuff to the world.  I am not sure that the world was so terribly worried about what we sent out.  We attempted it, anyway, because we had great, high and important notions about ourselves in those days.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrady" hpid="Mr. S. Brady Mr. S. Brady">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Brady</NameTxt>
      <P>Apparently they were never lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say that some success attended the efforts of various Irish groups all over the world at that time.  I strongly suggest to the President that when, in a matter of this kind, they want to buttress up their case, they should not always be dragging in their economic policy when they know that that economic policy is throttled now by their own actions.  I could adumbrate on that, but I see it is not relevant beyond the mere mention of it and, besides, I will have scope later on, perhaps during this day, to refer to that matter.  I just want to mention the need for attending to that end of the policy when they think it worth their while to introduce it at all.  If this Bureau is set up, I hope an assurance will be given to the House in regard to the nature of the documents to be issued from it.  I presume bulletins will be issued.  If so, we must not have those bulletins as a sort of Eleventh Commandment&mdash;that they must be obeyed and that it will be a <Col N="1701" /> sin against the State and Church if they are not obeyed.  If anything like that is attempted it will reduce the Press of this country to subserviency and it will mean the abolition of freedom of the Press.  I hope the President has not been tempted to set up this Bureau because of the ground that his paper is losing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SydneyBMinch" hpid="Mr. Minch Mr. Minch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Minch</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume that the necessity for a Bureau of Information has been forced on the President by reason of two definite ideas.  Is it because the material for home consumption has not got enough martial spirit behind it or is it that the material for consumption outside this country is not aggressive enough or strong enough?  We all know that such opportunities as we got at Ottawa may not occur again for this country to get away with a certain amount of political propaganda.  We all know that the wonderful opportunity that was given to the representatives of Saorstát Eireann on the League of Nations has gone by the board and we all know that the London Conference will not be renewed within the next few years.  Thus it is that the Government are now endeavouring to establish something to try to take the place of these opportunities that they had; they are now anxious to issue bulletins or communiques from Government Buildings once a week, twice a week or every day in the week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy Norton, the enigma of this House, who weeps bitter tears and makes appeals to the Government on behalf of those whose wages and salaries are to be reduced, says that as long as this Government co-operates with him he will co-operate with them.  He walked in here last night and immediately applauded and supported an appeal for £1,000 a year to be given to this Bureau of Information. Then he proceeded to make an unwarranted attack on the Opposition here who opposed the Government's proposal.  He endeavoured to make out that this Bureau of Information is going to counter the Rothermere Press, the Beaverbrook Press, is going to be read in Tokyo, is going to uplift the unfortunate, untouchable <Col N="1702" /> class in India and is going to take the Hearst Press in America by storm.  One would imagine that this information that would be issued from this country would receive caption lines in the leading newspaper chain organisations of this world and that this Bureau will ultimately bring truth, knowledge and light to the whole world, show what we are and show that we are fighting for our bare existence, that we are being downtrodden, that we are not free or independent, that we are still slaves and that we are living in serfdom. All this high-faluting political claptrap is to be sent all through the country.  The great national hero, the great national patriot to-day is Deputy Norton.  He is the one and the only real national patriot outside the President himself.  He walks in step with him.  He is trying to put before the world what a wonderful Party Fianna Fáil are and that the Labour Party are and always have been even better than Fianna Fáil. This is nothing more than political propaganda.  It is nothing more than bolstering up more than ever the sort of dope stuff that is being disseminated around the country by the Government organ.</P>
    <P>Now we are going to have sent out and paid for by the taxpayers of this country all this sort of thing and the effort is being made to prove that it is a national question and not a Party question.  Surely this is not the time to be spending £1,000 a year for political Party propaganda.  We heard Deputy Norton getting up here and making unwarrantable references to the Press, digging up certain things that took place in the past for the simple reason that the Press to which he objects has not made a marvellous hero of him and hailed him as the saviour of the country.  Deputy Norton could have gone further and brought in very many county councils and urban councils of that period.  But no.  The Deputy made references to Deputy Fitzgerald and charged that he was trying to fan the sparks of the civil war, bring them in here and fight again the battle in words.  Then having fired that pile of ammunition across the <Col N="1703" /> House he sits down.  All the time he has been shouting, he forgets the people who have to make sacrifices by cuts in their pay and salaries.  Surely it is about time that this sort of thing stopped.  As far as I can see this information that is going to be given out by this Press Bureau will be in the interests of the Government Party.  I do not know whether the Bureau will act as a Press censor.  It might.  I say that this Vote shows that the Executive Council are nothing more than a bunch of political bandits using the money of the taxpayers of the country for their own selfish ends.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGovern" hpid="Mr. McGovern Mr. McGovern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGovern</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to say a word or two about this Vote.  Might I ask first of all what is the need for this Bureau at the present moment? Heretofore the <i>Irish Press</i> was no doubt the organ of the Government Party.  That is an unquestionable fact and I can furnish proof of it.  When a Deputy in this House some time ago made an attack upon one of the leaders of the Opposition, which was blazoned in the <i>Irish Press</i>, I replied to that attack and sent that part of my speech to the <i>Irish Press</i>, but it was not inserted.  I think that shows that beyond question the <i>Irish Press</i> is a Party organ.  That being the case, how comes it to be necessary that this Press Bureau should be established here for Party purposes?  I can tell you why. It is because the circulation of the <i>Irish Press</i> has gone down.  The paper is not being read in the country notwithstanding the fact that some of the agents are forcing it on the people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I had yesterday to remind three Deputies that neither the circulation nor the policy of the <i>Irish Press</i> is in order in this debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGovern" hpid="Mr. McGovern Mr. McGovern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGovern</NameTxt>
      <P>Very well.  I will not pursue that matter.  I will merely say that the reason for this Vote is the fact that when the people will not take to the present propaganda of the Government Party this propaganda is to be sent out and it is to be applied like forcible feeding.  I tell the Government that a policy of forcible feeding will not succeed.  Where voluntary propaganda <Col N="1704" /> has failed, this Government propaganda that is sought to be rushed down the throats of the people will not succeed any more than the voluntary propaganda.  The people are already well served by the Press in this country. There is plenty of propaganda from both sides.  So long as it is open to the people it is for the people to make a choice.  It is because things are going against the Government Party that they are making this attempt to get in something extra at the expense of the taxpayers as a whole.  Of course asking for this Vote is in keeping with the general policy. This is only one side of Government policy.  The other is the attempt to prevent the Opposition being heard at public meetings.  We know that every effort is made to prevent the leaders of the Opposition from addressing the electors.  Now we have side by side with that attempt this other attempt to subsidise propaganda at the expense of the taxpayers.  I am quite confident that that sort of thing will not succeed. I do not know what sort of propaganda this Bureau will issue or for what it will be used.  I expect it will deal with the industrial policy of the Government.  It will no doubt explain the benefits of the agricultural policy to this country.  That will be broadcast. But I wonder will they be able to tell the farmers down the country who are unable to meet their liabilities and unable to dispose of their stock at the fairs that this is for their benefit&mdash; will they tell the people who are unable to get a remunerative price for what they produce how they are to find a solution of their difficulties.  I wonder will they be able to convince the farmers that they are more prosperous now than when they were getting economic prices for their produce? Will they be able to convince the unfortunate people in Cavan who are unemployed that the few factories set up in Dublin are a benefit to them?  The fact is that not one person from that county has been able to get employment in any of those factories that have been started.  In Cavan itself only one factory has been started.  It is true that that factory is giving employment to ten girls at the princely <Col N="1705" /> remuneration of 6/- a week.  Are these the things that this valuable Press Bureau is to broadcast to the people of the country?  If so, I am quite satisfied that the people of the country who of late are not taking voluntarily to the Fianna Fáil propaganda will not take to it when it is being shoved down their throats by this Press Bureau.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>We have heard the various reasons that have been put forward in support of the case for this Vote which is by the way for £148. That to the nearest fraction would be for one-sixth of a year at a yearly salary of £900.  I do not know whether we are to take it that this officer is already in office or that he is being paid or has been paid any money.  The purposes for which the Vote is being put forward were referred to last night by various speakers including the President who introduced the vote. It is to embrace practically every activity of every Department of this State so far as one can judge.  It is to deal with the annuities, with the colour of the bread we eat and with the policy of the Government in its various prospects and activities. Apparently it is to have a knowledge not alone of the policy but of the details of the policy and to make them presentable, I presume, to people at home and abroad.  The best explanation that could be given, I suppose, by the President in introducing this Vote is that this officer is going to be a sieve; that he is to get information from various Departments; that he is to put that in a more palatable form than the Ministers are themselves able to put it, and that it is to be dressed up for consumption in that order. Such a new departure of State certainly forces one to the conclusion that the Government political organ has been a failure; that the Government speakers and back-benchers, and their supporters in the House, the Labour Party, have been utterly unequal to the task that they have undertaken; and that failure distinguishes and characterises everything that they touch, everything that they have touched and everything that they say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Much play was made by some of the speakers who addressed themselves to <Col N="1706" /> this Vote on the history of this country during the last ten years.  It is characteristic of speakers on the Government side that no matter what subject they are putting before the House, no matter what the recommendation, they have some sort of criticism to pass on the events of the years that transpired before they took up office.  The strange thing about the development of their policy is that with the exception of wheat and tobacco everything else is a slavish imitation of somebody else.  This Vote in itself is, perhaps, the most slavish tribute that they could pay to the British during the War.  What is there the matter with ordinary Ministers of State that they cannot themselves go out and talk about their policy, or get their supporters to do it, or get the Labour Party to help them, or get their political organisation to do it?  Is it the fact that their own organ is not circulated to their satisfaction, and that they realise that something extra must be done?  The introduction of the word &ldquo;revolution&rdquo; here yesterday would have astonished anybody who had been listening to Ministers for the last two years.  For two years we have been told that there was nothing in the world like the peace that broke out here since they took office.  Why even their own political organ had to address themselves to that subject on Monday or Tuesday last.  One would imagine that they had been sleeping for two years and had now discovered that there was something to talk about.</P>
    <P>In the course of a speech which was made here by one of the Parliamentary Secretaries, reference was made to the fact that the President had followed the precedent established by me during my time of office, when he would not go out after the guns.  I am not going to discuss for the moment whether or not it was that they approved of the policy which they thought I had pursued, and that that was the reason why they did not do it, or whether it was that they were unequal to having a policy of their own, but in the course of a discussion here in this House on the 9th August last, the Minister for Justice read a report which he stated he had received from the Commissioner <Col N="1707" /> of the Gárdaí.  Included in that report of General O'Duffy there is this statement, which they say came from the chief superintendent of Tipperary:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;It is certain, however, that Mr. Jerry Ryan could, should the occasion arise, muster a fair number of the arms taken from the Templemore Military Barracks during the Mutiny.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I know Colonel Jerry Ryan.  He has no arms.  He has control of no arms, and no arms were taken from Templemore Military Barracks which were not returned.  He was particularly anxious that that statement should be made here when he heard of this report.  I draw attention again to the wording of this report:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;It is certain, however, that Mr. Jerry Ryan could, should the occasion arise, muster a fair number of the arms taken from the Templemore Military Barracks during the Mutiny.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Those arms were returned.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Mr. Ruttledge: It continues: &lsquo;Should it at any time desire to adopt other than constitutional methods, it can, without doubt, lay hands on a sufficient quantity of arms and ammunition to render it a very formidable insurrectionary force and a source of extreme danger to the peace and stability of the country.&rsquo;&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That refers to the A.C.A., or the National Guard, and it at no time desired to adopt other than constitutional methods.  &ldquo;It can, without doubt, lay hands on a sufficient number of arms and ammunition to render it a very formidable insurrectionary force and a source of extreme danger to the peace and stability of the country.&rdquo; Mark the words: &ldquo;Should it at any time desire to adopt other than constitutional methods.&rdquo;  It at no time desired, and never will desire to have other than constitutional methods, because its whole history and tradition and the history and tradition of every person in association with it stand against the use of unconstitutional methods, and have done so for the last 12 years at great costs to themselves <Col N="1708" /> and their families and their friends.  I repudiate absolutely any justification for any Minister or any member of the Fianna Fáil Party saying that during my term of office I allowed, or permitted, or countenanced, or condoned the possession of arms except under lawful authority, and I would advise them to do the same.</P>
    <P>On Saturday last, there was a meeting in No. 44 Parnell Square of engineers or other persons acting in that capacity, belonging to an organisation that has been condemned as unlawful by the Catholic Hierarchy in this country.  It may be lawful according to the legal advisers of the Government; it is unlawful according to the Church subscribed to and supported by the vast majority in this country.  On that same Saturday officers of State in the pay of the Government of the State entered the premises known as No. 5 Parnell Square, which were closed by order of the Military Tribunal and are not available for use by the persons who own them.  The Military Tribunal and the President of the Executive Council and the Attorney-General and all the Ministers of State have not the power under any Act, omnipotent or otherwise, to give any person authority to enter those premises which do not belong to them, for their use and benefit.  From No. 5 Parnell Square those officers of State, with the use of field glasses, kept No. 44 Parnell Square under observation.  The meeting that was held there was for the purpose of giving instruction in the use and construction of a land mine which was to be exploded on the following day.  That might be assumed to be in the County Dublin, but the only explosion which took place in this country on the following day was in Dundalk.  When dealing with these matters in this House the Ministry which is now looking for money to use for propagandist purposes should let this House and the country get the report of the police authorities as to why those premises, 44 Parnell Square, were not raided on that particular evening.  By what right and by what authority did police officers enter a premises closed by order of the Military <Col N="1709" /> Tribunal?  Is the Executive Council above the law?</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The question of the right of police officers to enter any premises is not relevant to the establishment of an Information Bureau.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>With great respect, sir, reference was made last evening to the censoring of a publication in this country.  The Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance, Deputy Flinn, referred to that question at great length.  He wanted to know whether it was by order of the Executive Council that censoring took place.  He inquired what responsibility the Government had in respect to it.  He stated, quite incorrectly, that the Cumann na nGaedheal Government had passed an Act authorising that sort of thing to be done and he practically attempted to absolve the Government of any responsibility, political or otherwise, in respect of that particular matter.  It was to be inferred from what he said that it was by order of the Military Tribunal that that censoring had taken place.  This is a vote for publicity matters in connection with the administration.  The administration appeared before the Military Tribunal to close the premises, No. 5 Parnell Square, and succeeded in getting those premises closed, notwithstanding an application by Deputy Dillon to have them reopened.  This Vote is for publicity on the part of the Government.  A considerable amount of publicity has already been directed towards the censoring of the newspaper in question and I submit that I am entitled to draw the attention of the Government to a breach of the law and to ask whether or not a defence in respect of that breach of the law by them will be one of the matters to be dealt with by the officer to be appointed under this Vote.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Yesterday the Chair submitted that if that line of argument were followed, every activity of every Government Department, every aspect of Government policy, might be raised on this Vote.  Any <Col N="1710" /> Deputy might submit that the economic condition, for instance, of County Cavan or the number of unemployed in Ballina, might be discussed for half-an-hour on the query whether that should be a matter to be dealt with by the Bureau.  The incident referred to by the Deputy who is in possession would, I submit, be more properly the subject of a Parliamentary question to elicit the information which he requires.  Instead of arguing that it is a matter for the Bureau, the Deputy has asked the President certain questions as to the facts.  The President is not the officer of this Information or Publicity Bureau.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>He is not the officer, but it is under his Departmental Vote that this officer will function and it is in respect of the policy pursued by the President and his Ministry that this officer will disseminate information. One of the items, and a very important item, in connection with the duties of this officer will be to endeavour to put some cover on the Government policy in respect of the persecution they have indulged in of the ex-Commissioner of the Gárda. There is victimisation there; there is persecution there and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to get this perfectly clear.  The alleged victimisation of General O'Duffy does not arise on this Vote.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good.  The annuities are in order because they were one of the subjects specifically mentioned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Brief reference may be made to the subject.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I will make one short reference to them.  I presume it will not be out of order to refer to what is described&mdash;humorously, I suppose, but nevertheless described&mdash;as the legal opinion on the matter?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is ill advised in asking the indulgence of the Chair in advance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1711" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>On a certain page, page 12, of &ldquo;The reply of counsel consulted by the National Executive of Fianna Fáil to the arguments advanced in respect of the action of the late Government in paying a sum equivalent to the Land Commission annuities to England&rdquo; we find:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;We may add that the state of Ireland in the years 1920-21, the Anglo-Irish war, the prohibition by Dáil Eireann of the payment of annuities, the non-collection and impossibility of collection of the annuities during those years, the outstanding fact that, to all intents and purposes, the annuities were a lost asset to the British, and the fact that the 1920 Act was on the Statute Book, are strong factors to be considered in interpreting the Treaty.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I do not think there was any speaker presiding over the deliberations of counsel when they were drawing up that opinion but I think that if there were he would probably have thrown that out.  &ldquo;The non-collection and the impossibility of collection of annuities during those years&rdquo;&mdash;they were never better collected during the last 12 or 14 years.  The collections in the years 1920-21 were bumper collections. The arrears of annuities at that period were less than they were in our history and that is a matter with which I should like the new Bureau officer to deal and explain. I think he might also explain to Ministers at some length that, when making speeches, they should make sure that the subjects to which they undertake to address themselves are sufficiently known to them to enable them to make an intelligent pronouncement. The Minister for Industry and Commerce, speaking down the country some time last year, referred to the fact that butter as good as any that could be produced in this country, from Australia and New Zealand, was selling on the English market for 8d. per lb.  That statement was not true either as regards the quality of the butter or the price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Deputy contend that the price of butter is relevant to this?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1712" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I am going to connect it up now if you will allow me for a moment, sir.  That is where I think this officer could be of great use to the State, if he were to address himself to the quality of the products produced in this country, to the better quality of them, the better marketing of them and the better advantage to purchasers.  I have got it in now.  In such a case price does not matter. The mistake the Minister makes in his quotation of the price is a negligible matter.  Everybody knows they are weak on figures&mdash;they always were&mdash; and, consequently, a very big responsibility falls on this new officer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnchadhOBriain" hpid="Mr. D. O Briain Mr. D. O Briain">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. O Briain</NameTxt>
      <P>He did not make the blunder about the adverse trade balance that the Deputy made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>The least said about the adverse trade balance the better. It was never higher than it is now&mdash; £16,000,000 with an export of about £3,000,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the one big nought?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>The one big nought is something that that Party can never succeed in emulating.  In the first place the sum of money in dispute at that time was £150,000,000 and we got out for nothing.  The sum in dispute now is about £80,000,000 or £90,000,000, but we are getting out now with our cattle going over and bearing the annuities on their polls or horns.  These stupid interruptions react always on those who make them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>They stir up unpleasant memories.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>No reference whatever was made, in the course of the plea for the appointment of this officer, to the quality of the goods that go out from this country.  Why?  Is it because we are satisfied, or that we hope that the export market of this country is gone, and gone forever?  Why, even recently, when there was an opportunity to sell the products of our Irish distilleries in America no reference whatever came from a single Minister as to the superior quality of Irish whiskey to all others.  The dry humbugs <Col N="1713" /> that are there on the Front Bench and that cannot appreciate quality or anything else&mdash;the Minister for Agriculture has now gone on to milk, and I suppose it is curdling in him&mdash;took no opportunity to refer to the superior quality of Irish whiskey, due to this that Irish whiskey is pot-still whiskey.  The Americans would be well advised, if they want to provide themselves with a wholesome diet, to pay twice or three times the price for Irish whiskey that they are paying for whiskey from other places.  There is nothing to indicate that there has been any activity on the part of this officer in connection with that matter.  There is no suggestion either that anything has been done to emphasise the fact that the quality of Irish butter going over fresh to the British market is insuperably better than the butter which comes to it from the ends of the earth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>And no reference to the superiority of Irish horses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>From what I have seen of Ministers who sit on Irish horses they simply make a show of them.  Everyone knows the quality of Irish horses.  There was no mention of that either in connection with this office, and no mention of the loss that the British themselves are sustaining by reason of the fact that they are not capable of getting into this market here or of stopping anything from coming over here.  Last year the amount that we got for horses was only about one-tenth of what we got in previous years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair has already ruled that such matters are not relevant to this debate.  The Deputy is now trying to discuss in another way all the matters with which this Bureau might deal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite, sir.  I am putting it that the Government could have made a far better case for this office than the case they have made: that they are going on the wrong line: that they have political spectacles on their eyes and are ignoring the great big <Col N="1714" /> questions which are at issue and which it might deal with.  What is it for? To put out to the country and to the world a different complexion on events as they are.  That is the Government case.  Where bread is slightly coloured they want to tell the people that it is in their eyes the colouring is: that the quality of the bread is perfect.  I am putting it that if there be a Vote for an officer of this sort there should be a direction as to how his activities might be employed, a slight change in the sphere of his activities, so that there might result some benefit, not alone to the trade of the country but to the general good of the country.</P>
      <P>Last night I was scandalised&mdash;I have occasionally been on a racecourse&mdash;to hear a Deputy want to make a bet, or a wager, which I think is the proper description of a bet, about something that had already happened and was decided.  For the information of those who are innocent about transactions of that sort I want to say that a wager can only be about some matter which has not yet been decided: in other words, about a race or an event which is to take place, the result of which is not known to the parties.  Anyone who has had experience of honest bookmakers will tell you that they will not take a bet after a race because it has then been decided.  The reason is that there is no question of speculation involved, and if one makes a bet in respect of a thing that is already settled he is either welshing or trying to make a welsher of the other party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>On that principle there is no use in you betting that you will ever get into office again in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>It is so much of a certainty that I would be almost taking your money.  As a matter of fact, if one were looking for any indication of that, this Vote is perhaps the surest indication one could have.  Reference was made last night to the usefulness of a certain organ.  I recollect that after the elections in 1932 practically every single &ldquo;i&rdquo; was dotted and every &ldquo;t&rdquo; crossed in its reference to the <Col N="1715" /> President of the Executive Council. There was no mistake there.  There was a reference made to myself.  It was very short.  It included only what everybody knew: that I had been President of the Executive Council for ten years and then it proceeded to lie&mdash; stating that I had been elected M.P. for St. Patrick's division in 1918 or 1919.  I object to this Vote.  If I were politically-minded I would be delighted and glad to see this office established because it is an indication of the state of mind of the Ministry: that they are weak, tottering, unable for their jobs, unequal to their responsibilities, and entirely unfitted to put their policy before the people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnchadhOBriain" hpid="Donnchadh O Briain Donnchadh O Briain">
      <NameTxt>Donnchadh O Briain</NameTxt>
      <P>The people do not think that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>The people make mistakes now and then.  Fortunately for themselves they can correct mistakes they have made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnchadhOBriain" hpid="Donnchadh O Briain Donnchadh O Briain">
      <NameTxt>Donnchadh O Briain</NameTxt>
      <P>And they have done it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>If the purpose was to put plain issues in an honest straightforward way before the country, the only question that would arise in connection with this office is: is it necessary? It is not necessary in our opinion.  The people are sufficiently intelligent here to be able to appraise for themselves the value of any and every economic, financial and political proposal put before them.  They do not need to be told, say, by this official of the State that the new officers are to be crown soldiers at 5/- a head.  They could learn that for themselves.  They do not need to be told that if we go in for an extensive tillage policy we must have a market for our live stock and live-stock products. They do not need to be told that if they cannot sell fat cattle in England, or if they have lost the sale of 50 per cent. of these fat cattle in England, they had better let them out on grass and let them become stores. They do not need to be told that if a man gets 15/11, as I have seen on one docket, for an animal sold in England for £6, that that is sound business.  It <Col N="1716" /> is not sound business and no possible activity of an officer such as this can convince anybody that this country is going to prosper if a man gets 15/11 for an animal which fetches in England £6.  They do not need to be told that the fact that sires such as Blandford, Stratford and Trigo are going over to England is benefiting the Irish horse trade.  What they really want to be told is when the Government intend to redeem the promise made last year that, when elected to office, the economic war would be immediately settled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJKeyes" hpid="Mr. Keyes Mr. Keyes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keyes</NameTxt>
      <P>Having heard the long, rambling mass of irrelevancies put forward by the Opposition, it is well to consider what the purpose of this Vote really is.  As I understand, it is a Vote for the establishment of a Bureau to give, with authority and truth, information as to the actual policy of the Party controlling the destiny of the country.  That there is necessity for that can be gleaned from the remarks &mdash;the envenomed and jaundiced remarks&mdash;of the Opposition; led by the chief vitriol-thrower, Deputy Desmond Fitzgerald.  Other members of the Opposition have shown that they are capable of doing the same thing, even the amiable Deputy MacDermot, who seems to have got contaminated with the virus by association and could find no better epithet to hurl at the President than liar&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>I protest most strongly against the statement that I called the President of the Executive Council a liar.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJKeyes" hpid="Mr. Keyes Mr. Keyes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keyes</NameTxt>
      <P>It was said more suavely. The statement of the Deputy was that he does not, and did not, believe the statement of the President that he was prepared to submit the question to arbitration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not calling the President a liar.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJKeyes" hpid="Mr. Keyes Mr. Keyes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keyes</NameTxt>
      <P>What I say is that it amounts to the same thing.  The Deputy was too suave to put it in that way.  The statement made a short time ago was that the nation was led by an &ldquo;arch-fanatic.&rdquo;  I suggest that if these are the terms <Col N="1717" /> and titles which the Opposition choose to adopt, it is very necessary that a Press Bureau should be set up to curb the evil machinations of people who, elected to do the business of this State, are trying to bring it down. Deputy Norton spoke of the necessity of an Irish Press Bureau to let the world outside know that this country is going through a period of economic evolution, that we are moving from a policy of grass to a new policy.  That should be made known to the people of the world generally.  That much is necessary and the necessity has been intensified by the attitude of the Opposition who seem to think and fear that this policy may succeed and, incidentally, the country with it, and that, with the success of the new policy, there will come the damnation of their hopes of ever getting back to office.  I suggest that their attitude has been most unpatriotic. That is disclosed by their wild shouting lest the truth may get out.  They seem to have only one fear&mdash;that the Bureau will be used for Party purposes.  They seem to forget that the Party for the moment happens to be the Government and that the new policy of the Fianna Fáil Party is entitled to get a trial, and a fair trial.  There seems to be no real objection to the Estimate except the suggestion that the Bureau will be used for Party purposes.  As a way out, why not use the Press Bureau for propaganda on behalf of the Cumann na nGaedheal or U.I.P. policy?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SydneyBMinch" hpid="Mr. Minch Mr. Minch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Minch</NameTxt>
      <P>Or the Labour Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJKeyes" hpid="Mr. Keyes Mr. Keyes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keyes</NameTxt>
      <P>If the policy of the Fianna Fáil Party, which has got the support of the country, is such a damnable thing in the eyes of the Opposition, it would be good political business for them to allow the Government to propagate their new ideas to the fullest extent.  According to them, that will mean their speedy dissolution.  According to the U.I.P., the policy of the Government can lead to nothing but bankruptcy.  The wider the publicity for that policy the better for the Opposition, because it will hasten the day when the saviours <Col N="1718" /> of the country will come back to office.</P>
      <P>It is most regrettable that, on a motion of this kind, five hours should have been spent in the delivery of most venomous speeches by Deputies on the Opposition Front Bench.  If we get that type of speech from the Front Bench what can we expect from the back benches and the rank and file down the country?  This Vote ought to have been discussed in a reasonable way.  Ex-President Cosgrave has devoted out of a speech of 45 minutes the last five minutes to reasoned opposition to the establishment of the Bureau.  I think that any impartial listener seated on these benches or in the gallery must be satisfied that if, for no other reason than the bitterness of the Opposition speeches, it is essential that the truth should be told&mdash;that it should be known that this country is not going bankrupt, that the productivity of the soil has lost nothing even though the land has lost some of its cash value, that the unemployed who are causing such anxiety to the Opposition&mdash;they did not worry them when in office, when they adopted the slogan &ldquo;No responsibility for the employment of a single man&rdquo;&mdash;are having their interests attended to. The Bureau can inform the world that steps are being taken to see that no man will go hungry in the country while there is a shilling left in the Exchequer.  The world can be told that we are getting back, by the scientific application of the labour of our people to production and tillage, to an era of self-sufficiency that has not been reached in 150 years of our history.  It is very essential that these things be told so as to remove the mists of calumny by which an attempt is being made to bar the progress of the country under the present regime.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="The Attorney-General The Attorney-General">
      <NameTxt>The Attorney-General</NameTxt>
      <P>I intervene merely to deal with the allegation of Deputy Fitzgerald that we have set up a censorship.  I shall explain to the House how it came about that certain passages not printed in this week's <i>United Ireland</i> came before me for consideration and how the printers or <Col N="1719" /> editors thought fit to excise these passages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>On instructions from the police.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="The Attorney-General The Attorney-General">
      <NameTxt>The Attorney-General</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know whether Deputy Fitzgerald, when he made the statement, really understood the position or knew the facts.  If he did, I doubt if, merely from the point of view of practical wisdom, he would have attempted to make capital out of what happened.  The facts are: On one occasion, the organ of the Opposition printed seditious matter.  The Military Tribunal decided that it was seditious and directed its suppression.  Since that date, by arrangement with the printer&mdash;and, as I understood and the Guards understood, by the agreement of those responsible for the publication. the publishers and editor&mdash;a proof copy of the paper was sent each week to the Guards with a view to having it looked at by the Guards and seeing whether there was any matter in it to which objection might be taken.  On the day before yesterday, the officer of the Guards who was given this copy brought it to me, and he informed me that it was a proof copy of the paper.  I looked through it and said that it seemed to me that certain passages in it amounted to sedition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Why?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="The Attorney-General The Attorney-General">
      <NameTxt>The Attorney-General</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to argue with the Deputy as to why I considered it seditious.  I wish the Deputy would not interrupt.  The Deputy made an unwarranted attack and at least I might be allowed to reply.  I told the officer that he might inform the printers that if they printed the paper with those passages in it I would consider whether an application might not be made to the Military Tribunal in respect to that matter. The officer concerned, I am informed by him, carried out those instructions. He went to the printers and told them that objection was taken to these particular passages.  The printer asked: &ldquo;Am I compelled not to print those passages?&rdquo;  The officer said: &ldquo;You are <Col N="1720" /> not so compelled, but if you do print them an application may be made to the Military Tribunal to deal with the matter.&rdquo;  Apparently, as I understand, the printer got in touch with the editor and between them they evidently accepted the view I had taken and decided not to print the passages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Attorney-General would now move to report progress.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>If it is in order, sir, I think it would be more satisfactory to everybody to hear the explanation of the Attorney-General now, if he will give it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to hear his explanation now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask the House to listen to the completion of the reply of the Attorney-General to the statement made last night.  It will only take a few moments more.  I do not suggest a debate on the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>My information is not identical with that of the Attorney-General.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>If there is general agreement that we hear the Attorney-General, and only him, on the matter, the Chair is quite willing to hear him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that course would be satisfactory to everybody.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It is understood that we only hear the Attorney-General and only with regard to the suppression of certain matters in the paper concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>As I said before, my information is not identical with the Attorney-General's information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="The Attorney-General The Attorney-General">
      <NameTxt>The Attorney-General</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy will have an opportunity of dealing with that matter afterwards.  There is very little to be added to what I have said to-day.  My information was verified <Col N="1721" /> this morning by the officer concerned, which was to the effect that he distinctly informed the printer that, if he wished to print that matter, it was quite open to him to do so, and that, apparently in agreement with whomever is in charge of the paper&mdash;and, judging by the contents of this paper, I should imagine the Deputy had a good deal to do with it and was probably consulted &mdash;it was decided not to print the passages.  In any case, the result of the consideration of the matter by the printer and his publishers and editor was that these passages were excised voluntarily by the people themselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Under threat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="The Attorney-General The Attorney-General">
      <NameTxt>The Attorney-General</NameTxt>
      <P>The only threat was that if this matter appeared I might consider making an application to the Military Tribunal.  Is there anything wrong about that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Was there not also the statement of the Attorney-General to the officer that, in his opinion, these passages were seditious?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="The Attorney-General The Attorney-General">
      <NameTxt>The Attorney-General</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already said so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a fair tip to the printer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="The Attorney-General The Attorney-General">
      <NameTxt>The Attorney-General</NameTxt>
      <P>It is possible that I may be guilty of some wrong-doing, but I understood that this was really in ease of the printer&mdash;an arrangement they themselves made voluntarily with the Guards.  I was only brought in in the way I have mentioned, when the Guard brought the paper to me.  I understood the whole matter was voluntarily arranged between the printers and the Guards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course, the printer is up against the tyranny of your own Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardSidneyAnthony" hpid="Mr. Anthony Mr. Anthony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Anthony</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Attorney-General read for the House the passages excised in this article so that the House might have some opportunity of judging whether they were seditious or not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKelly" hpid="Mr. T. Kelly Mr. T. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>They were read here last night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1722" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Attorney-General seems to think that the printer was under complete liberty to print these passages if he wished and I would like to get it clear that what happened was that the police officer told the printer: &ldquo;The Attorney-General's opinion is that this is seditious; you may print it if you like, but, if so, the Attorney-General will consider whether he will not bring you before the Military Tribunal.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="The Attorney-General The Attorney-General">
      <NameTxt>The Attorney-General</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, that is correct.  I move to report progress.</P>
      <P>Progress reported.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Deputies' Business. - Relief" RHead="of Rates on Agricultural Land">
    <Title>Private Deputies' Business. - Relief of Rates on Agricultural Land.</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:&mdash;</P>
    <P>That the Dáil condemns the action of the Government in reducing the total of the grants payable for the relief of rates on agricultural land.&mdash; (Deputies Belton, O'Higgins and Minch).</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee) Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>It may avoid unnecessary interruption, sir, and permit me to conclude my speech in an orderly manner if I, first of all, draw the attention of the House to the terms of the motion.  The motion is:</P>
      <P>That the Dail condemns the action of the Government in reducing the total of the grants payable for the relief of rates on agricultural land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I ask that, before that motion receives the support of any Deputy, they should ask themselves what grounds there are for condemning the action of the Government in reducing the total of the grants payable for the relief of rates on agricultural land.  Obviously, it can only be on the grounds that the present Government has not done as much as it is possible for any Government to do, in present circumstances, in order to relieve the burdens upon agriculture. I said, as much as it is possible for any Government to do.  The powers and possibilities of this, or of any other Government, to do more for the farmers than we are doing can only be measured and assessed by what our <Col N="1723" /> predecessors did.  In the course of this speech I have drawn the attention of the House to the fact that we have reduced the land annuities by over £2,063,000 yearly, that we have provided export bounties this year amounting to £2,350,000, or, in actual fact, as the expenditure that has taken place up to the present shows, to £2,500,000.  For a milk scheme we have provided £100,000, for the development of a turf scheme we have provided £150,000, for the promotion of tillage and the better marketing of our agricultural products, £85,000, and under the Old Age Pensions Act of 1932 we have placed in the households of Irish farmers and of Irish farm-workers no less a sum than £600,000.  We have taken effective steps to revive the tobacco industry, so that up to date, on the lowest computation, Irish farmers this year will reap a net profit of over £100,000.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this the same speech that the Minister made the other night?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope I will be allowed to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>Why do you not get the Official Report and read it out? Tell us something new.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputies have very short memories, and I merely want to remind them of what we did.  This is relevant to what I am going to say, if the Deputy will permit me to continue. In addition to reintroducing the cultivation of tobacco, we are extending the cultivation of sugar beet.  By incurring capital expenditure amounting to over £2,000,000 per annum, and assuming a considerable Exchequer burden, we are making it possible for farmers and rural workers, out of the beet crop alone, to make between £600,000 and £700,000 per annum.  As I stated last week, these are solid and lasting things we have done for Irish farmers.  In the last year our predecessors were in office, when they were, in the classic phrase of the ex-President of the Executive Council, &ldquo;bidding high for votes,&rdquo; they were only able to find for some of these, or <Col N="1724" /> for similar purposes, £1,812,000.  The difference between the two figures, £6,326,000 and £1,812,000, does not represent the margin by which we found it possible to do more for the Irish farmers than the Government which had been ten years in office, with ten years to think out some scheme of amelioration, and some scheme of national development, to put agricultural production upon a secure and prosperous basis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister say that the farmers got that money?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, every penny piece.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister say why agricultural labourers' wages have come down all over the country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Because of the ramp started by the Party opposite, a ramp in which those who participated last year will pay for this year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>Rubbish!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I will have to ask&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not so.  Where would the Minister learn about agriculture, not in the streets of Belfast?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is entitled to make his speech without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister explain what he meant by his reference to those who started the ramp last year, that they will pay this year?  It would be interesting to develop that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Wait and see.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not afraid of your threats.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask the Minister from whom all the millions came? Was it not from the people who have been injured?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister said that the other night.  It comes out of one pocket and goes into the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am going to try to ignore the interruptions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1725" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to interrupt the Minister, but I suggest, if he is making the case to the House that the farmers have got from the present Government £6,326,000 that they never got before, he should, when dealing with the motion before the House, address himself to the fact that all over the country agricultural labourers' wages are down, and that in every part of the country the people find a real difficulty in meeting their obligations, as far as rates and taxes go.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to take the Deputy's assertion as representing the real facts of the case.  On the contrary, we find that in the poorest districts people have been able to meet their overhead charges, annuities and rates, and pay the shopkeepers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister knows nothing about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy O'Leary can make a speech and tell the House what he thinks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>I have made my speech, but it is very hard for a man like me to listen to the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It may be painful.  The Deputy can make a speech afterwards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>I would have to go to the crossroads.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I find difficulty in resuming.  I do not know which of these gorillas I am going to tackle first.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnONeill" hpid="Mr. O'Neill Mr. O'Neill">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Neill</NameTxt>
      <P>What did the Minister say?  I ask him to explain.  I think he referred to some members as gorillas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, he spells it guerilla.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not conducting a kindergarten for the benefit of Deputy O'Neill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnONeill" hpid="Mr. O'Neill Mr. O'Neill">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Neill</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister ought to speak clearly so that we can understand him.  He is liable to be misinterpreted, because we do not know what he is saying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1726" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Mulcahy asked me how it was that people were not able to meet their obligations in certain districts.  I deny that people are not able to meet their obligations in certain districts.  I admit that people are not meeting their obligations in certain districts, and in the opening part of my speech on this motion I showed a fairly conclusive and convincing reason why people are not meeting their obligations. I ascribed it to the deliberate campaign to deter people from paying their rates and discharging their other debts, which had been embarked upon by some of those associated with the Opposition.  I say this, that recently I have been in contact with representative organisations of manufacturers and distributors, and I heard it stated there over and over again, by people who can speak with knowledge and experience, that never has it been so easy for them to collect their ordinary trade debts as it has been during the past 12 months. Therefore, I say, when you see the people in the poorer districts paying rates and annuities, when you hear manufacturers and distributors saying that they have fewer bad debts, and that it is easier to collect money this year than for the past ten years, there cannot be such a state of depression existing in the country as would justify the reduction in certain areas of agricultural wages.  That is only part of the ramp which has been started by the Party opposite.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister allow me?  In examining the case of country shopkeepers and banks, will he venture to say that either one or the other had no difficulty in collecting outstanding debts?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I know this, that the banks of this country are just in as safe, secure and stable position as they were at any time since 1918.  In fact they are in a stronger position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>That is another matter.  I am talking of collecting old debts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to say further that any reduction that exists in bank <Col N="1727" /> profits has been due almost entirely to the increased taxation which those undertakings have had to bear and not to any difficulty they have experienced in collecting amounts due to them by their debtors.  I was talking about the rates of agricultural wages in this country.  I was saying that if there was any reduction in agricultural wages, it was only part of the deliberate and organised ramp that has been undertaken by members of the Opposition Party, a ramp similar to that which was set on foot as the result of a conference here of leading supporters of Deputy Belton and his associates, who came together and began to consider what elements in agricultural production at the present moment were showing a substantial return to the farmer and who arrived at the conclusion that amongst them was milk.  They decided that the price of milk in certain areas must be brought down to an uneconomic level and approached certain large dairying undertakings in the vicinity of the city to get them to reduce the price of milk in order that they might be able to turn round and say that the farmer is not getting in 1933-34 the price for milk that he was getting in 1931-32.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister name the date of this conference?  Will he name the time and place that the conference took place?  Will he name a solitary individual that was at the conference?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am going to say this that Deputy Belton was the mover in the whole thing&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Belton denies that he knows anything about any such conference.  I never attended a milk conference in my life.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am taking his denial in the same spirit as his denial that he ever said that if the farmers of the country had sufficient backbone there would be a rates strike.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister wants to repeat a statement he made in the House and withdrew, he can go on. Because that is the character of the <Col N="1728" /> man who is Minister, I am not going to ask him to withdraw.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it only now you know?  You are a soft man if it is only now you know his character.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I was saying that if there is this air of depression, this atmosphere of depression that has been artificially engendered&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>You do not feel it with your £2,000 a year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I can take an example that will show that the position of this country at the present time is no worse than it was 12 months ago, or as bad as it was 24 months ago.  I am sorry, however, that Deputy Mulcahy led me off the direction which I intended to pursue this morning.  I would remind the House that I have endeavoured to show how much more we did than our predecessors.  We are told, of course, that the cattle trade is in a depressed condition owing to the restrictions which have been imposed on the admission of our cattle to the British markets.  We are not denying that the introduction of those restrictions and those tariffs has imposed undoubted burdens upon those engaged in the cattle industry, but we say that we have alleviated to the fullest possible extent any hardship that might have been occasioned, and that irrespective of the political course that we pursued the Irish farmer inevitably would have been faced with these restrictions, that it was only the lack of foresight displayed by our predecessors which left this Government when it came into office in the position that it had not the machinery available to deal with the development in British agriculture which was inevitable from the day that the National Government, as they call it, was returned in 1931.  If you want proof of that you have only to read the statements made by the British Minister for Agriculture speaking in the House of Commons last night.  He said that if the Government had not restricted Free State exports in December, it was absolutely certain that there would have been a catastrophic decline in the price of <Col N="1729" /> British home produced livestock. &ldquo;The British Government,&rdquo; Mr. Elliott went on to say, &ldquo;were accused of endangering the relations between Britain and the Free State.&rdquo;  I am sorry that Deputy MacDermot has left the House, because he is one of those who justifies his present attitude in regard to the dispute between Great Britain and ourselves on the question of the land annuities by saying that we have complicated the whole issue by political considerations, and made it more difficult to deal with.  Here is the answer given, not by a member of the Free State Government, but given by a member of the British Government, Major Elliot, to that allegation.  He says: &ldquo;The measure was not dictated by any desires of political expediency, but by the stern facts of economic necessity.&rdquo;  There are Deputies opposite, Deputy Keating for instance, who in every debate on this matter have but one parrot-cry to utter: &ldquo;Give us back our markets.&rdquo;  I saw during the last session one of the most disgraceful scenes I ever witnessed.  I saw the then Centre Party, as it was called, in a state of delirious excitement howling at the head of this Government, the head of the Irish people, and shouting: &ldquo;Give us back our markets.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeating" hpid="Mr. Keating Mr. Keating">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>There is Major Elliot for you stating that it does not matter what Government was in power in this country, those markets are no longer available to the Irish people on the same unrestricted scale as hitherto, that stern economic necessity has driven the British Government to reduce the imports into Britain&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeating" hpid="Mr. Keating Mr. Keating">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>Were you not asking for it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGovern" hpid="Mr. McGovern Mr. McGovern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGovern</NameTxt>
      <P>Are they not being sent to Britain from Canada?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Now, who is playing England's game?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Did not the Ministry opposite run away from Ottawa?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry that the beneficent Creator&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1730" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardSidneyAnthony" hpid="Mr. Anthony Mr. Anthony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Anthony</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister deny that if the markets were open tomorrow, the stern economic necessity would disappear?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry that the beneficent Creator of Deputy Belton did not endow him with greater intelligence, sufficient intelligence to prevent his asking a question of that sort.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask the Minister whether Major Elliot is not talking to-day in the way he is because the Ministers representing the Party opposite ran away from Ottawa?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Not at all.  If Major Elliot wished to find a simple justification for the measures which are now being taken by Great Britain he would have turned round and said it is because of the economic war; he would have taken up the parrot-cry of the benches opposite.  But instead of that he tells the truth about the matter, because he knows that whether we are in power or whether you are in power &mdash;and God forbid for the country's sake that that should ever happen again&mdash; the same thing will continue whether the economic dispute is settled or not. Whether political differences are resolved or not, all the time there will remain the stern economic necessity which will compel any British Minister for Agriculture, acting in the interests of the British farmers, to impose some restriction on the entrance of Irish cattle into the British market.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardSidneyAnthony" hpid="Mr. Anthony Mr. Anthony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Anthony</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is talking with his tongue in his cheek.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not the whole trouble in this matter the stern necessity for saving the faces of Ministers on the far side that keeps them out of engaging in a fight with the British authorities to get us our place in the British markets?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That statement is too involved for me to follow.  By the Ministers on the far side I presume the Deputy means members of the British Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot see the relevancy of the interruption&mdash;I am <Col N="1731" /> dense about it.  I must say that the Deputy's interruption is not very clear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister talked of the markets for this country in Great Britain.  The Minister knows that the Executive Council sent Ministers to Ottawa to discuss the whole matter, and that to save their political faces the Ministers sent to Ottawa evacuated their trenches and left the field to the British Government. The President, in an interview given to a British journalist the other day, said: &ldquo;We ask nothing from Great Britain any more than they would give to Denmark or Holland.&rdquo; We ask a lot more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Now that the Deputy has made his contribution to the debate will he allow me to proceed and to say that it does not matter what happened at Ottawa?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>It does.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The restrictions were not imposed at Ottawa.  They were imposed in December and, according to the member of the British Government responsible for agricultural policy at present, if these restrictions had not been imposed it was absolutely certain that there would have been a catastrophic decline in the price of British home-produced livestock.  If there had been a catastrophic decline in the price of British-produced livestock would not there have been an equally catastrophic decline in the price of Irish-produced livestock?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>So there is.  Has not the Minister for Agriculture suggested birth control for cattle?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>As a matter of fact, I understand that since the  were introduced there has been a rise in cattle prices here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeating" hpid="Mr. Keating Mr. Keating">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>If you were in the Dublin cattle market yesterday you would not say that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I think if I were in the Dublin cattle market I would be able to appreciate more intelligently the trend of events than Deputy Keating ever indicates he is able to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1732" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeating" hpid="Mr. Keating Mr. Keating">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy knows what he is talking about, but you do not.  You do not take an interest in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>All I know is that there is a grave difference of opinion between Deputy Keating and the other members of his Party as to whether  not the farmer gets any benefit from the bounties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeating" hpid="Mr. Keating Mr. Keating">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>Had not we a preference in the British market until you came into power?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware that we had any preference.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeating" hpid="Mr. Keating Mr. Keating">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>We had.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>We had not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeating" hpid="Mr. Keating Mr. Keating">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>Had we not free </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>You are not going  have that any longer, no matter whether we are in power or whether you are in power.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeating" hpid="Mr. Keating Mr. Keating">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>You did the dirty trick.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>We are the people responsible then.  We are responsible for it because we refused to pay the land annuities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeating" hpid="Mr. Keating Mr. Keating">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we not paying the land annuities?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Absolutely.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Keating has not made a speech on this motion yet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeating" hpid="Mr. Keating Mr. Keating">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to make one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Cannot the Deputy give us all this information by way of a speech instead of by way of interruption?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeating" hpid="Mr. Keating Mr. Keating">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>Why is he asking for it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is entitled to make his speech without interruption.  If Deputy Keating gets up to make a speech he is also entitled to make it without interruption. He ought to give us all this information by way of speech and not by way of interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1733" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeating" hpid="Mr. Keating Mr. Keating">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>He is asking for interruptions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Very well.  Major  does not carry conviction with the members of the Party opposite, and of course, the whole of the bother and all these cattle restrictions have not been made necessary by the stern economic necessity, as the British Minister for Agriculture declares them to have been, but are occasioned by political considerations merely; by the fact that we have refused to pay the land annuities.  I should like to make myself strictly relevant by saying that the Dáil is now asked to condemn the action of the Government in reducing the total of the grants payable for the relief of rates on agricultural land.  I pointed out the extent to which the Government has gone to alleviate the  representing, I believe, the  limit to which any Government could go.  As to the argument put forward by the Opposition, that the present situation has been created by our refusal to pay the land annuities over to Great Britain, I should like to refer to the statement made by General O'Duffy in Monaghan on Tuesday last, and fully reported in the <i>Irish Independent,</i> that any succeeding Government of which he might be the head, or with which he might be associated, would be in exactly the same position that we are and would be unable to do any more for the farmers towards the relief of rates on agricultural land.  We have been told now that the source and origin of this dispute has been our refusal to pay the land annuities.  What possibility is there of terminating that dispute, if, in fact, the non-payment of the land annuities has been the cause of it, when the Party opposite have adopted this as their policy: &ldquo;that the land annuities would never be paid to England again, no matter what Government was in power; the attitude that Fine Gael took up in the whole position was that the country was unable to pay 100 per cent. or 50 per cent. of its debts, and they only asked England to treat this country as she would wish America to treat her.  Even in that matter the basis of any arrangement <Col N="1734" /> must be &lsquo;honour.&rsquo;&rdquo;  Honour is put in inverted commas.</P>
      <P>If the land annuities are never again going to be paid by any other Government, no matter what Government may be in power, how are these restrictions which we have been told were occasioned by the non-payment of the land annuities ever going to be removed?  How and when are they going to be removed?  If they are not removed, what more can any Government do than we have done by granting relief of rates upon agricultural land?  We are told that it is not going to be done by sitting down at a table, as Deputy MacDermot on occasions has asked us to do, and trying to come to some give-and-take settlement.  According to General O'Duffy, we are unable to pay 100 per cent. or even 50 per cent. of our debts and there is not going to be one penny piece of the land annuities ever again to go to England.  We cannot have even this private hugger-mugger over a table which our predecessors were so fond of and as a result of which they entered into the 1923 and 1926 agreements and the Boundary Settlement.  Friendly hugger-mugger is ruled out.</P>
      <P>We are standing in this position, that we cannot pay a penny piece, according to General O'Duffy.  But the basis of settlement must be one of honour, honour being in inverted commas.  We are not saying that we are not paying them, according to General O'Duffy, because the amounts are not due and the land annuities properly belong to us.  We are merely saying: &ldquo;We will not pay them, because you are an arranging debtor yourself.  We will not pay because you are an arranging debtor in respect to moneys which you owe, and, because you are trying to bilk your creditors, we are going to bilk them too and we are going to see that an arrangement based upon that argument is going to be one of honour.&rdquo; It is not much wonder that even the <i>Irish Independent</i> could not stomach what General O'Duffy declared, and they put the word honour in inverted commas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The only way in which any element <Col N="1735" /> of honour might be imported into a settlement of that kind would be that General O'Duffy, or those who endeavour to negotiate the kind of arrangement which he foreshadows, should have reduced this country to such a situation that when they would be in office for an appreciable period as a Government they could go across and say: &ldquo;Look at us.  We could have paid the annuities in 1923 and we did pay them until 1932.  We have come into power; we were put into power because we induced the majority of the people to believe that we were supermen. We have been allowed to govern. There is nobody going up and down the country organising private armies, nobody suborning local authorities not to do their duty in collecting rates, no person conspiring to overthrow local administration.  We have been given a fair chance and yet, having got that fair chance, the country is in such a condition that we cannot pay a penny piece of its just debts.&rdquo; That is, the debts that Deputy MacDermot, if not General O'Duffy, contends are justly due.  That is the only sort of arrangement which, on the arguments made by the Opposition Party, would contain any element of honour.  And even then it would be a purely <i>ad misericordiam</i> appeal based on this fact, that General O'Duffy's administration had reduced this country and its people to a condition of abject poverty.</P>
    <P>The Party which envisages that situation asks the Dáil to condemn us because we have reduced the total of the rates upon agricultural land.  If General O'Duffy does succeed in throwing over, not merely Deputy MacDermot, but also Deputies Cosgrave, McGilligan and Fitzgerald and does enter into a settlement with Great Britain which would be an honourable settlement based upon his declaration that never again will the land annuities be paid to Great Britain&mdash;if he does succeed in doing that and the settlement is, in fact, an honourable settlement, is it not clear that it can only be an honourable settlement because the British will have admitted that what we have contended in this <Col N="1736" /> House is true, that the agreements of 1923 and 1926 were not valid agreements and were not agreements which those who entered into them had any right to make?</P>
    <P>I would like Deputy Mulcahy, who has not yet spoken, to tell us how the settlement which General O'Duffy envisages and under which never again will the annuities be paid to England, no matter what government is in power, can be one of honour and how the present Opposition can maintain the attitude which they have hitherto taken up on this matter.  They contend we are in honour bound to pay them; they contend that if they are restored to power the economic position of this country will be so improved that we will be able to meet all our obligations, even those which they desired to fix on us under the agreements of 1923 and 1926.  Even if the unexpected happens and General O'Duffy is returned to power, as things are at present shaping will he ever be in the position to convince the British or any impartial judges that we would not be in a position to pay these annuities if they were properly due?</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order.  As the mover of the motion I would be quite glad to see the debate ranging over as wide a field as possible, but I think it is going beyond the limit now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It is beyond that long ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>New elements are brought into it now as to how General O'Duffy, if he comes to power&mdash;he is not in power and according to the Government he is a long way from power&mdash;will settle a question that is not before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not care how wide the Minister goes I will follow him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I have shown, sir, that these questions are intimately associated with each other.  The House is asked to &ldquo;condemn the action of the Government in reducing the total of the grants payable for the relief of rates <Col N="1737" /> on agricultural land.&rdquo; If those who moved that motion were unable to show that they will be in a better position than we are to grant the additional relief asked for, then&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to submit to the Minister that he is not discussing No. 9 on the Order Paper, that is the motion about de-rating.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I am discussing No. 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>His present remarks should be more aptly addressed to the motion about de-rating. That is the motion which the Minister is seeking to avoid having to discuss.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid he is mixing them up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>If Deputy Belton had not to accept responsibility for the statements made by his leader and defend them here in the House&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>According to the Minister Deputy Belton has to accept responsibility for a lot of statements he has never made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I will try to deal with the motion from another aspect.  The motion reads:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the Dáil condemns the action of the Government in reducing the total of the grants payable for the relief of rates on agricultural land.</P>
      <P>I have recited already what we have done for the farmers in the course of the present year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SydneyBMinch" hpid="Mr. Minch Mr. Minch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Minch</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister going to continue wasting the time of the House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKelly" hpid="Mr. T. Kelly Mr. T. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Withdraw your motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not wasting the time of the House.  I am dealing with this matter as seriously as I am permitted to deal with it by the continuous interruptions from the Deputies opposite.  That motion means, I presume, that over and above the £8,189,000 which we have devoted to agricultural relief this year, that we should find some more money and spend it in the particular way which the motion suggests.  But Deputy <Col N="1738" /> Belton surely will not have forgotten the speech of his vice-leader, Deputy Dillon, in which he condemned us because we had increased taxation by, I think, £1,189,000 over and above the figure for 1928-29.  Possibly Deputy Belton in his reply will explain to us how we can increase the amount which will be available for the relief of rates on agricultural land, maintain our present agricultural services, continue the existing provisions for the relief of the farmers and at the same time reduce taxation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Sure.  I would not like to take your job away from you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>If we were to accept this motion, the effect would be to transfer some part of the existing burden borne by the agricultural ratepayers on to the Central Fund.  Deputy Belton knows, as well as I do, that the additional money which would be required in order to make that transfer operative could only be raised by imposing additional taxation on the necessaries of life.  If we were to do what this motion suggests we should do we would be simply transferring the burden from the backs of the people who can best afford to pay and passing it on to those who are least well off.</P>
      <P>That is what is really behind Deputy Belton's motion.  Deputy Belton is a large landowner.  Most of those associated with his Party are large landowners. Most of those associated with our Party are comparatively small farmers.  Those big men, those shopkeepers who own more land than they can work, the graziers who will not work the land that they own, and all those people who describe themselves as gentlemen farmers and who have led more or less a parasitic existence in this country for the last 60 years, are to go scot free.  That is the meaning of the motion.  And the agricultural worker, the small farmer and the majority of the people in the towns and in the cities are to pay this money in order that the gentlemen who drive in motor cars to protest meetings and who loudly proclaim that they cannot pay their just debts, are to be relieved of their responsibilities to the local communities amongst whom they live.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1739" /> I said last night that Deputy Dillon's Party is the one class-conscious Party in this House, the Party that works for themselves, the Party that thinks nothing of the country and everything of its own class.  That cry of theirs to put the rates on the Central Fund is only another unscrupulous dodge in the movement to bring the Government to its knees.  In the words of Mr. Smith at that famous Cork meeting at which Deputy Dillon participated, &ldquo;by paralysing the local and national administration, by upsetting our finances and destroying our credit,&rdquo; they seek to do this.  Deputy Dillon and Deputy Belton and the other Deputies on the Cumann na nGaedheal Benches who were associated with him in that unpatriotic activity have failed, and dismally failed.</P>
    <P>Outside observers coming here, after reading the speeches of the Opposition Deputies and the statements made by them, have been greatly surprised at what they have found.  They came expecting to find a land desolate and in decay, a people hopeless and famine-stricken. Instead everywhere they have gone they have found signs of prosperity prevailing.  Others who have examined the situation from the statistical point of view have found that the statements made by those who were opposed to the Government were without foundation.  No one will accuse a great English financial periodical like the <i>Economist</i> of being unduly biassed in favour of the present Government. On the contrary, that journal has the reputation of examining and discussing in a judicial spirit, without partisanship or bias, all questions to which its attention is directed.  In its issue of the 17th October last it published a survey of British and foreign banking. This has relevancy to the interruption of Deputy MacDermot.  In the course of that survey it examined the position of the Irish banks.  This, again, is important in connection with the cry that has gone up that the country is being drained of its wealth under the present Government.  In the course of that survey the <i>Economist</i> pointed out that the Irish bank returns at June last were valuable as shedding a light on <Col N="1740" /> the balance of payments of the Irish Free State.  We have been told by Deputy Brennan that this country was living on its capital, and that there was not a single industry paying its way.  Yet, that statement as examined and analysed by the trained staff of the <i>Economist</i> shows that the movement of the excess of the banks, external assets over their external liabilities provided an almost exact measure of the net flow of funds into or out of the Free State.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, is not the statement referred to by the Minister the statement of an individual who is paid for his job&mdash;the Irish correspondent of the <i>Economist</i>&mdash;and who is a civil servant, I think, in the Minister's Department?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I may say, sir, that so far as Deputy Belton's statement goes, I am convinced that the person who wrote that analysis for the <i>Economist</i> is not a civil servant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure he is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>And I am perfectly certain that a journal with the prestige and status of the <i>Economist</i> is not going to publish its considered judgment on a matter like this merely in order to conduct propaganda on behalf of one or other interest in this country or outside it.  The interruption is silly and ridiculous, even more silly and ridiculous than most of the interruptions that come from Deputy Belton. I was saying that the <i>Economist</i>, having pointed out that the excess of the banks' external assets over their external liabilities provided an almost exact measure of the net flow of funds into or out of the Free State, went on to stress that from the first quarter of 1932 to the first quarter of 1933 there was a steady net inflow of funds to the Free State, amounting to more than eight and a half million pounds. A roughly comparable figure for the United Kingdom, the <i>Economist</i> observer went on to say, would be £200,000,000.  Then he went further, and said that the Irish balance of payments in 1933 was therefore strongly favourable, and he ended his examination of this position by <Col N="1741" /> remarking that the accumulated reserves of the Irish banks are so much as to make the financial position of the country manifestly strong.  That statement, because it is the unbiassed opinion of a competent external observer, is much more important than all the vapourings of Deputy Belton or the flippancies of Deputy Dillon, or the frenzies of Deputy Fitzgerald-Kenney. It is the judgment, as I have said the deliberately expressed judgment&mdash; of a competent impartial observer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>It did not say that the economic position was strong.  It said the financial position was strong.  So is the financial position of the United States strong, whatever about the economic position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>What has been said by the <i>Economist</i> in regard to this country is borne out more emphatically even by a publication recently issued by the League of Nations, and entitled &ldquo;World Economic Survey for 1932-3.&rdquo; Deputy Belton has tried to draw some distinction between the financial stability of banks and the economic condition of the country in which the banks carry on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SydneyBMinch" hpid="Mr. Minch Mr. Minch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Minch</NameTxt>
      <P>Why does the President say there is a financial crisis?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Here is the result of a survey made by the League of Nations of the economic conditions, not merely of this country, but throughout the world.  In that volume there is published a diagram indicating the economic conditions of the principal countries of the world.  We figure in that diagram with, among other States, the United Kingdom, Belgium, Switzerland, Germany, Sweden, Italy, the Netherlands, Denmark, Norway, Finland and Poland.  We, this Irish Free State, are definitely shown in the year 1932-33 as one of the States in which economic conditions during the second quarter of 1933 had taken an upward turn.  The improvement had set in in the first quarter of that year, and had persisted through the second quarter.  Every economic index that can be consulted will show that that improvement has gone on continuously ever since.  There is no statistical <Col N="1742" /> index which will not show that our position now is much better than it was at the end of 1932.  Just think how much better it would have been if, in our affairs, the affairs of this State and its people, the Opposition had taken up a more patriotic attitude, an attitude similar to that taken up in other countries whose fortunes were at stake and whose people were going through a great economic change.  The mere fact that we have faced our difficulties, that we are overcoming them, that things are improving, and that all this has been achieved in spite of the Parliamentary Opposition here, and the unconstitutional opposition outside the Dáil, is the strongest condemnation that can be passed upon the futile and mischievous activities of those politicians who blaspheme the sentiment of Irish unity when they call themselves the United Ireland Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKelly" hpid="Mr. T. Kelly Mr. T. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear!  That is good for your souls.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SydneyBMinch" hpid="Mr. Minch Mr. Minch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Minch</NameTxt>
      <P>This debate has developed all round the subject without ever even barely touching it.  We have heard references made to the Ten Commandments, to fish, to the Twelve Apostles, to murder, and every single impossible subject that could be brought in.  Agricultural land is the invisible battlefield on which this economic war is being fought.  We do not know whether we are in the middle of the economic war or whether we have emerged from the economic war or whether there ever was an economic war if we are to listen to the Ministers in their different speeches up and down the country and in this House.  The President of the Executive Council gets up and says there is a national crisis on.  The Minister for Finance gets up and states that we have achieved victory and that his Budget is buoyant.  But when it suits one or the other or any of the back benchers of Fianna Fáil they will stand on one foot, according to the way they think they can win a sympathetic hearing from the electorate.  County councils are, in the main, the great rate collecting bodies in this country. County councils have to do the unpopular work; county councils have <Col N="1743" /> to pass estimates which will bring demands into every home and house in the county looking for money, and county councils, when they pass their full estimate, are generally the recipients of consideration from the Central Fund.  County councils, although they have to do this work, are simply the vassals of other bodies and, instead of being the parent company governing these bodies, they have got to meet huge demands.  What occurs?  The Government chooses a moment in the middle of trade turmoil, and when the majority of the county councils have passed their estimates, to bring in a reduction of the Agricultural Grant to the tune of £500,000, which makes a difference in County Kildare alone of £12,000, a minimum of 1/- in the £.  They chose to do that at a mean moment, and then, after they had gulled the county councils into going on in the hope that they will receive the same decent treatment that they got in the past, they complain when the racket starts, because the hearts and almost the souls are crushed out of the local bodies by that mean action, carried out at the time at which it was carried out. The county councils in some cases were not caught, and when, afterwards, they fought against this mean and low attitude, they were brought into court in several instances and mandamuses sought against them.  It was the only way they had of protesting, and at no period were they not prepared, in fairness and honesty and justice, to collect the rates and to do their duty as citizens, because in the past they have never failed, whether there was a national or an international crisis, to do their job and to do it well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy Norton walked into this House one day with a copy of the <i>Leinster Leader</i> in his hand&mdash;it was probably handed to him by his big secretariat outside or inside.  He had not read it, but he gets up here and accuses me of being a party to a conspiracy in County Kildare for the non-payment of rates.  When challenged on that he withdrew it and suggested that it was a question of the non-payment of land annuities.  Deputy Hugo Flinn, <Col N="1744" /> the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance, the Chairman of Piffle, Twaddle and Company, the absolute muck-raker in this House, who is never happy unless he has his hands up to his armpits in political swill and rubbing it all over his face, said that I was afraid to come into this House and accept the challenge that I advocated the non-payment of rates.  Where is Deputy Flinn now?  He has gone out to rest himself after the exhibition of clowning and buffoonery which he carried on here last night.  I answer Deputy Hugo Flinn that at no time did I advocate the non-payment of rates, and as he has called me &ldquo;this so-called Minch or Deputy Minch,&rdquo; I call him what he is and always was, a coward; and in many instances, in view of what he said here last night, a cad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Those expressions will have to be withdrawn. Deputy Flinn, so far as I recollect the statement made, referred to &ldquo;Minch.&rdquo; He was reminded that the proper way to address a Deputy was by the word &ldquo;Deputy,&rdquo; and he did so then.  The Deputy will have to withdraw the expressions &ldquo;coward&rdquo; and &ldquo;cad.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SydneyBMinch" hpid="Mr. Minch Mr. Minch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Minch</NameTxt>
      <P>Always having respect for the Chair, I will withdraw, and I am sorry for saying it in view of what the Chair has said.  A most unpleasant atmosphere has been created on this motion.  I am the last person in the world to indulge, in this House or outside, in any mud-slinging, but I am never afraid to stand up and take what is coming to me.  Deputy Flinn gets up here as if he were one of the great saviours of Irish nationality.  He spares nobody.  He refers to Deputy O'Higgins, first of all, as Dr. O'Higgins; he refers to him then as Colonel O'Higgins, and then as Deputy O'Higgins. It is all a low attempt to degrade the individual in front of him.  I have listened to Deputy O'Higgins' replies, and at no time has he ever stooped to the low methods adopted by Deputy Flinn, which are a disgrace to this House and to Irish nationality.  In the meantime, while all this is going on, we find that the actual motion and the object which it is designed to bring before the House and have honestly and justly aired, are completely forgotten. <Col N="1745" /> No attempt is made whatever to reply to it on the part of the Minister. He, the eminent statistician, simply juggles with figures, and according to the Minister, if there are two men and one dies, there are, therefore, two men half alive.  Anybody can prove by quoting statistics and plotting graphs any sort of a juggle that he wishes to prove.</P>
      <P>We had Deputy Flinn referring to stockbrokers whose graphs have shown that in the last few years there has been an upward trend.  That might be all right for the mug who does not understand it, but what has been the position?  Two and a half years ago, when the world's stock exchanges were gambling to the sky, there came a huge and appalling collapse, and with it good value shares, shares with intrinsic value which were paying substantial dividends, came down to rubbish prices and all over the world one share brought down another.  Ireland, with its investments in foreign countries, suffered similarly.  Every big stock exchange in the world has an influence on the stock exchange of its neighbouring country.  Large industrial securities&mdash;and the Deputy made no difference between stock and securities or between debentures, preference or ordinary shares&mdash;all went down and collapsed.  By degrees, however, with the righting of the financial exchanges of the world, with Governments grappling with the situation and with unhealthy companies being weeded out and the bucket-shop proprietors and the share-pushers being sent to jail, in many instances, confidence was restored and these shares began to come on a rising market again.  Deputy Hugo Flinn gets up and tries to represent that it was because of the prosperity of this country that these shares began to show an upward trend.  That sort of thing shot across the House is the sort of thing that makes any sane man feel like walking out and refusing to listen to the type of diatribe we have to listen to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What is occurring down the country? As I have said, a war is being fought on agricultural land.  It is being fought with a silver bullet, and the casualties are to be found in men's pockets.  The <Col N="1746" /> county councils are struggling and doing their best to meet the huge demands that will be made upon them by the boards of health, by mental hospitals and by county homes, and they know, and know better than anybody else, through their knowledge of local conditions, how difficult it is to get these moneys and how difficult it is to collect rates.</P>
    <P>We all know the difficulty there is in collecting rates.  In connection with landed proprietors, it is strange that references to class distinctions always emanate from the benches opposite. The man who has land, a motor car, or tries to be a decent Irish citizen, who does his best to live up to his station in life and behaves and acts like a gentleman, is represented from the benches opposite as one who tries to run away and not meet his obligations. But we all know how difficult it is for people to pay their rates.  People with land were never so hard hit as they are at present.  They find it an arduous task to make ends meet.  The local shopkeeper in the country town knows how difficult the farmer's position is. It is all very well for the Minister for Finance to get up and talk about the large manufacturers in Dublin, and their artificial prosperity: to say that they never had a better year than last. In my own business I know how difficult ordinary debt collecting from farmers is.  Business men are obliged to make big sacrifices by reducing debts owed to them and by giving large credits.</P>
    <P>The growing of beet has been referred to.  We are told what a great help it will be to the farmers.  We all know that beet at 30/- a ton is not much better than the growing of potatoes at 3d. a stone.  We have been told, too, what a great blessing the growing of tobacco is going to be to the farmer.  Deputy Cosgrave questioned the Minister for Agriculture about that this morning, and I think it was made pretty clear that it is going to end in a fiasco.  We have been told about the wonderful things done for the farmers, the millions that have been granted to them.  We do not hear from the opposite benches very much about the economic situation, or of all the <Col N="1747" /> millions that are taken off us at the other side.  Under normal conditions all that money would be retained in this country and would be going largely to our producers.  The position at the present time is that millions are being taken from the taxpayers without any direct benefit to this country.  Nearly all of it is collected at the other side.  Taxation has been increased by £4,500,000, while our losses in other directions might be put at more than double that.  What we really need is that farming should be put on a revenue-earning basis. We have subsidies being levied to enable our producers to get into the British market which is supposed not to exist.</P>
    <P>I feel so much about all this that I fear I have not arranged my facts as I should have, and, perhaps have been inclined to go to over-statement, but there is no doubt that things could not be worse than they are at present. This motion has been brought on from honest and sincere motives and yet we are told from the benches opposite that we are traitors, British henchmen and dishonest politicians.  I think it is a shame that such words should be used.  They are really an attempt to bring us under mob law, to incite people to attack our platforms and attempt to hound us down at the cross-roads.  I say that this economic war is being used to deal unfairly and dishonestly with the country.  The people that we represent are as good nationalists as any that ever sat on the benches opposite.  They are decent, Irish people, anxious to do their duty, with clean and honourable records and good family associations.  They will never be afraid to stand up and fight for their country with or without a silver bullet, as they have done in other times, whether it be on the fields of France or of this country.  They resent and repudiate the attacks that have been made on them, the attempt that has been made to degrade them by calling them British henchmen and traitors.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>So much has been said on this motion that one finds it difficult to say anything new on it.  I am <Col N="1748" /> quite prepared to admit that in the awkward position in which the Government find themselves, as a result of the dispute with Great Britain, they have done much from their point of view to mitigate the disadvantages under which our farmers labour at the moment.  While saying that I am not prepared to admit that as a result of the measures taken by the Government the farmers are in the sound financial position that the Minister for Finance would try to suggest.  The Minister made a very long speech to-day and a very long speech last week, and if my opinion is correct I would say it was prepared for him.  I am here to give expression to the opinions I have formed as a result of going amongst the people.  They are the only persons who can give an authoritative statement on the real position at present. Men who have been engaged in farming for 40 or 50 years have told me that never have they found it so difficult to make ends meet as at present. I was very much struck by a statement I heard from one of the largest farmers in the County Louth about a month ago.  What struck me most was the sincerity behind the statement.  He told me that he was forced to sell his farm, that he had to cut adrift from the old ways and that it almost broke his heart to have to dispense with the services of half a dozen labourers whom he had employed for a period extending over 40 years.  His ancestors had also been good employers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is the same story with all the farmers in that county who have to employ men.  Never have I been troubled as often as I have been during the past six months with young men, particularly from the rural areas, seeking the use of whatever little influence I possess to secure employment for them.  Anxious to find out why so many young men from the rural districts came to me in search of work, I made inquiries, and I found that in a very large number of cases their unemployment was due to the fact that the farmers who previously employed them were, owing to the position created by the Government, <Col N="1749" /> unable to employ them any longer. Knowing all these things, and not alone knowing them but feeling them and having sympathy with the position of these young men, I found it very difficult to understand the mentality of the Minister for Finance when he informed the House to-day that, in his opinion, this State whether judged from the economic, industrial or agricultural point of view was never in such a sound position.  Having heard that statement, my simple comment was: &ldquo;Rubbish!&rdquo;  As I said in the beginning, I always prefer the practical to the theoretical.  The Minister for Finance has not gone out amongst the ordinary farmers and inquired from them how they stand both in relation to the reward they receive as a result of their year's labour and in relation to the number of hands which they employ to-day as compared with the number which they employed, say, three years ago.  The Minister who made these statements in regard to unemployment overlooked the official figures of unemployment published in to-day's <i>Independent.</i>  Those figures, if I read them aright, prove only one thing.  I am sorry to say so because I am one of those who always held that country comes before party.  I should be delighted if those unemployment figures showed a considerable decrease but, to my amazement in view of the statements made here by responsible Ministers, the figures published to-day show an increase.  Again, the Minister has stated that if there are more unemployed amongst our rural population, it is because the members of the Opposition Party, backed up by their supporters throughout the country, have deliberately embarked on a campaign of dismissal of their labourers in order to show that the country is not doing well.  Again, I say that that is a deliberate misstatement of fact, in view of the inquiries which I have made.  Not alone are those statements untrue, but I am sure the Minister will, on calm reflection, agree with me when I say that, knowing the character of many of the large farmers of the county which I have the honour to represent, knowing their family history and knowing the <Col N="1750" /> good relations which always existed between them and those who served them, there is not one shred of truth in that allegation.  On the contrary, that is the last thing which these people would like to do.  I should like to inform the Minister if he were here and the President of the Executive Council as well&mdash;the members of the Fianna Fáil Party will, I think, agree with me in this&mdash;that there are many large farmers in every county of the State who are broken-hearted because they are no longer able to keep in employment the number of hands that they used to keep.  They did it as long as their financial resources permitted them.  Owing to the relations which exist between the Government of this State and the Government of Great Britain, they are not in a position to carry on any longer in the way which they did up to the start of the economic war.  For these reasons, I am convinced that there is need for such a motion as we are discussing to-day, and have been discussing for the past month or two.  It is a motion which, taking all the circumstances into consideration, the Government should regard with sympathy.</P>
    <P>I am not going to reply at any great length to statements made during the course of this debate.  You, sir, very properly, in my opinion, have ruled many of them out as being irrelevant and, therefore, I am not going to commit the same offence.  I do say this, however, in reply to some of the statements that have been made by certain Ministers, that they would be doing much better work for the country and for the people, and especially for the promotion of good relations between the peoples of the two Governments, if there were fewer references to what is usually called playing England's game.  We, here, as an Opposition think we are entitled to criticise any action of the Government in a fair and honest way.  I think we have done that up to the moment.  As far as I, personally, am concerned, I intend to carry on the same policy.  So that, there is no necessity whatsoever for Ministers hurling epithets such as &ldquo;loyalists,&rdquo; as has been hurled against the Deputy <Col N="1751" /> for Monaghan, Deputy Haslett, or against other Deputies on the Opposition Benches, such as that they are not nationally minded and that, if they were, they would be behind the Government in the steps they are taking at the present time.</P>
    <P>I am not going to say any more, sir, at the present time, except to state that, in my humble opinion, it would be well for the government to consider very seriously the position of the farming community, and of the agricultural industry generally, which has been responsible for the introduction of the motion that appears on the Order Paper to-day.  I advise the Government strongly, in the best interests of the people of this country, to consider that matter seriously.  If, perhaps, they are not inclined to pay heed to any words of mine, I should like to tell them that I have not confined my inquiries to people who support the Opposition, but in most cases the inquiries I have made have been made amongst very strong supporters of the Government in power at the moment. Any statements I have received in this connection have come from strong supporters of the Government, and they have honestly admitted to me that if this state of affairs continues much longer; if this dispute, which is, in the main, responsible for this motion being discussed at all, is not brought to some speedy settlement, they will not be in a position to earn their livelihood in the future.  That is an honest statement of fact, made from careful inquiries which I have made amongst my constituents in the constituency which I have the honour to represent.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I doubt if any motion, since the Dáil was set up, ranged over a wider field than this one, or if there was any motion which touched on so many points, and into which so many varied speakers came; so much so, that the difficulty is in deciding on where to begin to reply.  First of all, I shall re-state what I stated in introducing the motion on 4th October&mdash;that that motion, which was one of urgency, had been on the Order Paper from 24th <Col N="1752" /> March, and that it was not reached until 4th October.  It has been before this House since 4th October and it is still before the House at the present time.  I just wish to re-state that in order to point out that there are practically no facilities for Opposition Deputies in this House to bring a matter of great importance and urgency before the House or before the country.  The need for this motion might easily have disappeared.  It was introduced to meet a situation that arose a year ago, but the continuity of that situation in the current year makes this motion a matter of urgent importance and national interest now.  As I have said, however, it would have neither national importance nor national interest now were it not that the Government are still continuing in their stupidity this year on the same line they embarked on in their stupidity last year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One would appreciate the Government's difficulties much more than we do now if the Government had shown a little more interest in this matter, and if speakers, many of them on the Government Benches, who understand agriculture and are interested in it, had taken part in the debate.  Many of those who understand it and are interested in it were not put up to speak and did not speak, but two gentlemen, representing the same Department, a Minister and a Deputy-Minister, occupied Private Members' time on this motion for at least ten hours between them, and I doubt if they said anything during their two long speeches.  This motion was not put down in the spirit suggested by the Minister for Education, who referred to &ldquo;the audacity&rdquo; of the people who put it down.  The Minister for Education happens to be here.  That Minister for Education, before he became a Minister, had the audacity to stump his constituency and promise de-rating, and he will not deny it nor attempt to deny it.  If he raised his head to deny it I would put the statement down over his own signature.  He questioned the honesty of those of us who put down this motion, as, of course, did the Minister for Industry and Commerce and the Minister for Finance&mdash;I do not <Col N="1753" /> know whether any other Minister spoke on it.</P>
    <P>Ministers travelled over the whole field of activities of last year, and up to the present time, because they are acting in that field still, and I suppose the &ldquo;John Browns&rdquo; who were introduced then, are also active at this moment. As it is now within ten minutes of 2 o'clock, probably there is another &ldquo;John Brown&rdquo; auction in Prussia Street.  Allegations have been made in the course of their speeches by Ministers that Deputies engaged in conspiracies last year not to pay rates or annuities.  Certain definite statements were attributed to me, and I was singled out, I believe, by the Minister for Industry and Commerce, as one who was ordered by mandamus to strike rates in County Dublin, and that I was one of those convicted of an offence before the Military Tribunal.  Both of these statements are true, but I have nothing to apologise for or to regret. The apologies and the regrets will have to come from the Government that produced the conditions that made such incidents inevitable.  If I had entered into any conspiracy not to pay rates I would say so openly, and stand up to it.  I am more concerned with the implication in the accusation that I urged other people to do what I would not do myself.  I never asked anyone to go anywhere that I would not go myself, or to do anything that I would not do.</P>
    <P>But Ministers, and particularly the Minister for Education, promised the poor befooled constituents in Carlow-Kilkenny that if they elected them as the Government they would not have to pay rates on agricultural land any more.  I challenge the Minister for Education to question that statement. Although I admit that people are not able to pay rates and annuities, because of the depression consequent on the economic war, and the general depression all over the world, yet, I hold that there was no moral obligation on them to pay rates or annuities, because they had paid them in another way.  That was the real point of my speech when moving this motion on October 4th.  There were many minor points that I wished to make, but they <Col N="1754" /> required references, and at the time I had not those with me, because I had been in another place on that date, and did not expect when I arrived here to have to proceed with this motion.  I did so in the absence of documents.</P>
    <P>The whole case resolves itself into this.  Our Government was under an obligation under the Ultimate Financial Settlement of March, 1926, to pay £5,250,000 which, for the purposes of reference, I will call £5,000,000.  The Government here refused to pay that money, being elected, as they were, to take that line.  I am not questioning their right there, because they claimed to be elected on that policy.  I give them the benefit of the claim.  They proceeded to carry out that policy, and, in doing that, they were not going behind the backs of the people who elected them.  I grant that.  But there was another side to it, the British side. They said: &ldquo;Well, if you do not pay us the £5,000,000, we will collect the money.&rdquo;  They proceeded to collect it. My case simply was that the British had collected the £5,000,000.  In all the superfluous talk against the motion that has come from the Government Benches not a single speaker addressed himself to the case I put up.  The British collected the £5,00,000.  Who paid?  Agriculture paid.  I have sought relief of rates on or the derating of agricultural land, but I have never sought relief of rates on houses or buildings.  The agricultural land is the raw material of food production.  A different principle is involved in the retention of the land annuities.  I must not be understood as speaking against retention.  That is not directly concerned with this motion.  I am speaking of the fact of the retention, and what followed, and how the Government handled the situation that was produced by their action.  Whether retention was right or wrong is beside this motion.  I do not want to go into that question now, good, bad or indifferent. The British collected the land annuities.</P>
    <P>I stated on October 4, and it has not been contradicted, that agriculture would have to pay the £5,000,000, and agriculture has paid.  Perhaps a larger case than this could be narrowed down <Col N="1755" /> to definite limits, to an objection to the reduction of the Agricultural Grant.  I might claim the indulgence of the Chair to widen it to include a rates question and other questions now before the country.  I do not want to go that length now.  Agriculture has paid all the land annuities, and not only the land annuities, but other component parts of the debt to Great Britain.  It has paid the Royal Irish Constabulary pensions, and it has paid the local loans payments.  That is the ground I took up when I moved at Dublin County Council a year ago that we should strike no rates.  I have no apology to make for taking that action, because we were paying £2,000,000 over the land annuities.  The land annuities were the farmers' liability, but, as citizens, farmers contributed the other £2,000,000 to the Central Fund, which were paid.  As we have had to pay the whole of the £5,000,000, by taxes on goods sent to England, I think, we have liquidated that debt and the responsibility for it.  That is the case I put up. Nobody answered it.  The Minister for Finance spoke for one and a half hours <Col N="1756" /> last week, and for one and a half hours on Wednesday, and for one hour to day, but he never applied himself to that case.  Deputy Flinn talked of everything under the sun.  I was wondering if he was going to tell us the story of Beary discovering the North Pole.  He did not touch on the question at issue. The Minister for Education told us about a conspiracy.  There was no conspiracy.  We paid.  In any attitude we adopted we did not question&mdash;and it would be an impertinence to do so &mdash;the action of the Government in carrying out the mandate which they claim&mdash;and which I admit they got&mdash; from the people at the General Election of 1932, namely, to withhold the land annuities and the other payments. However, we paid them because we had no option.  The Government here could not protect us by keeping England from imposing taxation on our produce. I move the adjournment of the debate.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned until Wednesday, February 21.</P>
    <P>The Dáil adjourned at 2 p.m. until 3 p.m. Wednesday, February 21.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>