<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Fri" Date="12" Month="Feb" Year="1993" Vol="425" No="9" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 12 Feabhra 1993" DateEnglish="Friday, 12 February 1993" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1453" /> Chuaigh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 7 and 2. It is further proposed, nothwithstanding anything in Standing Orders, that in the case of Second Stage of No. 2 the following arrangements shall apply to the debate: (i) The opening speeches of the Minister or Minister of State and of the main spokespersons for the Fine Gael Party, the Progressive Democrat Party and the Technical Group shall not exceed 30 minutes in each case; (ii) The speech of each other Member called upon shall not exceed 20 minutes; (iii) A Minister of State shall be called upon to make a speech in reply not exceeding 15 minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Are the proposals for dealing with No. 2 agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that we will not have Finance questions for some time and in view of the fact that last night the vice-president of the German Bundesbank directly contradicted statements that have been made by the Minister for Finance in regard to assistance from the Bundesbank towards the maintenance of the pound in the ERM, what steps will the Taoiseach take to ensure <Col N="1454" /> that the Minister for Finance clarifies what could be a very serious and damaging conflict&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy knows that the matter he has referred to is clearly not one for the Order of Business.  There are many other ways of dealing with that matter in this House by way of question, motion, etc.  I am sorry. I will not have argument about that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>My problem is that the Minister for Finance will not be answering questions for quite some time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy should pursue that matter in the normal way.  My office will facilitate him in the matter if necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Taoiseach make provision for a future debate on this matter in view of the fact that there is now a direct conflict of evidence between the Bundesbank and the Minister for Finance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is seeking to circumvent the ruling of the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a very serious matter affecting probity of the Minister for Finance or the vice-president of the Bundesbank.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy should pursue the matter in the normal way.  This is not the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not a matter that can be left hanging in the air.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We must follow the procedures of this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BenBriscoe" hpid="Mr Briscoe Mr Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Party politics.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>It is important in an international market that our Minister for Finance be believable.  It is very serious that he has been contradicted.  Deputies opposite may not take this seriously but <Col N="1455" /> this party does.  We are entitled to have an answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>This is becoming quite disorderly.  The Deputy has had a fair opportunity of putting his point of view across in the House this morning and that should be adequate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that the Irish pound stood at 104½p sterling earlier this morning and has dropped very marginally below that to 104p and in view of the emergency that that represents for exporters and the danger of the possibility of a further devaluation, will the Taoiseach or the Minister for Finance make a statement on the position?.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Mr. Currie Mr. Currie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Currie</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the weekend, when anything could happen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We have had quite a debate on the matter of currency devaluation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvanYates" hpid="Mr. Yates Mr. Yates">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yates</NameTxt>
      <P>No credibility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest to Deputy Bruton that he has Private Members' time next week if he wishes to use it. We had a full debate in this House.  The Minister for Finance put on the record of this House all the actions taken by him and the authorities during the currency crisis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBarrett" hpid="Mr. Barrett Mr. Barrett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barrett</NameTxt>
      <P>What did the Taoiseach do?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I laid it on the record of this House, but I do not think the Deputy was here.  What the Minister for Finance laid on the record fully stands, that is, that the help was, as he described it then, too little too late.  If one wants to look at exactly what Herr Tietmeyer said it is not in contradiction at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>He said he did all he was asked to do.  What was he asked?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1456" />
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Read the record of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to raise a further question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I trust the Deputy will be relevant.  I have to dissuade the Deputy, and all the Members of the House, that I cannot and will not permit the Order of Business in this House to be used as a mini-Question Time with Members raising anything they feel they may raise.  That is not so.  It must be conformed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Taoiseach yet discovered when the Bill to allow leave for adoptive parents will be introduced in view of the fact that a Minister's promise in last year's budget has been unfulfilled because of the indolence of the Department of Labour in introducing this legislation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>That Bill is being prepared at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>We know that.  When will it actually be introduced?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>As soon as it is ready.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>When will it be ready?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not Question Time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LizMcManus" hpid="Ms. McManus Ms. McManus">
      <NameTxt>Ms. McManus</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the figures published today showing the continuing failure of many young people who are sexually active to take precautions against the HIV virus, could I ask if the Government intends to bring in this term legislation enabling easier availability of condoms which was promised in the Joint Programme for Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy may be assured that the Joint Programme for Government and the actions that are required under it will be taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask you, Sir, since <Col N="1457" /> this Government has the largest majority of any Government in the history of the State, whether you were indicating in your earlier remarks to Deputy Bruton that you intend to take a more restrictive view of the rights of the Opposition on the Order of Business&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It is most audacious of the Deputy to make that rather foul insinuation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>He loves you dearly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>I withdraw any imputation of any such&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair is merely seeking to observe normal tradition in dealing with the Order of Business and dissuading Members from raising matters that can be dealt with otherwise, by way of question or motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>The very nature of&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry, Deputy, but you may not argue with the Chair in respect of that matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to withdraw any imputation&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;but I want to put the question to you that, having regard to the nature of the issue raised by Deputy Bruton and O'Malley and having regard to the immediate and rapidly changing context&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Now the Deputy is getting around it another way. It will not work.  I am going on to item No. 7.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>Sir&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Bruton, I want to get on to the business of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Taoiseach <Col N="1458" /> what his proposals are in regard to the National Heritage Bill, which is promised?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The National Heritage Bill is in the course of preparation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Taoiseach what Minister is preparing it?  Does heritage include Mullaghmore?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought I had made the position clear when I read out the function of the various Ministers here. The Deputy is asking an unnecessary question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBarrett" hpid="Mr Barrett Mr Barrett">
      <NameTxt>Mr Barrett</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach did not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course it is the Minister for Arts, Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht who will be bringing in the Bill.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Mr. Currie Mr. Currie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Currie</NameTxt>
      <P>I have received representations from County Galway about the widespread use of illegal television transmissions in that area and throughout the west.  Could I be guided as to whom I should direct a question in relation to this most popular issue in that area?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Mr. Currie Mr. Currie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Currie</NameTxt>
      <P>Should I direct it to the Heritage Minister or the Minister for Communications, as I am sure both of them will be dying to deal with that subject?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>My office will be of assistance to the Deputy in that regard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>Separately from the National Heritage Bill, the Government has also promised and has with the Attorney General, I understand, a National Monuments (Amendment) Bill. May I ask the Taoiseach if the Attorney General has completed his consideration of that matter and if he would indicate which Minister will be introducing it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1459" />
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Deputy is holding up the House unnecessarily this morning.  I laid the functions of each Minister and his areas of responsibility before the House and I would have thought that Deputy Bruton and his other backbench colleagues would have read it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBarrett" hpid="Mr. Barrett Mr. Barrett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barrett</NameTxt>
      <P>Even the Taoiseach's own Ministers do not know which Department they are in charge of.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Let me repeat, for the benefit of the House, that the Bill he asked about is also within the responsibility of the Minister for the Arts, Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Deputy Bruton will appreciate this kind of Question Time cannot go on interminably. This is your final remark, Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that the Taoiseach is having to get prompts for his answers, it seems I am helping him to discover which of his Ministers is responsible for this legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardJDurkan" hpid="Mr. Durkan Mr. Durkan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Durkan</NameTxt>
      <P>They are also beginning to discover it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>Chuir an Teachta Currie ceist agus ní bhfuair sé aon freagra ar an gceist.  Tá deacreachtaí ag baint leis an rud seo.  The Taoiseach last week was indicating the various responsibilities for Ministers and Ministers of State.  The question asked by Deputy Currie does require an answer because there is confusion as to where the exact responsibility lies.  I contacted Departments and they were not able to answer me.  I would like to know if the Taoiseach could indicate to the House now as to where the responsibility lies in regard to the deflector issue?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Again, for the benefit and information of the Deputies, policy <Col N="1460" /> areas in relation to broadcasting was the responsibility of the Minister for Arts, Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Mr. Currie Mr. Currie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Currie</NameTxt>
      <P>Another poison chalice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoieach The Taoieach">
      <NameTxt>The Taoieach</NameTxt>
      <P>They want the answer but they do not want to listen to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Mr. Currie Mr. Currie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Currie</NameTxt>
      <P>They can have that one, but not Mullaghmore.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to hear the answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Responsibility for the area of transmission infrastructure was a matter for the Minister for Industry, Energy and Communications, Deputy Cowen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AustinCurrie" hpid="Mr. Currie Mr. Currie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Currie</NameTxt>
      <P>Industry?</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Department officials are still confused.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvanYates" hpid="Mr. Yates Mr. Yates">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yates</NameTxt>
      <P>We need the programme managers all right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardJDurkan" hpid="Mr. Durkan Mr. Durkan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Durkan</NameTxt>
      <P>And some minders as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="An Bille um Údarás na Gaeltachta (Leasú)," RHead="1993: An Dara agus na Céimeanna eile">
    <Title>An Bille um Údarás na Gaeltachta (Leasú), 1993: An Dara agus na Céimeanna eile.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Aire Ealáion, Cultúir agus Gaeltachta (Mr. M. Higgins) Aire Ealáion, Cultúir agus Gaeltachta (Mr. M. Higgins)">
      <NameTxt>Aire Ealáion, Cultúir agus Gaeltachta (Mr. M. Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>: Tairgim:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Go léifear an Bille an Dara Uair&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Is mór an onóir domsa an deis seo a bheith agam an Bille seo a chur faoi bhráid na Dála.  Is mó mo riméad é gur Bille é a bhaineann leis an nGaeltacht agus gur i nGaelige atá mo chéad óráid sa Teach seo mar Aire.  Tá ráite agam go poiblí gur cuid lárnach de shaol agus de chultúr na tíre seo í an Ghaeilge agus tá súil agam go nglacfar go fonnmhar leis an deis seo chun an Bille a chíoradh trí mheán na teanga sin.  Beidh fáilte agam roimh díospóireachtraí eile i nGaelilge <Col N="1461" /> amach anseo mar creidim ní amháin go bhfuil an Ghaeilge lárnach do shaol na hÉireann ach gur cheart í a bheith le cloisteáil chomh minic agus is féidir sa Teach seo agus sa Seanad.</P>
    <P>Tá dhá aidhm leis an mBille gairid seo. Is í an chéad aidhm foráil a dhéanamh le gur féidir caipiteal a chur ar fáil feasta d'Údarás na Gaeltachta, le haghaidh scaireanna a ghlacadh i gcuideachtaí agus le haghaidh caiteachais a thabhú ar mhonarchana nó eile, mar dheontas-i-gcabhair trí Vóta mo Roinne seachas mar airleacain ón bPríomh-Chiste.  Roimhe seo bhíodh caipiteal ón Stát á chur ar fáil don Údarás agus do Ghaeltarra Éireann ar dhá bhealach: ó Vóta na Roinne mar dheontais-i-gcabhair chun deontais a íoc; agus mar airleacain inaisíoctha ón bPríomh-Chiste chun a chumasú don Údarás scaireanna a ghlacadh i gcuid-eachtaí agus caiteachas a thabhú ar mhonarchana nó eile.  Nuair a rithfear an Bille seo, is trí Vóta mo Roinne amháin a chuirfear an soláthar caipitil in iomlán ón Stát ar fáil don Údarás agus beidh an tÚdarás ar an mbonn céanna leis an Údarás Forbartha Tionscail maidir le cúnamh Stát d'fhorbairt tionscail.</P>
    <P>Ó bunaíodh an tÚdarás ar I Eanáir 1980, tá suim £77.182 mhilliún airleactha dó ón bPríomh-Chiste suas go dtí deireadh na bliana seo caite.  Chomh maith leis sin, bhí suim £41.791 mhilliún airleactha do Ghaeltarra Éireann ó Aibreán 1965 go dtí 31 Nollaig 1979.  Faoi alt 23 (2) (c) den Acht um Údarás na Gaeltachta, 1979, níl an tsuim iomlán sin, i.e., £118.973 mhilliún inaisíoctha ná níl ús iníoctha ar an gcéanna go dtí dáta a chinn-fidh an tAire Airgeadais tar éis comhairle a ghlacadh le Aire na Gaeltachta (An tAire Ealaíon, Cultúir agus Gaeltachta anois).  Tá sé soiléir le fada nach mbeadh ar chumas an Údaráis na hairleacain sin a aisíoc in iomlán riamh.  Is í an dara aidhm leis an mBille seo, mar sin, foráil a dhéanamh nach mbeidh an tsuim sin inaisíoctha ná nach mbeidh ús iníoctha air.</P>
    <P>Luaigh mé roimhe seo go raibh sé soiléir nach mbeadh ar chumas an Údaráis na hairleacain a aisíoc in iomlán agus míneoidh mé cén fáth anois.  Léiríonn <Col N="1462" /> Cuntais fhoilsithe an Údaráis don bhliain dar chríoch 31 Nollaig 1991 gurbh é glan-luach monarchana, foirgneamh agus áiseanna eile, agus sócmhainní dochta eile an heagraíochta ar 31 Nollaig 1991 ná £59.013 mhilliún.  Léiríonn na Cuntais chéanna gurb é glan-luach (tar éis soláthar i gcomhair athluacháil a dhéanamh) infheistíochtaí an Údaráis i gcuideachtaí ag 31 Nollaig 1991 ná £9.047 milliún. Chomh maith leis sin, bhí féichiúnaithe iarchurtha de £1.68 mhilliún ag an Údarás.  Tagann na suimeanna sin ar fad go dtí £69.745 mhilliún.  Go dtí 31 Nollaig 1991, tugadh airleacain dar luach £113,473 mhilliún don Údarás.  Mar sin tá easnamh de £43.728 milliún sa chuntas. Déantar suas an £43.728 milliún sin mar seo a leanas:</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="40*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
            </entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">£milliúm</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Dímheas ar shócmhainní dochta</entry>
            <entry>12.183</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Infheistíochtaí díscríofa móide dochar/sochar ar shócmhainní a dhíol</entry>
            <entry>24.590</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Caillteanais na seanrannóga trádála a bhí ag feidhmiú faoi Ghaeltarra Éireann</entry>
            <entry>7.570</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Fuílleach ar chúltaca aoisliúntais ag 31 Nollaig 1979.</entry>
            <entry>(0.615)</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>£43.728</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Níl figiúirí iniúchtha do 31 Nollaig 1992 ar fáill go fóill ach meastar gur easnamh de £44.326 mhilliún a bheidh ann ar an dáta sin.</P>
    <P>Ag féachaint do na figiúrí atá tugtha agam d'airleacain ón Stát don Údaras i gcomparáid le glan-luach na maoine agus na n-infheistíochtaí anois, is leir go raibh agus go bhfuil forbairt tionscail sa Ghaeltacht costasach.  Ar an taobh eile den scéal, áfach, ní mór a chur san áireamh go bhfuil breis agus 5,600 post lánaimseartha agus beagnach 2,000 post séasúr-ach i dtionscail sa Ghaeltacht faoi scáth an Údaráis.  Chomh maith leis sin, tá oiliúint thionsclaíoch tugtha do líon mór oibrithe agus, ainneoin iargúltacht agus laigeachtaí bhunstruchtúir na limistéar sin tá bonn maith tionsclaíoch bunaithe sa Ghaeltacht anois.  Trí is tríd, táim sásta <Col N="1463" /> gurbh fhiú an caiteachas ar mhaithe le forbairt na Gaeltachta agus caomhnú na Gaeilge.</P>
    <P>Maidir le Cuntais an Údaráis, beidh athruithe le déanamh ar an leagan amach nuair a bheidh feidhm leis an reacht-aíocht is ábhar don Bhille seo.  Is ceist í sin a bheidh le socrú tar éis plé idir an Údarás, mé féin mar Aire, an Aire Airgeadais agus an Ard-Reachtaire Cuntas agus Ciste.</P>
    <P>Bliain deacair a bhí ann anuraidh maidir le fostaíocht a chruthú agus a chaomhnú sa Ghaeltacht.  Cruthaíodh 975 phost nua lánaimseartha ar an bhfód i 1992 i dtionscail a fuair cúnamh ón Údarás agus, tar éis caillteanais de 920 post a chur san áireamh, bhí méadú glan de 55 phost sa bhliain sin.  Ba í 1992 an t-aonú bliain déag i ndiaidh a chéile ina raibh glanmhéadú san fhostaíocht i dtionscail faoi scáth an Údaráis.  Ag deireadh 1992, bhí 5,652 dhuine fostaithe go lánaimseartha i dtionscail sa Ghaeltacht faoi scáth an Údaráis i gcomparáid le 5,597 nduine ag deireadh 1991.</P>
    <P>Chomh maith leis sin, tá acmhainn de 1,440 post nua i dtograí ar cheadaigh an tÚdarás cúnamh ina leith anuraidh. Meastar go bhfuil móriomlán infheist-íochta de £48 milliún i gceist sna tograí sin agus beidh a shochar sin le haithint ar an bhfód sa Ghaeltacht i rith na mblianta atá romhainn.</P>
    <P>Tá fostaíocht shéasúrach an-tábhachtach don Ghaeltacht agus tháinig méadú de 320 ar líon na bpost sin sa Ghaeltacht le linn 1922 ó 2,260 duine i 1991 go dtí 2,580 duine i 1992.  Chomh maith leis an bhfostaíocht shéasúrach/ pháirtaimseartha sin, bhí 77 Scéim Fhost-aíochta Shóisialta a raibh luach £1.4 mhilliún ag gabháil leo agus 635 dhuine fostaithe orthu á riaradh ag an Údarás i 1992 i gcomhar le FÁS agus coistí Gaeltachta.</P>
    <P>Maidir leis an 920 post a cailleadh i rith na bliana seo caite, tuigtear ón Údarás gur athchruthaíodh timpeall 300 díobh trí thograí nua a bunaíodh ar shócmhainní na gcomhlachtaí ar theip orthu.  Bhain formhór na gcaillteanas eile le laghduithe ar a bhfoirne oibre a b'éigean do chomh-lachtaí <Col N="1464" /> a chur i bhfeidhm de bharr deacrachtaí trádála i margaí éagsúla.  Is fadhb mhór í líon na bpost a chailltear sa Ghaeltacht gach bliain, a chealaíonn beagnach iomlán na bpost a chruthaítear go bliantúil. Tá sé ráite go soiléir sa Chlár le haghaidh Rialtais Chomhpháirtíochta go mbeidh an tÚdarás ag cur lena n-iarrach-taí, ní amháin chun fostaíocht bhreise a chruthú ach freisin chun an fhostaíocht atá ann a chaomhnú.  Is cinnte go gcaithfear scrúdú a dhéanamh ar na critéir a úsáideann an tÚdarás i dtaca le cúnamh a cheadú do thograí agus iarracht a dhéanamh chun na laigeachtaí a thagann chun cinn i gcomhlachtaí beaga maidir le bainistíocht, margaíocht agus teicneolaíocht a mhaolú.</P>
    <P>Tá dul chun cinn leanúnach á dhéanamh ag an Údarás maidir leis an meánchostas deontais in aghaidh an phoist a laghdú.  Anuraidh ba é an meánchostas ná £9,130 i gcomparáid le £9,800 i 1991 agus £11,470 i 1990.  Tá an laghdú seo ag teacht le cinneadh polasaí a glacadh cúpla bliain siar maidir le meánrátaí deontais a laghdú agus sciar níos airde den infheistíocht a lorg ó na hinfheisteoirí féin.</P>
    <P>Ní féidir liom figiúrí cinnte a lua inniu maidir leis an soláthar airgid a bheidh ar fáil ag an Údarás ón Stát i mbliana &mdash; foilseofar iad sin i Leabhar na Meastachán go hanluath &mdash; ach tig liom a rá go mbeidh méadú suntasach i gceist i gcomparáid le soláthar na bliana seo caite.</P>
    <P>Tá béim leagtha agam inniu ar aidhmeanna an Bhille seo agus tá léargas gairid tugtha agam ar an dul chun cinn a rinne an tÚdarás le linn 1992.  Beidh deis agam ráiteas níos iomláine faoin nGaeilge a thabhairt don Teach nuair a bheidh Meastachán mo Roinne á phlé anseo níos déanaí.</P>
    <P>Molaim don Dáil glacadh leis an mBille seo.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DinnyMcGinley" hpid="Mr. McGinley Mr. McGinley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGinley</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom comh-ghairdeas a dhéanamh ar dtús le mo chomhleacaí anseo le roinnt blianta, an tAire úr Cultúir, Ealaíon agus Gaeltachta. Is minic a labhraíomar anseo i rith na mblianta ar chúrsaí Gaeltachta agus cúrsaí an Údaráis agus tá lúcháir orm go <Col N="1465" /> bhfuil an cúram agus an fhreagracht sin air anois.  Tá sé cosúil le póitséalaí a cuireadh ar an dtaobh eile chun aire a thabhairt do na hainmhithe.  Tá súil agam go n-éireoidh go geal leis in a ról úr.  Failtím roimh an mBille seo.  Sílim gur moltaí ciallmhara atá ann agus is suntasach gurb é seo an chéad Bhille a thug an tAire isteach sa Teach.  Is doigh liom gurbh iad aidhm agus cuspóir an Bhille ná an tÚdarás ar chur ar aon bhonn le heag-raíochtaí forbartha tionscail eile sa tír, mar an IDA agus SFADCo, agus a chinntiú, as seo amach go mbeidh airgeadú an Údaráis ag teacht as an Státchiste agus go mbeadh aitheantas ag dul dó sin.</P>
      <P>Sílim go n-aontaítear go bhfuil jab níos deacra ag an Udarás i sólathar fostaíocht tionsclaíochta sa Ghaeltacht ná mar atá ag na heagraíochtaí eile a luaigh mé.  Tá an tÚdarás ag feidhmiú i gceantar atá scaite agus iargúlta i gcomparáid leis na ceantair a ndéanann SFADCo agus an IDA freastal orthu.  Tá a fhios againn go bhfuil fadhbanna cumarsáide agus infrastrúctuir ar leith ag baint leis an nGaeltacht agus go mbíonn sé níos deacra mar sin mórthionscail a mhealladh go dtí an Ghaeltacht ná chuig páirteanna eile den tír.</P>
      <P>Dá bhrí sin, tá sé thar am go mbeadh acmhainn ag an Údarás deontais agus breis tacaíochta a thabhairt do dhaoine a bhfuil fonn orthu fostaíocht a chur ar fáil sa Ghaeltacht.  Tá laincis ar an Údarás faoi láthair faoi choinne sin, i gcomparáid leis na heagraíochtaí eile.  Tá súil agam agus Aire nua i mbun dualgais anois go n-amharcfaidh sé ar an ngné sin de dheacr-achtaí an Údaráis agus go gcuirfidh sé a gcumas ráta níos airde deontais a thairisc-int do thionsclaíthe ná mar is féidir leis na heagraíochtaí eile a mbíonn an tÚdaras ag iomaíocht leo.  Tá tábhacht ag baint le costaisí ama tionsclaíochta agus soláthar infrastruchtúir agus bíonn costaisí méadaithe ag gabháil le tionscail atá lonaithe in áiteanna iargúlta.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As seo amach is í Éire an t-aon chuid den Chomhphobal Eorpach nach mbeidh ceanglaithe leis an chuid eile.  An bhliain seo chugainn, tar éis oscailt an Tolláin idir an Bhreatain agus an Fhrainc, beidh <Col N="1466" /> Éire ar an t-aon cheantar gearrtha amach ó na margaí, agus os rud é go bhfuil an Ghaeltacht suite níos faide ón Eoraip ná aon chuid eile den tír tá an cuidiú beag seo de dhíth uirthi go géar.</P>
    <P>Tá mé buartha mar gheall ar na boird fhiontar contae atá á mbunú i láthair na huaire.  Chomh fada agus is eol dom tá bord fiontar contae bunaithe cheanna féin i ndáilcheantar an Aire i nGaillimh. Ní dóigh liom gur bunaíodh ceann eile faoin dtír go fóill ach de réir tuairiscí ní fada go mbunófaí.  Cad é an tionchar a bheas ag na boird seo ar ról an Údaráis sna Gaeltachtaí?  An mbeidh a leithéid chéanna de chumhachtaí agus freagracht ag an Údarás sna Gaeltachtaí agus a mbeidh ag na boird seo sa chuid eile den tír?  An mbeidh Údarás na Gaeltachta ag brath ar airgeadú nó an mbeidh an tÚdarás fós ag fáil a chuid airgeadú agus acmhainniú ón Státchiste, ó Roinn na Gaeltachta?</P>
    <P>De réir mar a thuigim, beidh freagracht turasóireachta agus forbairt seirbhisí eile ar na boird úra fiontair.  An mbeidh a mhacasamhail de chumhachtaí agus de fhreagracht ag an Údarás sna ceantair Ghaeltachta?  Más mar sin a bheidh, ní mór athscrúdú a dhéanadh ar Acht Údarás na Gaeltachta mar beidh gále breis cumhachtaí a thabhairt don Údarás. Is beag cúram atá ag an Údarás i láthair na huaire maidir le forbairt thurasóireachta. Má bhíonn an cúram sin ag na boird fhiontar contae, cé ag a mbeidh sé sna Gaeltachtaí?  Tá soiléiriú ag teastáil sa cheist sin.</P>
    <P>Creidim, leis, go mbeidh sé de chumhacht ag na boird úra fiontair forbairt a dhéanamh ar sheirbhísí, cumhacht nach bhfuil ag an Údarás faoi láthair.  Tá seirbhísí go leor in easnamh fós sa Ghaeltacht agus b'fhiú amharc ar an ngné seo, feáchaint an bhféadfaí cumhacht a thabhairt don Údarás ann.</P>
    <P>Mar a dúirt an tAire, agus tá sé ráite i dTuairisc Shealadach Roinn na Gaeltachta, bunaíodh 975 phost sna Gaeltachtaí le linn 1992.  Uimhir mhaith postanna í sin agus is suntasach go bhfuil costaísí in aghaidh an phoist ag teacht anuas anois le roinnt blianta.  Cúis imní dúinn, áfach, gur cailleadh 920 post Gaeltachta sa tréimhse <Col N="1467" /> chéanna; fágann sé sin gur cruthaíodh 55 post nua Gaeltachta anuraidh. Tá gá le tacaíocht cúnamh ón Roinn le go ndéanfar sáriarracht postanna atá ann cheana féin a chosaint.  Go minic, tá sé níos fusa agus níos saoire postanna a choimeád beo ná postanna nua a chruthú.</P>
    <P>I rith na seachtaine seo, pléadh sa Dáil an ghéarchéim airgeadais.  Luadh láimhseáiliú an phuint agus sterling.  Chuir ísliú an phuint i gcomparáid le sterling isteach go mór ar thionscail sa Ghaeltacht. Díoltar an-chuid táirgí Gaeltachta leis an mBreatain, agus le sé mhí anuas le linn na géarchéime, tá buillí tubaisteacha á mbualadh ar thionscail Ghaeltachta.  Tá mioneolas agam ar thionscail i mo dháilcheantar féin atá ag dul ó lá go lá agus postanna i mbaol.  Tá cruinnithe prainneacha socraithe don tseachtain seo agus don tseachtain seo chugainn, de réir tuairiscí a chualamar maidin inniu, do thionscail atá faoi bhrú millteanach de bharr costaisí breise agus deacrachtaí margaidh ag éirí as an ngearchéim airgeadais.</P>
    <P>B'fhiú don Aire dul i dteagmháil le hÚdarás na Gaeltachta agus iníuchadh a dhéanamh ar thionscail Ghaeltachta atá sáite i ndeacrachtaí airgeadais faoi láthair d'fhonn iad a choimeád ag táirgeadh go dtí taréis na géarchéime.  Dhéarfainn go bhfuil a leithéid sin de dheacrachtaí ag tionscail i ndáilcheantar an Aire, chomh maith le ceantair Ghaeltachta eile.  Bhí trácht ar an ngéarchéim ar na meáin chumarsáide uilig agus chuir sé isteach ar mhuintir na Gaeltachta a oiread céanna nó níos mó ná ar pháirteanna eile den tír.  Tá iasachtaí le n-íoc ag muintir na Gaeltachta dála daoine eile faoin dtír.</P>
    <P>Ba mhaith liom go dtabharfadh an tÚdarás aire speisialta do na ceantair bheaga Gaeltachta.  Tá ceantair mhóra Gaeltachta i nDún na Gall, i nGaillimh agus i gCúige Mumhan ach is minic go mbíonn ceantair bheaga i mbaol a ligean i ndearmad.  Tá an Ghaeilge, an cultúr agus an dúchas láidir sna ceantair bheaga seo cé nach bhfuil daonra mór iontu. I mo chontae féin, smaoiním ar Chill Chárthaigh, Gleann Cholmcille, an Charraig, an Ghaeltacht Lár agus Cloch <Col N="1468" /> Cheann Fhaolaidh.  Is beag fostaíochta a bunaíodh ansin le roinnt bhlianta; is amhlaidh gur cailleadh an-chuid postanna ann.  Ba mhaith liom go dtabharfadh an tÚdarás aire ar leith d'áiteanna mar sin.  Tá mé cinnte gurb amhlaidh an cás i go leor pócaí Gaeltachta ó Charna go Ros a'Mhíl, agus i gCúige Mumhan i mBaile Bhúirne, i mBéal Átha an Ghaorthaidh agus i gCúil Aodha.</P>
    <P>Ní mór cuimhneamh ar na hoileáin Ghaeltachta freisin, siar agus ó thuaidh.  Cé go bhfuil daonra fiúntach ar na hoileáin sin &mdash; 600 nó 700 ar Árainn Mhór agus breis is céad ar Thoraí &mdash; is beag fostaíocht thionsclaíochta atá ar fáil faoi láthair ar na hoileáin sin.  Ba chóir iarracht a dhéanamh chun tionscail bunaithe ar cheardaíocht nó ar thurasóireacht a chur ar siúl ar na hoileáin. Tá sé de dhulgas orainn fostáiocht, teacht isteach agus slí maireachtála a chur ar fáil do, mhuintir na n-oileán dála aon mhuintir ar an mórthír.</P>
    <P>Molaim an tÚdarás as ucht scéim ina bhfuil siad páirteach ar oileán Thoraí. Don chéad uair riamh tá teacht ósta á thógáil ann a chuideoidh le tionscal na turasóireachta ann.  Is breá go bhfuil rannpháirtíocht ag an Údarás sa tionscnamh seo agus tá mé cinnte go gcuirfear fostaíocht ar fáil le linn séasúr na turasóireachta nuair a bheidh an obair críochnaithe.  Sampla é seo den rud a thig leis an Údarás a dhéanamh i gcúrsaí turasóireachta.</P>
    <P>Is breá liom go bhfuil an tÚdarás ag glacadh suim bhríomhar i soláthar theilifís trí Ghaeilge.  Is iad a bhí i mbun na tuairisce a cuireadh amach, trí nó ceithre bliana ó shin.  B'fhéidir nár déanadh mórán dul chun cinn fós ach tá an t-ábhar os comhair an Rialtais anois.  Sílim go n-aontaíonn gach páirtí sa Teach go gcaithfear seirbhís cheart Ghaeilge a chur ar fáil ní amháin do mhuintir na Gaeltachta ach do Ghaeilgeorí ar fud na tíre. Is maith liom go bhfuil an tAire ag glacadh suime san fhorbairt seo, ó ceapadh ina Aire é.  Is minic a d'éist mé leis ar Thráth na gCeist ag plé cúrsaí Gaeltachta agus bhí sé féin agus an taobh seo Tí ar aon intinn lena chéile.  Go minic athraíonn daoine a ndearcadh nuair a thrasnaíonn <Col N="1469" /> siad ó thaobh an Fhreasúra go dtí taobh an Rialtais.  Tá an tAire ina phost le cúpla seachtain anois agus ní fheictear dom gur tháinig athrú mór farraige air ó thrasnaigh sé an t-urlár agus tá súil agam gur mar sin a leanfaidh.</P>
    <P>Tá ról ag an Údarás i soláthar theilifís Ghaeilge.  Tá siad, faoi láthair, ag déanamh airgeadú ar chláracha Gaeilge a mbeadh suim ag daoine óga iontu agus sílim go bhfuil jab maith á dhéanamh acu.  Tá súil agam go bhfaighe siad gach cuidiú chun leanúint leis an obair seo.</P>
    <P>Tá baint ag an Údarás leis an gclár Leader a bhfuil airgeadú a dhéanamh air ag an gComhphobal ar son forbairt tuaithe áitiúil.  Ar na príomhlimistéir gníomhaíochta tá forbairt thurasóireacht tuaithe agus forbairt mioncheardaíochta. Tá an tÚdarás i dtús áite ag aithint cad iad na foinsí airgid atá ar fáil ón Eoraip agus ag baint usáid astu chun ceantair Ghaeltachta a fhorbairt.</P>
    <P>Tá obair mhaith á déanamh ag an Údarás ach tá go leor eile le déanamh. Tá lúcháir orm go ndúirt an tAire, cé nach bhfuil a fhios aige go baileach an mó airgid a gheobhas an tÚdarás i mbliana, go mbeidh sé ar chomhchéim nó thairis sin ar an méid a fuarthas anuraidh. I dTír Chonaill, tá mé cinnte gurb amhlaidh sna Gaeltachtaí eile.  Ní féidir an Ghaeltacht, an teanga nó an cultúr Gaelach a shábháil gan pobal beo sna ceantair Ghaeltachta.</P>
    <P>Tá ról mór ag an Údarás i soláthar slí bheatha do mhuintir na Gaeltachta agus is ar an Rialtas agus go mórmhór ar an Aire, a bhfuil Gaeltacht ina dháilcheantar féin aige, atá an tÚdarás ag brath.  Ta an-eolas ag an Aire ar na deacrachtaí a ghabhann le eacnamaíocht na nGaeltachtaí &mdash; chuala mé é, uair eile, ag léamh faoin gcoimisiún a chuir Risteard Ó Maolchatha ar bun sna fichidí agus na moltaí a rinne an coimisiún sin.  B'fhéidir go n-amharcfadh sé ar na moltaí sin arís feáchaint an bhféadfaí iad a chur i bhfeidhm go fóill.  Tá an t-eolas cuí ag an Aire; is socheolaí é agus beidh gach cúnamh le fáil aige ón dtaobh seo Tí fad a bheas mise ag déanamh ionadaíochta ar son ceantair Ghaeltachta.  Ta súil agam go <Col N="1470" /> mbeidh tacaíocht aige ó pháirtí eile an Rialtais faoi choinne acmhainn agus cuidiú don Údarás lena ngnó a thabhairt i gcrích.</P>
    <P>Táimid ag druidim le deireadh an chéid seo agus ag tús an chéid nua tá súil agam go mbeimid ábalta a rá go muiníneach go mairfidh an Ghaeltacht, an teanga, an dúchas.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom comhghairdeas a dhéanamh le mo sheanchara as dáilcheantar Iarthar na Gaillimhe atá anois ina Aire Gaeltachta.  B'fhéidir nár mhiste dom a rá gur thosaíomar beirt ár saol polaitiúil ar an dtaobh chéanna líne agus cosúil le clann madra, d'oscail ár súile ina dhiaidh sin agus táimid ar thaobhanna difriúla ó shin.  Ní thógann sé sin ó mo mheas pearsanta air agus tá áthas orm go bhfuil an post tábhachtach seo bainte amach aige.  Tá mé cinnte go gcomhlíonfaidh sé a dhualgais nua.</P>
      <P>Is fada ó shuigh Áire Gaeltachta ó dháilcheantar Ghaeltachta ag bord an Rialtais.  Tá tuiscint chuimsitheach aige ar na fadhbanna atá le réiteach.  Dála an Teachta McGinley, tig liom a rá go dtabharfaidh mé féin agus mo pháirtí tacaíocht d'aon bheart fiúntach a chuideoidh leis na Gaeltachtaí.  Tá sé tábhachtach go nglacfadh Aire na Gaeltachta cúram na Roinne sin air féin.  Fograíodh tuarascáil fadó ar a tugadh &ldquo;Gníomh don Ghaeltacht&rdquo; agus beidh mise, an Teachta McGinley agus Teachtaí eile ag faire anois ar ghníomh do na Gaeltachtaí ón Aire seo.</P>
      <P>Tá tuiscint níos cruinne ag an Aire seo ar fhadhbanna na nGaeltachtaí ná mar a bhí ag aon Aire a ghabh roimhe nár toghadh as ceantar Gaeltachta é agus ní ag caitheamh anuas ar aon Aire nó Aire Stáit eile atáim.  Tá sé tábhachtach go dtuigfeadh an tAire go bhfaighfidh sé tacaíocht uainne chun aon bheartas fiúntach a thabhairt i gcrích.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Is iad na Gaeltachtaí croí saibhris na hoidhreachta Gaelaí.  Caithfear eisceachtaí a dhéanamh dóibh i gcónaí ó rialacha forbairt thionscalaíochta a chuirtear i bhfeidhm in Éirinn go ginearálta.  Má chailltear an Ghaeilge, má théann caighdeán maireachtála mhuintir na nGaeltachta <Col N="1471" /> chun donachta, má mhéadaíonn ar an ndífostaíocht ann agus más iad Boston, Nuah Eabhrac agus an Astráil príomhdhóchas na n-áitritheoirí Ghaeltachta, is beag maitheas dúinn bheith ag trácht ar thábhacht na hoidhreachta.</P>
    <P>Is orainne atá an dualgas rud fiúntach a dhéanamh anseo.  Cuireann sé díomá orm nár déanadh níos mó go dtí seo, ó thaobh tuarascála a fhoilsiú agus ceist chasta na nGaeltachtaí a iniúchadh; bhí daoine ann a bhí dáirire faoin nGaeilge i gcónaí agus measaim gurb é an Teach seo a lig síos iad.  Ní mór dúinn uilig milleán ar son an easpa dul chun cinn a ghlacadh orainn féin.  Tá súil agam nach mbeidh aon díomá orm faoi obair an Aire seo nuair a thiocfaidh deireadh lena thréimhse oifige.</P>
    <P>Nuair a chuala mé go raibh Bille faoi Údarás na Gaeltachta á thabhairt os comhair an Tí, cheap mé go bhfeicfinn ann cuid de na rudaí a bhí á mholadh ag an Aire agus agam féin le blianta beaga anuas.  Mo thrua nach bhfuil ann ach cealú fiacha an Údaráis de bharr iasachtaí airgid ón Stát, agus bhí a fhios ag an saol nach gcuirfí iallach ar an Údarás an t-airgead sin a aisíoc.  Bhí súil agam go mbainfí úsáid as an mBille seo chun breis cumhachtaí a bhronnadh ar an Údarás. Bhí baint agam leis na díospóireachtaí agus leis an cinneadh Rialtais as ar bunaíodh an tÚdarás.  Is cuimhin liom go raibh cuid mhaith daoine i gcoinne cumhachtaí fairsinge a thabhairt don Údarás, nó i gcoinne a bhunadh, fiú, ach bhí slí ann chun cumhachtaí an Údaráis a leathnú, de réir an chéad Bhille, dá dtiocfadh an t-iarratas cuí ar aghaidh.</P>
    <P>Ag breathnú ar na blianta ó Eanáir 1980 nuair a thóg an tÚdarás cúramaí Ghaeltarra air féin agus gur baisteadh ina Údarás é, is beag cumhacht bhreise a bronnadh air.  Cúram maidir le forbairt thionsclaíochta is mó atá ar an Údarás ó shin i leith.  Beidh tacaíocht le fáil ag an Aire uaimse má thionscnaíonn sé Bille eile chun cumhachtaí breise a bhronnadh ar Údarás na Gaeltachta agus chuige sin bheadh athruithe ag teastáil i gcóras an Údaráis.  Ní mór seans a thabhairt do <Col N="1472" /> mhuintir na Gaeltachta breis tionchar a bheith acu ar fhorbairt a gceantair féin.</P>
    <P>Nuair a théann comhairleoir ó cheantar Ghaeltachta chuig cruinniú míosúil dá chomhairle contae, buaileann sé le huimhir mhór comhairleoirí ó cheantair eile a bhfuil easnaimh eagsúla ar a gceantair.  Is beag aird a thugtar ar fhadhbanna an cheantair Ghaeltachta mar tá tromlach na vótaí ag na comhairleoirí arbh lasmuigh den Ghaeltacht dóibh.</P>
    <P>Más é polasaí an Rialtais i gcónaí, an Ghaeilge a chur chun cinn, na Gaeltachtaí a chothú agus a neartú agus eisceachtaí áirithe a dhéanamh díobh caithfear gníomh speisialta a dhéanamh ar a son.  Creidim gurb é seo &mdash; cumhachtraí údarás áitiúil a thabhairt d'Údarás na Gaeltachta &mdash; an bealach is fearr lena dhéanamh; b'féidir, áfach, go bhfuil bealach níos fearr ann.  Ar aon chuma, ní mór athrú bunúsach a dhéanamh ar na córais chabhrach atá ann faoi láthair do mhuintir na Gaeltachta.</P>
    <P>Is dócha gur cúinsí stairiúla a chinntigh gurb sna Gaeltachtaí mar is eol duínn iad, a mhairfeadh an Ghaeilge.  Áiteanna iargúlta atá i geist, a thit lasmuigh d'achar suime sean-riaraitheoirí na tíre seo, agus inar cloídh leis an teanga agus an cultúr Gaelach.  Is orainne atá an tairbhe dá bharr.  Ó bunaíodh an Stát, áfach, tá na ceantair Ghaeltachta ag dul i laige agus líon na gcainteoirí Gaeilge iontu ag dul i laghad.  Tá an mhuintir iontu faoi bhrú ó chultúr an Bhéarla agus is constaic mhór í an teilifís dóibh siúd atá ag iarraidh a bpáistí a thógáil le Gaeilge.  Bíonn an teilifís ar siúl sa choirnéal an t-am ar fad agus Béarla amháin ag teacht amach as. Faigheann an Béarla stádas níos airde ná an Ghaeilge fiú i dteaghlaigh ina labhartar Gaeilge.  Thacaigh mo pháirtí ó thús le moladh go mbunófaí teilifís Ghaeilge chun an deacracht sin a shárú.  Cosnóidh a leithéid de sheirbhís cuid mhaith airgid ach caithfear an t-airgead a chur ar fáil ar mhaithe le slanú na teanga.</P>
    <P>Ní cóir dom a bheidh ag súil le héacht mhór sa Bhille seo óir gurb í seo céad seachtain na Dála nua agus céad ocáid an tAire a bheith anseo.  Beidh mé ag éisteacht go haireach le freagra an Aire <Col N="1473" /> inniu féachaint cad iad na smaointí atá aige féin mar Aire Gaeltachta.  Is airsean a bheidh an dualgas na fadhbanna seo a réiteach.  Tá dóchas agam go dtarlóidh rud fiúntach amach anseo.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PrionsiasDeRossa" hpid="Proinsias De Rossa Proinsias De Rossa">
      <NameTxt>Proinsias De Rossa</NameTxt>
      <P>Fáiltím roimh an Aire nua Gaeltachta.  Creidim go dtabharfaidh sé an cuidiú cuí don Ghaeltacht.</P>
      <P>Tá gá le diospóireacht bhunúsach sa Teach seo i dtaobh na Gaeilge agus na Gaeltachta.  Ní raibh a leithéid againn ó tháinig mé isteach sa Teach deich mbliana ó shin.  Ní mór fealsúnacht an Tí i leith caomhnú na Gaeilge a athbhreithniú, féachaint an bhfuiltear dáiríre faoi.  Má tá sé fúinn na Gaeltachtaí a chaomhnú ní féidir a rá go bhfuil ag éirí linn.</P>
      <P>Ní chloistear mórán na laethanta seo faoi aidhm an dátheangachais.  Léigh mé ráiteas leis an Ollamh Pádraig Ó Riagáin, le déanaí, a dúirt nach ionann aidhm an dátheangachais agus aidhm chaomhnú na nGaeltachtaí, agus go raibh cosúlacht ann nárbh fhéidir an dá aidhm a bhaint amach le chéile.  Deir gach Teachta beagnach, go dtacaíonn siad le caomhnú na Gaeilge.  Ní mór dúinn, ar a shon sin, a bheith cinnte go bhfuilimid ag cuidiú leo siúd atá ag obair chuige.</P>
      <P>Tá an Ghaeltacht anois in ísle brí.  Is cinnte go bhfuil daonra na Gaeltachta imithe i laghad, ó bunaíodh an tÚdarás, fiú.  Threisigh ar an imirce sna hochtóidí agus tá sé anois níos coitianta sna Gaeltachtaí ná mar a bhí ó bunaíodh an tÚdarás, trí bhliain déag ó shin.  Dóibh siúd atá fágtha sa Ghaeltacht, tá ceist na fostaíochta ag dul in olcas.  Chonacamar ar chláracha teilifíse na Nollag pictiúrí dár muintir dífhostaithe ag dul thar sáile.  Cé go maíonn an tÚdarás gur tháinig méadú ar líon na bpostanna sa Ghaeltacht anuraidh, níl staististiú ar líon na ndaoine a d'fhág an Ghaeltacht ar fáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Is fiú breathnú anois ar ról an Údaráis féachaint an bhfuil an tÚdarás ag freastal ar phobal na Gaeltachta mar ba chóir.  Tá córas bhóthar na Gaeltachta ar an gcóras bóthair is measa sa tír agus is náireach go n-iarrfaí ar an mhuintir ann díol as obair ar bhóithre portaigh.  Leagtar cáin agus árachas cairr sách trom cheana féin gan <Col N="1474" /> pionós airgid breise a chur orthu, go h-áirithe nuair atá a bhformhór ar an dól.  Tar éis comhairlí contae, údarás agus Roinn Ghaeltachta a bhunadh, ní féidir le dream áirithe daoine móin a bhaint gan bóthar a dheisiú chuige, iad féin.  Cuireann drochstaid na mbóithre Gaeltachta faitíos ar úinéirí comhlachtaí ann nach fada eile a mhairfidh a ngnó.  Ní fheicim cén fáth nach féidir trí nó ceithre chéad duine a fhostú láithreach ar obair dheisithe bóthar.  Tá an saol ag athrú.  An gá ról an Údaráis a athrú leis?  An fiú cumhachtaí breise a thabhairt dó?</P>
    <P>Fáiltím roimh an cinneadh a déanadh i dtaobh theilifís Ghaeltachta agus tá áthas orm gur sa Ghaeltacht a mbunófar í. Cuirfidh an tseirbhís breis postanna ar fáil ach tá súil agam nach daoine atá fostaithe cheana féin a gheobhas iad.  Ní mór foireann dhúthrachtach a fhostú agus na postanna a fhógairt, agus ní cóir go mbeadh ballraíocht i bpáirtí polaitiúil riachtanach dó.  Tá fianaise ann gur déanadh dochar do chomhlachtaí agus d'eagrais a d'fhostaigh daoine a bhí ina mbaill de pháirtí polaitiúil ach nach raibh oiriúnach don phost.  Guím gach rath ar an stáisiún nua seo.</P>
    <P>Ta gnáth fhadhbanna na Gaeltachta le sonrú ar na hoileáin Ghaeltachta freisin agus uaireanta bíonn an cás níos measa orthu.  Tá gá le céanna agus bóithre nua a thógáil ar na h-oileáin agus feabhas a chur ar an infrastructúr atá ann anois. Braitheann an-chuid oileáin ar thurasóireacht mar theacht isteach airgid ach níl córas ceart uisce ná sláintíochta orthu go léir.  Níl leithreas poiblí le fáil ar chuid mhaith oileán.  Measaim nach bhfuil an tÚdarás, an Roinn ná comhairlí contae ag déanamh freastail ceart orthu.</P>
    <P>Is deacair do na Gaeltachtaí beaga suíocháin a bhaint amach ar Bhord an Údaráis, agus ba chóir a réiteach dóibh sa ghné seo.  B'fhéidir go smaoineodh an tAire ar an bpointe sin agus é ag ainmniú baill do Bhord an Údaráis.  Ba chóir iachall a chuir ar bhaill an Bhoird dearbhú páirte a dhéanamh nuair atá tairiscintí tionsclaíochta á meas.</P>
    <P>I would like to say a few words about a number of matters regarding the attitude of this House to Irish.  It is traditional <Col N="1475" /> for those of us who have a few words&mdash;and I admit to having very few compared to some people in this House &mdash; to contribute to debates in Irish on the Gaeltacht, the Irish language and Údarás na Gaeltachta.  We rarely, if ever, hear any contributions in Irish on matters other than those relating to the Gaeltacht or the Irish language.  I do not believe that is because there is any misapprehension or unwillingness on the part of Deputies to speak Irish.  The majority us have some Irish.  Very few of us have a blas or a líofacht, which we would like to have and which some native speakers have. English is my mother tongue.  Having been born and reared in Dublin, I understand that Irish was never the language of Dublin; nevertheless a considerable number of people in the Dublin area&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DinnyMcGinley" hpid="Mr. McGinley Mr. McGinley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGinley</NameTxt>
      <P>More credit to the Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PrionsiasDeRossa" hpid="Proinsias De Rossa Proinsias De Rossa">
      <NameTxt>Proinsias De Rossa</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;speak and try to use the language as much as possible. The difficulties which I and other Deputies have in using the language in this House is time.  I simply do not have the time to sit down and translate my mother tongue, English, into Irish.  I do not have the facility to write a speech in Irish which I could deliver and which would be coherent and incisive.  I made this point before that there is a need for a translation service in this House which Deputies could use if they want to contribute in Irish on a particular debate where they could give speeches or notes to the translation service and receive them in Irish which they would then be capable of delivering.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The other point of some importance is that the lifeblood of Deputies or Senators is publicity and being mentioned in the national or local newspapers.  My experience is that, no matter what I say in Irish in the House it is virtually never reported unless I provide a translation in English. I have had the curious experience of having spoken for the best part of 20 minutes in Irish on Articles 2 and 3 and having provided a translation to the <Col N="1476" /> national newspapers, who duly carried it, but I discovered that the only weekly Irish language newspaper, <i>Anois</i>, totally ignored both the English and the Irish versions.  That struck me as rather odd; but then, given the political inclinations of that paper, I was not a bit surprised.</P>
    <P>I have mentioned the question of <i>Anois</i> before and I will be returning to it with the Minister at some stage.  I feel we have to provide a service for Deputies and Senators which makes it possible for us to make contributions in Irish when we choose to do so.  I do not believe it would be extraordinarily expensive to provide that service.  We already have the facilities here for instantaneous translation from Irish to English and we already have a service attached to the House which provides the Irish version of Bills and so on, so it should not be a huge problem to provide the kind of service that I suggest.</P>
    <P>There are a few further points I wanted to make in relation to Údarás na Gaeltachta which I did not have the opportunity or the time to translate into Irish. These points have been brought to my attention by people who live in the Gaeltacht and who are concerned about the way in which Údarás na Gaeltachta tends to operate.  I have already mentioned the need to ensure that there is a declaration of interest by members of Údarás so as to ensure that members who may have a personal interest in a project should withdraw from debate or decision in relation to such a project.</P>
    <P>There should also be a uniform form of vetting of applications for positions in Údarás grant aided places of employment. At the moment in some cases there are joint Údarás-employer interview panels and in other cases there is an employer only interview board.  In approving grant aid for companies, Údarás should ensure that a proper code of industrial relations is guaranteed. Industry was grant-aided in Kilcar, County Donegal, two years ago, but the employer would not recognise the trade union, paid low wages and insisted on employees working excessive hours in breach of legislation.  I believe Údarás should be given a more autonomous role, <Col N="1477" /> with no political strings attached, to promote the tourist industry in the regions, with special emphasis on language and culture.  The Údaras should hire expertise in order to undertake the setting up of projects on their own or by joint venture capital.  I assume that the Bill the Minister is promoting in this House today would facilitate that kind of approach to developments by Údarás.</P>
    <P>The role of Údarás has, I believe, never been properly defined in relation to the development of the Gaeltacht.  As I mentioned earlier, there is a need for a fairly fundamental debate about our approach to the language, our objectives and the role of Údaras and of the Department itself.  I recall trying to find out in this House which Minister was responsible for the revival of Irish and I discovered that Roinn na Gaeltachta is not responsible for the revival of Irish, it is the Department of Education.  Again, it seems an odd situation to be in.  The Department of Education is a fine organisation, but I do not believe the weight of the revival of Irish should be placed on its shoulders.  In any event, I think this displays a very narrow view of what a language is about.</P>
    <P>The final point I would like to make is that there is a need for some rationalisation of the bodies concerned with the Gaeltacht.  There is a need to look afresh at the boundaries of the Gaeltacht, which were established many years ago and which to a large extent are now irrelevant to the actual areas within which people speak Irish.  I am not suggesting that, for a variety of reasons, the boundary should necessarily be pulled in; but there is a need to look at different ways of dealing with the Gaeltacht and what is known as the breac-Gaeltacht, because I do not think one can have a single approach to both.  Indeed, where an area has become totally English speaking there needs to be a different approach to that again. Perhaps there should be grades of Gaeltachtaí, breac-Gaeltachtaí and so on.</P>
    <P>That is the nub of what I wanted to say here today.  I believe there is a need for a fundamental debate about what we are about and I have every hope that the <Col N="1478" /> Minister will help to initiate that debate I wish him well in his new position.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TrevorSargent" hpid="Mr. Sargent Mr. Sargent">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sargent</NameTxt>
      <P>Cuirim fáilte roimh an Bille seo.  Bhí áthas an domhain orm nuair a ceapadh an Teachta Higgins mar Aire.  Beidh an-tuiscint aige de bharr go bhfuil sé lonnaithe i gceantar a bhfuil cuid de sa Ghaeltacht.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Ó thaobh an Údárais de is cinnte go bhfuil ról an-tábhachtach ag an Udarás i saol na tíre i gcoitinne agus sa Ghaeltacht ach go háirithe.  Ag an am chéanna is gá a bheith an-chúramach mar gheall ar an airgead a chaitear.  Tá sé cineál deacair go minic a dhéanamh amach ó mo thaobhse de cad iad na monarcana a bheidh ag cur fostaíocht chun cinn sa Ghaeltacht nó cad iad na monarcana ar an imeall a bheidh ag sú airgead na Gaeltachta agus i ndáiríre b'fhéidir nach bhfuil chomh tugtha don Ghaelige agus gur mhaith liom a fheiceáil.  Tá ceisteanna agam faoi chúpla áit faoi leith.  Tá fhios agam faoi áit amháin ina bhfuil monarcha iascaireachta le bunú ann.  I ndáirire tá sé taobh amuigh de imeall na Gaeltachta ach de bharr go bhfuil píopa ag dul trasna teorann na Gaeltachta tá an argóint ann gur monarcha don Ghaeltacht í an mhonarcha seo nó an gnó seo agus gur gá go mbeadh deontais an Údaráis agus mar sin de tugtha dí.  Cuirfidh sé leis an siniciúlacht má cheadaítear dá leithéid dul ar aghaidh.  Ba cheart a bheith an-soiléir go bhfuil an tÚdarás i bhfábhar gnó trí Ghaeilge sa Ghaeltacht a chuirfeadh fostaíocht buan ar fáil, go mór mhór fostaíocht a bheadh ag teacht ó na daoine atá lonnaithe ann.  Tá mé ag smaoineamh ar cheardlanna agus mar sin de atá in áiteanna éagsúla sa Ghaeltacht.  Ba bhreá liom dá mbeadh an tacaíocht is mó á tabhairt do dhaoine atá ag smaoineamh as a stuaim féin fostaíocht a chur ar fáil san áit ina bhfuil siad féin ina gcónaí.  Tá ról ann, ar ndóigh, do chomhlachtaí a thagann isteach go dtí an Ghaeltacht agus cuirim fáilte roimh na comhlachtaí sin fhaid is atá siad i ndáiríre.  Muna bhfuil siad i ndáiríre, áfach, maidir le fostaíocht buan a chur ar fáil nó maidir leis an gcultúr, caithfear a bheith ag smaoineamh ar chonas a chaitear an t-airgead sin.  Ba <Col N="1479" /> cheart a chur ina luí ar ghnó ag teacht isteach sa Ghaeltacht nach bhfuil siad ann ar son fostaíochta amháin cé go bhfuil sé sin tábhachtach.  Tá mé cinnte go go dtuigfidh siad é sin má tá sé ráite go soiléir.  Ní chóir a bheith ag cur dallamhullóg orainn féin.  Má táimid ag cur fostaíocht ar fáil ní leor é sin chun an cultúr agus an Ghaeilge a choimeád beo. D'fhéadfadh an-chuid monarchan a bheith sa Ghaeltacht agus blas Meiriceánach ar an hoibrithe den chuid is mó.  Ní bheadh an Ghaeilge ann sa chás sin mar caithfear an dá rud a thabhairt le chéile.</P>
    <P>Is cinnte go gcabhróidh an tÚdarás má táimidne agus gach éinne eile i ndáiríre mar gheall ar an ngnó agus na haidhmeanna atá acu.  Cuirim fáilte roimh an mBille agus geallaim go mbeidh tacaíocht ón gComhaontas Glas ag an Údarás sa ghnó a bheidh ar siúl acu agus ag an Aire san chúram an-tábhachtach atá aige.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="An tAire Ealaíon, Cultúir agus Gaeltachta (Mr. M. Higgins) An tAire Ealaíon, Cultúir agus Gaeltachta (Mr. M. Higgins)">
      <NameTxt>An tAire Ealaíon, Cultúir agus Gaeltachta (Mr. M. Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>: Ar an gcéad dul síos gabhainn fíor-bhuíochas leis na Teachtaí a ghlac páirt sa díospóireacht seo.  Chomh maith leis sin gabhaim buíochas leo as an fháilte a chuir siad romham féin mar Aire agus as na deá-ghuíthe uathu.  Tosnóidh mé ar an ghné sin de mar, ag éisteacht leis an díospóireacht a bhí againn ar maidin, na pointí a léirigh na Teachtaí éagsúla, ní pointí ag teacht ó aigní cumhanga iad.  Bhí chuile Theachta ag déanamh iarracht fhiúntach moltaí a chur ar aghaidh a bheadh ar leas mhuintir na Gaeltachta agus lucht na Gaeilge. Bhí mé ag éisteacht go suimiúil leis na pointí a luaigh siad.  Ní rabhadar ag glacadh páirt sa díospóireacht ar leibhéal pháirtithe polaitiúla ach toisc go bhfuil géar chéim na Gaeilge sna Gaeltachtaí.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Dúirt an Teachta McGinley go raibh deacrachtaí ar leith ag baint leis na Gaeltachtaí &mdash; ó thaobh tionscail a bhunú iontu agus mar sin de.  Aontaím leis. Beidh sé mar cheann de na buntáistí tar éis an Bhille seo.  Rinne an Teachta Molloy tagairt dó sin freisin.  Nílim ach ag glanadh suas ar bhealach.  Ni bheidh <Col N="1480" /> orm teacht ar ais go dtí an Dáil agus an leibhéal a ardú arís agus arís eile.  Chomh maith leis sin beidh an tÚdarás ar chomhchéim leis na hÚdaráis eile atá ag déanamh iarrachta tionscail a mhealladh agus a bhunú.  Beidh na coinníollacha féaráilte agus ar an leibhéal céanna.  Tá mé féin báúil chun féachaint isteach sa scéal, an mbeidh mé in ann seansanna eile a thabhairt don Údarás amach anseo taréis an Bhille seo a rith.</P>
    <P>Ní bheidh aon bhaint ag na boird chontae leis na Gaeltachtaí.  Tá an socrú sin déanta.  Tá mé féin ag féachaint isteach ar an gcaoí is féidir linn oibriú amach as seo.  Rud eile atá tábhachtach: nuair a bheidh an Bille seo críochnaithe beidh seans agam tabhairt faoin gceist go ginearálta. Tá sin ag teastáil.  Ó 1979 ar aghaidh nuair a cuireadh an chéad Bhille bunúsach os comhair an Oireachtais, ar bhealach ní raibh an díospóireacht leathan go leor sna blianta atá imithe.  An bhfuil an t-am tagtha anois chun féachaint ar an mBille sin arís &mdash; na cuspóirí agus na cumhachtaí atá ann agus mar sin de?  Ba mhaith liom go mbeadh seans agam ar an gcéad dul síos &mdash; mar nílim anseo ach mí amháin &mdash; dul chun cainte leis an Údarás féin, leis na hoifigigh agus leis na ranna éagsúla.  An rud atá uaim ná sa ghearr-théarma, taobh istigh de bhliain nó dhó, go mbeadh na seirbhísí agus an obair go léir snoite le chéile ionas nach mbeadh aon iomaíocht ann.  Ba mhaith liom dá mbeadh na cuspóirí atá ag an Údarás níos soiléire agus nach mbeadh bac orthu a bheith a plé le údaráis eile agus mar sin de.</P>
    <P>Tá mé féin báúil don rud a dhéanamh simplí, níos soiléire agus níos scioptha i dtreo na haidhmeanna a bhaint amach. Chomh maith leis sin ní chóir go mbeadh aon amhras ar an Teachta McGinley ná go mbeidh mé ag déanamh cíorú ar na deacrachtaí, go háirithe atá ag comhlachtaí éagsúla de bharr na titime sa phunt sterling agus na ndeacrachtaí ó thaobh an currency de.</P>
    <P>Luaigh na Teachtaí go léir Teilifís na Gaeilge.  Ní gá dom an argóint a dhéanamh arís.  An pointe bunúsach atá ann ná má tá meán cumarsáide atá bunaithe ar <Col N="1481" /> an chluas in iomaíocht le ceann atá bunaithe ar an chumas féachana níl aon amhras orm féin ná go mbeidh an bua ag an teilifís i gcónaí.  Dá bhrí sin, má tá tú ag iarraidh do chlann a thógaint le Gaeilge ní féidir leat glacadh leis na coinníollacha sin.  Chomh maith le Teilifís na Gaeilge tá cumas eile ag an scéim. Glacaim féin leis na hargóintí toisc go bhfuil sé mar chuid den chumhacht chum-arsáide. Ba chóir go mbeadh sé in ann freastal ar chomhluadar na Gaeilge chomh maith.  Caithfimid féachaint chuige go dtógfaimid le chéile i gcónaí comhluadar na nGaeltachtaí agus comhluadar na Gaeilge mar a luaigh Teachtaí éagsúla.</P>
    <P>Tá súil agam go mbeidh dul ar aghaidh taobh istigh den téarma atá leaghtha síos déanta agam le Teilifís na Gaeilge, fiú amháin tosnú ar an obair bhunúsach an bhliain seo.</P>
    <P>Rinne an Teachta Molloy tagairt don am a chaitheamar le chéile in áit eile atá an-ghearr domsa agus níos faide dósan. Ba mhaith liom mo bhuíochas a ghabháil leis.  Tuigim gur Teachta é atá an-dáiríre faoi chúrsaí na Gaeltachta agus cursaí na n-oileán a bhfuil suim speisialta aige iontu.  Tá an pointe sin faoi tuilleadh cumhachta a thabhairt don Údarás freagraithe agam.  Tuigim an pointe atá á dhéanamh aige.  Is é sin má tá tú, mar shampla, chun tionscal a bhunúi nGaeltacht ar bith agus má tá ar an duine atá ag iarraidh comhlacht a bhunú deileáil leis an Údarás maidir le infheistíocht b'fhéidir in áit mar Ros a' Mhíl, in a dhiaidh sin tá comhairle chontae ag plé le cúrsaí bóthar.  Is féidir an buntáiste atá ag baint le airgead a chailliúint toisc nach bhfuil na seirbhísí á fhorbairt ag an am céanna chun an pointe céanna a bhaint amach.</P>
    <P>Tá deacracht ag an nGaeltacht mar is mionlach iad taobh istigh den chomhairle chontae.  Tá mé báúil don phointe atá á dhéanamh ag an Teachta agus mar adúirt mé i dteangbháil leis na h-údaráis éagsúla, tá súil agam go mbeidh seans agam teacht go dtí an Teach seo le Bille níos leithne i leith na bpointí sin.</P>
    <P>Aontaím leis an Teachta chomh maith faoi bhrú an Bhéarla.  Tá sin fíor agus <Col N="1482" /> luaigh an Teachta De Rossa pointe suimiúil faoi dhátheangachas agus an teanga a athbheocan.  Nílim féin cinnte go bhfuil freagra dearfach ar an cheist sin.  Tá daoine báúil don Ghaeilge.  Tá úsáid na Gaeilge ag méadú an t-am go léir sna cathracha agus ag an am chéanna tá an Ghaeilge faoi bhrú sna Gaeltachtaí.  Tá cúiseanna áirithe leis sin, a luaigh Teachtaí éagsúla.  Caithfimid féachaint chuige, agus sin an tábhacht a bhaineann le Teilifís na Gaeilge, go mbeadh dearcadh nuaaimsireach ar an nGaeilge, gur mhaith an rud é Gaeilge a úsáid agus go mbeadh seans ag daoine Gaeilge a úsáid.  Ag tosnú dom ar Aireacht na Gaeltachta, nílim sásta go bhfuil a gcearta á dtabhairt do mhuintir na Gaeltachta i leith úsáid na Gaeilge, ag an Stát nó ag eagrais Stáit. Ní mór é sin a cheartú agus deis a thabhairt do mhuintir na Gaeltachta a gcuid gnó a dhéanamh trí Ghaeilge le dignit.</P>
    <P>Thrácht an Teachta De Rossa ar úsáid na Gaeilge sa Teach seo.  Aontaím lena ndúirt sé i dtaobh deacrachtaí iriseoir-eachta, a bhain leis an Teach i gcónaí, agus nílim sásta gur comhlíonadh moltaí uilig Chomhchoiste na Gaeilge sa cheist. Níl áis chuí ann chun cóip d'óráid i nGaeilge a fháil go scioptha.  Tá an córas aistriúcháin faoi bhrú.  Má táimid dáirire faoi úsáid na Gaeilge san Oireachtas ní mór don Aire Airgeadais ciste airgid a chur ar fáil le háiseanna riachtanacha a sholáthar a chuirfeadh ar chumas Teachtaí mar an Teachta De Rossa, níos mó Gaeilge a úsáid sa Teach.  Déanfaidh mé mo dhícheall sa ghnó seo.</P>
    <P>Luaigh an Teachta De Rossa cumhachtaí an Údaráis, teilifís na Gaeilge, agus na hoileáin Ghaeltachta.  Ní móide ná go bhfuil deacrachtaí ar leith le sárú ag na hoileáin.  Tá bád nua ar fáil anois chun freastal ar Oileán Árainn ach beidh céanna nua ag teastáil ar Inis Meáin agus ar Inis Oírr chuige sin.  Tá súil agam go réiteofar na deacrachtaí taistil agus iompair ann sar i bhfad agus beidh seans againn go luath tagairt a dhéanamh do sin go foirmeálta.  Ní ligfidh an Teachta Molloy dom é a ligean i ndearmad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá súil agam nach rachaidh <Col N="1483" /> an Rialtas seo siar ar an cinneadh a déanadh i leith Inis Meáin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M. Higgins Mr. M. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá an cinneadh déanta agus is dóigh leis an Rialtas gur chóir an t-airgead a chur ar fáil chuige. Ní ghlacfaidh mé leis an dushlán an uair seo ón dTeachta; tuigeann sé cad atá i gceist.</P>
      <P>B'fhéidir, mar a luaigh an Teachta De Rossa, gur mithid dearbhú páirtí a lorg ó bhaill an Údaráis.  Tá Bille ar an ábhar seo á thionscnú ag an Aire Airgeadais agus tá teangmháil á dhéanamh ag oifigigh mo Roinne leis féachaint an féidir na leasuithe oiriúnacha a thabhairt i gcrích le chéile.</P>
      <P>Thagair an Teachta do theorainn caiteachais. Ceist theibí í seo ach i leith infheistíocht agus airleacain Ghaeltachta ní mór dúinn fiafraí i gcónaí an rachaidh gach caiteachas chun leas mhuintir na Gaeltachta?  Más ar leas na Gaeltachta atá airgead á chaitheamh, ní cóir cloí le sean sainmhinithe go hiomarcach; ba mhaith liom coimriú a dhéanamh ar an gceist seo ach is ceist chasta í.  Gabhaim buíochas leis na Teachtaí a ghlac páirt sa díospóireacht fhiúntach ar an Dara Céim agus molaim sprid an chomhoibreachais agus spéis na dTeachtaí éagsúla i leith an Bhille.  Aithním an cúnamh atá á thairiscint acu domsa agus dom' Roinn agus beidh mé sásta éisteacht le moltaí uathu.</P>
      <P>Cuireadh agus aontaíodh an cheist.</P>
      <P>Aontaíodh na Céimeanna eile a thógáil inniu.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="An Bille um Údarás na Gaeltachta (Leasú)" RHead="1993; Céim an Choiste agus an Chéim Dheiridh">
    <Title>An Bille um Údarás na Gaeltachta (Leasú) 1993; Céim an Choiste agus an Chéim Dheiridh.</Title>
    <P>Aontaíodh alt 1.</P>
    <P>Tairgeadh an Cheist: &ldquo;Go bhfanfaidh alt 2 mar chuid den Bhille.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>An bhféadfadh an tAire a chur in iúl don Teach, maidir leis na deontais a cheadaíonn Údarás na Gaeltachta, cad é an difríocht idir méid na ndeontas sin agus méid na ndeontas a thairiscíonn an IDA, agus an bhfuil difríocht <Col N="1484" /> idir na rialacha a cheanglaíonn deontais ar dá eagrais?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Aire Ealaíon, Cultúir Gaeltachta (Mr. M. Higgins) Aire Ealaíon, Cultúir Gaeltachta (Mr. M. Higgins)">
      <NameTxt>Aire Ealaíon, Cultúir Gaeltachta (Mr. M. Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>Faoi alt 2 den Bhille seo is féidir airgead Stáit a chur ar fáil don Údarás chun deontas-i-gcabhair a íoc le haidhmeanna an Údaráis a chomhlíonadh, is é sin, caiteachas riaracháin, caiteachas i gcoitinne, deontais scaireanna, tógáil, ceannach maoine agus mar sin de.  Sin é an coinníoll atá ann ó thaobh caiteachais go ginearálta.  Faoi sheirbhisí agus bunstructúr tionscail, tá an chonstaic sin imithe agus beidh an tÚdarás solúbtha i dtaobh caiteachais má mheastar go gcuideoidh an caiteachas le haidhmeanna an Údaráis.  Ar an mionleibhéal a bhí i gceist ag an Teachta, níl figúirí comparáideacha agam ach dob fhéidir liom iad a chur chuige.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>Sin í an cheist.  Bunaíodh an tÚdarás le go mbeadh údarás faoi leith ag freastal ar na ceantair Ghaeltachta i dtaca le fostaíocht thionsclaíochta.  Leis an aidhm sin a bhaint amach ní mór go mbeadh buntáistí ag an Údarás thar an IDA, ó thaobh leibhéal na ndeontas.  Cad iad na leibhéil éagsúla sa dá eagras?  Cad iad na buntáistí atá le tairiscint ag an Údarás?  Muna bhfuil aon bhuntáiste ann, ní féidir a rá go bhfuilimid i ndáiríre anseo faoi eisceachtaí a dhéanamh don Ghaeltacht agus aitheantas a thabhairt dá deacrachtaí speisialta agus iad ag iarraidh tionsclaithe a mhealladh isteach.  Méadaítear ar chostais tionsclaíochta de bharr iargúltacht agus deacrachtaí taistil na Gaeltachta, mar is eol don Aire.  Nuair a phléigh An Comhchoiste um Chomhlachtaí Stát-Tionscanta Tráchtála scéal Udarás na Gaeltachta roinnt bhlianta ó shin, léiríodh go raibh deontais etc. níos fiaile i dteideal an IDA ná mar a bhí ag Údarás na Gaeltachta.  Déanadh iarratas ag an am go n-athrófaí an scéal sin ionas go mbeadh an buntáiste ag na ceantair Ghaeltachta a bhí faoi chúram an Údaráis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M. Higgins Mr. M. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá dhá ghné sa cheist seo.  Teastaíonn uaim go mbeadh níos mó solúbthachta anois ná mar a bhí agus <Col N="1485" /> beidh mé in ann buntáistí a chur ar fáil don Údarás nach raibh acu cheana, sa mhéid sin.</P>
      <P>Tá tábhacht ag baint leis sin.  Maidir leis an bpointe a luaigh an Teachta ó thaobh an leibhéil chaipitil de, tá an leibhéal caipitil níos airde sa Ghaeltacht ná taobh amuigh de agus beidh, i leith infheistíochta.  Tá seirbhísí eile i gceist agam a thiocfaidh i gcabhair ar an Údarás sna deacrachtaí a luaigh an Teachta Molloy agus Teachtaí eile, deacrachtaí speisialta a bhaineann le áiteanna iargúlta agus a bhaineann leis na Gaeltachtaí. Ba mhaith liom na ceisteanna seo a phlé leis an Údarás sna cainteanna a bheidh agam leo.</P>
      <P>Tógann sin ar ais muid go dtí an chéad phointe, is é sin na seirbhísí a leathnú más féidir liom agus na seirbhísí a bheith i gcomhthéacs an leathnaithe atá á dhéanamh agam ó thaobh chaiteachais de.  Ansin bheadh buntáiste ag an Údarás ó lá go lá i gcomparáid le údaráis eile.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>An bhfuil rialacha i bhfeidhm ag an Údarás nach bhfuil sé de chead aige deontais a cheadú thar leibhéal áirithe gan an cheist ar fad a chur faoi bhráid an Aire?  Cad iad na leibhéil sin faoi láthair?  An aontaíonn an tAire leis an srian seo atá á chur ar bhord an Údaráis? Ó thaobh na mion-deontaisí cad é an leibhéal deontais atá ar fáil anois faoi sin?  Bhí moltaí áirithe ag an gcoiste ag an am sin go gcuirfí ar ceal an réiteach a bhí ann go rachfaí i gcomhairle le baill an bhoird ón gceantar áitiúil as a raibh an togra ag teacht.  Tá súil agam go bhfuil sin curtha ar ceal.  An bhféadfadh an tAire a chinntiú go bhfuil?  Nó cén sórt rialacha atá a gcur i bhfeidhm?  Ar láimh amháin tá sé maith go leor dúinne an Bille seo a thabhairt don Aire inniu ach má tá rialacha i bhfeidhm ag an Roinn atá ag cur srian ar an Údarás ba mhaith linn a fháil amach cad é meon an Aire nua faoi na rialacha sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M. Higgins Mr. M. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Má tá siad chun caiteachas £750,000 a dhéanamh caithfidh siad teacht chugamsa chun cead a fháil. Sin an freagra ar an chéid cheist.  Ach tá an dara ceist níos casta, is í sin cén <Col N="1486" /> dearcadh atá ag an Aire faoin rud seo ar fad.  An aidhm atá agam ná go mbeadh Údarás na Gaeltachta ag feidhmiú mar údarás réigiúnda.  B'fhéidir amach anseo go mbeadh an sórt leagan amach céanna ag an Údarás is atá ag aon údarás réigiúnda eile taobh istigh de Chomhphobal na Eorpa.  Is mian liom coimriú a dhéanamh ar aon chonstaic ar bith faoi na leibhéil éagsúla.  Tuigim pointe an Teachta, go gcaithfidh siad dul amach ag iomaíocht sa mhargadh faoi bhunú tionscail agus má éiríonn leo an bhfuil sé ag cabhrú leo go bhfuil orthu teacht ar ais chun ceadúnas a fháil uaimse?  An aidhm atá agam féin ná go mbeadh Údarás reigiúnda foirfe, fiúntach ann agus nach mbeadh constaicí in a mbealach. Caithfidh mé scrúdú a dhéanamh ar a lán nithe.  Tá nithe áirithe a bhfuil eolas le fáil agam féin orthu ach ní hionann an sampla atá ar fáil i nGaeltacht amháin agus i nGaeltachtaí eile.  Tá deacrachtaí ag baint le infheistíocht in áiteanna nach bhfuil ag baint leis in áiteanna eile.  Ach go ginearálta is fiú go mbeadh neamhspleáchas ag an Údarás taobh istigh de pholasaí agus go mbeadh an polasaí sin leagtha síos sa Dáil ó thaobh fostaíochta agus mar sin de.  Gné den pholasaí sin atá an-tábhachtach ná an chaoi ina thagann cúrsaí teanga, tionsclaíochta agus soceolaíochta isteach sa cheist.  Nuair atá an polasaí sin leagtha amach ba cheart go mbeadh an tÚdarás éifeachtach.  Tá mé ag déanamh iarrachta a bheith díreach leis an Teachta faoin rud seo.  Ba mhaith liom nach mbeadh mo Roinn ag seasamh idir tionsclaí ar bith agus an tÚdarás an t-am go léir.  Má tá constaic ann agus más féidir iad a bhogadh déanfaidh mé é sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>Mhol coiste na Dála go n-ardófaí an leibhéal sin ó leath-mhilliún punt go dtí millíun punt.  Má chuala mé an tAire i gceart tá sé anois ag rá gurb é an leibhéal atá i bhfeidhm faoi láthair ná £750,000.  Dá bhrí sin níor ghlac an tAire leis an moladh a bhí ag coiste Dála i 1986, is é sin é a ardú go dtí milliún punt.  Anois ag 1993 tá an leibhéal ag £750,000.  Tá mé ag iarraidh a fháil amach an bhfuil an tAire chun é sin a athrú?  An aontaíonn sé leis na moltaí a bhí ag an gcoiste Dála <Col N="1487" /> i 1986, mar dá gcuirfí sin i bhfeidhm i 1986 b'fhéidir go mbeimis anois ag labhairt faoi £1.5 mhilliún.</P>
      <P>Bhí mé ag iarraidh a fháil amach chomh maith an bhfuil srianta eile ann faoi dheontais ar leibhéal níos ísle ná sin. An é sin an leibhéal go gcaithfear dul go dtí an Rialtas leis nó go dtí an Aire?  Bhí rialacha curtha i bhfeidhm ag iar-Aire sa Roinn ina bhfuil an tAire go gcaithfí teacht chuige sula bhféadfadh an bord deontas a cheadú le haghaidh togra ar leibhéal i bhfad níos ísle ná sin.  Tá mé ag iarraidh a fháil amach an bhfuil sin i bhfeidhm fós nó an bhfuil sé curtha ar ceal.  Creidim go raibh an riail sin i bhfeidhm nuair a bhí Pádraig Ó Floinn ina Aire.  Tá sé sin difriúil ar fad ón riail go gcaithfí teacht chuig an Aire Gaeltachta, Aire Airgeadais agus an Rialtas a bheith curtha ar an eolas faoin cheist sula dtabharfaí cead do na mór-dheontais.  Tá leibhéal na mór-dheontas ag £750,000.  An aontaíonn an tAire nach bhfuil sin mór go leor mar ba chóir go mbeadh i bhfad níos mó neamhspleáchais, mar adúirt an tAire, ag an mbord deontas a cheadú suas go dtí leibhéal, b'fhéidir, £1.5 mhillúin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M. Higgins Mr. M. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Teastaíonn uaim dul chun cinn a dhéanamh faoi seo.  Glacaim nach bhfuil an figiúr £750,000 in oiriúint don am seo, b'fhéidir.  Nuair a bheidh scrúdú níos mion déanta agam ar an tuarascáil má fhaighim seans &mdash; agus b'fhéidir nach mbeidh Bille eile ag teastáil &mdash; tiocfaidh mé ar ais b'fhéidir má bhíonn leasuithe eile le déanamh ar an mBille agus beidh mé báúil don leibhéal a ardú.</P>
      <P>Chomh maith leis sin ba mhaith liom a rá nach bhfuil na ceilings ann a thuilleadh ach tá sin imithe.  An teora atá ann bain-eann sé leis an £750,000 agus tá mé báiúil é sin a athrú chomh luath agus is féidir liom é a dhéanamh.  Tuigim an comhréir atá á dhéanamh ag an Teachta, mar shampla, idir an figiúr a bhí ann agus an t-athrú atá tagtha ar an airgead agus mar sin de.  Déanfaidh mé e sin a chíorú.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>Níor fhreagair an tAire an cheist faoi na mion-deontais.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1488" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M. Higgins Mr. M. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl na mion-suim-eanna i gceist.  Níl aon teora leo.  Ní gá go dtiocfadh siad sin chugamsa.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá a fhios sin agam.  Ceist eile ar fad a bhí agam.  An cheist a bhí agam ná an rud a tharraing an coiste Dála suas ag an am.  Léifidh mé é amach i mBéarla mar tá an tuarascáil seo scríofa i mBéarla.  Seo moladh an choiste Dála: &ldquo;that the requirement to consult with the locally elected board representative during the processing of minor grant applications be discontinued&rdquo;.  Ar cuireadh an rud sin ar ceal?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M. Higgins Mr. M. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní dóigh liom go bhfuil ciall ar bith le dul i gcomhairle le baill den bhord faoi choinníol foirmiúl. Thuig mé go raibh baill den bhord i dteagmháil le hoifigigh go neamhfhoirmiúil agus tá an cheart acu dá réir.  Nílim i bhfábhar coinníol foirmiúil a dhéanamh de mar a mhol an tuarascáil, nach bhfuil os mo chomhair anois.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>B'fhéidir nach bhfuil sé i bhfeidhm an t-am ar fad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M. Higgins Mr. M. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní feidir liom an cheist sin a fhreagairt anois.  Gheobhaidh mé an t-eolas don Teachta.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertMolloy" hpid="Mr. Molloy Mr. Molloy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molloy</NameTxt>
      <P>Ach má tá an coinníol ann, cuirfidh an tAire ar ceal é?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M. Higgins Mr. M. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Sin é an dearcadh a bheadh agam féin.</P>
      <P>Cuireadh agus aontaíodh an cheist.</P>
      <P>Aontaíodh ailt 3 agus 4.</P>
      <P>Aontaíodh an Teideal.</P>
      <P>Cuireadh agus aontaíodh an Cheist.</P>
      <P>Aontaíodh an Sceideal.</P>
      <P>Ritheadh an Bille.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="National Stud (Amendment) Bill, 1993:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>National Stud (Amendment) Bill, 1993: Second Stage.</Title>
    <Col N="1489" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. J. Walsh) Joe Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. J. Walsh)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The Irish National Stud is located on over 800 acres of land at Tully, County Kildare, on the edge of the Curragh. Thoroughbred horses have been bred on the farm since 1900, when it was acquired by Colonel William Hall-Walker.  The land and buildings were presented to the State in 1943.  The National Stud (Company) Limited was set up under the National Stud Act, 1945, to lease the land from the Minister for Agriculture and to carry on the business of stud farming on the land.</P>
      <P>The 1945 Act gave the stud the power to set up and operate schemes for the improvement of thoroughbred breeding. The stud's main method of operation was to improve available blood lines by providing the services of highclass stallions to as wide a range of breeders as possible.</P>
      <P>The National Stud purchased its first stallion in 1946 when it acquired Royal Charger.  He went on to become one of the leading sires of his era.  The tradition has been maintained over the years with many outstanding stallion purchases, such as Lord Gayle, Ahonoora and Crash Course.  I think that it is fair to say that the stud has admirably fulfilled its role in thoroughbred breeding over the years. This is underlined by the fact that over 700 brood mares visited the stud in 1992.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In addition to its core stallion and thoroughbred breeding business, the Irish National Stud is involved in a wide range of activities, from farming to tourism and training personnel for the bloodstock sector.  While I am very conscious that the central activity of the stud must remain bloodstock breeding and the necessary related farming business, many of its other activities are very important and may not be generally well known. First among these is its tourism role.  The stud and the Japanese Gardens at Tully are now well established tourist attractions with over 80,000 paying visitors annually.  Last year 87,000 visitors called <Col N="1490" /> to the Japanese Gardens and the horse museum.  This activity has been turned into a profit maker in recent years and is capable of further significant development. However, the general facilities at the stud are not adequate to cope with an increasing throughput of visitors. Accordingly, a new visitors' centre, costing in the region of £600,000, is under construction and is scheduled to open at Easter this year.  This centre will be capable of servicing the increased tourist numbers projected by providing the ambience demanded by discerning visitors. The centre will incorporate a ticket office, restaurant, souvenir shops, toilet and washroom facilities.  This centre will provide an appropriate backup to the unique and celebrated Japanese Gardens.</P>
    <P>The Irish Horse Museum within the stud grounds was established in 1977.  The museum, featuring the skeleton of the great Arkle, traces the evolution of the Irish horse from prehistoric times to the modern era.  Included are exhibits of folk life, transport, racing, hunting and showjumping.  The existing building is rather cramped and plans for a new building are under consideration.</P>
    <P>The visitors' centre, Japanese Gardens and museum are complemented by the development of a walking trail through the general stud grounds where visitors can view horses in the paddocks at all times.</P>
    <P>Mindful of its role in the horse sector in general the stud organises a horse-breeding training course for 25 to 30 young persons each spring.  This course, which has been in operation for over 20 years, is recognised within the bloodstock industry as the best of its type in the world.  Graduates of the course manage some of the biggest stud farms in the world and have trained winners in three continents last year.  It has never been known for a graduate of the course to fail to be placed in employment.  This is a remarkable achievement in the present environment of high levels of umemployment, particularly in view of the fact that it is operated without any subsidy or assistance from the State.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1491" /> Horse racing and breeding have for many years formed an important part of Irish life.  Racing provides a valuable leisure activity for many people.  As an outdoor sport, it can be regarded as a true family activity enjoyed in a healthy, natural environment.  There is also a place for the armchair enthusiast, of course, whether it is in front of the TV in the living room or in the betting shop. Despite the generally difficult economic conditions prevailing last year, attendances at race meetings and betting on the tote held up well.  Attendances were up by 3 per cent and stood at over one million. This was the sixth year in a row that attendances topped the one million mark.  Tote betting also increased by 3 per cent in 1992.</P>
    <P>While many people look on the thoroughbred sector purely in terms of leisure activity I must emphasise that for other people it is a very serious activity from which they earn their living.  Up to 25,000 people are directly or indirectly employed in the thoroughbred sector. This industry must be considered an important source of employment.  This factor is all the more important when one realises that much of the employment is available in rural areas where alternative work can be scarce.</P>
    <P>While the breeding of thoroughbreds is a scientific activity, it is in Ireland primarily a farm-based enterprise.  I regard this as the basic strength of our thoroughbred breeding sector.  Breeding activity is characterised by the relatively large number of breeders with just one or two brood mares.  Obviously, the brood mares are normally used to supplement the farm income achieved from more conventional farm activities.  Most of these breeders are involved in the business of producing foals or yearlings for the annual sales.</P>
    <P>I must emphasise that a certain level of risk is associated with the breeding and production of livestock in general, but the thoroughbred sector entails a much higher level of risk than more conventional livestock production systems. While the cost of production of a foal or <Col N="1492" /> yearling can be forecast with reasonable accuracy, the price obtained at the sales is very difficult to predict.  This sets the thoroughbred apart from other enterprises on our farms.  Accordingly, it is prudent for many farmers to regard thoroughbred breeding as a supplementary enterprise.</P>
    <P>While mare ownership is traditionally a supplementary activity on farms, the stallion sector is characterised by a relatively small number of studs with ten or more stallions.  Such studs are professionally managed and many of the stallions command high fees.  These studs are part of a truly international breeding business and the market for top quality stallions is a highly competitive international one.  This is the environment in which the Irish National Stud must operate.</P>
    <P>The Irish thoroughbred sector was put on a solid footing with the introduction in the 1969 Finance Act of the concessionary tax regime in respect of stallion nomination fees.  This set the scene for the location of larger numbers of top class stallions in Ireland and enabled our breeders to emerge as a dynamic force in the world thoroughbred sector.  The emergence of a small number of larger, highly professional stallion studs over the last 20 years has led to a questioning of the continuing necessity for a national stud.  I am firmly of the view that there remains the need for a vibrant and competitive national stud to service breeders in the long term.  The Killanin report of 1986 was also of this view.</P>
    <P>Since its foundation, the Irish National Stud has played a significant role in the development of Irish bloodstock.  Historically, the stud has been a viable and profitable operation with a strong capital structure.  This profitable situation has been reversed, unfortunately, in the last few years when losses averaging over £500,000 per year were incurred.  The main contributory factors have been the downturn in the bloodstock industry worldwide, with a consequent substantial reduction in nomination fees, and the stud's difficulty in maintaining the quality of its stallions due to financial constraints. <Col N="1493" /> Faced with this situation, the stud made strenuous efforts to curtail the costs associated with its operations.  While these efforts have been moderately successful, the reductions achieved have not been sufficient to compensate for the very substantial decline in income from nomination fees.  The stud needs to acquire new stallions on an ongoing basis.  Currently, the stud has seven stallions and it urgently needs to acquire new ones and to increase the numbers standing if it is to retain its client base and improve revenues.  However, the company is unable to provide the capital required to do so from its own resources.</P>
    <P>The purchase of untried stallions is a high risk business.  However, in a large operation like the National Stud the risks can be spread over a number of stallions. The capital cost of a top class stallion can be from £1 million upwards and most stallions are syndicated to spread the ownership risk.  The National Stud has also used this mechanism to reduce exposure to acceptable levels of risk.</P>
    <P>The board of the stud submitted a five-year development plan to me last year. The main proposal was an injection of fresh capital, principally to purchase a number of top quality stallions.  Furthermore, the board has sought an increase in borrowing powers from the current £0.5 million to enable the stud to move quickly and effectively to acquire suitable stallions when they become available.  I have asked the new board to re-examine the plan with a view to restructuring the stud's activities in the most cost effective way, particularly in respect of the core stud activity.</P>
    <P>This Bill, which will amend The National Stud Acts, 1945 and 1976, proposes to increase the National Stud's borrowing powers from £0.5 million to £5 million.  It also proposes to increase the share capital of the National Stud from £5 million to £10 million.  To date the State has purchased all but £24,626 of the £5 million in share capital which is authorised under existing legislation.  The last purchase was of 800,000 shares of £1 each, which was made by the Minister for Finance in December last year.  These <Col N="1494" /> financial provisions are enabling ones. The power to borrow is subject to the consent of the Ministers for Agriculture, Food and Forestry and Finance.  The increased share capital will be issued when and as considered appropriate by the two Ministers referred to.  The Bill also provides for statutory control of staff pay.</P>
    <P>The stud, with its current staff complement of 46, will have to face a number of challenges in the future.  The proposed route of the Kildare town by-pass will go through a part of the stud and will cause some disruption to its activities.  I believe that the stud can play a significant role in the Irish thoroughbred industry in the years ahead &mdash; an industry that portrays a positive image of Ireland abroad.  The Irish National Stud has provided the farmer-breeder with access to the top blood-lines and enabled our breeders to carve out a special place in a competitive international business.  The Bill before the Members today is necessary if the Irish National Stud is to have the financial flexibility necessary to enable it to continue to deliver access to international quality stallions to small breeders at affordable rates.</P>
    <P>I commend this Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="IvanYates" hpid="Mr. Yates Mr. Yates">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yates</NameTxt>
      <P>We have no particular difficulty with this Bill, but it affords the House the opportunity to scrutinise the National Stud and its performance.  On this side of the House I believe there is an obligation to make a very critical analysis of the National Stud and its performance. A blind man could see that there is a need to increase the borrowing and share capital limits of the stud.  It cannot continue to operate in the present hamstrung way.  The stud is 46 years old. I regret to say that in recent years since 1988, it has traded with significant losses. My first criticism &mdash; and this is not just of the stud but of the Department &mdash; is that when I went to the Library to get the up to date financial picture of the stud I was given the last three published accounts, those for the years 1987, 1988 and 1989.  The latter runs to the end of the financial year, December 1989, and <Col N="1495" /> is three years out of date.  I know of no investor, equity fund manager or pension fund manager who would think of giving increased borrowing powers, increased injection of equity, to a company that had not produced or published accounts for three years up to December 1992.  As a practice, I have to say that that is wholly undesirable and, quite frankly, unacceptable, and that the taxpayer deserves better.</P>
      <P>From the latest published accounts we have, from 1988 and 1989, we see that in 1988 the stud made a net loss of £429,000, increasing to £467,000 in 1989.  It seems from what the Minister said, which was quite informative, that in the last few years it has lost about £500,000 per annum.  If we assume that to be the case, it seems to be in a fairly serious permanent loss-making situation; and from reading the chairman's comments it appears that this has been financed by increasing the overdraft limit in consecutive years and running down the stallion replacement fund.</P>
      <P>This brings me to my more serious criticism of the stud.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As someone who has a very keen interest in the racing industry and in the betting industry, I believe that the quality of stallions at the National Stud is not what it was in the past &mdash; stallions of the quality and renowned progeny of Lord Gale, who was a soft ground specialist; horses such as Carroll House, who won a Prix de l'Arc de Triomphe, and Executive Perk.  Crash Course, unfortunately, died when he was establishing himself as one of the best National Hunt stallions. Sallust was another very good commercial stallion producing good flat early two year olds.  Ahonoora was exceptional, producing many group and classic winners, including Don't Forget Me, a dual classic winner.  Through unfortunate deaths and sales &mdash; as in the case of Ahonoora, who was syndicated and sold &mdash; and through retirements as in the case of Lord Gale, there had to be replacements.  If we now look at the stallions in the National Stud, I believe those replacements are just not of the <Col N="1496" /> same quality at all and it comes to me as no surprise that the main business, the income from nomination fees, is falling off.  If one looks at sires such as Yashgan, Magical Wonder, Hatim, Broken Hearted, Coolmore Row, Digamist, Tremblant and, to a lesser extent, Dancing Dissident, they have their qualities; but they are not up to the quality that I believe is required.  They are not top class horses, but middle range horses.  They are not the type of horses, for example, that Coolmore Stud has been syndicating. They are not the type of horses that the Arabs have been syndicating, be it Sheik Mohammed or Kalif Abdullah or whoever.  This matter must be examined.</P>
    <P>I welcome the appointment of the most recent board by the Minister, but I have to say that the decisions made by the previous board in relation to buying and selling stallions left a lot to be desired. The reason this is becoming so significant is that the horse breeding industry is in crisis at the moment.  This is manifest in every sales ring from Goffs to Tattersalls, from Newmarket to Kentucky, Paris and Deauville.  A Nyjinsky yearling could be syndicated for £10 million five or six years ago; now it costs £1 million or £2 million. There is a major slump in the market and quite frankly, gross overproduction of bad horses in this country.  Pick up any racing card and you will see the position, both in flat or National Hunt.  This Sunday at Leopardstown The Hennessy Cognac Gold Cup might attract fewer than ten runners, but a maiden hurdle or a maiden bumper would have to have two divisions and probably a ballot, with about 60 declared.  The country is full of lousy, third rate horses, because the breeding practices result in more mares that never won a race being kept for breeding.  Also, there was a practice where stallions serviced about 45 mares a year; they are now servicing over three times that number.  In the sales catalogues and the results in <i>The Racing Post</i> or <i>The Irish Field</i>, most entries have &ldquo;NS&rdquo; after them, and in some cases there is no bid.  There is a huge depression.  As the Minister, rightly said many farmers <Col N="1497" /> who have one or two thoroughbred mares are really feeling the pinch.</P>
    <P>The best way for the National Stud to safeguard its position in this recession is to specialise in quality.  That does not necessarily mean having 12 stallions &mdash; both the board and the Minister seemed to indicate that seven were not viable.  If you had 12 mediocre stallions the problem would only get worse.  It would be better to have three superb stallions.  This means, in terms of flat breeding, concentrating almost exclusively on classic and group winners for new stallion replacements.  That brings up the question of affordability, because you are talking about large sums of money.  I implore the Minister to implore the National Stud to go for a policy of syndication. The only way you can do it is to have half or quarter of a stallion, to have a number of nominating shares. That is the most viable route for the National Stud to take.</P>
    <P>The role of the National Stud in terms of horse breeding must be looked at anew and in a modern context.  When it was originally established under the 1945 Act, Ireland had a rich tradition of horse-breeding and bloodstock; but we were not then the premier force we are now. We are now, for tax and other reasons, the mecca of the bloodstock world.  We have Sheik Mohammed and the Dubai Ministers.  The Aga Khan is here, he moved out of the UK for a number of reasons.  We have a number of top French operators.  We have studs such as those at Coolmore, Ballycastle and Moyglare Stud &mdash; all the very top international breeders, who could sell their progeny in America or other countries and who would come to any invitation day.  Things have changed.  The National Stud is no longer required as a flaghsip for the industry.  It is not a flagship, because things have moved on and, for tax and other reasons, we have outstanding studs here.</P>
    <P>The National Stud is undercapitalised, it is no longer the flagship, and the question then arises as to what should be done.  A new and more imaginative policy is required.  Purely in the context of horse-breeding, <Col N="1498" /> the National Stud should be open to joint ventures with other top class studs &mdash; for example, with Moyglare Stud.  I know some board members have links with a number of studs, I am not exclusively picking on Moyglare and there should be a joint venture with an Irish stud because it would have huge mutual benefits in terms of cross entitlements to nomination shares and rights.  If you fail to go down this route you will continue to be undercapitalised, to have mediocre stallions, a reducing stallion income and sustained losses.  The shareholder is entitled to better.</P>
    <P>I am talking exclusively about horse breeding, because I fully accept that the Japanese Gardens, the Horse Museum and the renowned &mdash; as the Minister rightly described it &mdash; students stud management course are public service functions, I have no problem with that.  That could be dealt with in two ways, either the State could in all circumstances, retain a majority shareholding or, alternatively as in the case of heritage parks and so on, those aspects of the stud could be put into a trust.  However, those elements could benefit from a more commercial approach.</P>
    <P>Last year I visited the National Stud, because I am interested in horses and so on, and the Japanese Gardens.  I was disappointed with the Horse Museum; I had seen it some ten years previously and it had not changed.  You can only see or be interested in a skeleton of Arkle so many times; when you have seen it there is no particular interest in seeing it again. Some things could be done.  For example, there is no promotional material available to buy, mementoes of horses or anything like that.  There is no video material of the stallions there winning their best races.  That would be of great interest and would attract horse racing enthusiasts, who are perhaps not even aware of the existence of the museum.  I have never heard on 2FM or on any radio station, in the same way as you hear advertisements for greyhound racing or horse racing, any promotional material for the National Stud.  A commercial attitude would be of great help.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1499" /> I welcome the appointment of the new board.  Messrs.  Shubotham and Dermot Weld for whom I have a very high regard in respect of their wisdom in buying and selling, which is a key part in the stud's activities.  However, I regret that some of the purchases made &mdash; and I accept that this is undoubtedly a high risk business &mdash; are stallions that others shied away from.</P>
    <P>I would like to make a few more points. I note that the last President ran a number of horses.  I think Seskin Bridge was perhaps one of the better known, it won a number of races and is now breeding.  The Minister should encourage the President to support our large horse racing industry by ensuring that one or two horses, both on the flat and under National Hunt rules, would be kept in training &mdash; perhaps progeny from the stud &mdash; and to take a more active role than she has done to date.  As far as I am aware, I do not recall seeing much high profile in that sphere of her activities.</P>
    <P>In relation to the problems with Kildare County Council about road development, I understand that this is a national primary route and I ask the Minister to use his influence with the Minister for the Environment to ensure that that matter is satisfactorily resolved.</P>
    <P>The backdrop to the Bill is provided by the Killanin Commission report in 1986 and the report of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on semi-State Bodies some time later.  The most significant thing about this Bill is that it is long overdue.  I am glad, therefore, that we are taking all Stages, because the sooner it is enacted the better.  It is over six years since the recommendation to raise the borrowing limits and so on.  All businesses &mdash; retail, manufacturing or agricultural &mdash; have changed enormously in the last 20 years.  The National Stud has changed very little in 46 years.</P>
    <P>Therefore we have to look at new policies and new ways of moving forward.</P>
    <P>The Minister has promised a new horse racing authority and the necessary legislation for that.  I was somewhat disappointed that it seemed to have as its <Col N="1500" /> primary focus getting the agreement of producers for the industry.  That is entirely valid in its own right.  But, essentially, racing, unlike breeding, is a leisure business competing with every other leisure business to attract crowds.  The lifeblood and future of racing is the levy, and the levy comes from punters.  If some of the large carpet dealers or large meat barons do not turn up at Leopardstown on Sunday you will know in your levy returns that they did not turn up.  In other words, there has been a growing dependence on large betting by a few individuals, which, I believe, masks the figures.  In fact, I think the turnover in levy terms peaked in 1988 and has gone down ever since in real terms, although it has not got back to its 1989 level.  While attendances are up, that must be a very worrying situation.  I believe that the primary role of this new authority &mdash; and I am all for bringing the Racing Board and the Turf Club together &mdash; must be to get more people racing and more people betting.  The way you do that is not running ten maiden EBF seven furlong races at Roscommon and places like that. Mixed cards, handicaps and holiday type fixtures and festival cards attract the punters. I have been to places like Mallow and Roscommon.  These are tracks I like, unlike Tramore and Bellewstown, which I do not like and, most especially, that Kilbeggan track, which I think is a waterloo for any punter because of those hills and undulations they have to encounter. The point I am making is that it is not market driven, it is not consumer led, and unless the right people &mdash; and I do not mind if they are your nominees, Minister &mdash; are put on that board, it will not work because you cannot run racing for producers, you must run it for consumers.</P>
    <P>I would also like to say that there is a rumour in the betting business that the betting tax is going to be raised &mdash; 12 per cent and 15 per cent have been mentioned. I can tell the Minister, on behalf of those who are in the business and conducting it entirely legitimately and legally in which I would include some associations I have myself, that this is like <Col N="1501" /> a piece of elastic and if you stretch it too far it will break.  There are plenty of people who will facilitate tax free betting. Therefore you will make the margins such that, while people are prepared to pay 10 per cent, they are not prepared to pay beyond it.  In so far as it is now the case that money from off course is financing on course racing in terms of the Government grant, it is absolutely imperative that that revenue be buoyant and that it stays at 10 per cent.  No matter what happens on 23 January when the Minister for Finance is struggling with his Labour colleagues to fill the last remaining gap in the deficit, it must be hands off the betting tax, because that is not on.  One of the biggest single advantages we have in bloodstock sales is the advantage we have over the UK in the way we treat VAT, the 2.7 per cent rate as opposed to the British rate, which is a multiple of that.  That must be retained.</P>
    <P>I believe it is a time for a more imaginative approach to the National Stud. There is no point in the people on the board being so busy running other things that they do not give this their primary attention.  I would ask them to adopt a policy of having an alliance or joint venture with other studs, of seeking to get a reduced number of top quality flat and National Hunt stallions, stallions of the Sadler's Wells ilk, at the very top of the market.  You will have to pay for them and I suggest that that be done through syndication.  I would also support an increase in the practice of selling stallions to the southern hemisphere during our offbreeding season for their breeding season to maximise their revenues and to ensure that the glut of overproduction taking place at the bottom end of the market is not a policy pursued by the National Stud.  I do not accept the view that the National Stud is there to provide the type of stallion that is affordable for farmer breeders.  Unless that policy can stand up in commercial reality, it will not succeed.  This is not a social welfare policy for breeders.  Breeders are only interested in selling animals that will give a rate of return.  The best way to do that is to ensure that you have quality animals <Col N="1502" /> and I think that can be done through syndication.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill.  It is long overdue, but I think it is time for a new approach to the National Stud.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to express my satisfaction that this Bill has been introduced.  I am glad to see that it will pass through this House today without any opposition because I think it is badly needed.  While I obviously welcome the Bill and its enactment at a very early date, like Deputy Yates, there are some things one is forced to say in regard to the National Stud.  The Minister gave us a certain amount of information, but I found Deputy Yates's speech perhaps more informative and more entertaining.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvanYates" hpid="Mr. Yates Mr. Yates">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yates</NameTxt>
      <P>The civil servants do not write my speeches.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>When I saw this Bill was being taken today I went to the Library to get the latest annual report and it is an absolute disgrace that it is the 1989 report.  The fact that it is three years and two months out of date and that that is accepted as the norm by the Irish National Stud, and possibly by the Department of Agriculture, is symptomatic of many of the things that are wrong with the National Stud.  That they should run their affairs in such a haphazard way as that is simply not acceptable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The 1989 report discloses very substantial losses in that year and in the previous year.  I do not know what the figures are since then, but the Minister said that the losses are running in recent years &mdash; that is, the years since the report &mdash; at approximately a loss of half a million pounds every year.  That means that this stud has lost £2.5 million in the last five years.  It is very regrettable that that should be so.  I know that the breeding industry has been passing through a difficult time.  I am sure some other stock farms at least have lost significant sums of money too, but what amazes me is that, as well as running a stud, the Irish National Stud has a lot of land which it <Col N="1503" /> farms in a conventional way and that that succeeds in losing a great deal of money too.  Not alone have they 800 acres beside Kildare town, but I think they also have the land that is attached to Barretstown Castle some miles away.  They have these large quantities of good quality, valuable land entirely free and they lose more than £50,000 a year on farming it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="IvanYates" hpid="Mr. Yates Mr. Yates">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yates</NameTxt>
      <P>If they set it, they could not go wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>This is quite an achievement. Even if the average farmer in this country were offered 1,000 acres of high quality land in Kildare for nothing, he certainly would not lose over £50,000 a year on it.</P>
      <P>I agree fully with the Minister that, having such a large infrastucture and having only seven stallions standing there, does not make sense.  One of the several reasons I welcome this Bill is to have the opportunity to increase the number of stallions standing.  Like Deputy Yates, I would say that there is no point having stallions that are no good.  One advantage at least for the National Stud and one reason this Bill is particularly timely at the moment is that the market for stallions is depressed and even the best ot them are costing less than they did some time ago.</P>
      <P>Even though they are still very expensive, world class stallions may be bought now for less than they would have cost five years ago.  It is very much in the interest of the stud that it acquires top class stallions and the obvious way in which to acquire several such stallions &mdash; they are needed &mdash; is by taking shares in stallions, as Deputy Yates has suggested, rather than by buying them outright.  Other countries are quite happy to syndicate stallions and the Irish National Stud should be equally prepared to do so.  If it cannot afford to buy a world class stallion outright it may well afford to take shares, which would make a major difference to breeding here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The losses continuously incured at the <Col N="1504" /> stud will have to cease.  Otherwise the money being voted today in this Bill will be simply money down the drain.  The Irish National Stud is not all as well regarded these days as it was in the past. Apart from its financial results it does seem to have declined in the esteem of breeders in recent years.  There may be reasons for that which might not be appropriate to personalise here and I do not want to go into that now.  The Minister and the board must be aware of these reasons, and they should take whatever steps are open to them to try to reverse that decline.  With the form of syndication which has become common there are opportunities open to the National Stud which were not open to it in earlier decades and these opportunities should be fully availed of now.</P>
    <P>The Minister refered to a five year plan which the board of the stud submitted to him last year.  That plan should be published so that people would have an opportunity of working out where the stud is going.  Certainly on its published reports, which are more than three years out of date, one had no official information on what are its plans.  Perhaps the Minister will consider putting that development plan in the Library of the House so that Deputies may study it.</P>
    <P>The Minister made various references to racing, which is the other side of this coin, as did Deputy Yates.  I would urge the Minister to take note of what Deputy Yates has said because it is common sense.  We have a remarkable racing industry but it is more notable for its quantity than its quality.  The number of race meetings held is huge.  The reason for that is the number of horses we have is huge.  However, a great number of horses are not of good quality &mdash; the huge entries for maiden hurdles are indicative of that.  The same horses may run in maiden hurdles three or four seasons after they ran in their first one and that practice is likely to continue.</P>
    <Speaker pid="IvanYates" hpid="Mr. Yates Mr. Yates">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yates</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope they are not carrying the Deputy's money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The future of racing <Col N="1505" /> here would be assured if the cards were more attractive and particularly if national hunt racing got greater support proportionately than it does at the moment.  Racing is a consumer driven industry, whether or not those running it realise that.  The public in general prefer national hunt racing to the type of flat racing that takes place every summer, which is not particularly attractive and in which the quality of horses taking part is very poor.</P>
      <P>The Minister has spoken &mdash; this is appropriate here &mdash; about the thoroughbred industry.  I would take the opportunity to remind him that while we may have an over-population of thoroughbred horses, some of whom are of very poor quality.  There are and should be great opportunities for farmers and breeders in non-thoroughbred breeding.  The dangers of over-population in this area are not as great and very good prices may be obtained for non-thoroughbred horses that are suitable for equestrian events of various kinds.  At a time when farmers are increasingly restrained by milk quotas and difficulties with intervention for beef the Minister should seek to encourage people to take part in this industry.  Even though it is a somewhat risky and difficult business, it is one that is very much associated with this country and in which this country has been and can continue to be eminently successful.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am glad this Bill has been introduced; it is not before time.  Ideally it might have been introduced several years ago, particularly as it was recommended by Lord Killanin.  However, there is at least one advantage in its coming now in that the moneys that will be made available through the passing of the Bill can be utilised at a time when prices are lower than has been the norm.  I would urge the National Stud to acquire some outstanding stallions and acquire shares in as many as possible.  The National Stud is attractive as a location in which to stand stallions for shareholders.  It should be borne in mind that much of the success in the breeding industry here, with the advent of very large and successful privately owned studs, is tax driven and tax <Col N="1506" /> related.  I greatly fear that many of those studs would close if changes were made in the tax system.  If that were to happen breeders would have to rely very much on the National Stud and I doubt very much, with the way the National Stud is operated at the moment, if their needs would be met.  For that reason it is very timely that we build up the National Stud and ensure it is a place of which we can be proud, with outstanding horses.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, it is inexcusable that such large sums of money should continue to be lost by the stud year after year.  If the stud was privately owned that could not happen.  I regret that it happens at public expense.  I hope the investments that will be made as a result of this Bill will turn things around.  I support the Bill and I wish the National Stud well.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesLeonard" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Leonard) Acting Chairman (Mr. Leonard)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Leonard)</NameTxt>
      <P>I call Deputy Rabbitte who has 30 minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Mr. J. Walsh Mr. J. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>A photo finish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope there are no female gender references in this speech which would make it somewhat awkward.</P>
      <P>County Kildare has been synonymous with the bloodstock industry for years and the jobs and prosperity of many Kildare people are dependent on the success of the industry.  The location of the National Stud in the county reinforces the close relationship between this county and horse breeding.  During its 46 years of operation the National Stud has established a fine reputation at home and abroad and has become an international flagbearer for our bloodstock industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the fact that legislation to update the financial basis of the National Stud is finally being put in place.  As long ago as July 1986, the Commission of Inquiry into the thoroughbred horse breeding industry under the chairmanship of Lord Killanin reported to the then Minister for Agriculture, Deputy Deasy, and made a strong case for increasing the scope for borrowing by the National Stud.  It is a pity that it has taken so long for this recommendation to be <Col N="1507" /> acted upon.  The Killanin report recommended that the borrowing authorisation should be £5 million, as the Bill proposes. This was the figure also recommended by the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Commercial State-sponsored Bodies in 1990.  However, costs and inflation have risen since then and I wonder if the authors of the Bill should not have taken note that the recommendation in the Killanin report was for a periodic review of that figure.</P>
    <P>Many of the points made in the Killanin report are pertinent today.  It pointed out that unless fresh acquisitions were made the stud would slowly decline as its stallions aged.  It argued the case for a viable future for the National Stud in order to protect against any possible disasters in the bloodstock business, whether financial or disease-related.  The acquisition of more and better stallions is a costly business but the depressed market favours investment at present.</P>
    <P>The Minister recognises the vital role played by the National Stud in the education and training of young people in stud management.  It is remarkable in these tough days to be able to guarantee a job to any graduate of any training course.  Yet this is the case for the 15 Irish people who qualify each year from the training course.  One-third of all students who attend the course come from overseas and the general demand far outstrips the number of places.  Investment in the National Stud should mean that its training capability will expand with the number of stallions bought in.</P>
    <P>When it comes to creating new jobs, it has been shown that the one area where Ireland can excel is selling quality education to overseas students.  We have no better opportunity to do this than inhorse breeding management.  Our National Stud has a good name world-wide. Indeed, many stud managers operating around the globe learned their skills in Kildare.</P>
    <P>The relationship between visitors and the stud has been built-up over the years so that yet again demand is outstripping accommodation.  Since the National Stud <Col N="1508" /> is strategically placed close to a national primary route, the build-up of tourism has been considerable.  As many as 74 tour companies and groups have dealings with the stud and 108,000 people visited the centre last year.  Expansion of visitors' facilities is overdue.  To give one example of the urgency of the matter, the Museum of the Irish Horse housed at the National Stud is capable of holding only 30 people at any time.  This creates major logistical problems.  The growing interest in the National Stud as a tourist destination, together with its ancillary attraction, the Japanese Gardens, augurs well for the future.  However, if the spin-offs in terms of jobs and prosperity are to come about we must ensure investment in high quality facilities.</P>
    <P>Certain services are provided to breeders nationally &mdash; a countrywide foster mare service, a plasma bank and a limited amount of assistance for research and development.  The role of the National Stud in developing the thoroughbred industry is critical.  It is an industry whose job creating potential is generally underestimated by the general public.</P>
    <P>Traditionally, however, it is an industry with archaic practices when it comes to industrial relations.  It is not common for workers in the industry to be unionised. The tied cottage is still a feature for many people employed on stud farms and stable lads can often work for low wages. Modernising that aspect of the through-bred industry should go hand in hand with the improvements that this Bill will bring about.  An attempt was made by my union to organise this category or worker but it did not have a great deal of success. Because of its nature, it is an exceptionally difficult industry to organise.  It is an area that requires attention, and to the best of my knowledge no minimum pay legislation applies.</P>
    <P>The benefits of having a National Stud at the heart of a long-established thoroughbred industry have been long proven.  It is important that as a semi-state company it plays its part in ensuring that these benefits can be enjoyed right through the industry by everyone who <Col N="1509" /> contributes to making it an integral part of Irish agriculture and of the Irish export business.</P>
    <P>I welcome the endorsement of the future role of the National Stud as a semi-State body.  In its 1990 report the Oireachtas Joint Committee on commercial State-sponsored bodies came out clearly against privatisation and spelt out the arguments against such a move. Those arguments are detailed at page 40 of that report.</P>
    <P>The report recognised that the company's borrowing powers of £500,000 were totally inadequate, especially in the context of an industry where even a moderately priced stallion costs over £1 million. The decision to raise this borrowing level to the more realistic figure of £5 million is obviously an improvement.  The report sensibly argued that the statutory limits on the company's borrowing powers be lifted altogether and be replaced by a requirement that the company get ministerial approval for its borrowings. The Bill provides for both a ceiling on borrowings and a ministerial authorisation.  This would seem to be a &ldquo;belt and braces&rdquo; approach.</P>
    <P>It is not always a good idea to stipulate a precise sum of money in legislation of this kind as in a few years time that figure could be quite meaningless due to changes in cost structures and other changes that may occur in the bloodstock industry. If we are to encourage State enterprise we should not be setting unnecessary strictures to it.</P>
    <P>Finally, the &ldquo;direction&rdquo; referred to must include the creation of more sustainable jobs.  Investment in a national resource of this type must have spin-offs in employment if its benefits are to be felt by those most in need.  I hope that in its future plans the National Stud will play its part in helping to reduce the overall numbers of those out of work as well as generating new life into the horse breeding industry, thereby increasing tourism and the number of overseas students.</P>
    <Speaker pid="IvanYates" hpid="Mr. Yates Mr. Yates">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yates</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I have no doubt Deputy Power is about to make <Col N="1510" /> a very significant speech and it is appropriate, therefore, that there would be a quorum to listen to him.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Notice taken that 20 Members were not present; House counted and 20 Members being present,</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanPower" hpid="Mr. Power Mr. Power">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Power</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I thank my colleagues for coming into the House to listen to me, and I hope they will not leave.  As we are debating the racing industry I might be tempted to give them the name of a winner.  There is a big race in Leopardstown next Sunday and if they put their money on Jodami they will not be going too far wrong.</P>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity to speak on this Bill.  It is very fitting that 50 years after the lands and buildings were presented to the State this has been brought before the House.  The Bill is fairly straightforward in that it proposes to increase the National Stud's borrowing powers from £500,000 to £5 million and increase its share capital from £5 to £10 million.  As someone who comes from Kildare it is easy for me to recognise the important role the National Stud has played in developing our racing industry, increasing tourism and creating employment. The National Stud has been a tremendous success since its foundation and it has been very well managed.</P>
      <P>The racing industry has been taken for granted by successive Governments. When one looks at the various sectors involved, the racing industry employs in the region of 25,000 people.  It is only in the last few years that the industry has fallen on bad times.  When this was recognised by Government it was decided to put the money back into the racing industry. This industry, particularly in regards to off course betting, has given a good return to the Exchequer over the years and I am glad that the Government was prepared to put money back into the industry during its hour of need.  Unfortunately, the problems in the industry have not been solved and it is in urgent need of attention.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I thank the Minister for the interest he <Col N="1511" /> has shown in the racing industry.  I know that like Deputy O'Malley and a few other Deputies in the House, he is a very keen racegoer.  He may not be making any money out of it but he certainly has the interests of the industry at heart.  The decision taken by the Minister earlier in the year to set up one authority to run the racing industry has to be welcomed. The racing industry is very important to the consumer.  Many people involved in this industry have taken the consumer for granted and if more people do not attend race meetings the racing industry will remain in decline.  The racing industry in Britain is in a poor state at present and it is important that we make every attempt to benefit from that.  We have seen over the last couple of weeks the difficulties the fall in the value of sterling has caused for us, and we have an opportunity to benefit from the difficulties in the British racing industry.</P>
    <P>I should like to give the House some statistics which indicate the extent of the difficulties being experienced by the British racing industry at present.  During the last 12 months the number of owners in Britain has fallen by 8.2 per cent and the number of horses in training has fallen by 9.5 per cent.  In January 1992 there were 11,469 horses in training in Britain but last month that figure had fallen to 10,374.  Since 1990 the number of horses in training in Britain has fallen by 13 per cent.  These figures tell their own story about an industry that has been taken for granted both in Britain and Ireland, an industry which Governments have not given the attention it deserves. We should recognise that the racing industry is a big employer, and try to help it as much as we can.  Some months ago Tattersalls announced its intention to bring one of its premier sales to Ireland. this would be a major embarrassment for the British racing industry.  We should facilitate this company in every way possible in this regard.  It would be a marvellous help to the Irish racing industry if a premier sale was held here.</P>
    <P>Apart from the breeding aspect, there has been a tradition for a long number <Col N="1512" /> of years whereby the National Stud has supplied the horse, or placed the horse in training, which ran in the colours of the President.  That in itself is a very significant practice and has shown the world that we have a great interest in racing.  In the not too distant past a mare called Seskinbridge, which was trained by the late Peter Creery, ran in the President's colours.  If my memory serves me right, it won the Thyestes Chase and finished second in the Irish Grand National. I think the only horse in training at present is a two year old which, hopefully will run in the President's colours in a few month's time.  I appeal to those in authority to ensure that over the next couple of years more horses run in the colours of our President.  I agree with Deputy O'Malley that the National Hunt appeals more to Irish people; there is much more excitement at the National Hunt that at flat racing.  If more horses run in the President's colours, the world at large will realise the seriousness with which we take the industry.  This suggestion should be given serious consideration.</P>
    <P>I welcome the proposal to increase the National Stud's borrowing powers.  At present the stud has a number of good stallions, for example, Dancing Dissident, Magical Wonder, Digamist, Magical Strike and Broken Hearted.  It has also had some excellent sires, the most notable of which are Ahonoora, a Classic Winner, and Don't Forget Me. These horses, which were owned by a number of Irish men, created great excitement when they won at Newmarket.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Mr. J. Walsh Mr. J. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Cork men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanPower" hpid="Mr. Power Mr. Power">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Power</NameTxt>
      <P>They came from the same county as the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is directing the Deputy; he said Cork men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanPower" hpid="Mr. Power Mr. Power">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Power</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a difference.  The victories of Don't Forget Me and a number of other Irish horses, including Carroll House, which was sired by Lord <Col N="1513" /> Gale and which went on to win the Prix de L'Arc de Triomphe, a race regarded by many as the most important in the world, has shown the success achieved by the National Stud.  Despite enormous competition throughout the world the stud was able to produce these winners.</P>
      <P>I would like to avail of this opportunity to thank all those people involved in the National Stud and the Japanese Gardens.</P>
      <P>They are a marvellous tourist attraction in County Kildare, although most people would not consider Kildare as being a tourist county.  The National Stud and the Japanese Gardens were visited by approximately 100,000 people last year and this represents a boost for tourism in Kildare.</P>
      <P>I met with members of the local authority, the county council and people from the National Stud who expressed concern in relation to the Kildare by-pass which will cut through part of the National Stud and in effect divide it in two.  Unfortunately, this development cannot be avoided and I hope that when it is built and up and running it will cause as few problems to people as possible.  It would be dissappointing if the National Stud was affected to any great extent as a result of the new road..</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Reference was made by Deputy Rabbitte about the training in the National Stud.  This is an important area and one about which I wish to comment.  Approximately 25 young people are taken on and trained at the stud every year.  The course lasts approximately five months and they are given training in every aspect of the racing industry.  Our record here has been unequalled in any other industry in that 100 per cent of these graduates succeeded in getting employment following their training at the National Stud.  They work and manage studs throughout the world. Graduates from the National Stud manage the Coolmore Stud; the English National Stud and the Windfield Farm in Canada, the home of Northern Dancer, are managed also by graduates from the National Stud.  This is indicative of the enormous contribution made by the Irish National Stud, not just to racing in Ireland but throughout the world.  I wish <Col N="1514" /> to thank those people for their tremendous effort in bringing that about.  Those people who are presently working in the National Stud will be very influential in the industry in the future.  Therefore, it is important, while we have the opportunity, to give them every assistance in their work to make life a little easier for them.</P>
    <P>The breeding industry has gone through a difficult period, although some might argue that in the not too distant past the fees were beyond the reach of the ordinary person.  The industry has often been referred to as the sport of kings and the prices obtained for yearlings and foals in the past made it almost impossible for ordinary people to become involved in it.  Whether it is due to common sense, the recession, or a mixture of both, prices are at a more realistic level now and I would recommend that those who have a few pounds should get involved in the racing industry.  Enormous pleasure and satisfaction can be gained by people involved in the racing industry.  This has been evidenced over the past few years by the growth in syndicates here where people can buy a share in the ownership of a horse for a small sum of money.  All horses cannot win and, as one speaker pointed out earlier, some of them may only have run a maiden race three or four years ago.  That point may be slightly exaggerated but may not be too far out.  I met a man recently who suggested that the meat industry had caused such problems of late that we should consider setting up a horse meat factory, the implication being that some of the horses running today might be more suitable for a meat processing factory than a racecourse.  Perhaps that is something which could be considered, I am not sure what sort of demand exists for horse meat but we certainly have an abundance of it here at present.</P>
    <P>I wish to refer briefly to the Killanin report produced a number of years ago and which has not been acted on to the extent that I would have wished.  As we approach budget day it is no harm to remind the Minister for Finance and his colleague, Minister Joe Walsh, that a <Col N="1515" /> recommendation in the Killanin report was that we should operate a betting tax system here preferably lower, but certainly not higher, than that pertaining in Britain.  While the English system is a little more complicated than ours it works out at approximately 10 per cent, similar to that here.  Over the past few years we have seen the movement of large book-making firms from Britain to Ireland.  If we were to increase the betting tax here, no matter how small the increase, it would be counter-productive and if the Minister intends to make any change in the tax, he should take a gamble and reduce it.  A phrase used a couple of years ago, self-financing tax deductions, could perhaps be one charge.  A large export market exists in Europe, and if we had a betting tax here which was lower than that in Britain it could be of enormous benefit to our Exchequer.</P>
    <P>I thank the Minister for bringing forward this Bill which will be of enormous benefit to the National Stud.  I would like again to thank the people in the National Stud for the professional manner in which they have conducted their business and the honour that they have brought to County Kildare and, indeed, to the country at large.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardJDurkan" hpid="Mr. Durkan Mr. Durkan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Durkan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill and what it proposes.  As has already been alluded to by previous speakers, at a time when the need for job creation is at its greatest we should recognise the work done by the National Stud in regard to job creation in the racing industry generally. Very often we forget the important role played by the National Stud in building the foundation for that kind of job creation.  Those who visit our racecourses will be aware of the ancillary industry associated with the racing industry. For some unknown reason the view is often taken that this is an exclusive industry providing for an exclusive set of people.  In fact the large number of jobs associated with the industry generally has never been appreciated by the public.  If an industrialist arrived here, particularly at the present time, with a proposal to <Col N="1516" /> create anything like the number of jobs to that the horse breeding and racing industries provide, he would receive large amounts of money in grants and inducements.</P>
      <P>This is an indigenous industry providing jobs from entirely native sources and we must give a modicum of recognition to that industry.  I wish to express our appreciation for the constructive input of the industry over the years.  I hope this Minister and this Government will continue to appreciate that work and will assist in every way possible to ensure the industry is given the latitude that it needs to expand.  It is easier for an industry that is up and running to further improve in the area of job creation than to introduce that which is new or untried. Again, I emphasise the native sourcing in this industry and compliment the Minister for introducing the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. J. Walsh) Joe Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. J. Walsh)</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to reply to a number of the points made before I go on to next Stage.  I appreciate very much the House's acceptance to conclude this Bill today.</P>
      <P>First, the contributions were excellent, well researched and constructive and I thank the Deputies for that.  All the Deputies referred to the scandal of annual reports and accounts not being available and I concur totally with that. I sought those reports at the first opportunity available to me.  It is not good enough for any State body to say to a Minister that they are in serious financial trouble when no report has been produced by them for three years.  I now have the reports for 1990 and 1991.  They will have to be examined by the Government and will be circulated and laid before both Houses of the Oireachtas and put in the Lilbrary at an early date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I agree also with the suggestions regarding the quality of the stallions.  We must produce very high class stallions. When I called to the stud last year and observed what was taking place there, including viewing the skeleton of Arkle, I came to the conclusion that they were better at breeding plants and rare species <Col N="1517" /> of flora than breeding horses.  The only money making activity there was the Japanese Gardens.  The core activity was in a shambles.  I concur totally with Deputy O'Malley when he said that however bad the recession is in the horse industry, to fail to make money out of 800 acres of prime land seems to be an uncanny exercise and just not good enough.  As Deputy Yates said, even if the land was rented it would show a credit at the end of the balance sheet.  The issue is being addressed.</P>
    <P>Reference wes made to the five year plan.  In inviting a number of new people to join the board as a first priority I asked them to examine this five year plan, amend it, bring it up to date and to strengthen the finances.  For that reason a person with a financial background was invited to take over as chairman of the National Stud because I do not accept that State bodies must be making losses. In this case the reality is that the British National Stud, which is fairly similar to our National Stud &mdash; they have less land but approximately the same number of stallions &mdash; is managed by a graduate of the Irish National Stud and is making a net profit on a commercial basis.  If it can be done in the UK, which has an even more depressed thoroughbred industry than ours, I do not see why we cannot do the same here.</P>
    <P>The Irish National Stud is being given an opportunity to get its financial house in order and to increase the profile of the stud to what it had been in the past.  I realise that competition is greater now with a number of world class studs in operation but many people who have an interest in the thoroughbred and non-thoroughbred industry hardly know the location of the National Stud and know very little about its operation.  As I said, if it were not for the Japanese Gardens few people would visit it or know much about it.  In future I would like some of the owners of our top class brood mares to consider availing of the facilities at the National Stud.  That has not been the case up to now.  Owners of horses such as the Flame of Tara, would not even consider <Col N="1518" /> using the National Stud and I would like to see a change in this regard.</P>
    <P>Deputy O'Malley asked that the five year plan be made available.  I have no difficulty with that; however, it is being amended at present and as soon as it is available I will circulate it.  Deputy O'Malley referred also to the non-thoroughbred horse industry; we have an over-supply in that industry also.  I established an interim horse board under the chairmanship of Noel Cawley of Bord Bainne, who has a tremendous amount of administrative experience, to draw up a programme for the rational development and the improvement of quality in the non-throughbred industry.  In many cases the commercial aspect is greater in the non-thoroughbred sector than in the thoroughbred industry.</P>
    <P>Deputy Rabbitte referred to employment. There are 12,500 people in direct employment in the horse racing industry. In the ancilliary support industries such as betting shops, many fine people operate these institutions around the country and offer employment with good conditions. There is a margin involved, I understand.  I am in favour of decent pay and conditions for everbody connected with the horse racing industry.</P>
    <P>Reference was made by a number of speakers to the wider racing industry.  I hope before the year is out to bring in legislation which will provide for an overall authority and put that issue on a sound footing as well.</P>
    <P>A number of speakers referred to the good days when good horses ran in the President's colours.  I have already asked the Irish National Stud to resume that practice.  It affords a high profile opportunity for our presidential colours to be worn by good horses.  A start has been made in this regard in that a two year old has been put in training with Michael Grassick and hopefully we will have a listed or group winner running in the national colours in the not too distant future.</P>
    <P>I thank Deputies for their extremely constructive contributions in relation to this Bill and for facilitating the passage <Col N="1519" /> of the various amendments to it this afternoon.</P>
    <P>Queston put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="National Stud (Amendment) Bill, 1993:" RHead="Committee Stage and Final Stages">
    <Title>National Stud (Amendment) Bill, 1993: Committee Stage and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand the Minister to say there were amendments but I do not think they have been circulated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Minister for Agriculture, Food and Industry (Mr. J. Walsh) Minister for Agriculture, Food and Industry (Mr. J. Walsh)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture, Food and Industry (Mr. J. Walsh)</NameTxt>
      <P>This is an entirely new Bill which has been circulated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Are there amendments to it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
      <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvanYates" hpid="Mr. Yates Mr. Yates">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yates</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to raise some points with the Minister concerning share capital. I would like the Minister to clarify one point for me.  He referred to the fact that the 1990 and 1991 accounts are now available.  It strikes me that the losses could have been worse but for the fact that they keep bringing forward onto the balance sheet losses transferred to bloodstock replacement fund.  Following the sale of Ahonoora the bloodstock replacement fund was very high.</P>
      <P>At the close of business at the end of 1989 the bloodstock replacement fund stood at £5.5 million.  I should like to know the present level of the bloodstock fund.  This is a vital question because if the bloodstock replacement fund has not been adequately replenished and a bookkeeping exercise has been done to keep the losses to a minimum the losses may, in fact, be much greater than £500,000 a year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1520" /> Reference has been to the depreciation in horse prices.  Has the value of the six or seven stallions in the stud been devalued.  The market values of even the most prolific stallions with the best progeny have been reassessed.  As has been said, it is bad enough not to have accounts, but it is worse if there is an attempt to conceal the true effects of the recession.  Those points need to be clarified.  My two questions to the Minister are first, what is the present level of the bloodstock replacement fund and, second, have the stallions been devalued to meet current market situations?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Mr. J. Walsh Mr. J. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>At 31 December 1991 the bloodstock replacement fund stood at £2,587,604 and the value of the stallions has been depreciated by £2.8 million.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvanYates" hpid="Mr. Yates Mr. Yates">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yates</NameTxt>
      <P>My worst fears have now been realised.  If the bloodstock replacement fund fell from £5.5 million to £2.5 million between 1989 and 1991, that indicates a reduction of £3 million.  Therefore, the losses must be greater than £500,000 a year; they must be almost £1 million a year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Mr. J. Walsh Mr. J. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>If the reserves go down, that would appear to be the case; it follows logically.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvanYates" hpid="Mr. Yates Mr. Yates">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yates</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a matter of deep concern.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The information is useful and indicates the necessity for the publication of the accounts.  In addition to what would seem to be a trading loss of £500,000, the stud is also dissipating its assets each year.  This section proposes that the share capital should be increased to £10 million, divided into shares of £1 each.  It is probably assumed that those shares will be taken up by the Minister for Finance.  Is there anything in the Principal Acts which would prevent the shares being offered to or taken up by other parties?  It could be very helpful to the National Stud if other parties were to be encouraged to take up shares in it. <Col N="1521" /> This would relieve the Exchequer, at a time of particular stringency, from the necessity to take up all these shares.  The amounts involved are not huge and it could do a great deal to integrate the National Stud with the other outstanding privately-owned studs in this country if some of the owners of those studs were offered the possibility of taking up shares in the National Stud.  It would be helpful if something on the lines of a joint venture, as mentioned by Deputy Yates, could be undertaken.</P>
      <P>The Minister referred to the skeleton of Arkle.  In order to make the National Stud more attractive I suggest that he might arrange to place the skeleton of Shergar beside the skeleton of Arkle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvanYates" hpid="Mr. Yates Mr. Yates">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yates</NameTxt>
      <P>Sam Cosgrave was looking for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Mr. J. Walsh Mr. J. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 17 of the National Stud Act, 1945, provides that the shares have to be purchased exclusively by the Minister for Finance.  It would require separate legislation to make them available to other parties.  I will consider Deputy O'Malley's suggestion and look at the feasibility of doing this.  However, as I said, it would require separate legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvanYates" hpid="Mr. Yates Mr. Yates">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yates</NameTxt>
      <P>I support what Deputy O'Malley has said in so far as it strikes me that we are now dealing with a company analogous to a company with a rights issue.  The stud needs more capital, it already has a certain asset base and, as the Minister so rightly said, Ms. Pat Kelly and others should let mares like the Flame of Tara be serviced by National Stud stallions.  The better the quality of the mare, the better the quality of the progeny that will be produced by those stallions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If a person can buy 50,000 shares in the National Stud without in any way impinging on the dominant State position it will make it far more attractive for top breeders to send their mares to the National Stud.  The Minister should consider any suggestion.  The public service aspects &mdash; the gardens, the museums and <Col N="1522" /> the retention of the stud &mdash; are all a matter of public policy, but from a strategic breeding point of view my suggestion would be highly beneficial.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="IvanYates" hpid="Mr. Yates Mr. Yates">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yates</NameTxt>
      <P>Why was the figure of £5 million decided on?  The Oireachtas Joint Committee on Commercial State-sponsored Bodies recommends in its report that no borrowing limit be put in place and that the present ceiling of £500,000 be removed.  Why did the Minister decide not to set an upper ceiling?  I assume that in practice he will have to get the consent of the Minister for Finance for any borrowing. Will it be the case that additional legislation might be required in years to come which might just add to the bureaucracy?  It should be remembered that Lord Killanin recommended this legislation seven years ago.  It might be more prudent to have no limit.  Why was the limit set at £5 million?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Mr. J. Walsh Mr. J. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>The approval of the Minister for Finance has to be obtained in this case.  The reason we decided on a figure of £5 million was that in its five year plan the National Stud argued very cogently that the figure of £5 million would be appropriate.  I accepted that figure and if it needs to be changed at a future date &mdash; hopefully, it will not have to be changed for some considerable time &mdash; then legislation will be required at that point.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 4 and 5 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1523" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. J. Walsh) Joe Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. J. Walsh)</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to thank the Members who contributed to the debate and to express my appreciation for their co-operation. I will act with all due haste to have the 1990 and 1991 reports made available to Deputies and placed in the Library.  As Deputies will note a member of the staff of the Department of Agriculture, Food and Forestry has been made a director of the stud &mdash; I want to know what is going on there.  I assure Deputies that the contributions made here today, which were extremely helpful, constructive and knowledgeable, will be taken into consideration by the board of the National Stud.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvanYates" hpid="Mr. Yates Mr. Yates">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yates</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for his comments.  Even though this Bill is quite small and has been gone through very quickly, there is a great deal of support in this House for the work of the National Stud, its management board and staff. We wish them well in the future.  I hope that the development plan will be published. I would emphasise again to the Minister that up to 1989 the only syndicated stallion was Dancing Dissident, a <Col N="1524" /> particularly speedy flat horse.  Syndication, which is the upper end of the market, is the way to go.  That requires a direction and a push from the Minister, irespective of legislation.  I hope that this will be visible immediately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to section 2 and the question of share capital &mdash; I did not want to hold up the Bill by putting down amendments &mdash; I would ask the Minister to consider what I said about the possibility of others taking up shares. It would strengthen the position of the National Stud greatly if some Irish stud owners were to buy shares in the National Stud.  This would not affect the control of the stud &mdash; there would be no question of a majority holding.  Rather it would strengthen the position of the National Stud and also help the Exchequer.  Whatever about the trading results over the last five or six years, which have been rather disastrous, the National Stud as a company has very substantial assets.  That point should not be overlooked.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 2.5 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 16 February 1993.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>