<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Fri" Date="21" Month="Nov" Year="1930" Vol="36" No="3" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 21 Samhain 1930" DateEnglish="Friday, 21 November 1930" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="333">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="333" /> Do chuaidh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <P>Ordered: That Public Business be not interrupted at 12 o'clock for the taking of Private Deputies' Business.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="FINANCIAL RESOLUTION. - Customs" RHead="Duty on Imported Butter">
    <Title>FINANCIAL RESOLUTION. - Customs Duty on Imported Butter.</Title>
    <P>The Dáil went into Committee on Finance.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>I have received the following statement from the Tariff Commission:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Minister for Finance,</P>
      <P>&ldquo;We beg to advert to the application under the Tariff Commission Act, 1926, for the imposition of a customs duty on the importation of butter into the Saorstát made to you by the representatives of certain creameries, and referred to us for consideration.  It will take some time to hear the evidence of applicants and other representative persons desiring to be heard, to collect the relevant facts, and finally to prepare a considered report.  In the first instance it will be necessary to publish in &lsquo;Iris Oifigiúil&rsquo; and the daily press a notice stating that the application has been made.  We are of opinion that this notification would have the effect of attracting to the Saorstát abnormal imports of Australian, New Zealand, Danish and other butters which are at present held in cold storage in Great Britain in exceptionally large quantities, and that such imports would have an immediate and extremely detrimental effect on the home producers of butter and add to the serious difficulties under which the dairying industry is already labouring.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;We feel bound, therefore, before issuing a public advertisement which would attract attention to the possibility <Col N="334" /> of a tariff on imported butter to direct your notice to the position so that the Government may consider the desirability of taking steps to secure the immediate prohibition of imports of butter into the Saorstát. This prohibition, if made, would have to be without prejudice to the merits of the application for a permanent customs duty on butter and be regarded as a means of obviating a serious situation arising as an inevitable consequence from the decision to consider the application for a tariff.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;From information which we have sought from the Department of Agriculture we are satisfied that, taking into account the existing stocks and future production there will, even if imports of butter are prohibited, be a substantial surplus over domestic requirements up to the end of December, 1930, and that there is no immediate danger of a shortage of butter in the Saorstát.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Professor Smiddy has not yet been able to come across from London so that it was not possible to consult him, but we have felt that if the preliminaries for the hearing of the application for a tariff on imported butter are to proceed without delay it is advisable that you should be informed in the sense of this report.</P>
    <P Just="Center">&ldquo;(Signed) EINRI O FRIGHIL.</P>
    <P Just="Center">&ldquo;D. TWOMEY.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;20adh Mí na Samhna, 1930.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Following the receipt of that statement, the position was considered by the Government and they decided that action must be taken in the sense of the statement of the Tariff Commission. There is no machinery for prohibiting imports into the Saorstát and effect can only be given to the advice tendered by the Tariff Commission by putting on an absolutely prohibitive tariff.  Therefore, I submit the following Resolution to the Dáil:&mdash;</P>
    <P>1.  That a customs duty at the rate of five pounds the hundredweight shall be charged, levied, and paid on all butter imported into Saorstát Eireann on or after the 21st day of November, 1930.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="335" /> 2.  That whenever the Revenue Commissioners are satisfied that any butter which but for this clause would be chargeable with the duty mentioned in this Resolution is imported for use by the importer in the manufacture by him in Saorstát Eireann of articles of food for exportation, the Revenue Commissioners may, subject to compliance with such conditions as they may think fit to impose, permit such butter to be imported without payment of the duty mentioned in this Resolution.</P>
    <P>3.  That it is expedient in the public interest that this Resolution should have statutory effect under the Provisional Collection of Taxes Act, 1927 (No. 7 of 1927).</P>
    <P>The second clause is for the purpose of meeting possible cases of hardship that might arise to manufacturers who export.  Possibly it will only have to be used to a very small extent.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I have only to say that we welcome this action on the part of the Executive Council.  However, it seems to us to be really tantamount to a vote of censure on the Minister for Agriculture for his indiscretions recently in this particular matter.  The Minister for Agriculture indicated very clearly to those interested in the import of butter that he was considering this whole question, and so widespread was the dissatisfaction caused by it that at our Ard-Fheis a special resolution was passed calling upon the Minister to consider the matter and to prevent immediately the import of butter.  I am glad that the Executive Council are aware now of the danger that is being run by premature statements of that kind.  All we are sorry for is that this matter is going to be referred to the Tariff Commission. Speaking for ourselves, we had not very much confidence in the Tariff Commission as it existed, and I must say from looking at the personnel that we have less confidence in the Tariff Commission as now reconstituted. One of the members of that Tariff Commission is a man who is definitely, I might say, a doctrinaire free trader.  He was Chairman of the <Col N="336" /> Fiscal Inquiry Committee and those of us who have considered his report feel that if a way out of protecting Irish industries can be found or if any excuse can be found for non-protection he will find it.</P>
      <P>As I say, we are glad this particular action is taken, and we only regret that it is not definite action taken at once on the question of imported butter and not merely a reference to the Tariff Commission.  We hear about examining all the facts of the situation. All our lives could be spent in examining facts and yet there will be some relevant facts perhaps not discovered. We must make up our minds at some particular time some action is necessary and we ought to take it, and I think the mainly relevant facts in these important matters are pretty obvious.  In other matters, we have constantly to take decisions broadly on what I might call mass results without being able definitely to disentangle all the intricacies by which these total results are arrived at, and in connection with this particular item I think that unless we can get some speedier action from the Tariff Commission than we have got in the past there is very little hope from it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. Morrissey Mr. Morrissey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Morrissey</NameTxt>
      <P>We welcome this tariff upon butter, and, I should like to say, also, that it is a pity that the same methods were not used in dealing with the application for a tariff on coach bodies and so on.  If the new Tariff Commission are to deal in this way with future applications, I think it would be to the good.  Certainly, on behalf of the Labour Party, I should like to say that we welcome very much this tariff the Government has seen fit to impose upon butter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret that Deputy Ryan is not here to deal with this matter.  It certainly speaks well for the Executive Council that, having wasted the time of the Dáil for the last two days telling us that there was absolute need for careful and protracted consideration of applications for tariffs on butter and other commodities, they now come along and rush this proposal without giving even the responsible person on this side an opportunity of discussing it.  Deputy de Valera has, very rightly, called <Col N="337" /> attention to the remarks of the Minister for Agriculture and other members of the Government Party in connection with this matter.  While they have been preaching, in and out of this House, the dangers of tariffs and the need for consideration, and the impossibility of putting on tariffs without having every possible objection explored to the fullest extent, they have gone down the country saying that a tariff on butter was the only tariff that held out a possibility for the future of agriculture.  Not alone has the Minister said that, but Deputy MacEoin and Deputy Heffernan have also followed him in the Press.  Are we to take it, therefore, that the Cumann na nGaedheal Party, in their efforts to patch matters up and to prevent the Minister for Agriculture from resigning, have foreshadowed the findings of the Tariff Commission and practically given orders to the Tariff Commission to issue this statement?</P>
      <P>Has this new Tariff Commission any legal powers to act at present?  One of the members of it is in London and, as far as I can see, it has no status whatever.  Furthermore, it has taken upon itself to recommend the prohibition, while at the same time saying the whole question of a tariff must subsequently be examined.  If prohibition is put on it must be obvious to everybody that an entirely new situation will be created, and that when it comes to be considered in a semi-judicial manner, as we are told by the &ldquo;Irish Independent,&rdquo; the case will have been prejudiced.  The obvious thing is to prohibit the importation of butter for a certain length of time, and after some time to examine the whole question. But to go and examine the tariff on butter immediately after having first prohibited importation seems to me to be an impossible thing.  For instance, what will be the effect on the price of butter to the consumer?  Will there be any safeguard?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We heard a great deal of talk from the Minister for Agriculture about the poor who will have to pay more if a tariff is imposed on bacon, or if bacon is prohibited.  What about creamery butter?  What is to stop the Dublin retailers increasing the price <Col N="338" /> by sixpence in the pound to-morrow? Nothing whatever.  I suggest that the least that ought to be done is to fix a price in &ldquo;Iris Oifigiúil&rdquo; which will have some relation to the farmer's cost of production, and will also have relation to what would be a reasonable price to the consumer.</P>
    <P>There is no protection whatever for the consumer in this thing.  At any rate, when it is being rushed in this manner it is up to those responsible to see that some safeguard is inserted.  I agree that it is absolutely necessary to prevent the situation arising of having heavy imports of butter dumped into this country, but at the same time, in a city like Dublin, where we know there is a milk combine, and also that profiteering prevails in regard to food-stuffs, it is necessary that something should be done.  One method that might be adopted would be to publish a price list, either daily or weekly, and make an order to the effect that retailers must not sell butter above those prices.  The tillage farmers of the country are interested in this question also.  As Deputy Dr. Ryan pointed out in the concluding portion of his statement last night, it is very remarkable that those Deputies who represent dairying districts are out for a tariff on butter, and while last night they did not want tariffs without full and adequate consideration, to-day they are ready to swallow them.</P>
    <P>I suppose that this tariff has been discussed in full in the private conclave of Cumann na nGaedheal.  They are going to swallow it but they are not, however, going to hold out any relief to the tillage farmers.  We have said, and will continue to say, that this is an effort to extricate the Minister for Agriculture from the position in which he finds himself.  As Deputy Dr. Ryan said, there is no future for the butter industry in this country.  I go further and say that at present there is no possibility of that industry repaying the capital expenditure, amounting to about £600,000, or an annual expenditure, running into hundreds of thousands of pounds more, which the taxpayer is forced to expend for the benefit of this branch of agriculture. If our tillage farmers in their present position&mdash;one of the worst in <Col N="339" /> human memory&mdash;are to be asked to pay additional prices, not alone through taxation but directly on the food they consume, they have a right to demand from Deputies who stand for that in this House some quid pro quo.  They have a right to demand, while that money is being spent annually by the Department, practically altogether on the dairying and livestock industry, that some attention shall be paid to the needs of tillage farming.</P>
    <P>As well as spending £90,000 this year on the purchase of creameries, £40,000 on the Dairy Faculty in Cork, £30,000 on the improvement of milk production, £18,500 on the Dairy Produce Act, and £8,500 on the I.A.O.S., practically all the money spent on salaries of officials and the central administration of this Department is going for the development of those branches of the agricultural industry.  Before our tillage farmers and their representatives here are asked by these gentlemen who have been lashed and stampeded by the Minister for Agriculture into this tariff because he wants to drag himself out of his predicament and before the rest of the House is asked to support that proposal I hope that they will have something to offer to the Irish tillage farmer.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Hogan) Patrick J. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Hogan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not propose to deal with this matter at any length but I want to say that it is quite clear to me, especially from the speech which we have just heard, that Deputy Derrig, at any rate, regards this whole question as political.  His was a political speech pure and simple.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBoland" hpid="Mr. G. Boland Mr. G. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>What else is it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLittle" hpid="Mr. Little Mr. Little">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Little</NameTxt>
      <P>What are we here for?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>There are Deputies here who have advocated tariffs for a long time and when the Tariff Commission recommends, for a certain reason which I shall go into again, a preliminary prohibition, not a tariff, on a certain article, I find that exactly the same language is used against it as was formerly used for it.  Exactly <Col N="340" /> the same criticism was directed against the Government for doing that which the Tariff Commission had recommended as was formerly directed against it for not doing something not recommended by the Tariff Commission. It is plain that, so far as Deputy Derrig is concerned, his point of view on the dairying and agricultural industry is, as to what political capital he can make out of it.  I say quite deliberately that the speech which we have just heard indicates no other point of view.  Further, I want to draw the attention of the House to this point.  I have heard a good deal about dairying, both from Deputy Dr. Ryan last night, and from Deputy Derrig who has just repeated what Deputy Dr. Ryan said, and non-farmer Deputies are apparently being told that I established dairying in this country.  I did not.  It was there before me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A Deputy A Deputy">
      <NameTxt>A Deputy</NameTxt>
      <P>You are disestablishing it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>There were practically as many creameries in the country in 1922 as there are to-day.  What I did, through the Department, was to reorganise the creameries and to put them in an extremely strong position to meet the depression which they are experiencing for world reasons now. I make no apology whatever to Fianna Fáil for the money spent on dairying, for our actions in transferring the dairying industry to the farmers, for closing redundant creameries, for cutting down the overhead expenses in Limerick and Tipperary by half and for other measures which, at least, ensure that now, when the dairying industry has encountered a period of depression, it is in a much stronger position to meet it than it was in 1925. I make no apology for any measures which I took to put the dairying industry, which is a very important side of agriculture, in a strong position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I draw attention to the point that actually the party opposite is now using against the Government in a time of agricultural depression, the fact that we were long-headed enough to see what was coming and that we took measures years ago to put dairying in a strong position.  The speech which we heard just now indicates only one <Col N="341" /> point of view and that is that, so far as Deputy Derrig is concerned, he has no other interest in agriculture except to use a temporary depression in a particular part of agricultural production for the purpose of dishing us or making political capital at our expense.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>The dairy farmers will give you your answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that the dairy farmers will be deceived by that attitude.  If the position were otherwise, if dairying were in a stronger position, if grain growing were still more depressed than it is, and if we had spent money even foolishly on encouraging grain growing for sale, as Deputies opposite advocate now, Deputy Derrig would have used that fact for the purpose of making political capital out of it.  I pay no attention to Deputy Derrig's speech and I do not regard it as a genuine contribution. The Tariff Commission is sitting and, as stated in the Act, two members constitute a quorum.  With regard to Deputy de Valera's point, I may say that it is a debating point. I am perfectly entitled as Minister for Agriculture at any time to give my views as to the effect of any suggested tariff, and if I am to be debarred from giving my views to the country in regard to any such tariff or as to the possibility of there being reactions of this sort from my utterances, I am afraid that I would be unable to speak at all.  I do not agree with Deputy de Valera that anything which I have said about butter has had any effect on the commercial transactions that take place or have taken place up to date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The position of the Tariff Commission is this: They have advised us that if they advertise the fact, as they are doing immediately, that they are actually considering this question and want evidence for and against it, that that in itself will bring in large imports of butter.  The present position is that up to the end of December there is almost a 60 per cent. surplus of butter in this country.  The Tariff Commission are of opinion that if at this stage they advertise the fact that they are actually <Col N="342" /> considering evidence for and against a tariff on butter it will bring in considerable quantities which must be sold here at slaughter prices and that will further depress prices below the international level.  It is a matter for them entirely.  It is their advice and we are acting on it.  May I say for myself, what I have said before; I want to make it quite definite, and time will tell whether I am right or not and I am willing to be judged by it.  I am still strongly of opinion that the benefits of a tariff on butter are going to prove extremely doubtful.  That is my personal opinion, but it does not matter.  I do not want to go into it any further or to give my reasons because the matter is before the Tariff Commission.</P>
    <P>I am of opinion, as I said last night, as I stated previously, and indicated even in Carlow-Kilkenny, that the merits of a tariff on butter are extremely doubtful.  There is this to be said about butter.  It is the only item of our agricultural production, leaving out feeding-stuffs and wheat, which I regard as out of the question, in which there is a shortage, even though it is for a short period.  For that reason there is an a priori case from the point of view of seeing whether a tariff would improve the position.  I am, personally, of opinion, having examined all the figures as carefully as I possibly could, that the possibilities of a tariff on butter are extremely doubtful.  I happen to know that some of the leading men in the producing end of the industry who have considered this matter extremely carefully are of the same opinion as myself.  I say that in view of the statements made here and in order to have it on record, and I do not intend to go into the matter any further.</P>
    <P>I have only one matter more to deal with.  I do not intend to deal with Deputy Derrig's interest in the consumer. The consumer is fleeced by the industrialist, and he thinks it is all right.  When, however, the consumer is going to be fleeced in the interests of agriculture, it is all wrong.  I have a very keen interest in the consumer. We are asking for a prohibition on butter.  It is a prohibition, and the <Col N="343" /> only way we could put it on is by imposing a tariff of £5 per cwt.  It is not a commercial tariff.  We do not wish to prejudice the consideration of the tariff.  We are not in a position to say now, without advice, whether a tariff of ten or twenty-five per cent. should go on.  This is simply a tariff of almost 100 per cent., in other words, prohibition.  Naturally, the interests of the consumer have to be looked after as a result of putting on that tariff, and they are being very carefully looked after.  I have no intention of fixing prices or, in other words, to run the dairying industry for the next two months and to fix prices in Dublin. Such expedients are not employed in commerce; they are only for politics. The prices would have to be fixed after putting on the tariff, and every business man knows what the effect was of fixing prices during the war.  I do not intend to rush the country into any foolish programme of fixing prices, but the position of the consumer must be safeguarded.</P>
    <P>The position is that until December there will be a big surplus of butter in the country.  This prohibition will have to come up for review in the Dáil within a fortnight at least from now, and the whole position will have to be reviewed then in the light of prices. If there is any attempt to exploit this prohibition as against the consumer&mdash; I do not say that prohibition will not cause an increase in prices; any prohibition will cause some increase in prices&mdash;we can deal with that in our own way.  I do not propose to indicate the manner in which we propose to deal with that now, but if there is any attempt to exploit the situation we can deal with that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister think that the fact that there is a surplus is a fair guarantee that the prices will not go up?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Prices will go up.  Why not?  Supposing prices do go up what are people advocating a tariff for? Surely it is to put up prices.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>But not unduly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will accept the distinction. I stated that I have no use for <Col N="344" /> agricultural tariffs unless they put up prices.  They are of no use to the farmer unless they do.  The position is that now when we have found out for the first time what is the real effect of tariffs, the people who have been advocating tariffs do not want them.  I am supporting the action of the Tariff Commission for the reason I have mentioned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister realise that there are many people in the country other than those represented by Deputy Derrig?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I quite agree.  I am dealing now with a certain argument put up up to the present, but I have been asked why it is that a tariff is necessary.  It is not a tariff.  It is a prohibition proposed by the Tariff Commission for the reasons I have given.  I am told that it will increase prices.  A tariff is no good that does not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the farmers' point of view.  No tariff is any good that does not put up prices.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLittle" hpid="Mr. Little Mr. Little">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Little</NameTxt>
      <P>Suppose you can secure to the farmer a continuing profit without putting up prices by a tariff, by reducing transport costs and so on?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>You do not do that with a tariff.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLittle" hpid="Mr. Little Mr. Little">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Little</NameTxt>
      <P>You can do that with a tariff.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, can you?  I did not know that you could.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLittle" hpid="Mr. Little Mr. Little">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Little</NameTxt>
      <P>You have a lot to learn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like the Deputy to explain that, perhaps at some other time.  That is what tariffs are for.  The farmers have no respect for a tariff that does not put up prices.  They measure prosperity by the prices they get.  If they get bad prices they are dissatisfied, and if they get good prices they are satisfied.  It is just the same with myself.  The psychological effect will be, for the moment, to put up prices, but we can control the situation. This must come before the Dáil within a fortnight and, if there is any <Col N="345" /> attempt to exploit the situation, then we can deal with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>We have just listened to a speech from the Minister for Agriculture delivered in his usual style. There is no member of the Dáil who finds it so easy as the Minister for Agriculture after a speech has been delivered from the Opposition Benches, to say so many untrue things about it. Deputy Derrig made a perfectly fair criticism of the imposition of this tariff or any other tariff without some regard to the consumer.  Deputy Derrig asks that something might be done to see that the consumers would not be robbed by retailers and others who could fleece the consumers when they get an opportunity without any benefit to the producer.  We have been urging on the Minister for Agriculture, not yesterday but for years past, to see that the markets that are here for Irish agricultural produce should be protected and the money thereby kept within the country.  It is going to be a very good thing for this country that the half million pounds that formerly went to foreigners for foreign butter is going to be kept in the country and circulated amongst the people.  We want to see if possible that that half million pounds will benefit the producers who have to their detriment been encouraged by the Minsiter for Agriculture to export their butter for the last four years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I cannot see the case from the economic point of view that can be made for a tariff on butter that cannot also be made for a tariff on bacon.  From the political point of view, of course, the prestige of the Minister for Agriculture is bound up with butter.  But we are only importing a half million pounds' worth of butter and we import one and three-quarter million pounds' worth of bacon.  Yesterday the Minister for Agriculture kept us for about an hour explaining what the effect on poor people would be through the imposition of a tariff on bacon.  Yet he comes along to-day to impose a tariff on butter without any regard to safeguards for the consumers of the country.  We have not at any time advocated the imposition of tariffs or <Col N="346" /> prohibitions without at the same time having proper safeguards taken for the protection of the consumers so that the consumers and producers would benefit by those safeguards and by the tariffs or prohibitions.</P>
    <P>There is nothing in this resolution of the Minister that is going to secure that a greater price will be got by the producer or that the benefits will be given to the consumers&mdash;that the producers will get a fair and reasonable price and that the consumers will be charged a fair and reasonable price.  We complain of that.  While we are glad that the Minister knows that this country is going to see in the future that the home market is going to be kept for the home producers, we realise that these safeguards are necessary.  We hope that if the Minister finds it impossible to get a farmer to preside at some more of his meetings and has to fall back on a school teacher, he will realise the necessity for doing something further for the protection of Irish agriculture.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not catch what the Deputy said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I said that I have hopes when the Minister goes down the country in the future and has a few more meetings at which he will find it impossible to get a farmer to act as chairman he will realise that it is important to do something for the protection of agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>The trouble at my meetings is that there is always competition amongst the farmers as to who is to take the chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>And the competition is advertised in the &ldquo;Irish Independent.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>In that respect I suffer from embarras de richesses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>At Carlow, anyway, there was a competition as to who would not take the chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>There were numbers of people frightfully annoyed because they were not invited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>There were a number of farmers who refused to take the chair because they would have nothing to do with the Minister.  The Minister did <Col N="347" /> not explain why he thought it necessary, from the economic point of view, to impose a tariff on butter of which we only import half a million pounds' worth in the year and not on foreign bacon, of which we import one and three-quarter millions a year.  From my point of view, I would like to see a tariff or prohibition on bacon just as I am glad that a prohibition is to be placed on foreign butter.  A better case can be made for bacon because we import one and three-quarter million pounds' worth of bacon into this country whereas we import only half a million pounds' worth of foreign butter.  We are glad, however, that this prohibition is being imposed.  We are satisfied that if the retailers or wholesalers attempt to take enormous profits out of this butter the people of the country will settle with them in a very short time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>I have never been at any time a very strong advocate of protection through tariffs for the farming industry.  In my speech here last night, as well as on other occasions, I said definitely that with the possible exception of butter there can be no resultant benefit to the farmers by a tariff on agricultural produce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, on butter, because it affects your own county.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>From the opposite benches last night we had a wail of pity as to the condition of the unfortunate farmers in this country, and a demand for tariffs on agricultural produce in this country was advocated. There was a demand for a tariff on every article that the farmer produces. Yet here on the one article which the farmer produces for which there can be a reasonable case made for a tariff we hear a very different cry.  When the Minister takes action on that one article, butter, and when he proposes during the period when the tariff is being considered that a prohibition be placed on imports of butter, exception is taken.  If some action such as the Minister is proposing were not taken, there would possibly be an influx of foreign butter so great that it would interfere with the ordinary course of trade and have a very adverse effect. <Col N="348" /> There was no other course open to the Minister but to take the action he has taken.  When the Minister did take such action, one would have thought that the members on the opposite benches to-day would, at least, feel gratified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>We are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know that you are.  We have already had two speakers on the opposite benches, and with all your sympathy with the farmers in this House and outside it, the very moment that there is any possibility that the price to the consumer may be affected, we hear nothing but cries of &ldquo;The unfortunate consumer.&rdquo;  There was no mention of the &ldquo;unfortunate consumer&rdquo; here yesterday when the proposition was made to have a tariff on wheat, flour, and other farming products, and there were no fears expressed that this would raise the price on the consumer.  We heard no wails from the opposite benches as to what may happen the consumers.  Here now, when we have one instance when a prohibition is advocated on one definite article that the farmers produce, the one article that might possibly be protected, we hear nothing but cries about the consumers, and we have a wail of adverse criticism from the opposite benches as to the possible consequences.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of information, did the Deputy ever know of a farmer producing an article and getting a price for it that would not pay him, at the same time, the consumer having to pay four times as much for that article as the farmer has got for it?  Is there not a possibility that the same thing will happen in the case of butter, that the farmer will get only 4d. a gallon for his milk and the consumer be charged 2/- a lb. for the butter?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is easy to give that information.  Ninety per cent. of the butter is held by the Farmers' Creameries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy asked: Is there a possibility of the price being raised?  There is a possibility of the price being raised.  Under all tariffs, <Col N="349" /> there is a possibility of the price being irregularly and unfairly raised.  I have, on several occasions, pointed out that danger, that there was a possibility of an increase in price to the consumer without any resultant benefit to the farmer.  But here, in the one possible section where there might be a benefit accruing to the farmer and a certain disadvantage to the consumer, we have a wail.  In this case, there is a possibility of benefit to the farmers with a resultant disadvantage to the consumers.  We have seen what has been the attitude of the members of the Fianna Fáil Party on that.  The cat at last is out of the bag.  There were really two cats in the bag.  I hope that the Deputies who have spoken will go down to the country and preach to the farmers there what they have said here in the one and only case in which a tariff or a prohibition was designed to give a benefit to the farmer. Here, possibly, is the only article produced by the farmer that can be tariffed but when an attempt is made to help the farmer in that way there is a cry from the opposite benches that the cost of this will fall on the consumer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>We have no objection to the Minister saving his own particular baby, but we think he ought to prevent the strangulation of other people's children as well.  We have not the slightest objection to a tariff, amounting virtually to prohibition, being placed on imported butter, provided something is done to safeguard the interests of other sections of the community.  If a tariff on butter is justifiable, a commodity the net import of which, during the last three years, was only about £120,000 per annum, surely there is a much bigger case to be made for a tariff on bacon, the average import of which is 1½ millions annually?  A tariff in each case will, I believe, have its reaction on the price to the consumer, but we feel that in the case of a butter tariff imposed under the present circumstances the reaction on the price is going to be very much more marked than it would in normal circumstances, because of the history of the butter industry in the past twelve months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="350" /> The Minister for Agriculture has admitted that there is already a large surplus, an enormous surplus, of butter held in this country.  By whom is it held?  The Minister says it is held by the farmers' creameries.  Is it held by the farmers' creameries or by a certain marketing organisation in this country, a marketing organisation the policy of which has been subjected to very severe criticism by creameries in this country?</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Deputy looking for information?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps it would be as well to have the answer now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I know about 30 per cent. or 40 per cent. of the butter is held by the said organisation. The rest is held by outside creameries. The bigger proportion is held in creamery cold stores and some two or three per cent. is held by the merchants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>There is some discrepancy in the Minister's figures.  He has already stated 90 per cent. as the figure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will give the Deputy more accurate figures.  There are about 3,000 cwts. in the hands of merchants. The difference between that and 33,000 or 34,000 cwts. is held by creameries.  The Deputy can make up the percentages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not the remainder held under contract to be sold through that selling organisation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should say that half the butter is held by the creameries. Leave out the butter that is held by merchants and consider what is held by the creameries.  About one-half the quantity is held either by the I.A.C. or is in the cold stores of the creameries affiliated to the I.A.C., and the other half or a little more would be held by creameries not affiliated to the I.A.C.  That is my information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The position is that 60 per cent. is held either by the I.A.C. or by creameries under its control or under contract with that body.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="351" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>These are not the figures that I have given.  The information I have is that, roughly speaking, a little less than one-half the quantity of butter is held by the I.A.C. or creameries affiliated with it and a little more than one-half is held by outside creameries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>A very substantial quantity of this surplus stock is held by one concern.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  Any butter held by the I.A.C. is owned by the creameries and they must stand the loss.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Exactly, they must stand the loss in consequence of the policy pursued by an organisation which is being subjected to very severe criticism, not only by the members of the organisation itself, but by those outside it.  The criticism was so severe that the probabilities were that the organisation, one of the Minister's own children&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, what have I got to do with the organisation? A mis-statement is being made here, and I would like to have it corrected.  What have I to do with it, directly or indirectly, good, bad or indifferent?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not the Minister responsible by reason of a grant of £8,500 which he makes to the I.A.O.S. for the organisation of this scheme?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly not.  It is true that through the Department of Agriculture certain moneys have been voted to the I.A.O.S.  They were always voted, and they were increased by me. This is an organisation organised by the I.A.O.S., over whom I have no control, and for whom I accept no responsibility.  I have no control over them, good, bad or indifferent, and I have no responsibility for them.  This organisation was organised by them, and it consists of about 70 per cent. of the creameries of the country, over whom I have no control and for whom I have no responsibility of any kind.  I had nothing to do, good, bad or indifferent, with the inception, organisation or administration of the I.A.C. at any time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="352" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I see that it is not one of the Minister's children; it is only one of his foster children; it is, at any rate, one for the support of which he contributes to the tune of something like £8,500.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not allow any misstatements to pass.  There is no contribution, direct or indirect, from the Government to that organisation.  If there were, I would not be the smallest bit ashamed of it.  I do not think there is anything wrong in the farmers trying to build up an organisation.  I am not concerned with attacking or defending the I.A.C.  I could make a very good case for it, but the point is that I do not contribute money directly or indirectly to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BenMaguire" hpid="Mr. Maguire Mr. Maguire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maguire</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there not a sum of £8,500 contributed by the Government to the I.A.O.S.?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think I feel called upon to give a reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to have my own mind clear upon this subject.  It may be a difficult mind to clear, but still I want to have it clear.  Is it not clear that there is a grant made to the I.A.O.S.?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>And is it not clear that the I.A.O.S. has taken an active part in bringing the I.A.C. into being?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but the I.A.O.S. is not controlled by me, and does not contribute anything to the I.A.C.  Once the I.A.C. was established the I.A.O.S. has no control, good, bad or indifferent, over its administration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The real point is that the Minister has paid £8,500 to a certain organisation, one of the activities of which has been to bring into being another organisation.  The Minister says he has not, directly or indirectly, subsidised the I.A.C.  He simply did the part of midwife.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Not only have I not subsidised the I.A.C., but the I.A.O.S. has not subsidised the I.A.C.  Not a single penny from the I.A.O.S. has gone into the I.A.C.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="353" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Before this matter goes much further, I would like to see more clearly the connection between the I.A.O.S., the I.A.C. and the tariff on butter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to try to relate the I.A.O.S. to the proposed tariff, but I am going to try to relate the I.A.C.  The I.A.C. has recently been in rough water.  All the portents seem to indicate that it is going to cease at the end of the year as soon as the farmers' contracts with it will expire. We know their commercial operations this year have been particularly unsuccessful.  We have now heard that they hold almost 50 per cent. of the surplus stock in this country. There is, naturally, in such circumstances a great temptation on the part of those who have been responsible for the I.A.C., and who really have a controlling position in the home market, or will have a controlling position in the home market once this tariff is imposed&mdash;there is an overwhelming temptation on the part of those people to take an unfair advantage of the tariff by unduly increasing the price to the consumers in order that they may retrieve their own position.</P>
      <P>We, who have to speak, to a certain extent, not only for the agricultural population but also for the urban population, want to know what steps the Minister has taken, or what steps the Executive Council propose to take, to ensure that, in the special circumstances which now prevail, the consumer will not be asked to pay an undue price for the surplus commodity which the I.A.C., and even some of the merchants, have in cold storage at present. There is nothing unfair to the dairying industry in asking the Minister to disclose to the House and to the country as a whole the precautions he has taken in that respect.  It is not a political issue, and it is not making a political catch-cry of the present situation to ask the Minister to inform the House in this regard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. Hogan (Minister) Mr. Hogan (Minister)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan (Minister)</NameTxt>
      <P>I can answer that question very simply: remove prohibition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Now that I know that the Minister really proposes to deal with the position that might be <Col N="354" /> created if an attempt were made to extract an undue price from the consumer under the tariff, any objection I had to the method in which this matter has been brought before the House is removed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. Hogan (Minister) Mr. Hogan (Minister)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan (Minister)</NameTxt>
      <P>What do you mean by an undue price?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>A price which bears no relation whatsoever to the cost of production.  And remember that if undue prices are charged it is not the primary producer who will get the advantage of them in many cases.  There is a series of intermediaries, not one of whom actually produce the butter, who will be able to take an unfair advantage of the consumer unless the Government are wide-awake enough to prevent their doing so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardSidneyAnthony" hpid="Mr. Anthony Mr. Anthony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Anthony</NameTxt>
      <P>I am beginning to wonder where we stand in relation to the whole fiscal policy of this country. On the one hand, we have clamour on the part of a certain section of the community for tariffs on everything. On the other hand, we have a party which favours a policy of selective tariffs&mdash;a policy, I might say, which I support myself.  I find&mdash;this is why I intervened in the debate&mdash;that when a tariff on flour or a tariff on any other commodity that enters into the working class menu is under discussion we have Deputies of the Cumann na nGaedheal Party making very vehement speeches against the tariff, while, on the other hand, when a commodity in which they are interested is to be tariffed we have them making just as vehement speeches for the tariff. There is, undoubtedly, a great deal of selfishness manifested in these discussions and debates on tariffs.  Nobody in this House has greater sympathy with the position of the farmer to-day than I have.  Most of us come from farming stock.  In addition to the affinity and blood relationship that we bear to the farming community, we have, as business men and men with a national outlook considerable sympathy with the farmer in his plight to-day. At the same time, while we hear the words &ldquo;unfortunate farmer&rdquo; quoted very frequently and by no less a person than Deputy Bennett, we hear very little about the unfortunate consumer <Col N="355" /> or the working class people in the towns and cities.</P>
      <P>This may or may not be a proper tariff to impose.  Personally, I am not yet convinced regarding the tariff though I may be when I hear a better case made than has been made up to the present.  I have an open mind on the question, but I am amazed at the rapidity with which the Tariff Commission dealt with the question when it took them months and months to decide whether or not they would impose a tariff on rosary beads.  It may be that the butter position is one which requires immediate treatment and that because of the perishable nature of the product the rather slow methods of the Tariff Commission do not apply.  We heard yesterday from the Cumann na nGaedheal benches that the farmer was not in that desperate condition in which he was represented to be by leaders of the Fianna Fáil Party.  I am at one with the President and other speakers who decry the attitude of many of our public representatives who go about the country proclaiming that we are all down and out.  I have sufficient confidence in the Irish farmer and in the Irish worker to feel that while we may at the moment be going through a period of depression, we have the grit to get out of it and to make this country what it should be&mdash;one of the happiest and most prosperous countries in the world.  I do not believe, at the same time, that what I can only describe as a sort of intensified Coueism is going to get us out of it.  I do not agree with the counsel that if we keep on saying: &ldquo;We are getting better and better, we are not so badly off,&rdquo; we will get out of our difficulties.  That is, in fact, what most of the Cumann na nGaedheal Deputies have been saying during the last few days.  They suggest that the only panacea for all our economic ills is to keep on saying: &ldquo;We are getting better and better.&rdquo;  They should call themselves &ldquo;the intensified Coueism party.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This tariff on butter may or may not be necessary.  I have, however, sufficient confidence, having heard the Minister for Agriculture, that the impost <Col N="356" /> will not continue over a lengthy period.  I have grave doubts that this impost would have been placed upon foreign butter were it not for the fact &mdash;I make no charge and use no innuendoes&mdash;that there are large financial interests behind this motion. I should like to get an examination of the stocks of butter held in cold storage in the country over a long period. I should like to know why it was that that butter was not released during the earlier months of the year when butter was cheap.  I should like to ascertain through the Minister whether or not large quantities of Irish butter were available during these months and were put into cold storage and whether or not there was then a sufficient quantity of other butter in the market at a competitive price.  These are the things I should like to be clear upon before I vote for this motion.  Let me say, openly and frankly, that I do not intend to vote on the matter at all until I have further information.  I hope to be convinced before this discussion closes that there is an absolute necessity for this tariff, because I believe that, in the final analysis, the one person who will foot the bill and pay for the tariff is the unfortunate consumer and not the unfortunate farmer.</P>
    <P>There is this much to be said about the whole position in relation to tariffs.  Industrialists want a tariff on boots.  All the people in that industry, and all the people having contact with it, support and clamour for that tariff.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>Who is going to pay it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardSidneyAnthony" hpid="Mr. Anthony Mr. Anthony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Anthony</NameTxt>
      <P>Who is going to pay for your butter?  There is a clamour for a tariff on this, that and the other commodity.  The various vested interests in these particular commodities become very active, and insist on their public representatives supporting their claim in the Dáil and outside it.  I am not going to comment on the morality of that position.  I would much prefer that all public representatives should be free of this kind of shackles.  But when a tariff is proposed on any of the commodities I mentioned, boots, clothes or anything else that the farming community <Col N="357" /> have to buy, they, through their representatives, are up in arms against it.  Now, when a commodity produced on the farm is to be tariffed, we have Deputy Bennett and other Deputies getting up to support it.  That is quite a natural position.  I want to find a mean between the two attitude in relation to the whole question of tariffs.  Personally, I am not satisfied that a case has been made out for this impost, and I must have regard to the working-class people in the cities and towns.  I want to be assured&mdash;by the Minister&mdash;and I believe the Minister is sincere&mdash;that the working-class people are not going to be brought down to eating margarine, or some other commodity having less nutriment than butter.  I feel that I must enter a mild protest against any further imposition upon the food of the ordinary people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardSidneyAnthony" hpid="Mr. Anthony Mr. Anthony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Anthony</NameTxt>
      <P>It is all right for the farmer, with whom I sympathise in his present plight.  He will get over it if he is let alone and not exploited.  I have never gone on a public platform and appealed to the basest instincts of the people as some Deputies have done. They go to the farmers and to the working men when they are down and out and preach a popular programme. By that I mean telling them to pay no rent.  There is a new party immediately. They tell them to pay nobody. They are head and heels with you then. That is the kind of thing I want to get at.  I am not yet satisfied that a case has been made out for this tariff, but if the Minister for Agriculture will give me his own guarantee&mdash;and he is an honourable man with all his faults &mdash;that the impost shall not remain on for a longer period than is absolutely necessary to help the farmer, and not the speculator, I may be able to make up my mind.  The Minister knows as well as I do that there are too many speculators in the food of the people of this country.  I hope that shrewd as the Minister is and tactful, though not too tactful&mdash;he is too honest for that&mdash;he has satisfied himself that this is a genuine proposal coming from the farmers themselves, and not having its urge in the gombeen men of this country, who battened on the farmers' trials and vicissitudes in the past.  I <Col N="358" /> want to be satisfied that it comes from the farmer, that, as far as the farmers' butter production is concerned, he has had to meet unfair competition, and by unfair competition I mean butter landed on our shores at a price below that at which the Irish farmer can produce and, possibly, below the cost of production in the country of origin. In other words, I mean butter that might be dumped here.  I view with alarm and with a considerable amount of suspicion an impost of this kind on the food of the ordinary people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Finance and the Minister for Agriculture appear to be sublimely oblivious of the distance they have moved from their base, but they need not be so astonished when others are a little dazed at the rapidity of their movements. I think, however, Deputy Anthony is moving just as fast. Deputy Anthony voted yesterday for a tax on butter, pigs, bacon, oats and barley, but to-day he stands for no tax on foodstuffs at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardSidneyAnthony" hpid="Mr. Anthony Mr. Anthony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Anthony</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order. It was pointed out by Deputy O'Connell yesterday that the motion before the House was not a Party motion. Deputy O'Connell registered his opinion there and then on behalf of our Party&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely that is not a point of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardSidneyAnthony" hpid="Mr. Anthony Mr. Anthony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Anthony</NameTxt>
      <P>Like the curate's egg, the proposal was good in parts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Not merely have we got a Bill now on the Order Paper to amend the Tariff Commission Act, by the insertion of provisions, every one of which has been denounced in season and out of season by the Minister for Finance during the past four years, but we have submitted to the Dáil this morning a proposal which, on the face of it, is a condemnation of the whole Tariff Commission method.  Yesterday the Minister for Agriculture, Deputy Bennett, Deputy Hennessy and other members of the Cumann na nGaedheal Party stood up and declared that under no circumstances whatsoever would they agree to the imposition of a tariff on butter until the matter had been fully considered by the Tariff Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="359" />
    <Speaker pid="DrThomasHennessy" hpid="Dr. Hennessy Dr. Hennessy">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Hennessy</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Lemass is misrepresenting me.  I was not here yesterday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I apologise to Deputy Hennessy.  I meant to refer to Deputy Heffernan.  To-day we have a motion to impose a tariff on butter which has not been considered by the Tariff Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Recommended by the Tariff Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It has not been considered by it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Recommended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nothing in the statement submitted by the Tariff Commission which was not stated yesterday by a number of speakers on these benches.  There is not a single case put forward by the Tariff Commission for this motion that was not put forward on many occasions during the past six months.  The information contained in that statement was available to the Minister.  We are glad that this action has been taken, that this sham of the Tariff Commission has been shown up, and that the Minister for Agriculture has discovered that when it is necessary to take action, and speedy action, to protect the economic interests of a section of our people, he has got to devise an entirely different method of doing so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is our policy.  At long last we have succeeded in convincing the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Agriculture that the Fianna Fáil policy in relation to butter and to the Tariff Commission is the right one.  One thing, however, we do ask, and it is that they should honestly admit their conversion.  Is it too much to expect that we should be saved the childish excuse which is contained in this statement for the abandonment of the Tariff Commission methods?  We are told that if an advertisement were inserted in the Press those who control the large stocks of New Zealand, Australian, Danish and other butters in England would immediately tranship them here.  Does the Minister for Agriculture, or any other member of this House, really believe that those who control these stocks did not know that the matter of the imposition of a tariff on butter was under consideration <Col N="360" /> by the Tariff Commission, and that they would not know until an announcement to that effect had appeared in &ldquo;Iris Oifigiúil&rdquo;?</P>
    <P>The Minister for Agriculture made a speech in Carlow a month ago which indicated that a tariff was going on butter.  That speech had all the effect which the Tariff Commission feared would follow from the publication of this advertisement.  Foreign butter has been coming in here during the last two or three weeks in anticipation of a tariff.  The only reason why that statement is included in that document is because the Minister is trying to find some method of saving his face and of justifying the change of attitude which occurred overnight.  Deputy Ryan's motion, which was debated yesterday, was defeated by thirteen votes, but it won all the same. Apparently the arguments used succeeded in convincing, if not the Minister for Agriculture, at least the available members of the Tariff Commission.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>They must have been up all night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a good job, however, that the two members of the Tariff Commission had the good sense to take action before their activities were hampered by the arrival of the doctrinaire Free Trader from London. We are very glad that this action has been taken.  We believe that there is an overwhelming case for the imposition of a prohibitive import duty on foreign butter.  We cannot see that there was at any time any justification for permitting the importation of foreign butter here.  We are equally glad that the dilatory machinery of the Tariff Commission has been ignored, and that the Government have, for once, taken courage in their hands and done the right thing by the Irish producers.  The one matter on which they are open to criticism is that they have not taken any steps to safeguard the interests of consumers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>What does the Deputy suggest?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I will tell the Minister in a moment.  Deputy Bennett and others seem to think that it is only in relation to butter there has been any <Col N="361" /> suggestion of fixing prices.  That is not correct.  The manufacturers of margarine, before they got their tariff, had to give an undertaking to the Tariff Commission that at no time would the price of their commodity here exceed the price of margarine on the English market.  They were told that if they did not give that undertaking they would not get the tariff.  The manufacturers of flour were refused a tariff because they could not give a satisfactory guarantee concerning the price at which they would sell their commodity. Why is it not thought necessary to get some such guarantee in the case of butter?</P>
      <P>We are not asking for anything new. We are merely asking, in relation to this particular commodity, that the Government or the Tariff Commission should take the same action as they took in relation to every other commodity in respect of which an application for a tariff was made.  We strongly suspect the motives that have inspired this action.  We do not think, and do not believe that this prohibition on butter is being imposed because the Minister for Agriculture has suddenly been fired with a desire to help the farmers concerned.  We think that if the directors of the I.A.C. had not withheld butter on a falling market we probably would not have this proposal for a tariff before us at all.  The Minister for Agriculture is constantly talking about politics and politicians. He is an astute politician himself.  He thinks that because a number of politicians, masquerading as non-politicians, succeeded in getting elected to the Dublin Corporation, that he will be able to stave off disaster at the next election by posing as a non-politician.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a sore point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nothing sore about it at all.  We like to see hypocrisy exposed.  It is a good thing for the people to have hypocrisy exposed, and the only mistake the Government Party made in relation to these elections was that they did not wait long enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>You are very excited about the Dublin elections, and no wonder you cannot forget them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The <Col N="362" /> Dublin elections have nothing to do with the motion before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The only thing that is obvious from the speech the Minister made is that the next campaign is going to be &ldquo;no politics in the Dáil.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>No aldermen in the Dáil.  That is to be our next campaign.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>No other politics but Cumann na nGaedheal in the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nothing else that I have to say in reference to this matter except to emphasise the point made by Deputy Morrissey that it is a pity the Government has only now discovered the advisability of taking immediate action when a prima facie case for the imposition of a tariff exists.  If the Government had acted with equal expedition when the application for a tariff on coach building, for example, came before them there would be a much larger number of people in employment in this country now than in fact there are.  If the Government had acted with equal expedition when a number of other tariff applications had come before them the industrial situation in this country would have been considerably improved, but of course the political reputation of the Minister for Agriculture was not bound up in these applications as it is in this.  The Minister for Agriculture has staked his whole political career upon the action which he took in relation to the butter industry, and now that he is being exposed, now that the futility of his methods are being demonstrated, he is willing to take any measures, even if these measures involve the abandonment of the principles which he was declaring no later than yesterday, in order to try and stave off disaster.  We are glad he has done it, no matter what his motives.  It is the right thing, and we hope the Dáil, irrespective of what Deputy Anthony may think, will pass the motion, and that the resulting benefits which we beleive will follow will accrue to the dairy industry in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree with Deputy Lemass that the House should pass this motion.  I intend to vote against it if for no other reason than <Col N="363" /> that of consistency.  Of all the extraordinary situations that have arisen in this House during the last few years, the situation created by the introduction of this motion seems to me to be the most extraordinary of all.  Yesterday the Minister for Agriculture was an ardent Free Trader, and to-day he is a total Prohibitionist.  Owing to unforeseen circumstances, I was not able to attend in the House yesterday. If I had been able to do so, I would have voted against Deputy Ryan's motion, although I must say I agree with many of the things he advocated. I would vote against the motion because the Deputy advocated a tariff on butter, and that is why I am going to vote against this motion.  The Minister for Agriculture cannot deny that he stated here in my hearing that if the farmers of Ireland are not able to face up to competition they should go out of farming.  Now, because there is a certain amount of competition due to the coming in here of foreign butter, the Minister, in order to please certain interests in the South of Ireland, has introduced this motion which will penalise the people in the rest of Ireland.  I object to any prohibition on foreign butter coming in here at a time when there is no prohibition on the importation of Russian and German oats.  It is no excuse for the Minister to say as he did in answer to a question by Deputy Aird, that the quantity of Russian oats coming in here is small.  It is the principle of the whole position with regard to prohibitions that I am concerned with.  If there is only one cwt. of German and Russian oats coming in here, then I think it should be prohibited if there is to be a prohibition on butter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot go back on the motion that was decided last night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am only giving an analogy.  The Minister is prohibiting the importation of butter, and that being so, I would like to know why he does not prohibit the importation of other agricultural commodities.  For instance, the farmers in Louth are finding it very difficult to get a market for their barley.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="364" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is now making the speech which he should have made last night on Deputy Ryan's motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The trouble is that I do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister allows Russian and German oats to come into this country, but he proposes to prohibit butter coming in.  Am I not in order in dealing with that?  I maintain the thing is dishonest and inconsistent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy would be quite in order in discussing the motion before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, and I think I am giving reasons why this motion should not have been put down here at all. The Minister for Agriculture has said on several occasions that before a tariff would be imposed on any commodity imported, the matter would first have to be examined by the Tariff Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>So it has been.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>When did the Tariff Commission examine this proposal?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>The application had been before the Tariff Commission for a week.  They met to consider whether they would issue an advertisement in the Press.  Before issuing that advertisement they came to the conclusion they ought to give this advice to the Government in view of the effects the advertisement would have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCleary" hpid="Mr. Clery Mr. Clery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Clery</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the result of a Cumann na nGaedheal nightmare.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>This recommendation from the Tariff Commission was in the hands of the Government before lunch yesterday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>There are other people in the country to be considered besides the people who vote Cumann na nGaedheal and Fianna Fáil, and I might remind the House that these people are becoming more numerous every day.  When the Greater Dublin Bill was being discussed here, I gave it as my opinion that the Independent candidates would head the poll when the election took place, and I was laughed at, but the results showed I was right, and that the surest way to <Col N="365" /> secure defeat was to stand as the official candidate of Cumann na nGaedheal or Fianna Fáil.  What proof has the Minister given that there is a surplus of butter in the country, or that there will be any?  I have it on the authority of one who holds a position in one of the biggest institutions in the country, and no later than last evening, that during the winter months they could not get an adequate supply of Irish butter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a surplus up to the middle of December.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>And he said that as a consequence they had to pay increased prices for foreign butter.  If that is so, I would like to know what the effect of this resolution will be on the masses of the people, in view of the present deplorable state of the country, with large numbers of unemployed in the cities and towns, and the low wages paid to agricultural labourers.  I would like to know whether the price of butter is going to be increased.  The Minister has not given us a guarantee that there will be no increase.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>There will be an increase. Any tariff or prohibition that does not give an increase is not worth putting on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>I really sympathise with the Minister owing to the impossible position in which he has been placed, but I blame him for allowing himself to be placed in that position. The Minister is acting, no doubt, at the dictate of certain vested interests. It is because this is going to affect the farmers in Limerick and elsewhere in the South of Ireland, and the shareholders in the associated creameries, that the resolution has been introduced.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not denied that this is in the interest of vested interests&mdash;the creameries of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>And you are a party to that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, openly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>And yet&mdash;though the Leas-Cheann Comhairle ruled me out of order on this point&mdash;the Minister refused <Col N="366" /> to safeguard the interests of farmers in other parts of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>You cannot do it with the same methods.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>I disagree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is my position, anyway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>As I said, I am going to vote against this resolution because it is the most inconsistent that has ever been introduced into this House. It seems to me that there is an utter lack of moral courage amongst the rank and file of Cumann na nGaedheal.  They are here to swallow anything and everything put up to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. T. Sheehy Mr. T. Sheehy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Sheehy</NameTxt>
      <P>(West Cork): That is where the Deputy makes a mistake.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>There are men on the Cumann na nGaedheal benches who are going to vote for the resolution and who do not agree with it.  Sooner than vote for a proposal with which I did not agree I would clear out of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. T. Sheehy Mr. T. Sheehy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Sheehy</NameTxt>
      <P>There are men on those benches who were fighting and working for Ireland before the Deputy was born.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>I fought for Ireland in a sense, and I tried to preserve Ireland when the majority of the Irish people were trying to put it 20 feet under the earth.  I never took a gun in defence of Ireland.  I was a constitutionalist all my life.  It takes as good a man to live for Ireland as it does to die for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. T. Sheehy Mr. T. Sheehy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Sheehy</NameTxt>
      <P>I was as great a constitutionalist as ever you were.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>We will agree on that, but when the Deputy speaks of moral courage let him look up the records. The Minister, as I have said, has given no intimation to the House that there will not be any increase in the price of butter resulting from the resolution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>There will be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has admitted <Col N="367" /> that there will be.  I cannot see how the working classes of this country will be in a position to meet an increase in the price.  As has been stated here by several Deputies, we have had the spectacle of Cumann na nGaedheal members who are ardent Free Traders opposing any tariff on oats, barley or other agricultural commodities, and yet they are prepared to vote for this resolution to-day.  The truth of the matter, as far as I can see, is that neither of the Parties in this House seem to have a proper appreciation of the situation in the country.  They are looking at everything from the wrong angle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Everybody but you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputies should come down to hard facts and realise that they are living in a little country, and a poor country, to a certain extent. The sooner all parties realise that fact, the sooner will this country be restored to comparative prosperity. Until we recognise our limitations and stop this artificial manner of trying to keep up a standard of living which the country cannot afford&mdash;the sooner you face those facts the better it will be for the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I really feel that the Minister for Agriculture has a grievance. I not merely sympathise with him, but I do not know any words strong enough to express the cordiality of the reaching out of my heart to him in this moment of his necessity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this me?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Most certainly you. There is no man in this House whom I have, as a political opponent, more reason to love and venerate.  Surely the Minister for Agriculture was entitled to a glad and to a cordial welcome. &ldquo;There is more joy in Heaven for one sinner that does penance than 61 just men.&rdquo;  I think he is entitled, when sitting on the stool of repentance, showing the moral courage of throwing away in one single act the whole of the principles which he has professed, to be welcomed cordially and enthusiastically as a black sheep into the true fold.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="368" /> The peculiar thing about the Minister for Agriculture is that while he is wrong-headed many of us believe him to be honest, and if in this particular case he has shown the moral courage to put himself politically in an impossible position, his action most certainly ought to be appreciated.  What has he done?  He has thrown away the whole principle and the whole doctrine of selective tariffs, founded upon a careful and deliberate and specific examination of the particular tariff by a Commission.  He has thrown that away completely.  In the interests of the farmer, or in the interests of the political exigencies of the Party to which he temporarily belongs, he has thrown down that principle at once. Here you have a tariff which, on the confession of an ad hoc body which has only been in existence a week, which has never met as a Tariff Commission, has never been examined.  Not a small industry, not a thing which concerns in a small degree the livelihood of this people, but a very big industry. The Minister has thrown away the whole principle of examination of tariffs on their merits, in order to do this great benefit either to the farmers, the Farmers' Party, or the electoral prospects of the back benchers of Cumann na nGaedheal.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;We have received a written statement from the Tariff Commission which says: &lsquo;It will take some time to hear the evidence of applicants and other representative persons desiring to be heard, to collect the relevant facts and, finally, to prepare a considered report.&rsquo;&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Any ordinary person faced by the fact that something had gone to a Tariff Commission under Cumann na nGaedheal would know that they had three years in which to consider the proposition.  Is the Minister going to tell us that, due to the obvious political emergency which was behind this matter, due to the obvious disruption in his own Party, due to the obvious discontent and the atmosphere of crisis in relation to the political life of Cumann na nGaedheal, those who would be concerned with this tariff would know that it was so terribly urgent that none of the delays which Ministers say should take place in <Col N="369" /> relation to the consideration of any tariff would be allowed to interfere in this particular case?  That is the argument he puts up, and I am giving him credit for the honesty of coming here in a white sheet and admitting that, for political purposes, he does not dare to leave this particular thing to be considered in the way he has said every tariff should be considered.</P>
    <P>The second thing that has gone by the board is the main economic doctrine in relation to tariffs which has been enunciated with ability, with courage and moderation, and certainly with reckless persistency by the Minister for Agriculture, namely, that &ldquo;it is no good whatever to the agriculturist to put a tariff on an industry which has an exportable surplus.&rdquo;  I, personally in matters of economics and very specially in matters of tariffs, am a student, am one who is anxious to examine evidence to see the reactions of policies and to take a decision upon them on balance.  I have never, since I came into this House, and never in the controversies which in relation to this matter took place in another country, taken a line of black and white as between tariffs and no tariffs.  In speaking to members of my own party in relation to the motion which was coming on yesterday, I said that the one thing that the Minister for Agriculture had on his side if he would stick to it and fight on it, was this doctrine of the exportable surplus.</P>
    <P>Technically, there was a good case to be made there, even though when you try to fit that technical case into the humanities of the actual life of this people, it was not by any means sound.  That principle upon which his whole economic policy is founded, is thrown away in this tariff, because there never was a tariff which could possibly have been offered to this country in which it was so clear that there was an exportable surplus.  Now we have ad hoc and to meet the electoral necessities of Cumann na nGaedheal delivered overnight a tariff upon that very particular commodity which, if the doctrine which the Minister has been preaching is correct, should never have been tariffed.</P>
    <P>Let me again say that the Minister for Agriculture&mdash;I am assuming now for a moment that he is sincere&mdash;is to <Col N="370" /> be congratulated upon the moral courage with which he has turned his back on all the doctrines which he has been preaching to the farmers of this country for the last four or five years. I hope&mdash;perhaps there is a difference between the word &ldquo;hope&rdquo; and &ldquo;expect,&rdquo; I will use the word &ldquo;hope&rdquo;&mdash; that this is a sign, not just a temporary inspiration of grace, but that possibly that light which I personally have seen very slowly dawning into that obscure mind for the last few months, may develop into a white light of understanding of the basic economic problems of this country.</P>
    <P>The next thing that has gone is the whole reputation for integrity of the Tariff Commission's examination of tariffs.  We are all entirely familiar with the woollen tariff which dropped from Heaven in very much the same way to fill a gap in one of the Minister for Finance's budgets.  At that time, the accusation was made that that tariff was provided ad hoc.  It was proposed in this House before the report had ever been reduced even to script, before it had ever been considered by the Executive Council.  As one who had tried to defend as a composition for a Tariff Commission the particular composition adopted, namely, of men to a certain extent representing the Civil Service, I then said that I could no longer defend any system which left the members of that Tariff Commission holding their livelihood at the will and pleasure of the Executive Council.  Now what has happened? Another Tariff Commission has been set up ad hoc.  It has never officially met.  To use the expression here: &ldquo;Professor Smiddy has not been able to come across.&rdquo;  But the rest of the Tariff Commission &ldquo;came across,&rdquo; came across when they were wanted, &ldquo;came across&rdquo; to get Cumann na nGaedheal out of the mess into which they had got themselves, &ldquo;came across&rdquo; in time for a by-election, &ldquo;came across&rdquo; in time to allow the Cumann na nGaedheal back-benchers to go back to their constituencies this week-end and not be kicked out before Monday.  Oh, yes, Professor Smiddy could not &ldquo;come across,&rdquo; but the rest of the Tariff Commission &ldquo;came across&rdquo; very well indeed.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="371" /> But not merely have we thrown away selective tariffs as a principle, not merely have we thrown away the basic argument against tariffs by the Minister, not merely have we thrown away the whole reputation for impartiality of the Tariff Commission, but we have actually thrown away the Cumann na nGaedheal general election manifesto. And that is very serious.  &ldquo;Cumann na nGaedheal Government Party Organisation. To the electorate of the Irish Free State.&rdquo;  I am not going to read the whole of it.  It is signed by &ldquo;John M. O'Sullivan, T.D., Chairman, Executive Committee of Cumann na nGaedheal.&rdquo;  You heard the discussion here a few minutes ago on the I.A.C.  You heard the Minister for Agriculture repudiate his own child. He has nothing whatever to do in Heaven or earth, directly or indirectly, corporately or individually, with that organisation.  He has nothing to do with the selling organisation.  He has nothing to do with either their triumphs or their failures.  &ldquo;Eight years of reconstructive effort.  The Government has reorganised the railways.&rdquo; The Great Southern, 16?. &ldquo;Extended and improved the roads.&rdquo;&ldquo;Instituted an elaborate system of arterial drainage.&rdquo;  Introduced a flourishing sugar-beet industry.&rdquo;  Those are all the children which until we examine them here they are prepared to acknowledge.</P>
    <P>Now, let us take a look at the illegitimate children, the ones of which they proclaim ownership at the crossroads, the ones they tell &ldquo;the electorate of the Irish Free State&rdquo; are part of their &ldquo;eight years of reconstructive effort&rdquo; but which later when they are asked to acknowledge them in face of this House they repudiate.  &ldquo;We have organised and systematised agricultural marketing.&rdquo;  They have organised and systematised agricultural marketing, but they have nothing whatever to do, directly or indirectly, no connection, no responsibility whatever, for the organised and systematised agricultural marketing itself! There certainly is the amazing moral courage which the Minister for Agriculture showed when he ran away from his own back benchers and produced <Col N="372" /> this ad hoc report from an ad hoc Tariff Commission in order to do to-day what he said would be wrong to do yesterday.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnJosephByrne" hpid="Mr. J.J. Byrne Mr. J.J. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.J. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>He did not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>But that moral courage did not last quarter of an hour.  It did not last long enough to make him continue to recognise as his own child the thing he had produced.  Who brought into being the creameries' scheme?  The Minister for Agriculture. From what did the I.A.C. selling organisation originate?  From the creamery scheme brought in by the Minister.  By whom is it administered? Through the Agricultural Organisation Society.  On whom does the Agricultural Organisation Society depend for the funds to keep it in existence? On the Minister for Agriculture. The Minister for Agriculture is very much in the same position as the man who said: &ldquo;I did not murder the man.  Oh, no, I only pressed the trigger.  That fired the cap.  That fired the gun powder.  That expelled the bullet.  The bullet hit and killed the man.  I did not kill the man.  I only pressed the trigger.&rdquo;  He was not the midwife.  He did not bring the child up.  He did not educate it.  He left it to its own sweet will.  But he did generate the I.A.C. selling organisation, which to-day is selling butter so low and has got itself into such an utter mess by its so-called &ldquo;organised and systematised system of marketing&rdquo; that it has actually told the creameries that contracted for a year to sell to nobody but to them, that they can sell to any body they like and for God's sake to do it.  He has repudiated his I.A.C. which to-day is selling butter at 95s. when the ordinary man is selling it at 10s. or 12s. dearer.  He has got no connection with it here, but when John Marcus O'Sullivan, T.D., Chairman of the Executive Committee of Cumann na nGaedheal, is talking to &ldquo;the electorate of the Free State&rdquo; and speaking of its &ldquo;eight years of reconstructive efforts&rdquo; he is perfectly satisfied that Cumann na nGaedheal was responsible &ldquo;for the organised and systematised system of agricultural marketing.&rdquo;  When we go through the <Col N="373" /> rest of this interesting report we see the only evidence that this ad hoc Tariff Commission got for the purposes of this ad hoc report was from the Minister for Agriculture.  That is all. It would not do to go anywhere else. Again let me apologise to the Minister for Agriculture for any apparent lack of cordiality in his welcome.  After all, some allowance must be made for our amazement.  We could not expect that this great apostle of no tariffs, or, if tariffs are forced upon him, only selective tariffs, and then tariffs only after the highest possible examination, and emphatically no agricultural tariffs, would come to us without any notice whatever to give us a tariff on agriculture, a tariff on agriculture without examination, without selection, in definite and open defiance of every economic principle which he professes. If in our amazement our welcome has seemed to be a little cold, let him be assured that our hearts are warm.  We intend that our welcome will be so warm that the country will be too damn hot to hold him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLittle" hpid="Mr. Little Mr. Little">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Little</NameTxt>
      <P>Let one put himself in the position of the innocent farmer who has been misled some little while ago, according to the Minister for Agriculture, by the awful pronouncements of the Fianna Fáil Party, who had been so far misled as to develop a belief in tariffs, who yesterday had his mind cleared for him by the Minister for Agriculture, who read his paper this morning, and who to-morrow morning will read the paper to see that the Minister has swallowed all his principles. There is an old rhyme: &ldquo;A merciful Providence fashioned us hollow so that we might our principles swallow.&rdquo;  It is a very edifying sight for the Irish people to see leaders performing this hollow operation in such a short period of time.  I think it is a very terrible thing for the country to have lessons of cynicism of this sort taught to them.  For political purposes the Minister to-day does his best to discredit the efforts of an Opposition to remedy the conditions of the farmers, and to-morrow, in a state of panic, he adopts the very suggestions put forward by the Opposition Party. When pressed upon the question of a <Col N="374" /> tariff he admitted that it amounted, not to a tariff, but to an embargo, an entire prohibition into this country. He has adopted the method of tariff reform for the very worst reasons&mdash; for the very reasons for which he was against it in principle.  The reasons why he was against it in principle were because it created vested interests for which the whole community had to pay.  Now he has adopted a tariff to protect a vested industry in which his political reputation is personally involved, and he does it at the cost of the community in general, because he will not take steps to secure that that butter will be sold at a reasonable price.</P>
      <P>As a representative of Waterford, I am interested in the prosperity of the farmers, but I am also interested that the poor people of Waterford should get butter at a reasonable price.  I do not say that they should get it too cheap, but at a price which is reasonable to the farmer.  We have to get a compromise between the interests of the farmer and the interests of the poor people.  When the Minister concentrates upon the pure question of price he is appealing merely to the cupidity of one section of the community. He is demoralising these people at the cost of the whole community.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The question of price is not the only question involved.  I take the example of Waterford.  I do not refer to this particular instance, but it applies just as much now as it will in future.  It must be cheaper for farmers to be able to put their butter on the Waterford City market and sell it there, and to be certain of that market, than to be involved in the various expenses of transport to the other side, and the various things that may happen to such a perishable commodity as butter. After all, with perishable commodities one of the things that send up the price is the fact that a certain percentage has to be counted out as certain of perishing, and if the farmers around the city of Waterford&mdash;to take an example; it applies to the whole country&mdash;know that they can put their butter on that market, that the surplus can be stored for winter sale and can be sold there and then, they are certain <Col N="375" /> of a considerable profit, and yet the price need not be raised unnecessarily. Yet, as the Minister leaves the matter at present, these prices may soar.  It will fit in very nicely with his plan if these prices do mount up and help him out of the mess that he has made of the whole butter market by what he claims himself to have been his reorganisation of the butter trade.  If the prices soar, he is going then to make that an excuse for taking off the embargo again.  There is nothing so rotten from the point of view of statesmanship as putting on an embargo and saying: &ldquo;Oh, I may take it off again&rdquo;&mdash;put it on, take it off; put it on, take it off.  Nothing could be worse from the point of view of creating a feeling in the country that the Government has some sense of principle, some rule of action in life, and in the conduct of affairs in the country.  The Minister for Agriculture's view of the transaction of business generally is the &ldquo;skin game&rdquo; price: skin your neighbour and get the biggest price off him, and damn him; he is no relation of yours.  &ldquo;I am not my brother's keeper!&rdquo; That is his attitude when it comes to a question of trade.  It comes from across the water.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Exactly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLittle" hpid="Mr. Little Mr. Little">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Little</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  His views have been reinforced by his interviews with Mr. Snowden across the water.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>When it comes to trade.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLittle" hpid="Mr. Little Mr. Little">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Little</NameTxt>
      <P>As regards trade, it is not a Christian attitude, and it does not represent the kind of culture which we hope to establish in this country for the sake of the whole community, not for the sake of any particular section.  The attitude of the Minister and the Government is to make the rich richer and the poor poorer.  It must follow, as it is following in those countries which pursue that line and encourage it, of individualism run rampant.  If you like, that is politics.  If you like, that is the kind of game of politics we are playing.  It is the thing we live for&mdash; that kind of politics.  As soon as we have convinced the Irish people that <Col N="376" /> our politics represent the application of real principles of public life, and that in the course of their application we are going to sweep the present Government out of existence&mdash;or out of political existence&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a consolation&mdash; that distinction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLittle" hpid="Mr. Little Mr. Little">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Little</NameTxt>
      <P>The time will come when the people will realise what a terrible wrong the Government has done to them, when we shall have to stand between the present Government and the people to prevent them from being swept out of anything else except political existence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnFOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>This resolution comes on the House as somewhat of a bombshell, having regard to the statement of the Minister for Agriculture yesterday.  Now we find a complete change.  Fianna Fáil are entitled to their laugh and are enjoying it.  The Government had their innings yesterday, and without a change of bowlers Fianna Fáil comes on and punishes the bowling very severely.  I know something about the butter industry, but there is one thing I do not know, and it has not yet been explained to me in any official statement from the Government or the market, and that is why to-day Danish butter is 42/- per cwt. higher in price on the British market than Irish, when but a few short years ago Irish butter on the British market ranked second to Danish, and, in many instances, some of the older creameries were getting up to the Danish price.  Now we are relegated to the 8th place.  Is that due to the fact that our standard is reduced, or to the fact that we have yet to learn something about the marketing of butter, one of our principal products? I leave that to the Minister to answer.  Has the Irish Associated Creameries been a failure, or has the money spent on the creamery industry to bring it into line&mdash;practically £1,000,000&mdash;been lost to the country? Has the only effect of that been to bring Irish butter from practically the first to the eighth place in the market? All these questions want to be answered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="377" /> In dealing with this resolution I can sympathise with the Minister for Agriculture and the Government taking a line suggested, not by the Tariff Commission as Deputy Flinn pointed out, because the Tariff Commission had not actually functioned yet or put their house in order or met yet&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>They have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnFOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>From their own statement they have not.  The statement in their own report is that Professor Smiddy was not there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>But a quorum of the Tariff Commission met.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnFOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>Anyhow, two members of the Tariff Commission recently appointed took upon themselves to do what I objected to the Fianna Fáil Party doing yesterday, namely, to short circuit their own Commission. But to come back to what I was saying. If the Government adopted what is suggested here by the Tariff Commission I think they would be justified. In order to avoid dumping they would be justified in prohibiting the imports of butter, as a temporary expedient, until such time as the Commission reported.  I would like to know from the Government why they are putting on a tariff amounting to £6 per cwt. and why they adopted that course instead of simply prohibiting the imports of butter without a tariff? There may be a reason for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a question which can be answered at this stage shortly.  The Tariff Commission recommended prohibition.  We have no legislative power to apply prohibition but it occurred to us that we could do the same thing in another way by putting on 100 per cent. tariff.  That is not a tariff in any sense of the word, it is prohibition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnFOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a complete answer.  I am not going to vote for the motion or against it.  I have it from some of the men in the creamery industry that something should be done and that the situation should be examined. Whether the proper way to examine the situation in the butter industry is by the Tariff Commission I <Col N="378" /> doubt very much.  I think something else should be set up to discover what is wrong with the marketing, and to find out why Irish butter has gone down to eighth place to-day in the British market.  The Minister will say that quality for quality Irish butter is as good as Danish, yet we cannot get the price in the market.  If one goes into a shop in Dublin he will also find that he has to pay 3d. more for Danish than he will have to pay for Irish butter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCleary" hpid="Mr. Clery Mr. Clery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Clery</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very glad that this motion has been brought in by the Minister for Agriculture.  In fact some time ago we found it necessary at the Ard-Fheis to demand from the Government that this action should be taken.  We welcome this motion, but certainly we protest against the tactics of the Minister for Agriculture in introducing it in this manner.  If there is anything more lamentable than another, it is to see the greatest agricultural Minister in the world&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>No, in Europe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCleary" hpid="Mr. Clery Mr. Clery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Clery</NameTxt>
      <P>No, in the world.  If there is anything more lamentable than another, it is to see this great Minister running amok in this fashion. After enunciating a number of arguments yesterday against tariffs and a lot of trash at the same time, he comes in to-day and makes a public exhibition of himself by swallowing both his principles and his trash of yesterday. If there is anything I dislike, in the interests of the State and the country, seeing that we have now come into our own and are members of the League of Nations, and should be dignified, it is this exhibition.  If there is anything I protest against more than another, it is that our greatest Minister should make such an exhibition of himself, and run amok in this fashion.  We had a debate yesterday, and the Minister feared the result of the vote taken would have the lamentable effect, as he suggested to-day, of causing a split in the Cumann na nGaedheal ranks.  I hope they will not split, because whatever chance Cumann na nGaedheal has of breaking the rope by hanging altogether, they have no chance of smashing it by swinging in odd groups.  I <Col N="379" /> trust that there will not be a split, and that this motion will keep them together a little longer.</P>
      <P>The President yesterday threw out a few loaves to the Cumann na nGaedheal back benches.  The Minister for Agriculture to-day throws out an odd few pounds of butter, and if Deputies opposite could only succeed in waking up the Minister for Fisheries and inducing him to throw out a few fishes, that might succeed in holding the Cumann na nGaedheal Party together a little longer, both in the Dáil and in the country.  We had the funniest argument yesterday from the Cumann na nGaedheal Benches against tariffs or prohibition on the question of butter.  We had Deputy Bennett, who has butter to sell, agreeing with our motion as far as butter is concerned, but he wanted cheap oats for his horses, and so did Deputy Shaw.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>He desired, of course, that bacon would not be prohibited either.  Deputy Gorey wanted butter to come in and bacon to be kept out.  He must have pigs to sell and butter to buy. Deputy J.X. Murphy, who said he knew nothing about the question, voted against the motion.  Then you had the Minister for Justice, as he is called, speaking on the front bench, and I heard him saying that he is entirely against tariffs and embargoes, because they raise the cost of living. One reason why Cumann na nGaedheal Deputies opposed the motion for tariffs yesterday was because it did not raise the cost of living.  The Minister for Agriculture said that he would prove that an embargo or tariff on butter and bacon would not increase the price, would not increase the cost of living, and therefore he voted against the motion.  Deputy Bennett voted against it for the same reason, namely, because it would not increase the price of bacon or the cost of living. The Minister for Justice said that a tariff or embargo was no good, because it would not increase the price of the commodity, and would not increase the cost of living.  Here we have the Minister for Agriculture coming in to-day and turning about and introducing a motion to put an embargo on the importation of butter, and the reason he <Col N="380" /> says he does it is because it will increase the cost of living.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is quite logical.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCleary" hpid="Mr. Clery Mr. Clery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Clery</NameTxt>
      <P>Where do Cumann na nGaedheal Deputies stand as regards their policy?  As Deputy O'Hanlon said, we are having our laugh to-day, but it is a really lamentable thing to see such a lack of policy on their part. None of them, except Deputy Bennett, who has butter to sell, knows why this motion is being introduced.  It was so necessary that they had to forestall an examination of the subject by the Tariff Commission.  As Deputy Flinn said, they could not wait for Professor Smiddy, this doctrinaire free trader, to come across from London, because when he came he might examine the position and object to the embargo. Therefore, they had to bring in this motion before he landed here.  He might be up against the members of Cumann na nGaedheal.  However, what is said and done in London may not be the same as is said and done here.  If they are able to succeed in hoodwinking Professor Smiddy as well as the gombeenmen in the Cumann na nGaedheal Party, I would be almost inclined to join that party.  The Minister's policy a few years ago was, &ldquo;One more sow, one more cow, and one more acre.&rdquo;  He went to Limerick a few years ago, and if any man was responsible for smashing the creamery industry there it was he.  Owing to the Minister having said that there was no future for creameries, the farmers sold out their cows.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCleary" hpid="Mr. Clery Mr. Clery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Clery</NameTxt>
      <P>Absolutely true.  There was a surplus of milch cows, but after the Minister's statement&mdash;I think it was in Hospital&mdash;that surplus disappeared. Why did he not then go to the Tariff Commission?  He went to Carlow a short time ago.  Of course, he did not say there what he meant to say, so he wrote it to the Press afterwards.  He discovered in Carlow that there was something really wrong with Cumann na nGaedheal.  He made a statement there which, in essence, meant that a tariff would be put on butter.  That may have been <Col N="381" /> done in order to recover himself and to prevent the dumping of butter which is taking place because of his statement.  If this system is to go on, and if the Government Party are to continue bringing in motions of this kind putting on tariffs, then I protest against having a Tariff Commission at all.  I do not see the need for it, full time or half time.  It was appointed last week, but before ever it had a chance of inquiring into the subject the Minister, in order to throw a squib into the Cumann na nGaedheal Party, introduced this motion.  Deputies heard the argument of Deputy Heffernan yesterday.  Perhaps the Minister for Agriculture in a nightmare last night saw the spectral form of Deputy Heffernan passing across the canopy of his bed dressed in the apparel of the Chinese shirt which he described yesterday.  Perhaps he told him that something ought to be done to retrieve his fallen fortunes.  As I said at the beginning, we welcome this motion, but surely it is not in the interests of the country that such stunt tactics should be carried on by this dud Party.  If the Minister is in earnest he will not turn every industry into simply being a hack for Cumann na Gaedheal.  I think it is about time that politics should be banned in regard to matters of this kind.  If the Minister would think more about business and not mind political stunts we might appreciate his tariffs, but for the manner in which he has introduced this motion we have nothing but contempt, and it is contempt which he and his Party deserve both from us and the country because of their tactics.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very glad that this motion has been brought in because it is, at least, part of what we have been asking for, namely, that the home market should be confined to at least one of the commodities produced in this country, and in so far as the Minister has advanced towards that policy I am glad.  The Minister expressed himself yesterday on bacon. I believe that if I were to express myself as the Minister did yesterday on bacon and if I wanted to be logical in regard to the butter position I <Col N="382" /> would argue something like this: I would say, as we produce more butter than we want it cannot possibly raise the price to the consumer to put a tariff on it.  Secondly, as we have had a connection with a foreign market, and if we take £400,000 worth away from that market we shall lose our connection with the big buyers with the chain shops.  The result would be that we would be getting less on the foreign market and, the price being regulated here by the supply, goes down to the consumer and we are worse than before.  Thirdly, I would argue that a certain amount of butter is being dumped here at present.  Some of it may be low-grade butter, but we are going to raise the price of that butter to the consumer, who is the small farmer and town worker.  I have not heard that argument in regard to butter, but I have heard it on bacon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be wrong on butter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course.  It would be wrong naturally when the Minister wants to get this tariff through to save his reputation in three or four creamery counties.  The two arguments are exactly similar, but they are just as false in the case of bacon as in butter, and I do not say that they should be used in the case of butter, because, if they were, they would be false.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It should be a small advantage to the producers of butter here to have the home market confined to them as well as the markets we have secured for our exports.  The same thing applies to bacon also.  I am very glad the motion has been brought in, and I have no doubt that it is going to go through whatever stages it has to pass through in this House, but why should butter alone be selected?  When we look up the returns dealing with the production of butter in this country, we notice that there are only three or four big butter-producing counties in the country.  On the other hand, the people who produce grain, who are thought to be so insignificant, reside in ten or eleven counties in the Free State, not three or four counties like the big creamery counties.  Yet the tillage counties are thought to be of no <Col N="383" /> consequence by Deputies on the other side while the creamery counties are.</P>
    <P>We are asked what is all this concern about the consumer.  We have never brought in any proposals here for discussion either for a prohibition or for a tariff on any article of food, that we have not at the same time said that the interests of the consumer should be looked after.  When we brought in a motion to impose a tariff on wheat and on flour, on both occasions we asked the members of the Government Party why they did not see that the recommendations of the Food Prices Tribunal were enacted or that whatever else was necessary to be done to carry them into effect.  We have always looked after the interests of the consumer in these cases because if we sought to get better prices for the producers, we have at the same time sought to secure that there is no profiteering done by middlemen or by anybody else.  We have tried also to see that the producer should get the largest possible percentage of the price paid by the consumer for every article.</P>
    <P>I was rather late in arriving here to-day but what struck me most about the motion was: what was the reason for bringing it in, in this manner, within two or three days of its consideration by the Tariff Commission? It was only on Wednesday that we heard from the President that this matter had been submitted to the Tariff Commission, and on Friday of the same week we had these proposals brought before us.  We know that other applications have been made to the Tariff Commission in regard to other industries.  They have been up to four years before the Tariff Commission and yet no proposals have been made.  Yet we have a proposal brought in here to have the importation of butter prohibited&mdash;it amounts to prohibition&mdash;pending the decision of the Tariff Commission.  Why was that done?  Was it done because the Minister had expressed himself in favour of this prohibition?  Did the Tariff Commission seeing that the Minister was in favour of it, recommend this?  When there was an application for a tariff on flour, was there not a case of dumping there while the <Col N="384" /> Tariff Commission was considering its report?  However, the Tariff Commission at that time, having seen that the Ministers expressed themselves against the tariff did not see the necessity for bringing in any such motion as this.  In that case they could not stop the import of flour, but they could have at least said that it should not be allowed in except under licence, but the Tariff Commission, the old Commission as well as the new, having seen the Ministers were against a tariff on flour, knew it was their business to report against a tariff on flour.  The Tariff Commission, now having seen that Ministers are in favour of a tariff on butter, will take it for granted that it is their business to report in favour of such a tariff. That is the impartial Tariff Commission, the new as well as the old.</P>
    <P>Was there not dumping in other cases, even apart from food stuffs? There was an application for a tariff on down quilts.  That is a commodity that is not perishable and we could get four or five years' supplies imported before the Tariff Commission had time to report, but there was no stoppage of imports while the advertisement was being issued and whilst the application was being considered. The same thing is true of rosary beads. It is quite obvious that the Tariff Commission have nothing whatever to do with the question, that the Minister has made up his mind&mdash;whether from pressure from Cumann na nGaedheal or not I do not know&mdash;that prohibition must come on butter and that prohibition is going on from to-day, whether the Tariff Commission report in favour of it or not.  All this talk about selective tariffs and a report from the Tariff Commission is only moonshine.</P>
    <P>Another thing is that the butter that is held by the I.A.C., the butter held by the merchants at any rate, has been paid for at the prices ruling, whatever they were, in the last three or four months.  The Minister says that the price will naturally go up.  Why should it go up if the merchant has bought that butter at a certain price from the producer?  Why should he charge a bigger profit now on account of this motion than he could have <Col N="385" /> charged if this motion were not passed?  That butter was there, I presume, before November.  The farmer is paid for it and he will not get any more for it now.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, he is going to get more for it.  Any loss will have to be settled by the creameries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what I say.  The farmer will not get more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>He will.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>He is not going to get any more.  He may be saved in this way.  He may be saved by the I.A.C. going bankrupt as a result of this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Why should not the farmer be saved?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>You will not put me in the position of saying &ldquo;Why should the farmer be saved?&rdquo; This resolution was not brought in to save the farmer. It was brought in to save the Minister for Agriculture from the mess which he has brought upon himself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask is it not the Minister's duty to save all farmers, not creamery farmers alone?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly, wherever he can.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>He did not do it for the Cooley farmers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We notice that in the month of October the price paid, as far as the farmer was concerned, was about 95/-.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>No, about 109/-.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you prepared to state that publicly?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>It might be 107/- or 108/-.  The 95/- only applies to special areas for certain reasons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The price certain farmers got for butter from the I.A.C. or the creameries was 95/-, and the price as quoted in the &ldquo;Irish Trade Journal,&rdquo; which was issued a few days ago, for Irish creamery butter on the London market was 122/-.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="386" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Your figures are always wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>My figures are not wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>You do not know anything except what you read in the papers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Look up the &ldquo;Irish Trade Journal&rdquo; for December.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>If I quote the &ldquo;Irish Trade Journal&rdquo; as showing that the price of Irish butter was 122/- on the London market, is the Minister prepared to say that I am telling lies?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say you were telling lies.  I happen to be in closer touch with the trade.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the &ldquo;Trade Journal&rdquo; unreliable?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>It will have to be taken with certain limitations and certain adaptations which it would take too long to explain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has the advantage of being able to limit and adapt those figures, but I think they should be taken as they are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>All right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The farmers get 95/- for butter in October, but butter was sold on the London market at 122/-.  The marketing of the butter costs the farmer 27/- per cwt.  One would imagine that, because of the high cost of marketing, the marketing people would have a big surplus for advertising and organising.  In spite of all that they have dropped back in their prices on the British market as compared with other countries; they have dropped to a worse position than they were in before the Dairy Produce Act and other Acts were introduced in the Dáil.  It has been definitely established here that the Minister has a certain responsibility for the price of butter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a mis-statement. Show me the responsibility; indicate it even.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="387" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy MacEntee stated it.  He said the I.A.O.S. received a certain grant from the Minister for Agriculture.  Working on that grant the I.A.O.S. built up the I.A.C.  If the Minister is prepared to grant money to the I.A.O.S. to establish such organisations, surely he must take some responsibility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>On that basis I admit I am responsible for the I.A.C.  That is admitted now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Seeing that the marketing organisations, whatever they may be&mdash; either the I.A.C. or the other creameries&mdash;have given such a small proportion of the price they received on the export market to the producers, and seeing that they have fallen so much behind the prices received by other countries exporting butter to Great Britain, naturally the people producing the milk and supplying it to the creameries have great cause for dissatisfaction.  Something must be done for them.  The Minister has brought in a resolution in which he does not believe.  He has no faith in it because he is essentially in favour of free trade.  He has brought it forward at a time when the milk-producers have been agitating for tariffs on agricultural produce and have been calling on Cumann na nGaedheal Deputies to do something to save them from ruin so far as the butter industry is concerned. They have approached the Minister and told him that something must be done for the milk industry, and the result is that the Minister brings forward a resolution in which he does not believe.  There can be only one explanation for that, and that explanation is that it is a political resolution.</P>
      <P>[<i>Several Deputies rose.</i>]</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that it is understood this debate must conclude to-day as it is concerned with a tariff.  The Minister must get some time to reply.  I shall call on Deputy O'Connell, and perhaps on Deputy Gorry, and then let the debate conclude.  Deputies are aware there will be another opportunity to discuss this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'Connell Mr. T.J. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am really rising to protest against the continuation <Col N="388" /> of this debate on the lines which have been followed for some time. There is a very important matter on the Order Paper in which we are interested, and we are anxious to see it concluded to-day.  I refer to the Vote for relief schemes.  I fail completely to understand the object of prolonging the debate on this particular resolution. It would seem to be really a game of tactics between the two big Parties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Politics!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'Connell Mr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>Yesterday I supported a claim for the prohibition of imported butter, amongst other things. On the Government side the matter was fiercely contested.  To-day a particular resolution is brought forward, and the very Deputies who yesterday favoured prohibition and tariffs are now making violent protests.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>There were no protests from these benches.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'Connell Mr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Ryan does not seem to be satisfied to get what he was asking for yesterday.  Apparently he will not be satisfied until the Minister himself believes in what he is giving.  To me it does not matter what the Minister believes, so long as it is given.  I protest against the continuance of this discussion, and as no one apparently is going to vote against the proposal, it ought to be carried at once.  All this kind of talk can be indulged in later on at the cross-roads.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>There is the very important matter of price yet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'Connell Mr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>We did not hear anything about it yesterday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephGorry" hpid="Mr. Gorry Mr. Gorry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gorry</NameTxt>
      <P>As one intensely interested in the development of creameries, particularly the new creameries that have been started within the past three or four years, I am delighted that this motion has been brought forward.  It comes as a happy surprise after the Government refused to consider protecting the people from foreign imports. We are to-day on the right road, and I hope that in the future the Government will brighten our path by successive motions of this kind in <Col N="389" /> favour of protection for agriculture. I welcome this motion, because for months past many of our creameries have been calling for protection.  It may not be generally understood that the new creameries are affiliated to the I.A.O.S.  The I.A.O.S. organisers helped in the development of the creameries, and as they were more or less responsible for leading the way, it was up to the creameries to call on the I.A.O.S. for assistance, particularly when they had encouraged groups of farmers in the different districts to start co-operative creameries.  When the slump came, and bad prices prevailed, they have been calling on the parent body to use all the influence possible to get the Government to move, and they recently renewed the demand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>Have the independent creameries called for protection?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephGorry" hpid="Mr. Gorry Mr. Gorry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gorry</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not seen it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephGorry" hpid="Mr. Gorry Mr. Gorry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gorry</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the position as regards the independent creameries is misunderstood.  There was a complete mix-up as regards the associated creameries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>A deliberate mix-up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephGorry" hpid="Mr. Gorry Mr. Gorry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gorry</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not say that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>You know it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephGorry" hpid="Mr. Gorry Mr. Gorry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gorry</NameTxt>
      <P>We have a conflict between the independent creameries and the people affiliated with the associated creameries.  There are independent creameries associated with the I.A.O.S., and they are calling for protection. It is not very hard to see why they call for protection for butter.  I am totally opposed to the clamour that Deputy Anthony and my friend who spoke just now raised in the interests of the consumer.  There is room for an advance in price without unduly hurting the consumer, and such advance is necessary to encourage winter production here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not a fact that the independent creameries are demanding higher prices?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="390" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephGorry" hpid="Mr. Gorry Mr. Gorry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gorry</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a usual practice for me to interrupt Deputies in this House and I think I ought not to be interrupted myself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not an interruption, but I am putting it by way of explanation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>An explanatory interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephGorry" hpid="Mr. Gorry Mr. Gorry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gorry</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no reason why the dairy farmers should not be helped. In the debate which we had here yesterday and in which I would have liked to participate whole-heartedly in favour of the demand put forward in the motion because I happen to be closely connected with the matter of the creameries, I heard with interest the views put forward.  I made inquiries in connection with the motion on the Order Paper and I found that what was actually occurring and what was depressing our butter industry was that Australian butter was offered on the London markets at 102/- to 104/-, and that they could land that in Dublin for approximately 3/9 a cwt. extra.  At the very last meeting of our creamery, at which I attended, we fixed our price for milk for October, and we were forced to reduce the price by a halfpenny per lb. butter fat in order to keep our creamery going. That reduction in our price might cause a number of farmers to cease sending us their milk.  When the quantity of raw material is reduced and our overhead charges remain stationary it is evident what is likely to happen.  The position is that some of the farmers around our area will start to sell off their best cows, which will be sent to England, and it gives farmers an excuse to go out of the dairying industry.  We want some steps taken to encourage the farmers to remain in the industry.  We want to have the backbone of them remain there until we succeed in having a better position built up for ourselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The position according to the information that I received yesterday was that there were chains of colonial concerns in this country, such, for instance, as the Maypole, Liptons, and the Home and Colonial, and for some reason or other they all appear to <Col N="391" /> have an interest in introducing into this country butter from countries that take none of our produce in any way.  New Zealand, Australia and Denmark buy very little, if anything, from us.  How much of our goods do these countries take?  Still they are allowed to import here and dump their produce on us.  That is because of these interested distributors such as I have mentioned.  These distributors are linked up and are importing butter at 102/- when our price should be at least 140/- or more.  New Zealand sent us, in the first eight months of this year, £68,000 worth of butter; Australia, £42,000 worth; Denmark, £26,000 worth; Sweden, £15,000 worth, and Finland, £5,000 worth.  All these imports are depressing our prices here.  For that reason I say it is full time that the Government adopted the attitude that they have adopted to-day. It is almost too late, but it is a decision with which I am in full agreement and I welcome it. The Minister for Agriculture referred to the possibility in anticipation of a tariff being put on butter and its coming into operation in the immediate future, that butter would be dumped here.  That placed a responsibility on the shoulders of the Minister for Agriculture because since the matter was referred to by the Minister there has been a dumping of butter into the country.  In the earlier part of the present season the Minister for Agriculture made another mistake when at Limerick he spoke of the position of the farmers and mentioned the fact that we were going to have a depressed period in the butter industry.  In my area, farmers who were not long enough in the creamery industry to stick it out, sold out their springers as soon as they had them ready for sale, and sent us only half the supplies or less than they had intended sending.  For that reason I am glad that the present action has been taken. For the sake of the creameries I hope that a tariff will be given and that we will have the advantage of it.  But while that question is under examination it would be nothing short of madness to allow outside people to send <Col N="392" /> us in more and more of their surplus butter so as to depress our markets all the more.  This action to-day is, therefore, desirable and right.</P>
    <P>I do hope that as a result of this move on the part of the Government that it will be followed up in other directions and that full use will be made of the tariff weapon for the protection of the agricultural industry as a whole.  I speak for creameries in the tillage areas in the country.  I do not speak as an authority.  I speak as a student of agriculture and one sincerely interested in its development.  I give it as my opinion that the tariff is a flexible instrument which if sympathetically and sensibly used can be of great value to many of our farmers, and of some help to all of them.  For that reason I hope that the people who are opposed to protection for agriculture will see their way to change their minds.  I speak now of people who are hopelessly opposed to a tariff on farm produce.  I think if those who are whole-hoggers in favour of free trade in this country would think and act in the national interests they would examine the matter impartially before they continue whole-hog in support of free trade.  I would like to see them examine impartially into the merits of tariffs or prohibition.  We must remember that we are a country with a small population, and not only a small population but a dwindling population owing to various causes.  It is up to us to try to find out whether we can stop that dwindling of our population and whether we can hope to absorb into employment our unemployed. There is no way in which they can be so easily absorbed into useful occupations as through work in the fields and in the farms through our countryside. Something further will want to be done.  We will want to get down to an examination of this question, coldly and impartially.  We must follow up the programme which was accepted on all sides here.  That programme has in some quarters been classified as the programme of the Minister for Agriculture and it consists in using more and more of our grain crop for the production of bacon, beef, butter and poultry. That is, using the grain crop as the raw material for agricultural production <Col N="393" /> generally.  If we get down to that I believe it can be done, and I believe that the first and necessary step in that direction is for us to agree, as Irishmen, that this country wants protection immediately.  Increased production will follow.  I am quite satisfied that the step that is being taken now is a step in the right direction.  If this step had not been taken our position would have been worsened by the fact that the call from the creameries or the group of creameries for this prohibition would certainly influence those people interested in bringing in foreign or colonial butter to the ruin of our position and the dairying industry.</P>
    <P>I read recently&mdash;and I think the same statement has been made again by the Minister for Agriculture and others at farmers' meetings&mdash;that the farmers of the country do not speak with an united voice, that they have no organisation to put forward their please.  Now, after that, I think that anyone who says anything in a depreciatory way against the organisations that are working for the protection of the farmers, whether these are farmers' protection associations or anything else, are acting very unwisely and unfairly. We want to get our farmers to co-operate, and our farmers can at present usefully co-operate.  Having met, the farmers can go back and find out what they want.  Nobody can tell the farmer better than he himself what it is exactly he wants.  For that reason, it is wrong for people in governmental positions to say anything against organisations that have been calling for protection for the farmers recently.</P>
    <P>When the individual farmer has done all within his power towards improving his effectiveness as a profitable producer, he faces certain adverse conditions beyond his personal control.  A few of these are circumstances that can be changed by Government, by other organisations, or by the efforts of organised farmers.  I believe the farmers are organising, and rightly so. I believe that there are things the farmer, even if properly organised, cannot do, and that he must fall back on the people responsible, on the Government, who in the final resort have the power to put the findings of the farmers into execution, and to give <Col N="394" /> them the support needed.  That call to the Government is arising all over the country, to consider the question of protecting agricultural industry, to step the dumping of the products of slave labour of other lands, and give our farmers, who, it is admitted, are badly hit, the advantage.  The fact that we had a motion in this House the day before yesterday for the expenditure of £300,000 for relief work this winter is proof that the situation is serious, and when that money is almost ear-marked, as the President stated, for the rural areas, it shows that depression is specially acute in the rural areas.  I know there is a depression also in the cities and towns.  By protection we can certainly right the wrongs of this country, particularly agriculturally.  I hope that this is only a preliminary step, and that we will have protection for our butter industry followed by protection for our bacon industry, and also for our grain produce.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BenMaguire" hpid="Mr. Maguire Mr. Maguire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maguire</NameTxt>
      <P>rose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall have to have all this again within ten sitting days, so that Deputies will have an opportunity of saying what they desire to say.  The Minister should have half an hour in which to conclude.  That is desirable not alone from his own point of view, but from the point of view of the House.  If he is pressed for time, he cannot be expected to answer questions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BenMaguire" hpid="Mr. Maguire Mr. Maguire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maguire</NameTxt>
      <P>Various points of view have been expressed, but they did not deal with the position in the West, which, of course, requires special attention.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be a mistake for Deputy Gorry or any other Deputy to conclude that a tariff on other agricultural products would follow this Resolution.  The position of butter is certainly a special one.  Although there is a great exportable surplus, that surplus arises seasonally, and there is also a seasonal shortage.  The case put forward for a tariff on butter could not be put forward in regard to other articles.  Moreover, there is a <Col N="395" /> special position which is the cause of this Resolution.  You have the fact that butter is being sold at present below the cost of production.  With butter selling below the cost of production both here and elsewhere, an application comes before the Tariff Commission. With these facts a situation has arisen which has not arisen in connection with any other application for a tariff.  With butter selling below the cost of production, with huge stores in Liverpool and elsewhere, the Tariff Commission was faced with the fact that people here, who already had to sell below the cost of production, might be forced by the mere publicity that would arise from the application for a tariff to sell still further below the cost of production.</P>
      <P>The speech of the Minister for Agriculture, to which Deputy Lemass referred, had not, as far as I know, any effect in bringing any abnormal quantity of foreign butter into the Saorstát. It was a very tentative statement with regard to a tariff.  Actually there was no application before the Tariff Commission, but the coming of an application and the hearing of evidence would produce a new situation which undoubtedly&mdash;I agree with the view taken by the Tariff Commission&mdash;would lead to the importation of large quantities of butter which the owners would desire to get inside a possible tariff ring.  That would tend to depress the prices here after a tariff was put on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If it happened after that that butter came in and a tariff was not put on the effect would be that people, for various reasons, would be willing to cut prices further rather than send the stuff out. Personally, I regret that the Tariff Commission saw the necessity of recommending this, and I regret that the Government felt, as I feel myself, having received this statement from the Tariff Commission that we could take no further action than what we are doing by bringing this Resolution before the Dáil.  Nevertheless, what is recommended is a temporary prohibition to enable the Tariff Commission to consider this application without the mere consideration of it doing <Col N="396" /> harm to the group of producers who are already hit hard.  I have no doubt at all that this temporary prohibition. will bring about a rise in prices.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Why?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>If that rise in prices becomes too great I think this prohibition should not last, in any case more than six or eight weeks.  If the Tariff Commission were not able to complete their report before six or eight weeks it would be necessary for the Government to consider what other action they should take in regard to it.  I believe this prohibition will not last in any circumstances more than six or eight weeks and that there is butter enough in hand, with the certain production which is taking place, to prevent any great rise or any great shortage.  Instead of there being a surplus supply there will be only something like a reasonable supply for the market.  In the circumstances that is going to lead to some sharpening of prices.  How great the increase will be it is difficult to say.  But if the increase became very great, and if there were some sort of combination to hold butter off the market, and to extract unreasonable prices from the consumers, then the people whom we are trying to help by bringing in this Resolution would have forfeited the right to such help, and I certainly would stand for letting the Resolution lapse. This is the Committee Stage.  If the Resolution is not confirmed on Report to the Dáil by 12th December&mdash;assuming that the Dáil sits three days weekly, as usual&mdash;it lapses.  However, if everyone concerned behaves reasonably we can confirm the Resolution, perhaps before the Christmas adjournment, and we might then have a report from the Tariff Commission.  If we had no report from the Tariff Commission, and if prohibition continued, I think we would have to get the Dáil to meet even for a day very early in January to consider such a report, if available. If it were not going to be available, I think it would probably be necessary for the Dáil to meet to consider the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It has been said that the Tariff Commission was influenced by Ministers, <Col N="397" /> that it took the view that Ministers were in favour of a tariff on butter.  I do not know what Deputy alleged that the Commission was influenced by that consideration.  As a matter of fact it is not correct to say that Ministers are in favour of a tariff on butter. I do not know that any Minister has made up his mind in favour of a tariff on butter.  The most the Minister for Agriculture said was that there might be some advantage in a tariff on butter, whereas in regard to other agricultural products there could be no advantage at all from a tariff.  I do not pretend to have considered the matter as closely as the Minister for Agriculture, but my opinion is that if there can be any advantage to farmers from a tariff on butter it can only be an infinitesimal advantage&mdash;so small an advantage that probably it would scarcely be worth while taking any steps to obtain it.  The effect of a tariff on butter, if it has any effect, will be simply to cause some increase in prices in the summer.  There is a great surplus production of Irish butter in July and August.  If there was a tariff on butter what would happen then would be that creameries and other producers would take some of it off the market and put it into cold stores. The price that would be obtainable for that cold stored butter in winter would be determined by the price obtainable for it in July and August. If the taking of a certain quantity of butter off the market in July and August caused the July and August prices to be rather higher than they would be if that butter was put on the market, there would be some small advantage.  If on the other hand the taking of that butter off the market in July and August does not increase the July and August prices there will be no advantage whatever to the farmer. There will be risk in the whole business.</P>
    <P>There has been great condemnation of the I.A.C. for their lack of foresight in holding up butter instead of selling it early in the year.  The outside creameries did the same thing. What will happen under a tariff if it is imposed will be that creameries will hold much larger quantities&mdash;immeasurably <Col N="398" /> larger quantities&mdash;than they held this year, or than they ever held in the past, in cold storage.  Milk suppliers will have to be paid, and, of course, money will be borrowed to pay them, and bank interest will accrue.  Certain expenses will have to be incurred for cold storage.  There are factors in connection with the quality of butter which will come into account.  If certain butter were cold-stored there might be a loss on it, because in the end its quality might not be very palatable.  When this immeasurably greater quantity of cold stored butter is kept over, possibly we will have a falling market such as we have had, or, possibly, a greater fall.  We might have creameries making great losses as a result of cold storage.  Perhaps they would have to sell in winter at prices less than the July prices, having incurred all these interest charges in connection with cold storage.  In the meantime, no matter what the Tariff Commission might do, there might be considerable numbers of people who could afford it who would insist on having fresh butter rather than cold-stored butter.  Possibly you might have people, in certain cases, turning over to the use of a substitute for butter.</P>
    <P>Generally the position is that no Minister is in favour of a tariff on butter.  All we say is that there is a possibility that the July and August prices may be raised by a tariff and that some infinitesimal advantage might go to the farmer.  Personally I am not convinced that any advantage at all will go to the farmer.  We want the question examined, and we do not care in the least what conclusion the Tariff Commission comes to.  We want to have it examined impartially and carefully, and after that examination on the balance, if there is a prospect of some advantage to the farmer, then we will take our usual steps and accept the recommendation of the Tariff Commission.  If after careful examination it appears that there would be a likelihood of no advantage to the farmer and certain disadvantages to the rest of the community, or the possibility of some disadvantage to the farmer, then we will refuse a tariff on butter.  Anybody who concludes that we have adopted the Fianna Fáil policy <Col N="399" /> in proposing this Resolution is entirely wrong.  What we simply want is, that when the Tariff Commission have made the recommendation, the farmer who is now hard hit should not be still harder hit by the mere operations of the Tariff Commission.  This operation will secure that.  On the other hand, we will take steps, if necessary, to see that the consumer is not mulcted.</P>
    <P>Under the circumstances that will arise when prohibition is imposed, there will be only a reasonable supply, instead of an abnormally great supply, available for the market, and there will be some increase in price to the consumer. There is nothing to apologise for in that.  I do not think that the price will rise to last year's level. Nothing should happen that would be serious to the consumer.  But if there is going to be a small increase in price to the consumer, as has been stated before, there is no reason why that should be grudged to the farmer. Quite a number of manufacturers have got increases, and when you put on a tariff you must be prepared to face increases to the consumer.</P>
    <P>There is absolutely no use in talking about regulating prices.  The regulation of prices was carried on during the war for an entirely different object. Firstly, it was intended to secure a certain general distribution; and, secondly, to put up the prices as a means of getting revenue.  There was really no attempt during the war, when there was regulation of prices, to keep prices down.  The keeping of prices down was not a factor at all.  The object was to secure distribution, to prevent local crises, and so forth.  The regulation of prices has had to be considered by the Government time and again, because of applications of all sorts which have been put up to them. If you attempt to regulate prices, you will have to set up machinery that will be costly, troublesome, and vexatious in many ways.  In addition, you generally have to take the least efficient man as your measure&mdash;the least efficient shopkeeper, the least efficient distribut or, the person who labours under most disadvantages.  You have to cater for him, and if you fix a price at which, perhaps, a more efficient person <Col N="400" /> would be prepared to sell more cheaply and get a reasonable profit by so doing, that person will be inclined to work to the price fixed.  That has been found to take place everywhere the regulation of prices has been tried. You might temporarily, or on the occasion of some great crisis, do something in connection with price-fixing, but, generally, the way to fix prices in relation to tariffs is to give the minimum tariff that will operate as far as possible, let the manufacturer get all he can out of the tariff, and trust to the competition between the manufacturers and increasing efficiency amongst them to reduce gradually the price so far as it is possible to reduce it economically.  As I said, we have no intention of trying to set up elaborate price-fixing machinery.  We simply warn those who are going to benefit by our action that if they take advantage of this measure to do something that is entirely unreasonable, then they will have to suffer the consequences, and they will lose the advantage given them.</P>
    <P>Deputy O'Hanlon referred to the difference in price between Danish and Irish butter.  As I understand it, during the summer for the last three or four years the gap in price between Danish and Irish butter has shown a very definite tendency to close.  The price of Irish butter in the summer over that period has been approaching more closely to the price of Danish butter.  At present, in the winter, you have an entirely different situation. You have fresh Danish butter against cold-stored butter, against Australian, New Zealand and other butters.  We are not really producing any fresh butter at the present time.  Our price is regulated and must fall in with the price that is available for cold-stored butter.  The position at present is something like the difference that prevails between the price available for fresh beef and the price available for chilled beef.  There is no possibility that Irish butter in the winter is going to get the price that Danish butter can get.  No one is going to pay the price for cold-stored butter that they will pay for fresh butter.  Nothing would be gained, and perhaps something might be lost in the future, by a tariff <Col N="401" /> which would encourage our creameries to hold too much butter in the winter. It is possible that if four or five thousand pounds worth of butter had to be put into cold storage by our creameries for the winter each year, that without complete regulation of the industry, without co-operation amongst themselves, a great deal too much butter would be put into cold storage and you would have that being shoved out, perhaps, next year when the only Irish butter on the market should be fresh butter.  In that way definite harm would be done to the industry.</P>
    <P>I regret very much that we have to do this, that we have to propose this Resolution.  On the other hand, I think that the Tariff Commission took the right view.  If there had been very little cold-stored butter here and if we had not had the position that it was already going at a price that was below production price, then I am sure that the members of the Tariff Commission would have taken the view that was taken by the former Tariff Commission in regard to all other applications. That is to say, they would let the hearing of the application proceed and issue their report in the normal way, and while some harm might be done by dumping, on the other hand people would be afraid to dump to a very large extent, because in the end there might be no tariff.</P>
    <P>Uncertainty with regard to the findings of the Tariff Commission has prevented, in the case of other industries, anything in the nature of serious dumping.  There has been of course an enormous amount of dumping, but there has not been anything like wholesale dumping, perhaps for the reason that people were not prepared to bring in large quantities of goods because of the fear of being caught as there might be no tariff after all.  For all ordinary applications the attitude of the Tariff Commission was right.  In the present case, although they had not any application before them I think they were justified in making the recommendation that they did, and I think the Government had really no option but to act on that recommendation.  It is all very well to let some small injury happen to an industry or to a group <Col N="402" /> of producers whose position is strong, but when you get them in a particularly unfortunate position then it would not be fair or reasonable to refuse to take the step necessary even though there could be arguments against refusing to take that step temporarily to avoid a crisis.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I just want to ask the Minister about this question of the raising of prices.  I am more than disturbed by the attitude of the Minister for Agriculture and the Minister for Finance which is practically inviting an increase in price. We see no reason whatever why there should be any increase in price.  As was pointed out by Deputy Ryan, if the argument of having an exportable surplus holds in the case of bacon it ought to hold here.  If there is a marketing loss of nearly one-third why should not the farmers be able to get the same price as they would ordinarily get if this prohibition was not on?  I think our attitude ought to be that if there is any increase in price over the price that would naturally obtain in the ordinary course of business without this prohibition at all that we ought to stand against it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>My attitude is different. My information is that the dairy industry is in an extremely bad way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>There are other industries in a bad way too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Deputy would allow me to deal with this point.  I am told, and let us admit it for the sake of argument that the dairy industry is in a very bad way.  I am asked what is the Government going to do about it.  I am giving my point of view, and I have only one point of view in the matter, and it is: that if the industry is in a bad way it is because prices have collapsed.  If the Government have a duty to do anything for it and if its object is not merely to deceive the industry, then it is faced with two alternatives, either to come here to the Dáil and ask for a sum, say, of £100,000 for the creamery industry and give it to the industry at the expense of the tax-payer&mdash;either to do something like that, or give it to them at the expense of the consumer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="403" /> That is simply the position I am in. There is a lot of talk about the I.A.C. Though the I.A.C. directors are quite competent men, it is alleged that they made a bad job of the marketing of the butter, and that in order to pay back the I.A.C. we should refrain from doing what we could for the creameries associated with the I.A.C.  I am not expressing any opinion about the I.A.C., but I know that the directors are competent.  I am concerned with the creameries.  They have to accept slaughter prices for their butter. The temporary effects of immediate prohibition, as I am advised by the Tariff Commission, would be to increase the price.  I welcome that, looking at it purely and simply from the point of view of the dairying industry. If it does something for the dairying industry I make no excuse for it, because I allege that in a hidden way we have done far more for the woollen manufacturers, and the clothing and other manufacturers, who have been well protected already by the Dáil.  I welcome it also, for it is an example to the country which we should openly bring forward of the effect of tariffs.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister wants to prejudice the case for tariffs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Not for a moment.  I am taking the straight course.  I could come in and say that the taxpayer ought to pay for this, but instead I am saying the consumers ought to do it, and the people who ought to support me are the Deputies on the opposite side.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. Blythe Mr. Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blythe</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to say, on the economic point, that the real position is that there is an immense supply of butter available now on the market. The thing that has caused the slaughter prices is that there is an enormous supply out of all reason.  Once this ring is put in, there will be a reasonable supply to the Free State, but it does not necessarily follow that prices must rise.  Looking at the economics of it, once the supply is confined to a normal, reasonable supply, the effects of the immense world surplus, if they do not disappear, would be considerably modified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="404" />
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not be in order in arguing at this stage, but I want to say that we support the motion, but we also want to disassociate our side from the point of view expressed by the Minister for Agriculture.  The Minister is using this as an occasion to try in certain circumstances to prejudice the whole question of tariffs.  The I.A.C. are a strong combine.  The whole question of marketing is more centrally controlled than any other Irish industry.  Therefore, we think that in this case there is a greater danger than there is in the case of bacon or anything else.  We are supporting the Resolution because we think there is a necessity for the prohibition of dumping, and because we believe as a general policy that tariffs would be useful to the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>If anything I have said is going to give the impression outside that we will stand for exploitation I want to impress that there will be no exploitation, and if from my statement people deduce there is going to be such they are making a mistake.  If there is any attempt to exploit the statement I have made, then prohibition will come off or be lowered to such an extent that the exploitation will stop. The Deputy was of a different opinion and I wish to answer him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We are bound to have all this again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The price will not come up again.  According to the Minister for Agriculture, the price will be sent up immediately the Resolution is passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hogan Mr. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Not by my statement.</P>
      <P>Resolution put and declared carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to be recorded as opposed to the Resolution.</P>
      <P>The Dáil went out of Committee.</P>
      <P>Resolution reported.</P>
      <P>Report Stage ordered for Friday, 28th November.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 2 p.m. until Wednesday, 26th November.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>