<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Fri" Date="7" Month="Jul" Year="1933" Vol="16" No="31" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 7 Iúil 1933" DateEnglish="Friday, 7 July 1933" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="2245">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="2245" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 11 a.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Cement (No. 2) Bill," RHead="1933&mdash;Report Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Cement (No. 2) Bill, 1933&mdash;Report Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be considered on Report.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Acting Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Derrig) Acting Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Derrig)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Derrig)</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we proceed to discuss the amendments on the Order Paper, in the name of Senator Farren, I would like, a Chathaoirligh, to point out to the House that I am advised by the Parliamentary draftsman that if the amendment is accepted&mdash;and arising out of the proceedings on Wednesday, it is probable the Seanad may agree to accept it&mdash;some consequential amendments may be necessary in parts of the Bill.  Under the circumstances, if the House is agreeable, I think we should postpone consideration of this stage of the Bill until Thursday next, by which time the consequential amendments will be on the Order Paper, when the Seanad will see exactly how the position stands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I saw that position. There is no doubt that the amendments are consequential.  I move that the Report Stage be further adjourned until Thursday next.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the House will agree to that course.  The Minister has given very cogent reasons for doing so.  Owing to the manner in which he conducted this Bill through the House, I think the Minister deserves every consideration that we can give him. For my own part during the hot phase I am afraid my temper was considerably perturbed.  I hope it will be in a more placid mood in future.  The Minister conducted this Bill admirably and the least we can do is to agree <Col N="2246" /> to what he suggests, to adjourn this stage until next Thursday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. Guinness Mr. Guinness">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Guinness</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to give the House a little information that reached me since the House last met in connection with the technique of this Bill.  It is proposed to put up two factories with the capacity of 100,000 tons each. I have very reliable information that the smallest factory for the manufacture of high-class cement cannot be economically conducted to deal with less than 200,000 tons.  If my information is correct it would be rather a pity if two factories, which would not be economic should be established in the Free State.  The Minister, no doubt, will look into the matter.  As the information I got is from a very reliable source, I thought it only right to give it to the House.</P>
      <P>Report Stage ordered for Thursday, July 13th.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="National Health Insurance" RHead="Bill, 1933&mdash;Report Stage">
    <Title>National Health Insurance Bill, 1933&mdash;Report Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be considered on Report.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Séamus Robinson I move amendment 1:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 22, sub-section (3).  To delete the words &ldquo;the remuneration for the last calendar year before the date of termination of service&rdquo; inserted in Committee after the word &ldquo;be&rdquo; in line 28, page 9, and to substitute therefor the following:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(i)  in case such person had at the 30th day of June, 1932 five or more completed years of qualifying service, his average annual remuneration as the holder of a qualifying post or posts under any approved society or societies during the five years ended on the 30th day of June, 1932, and</P>
      <P>(ii)  in any other case, his average annual remuneration as the holder of a qualifying post or posts under any approved society or societies during so much of his period of qualifying service as ended on the 30th day of June, 1932.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2247" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O'Kelly) Seán T. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O'Kelly)</NameTxt>
      <P>As the House will remember, the subject of this amendment was discussed on Wednesday, when certain action was taken.  I am now asking the Seanad to consent to change its mind in the matter.  The reason for pressing for the deletion of the amendment passed on the Committee Stage is that some societies, knowing that unification was approaching, did not act quite fairly in the matter of the salaries of their staffs, and gave increases which would never have been given under normal circumstances.  It would be very unfair to force the Unified Society to pay compensation on these inflated salaries.  The principle of averaging for compensation purposes is not new, as was suggested in Committee. Under the Local Government Act, 1925, the salary and emoluments of an officer are averaged over a period of three years preceding the termination of his services.  It must be remembered that increases of salary to such officer are subject to the consent of the Minister, while in the case of officials of approved societies, the Minister has not the same power of control.  The societies are free to pay what salaries they please.  Averaging also applies in the Civil Service in certain cases.  To understand the significance of the necessity for averaging remuneration for compensation purposes it is necessary to state that this question of unification has been under discussion since 1925.  Last year the societies were informed, and a public notice was issued to the effect, that owing to the financial position of approved societies as a whole it would be necessary to unify.  Certain societies which had accumulated surpluses in their administration accounts from which salaries are paid, have from time to time, in anticipation of unification, raised salaries for the purpose of (1) using up any surplus in administration funds and (2) with a view to increased compensation on unification.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One flagrant example since the introduction of the Bill was the case of a society which summoned a special <Col N="2248" /> general meeting and authorised increases in the salaries of the secretary and each of the two clerks by £100 a year each, and an increase of 50 per cent. in the fees paid to agents. Other societies have also given increases to officials and the principle of averaging was adopted so as not to permit certain persons to benefit by their loading of the dice against the new society and its members and staff.</P>
    <P>Again, on the question of the compensation that the Bill proposes to pay officials it may be useful for the members of the Seanad to know what we have done already in the way of meeting the compensation terms that were suggested in the Bill, as it was originally introduced in the Dáil.  The history of the compensation proposals in the Bill shows that the Minister has been very generous in meeting the representations made on behalf of the officials concerned.  The original proposals were to give compensation to every secretary, whole-time employee or part-time employee whose health insurance remuneration was his principal means of livelihood on the basis of (a) where service was less than ten years, one-eighth of the average annual remuneration for five years for each completed year of service, and (b) where service was ten years or over one-sixth of the average annual remuneration for each completed year of service, with a maximum payment of three years' remuneration.  In the Dáil I agreed to proposals by Deputy Dillon to increase the compensation in these cases to (a) where the service was less than five years, one-fifth of the average annual remuneration for each completed year of service, an increase of 60 per cent; (b) where the service was five years or over to give added years at the rate of one year for each two completed years of service, and to give one-sixth of the average annual remuneration, reserving the limit of five years' remuneration, to everybody above five years' service, an increase ranging from 50 per cent. to 90 per cent. in individual cases.</P>
    <P>I believe these concessions were accepted by the officials concerned as final.  No provision was made at that <Col N="2249" /> stage for part-time officers, other than secretaries, or for part-time employees whose earnings from health insurance were not the principal means of livelihood. When the Bill came before the Seanad a Select Committee was appointed to take evidence, and to consider and to report as to the amendments to be made.  Apart from the outside evidence the Minister appeared at the Select Committee and gave all the information asked for by the members. Certain amendments were dealt with, and the Minister, in response to the pleas for consideration for part-time officials, agreed to insert an amendment to give compensation not exceeding in any case one year's remuneration to part-time officials, on the basis of one-twelfth of the annual remuneration for each completed year's service.  The Select Committee, after full consideration, recommended to the Seanad only two amendments, including Senator's Farren's amendment dealing with compensation to part-time officials which had been accepted in principle.  Had I considered that the amendment under review would have been passed in Committee by the Seanad I would have had to reconsider my acceptance of the other amendments, which so largely increased the compensation.</P>
    <P>If I may I will give the Seanad some further details.  It must not be forgotten that this compensation will have to be paid out of the administration funds of the new society which will not exceed 4/5 per head per year, out of which will have to be paid (a) the ordinary normal cost of administering the society; (b) the heavy cost of transferring the approved societies to the Unified Society, including in addition to the cost of extra staff, the provision of suitable premises, new printing, equipment and organisation expenses; (c) payment of interest, and repayment of principal in respect of the funds advanced out of the National Health Insurance Fund to meet the cost of compensation.</P>
    <P>While these heavy costs will have to be met by the Unified Society out of the annual 4/5 per head it is interesting to note that certain existing <Col N="2250" /> societies, in their anxiety to dispose of their surpluses before unification, have been spending on administration, on salaries alone 4/1½ per head per year, out of a total administration expenditure of 4/9.  Others have spent 4/4, 4/7, 4/8, 4/8½, 4/6, 4/4½.  Out of the 65 societies 40 actually spent, in 1932, amounts exceeding 4/5 per head on administration expenses of all kinds, including salaries, ranging as high as 5/5 per head, the average of all societies being 4/9 per head, although they were only supposed to spend 4/5. Under these circumstances, in view of the generous consideration that has been given to the employees, particularly the whole-time employees&mdash;I will not say generous compensation to part-time officials&mdash;it would be unfair to the Unified Society, and would hamper materially its establishment in the beginning, in case difficulties which we cannot foresee arose, if the amount to be drawn from the administration fund for compensation purposes was to be further increased.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelStaines" hpid="Mr. Staines Mr. Staines">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staines</NameTxt>
      <P>I must oppose this amendment which has simply for its object the deletion of the amendment for which I was responsible on Wednesday.  You will remember, a Chathaoirligh, that there were plenty of supporters of mine in the House then.  I called for a division and you asked whether I would be satisfied with a show of hands.  In, I think, a very sporting spirit I said &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; and on the show of hands I won.  The reason I must oppose this amendment is that, as I have already stated, in other recent Amalgamation Acts, compensation is based upon the salary for the last calendar year before the date of dismissal.  The Minister to-day makes the point that some societies have increased salaries unduly recently. I sympathise with the Minister on the fact that a very small proportion of the societies have done so but, in effect, it might really be that these increases were long overdue.  Even if there were a few societies guilty in this respect, I think the Government should be strong enough and should know enough about these societies to bring them to justice but it is unfair to penalise 90 or 95 per <Col N="2251" /> cent. of other employees whose salaries were increased only at regular periods and moderate rates.  In addition to the loss of present salary, the dismissed employee loses also the future increments to which he would be normally entitled.  I am glad that the Minister admits that the compensation offered is not generous.  He at first said it was generous but then he said it was not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister did not say anything of the kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>He said that it was not generous for the part-time employees.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelStaines" hpid="Mr. Staines Mr. Staines">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staines</NameTxt>
      <P>Any way at the present scale of compensation offered in the Bill, it would be to the advantage of the Unified Society to dismiss all employees in receipt of £5 per week or over.  Even if the administration account had to borrow the money for compensation, it could all be paid back in ten years and during those ten years the Unified Society would have half the original salary to pay a new clerk.  After ten years there would be a saving of almost half the salaries of all dismissed employees.  Take the case of a person in receipt of £200 per annum and with 20 years' service.  The compensation he gets will only enable him to purchase an annuity of £71 per year.  That means that a man, at the age of 50 is giving up a salary of £200 for £71.  That is about one-third of his past remuneration.  The compensation is certainly not generous, even if my amendment were allowed to stand, that is, that it be computed on the basis of the salary for the last calendar year worked.  But it is much worse when you spread it over a five-year period.  As a matter of fact the compensation is so poor that the Provisional Committee of three will find it to the advantage of the Unified Society not to transfer any employee who is now in receipt of a salary of £5 per week or over.  I must, therefore oppose the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I have taken some interest in this Bill and some part in endeavouring to secure compensation <Col N="2252" /> for people who will lose their employment. I must say that the Minister has gone a good part of the road, in the amendment put down on behalf of the Government, to meet the present position.  It is well known to some people who have taken an interest in the question of the conduct of approved societies that some of them have not played cricket.  Some of them have been aware of the impending doom hanging over their heads and knew there was such a thing as unification coming, and took advantage of the knowledge in their possession to increase abnormally salaries, having in mind the compensation clause that would be bound to be inserted in the Bill.  I do not think that is fair and I think that even when the Minister is prepared to take an average of the last five years, they are getting some advantage from the abnormal increases which they were not entitled to receive. I have a considerable amount of sympathy with junior clerks and people of that type who would get annual increments merely of 2/6 or something of that kind, increments which they would get in the ordinary course of business if there was no unification, but I have no sympathy with people who loaded the dice, and they did nothing else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I heard somebody, speaking on the amendment of Senator Staines, refer to the Railways Act, but they conveniently lost sight of this most important fact, that I think at least 12 months prior to the introduction of the Railways Act, a special Bill was passed for the purpose of preventing directors of railway companies increasing their own salaries or the salaries of the staffs.  It is not fair for people who cited the compensation given in the case of the railways to forget that most important fact.  If the Government had foreseen what was likely to happen in this case they would probably have taken steps to forestall similar efforts. When we come to the question of compensation we must not lose sight of the fact that the unfortunate people who will have to foot the bill are the casual labourers, servant girls and people of that type.  In the last analysis the people who would pay <Col N="2253" /> compensation are some casual employees, people who can ill afford to pay it.</P>
    <P>If there is any money to splash about, the way to splash it is to reduce the contributions these unfortunate people are paying and which they are not able to pay in many cases.  It is all very easy to be generous at other people's expense.  I have endeavoured to take some part in providing compensation for people who are deprived of their employment.  I believed there was a principle involved and I brought forward an amendment about part-time employees.  The Minister met me fairly and squarely in that matter. Again, I would say that in the last analysis the people who would pay all this compensation are people who can least afford to do so, people whose contributions go to build up both the administration fund and the benefits fund of these insurance societies. With all respect, I say to the people who take an interest in this matter that they should be satisfied, because I think the Minister has met them fairly in the amendment put down to-day.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I fail to understand the mentality expressed by Senator Staines in regard to this amendment. The Minister explained that his motive was to protect the Unified Society against certain actions&mdash;that certain societies had, because they knew this legislation was being enacted, increased the salaries of certain officials.  Now, Senator Staines comes along and says that he personally is aware that such things have occurred.  He says it may have occurred.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelStaines" hpid="Mr. Staines Mr. Staines">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staines</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say that I was aware of it.  I said it may have occurred.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I claim that Senator Staines admits it has occurred.  As he states it has occurred, I ask Senator Staines, does he intend to acquiesce in the attitude of these societies who have carried on, as Senator Staines suggested, something which is tantamonut to corruption?  Are we to understand that the Party represented by Senator <Col N="2254" /> Staines acquiesces in that attitude? Senator Staines claims that when the question was being discussed in the House on the last occasion he had a considerable number of supporters and that they put up their hands in his support.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelStaines" hpid="Mr. Staines Mr. Staines">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staines</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say anything of the kind.  I said that if the Division Bell were rung I could easily have won but I had made a sporting offer and I agreed to a show of hands.  I do not think I should be misrepresented in that way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall ask Senator Quirke to accept your statement but further I cannot go, until we have the Official Report of your words.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>In the circumstances I accept the Senator's statement.  I would appeal to the House seriously to consider the explanation given by the Minister and to accept the fact that the Minister is trying by every means in his power to do justice to the people directly concerned under this Bill.  As Senator Farren has pointed out, the people who will eventually be mulcted by any abnormal expenditure in connection with the Bill are the ordinary workers throughout the country.  The Minister is leaving nothing undone to protect the workers and the people concerned against any abnormal expenditure.  I would ask Senators who are members of the Opposition seriously to consider the Minister's explanation and to accept it.  The Minister has given a very exhaustive explanation of his attitude and I would recommend it to the House for acceptance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not here to hear the Minister's explanation but I think his objection to the amendment which was carried the last day principally is on the grounds of the financial inability of the new society to bear what may be an increased burden. That is a different type of opposition to opposing in principle the acceptance of the basis of the last year's salary as compared with the five years average.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I favoured Senator Staines' amendment on the last day and in principle I support it to-day, because what you <Col N="2255" /> are depriving a man of is not the average amount of his salary in the past years but the salary which he is at present enjoying and which he would hope to enjoy for the future.  Nobody can get away from that.  If you take away a man's property you generally pay him what it is worth to-day.  It may have been improved considerably in the past couple of years but you are not going to go back and pay him on what the average value of his property was during the past five years.  You pay him for what you deprive him of. To that extent the amendment was a sound and reasonable one and was, in the main, the principle which has been adopted by the Oireachtas in regard to compensation right through from 1922, as far as I am aware and I took an interest in all these questions.  It is a very serious thing to deprive a man of his livelihood.</P>
    <P>It is all very well to say that it will be the poor people who will pay for this compensation.  The very same thing applies when you deprive public board employees of their employment. Very poor ratepayers, the very same people who would be compensating officials under this Bill, would also be compensating officials of public boards who lose their employment.  We never heard their case pleaded very pathetically or the taking away of a man's livelihood being justified on the grounds that the people who would compensate him are poor people or that some of them, in any case, are poor people.  The Minister has indicated that the funds of some of these societies were in a bad way and it might be argued that if unification did not take place some of these people would in any case lose their employment.  I can quite see that point and that you might also have a reduction in rates of pay.  I also agree payment of benefit because of unemployment, and consequent ill-health and so on, may have been very heavy, and that the administrative expense may not be able to bear the compensation.  It is only on these grounds that I would suggest to Senator Staines that it might not be wise to press his amendment.  While I entirely agree with it in principle, <Col N="2256" /> it is merely because of expediency, by reason of the financial position to which the Minister has drawn attention, that I would suggest that it is, perhaps, not wise to press the amendment which was carried on the last occasion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps, as you were not here, Senator, I may point out that one of the major grounds on which the Minister wished to change was that certain societies had raised men's salaries beyond all thought, during the last year, with the intent of getting further sums in compensation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>In no circumstances would I support a position like that.  I know that a similar position developed in regard to a few of the small railways prior to the Act of 1924, and there was special provision put in the Act to deal with it, so that any increases in salary given after a certain date would not count for compensation.  I certainly would not support a principle of that kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to supplement what has been said on a particular ground&mdash;a very sordid ground, perhaps, but very real and serious.  The Minister has shown very definitely that he has conceded the last amendment&mdash;the amendment referring to the part-time agents&mdash; under pressure, no doubt, he himself being personally desirous of yielding to the pressure, but feeling that he was acting against the expert advice of his Department that the society's funds would not bear it.  He has gone with the Seanad to that extent, but he is not bound to support that in the Dáil and, if he feels that, having given way on one point, another is being piled upon him, he may say: &ldquo;I will have to insist on the Bill as it left the Dáil,&rdquo; and I do not want to tempt him into that position.  I do not want to lose what we have pretty well secured, because we are aiming at a little more.  There were two or three other amendments which I had serious intentions of bringing forward, and which would cost a little but which I thought should be accepted on, at least, as sound grounds of principle as those of <Col N="2257" /> Senator Staines but, in view of the force of circumstances, I refrained from putting them forward.  On the mere grounds of expediency and hard bargaining, I think we should accept the amendment and not ask for more than we have secured.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Senator Staines rose.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You cannot speak again, Senator.  This is Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelStaines" hpid="Mr. Staines Mr. Staines">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staines</NameTxt>
      <P>I wanted to explain&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it an explanation you want to make?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelStaines" hpid="Mr. Staines Mr. Staines">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staines</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  I think the Senator on the other side has made an uncalled-for attack on me.  I am quite prepared to withdraw my opposition on the ground of expediency but Senator Quirke said that he did not understand my mentality.  My attitude on this question is that, if 5 per cent. of any group of societies, or of men, or of Governments do wrong, it is not just to make the 100 per cent. suffer for the wrong done by that 5 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You are making an argument, Senator, and I cannot allow that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelStaines" hpid="Mr. Staines Mr. Staines">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staines</NameTxt>
      <P>That is my mentality, and I explained that.</P>
      <P>Amendment put, and declared carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Government amendment No. 2:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 22, sub-section (3).  Before the word &ldquo;annual&rdquo; in line 40, page 9, to insert the word &ldquo;average.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This amendment is consequential on amendment No. 1.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Government amendment No. 3:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 22, sub-section (4).  Before the word &ldquo;annual&rdquo; in line 61 to insert the word &ldquo;average.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This is also consequential.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2258" /> Question put: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to make a short statement, somewhat in the nature of a personal statement&mdash;not wholly so but having some of that tinge.  On the Second Reading Stage in the Dáil, a speech was made by General Mulcahy, late Minister for Local Government and Public Health, who was responsible to Parliament for national health insurance work in the previous Government.  In the course of that speech, as reported in column 183, Dáil Debates, of 27th April last, he said:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;Deputy Norton considers that it is unfair that persons in one society should receive better benefits than those in another.  If you take successful societies or, at any rate, societies that are supposed to be successful, such as the Distributive Workers and Clerks in Dublin, the Tramways and Omnibus employees in Dublin, the Dublin Typographical Provident Approved Society, the Dublin Operative Plasterers' Society, the National Amalgamated Bakers' National Health Insurance Society, the Irish National Painters' and Decorators' Trade Union, the Great Southern and Western Railways employees and the Dublin United Brassfounders&mdash;note that these are all trade union societies&mdash;I should like to hear from anyone on the Labour Benches whether these societies are to suffer in their benefits, in cash or otherwise, in order to make up for the bad running of the Irish Trade Union Congress Health Insurance Society.  While Deputy Norton may complain about the Minister not giving him information enough to enable him to judge of the financial position, I suggest very definitely to the Deputy that he is able to find what the position of these societies is in the City of Dublin.  The Minister simply having made up his mind that he is going to have a Unified Society even if he has a majority of one and, possibly, that he has the benediction of the Labour Party in the matter, if he does not want to go into the elaborate <Col N="2259" /> detail that no doubt would be necessary to make the situation a little plainer to the House, I think in all fairness to the workers in the City of Dublin that Deputy Norton might let us know whether in fact those people in societies in the City of Dublin, whom I have named, are going to be called upon to make sacrifices to make up for the bad running of the health insurance societies run in the name of the Irish Trade Union Congress.</P>
    <P>A certain amount of heat followed on that after a time, nobody in the House being in a position to speak with authority on the matter and some correspondence, apparently, took place between the Irish Trade Union Congress Health Insurance Society, first, in the newspapers and, then, by direct address to Deputy Mulcahy, and, on the Fifth Stage, Deputy Mulcahy said:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Exception has been taken on the part of the officials of, I think, the Irish Trade Unions' Congress Approved Society to certain remarks made by me on the Second Stage to the effect that the management of the society was bad management. It is felt by the officials of that society that the statements that have been made here may prejudice their future in the eyes of the Minister, or the body of trustees that is going to be set up to carry out the re-organisation scheme that will be necessary in setting up the Unified Society.  I do not think that the officials of that society need be in any way concerned with that, and I do not believe they are.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>He goes on, later, to say:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;If I individualised one labour society it was because of its name, and because of a connection that I supposed it had with the Irish Trade Union Congress.  I am told it has not, but whether it has or not, I do not think it is at all unreasonable to make the case here that you had a unified society being formed under the National Health Insurance Scheme that was going <Col N="2260" /> to prejudice the interests of, not only small, well organised and well managed societies throughout the country, but other smaller labour societies; that in my opinion a lot of the support of the Labour Party to this particular Bill came from a desire to cover up the bad management of some of the national health insurance societies that have been run under labour management.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There was in no sense a withdrawal of the statement that General Mulcahy made on the Second Reading of the Bill and, as it has gone on the record of the Dáil, with the authority of the Minister, who, for seven or eight years was responsible for the conduct of national health insurance affairs, so far as a Minister is responsible, it would stand unless contradicted officially as an authoritative statement.  It is, in fact, a gross libel. I was connected formerly with and was the responsible official of the Irish Trades Union Congress at the time of the change over from the British societies to the Irish societies of the amalgamated societies, as they were called. Societies having headquarters in Britain and members in the Irish Free State had to be dissolved and their Irish membership transferred to an Irish society.  The members of trade unions having headquarters in Britain were, therefore, obliged to transfer into a society on this side of the water and it was thought wise that a trade union society should be formed to take in as many as were willing to come in of the small membership of these societies and, in fact, a society was formed, under the name of the Irish Trade Unions Congress Health Insurance Society and consisting of members of 27 different trade union societies having headquarters in Great Britain. The membership of these societies ranged from 1,760 down to a single member and the benefits that were enjoyed by each one of these individual societies were transferred to the new society and went over with the membership.  The new society was formed and had, I think, a membership of round about 10,000.  Its management was in the hands of the <Col N="2261" /> responsible officials of no fewer than eight different trade unions.  These officials feel very much aggrieved that their management of that society, in the years since 1923, has been maligned in the way it was maligned in the Dáil and they have asked me to have placed on record some, at least, of the salient facts in the matter and that is what I propose to do in a very few words.</P>
    <P>There were 27 societies having headquarters in Great Britain taken into the Irish Trade Union Congress Society in 1923.  The additional benefits which had attached to those societies having headquarters in Britain were carried over to the Irish membership, and it was pointed out here, bear in mind, that the British societies had an advantage over the Irish societies because of the widespread membership and the greater economy that resulted. Nevertheless, those additional benefits of those United Kingdom societies were all taken over by the new society.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask a question? Were they taken over with regard to the resources of the society or taken over as an obligation, apart from the ability of the new society to bear them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>The new society took over all responsibilities, that is to say, there was a general transfer of all kinds of membership from the British societies and whatever benefits had accrued to the membership of the United Kingdom society had to be borne by the new society&mdash; one society having much better additional benefits than another &mdash;but whatever would be the benefits carried over from the old society had to follow until the next valuation.  I am pointing that out for this reason, that, at the time they were taken over, in 1923, the valuation report showed that there was a benefit fund averaging £15.77 per member.  In 1928, on the new valuation after five years' management, the benefit fund showed an average in favour of the members of £16.06 per member.  That is an improvement in the Irish position over and above the position that prevailed under the British societies' management. <Col N="2262" /> It possibly would have been higher still for those particular members if there had been no change over, but the very least that one can claim is that there is no evidence of bad management and bad control in those circumstances.  There was an increase in the additional benefits after five years of Irish management by the Irish Trades Union Congress Society from an average of about 2/3 per member to an average of about 4/- per member.  Since 1923&mdash;since the 27 societies were taken in&mdash;other societies were added.  Following the policy of the Commissioners in favour of unification and of absorption, the Trades Union Congress Society was induced, and by its own volition in one or two cases, to take over six other societies.  One or two of them were not by any means flourishing, but because one good society was taken over it was thought fair and reasonable that one bad society should be taken over.  In fact, six other societies have been taken over with the approval of the Commissioners.</P>
      <P>In the auditor's report on the last valuation in 1928, a report which was issued on the 11th April, 1931, we find this: &ldquo;The result of the present valuation shows a surplus of £30,640.  The sum carried forward from the last valuation on the 31st December, 1933 amounted to £27,181 made up as follows: surplus at last valuation £41,769; less amount applied to additional benefits £20,235; balance not distributed £21,534; contingencies fund added 1st January, 1924, £5,647; total carried forward £27,181.&rdquo;  The result of the present valuation, therefore, the auditor says, shows that the surplus has increased by £3,459 in the five years 1924-28, and then the auditor goes on to enlarge upon that.  It is not possible to say with authority and definiteness what the position of the society would be in the years subsequent to 1928, but it is believed by those most fitted to judge that the society would be in at least as healthy a condition as it was in in 1928.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That is all I have to say.  I want these authoritative and undeniable facts to be placed on the records of this House so that they will be read, <Col N="2263" /> or can be read, with equal facility by any historian or person who wants to judge the truth or otherwise of General Mulcahy's charge: that one statement shall have, at least, the same amount of publicity as the other.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Services (Temporary Economies)" RHead="Bill, 1933&mdash;Second Stage (resumed)">
    <Title>Public Services (Temporary Economies) Bill, 1933&mdash;Second Stage (resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I have hesitated to speak on this Bill until now for what I consider to be a good reason.  I made up my mind some time ago that, in view of the fact that I was concerned personally in the effects of the Bill, I would not vote on this Bill at any stage.  But I feel bound to express a point of view which has not yet been expressed, and to state my position in regard to the Bill.  There are two facts which govern any judgment that I make on this kind of question which, I believe, ought to be present in the minds of everybody concerned with such questions.  Those facts are: the relative position of the great part of the community which is engaged in the production of the vast majority of our transportable saleable commodities&mdash;agricultural produce&mdash; with the rest of the community, and, secondly, the undeniable fact that retail price levels have been for some time tending downwards.  These two facts, I think, must be present in the mind of anybody trying to look at this problem, and related problems, with anything like a non-partisan mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Crosbie yesterday treated us to a very interesting review of the economic and social position in Cork about 50 years ago.  I thought it extremely interesting and valuable if it had had any relation to the Bill.  I hope the Senator will pursue that and add a little to our enlightenment by an examination of the mode of life and the social habits of the people of Cork and district who were not living in that deplorable condition in which, he said, the workers of Cork at that time were obliged to live.  At that time <Col N="2264" /> there was a social life in Cork and other parts of the country enjoyed by the propertied classes which was a very great distance from that of the working classes to whom he referred. I think it would add to our interest if, at some time in the future, the Senator would enlighten us on that side of that social question.</P>
    <P>Getting away from that, the Senator expressed a kind of desire and hope that agriculturally we would get back to the halcyon days of 1931.  He pointed out how as a result of the great improvements in agricultural conditions&mdash;owing to improved croppings and agricultural education&mdash; prices had risen: that agriculture was prosperous in 1931, and said that was the ideal to aim at.  Now I do not think it has been mentioned before, but there ought to be some attention drawn to the fact that the year 1926 is the year upon which we might rely to build a good deal of our economic thinking because of the fact that there was a census of production taken that year, as well as a census of agricultural output and a census of population. From those records there has been compiled material of very great importance and value for the guidance of members of the Oireachtas, of Ministers and publicists generally.</P>
    <P>I am going to invite members of the Seanad to read an article in the <i>Economic Journal</i> for March of this year&mdash;it will be found in the Library&mdash; by Dr. T.J. Kiernan, who is in the High Commissioner's office in London, and also, when the opportunity arises, to read his subsequent paper upon the national expenditure of the Irish Free State.  I am giving him that free advertisement, not that it will be of any value to him personally, but it will be of really great value to those who are interested in such matters, and to those who are not yet interested but ought to be.  From the articles that have been compiled by him from official statistics &mdash;the estimates that he has made have been fairly well confirmed by other independent inquirers&mdash;it will be seen that the position of the agriculturist in 1931 that Senator Crosbie referred to was not by any means happy, materially.  The figures that have been <Col N="2265" /> given by Dr. Kiernan show that, in 1926, the net output of agriculture, after paying annuities, rents and rates, was round about £48,000,000, and out of that sum wages of labourers had to be paid.  If we allow the very small figure of 25/- a week for the 127,000 wage-labourers of that time we get the net output of agriculture, including the value of the produce consumed on the farms, at £40,000,000, but in the happy year of 1931 that figure of £40,000,000, had come down to round about £25,000,000.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>What is it this year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator please wait a minute?  In that happy year of 1931 the figure which was available for the agricultural community was about £25,000,000, assuming that they paid the agricultural labourers at the rate of 25/- a week.  Since then there has been a decline in agricultural prices.  There has been a decline since then, if one is to take the price index figures for January, February and March of this year, of another £8,000,000.  Of course, against that decline there has been, probably, a a very much greater increase in the amount of agricultural produce consumed by the farmers on their own farms, and there has been some saving to them by virtue of the land annuities' remissions and reductions of rates.  I am not now going to enlarge upon that any further except to say this: that it is a factor, a very important factor, which should govern our thinking in regard to the social and economic conditions of the non-agricultural population, and particularly that part of the non-agricultural population which is engaged in distribution and administration, as distinct from economic production.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There has also been, as I indicated, a decline in retail prices.  So far as there has been a decline in retail prices, it has improved the position of the agriculturist of this year as compared with that of the agriculturist of 1926.  Having that in mind in considering the effects of the Bill, I want to ask the Minister what principle is at work in this measure?  By what test does he ask to have the Bill judged? <Col N="2266" /> I cannot reconcile the Bill with any principle at all.  If the Minister argued, on the basis of the outstanding figures I quoted, that it was necessary there should be a general levelling down of the position of the better-off class of the community, then, though one might disagree with that argument, one could understand it.  But that is not his argument.  If it were, this Bill would not be confined to those people whom the Minister can directly influence by a cut in salaries.  If that were his object, it could have been accomplished by a general additional tax upon all those people whether in, or outside, Government service.  So that we cannot take it that it is that principle which is at work.  It has been suggested that the Minister's view is that the general level of salaries in the Civil Service and in quasi-public employment is too high.  That, again, must be abandoned as the theory behind this Bill, because the Bill is only intended to apply for one year. We cannot, therefore, give credit to the Minister for that as his motive of action.  He said, in his opening statement, that the object of this Bill was economy&mdash;that is to say, that the Exchequer requires £270,000 and that he proposes to obtain it in this way because he cannot get it in any other way.  I cannot reconcile even that with the Bill, because the purpose of certain sections of the Bill is to reduce the salaries of people in circumstances in which the Exchequer will not receive the benefit of the saving.  The Minister cannot justify the Bill on that count. I do not understand what the motive of the Bill is.  There may be a complexity of motives.  If that be so, I think we should be informed what they are.  If the case is genuine, that the aim is to obtain for this year £270,000, that there is no other way of obtaining that sum except by cutting down expenditure on social services, that the money cannot be obtained by additional taxation, then I ask: &ldquo;Why should a new form of super-tax of a graded character to last one year be made to apply to one small section of the salaried officials of the country?&rdquo; If the intention was to grade down <Col N="2267" /> the higher range of salaried persons in the country, surely it would have been advisable, in carrying out that policy, to introduce an amendment to the income tax law so that all people in receipt of salaries within these ranges for administrative work, whether inside Government service or outside it, would be made to pay.</P>
    <P>I think that the general effect of the Bill will not be good.  I think that the price to be paid for obtaining £270,000 is too great.  It would have been better politics and better statesmanship if the Minister had moved in the direction of applying the same principle to all persons who are in receipt of the higher ranges of salary, and not confine his attack to those who come within the direct range of his Departmental activities.  That last phrase requires some modification because he has gone out of his way in a manner which I cannot understand, to make his policy apply to persons in services which are, undoubtedly, quasi-Governmental, but the economies in which will not go into the Government coffers.  One can only deduce from that extension of the range of the Bill that the Minister desires that there should be a general scaling down of salaries in the administrative services, whether Governmental or otherwise. I think that there is an arguable case for that kind of scaling down. Whether the scaling down should take place by this method or by an extension of the income tax law, is open to argument. But let the matter be argued on its merits, and do not let us try to get to that objective by means which are indicated in this Bill and which do not seem to me, at any rate, to be derived from any definite principle, or to be in fulfilment of any publicly-stated policy.</P>
    <P>These are my views upon the Bill.  I think that a case can be made for a scaling down of the remuneration, whether derived from salaries or otherwise, of the higher-paid citizens of the country.  I am not going to lose this opportunity of drawing attention to one of the salient features of the analysis of Doctor Kiernan, which is <Col N="2268" /> printed in the <i>Economic Journal</i> for March of this year.  He shows that the distribution of the national income of the Irish Free State is something like this: Total, £164,500,000; income derived from the occupation of agriculture, whether by farmers or labourers, about £50,000,000; other wages, about £43,000,000; salaries, about £21,000,000; total of these three groups of the population, combining in themselves all the active, creative agencies of the country, £115,000,000, out of £165,000,000.  Rents, interest, profits and income from abroad amount to £49,000,000, or nearly one-third of the total national income.  That is a statement which is well worth thinking over. I should put against it another important fact, that out of that £49,000,000, plus a big proportion of the £21,000,000 paid in salaries, the estimated expenditure of the non-agricultural population in the way of direct taxation is £10,000,000.  I give those figures to the House and to the Minister to think of.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>If we were considering this Bill in anything like normal times, if the depression was what I might describe as &ldquo;natural depression,&rdquo; due to causes over which we had no control, we could look at it from quite a different point of view from that which we must look upon it now.  We have to consider the actual state of affairs in the country.  The depression is not a natural depression.  It has been caused largely, but not altogether, by deliberate action of the Government so far as the agricultural population is concerned.  I am a farmer.  The only thing in which I am really interested in the world is my own farm.  I have nothing else out of which to live.  I can speak from first-hand knowledge. How much is the farmer going to benefit by these cuts?  I do not want to refer to the economic war again but I must briefly refer to what Senator Johnson said just now with regard to the land annuities.  What the farmer has gained by not being asked to pay his land annuities for the last couple of terms is very little compared with what he is losing by being unable to sell his produce.  I know farmers who <Col N="2269" /> have lost from five to ten times the amount of their land annuities and they will not be much impressed by what Senator Johnson has said.  Neither are they impressed by the fall in retail prices.  The prices of a good many commodities have been raised owing to the tariffs.</P>
      <P>We have seen money wasted wholesale. We have seen it thrown about and we can only call that action by its proper name.  A great deal of the taxpayers' money has been thrown to a certain class of people to purchase their support for the Government. There is no other way of saying it. We have, at the moment, the first financial scandal we have had since we got a native Government in the country&mdash;a first-class financial scandal, by which the reputation of this country will sink very low in the eyes of the world.  People are going to be taxed and taxed severely to finance a Party enterprise.</P>
      <P>My view with regard to the farmer is the long view.  I think that the money which will be saved by the cuts will be used to prolong the farmers' agony and to finance the economic war. One cannot look at this matter from the view-point that one would look at it if there were no economic war.  That is impossible.  Senator Dowdall tried yesterday to cover up a good deal of what Senator MacLoughlin had said. He denied that places were being found for Fianna Fáil camp followers and that the money which would be saved by the cuts would go to pay the new Fianna Fáil officials.  I am not going to say whether that is correct or not but, considering the experiences we have had, it is highly likely.  The Minister for Agriculture did not deny in the Dáil that places were being found for Fianna Fáil camp followers.  What he said was that it was quite right they should get them and that they had been a long time waiting for them.  He did not deny that money is being squandered to make jobs for Fianna Fáil camp followers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When the Government came into power, one of their first actions, ostensibly, was to cut their own salaries.  There was a great &ldquo;to-do&rdquo;<Col N="2270" /> about that in the country, but nothing was said about the little accompaniment in the way of relief from income tax.  That was not broadcast to the people.  What the Ministers suffered in cuts in salaries was very small indeed. This is a difficult question for farmers to deal with, because the farmers' means of living has been almost taken from them.  I maintain that.  Every time that I have a chance I will say that that has been done by the deliberate action of the Fianna Fáil Government.  I do not want to see anybody in this country taxed in order to enable the Government to keep the economic war going, because it is ruining the farmers.  Practically speaking, that is what this Bill means, raising money to keep the economic war going.  I will not agree to the proposals in the retrospective clauses.  I think that is simply swindle and robbery.  There are other matters in the Bill to which amendments will be introduced upon which I will have more to say.  These are my views generally.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is difficult to discuss this Bill without referring to the economic war.  I believe the economic war is responsible for the introduction of this Bill, and for the necessity of cuts in salaries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator for or against the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>As we are accused of preventing a settlement, I will try to refrain, for the present, from saying much about the economic war.  I do not agree with Senator Johnson's statement that farmers have suffered very little, when the concessions they got from the Government are taken into account.  At a later stage I will take an opportunity of attempting to refute that statement.  Senator O'Farrell stated that it was not just to take away any man's livelihood.  It is difficult to understand the attitude of Senator O'Farrell and the Labour Party with regard to this Bill.  It is very difficult to understand their squealing and wailing with regard to cuts in salaries, having regard to the attitude they adopted all along, when <Col N="2271" /> the farmers' means of living was being taken away.  They were very acquiescent towards every motion and every Bill that the Government brought forward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Any time we stood up here to plead the farmers' case, and to point out what Senator O'Farrell mentioned to-day, that it was not fair or just to take away any man's livelihood, they turned a very deaf ear to our pleadings.  We hear the Labour Party squealing now when there are proposals&mdash;necessary proposals if the policy of the Government is to be continued&mdash;for cutting salaries and reducing the standard of living all round.  It is very difficult to believe that the Labour Party are genuine in this, judging by the close connection between the Labour Party and the Fianna Fáil Government.  We must only come to the conclusion that they are either deliberately dishonest or painfully stupid.  My own opinion is that the attitude of the Labour Party towards this Bill is a deliberate piece of play-acting. I heard statements made yesterday by Senator O'Farrell and by Senator Comyn, that during the last two elections the dead walls of the country were covered with posters by the teachers' organisation; that teachers had backed up Fianna Fáil but that there were to be no cuts.  The president of the teachers' organisation is a prominent member of the Fianna Fáil Party and it is very difficult to come to any other conclusion, but that on the part of the Labour Party it is play-acting; that they are insincere.  I am not out for a reduction of wages or for cutting salaries.  I do not believe that that policy is going to improve any industry, or is going to lead towards the prosperity of the country. Although I will be compelled to support this Bill, under the present circumstances, I do not believe in it.  I make the suggestion to the Labour Party that if they assist the other Parties in this House, in putting this Government out of office, as soon as a new Government comes into power, <Col N="2272" /> I will do all in my power to cancel the cuts in salaries.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator responsible for all that happened in the last six or seven years under Cumann na nGaedheal?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Is Senator Johnson responsible for all the Labour Party has done?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has assured the House that on certain conditions he will secure that there will be such a change.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I said I would give my own support.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am trying to find out what weight is to be attached to that statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will guarantee it on behalf of the honest farmer representatives in this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>How many are there?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Who are the dishonest ones?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to discuss the economic war.  It has been stated that there is a possibility of settlement and, for that reason, I do not want to say anything which would prejudice matters.  In discussing this Bill the whole concern of the Labour Party, and of others, is for the civil servants and other officials whose salaries are being cut a few shillings a week.  No consideration is given to the higher officials, whose salaries are being cut by £100 or more.  I contend that the men with the bigger salaries are just as worthy of consideration as men with £3 a week.  I want to give an example of the fallacy of a statement made by some member of the Labour Party that no man is worth more than £500 a year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, the Senator stated that some member of the Labour Party made such a statement. None of the Labour representatives here is aware of that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is hardly a point of order.  You got in the point, at any rate, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2273" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the Electricity Supply Board, the Minister's predecessor insisted that one of the officials of that Board should not get a salary higher than £800 a year. We know with what disastrous results the Board tried to carry out the Minister's instructions.  When the Board was reorganised they advertised for a secretary who understood electricity costings.  They advertised in all trade papers connected with the industry, and I am informed the lowest amount demanded by applicants for the post was £2,500 a year.  I have been informed that the Board appointed a German, who was previously in the employment of Siemens Schuckert, and agreed to pay him £1,700 a year, considering it a good bargain to do so.  I mention that owing to the contention that there should be no sympathy for officials with £1,000 a year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it the Shannon scheme we are discussing or the Public Services (Temporary Economies) Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are dealing with the Public Services (Temporary Economies) Bill, but the Senator is developing arguments as to why the cuts are or are not necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>The whole contention is that there should be no sympathy for that class of people.  It would be a disastrous thing if the higher officials were to be victimised to the extent that this Bill proposes to victimise them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRobinson" hpid="Mr. D. Robinson Mr. D. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I remember an occasion, not so very long ago, when Senator Miss Browne was conducting one of those gallant and spirited attacks on the Government which have become such a feature of her debates.  In my opinion, while Senator Miss Browne, if not a magician like Circe, whatever the subject of the debate, hey presto, she can turn it on to the economic war. She told us that she was a practical farmer.  Shamefacedly I admit that up to this I was rather sceptical of the justice of her claim, but the insight she has given us into her ideas of farming has not been encouraging, judging from her inability to grow millable wheat.  She said that rushes followed <Col N="2274" /> tillage, and that tillage ended with seeding.  That was not very encouraging.  However, I realise the justice of her claim to be considered a practical farmer when she stated that the wages paid by practical farmers in Wexford were 15/- a week if a labourer took his meals out, and 7/- or 8/- a week if he took his meals in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>To my knowledge I did not give any such figures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Robinson Mr. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I expected to see at least one member of the Labour Party swoon in his seat at that, but the members of that Party proved themselves to be strong, silent men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Nothing would shock us now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Robinson Mr. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>They may have blanched but, from the position in which I am in the House, I was unable to discern any appreciable alteration in their condition.  People who live in the country and who work there are supposed to be able to have food whenever they like.  They are told that they do not need good clothes, because they have to work in all sorts of weather; they do not need picture-houses or anything of that kind&mdash;such as city dwellers do&mdash;because they are surrounded by such beautiful scenery. They contribute to the revenue of the country by indirect taxation.  They assist out of their 15/- a week, if they take their meals out, and out of their 7/- a week if they take their meals in&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Miss Browne states that she made no such statement. I think the Senator should withdraw.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Robinson Mr. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I absolutely decline. I know that Senator Miss Browne did so, and I am prepared afterwards to produce a copy of the Official Debates, with the Senator's statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot decide the issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that I will be allowed to explain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have some slight recollection of such a statement, but I cannot be positive.  I would ask the <Col N="2275" /> Senator to desist from further reference to 15/- a week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Robinson Mr. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not mention the 15/- or the 7/- again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>These people will be lucky if they get it after a short time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Robinson Mr. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>They make such contributions as are demanded from them, and they assist in paying the salaries of the grades of society which are to be the subject of these cuts.  From the day they receive their first job, to the day they receive the old age pension, they never know when they go to work when they will receive one week's notice, and perhaps they will never get another job in their lifetime.  They spend their whole lives in dread of that happening.  I imagine that the wail that has gone up about salary cuts for people in these very sheltered positions will leave that class of the community, and they are a very large class, very cold indeed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Notwithstanding all the wild statements we have heard in opposition to the Bill and the various inaccuracies of certain Senators, I wish very definitely to support the Bill.  I cannot, for a moment, understand how some people in this House have the nerve to stand up and denounce this Bill as they have done. They are like the man who insisted on having his loaf, eating it and then selling it to somebody else.  Several Senators here have gone time and again to the various Departments looking for grants for this, that and the other thing but when it comes to a question of providing money for the various requirements of the State&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>The <i>Irish Press.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;they are up in arms. Senator Miss Browne interrupts by mentioning the <i>Irish Press</i>&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a requirement of the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>As she has done that, I would like to thank Senator Miss Browne for her contribution to the unsuccessful attack on the <i>Irish Press.</i><Col N="2276" /> Possibly, the fact that the <i>Irish Press</i> has been attacked in this House by Senator Miss Browne and in the other House by various Deputies will do far more good to the <i>Irish Press</i> and to the cause of the <i>Irish Press</i> than could possibly be done by any other attitude taken up by the people responsible for that attack.  However, I am very sorry to hear a good Christian like Senator Miss Browne come out openly here to accuse members of the Government, not alone to accuse members of the Government but to accuse anybody, of daylight robbery and corruption.  The attempt to prove anything of the kind has been absolutely defeated.  It has been absolutely defeated in the Dáil and it will be absolutely defeated anywhere it is tried to be pressed.  The people of this country are not going to be influenced by the tactics of people who have been thrown on the political scrap-heap of this country.  They are not going to be twisted about in their ideals.  They know the policy advocated by the <i>Irish Press</i> and Senator Miss Browne and her kind had better turn their energies in other directions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not go any further on that point, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to.  As I say, Senators want to have their loaf and eat it.  The fact that the Minister, in explaining this Bill, described it as a Temporary Economies Bill should be sufficient to recommend it, at least, to any sensible member of the House. Not alone did he describe it as a Temporary Economies Bill but he went on to explain that it was his hope that in the coming year it would be possible to get back to the former position, though some members are not so optimistic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask a question?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is really not the time to ask questions.  We are listening to a speech on the Second Reading debate.  The Senator can make a speech afterwards, but the Senator who is speaking is not here to be questioned.  That is my feeling in the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2277" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>If the people who are so vigorous in their attack on this particular Bill would instead turn their efforts to bringing about that condition of things in this country which the Minister and most of us expect to see, they would be doing far more good for the country and far more good for themselves.  I support the Bill because I believe it is an attempt to make money available for the needy people of this country.  Some people who are denouncing this Bill seem to imagine that there is an unlimited amount of money at the disposal of the Minister for Finance.  Of course, we all know that such is not the case.  We know that, so far at least, we have no gold mines in operation.  I believe there is a gold mine down in Senator Miss Browne's county or in County Wicklow but in any case it is not at present in operation.  We all know that economy is necessary at the present stage.  Of course, Senator Counihan, Senator Miss Browne and other Senators insist on dragging in the economic war.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>You cannot get away from it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>You cannot indeed. They insist that it was because of the alleged action of the Fianna Fáil Government that the present economies were made necessary.  I do not want to go into that subject.  I do not want to point out again who are the people responsible for this economic war.  The speeches made in opposition to this Bill and the speeches made on every occasion that the economic war was dragged into this arena, smacked of an insincerity which would convince anybody that even the people attacking the Government on that question knew very well that the Fianna Fáil Government were not responsible for the economic war.  I would appeal to them even at this eleventh hour to sever their connection with the common enemy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I resent that.  It is a most insulting expression.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no connection between the critics of the Government and the common enemy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2278" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>Examine your conscience.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>My conscience will stand quite as close a scrutiny as that of any member on the Government Benches.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacEllin" hpid="Mr. MacEllin Mr. MacEllin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEllin</NameTxt>
      <P>It must be very elastic then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I say the statement is a lie and it should be withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot allow anybody to be called a liar.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I take the attack on me by Senator Milroy as a compliment.  I am afraid that Senator Milroy and his Party, whatever that Party is, will have a terrible time convincing posterity as to the truth of his statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall not be here then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I was amazed to hear Senator Dowdall say that he was amused at the statements made by Senator MacLoughlin.  Perhaps every man to his taste, but I certainly could not be amused by the sort of cheap flamboyant language that is used on every occasion by Senator MacLoughlin in this House.  Perhaps it will make good fodder, good dry feed, if you like, for the Senator's newspaper, on which I presume it was printed before the Senator had finished his speech in this House.  However, that is his own affair, and it is a proof of his efficiency. He said, amongst other wild statements, that Fianna Fáil floated into power on promises.  Before the last election there may have been some excuse for a man making a statement such as that, but if Senator MacLoughlin suggests that the Fianna Fáil Government floated into power at the last election, then I say they floated into power, not on promises, but because they had delivered the goods. Senator Milroy knows that even though he lies back to laugh in his easy chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>They delivered the economic war, carriage forward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Milroy joins with the other warriors in dragging in the economic war.  He accuses Fianna <Col N="2279" /> Fáil of plunging this country into the economic war.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>That is their only achievement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>A noble achievement, the Senator says.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I said it is their only achievement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator was not here when they were achieving a good many things.  Now that he has come back it is regrettable that he should have taken the wrong side when there is a war on in this country.  Senator Milroy went on to point out the extravagance of the Government in their various Departments.  He pointed out that there has been no decrease in the membership of the Civic Guards or the membership of the Army.  Does Senator Milroy suggest that the Guards should be disbanded indiscriminately?  That kind of propaganda was used&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>By Fianna Fáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>By the Opposition, before the last election or, at least, before the second last election.  Does Senator Milroy suggest now that that should be done?  Senator Milroy knows perfectly well that such was never the intention of the Fianna Fáil Government.  He knows perfectly well that one of the reasons why there cannot be that reduction in the membership of the Civic Guard is that certain members of his Party demand protection, which I claim is not necessary.  He knows very well that heavy guards are even now, under the peaceful conditions existing in this country, being provided for certain members of the late Administration. Does he propose to withdraw these guards?  If he does, I think he should have a talk with the people who are accepting the guards and perhaps some little economy could be brought about in that direction.  Perhaps then the Guards can devote their time to some sort of useful work besides protecting people who have nothing to fear except the contempt of the Irish <Col N="2280" /> people.  Perhaps some of them may be afraid of ghosts but they do not need any bodyguard to protect them from the dead.  Senator Wilson may perhaps get credit for making an amusing speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not what the Senator is doing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not finished yet. Do not always be a pessimist.  He went over all the old proverbs but, to my mind, he forgot the only one that really applied in this case, and that is &ldquo;A stitch in time saves nine.&rdquo;  I will make him a present of that one. As I said before, I am perfectly convinced that many of the speeches in opposition were made by men who were not sincere in their statements. It was pathetic, for instance, to hear people making statements on behalf of the distressed medical practitioners in this country.  While I admire the work done by certain members of the medical profession in this country, in fact by most of them, I certainly will shed no tears for the little remuneration which will be lost by them under this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It has been put up as an argument that many of them gave their services free to the poor.  Why should they not give their services free to the poor? It is only right and proper that a medical practitioner, who has the advantage of being able to collect considerable fees from people possessed of riches, people who, perhaps, would not value the professional advice or attendance of these practitioners if they did not charge them a good fee, should get the opportunity of doling out some charity if you like in the way of attendance to people who are not blessed with the riches of this world. But, worse than all, capital has been made out of the fact that the teachers are coming under this cut.  I, perhaps, have as much sympathy with the teachers as a body as most people in this House but I must say that I resent very much the statements made here that the teachers as a body backed the Fianna Fáil Government because of the monetary advantage they expected to gain for that support.  I think it is <Col N="2281" /> a terrible state of affairs that such a suggestion should be made against any responsible body in the community. Several people made it.  I agree with the suggestion that a good many of the teachers backed Fianna Fáil in the elections, but I insist that they backed Fianna Fáil because their national outlook was right and because they believed in the policy of Fianna Fáil.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;Vote Fianna Fáil and save the cuts.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>They backed Fianna Fáil during the last two elections and, despite all the propaganda of the Opposition here, they would back Fianna Fáil again if there were an election in the morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>Not this time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>It is bad enough when, time and again, I have had to stand up in this House to defend the real farmers from the farmers' representatives here.  I daresay that Senator Counihan included me in what he described as the dishonest farmers.  All the honest farmers were in his Party so that all the dishonest farmers must be on the other side.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>There are no farmers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I repudiate that statement. I am a farmer, anyhow, even if Senator Miss Browne was not able to make any defence as a farmer.  However, at any time that the farmers as a body are being attacked in this House or anywhere else, I hope that I will rise to the occasion and defend them.  As I say, I am perfectly convinced that the various insinuations and suggestions made in relation to the teachers are unjustifiable and I am convinced that the teachers voted Fianna Fáil because they were too intelligent to be on the side of Cumann na nGaedheal.  They voted Fianna Fáil because they believed that the policy of Fianna Fáil was the proper policy for the people of this country as a whole and I am sure they would vote <Col N="2282" /> Fianna Fáil again if we had an election to-morrow morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to me that the principle of this Bill was touched upon only in two speeches&mdash;the speech of Senator Johnson and the speech of Senator Douglas.  Senator Johnson asked us by what test is this Bill to be judged.  It is to be judged by this simple test: that the interests of the Exchequer require that certain moneys should be provided, either by way of economies or by way of taxation, and the Government has decided that, in order to avoid imposing additional taxation on any section of the community, the balance is to be sought by way of economy.  I should like to emphasise that because it seemed to me that Senator Johnson thought that the Bill carried with it the implication of a certain social policy.  There is no social policy expressed in this Bill beyond the simple one that it is not considered socially desirable to impose additional taxation upon any section of the community in present circumstances.  The Senator has endeavoured to associate, I think, with Part III of the Bill, the policy of levelling down and his reason for that is that any economies which may be secured under this section will not immediately and directly inure to the benefit of the Exchequer.  Every one of them, however, will indirectly inure to it. There are certain official undertakings whose administrators enjoy a considerable autonomy, but in respect of which the State has had to assume certain financial obligations, obligations either to provide the interest on their capital, as in the case, say, of the Agricultural Credit Corporation, or obligations to ensure that because they do provide a widespread public service, as in the case of the Electricity Supply Board, the extension of this service and its adequate provision will not be hampered by lack of capital.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In circumstances like the present, it is quite possible that the Agricultural Credit Corporation might have to call on the State to meet interest charges <Col N="2283" /> on bonds circulated by us, and the State might be called on to fulfil guarantees given in relation to certain issues of that Corporation.  I do not wish it to be understood that that is a probability, but, at any rate, it is a contingent liability which this State might, at some time, have to face, and, against it, the State should take whatever steps it can, in time, to secure itself for this year or any other year in which circumstances might be the same as they are at present.  One of the ways by which the State can secure itself is to ensure that there will be a reduction in the internal expenditure of that or any similar undertaking which bears the same relation to the State, and it is because we must take care that the liabilities which we have foreseen and have provided for, and the deficiency, the extent of which we now know, should not increase in any way as a result of this Budget, that steps to secure that reduction in internal expenditure to which I have referred must be taken in this Bill.  In the same way, if the existing income of the Electricity Supply Board does not permit it to fulfil its obligations under statute to the State, in respect of repayment of its borrowings from the State, and if, as a result of the experience of the last two years, we are satisfied that it is not practicable to increase the price of electricity to consumers, then we must ask the Electricity Supply Board, or any organisation in a similar position, once again to reduce its internal expenditure in such a way as will enable it to meet its obligations to the source from which it has secured its finances, and it is for these reasons, and for these reasons only, and not because the Government has adopted as a principle the reduction of salaries or remuneration, that corporations and bodies of the kind to which I have referred are brought within the ambit of this Bill.</P>
    <P>The next question of principle that arises is that which was raised by Senator Douglas&mdash;if economies are to be made, is this the direction in which they should first be sought?  Senator <Col N="2284" /> Douglas said that, if he were in a position to determine the course of the Government in a matter of this kind, he would seek other economies first and cuts last.  I think Senator Wilson answered Senator Douglas in that respect with compelling force and very cogent argument.  Where are the other economies that I could make?  Am I to seek a reduction in the expenditure made for the promotion of agricultural interests in this country, to restrict the activities of the Department of Industry and Commerce, to reduce the old age pensions and curtail the grant for education?  Before I could pursue the policy which Senator Douglas suggests that I ought to have pursued, I should, first of all, have to assure myself that there is in respect of every one of these items a considerable amount of wasteful expenditure at present.  During the past year we have made every attempt to reduce the Estimates from these Departments.  We have refused, in regard to most of them, to sanction an enlargement of Departmental activities even in a way in which those who are most concerned with the efficiency of the Departments and with fulfilling the object for which they were first established have represented to us as being vital and necessary, because we were anxious to secure that there would not be one penny piece of expenditure incurred in this year that could be wisely dispensed with.</P>
    <P>I have to ask the Seanad to take that as an assurance given by me as the one that represents the exact position. Economies could not be made in any other way, and at the same time maintain our present services.  Accordingly, we are thrown back on this, the only way in which at the present moment economies could be secured.  I know that those who take the point of view of Senator Douglas in this matter take it because it has been represented to them that a Bill of this nature will ultimately represent a decrease in the purchasing power of certain sections of the community.  I cannot conceive that there are any other economies that we could make that would not result in a <Col N="2285" /> reduction of the purchasing power of a much greater number of people: a greater reduction in the absolute purchasing power of the community as a whole.  All those who are in receipt of salaries affected by this Bill are in receipt of salaries that do allow for some margin, in many cases a considerable margin, above the mere subsistence level.  Therefore, because of the extent of this margin they are not compelled to expend their remuneration to the last penny piece.  Many of them are able to make savings, in some cases considerable savings, for which at the present moment there, possibly, is not an attractive or legitimate opening for investment.</P>
    <P>In the case, however, of some other people who might be affected if we were to seek economies in other directions: for instance, in the case, say, of those who are in receipt of old age pensions, the pension which they draw from the State is one which barely enables them to exist at the mere subsistence level.  Its size is such that they have to spend every penny piece of it.  That does represent real purchasing power inasmuch as there is no purchasing power lying fallow, so far as they are concerned.  If, therefore, we were to seek economies in that way it must be clear to every one of us that there would be, as I have said, a much greater reduction in the purchasing power of the community as a whole than there is, if there is any reduction at all, when we seek it in this way.</P>
    <P>Now as to whether a proposal to reduce the salaries and wages of public servants must necessarily result in a reduction of the purchasing power of the community as a whole, I should like to say that it seems to me that is a contention that cannot be borne out, because these moneys are provided out of taxation.  If we are not going to seek to balance our Budget by a measure of this kind, then we have got to balance it by imposing additional taxation. That taxation in the present circumstances of the time would, I am afraid, have to belong to that category which is generally referred to as indirect <Col N="2286" /> taxation: a tax upon expenditure which would necessarily result in an increase in prices and, once again, we would have on the part of that section of the community, the very large section to which Senator Johnson has referred which lives upon a mere subsistence level, a considerable reduction in purchasing power which would necessarily eventuate in a very considerable reduction in production in this country and, eventually and ultimately, result in a general decline in the purchasing power of the community as a whole.  But we do not propose to follow that course.  We propose instead to allow this £270,000 in the pockets of the general taxpayer to remain there: to constitute for them real purchasing power, to enable them, and the poorer classes particularly, to take advantage of the general fall in prices, and to increase the standard of living of the general mass of the people as a whole, and, by doing that, increasing their purchasing power and increasing production in this country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Now I think the fact that that will be the effect of this Bill must be, in the general circumstances of the time, the strongest argument that I could put forward on its behalf here in the Seanad or in the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister should not forget that the Finance Bill is coming on, and that these arguments may be used against him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Possibly; but, however, when they are used we will be able to deal with them also.  Now there were a number of other matters dealt with in the course of this debate which, in my opinion, might be more properly reserved for the Committee Stage of the Bill.  I do not know whether I should occupy the time of <Col N="2287" /> the Seanad in dealing with them at any length now.  But there are one or two things, I think, that I cannot allow to pass without comment.  One of these, in particular, was the speech of Senator O'Farrell, the main burden of whose statement was that some people had received the desert which they merited because they had placed faith in the word of a professional politician.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of explanation. I did not say that.  I said that members of the Opposition might say the teachers deserved what they got, but that there was a far more important question than that involved. I did not say what the Minister has just stated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad the Senator is not prepared to stand over the innuendo which a statement of that sort would convey to me or convey, I think, to people as a whole.  It is not necessary for me, as he has explained it away, to deal with that further.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no explanation at all.  The Minister is simply setting up a straw man.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Except to say this: that no section amongst those who are affected by this Bill had less reason to misunderstand the real position than the national teachers.  It is true that on the morning of the general election, 1932, a statement was issued which was made to cover them but, as Senator Cummins has informed the Seanad, in June, 1932, I met the teachers.  I told them that, in view of the financial position in which the State found itself, the pledges of 1932 could not be fulfilled in the manner in which we had hoped to carry them out: that, in fact, it would be necessary for us, in the changed circumstances, to ask the teachers to do for the new Government what they had <Col N="2288" /> been prepared to do for the old.  I would remind the Seanad that in December, 1931, an agreement was reached between Mr. Cosgrave's Government and the Irish National Teachers' Organisation to accept an additional cut of 6 per cent. in salary, making, in the words of the agreement, &ldquo;with the then existing 4 per cent. contribution, a total reduction in pensionable salary of 10 per cent.&rdquo; That agreement was reached in December, 1931, and was duly ratified by a vote of two to one at a delegate conference, the body which Senator O'Farrell has rightly described as being the Parliament of the teachers. The proposals which I then submitted&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamCummins" hpid="Mr. Cummins Mr. Cummins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of explanation.  The Minister has stated that it meant a total reduction of 10 per cent.: that it is in the draft.  The 4 per cent. that he refers to had always been paid by the national teachers, so that the additional reduction was a reduction of 6 per cent. and not 10 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am using the words of the agreement: &ldquo;making a total reduction of 10 per cent. in pensionable salary.&rdquo;  However, as I was explaining, in June, 1932, it was necessary for us to reopen the position.  I met the teachers and I put certain proposals before them which represented at that time the absolute limit of concession, a limit that will never again be reached so long as I have any responsibility for the national finances.  Those proposals, as Senator Cummins and officers of the National Teachers' Organisation have admitted, were very much more favourable than those that had been accepted by the organisation in December, 1931, and yet, notwithstanding the greater needs of the State and of the country, they were rejected by the National Teachers' Organisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The first point that does emerge is this: that when the general election of 1933 came round the national teachers of this country, as a whole, had every reason to believe that it would be necessary to make some deduction from <Col N="2289" /> their salaries: every reason to believe that they could not close their eyes and shut out from recollection what had happened in June of 1932.  They knew that the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Education had both informed them that the stringency of the financial position was such that they would have to undertake sacrifices in common with every other person paid out of the public purse.</P>
    <P>Armed with that knowledge, they approached the President and other people and they endeavoured to get from them an undertaking that the pledge given in 1932 would stand. They failed&mdash;utterly failed&mdash;to get that pledge.  The President, in fact, said he was not prepared to give any pledge or undertaking without special consideration, and consultation with the Minister for Finance.  That statement was made and published by the National Teachers' Organisation on the morning of the General Election of 1933 so that, so far as this year is concerned, there cannot be any question of broken pledges.  The national teachers were well aware of our policy and of what we would be compelled to do with regard to them in 1933 and, therefore, there cannot be any substance in the charges levelled against the President or myself or any member of the Executive Council of breaking pledges or breaking promises.</P>
    <P>As to the Gárda Síochána, Senator Staines mentioned that he had been responsible for putting the Desborough scales in force.  If so, he must quite clearly recall that the Desborough scale itself was based on a cost-of-living figure and made provision for reduction in remuneration when the cost of living fell.  On this point, I should like to refer to a statement made by the then Minister for Justice, now Deputy Fitzgerald-Kenney, in the debate on the Gárda Síochána. Allowances Order, 1929, on the 8th May, 1929.  On that occasion, the then Minister for Justice said (Official Report, vol. 29, cols. 1660-1):&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I have before me the memorandum which accompanied the penultimate order.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2290" /> That was the order fixing the present Gárda Síochána scales&mdash;and it is this&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;It is not proposed that the rates of pay to the force should be subject to variation to meet trifling or temporary fluctuations in the cost of living and the rates now proposed are based on a cost of living of 85 above pre-war and are intended to be applicable while the cost-of-living figure varies from 70 at the lower limit to 100 at the higher limit above pre-war.  These figures will, accordingly, be subject to adjustment if the cost-of-living figure passes outside that range.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Mr. Blythe, who was then Minister for Finance, said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Obviously, if something occurred which caused the cost-of-living figure to go down 35 or 30 points, a new situation would be created and the value of pay on the present scales would be very considerably increased.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There is there quite clearly the intention to relate in some measure the pay of the Gárda Síochána to the cost-of-living figure.  Since 1925, the cost-of-living figure has fallen by 25 or 30 points.  The cost of living figure at present is 50 points above pre-war days.  Accordingly, on the basis of the agreement I referred to on which the members of the Gárda Síochána joined the force, their pay would naturally fall for revision. There, again, there has been no attempt to break the pledges and no attempt in any way to deal unfairly with these men or go outside the contracts or engagements entered into with them.</P>
    <P>Senator Johnson asked why this new form of super-tax should be made apply to one small section only.  I think that Senator Johnson supplied the answer to that question himself in the reference which he made to the very interesting statistical facts, and deductions from those facts, which Dr. Kiernan recently laid before the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society of Ireland.  One <Col N="2291" /> thing is quite clear from that paper and the statistics on which it was based.  That is, that the money value of the incomes of the primary producers of this country has considerably decreased.  That is not to say that the real value of those incomes, as represented by purchasable commodities, has decreased.  The money value has, however, decreased.  On the other hand, the real value of the incomes of those who derive their remuneration from the State has, if not actually increased, at the very worst, remained constant.  Therefore, the real value of that income as represented by its purchasable power over commodities has considerably increased also&mdash;increased, I think, in greater <Col N="2292" /> measure that the real incomes of the population as a whole.  When these scales of pay were first laid down, I think the presumption underlying all of them was that there must be a certain relation between the pay of the public servants and the standard of living of those who are their paymasters&mdash;the general public.  One of the reasons why this Bill is applied to that small section and that we do not proceed by way of super&mdash;tax is to preserve the basis upon which these scales were originally devised&mdash;to preserve that relation between the salary, remuneration or standard of living of the general public and that of that small section which constitute the public services.</P>
    <P>Question put.</P>
    <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided:&mdash;Tá, 15; Níl, 5.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Brown, Samuel L., K.C.<br />Costello, Mrs.<br />Counihan, John C.<br />Dowdall, J.C.<br />Guinness, Henry S.<br />Keane, Sir John.<br />MacEllin, Seán E.<br />Moore, Colonel.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Moran, James.<br />O'Rourke, Brian.<br />Parkinson, James J.<br />Quirke, William.<br />Robinson, David L.<br />Robinson, Séumas.<br />Wilson, Richard.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Cummins, William.<br />Farren, Thomas.<br />Foran, Thomas.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">O'Farrell, John T.<br />Staines, Michael.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers:&mdash;Tá: Senators S. Robinson and Quirke; Níl: Senators Farren and O'Farrell.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage fixed for Thursday.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It would suit the convenience of the Minister for Finance if he would take his opening statement on the Finance Bill now, and then adjourn the Second Reading debate until next week&mdash;say, Thursday.  Is that agreed?</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Finance Bill, 1933&mdash;Second" RHead="Stage (Certified Money Bill)">
    <Title>Finance Bill, 1933&mdash;Second Stage (Certified Money Bill).</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee) Seán MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>The basis of the Bill is, of course, the White Paper giving the Estimates of Receipts and Expenditure which was circulated on 9th May last.  According to the figures the total expenditure on Central Fund and Supply Services was estimated at £30,654,220, of which £4,729,269 was for Central Fund services, and £25,924,951 for Supply. The figure for the Supply Services includes items totalling £3,379,800 which do not appear in the Estimates prepared for 1932-33 by the outgoing Government.  These items were: for the Old Age Pensions Act of 1932, £479,800, representing an increase over the original Estimate for old age pensions for 1932-33 of that amount. <Col N="2293" /> Housing grants represent an increase over the original provision for 1932-33 in Vote 41 of £360,000; milk for necessitous children, £100,000; loans for housing purposes which, again, were increased over the original provision for 1932-33 by £1,340,000; the Land Bill, 1933, £150,000; to meet the deficiency in respect to Land Bond Fund payments resulting from the decrease in the annuities from the moratorium granted last year and this year, £800,000; and additional provisions for damage to property compensation, £150,000.</P>
      <P>In the figure for the Supply Services there was also included £2,450,000 for the payment of export bounties and subsidies.  In the Estimate for Central Fund expenditure there was included £320,000 to cover the interest and sinking fund charges on a new loan which, it is anticipated, we shall have to float this year.  The increase in this figure was offset to some extent by savings on Exchequer Bills, which, including the £1,000,000 issued by our predecessors, were all redeemed at the close of the financial year.</P>
      <P>In addition to the items to which I have just referred, however, there are other features of the Government's policy for which provision had to be made.  To deal with the unemployment situation as it found it, the Government, on first taking office last year, had to adopt emergency measures and to provide, out of abnormal sources of revenue, considerable sums for unemployment relief.  Since then the Government has come to the conclusion that it will be necessary to introduce a measure to deal with the problem of maintenance for the unemployed this year.  The new scheme, it is hoped, will go far to relieve the local authorities of the burden of providing assistance for the unemployed.  In order to initiate it the sum of about £450,000 net will be required, and for this provision has had to be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In addition to this provision, it is to be noted that in the Estimates to which I have referred, particularly in Votes 8, 41 and 54, generous assistance amounting in all to £2,806,000, is being provided <Col N="2294" /> by way of grants and loans to encourage and finance constructive expenditure, and so to provide employment, as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Out of the Local Loans Fund:&mdash;</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="35*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">For Arterial Drainage Loans</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">£40,000</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>,, Public Health Loans</entry>
            <entry>200,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>,, Housing of Working Classes Loans</entry>
            <entry>£1,000,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>,, Loans under Labourers (Ireland) Acts</entry>
            <entry>500,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>,, Loans under Small Dwellings Acquisition (Ireland) Acts</entry>
            <entry>200,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>,, Loans under Gaeltacht Housing Acts</entry>
            <entry>40,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>,, Loans under Vocational Education Act</entry>
            <entry>30,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>,, Loans for Minor Works</entry>
            <entry>13,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>,, Loans sanctioned but not provided last year for works, mainly housing, to be executed this year</entry>
            <entry>318,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>,, Contingencies</entry>
            <entry>13,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Out of Vote 41.  For Grants for Housing Purposes</entry>
            <entry>370,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Out of Vote 54.  For Grants for Housing purposes in the Gaeltacht</entry>
            <entry>82,000</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>While it is anticipated that the amount provided for free grants for housing purposes will render effective for their purpose the loans for housing, it is considered that some further assistance may be required to stimulate the local authorities to proceed with public health works.  Accordingly, in addition to the sum of £150,000 for unemployment relief which already appears in the Estimates a further £250,000 will be provided making £400,000 for public health and relief works generally.</P>
    <P>Then there is the peat scheme.  The sum of £100,000 has been devoted for the drainage of bogs, the construction of bog roads and minor works of a like character or ancillary thereto.  The sum of £50,000 has also been set aside for the organisation and development of the peat industry, with the special objects of securing improvements in the method of winning, marketing and utilising turf.  The total amount thus to be provided for the initiation and <Col N="2295" /> encouragement of works to give employment, apart altogether from the housing grants of £452,000 and the loans for various purposes amounting to £2,354,000, already referred to, is £550,000.  In addition to the foregoing provisions, the Dáil has granted the sum of £25,000 in order to provide native fuel for necessitous homes in districts where such fuel is not usually available.</P>
    <P>The complete programme of expenditure on Central Fund and Supply Services, therefore, amounts to £31,529,220, £4,729,269 being for Central Fund Services and £26,799,951 for Supply.  As against this expenditure the total revenue for the year from tax and non-tax sources was not expected to be more than £26,440,000, representing decreases of £1,732,000 and £1,818,935 in tax and non-tax revenue, respectively. As regards non-tax revenue, the decrease is anticipated to occur almost entirely among the miscellaneous items, and in that category is more than accounted for by a decline from £2,969,000 to £800,000 in the receipt from pre-Treaty land annuities.</P>
    <P>As regards tax revenue, the principal decrease in the Estimate as compared with last year is on the Customs side, and this is almost entirely due to the increasing protection and increasing employment afforded by the new duties which were imposed for that purpose last year.  Nevertheless, as I have said, it has been estimated that the total revenue for the year will not exceed £26,440,000, which amount is to be set against the prospective expenditure of £31,529,220, leaving £5,089,220 to be found.  I feel safe in allowing for over-estimation on the Supply Services a sum approximately equivalent to 1½ per cent. on the figure of £25,924,951, at which those services stand on the White Paper.  The expenditure side of the account is thus reduced by £388,220 to £31,141,000.</P>
    <P>As I have already pointed out, among the additional services for which provision is covered is the sum of £800,000 to meet a deficiency which arises in the Land Bond Fund, by reason of the moratorium which has <Col N="2296" /> been granted in respect of the May-June gales of this year, and the permanent reduction in the land annuities. Of this amount £226,000 arises from the reduction in the annuities. It is a deficiency which henceforward will recur yearly.  It must be met, therefore, out of revenue.  The remainder, however, is a capital liability which is wiped out by taking an equivalent amount from last year's surplus but leaving a surplus still remaining of £607,000 which is appropriated in the following manner.</P>
    <P>Last year a sum of £550,000 which for many years has represented the normal contribution to the Local Loans Fund, was provided out of nonrecurring revenue.  The same course was followed this year, and a similar amount to last year is provided out of the balance of the surplus.  The provision of the two sums of £534,000 and £550,000 respectively, virtually absorbed the surplus and left us with £57,000 which we have appropriated for the general purposes of the Budget, leaving a further £3,560,000 to be found.  I have already informed the Seanad that there is being provided this year £2,450,000 for export bounties and subsidies.  Against this expenditure, however, certain assets have been created and on the security of these assets it has been decided to borrow £1,225,000 and to use it to defray one half of the cost of the subsidies.  There is still a balance remaining, but included in this balance there is an outlay which is to be made for &ldquo;services unusual in their magnitude and generally unusual also in their character.&rdquo;  Outlay of this nature may properly be defrayed by borrowing. In this year's Estimates the items of this kind which have to be provided for are:&mdash;(1) the provision, amounting to £256,000, required to provide compensation for damage to property and property losses and for the completion of the repayment of the Dáil Eireann (Internal) Loan; (2) £1,600,000 required for loans to local authorities mainly in connection with housing schemes, and (3) £85,000 required for the completion of the Barrow drainage scheme.  These <Col N="2297" /> amount to £1,941,000, and after deducting them and the other items to which I have already referred, there remains £394,000 still to be found.</P>
    <P>As I have already indicated to the Seanad, in connection with the Public Services (Temporary Economies) Bill, it is the desire of the Executive Council to avoid imposing additional taxation. Accordingly when it became clear that unless firm and definite steps were taken to reduce expenditure in the public services, it would be necessary for us to increase taxation heavily or, failing that, to reduce the expenditure on social services drastically&mdash;alternatives which in present circumstances are equally unthinkable&mdash;the Public Services (Temporary Economies) Bill was introduced.  As a result of the passage of that measure, which, I trust in the circumstances as I have recited them, will not be longer delayed, we hope to be in a position, after allowing for loss of income tax as a result of that measure, to reduce expenditure during the present year by a net figure of £270,000.  We are still left with a gap between revenue and expenditure of £124,000.  To provide this £124,000 a tariff has been imposed on apples, pears, plums, cherries, strawberries, raspberries, currants and gooseberries. Our proposals in this regard, however, envisage a general licensing system during the seasons in which homegrown fruit will not be available. Therefore, the tariff is expected to bring us in only about £25,000.  Further proposals by the Minister for Industry and Commerce for protection for a number of articles which are duly set forth in the Schedule to the Bill, together with an expectancy of revenue from cement, in accordance with the general principle of the Cement Bill now before the Oireachtas, and the proceeds of a tariff of two-fifths of a penny on daily newspapers imported into the Saorstát, will bring in a revenue, it is hoped, of £115,000, leaving us with a balance at the close of the current financial year of £16,000.</P>
    <P>These proposals, as I have said, form the basis of the Bill now before the House.  In addition, however, to the <Col N="2298" /> provisions necessary to give effect to these Budgetary decisions, the Bill proposes to make certain changes in the law relating to the collection and administration of the revenue.  I propose to explain these changes briefly at this stage, on the presumption that if the Seanad desires to discuss them in detail an opportunity for that discussion will arise on the Committee Stage.  By far the greater part of the new proposals relates to the general administration of the customs and excise laws and will be found in Part II of the Bill, Sections 14 to 16, Sections 19 to 28 and Sections 32, 33 and 35 inclusive.  The remaining innovations will be found in other parts of the Bill.  Of these, Sections 2 and 3, which are in Part I, relate to income tax and surtax, and Sections 36 to 39, which are in Part III, relate to excess profits duty, while Sections 42 and 43, which relate to stamp duty, will be found in Part IV, and Section 44, relating to the general provisions of the measure, in Part V.</P>
    <P>Section 2 proposes to grant relief in certain double taxation cases and the necessity for it arises in the following way.  Persons resident in Great Britain and also resident in Saorstát Eireann are entitled to a measure of double taxation relief under the provisions of the First Schedule of the Finance Act, 1928, the underlying intention being to relieve such persons completely of the tax of one of the countries, the cost of such relief being borne between the two Exchequers. Owing to differences in the method of assessment of the two countries, it occasionally happens that the existing legal provisions do not enable complete double taxation relief to be granted.  If this occurs in the case of a wealthy Englishman, it tends to operate to induce him to give up his residence in this country.  The result might be that there would be serious loss to the Saorstát Exchequer, in addition to a certain economic loss to the country as a whole.  The section is therefore designed to give the Revenue Commissioners discretionary power to grant further relief in such cases and to see that persons whose <Col N="2299" /> main place of residence and main centre of life are in England are not mulcted through taxation for maintaining a residence in the Free State.</P>
    <P>Section 3 is consequential on the provisions of the Public Service (Temporary Economies) Bill, and is designed to enable the income tax assessment on State employees for the year 1933-34 to be adjusted by reference to the reductions imposed by the Economies Bill.  Section 14 of the Bill provides for the importation, free of duty, of trophies and cups, bowls and shields or articles of a similar type which Saorstát competitors have secured in contest outside Saorstát Eireann.  Section 15 is occasioned by the operation of the Agricultural Produce (Cereals) Act, 1933, under which many articles are prohibited to be imported, except under licence from the Minister for Agriculture or the Minister for Industry and Commerce. The duty on most of the articles is removed by a new section, and where such is not the case the intention is to exempt the article still dutiable and which the Minister will decide to admit under licence.</P>
    <P>Section 16 provides for a drawback on the exportation of blended tea.  It appears that an export trade is springing up in this blended tea in the Saorstát.  Hitherto the blend had to be performed in bond to secure the benefit of the drawback.  The new provision will enable this operation to be carried out on private premises. Of course that concession is secured by a number of very stringent safeguards which would protect the revenue. Section 18 makes provision for charging an annual excise duty of £15 upon moneylenders' licences.  As possibly the Seanad may be aware, the Minister for Justice yesterday introduced, as a Government measure, a Bill to license moneylenders, and Section 18 is the consequential provision in the finance law following upon that.</P>
    <P>Section 19 of the Bill proposes to grant certain exemptions from entertainments duty.  Section 20 grants a reduction of five guineas in the licence <Col N="2300" /> duty imposed upon rectifiers or compounders of spirits.  Section 21 arises out of the position created by the imposition of the Emergency Duties Order No. 5, which provided amongst other things for the removal, as on and from the 24th December, 1932, of the 20 per cent. <i>ad valorem</i> emergency duty payable on imported motor cars and parts thereof, and the admission, from the same date, of non-British motor cars and parts at the preferential in lieu of the full rate.  As a result of this concession traders found themselves with motor cars on hands which had borne the emergency duty or the full, as distinct from the preferential duty.  The position was that they could secure a refund of the difference between the full and the preferential rate by exporting and re-importing any cars affected, but they could not obtain relief from the emergency duty, because the emergency order imposing the duty made no provision for drawback on exportation.  In these circumstances the traders asked that they should be relieved of the necessity of exporting cars, and also to be refunded without incurring trouble or expense, the amount of the emergency duty paid on unsold cars in stock.  It has been decided to grant this concession, and Section 21 gives effect to that decision. This section also contains a provision affecting all classes of goods in respect of which licences to import free of duty may be issued.  In many cases licences were not issued immediately on application, because the merits of the case had to be explored.  Importers, being unable to wait upon the decision, paid the duty and took delivery of their goods, and subsequently the issue of a licence was recommended by the Department of Industry and Commerce or the Department of Agriculture, as the case might be.</P>
    <P>It was found that the refund and the issue of a licence was not strictly legal and paragraph (b) of the section is intended to regularise the matter and to cover any refunds which may have been made.  Section 22 is similar in scope to Section 21.  Section 23 provides for relief from conditions on payment of duty.  It was found that importers who were granted a licence <Col N="2301" /> to import goods, free of duty, under licence, for use which was deemed to qualify for such free licence importation, sometimes wished to utilise the goods, or portion of them, for some other purpose and to pay the duty. The provision is introduced to cover such cases.  Section 24 makes general provisions for a drawback and Section 25 relates to the re-importation of goods.  This section is a general one for this and for future acts and it is intended to make provisions known as the &ldquo;re-importation provisions&rdquo; which hitherto have enabled a home-made article, or articles on which duty has once been paid, to be exported and re-imported without further payment provided no drawback was paid on exportation.  Section 26 continues that provision in respect of certain articles as does Section 27.</P>
    <P>Section 28 provides for the repayment of duty on return or destruction. It is intended to provide limited powers of relief in certain cases of which the first is the case in which articles are found, on importation, to have been damaged in transit or not to be in accordance with the order, the second being that in which articles are destroyed in the Free State without having been used for some such cause as having become obsolete.  Section 29 and Section 30 deal with the modification of the tariffs, all of which are set forth in the Schedules to the Bill. Section 31, I might say, repeals the duties on oats, oatmeal, maize, wheat-meal, wheat flour and bread, which were imposed under the statutes enumerated in the Schedule.  These articles are now prohibited to be imported except under licence and, where a licence is issued, it is desired to free the goods of duty.  Duties on similar classes of goods were enforced by Emergency Orders and these have also been withdrawn.  Section 32 gives the Revenue Commissioners power to determine the category or class to which an article belongs.  It has been found that, owing to the increased complexity of the customs laws, there has been certain overlapping of tariffs at many points and doubt sometimes arises as to the <Col N="2302" /> heading under which an article is liable for duty.  Furthermore cases have arisen where an article, not specifically designated as free, falls accidentally within the ambit of a general dutiable class.  Under this section, it is proposed to give the Revenue Commissioners discretion in such cases and power to determine the heading under which the charge on an article, if any, should be raised.</P>
    <P>Section 34 gives the Revenue Commissioners power to determine the value of dutiable articles and goods. Section 35 is a penalty section in respect of breach of the regulations or conditions.  Sections 36 to 39 are intended to strengthen the law relating to excess profits duties.  Section 36 is a section to remove doubts and to confirm that the law is as it has hitherto been acted upon.  Section 37 gives statutory effect to the decision, given in the House of Lords, so far back as 1922, and which has hitherto been acted upon by the Revenue Commissioners in this country and Great Britain in respect of assessments of excess profits.  Section 38 provides for the issue of a certificate of discharge in certain cases, and Section 39 for the assessment of executors and administrators for excess profits duty. Section 40 provides that, where an instrument is chargeable with <i>ad valorem</i> duty in respect of money in any currency other than the currency of Saorstát Eireann, the said duty shall be calculated on the value of that money in Saorstát Eireann currency. Section 41 provides a consequential change in the law following the repealing and replacing of the Public Charitable Hospitals (Temporary Provisions) Act, 1930, by the measure which the Oireachtas has just had before it.  Section 42 proposes to exempt receipts which have been given by county registrars.  Section 43 exempts from stamp duty, in certain cases, corporations which were previously unlimited, and which were made subject to Corporation Profits Tax by the Act of 1932.  Section 44 gives power to the High Court to issue an originating summons in the case of a debtor who owes money to the revenue of Saorstát <Col N="2303" /> Eireann but who resides not in this country but in Great Britain.  These are all the principal provisions of the Bill and, as I presume that the Seanad would like to have further time to consider them, it would, possibly, be better for me not to take up any more time at this stage but to allow any <Col N="2304" /> further points that may require to be dealt with to be developed by the members on another occasion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Second Stage will be adjourned until next Thursday, 13th July, 1933.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 2.10 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Tuesday, 11th July, 1933.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>