<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="13" Month="Jul" Year="1933" Vol="17" No="3" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 13 Iúil 1933" DateEnglish="Thursday, 13 July 1933" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="191">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="191" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Musk Rats" RHead="Bill, 1933&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Public Business. - Musk Rats Bill, 1933&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan) James Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill seeks power to deal with the musk rat menace, which has lately invaded this country, but which has been known in other countries for some time.  They are, so far as we can find out, with the limited powers that we have, already fairly well in the Nenagh district, and they will take some time to eliminate even with the powers we seek here.  They have been in England for some time and, up to the present, a considerable amount of money has been expended in an effort to get rid of them, and it is estimated that very much more will have to be expended before the end of them has been seen.  We intend, if this Bill goes through, to send an officer of the Department to the Severn Valley, in England, where they appear to be dealing successfully with these musk rats, with a view to securing whatever information he can with regard to the methods adopted.  They have brought across a German expert, who appears to be very successful, and we want, if possible, to get a knowledge of the methods that have been adopted there. Senators may, perhaps, think it rather strange that we should provide in the Bill for giving a licence to keep musk rats, seeing that they are so dangerous, but we do not intend, however, to give any licence except to such institutions as the Zoological Gardens or some of the research laboratories.  As the House is, I am sure, aware, one of the most successful ways of killing ordinary rats is by injecting them with a certain virus.  It is successful, at any rate, up to a certain point.  The <Col N="192" /> disease spreads from one to the other until they become immune from it.  It might be possible that some of our research laboratories might discover some rather exclusive disease that would attack musk rats and not other animals and we might be able to get rid of them in that way.  It is, therefore, necessary to take powers in the Bill to allow these research laboratories, if necessary, to keep musk rats as well, of course, as the Zoological Gardens.  The Zoological Gardens, naturally, could be trusted to keep them under proper control, and it might be useful for the purpose of enabling people to see what the animals are like in case they were trying to identify them in their own localities.  There is provision for a licence to purchase pelts so that we may, first of all, control the export of these pelts and know what the extent of the business is and, secondly, so that we may prevent people from going into the breeding of musk rats for the purpose of making money out of the awards that may have to be given under the Act for pelts as a means of getting rid of the rats.  There is provision, also, for compensation for those who have musk rats.  I, personally, know of only one instance, and the Department knows only of one instance, where musk rats are kept under proper control, and I think that there are only seven rats kept by that particular owner, so that the amount to be paid in compensation will be very small.  The powers we seek are, I think, all necessary, and they are rather urgent, because these animals multiply very quickly.  They multiply practically as quickly as rabbits, and many of us who are from the country, at any rate, know what that means, so that the quicker we get on to the thing the better.  As soon as we get the proper authority from the Oireachtas, we mean to lose no time in getting after the menace and getting rid of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the Bill. The Minister has certainly made a case for licensing the keeping of musk rats by research laboratories, but I cannot see any reason why musk rats should be allowed in any other place, the <Col N="193" /> Zoological Gardens or otherwise. Every musk rat in the country, outside those for use by research laboratories, should, I think, be exterminated, and the Minister should consider altering the Bill in such a way as to provide for that extermination.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for the next sitting day.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Electoral (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1933&mdash;Final Stages">
    <Title>Public Business. - Electoral (Amendment) Bill, 1933&mdash;Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There are no amendments to this Bill.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the Bill be received for Final Consideration.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret that the responsible Minister is not present, because I wanted to ask a couple of very pertinent questions on this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps we might take the Fifth Stage now, and it would then be more appropriate to have a speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought it was the Final Stage we were considering.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take the Fifth Stage now.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>Before this ghost of Article 17 is finally laid, I want to inquire from the Minister if there are any other pale shades of the empty formula lurking in our statutes.  This Bill, we were told, on the Second Reading, is consequential on the Removal of Oath Bill, and I gather from the Minister's statement in the Dáil, on June 27th or 28th, that a further consequential Bill, consequential on this consequential amendment, is to be introduced.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government is now here and is in charge of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Parliamentary Secretary may be able to give me the <Col N="194" /> assurance I want.  I gathered from that statement of the Minister in the Dáil that a further consequential amendment&mdash;consequential on this consequential amendment&mdash;is impending though it has not yet been introduced. The Minister further said:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;This Bill is merely implementing an Act already passed.  If it be found necessary at any time to introduce further measures for this purpose such Bills will be introduced.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>So that there looms ahead the prospect of further consequential Bills, consequential on a consequential Bill which has not yet been introduced, but which will be consequential on this, which is consequential on the Removal of Oath Bill, and, as it is apparent from the statement made by the Minister in the other House that neither he nor the Executive Council are very clear as to what the situation is as regards the constitutional position of this State, I think it is desirable that, on this Final Stage of this Bill, we should have some considered statement from the Minister on the point.  On another Bill that was discussed in the Seanad, I drew attention to certain anomalies relative to this Bill, and I think it is well that we should give attention to this so that there will not be a repetition or a continuance of the somewhat anomalous and rather grotesque constitutional position which existed since 3rd May as a result of the lack of clear thinking and legislative impetuosity on the part of the Executive Council.  I pointed out that, on 3rd May, in connection with the Removal of Oath Bill, a motion of enactment was passed which gave sanction to that Bill equivalent to the sanction of both Houses, and when that motion was passed in the Dáil on May 3, Article 17 of the Constitution ceased to have statutory effect.  This Bill proposes to repeal the Electoral (Amendment) (No. 2) Act, 1927, in so far as it is unrepealed.  That Act is law to-day, in so far as it is unrepealed.  The other Act has been law since May 3, but in the Schedule of that Act a form of affidavit is inserted which is to <Col N="195" /> apply to candidates for the Dáil and Seanad.  It reads:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I ..................... of ..................... intending to permit or having permitted myself to be proposed as a candidate for election to Seanad Eireann in accordance with the Treaty, the Constitution and the Law, do hereby make oath and say that if I am elected to be a member of Seanad Eireann I will duly take my seat therein as a member thereof and for that purpose will duly take in the manner prescribed by Article 17 of the Constitution and within the time limited by law for so doing the oath required by that Article to be taken and subscribed by every member of the Oireachtas before taking his seat therein.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That is part of the law to-day, though the Oath has been abolished and ceased to have statutory effect on May 3.  This is where the culpability of the Executive Council is concerned, that this Bill, which renders void that Act was not introduced until May 24.  Had there been a vacancy in the Dáil or the Seanad since May 3 the candidate for such vacancy would have to sign an affidavit or swear an oath that had been already abolished.  I think that is an absurd position, and one calculated to bring ridicule upon the Oireachtas, and especially upon those responsible for presenting legislative proposals to this House.  I would be lacking in my duty if, having cognisance of that, I failed to bring this strange anomaly&mdash;I think I might call it legislative irregularity &mdash;before this House.  There was the statement made by the Minister on the 28th June in which he said:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;This Bill is merely implementing an Act already passed.  If it be found necessary at any time to introduce further measures for this purpose such Bills will be introduced.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That was the Act for the removal of the Oath.  It is obvious the Minister, and, I presume he speaks for the Executive Council in the <Col N="196" /> matter, was not clear in his mind as to whether or not the proposal embodied in the Removal of Oath Bill has yet reached that full legislative implementation which is necessary in order to make it inoperative.  In the discussion that took place on the 27th June, as to the effect of this Bill, which removes the circumstances by which the period of actual operation of membership begins, this discussion took place, according to the Official Debates, column 1287.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Mr. Fitzgerald: I take it that, as the law will be when this Act is passed, there will be nothing to stop a Deputy drawing his pay whether he attends or not.  Why does the Minister say he cannot?</P>
    <P>Mr. O'Kelly: We are not dealing with that in this Bill.  The law will be altered.</P>
    <P>Mr. Fitzgerald: But when we pass this Bill a man can draw his £360 a year without ever coming into this Dáil&mdash;until such time as the Dáil itself legislates a change.</P>
    <P>Mr. O'Kelly: That is so.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Having drawn attention to one anomaly existing since May 3, here we are confronted with another anomaly. Possibly on May 3 the Minister did not foresee that anomaly.  Here the anomaly was foreseen, according to the discussion, but so far as one can judge, it is not proposed to make any provision to deal with it until some time before Christmas.  I say that is most unsatisfactory.  The whole procedure dealing with this matter has been irregular, and has shown a certain amount of slovenliness in procedure, in exact judgment in accurate knowledge of what is required.  Judging by the Minister's statement which I read, he and his colleagues in the Executive Council are still in a state of bewilderment to know when and why the bugbear which has been a menace to their peace, and the anti-formula, has been got rid of.  It is well that we should have some explanation, first about the irregularity and the anomaly to which I have drawn attention, and secondly some assurance that further anomalies, <Col N="197" /> which seem to be hovering about will not be permitted to eventuate.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusRobinson" hpid="Mr. S. Robinson Mr. S. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>Can I propose now that the Minister be allowed to close the debate?  I do not like the idea of this discussion continuing indefinitely, because something is sure to arise on the Minister's reply.  The debate may then go on interminably.  Unless some other Senator wishes to speak I suggest that the Minister should close the debate now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think I could take such a motion.  Each Senator has the right to speak once on this stage. It is improbable that any other Senator wishes to raise any point.  If any Senator so desires it would be only fair that he should do so now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O'Kelly) Seán T. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O'Kelly)</NameTxt>
      <P>If I understand Senator Milroy aright he said that anomalies existed, owing to the delay in introducing this Bill, which is merely a Bill to put certain matters in proper legal form as a result of a Bill that was passed, which is now an Act, abolishing the oath or declaration.  The oath or declaration disappeared by law in the month of May, and this Bill was introduced in the month of June.  It could hardly be introduced earlier.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Act is still law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O'Kelly Mr. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill was introduced in June, and in all the circumstances I doubt if it could be introduced earlier by anybody, even by a Minister who might be as active or as energetic as the Senator.  This Bill is introduced to put the law into proper form, after the changes that were agreed upon by this House and by the Dáil.  The Senator raised one other point with reference to the payment of members.  A Bill to deal with that matter which, I respectfully suggest, is not urgent at the moment, is being prepared, and, I expect, will be introduced at the earliest possible date.  I do not think any other point was made against the Bill.  This is not a Bill of first rate importance.  It is merely consequential on Bills that <Col N="198" /> have been put through both Houses in order to make the necessary repeals and amendments in the law required, as a result of the legislation we have passed.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Public Hospitals" RHead="Bill, 1933&mdash;Report Stage">
    <Title>Public Business. - Public Hospitals Bill, 1933&mdash;Report Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be considered on Report.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDowdall" hpid="Mr. Dowdall Mr. Dowdall">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowdall</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 1:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 1.  To add at the end of the section the following:&mdash; the word &ldquo;nurse&rdquo; means a person registered by the General Nursing Council of Saorstát Eireann or certified as a midwife by the Central Midwives Board of Soarstát Eireann.</P>
      <P>I am not sure if this amendment is necessary or advisable in view of the amendments previously inserted in the Bill.  There is a definition of a nursing organisation, but that only applies to the nursing of the poor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Dr. Ward) Francis Constantine (Dr.) Ward">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Dr. Ward)</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Committee Stage the Seanad inserted a number of amendments designed to give the Minister power to make a grant out of the Hospitals' Trust Fund to a nurses' pension fund.  I do not think it would be in order at this stage to offer any observations on these amendments, but there is considerable doubt whether they are capable of achieving the object that was in the minds of the Senators responsible for them.  The amendments really mix up two matters that to me appear to be separate.  One is a subvention of portion of the fund towards a pension fund, and the other, a subvention of the fund towards a benevolent fund.  A fund for helping necessitous, aged and infirm nurses is quite a different proposition from a pension fund of the type that Senator Sir Edward Coey Bigger had in mind.  The latter is <Col N="199" /> essentially a form of endowment insurance, to which hospitals and nurses contribute, by which nurses benefit as a matter of legal right, whether necessitous or not.  I realise that it is open to considerable doubt whether these remarks are in order or not, but I am leading to the point that this whole question has not got the examination that it should have got, even before this amendment could be accepted by the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have given a considerable amount of thought to the question, both since it came before this House and while it was before the Dáil.  I think if the matter were not pressed on this particular Bill and if Senator Dowdall and the House would agree to the withdrawal of the amendment until the question had further examination, I would undertake to the House to try to bring together the nursing organisations, the Committee of the Associated Hospitals and the various interested parties to see if a pension scheme could be evolved and, possibly, a benevolent fund established apart from any contributory pension scheme that might be evolved: that when that scheme would actually be in operation and a body set up to administer it, further legislation could be introduced enabling the Minister to give it the necessary financial assistance.  I would suggest to Senator Dowdall that perhaps that undertaking might satisfy him and that it might satisfy the House.  The question of a benevolent fund is a very simple matter, but a pension fund, as I indicated on amendments that were before the House on Committee Stage, is extremely complicated and difficult of solution.  I cannot give an undertaking that these difficulties will be resolved because the establishment of a pension fund for nurses depends on factors that are altogether outside the control of the Minister.  The undertaking which I do wish to give is, that we shall endeavour to bring the affected parties, or their representatives, together and see what can be done, and that we shall consider favourably proposals for legislation to enable any agreed scheme that <Col N="200" /> may be evolved to be assisted out of the Hospitals' Trust Fund.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDowdall" hpid="Mr. Dowdall Mr. Dowdall">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowdall</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the statement made by the Parliamentary Secretary I ask the leave of the House to withdraw the amendment.  When I was tabling this amendment I did recognise that this was a very complicated matter.  I am pleased to learn that the Parliamentary Secretary has devoted his attention to this, and I am sure, having regard to what he has said, that if all we desire is not obtained a considerable amount will be obtained.  I do not know what the procedure is as regards deleting the amendments already adopted, but if the Minister moves in the Dáil to disagree with them, I can assure him that when the matter comes again before the Seanad he will have my support.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardBigger" hpid="Sir E. Coey Bigger Sir E. Coey Bigger">
      <NameTxt>Sir E. Coey Bigger</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the statement made by the Parliamentary Secretary.  I think he has taken a very wise and judicious course.  I think if it results in a scheme such as he anticipates&mdash;I hope it will eventually be introduced&mdash;it will be not only to his credit but to the credit of his Department.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 2:&mdash;</P>
      <P>New section.  Before Section 18 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>18.  Nothing contained in the last preceding section shall empower the Hospitals' Commission to make and submit to the Minister a scheme which shall involve an alteration of the constitution or an interference with the administration of a hospital which did not receive any benefit from any sweepstake promoted under the Public Charitable Hospitals Acts, 1930 to 1932 and does not receive any benefit from a sweepstake promoted under this Act and which does not receive any grant from a local authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The object of this amendment is to protect the hospitals, which take no money from the sweepstakes, from any interference by the Government in their constitution or their internal <Col N="201" /> administration.  It is only in Section 17 of the Bill that any danger of that kind can exist.  The only danger to the hospitals which do get money under the sweepstakes is because of the conditions which the Minister can put on any grant that is made from the Hospitals' Trust Fund.  I am speaking of hospitals, of one of which I am myself a governor, which do not take and have not taken any money whatever under the sweepstakes and, in all human probability, never will.  Now the danger to these hospitals of possible Government interference is in Section 17.  That is the section which applies to all hospitals, whether they take money under this Bill, or have taken it under the old Hospitals Acts: May I call the attention of Senators to two paragraphs of this section which define the functions of the Hospitals' Commission.  The first of these functions is in paragraph (a).  They are to do the following things:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  on their own motion to inquire into, examine, and survey generally the hospital and nursing facilities existing in Saorstát Eireann and to collect, record and digest information in relation to such facilities, the needs of the people for such facilities, and the adjustment of such facilities to such needs;</P>
    <P>That is altogether right.  There is no objection whatever to that paragraph in the section applying to the kind of hospital on behalf of which I am speaking.  On the contrary, I know from the board, of which I am a member, that they will welcome any application to them under that paragraph. They will be delighted to give any information and any help possible. It is paragraph (c) that contains the danger.  Under this paragraph the Hospitals' Commission shall:</P>
    <P>(c)  at the request of the Minister, to make and submit to the Minister schemes for the improvement and co-ordination of hospital or nursing or both hospital and nursing facilities in the whole or any particular part of Saorstát Eireann.</P>
    <P>Now that includes hospitals that do not take a grant; that do not take <Col N="202" /> money under the sweepstakes.  Under such a scheme for the co-ordination of hospital facilities&mdash;say a scheme which amalgamated a hospital that takes no money from the sweepstakes with another hospital&mdash;it would be quite possible that the scheme would interfere with the constitution and the internal administration of the affairs of a non-participating hospital.  It is quite true that probably that could not happen without further legislation. I do not know what view the Parliamentary Secretary takes of that, but it is quite possible that that is the case.  My objection is that it should not get into a scheme even under this Bill.  There should not be any possibility under this Bill, which is really a measure for the administration of money that comes from the hospitals, of interfering, in the way I have described, with the internal affairs of a hospital that takes no benefit under these Acts.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no difference of opinion between Senator Brown and the Ministry is so far as the principle aimed at in his amendment is concerned. It seems to be entirely a question of the legal interpretation of the Minister's powers under the Bill. I am advised by the legal advisers that the Bill, as it stands, does not confer any power on the Hospitals' Commission to enter any institution that is not participating.  Section 17 sets out the functions and duties of the Hospitals' Commission.  The Senator will observe that these functions and duties are purely advisory.  The Hospitals' Commission will not be an executive body.  They will inquire, examine, investigate and report on draft schemes, but they may not visit the premises of non-participating hospitals.  May I direct Senator Brown's attention to sub-section (6) of Section 14.  As I have already stated, Section 17 sets out the functions and duties of the Hospitals' Commission. Sub-section (6) of Section 14 states that:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>For the purposes of performing his duties under this Act every member <Col N="203" /> of the Hospitals Commission may visit all or any of the premises of any hospital or nursing organisation which shall have participated in any sweepstake promoted, under the Public Charitable Hospitals Acts, 1930 to 1932, or under this Act, or which shall have applied for a grant out of the Hospitals' Trust Fund under Section 23 hereof ...</P>
    <P>and so on.  That sub-section enables and authorises the Hospitals' Commission to visit the hospitals that are participating or applying for a grant for the purpose of performing the duties set out in Section 17.  But there is nothing whatever in the Bill empowering the Hospitals' Commission to visit any institution that is not participating, or that does not apply for a grant. If this amendment were accepted it would raise the assumption that the Minister had power to alter the constitution of non-participating hospitals.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not alleged that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, it would naturally be assumed that the Minister had power.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I have only stated that something included in a scheme say, for the co-ordination of hospital facilities might bring about Government interference with the internal affairs of a non-participating hospital.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>At any rate it is a matter of interpretation of sub-section (6) of Section 14 read in conjunction with Section 17, and I am very definitely advised that the Minister has no such power.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree that the Minister has no such power.  That is not my point.  My point is that the Hospitals' Commission have the power of making and submitting to the Minister a scheme which might include conditions which would affect the internal administration of a non-participating hospital.  If it is quite clear that there is no such power in the Bill, why not put it into the Bill?  It can do no harm.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>The only reason why we do not put something into a Bill prohibiting <Col N="204" /> the Minister from doing something that he has not power to do is, that if we were to include all the things that the Minister has no power to do, the Bill would become very unwieldy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I point out to the Parliamentary Secretary that sub-section (6) of Section 14 only defines the powers of entry and examination into the accounts which the Hospitals' Commission shall have. If they were preparing a scheme for submission to the Minister they would, of course, prepare that scheme with a view to the Minister taking action, whether he had to get Parliamentary sanction or not.  Assuming that he would have to get Parliamentary sanction for most schemes, they would include such a hospital, but they would have no powers to force such a hospital to submit to entry or examination of accounts. It is pretty obvious, however, that if the non-participating hospital found that it was going to be referred to in the scheme, it would much prefer that the full details should be available. It would not refuse permission because if it did, then it would be placing itself in an impossible position if it were liable to be included under a scheme which had not proper examination.</P>
      <P>It is quite true that sub-section (6) does safeguard the non-participating hospitals so far as entry and examination are concerned but it does not safeguard them from being included in a scheme without such examination.  While I do not think that that is likely to happen or that the Hospitals' Commission is likely to include a hospital without investigation, it might place a hospital in such a position that it would be virtually forced to comply inasmuch as, if it did not agree, it might give a false impression.  This is not quite on a par with the suggestion of the Parliamentary Secretary as to putting everything you cannot do into a Bill.  In this case, there is a definite section suggesting that the Hospitals' Commission may make an investigation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="205" />
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Brown admits that the Minister has no power to alter the constitution of these hospitals?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>Apparently, he has some uneasiness lest the Minister should attach conditions to the making of a grant which would have the effect of altering the constitution of a hospital.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I never suggested that. I merely said that the Hospitals' Commission might submit a scheme which would involve interference.  I do not deny that the Minister has no power to interfere but, with the Commission, it is a case of &ldquo;shall.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Hospitals' Commission did put something into a scheme which would involve alteration of the constitution of a hospital, the Minister would naturally delete that from the scheme, as he would have no statutory power to interfere with the constitution.  The fact that such a recommendation was embodied in the scheme of the Hospitals' Commission would not bring it any further.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister might have to take statutory powers to carry out the scheme.  I want to prevent this being included in the scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>If a group of hospitals refuse to apply for assistance from this fund, does Senator Brown suggest that this Commission, which might be inquiring into the hospital and nursing services of the Free State, should be prohibited from suggesting anything to the Minister which might ultimately involve some interference with them?  If that is the argument, I think that the amendment goes altogether too far.  Surely, the Commission, if its inquiry into the larger question of hospital services is to be of any value, should be empowered to make a report to the Minister which might involve non-participating hospitals?  Something else will have to follow that.  We are not now speaking of empowering the Commission to <Col N="206" /> do certain things but merely to make a report on hospital services.  Half a dozen hospitals may decide to have nothing more to do with this scheme and yet the Commission might find that, in the interest of hospital services, there should be some sort of general co-ordination.  If the Commission were prohibited from reporting in favour of such a reform, it would be calamitous.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Johnson has, to some extent, raised the exact issue. This scheme is connected with the sweepstakes.  If the State decides upon an investigation of the whole question of hospitals, apart from the question of sweepstakes, then a different question will arise.  But here we have a scheme connected entirely with the sweepstakes.  A hospital which decides, for its own reasons, to remain independent and to accept no assistance from the sweepstakes should be free to retain its independence unless some other complete State scheme is brought in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment would prohibit the Commission from reporting or inquiring with regard to such a hospital.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>The Commission will be dealing with the allocation of funds in connection with the sweepstakes.  The Senator wants, through the medium of this Bill, dealing with sweepstakes, to drag in these other hospitals so that the Hospitals' Commission will have power to include them.  Hospitals which, for their own reasons, prefer to rely on voluntary subscriptions should not be interfered with except a general State scheme is brought in.  Two or three hospitals may prefer to remain absolutely independent.  They should be free to do so, so far as any Commission set up under this Bill is concerned. If the Minister desires an investigation of all the hospitals of the Saorstát, that will be a subject for a Hospitals Bill and not for a Sweepstakes Bill, since the sweepstakes may go on only for a few years or, on the other hand, may go on for a considerable time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="207" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that there must be some misunderstanding.  The Minister cannot interfere with non-participating hospitals.  The Commission, which formulates a scheme for him, cannot interfere with non-participating hospitals.  The scheme may, however, contain some reference to a non-participating hospital.  Senator Brown is afraid that, if the scheme contains such a reference, which the Minister has no power to accept, it will be, in some way or other injurious to the non-participating hospital.  Is not that what the Senator's amendment comes to?  I do not see that the acceptance of Senator Brown's amendment can do any harm, nor do I see that it will do much good.  I do not know why he should be so desperately anxious to preserve his non-participating hospitals from all inquiry.  If they are so anxious to avoid inquiry and so afraid of the possibility of being mentioned in any hospitals scheme, it rather gives the impression that there is something to conceal.  I know that there is nothing to conceal in respect of these non-participating hospitals.  If the Parliamentary Secretary has no real objection, I should favour the acceptance of Senator Brown's amendment. However, that is a matter for the Parliamentary Secretary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I am authorised by the Hospital Board of which I am a member to say that we will welcome any inquiry and give any assistance so long as our internal administration is not interfered with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardBigger" hpid="Sir Edward Coey Bigger Sir Edward Coey Bigger">
      <NameTxt>Sir Edward Coey Bigger</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the amendment, which I think is a very reasonable one.  I see no real objection to it.  If certain hospitals prefer to remain outside the sweepstakes, I do not see how it will interfere in any way with the functions of the Hospitals' Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to support Senator Brown's amendment if I thought it was necessary.  Let us suppose this amendment was not inserted in the Bill, and the Hospitals' Commission made a recommendation which included alterations in a non-participating hospital.  If the Minister <Col N="208" /> thought the idea was a good one, am I not right in assuming that he would have to bring in legislation in order to include that hospital in the scheme?  I do not see the necessity for the amendment.  It presupposes that, because hospitals have accepted moneys from the sweepstakes, their whole internal management is to be interfered with by the Hospitals' Commission. I do not believe that is going to occur.  I hope it will not occur, and I do not think the Minister or anybody else would encourage that sort of thing. I do not see what real difference Senator Brown's amendment would make.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. Jameson Mr. Jameson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jameson</NameTxt>
      <P>One point has, I think, been forgotten in this discussion.  We know that these hospitals depend on private subscriptions.  There has been a great deal of discussion as to persons sending subscriptions to hospitals which have accepted money from the sweepstakes.  If any scheme was put forward by which an independent hospital was joined with a hospital accepting aid from the sweepstakes scheme, I can easily understand that the board of that hospital would be seriously concerned lest they should lose subscriptions.  As Senator Brown has said, inspection is not the thing that is feared at all.  What is feared is interference with internal management and the effect on the finances.  If one of these hospitals was joined up with a participating hospital, subscribers would probably decline to send in their subscriptions.  The Parliamentary Secretary ought to consider seriously whether Senator Johnson's reading of this provision is not the right one.  Senator Johnson reads into the Bill what Senator Brown fears. The Parliamentary Secretary says he has no power to do anything of this kind.  Senator Johnson says: &ldquo;I think it is a very good thing, and the Minister should have power, if this Hospitals' Commission puts up a scheme whereby hospitals that have never taken money from the sweepstakes should be joined up with those who have&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not the point at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="209" />
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. Jameson Mr. Jameson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jameson</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator would enable the Hospitals' Commission to bring in a scheme, and he sees no reason why that scheme should not include hospitals which never had anything to do with the sweepstakes. The Parliamentary Secretary said it was impossible that such a thing should happen.  I understood Senator Johnson to say that he thought that was included and that it ought to happen. Even if I have misquoted the Senator to any extent, it is quite evident that there is a difference of opinion.  There are people who believe&mdash;perhaps they are right in their belief&mdash;that this Hospitals' Commission can put forward suggestions even without making inquiries in respect of hospitals that have not partaken of assistance from the sweepstakes.  That fear shows that Senator Brown's amendment requires a great deal of attention.  I think really that the Parliamentary Secretary ought to look into the matter and be quite clear that what Senator Brown is afraid of cannot possibly take place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>May I continue my original speech and draw attention to the change in the form of this amendment? An amendment introduced by Senator Brown on the Committee Stage read as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Nothing contained in the last preceding section shall empower the Minister to alter the constitution.</P>
      <P>Senator Brown gave notice of that amendment on the Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I withdrew it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am drawing a distinction between the two wordings.  I would have been entirely in favour of that proposition.  The amendment read:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Nothing contained in the last preceding section shall empower the Minister to alter the constitution or to interfere in the administration of an hospital which did not receive any benefit from any sweepstake, etc.</P>
      <P>That is a proposition to which I imagine there would have been no difficulty in agreeing, on any side of the House, but Senator Brown did not proceed with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="210" />
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>It did not arise under Section 17.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>The same idea is there nevertheless.  Here is the amendment now.  It deals with Section 17 which imposes on the Hospitals' Committee certain duties one of which is &ldquo;at the request of the Minister to make and submit to the Minister schemes for the improvement and co-ordination of hospital or nursing or both hospital and nursing facilities&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I suggest that the Commission surveying the facilities for hospital services in the country may come across one, two or three hospitals that are entirely apart from the scheme and may suggest to the Minister that it would be desirable to bring those hospitals into review and to fit them into a scheme with the hospitals which are getting a benefit from the sweeps, without at all touching the administration, without in any way interfering with the management but simply saying: &ldquo;Here are hospitals that are entirely apart from the sweepstakes and they are doing certain work.  There are other hospitals which are participating and they are doing certain other work.  Let us see whether we cannot suggest to the Minister a scheme for co-ordinating the work of these hospitals but leaving the independent hospitals still with their independence&rdquo;.  This amendment would prevent the Commission from making any such suggestion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;Nothing contained in the last preceding section shall empower the Hospitals Commission to make and submit to the Minister a scheme which shall involve an alteration of the constitution or an interference with the administration of a hospital&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the only limitation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>But the report of the Committee does not alter the Constitution, the administration or the management.  The report of the Committee simply says to the Minister: &ldquo;There are services and facilities for <Col N="211" /> dealing with the sick and infirm.  Here is another institution which is outside this general scheme and it is also dealing with the sick and infirm.  We suggest to the Minister that that institution ought to be approached with a view to co-ordinating its work with the general hospital services&rdquo;. It seems to me that if you prevent this Commission making an enquiry and reporting on those lines you are diminishing very gravely the value of the Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Johnson in his very laboured speech has not answered what Senator Jameson has said. Senator Jameson's objection is that the mere fact of this Commission making a report involving a non-participating hospital will have the effect of depriving the non-participating hospital of its charitable donations. What answer is given to that?  I think the Minister ought to consider carefully what Senator Johnson has said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I remind Senator Johnson that my amendment objects to a scheme involving interference? I specially set that out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the House ought to remember that there are a number of people here who, possibly for very bad reasons, dislike sweepstakes. They are extremely chary&mdash; one hears it from various quarters&mdash; that the few hospitals which remain independent should be brought into the scheme or forced into the position later that they would have to take part in it.  I am not suggesting that that is a good or a reasonable point of view.  I am only stating that I know it to be a fact that some people hold that view.  If this Bill gives to the Committee the liberty of suggesting, as Senator Johnson said, the inclusion of such hospitals in the scheme, even though that gives them no actual power, there is very grave danger to the hospitals who remain independent. People may say to them: &ldquo;You cannot hold out much longer, and we will stop subscribing.&rdquo; I think the House may take that as being the fact.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="212" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest this amendment would prevent the Minister doing things which he has power to do now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>There are a couple of points to which I should like to refer. It appears to me that if this amendment were accepted by the House it would interfere with the Hospitals' Commission in completing a survey of the hospitals services.  Senator Brown agrees with me that the Minister has no statutory power to alter the constitution of any hospital, participating or non-participating.  It is perfectly clear then that there can be no damage done to any non-participating hospital, if the Hospitals' Commission in their report make a recommendation in regard to that hospital in the scheme that they submit to the Minister.  It is argued by Senator Jameson and Senator Douglas that it might do definite harm or might interfere with the flow of subscriptions if it became known or if a suggestion for the incorporation of a non-participating hospital in a scheme of co-ordination, went out.  Senators should bear in mind that the report of the Hospitals' Commission regarding any scheme of co-ordination will be to the Minister and no scheme will go to the public until the Minister has approved of it.  He cannot approve of any scheme or operate any scheme that involves interference with the constitution of the hospitals.  Senator Brown admits that the Minister could not operate such a scheme interfering with any of the non-participating hospitals, but he says that the Minister may come along and take statutory powers to put such a scheme into operation.  It appears to me that it would be quite time enough to press that point when the Minister sought statutory powers to put such a scheme into operation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I put it this way to the Parliamentary Secretary?  Suppose, instead of a number of subscribers, one philanthropic gentleman maintained a large hospital, regulated it himself, and bore all the expenditure on it, would that hospital not be independent of the Hospitals' Commission? Are not these hospitals <Col N="213" /> exactly in the same position?  I think it would be monstrous to expect that these hospitals, who get nothing out of the sweep, should be in any way interfered with, or that anything should be done in regard to them which would deprive them of subscriptions.  As Senator Johnson has said, the effect of the sweep has been to reduce voluntary subscriptions all round.  These hospitals that have to depend on voluntary subscriptions would probably lose practically all their subscriptions if they were included in such a scheme as is suggested.  I think Senator Brown intimated that there would be almost a complete desire to have inspection and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask the question: is there anything in Senator Brown's amendment, if carried, to prevent the Commission from making reference to the non-participating hospitals in regard to any scheme, provided that scheme does not involve <Col N="214" /> interference with the hospitals?  I think there is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>The wording of this amendment is perfectly clear.  If it were accepted the Commission would not be empowered to make or submit a scheme &ldquo;which shall involve an alteration of the Constitution or an interference with the administration of a hospital.&rdquo;  They could not report to the Minister in regard to it.  To my mind it would be necessary that they should report to the Minister and recommend schemes of hospitalisation that would involve all institutions. While the Minister would have no statutory power to interfere in the way that the Senator is afraid he might, he could not, if this amendment were accepted, negotiate with the non-participating hospitals to see how far they might be included in a co-ordination scheme.</P>
      <P>Amendment put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 19; Níl, 11.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Barniville, Dr. Henry L.<br />Bigger, Sir Edward Coey.<br />Brown, K.C., Samuel L.<br />Browne, Miss Kathleen.<br />Costello, Mrs.<br />Counihan, John C.<br />Crosbie, George.<br />Dillon, James.<br />Douglas, James G.<br />Farren, Thomas.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Griffith, Sir John Furser.<br />Hickie, Major-General Sir William.<br />Jameson, Right Hon. Andrew.<br />Linehan, Thomas.<br />Milroy, Seán.<br />Moran, James.<br />O'Connor, Joseph.<br />O'Hanlon, M.F.<br />Staines, Michael.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Chléirigh, Caitlín Bean Uí.<br />Comyn, K.C., Michael.<br />Foran, Thomas.<br />Johnson, Thomas.<br />Moore, Colonel.<br />O'Neill, L.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">O'Rourke, Brian.<br />Quirke, William.<br />Robinson, David L.<br />Robinson, Séamus.<br />Toal, Thomas.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers:&mdash;Tá: Senators Brown and Douglas; Níl: Senators D.L. Robinson and S. Robinson.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelStaines" hpid="Mr. Staines Mr. Staines">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staines</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 3:</P>
      <P>Section 24, sub-section (5).  To add at the end of the sub-section the words: &ldquo;Provided, however, that no conditions shall be attached to the receipt of any such grant in any way relating to the appointment, dismissal or control of the staff of any hospital or nursing organisation or to the management or administration of any hospital or nursing organisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The purpose of the amendment is to prevent undue interference by the Minister in the ordinary management of the participating hospitals.  As I am anxious to meet the Parliamentary Secretary as far as possible, I should like, with the permission of the House, to alter the wording of the amendment and, in the second last line, to delete <Col N="215" /> the words &ldquo;or administration&rdquo; and to insert the word &ldquo;internal&rdquo; before the word &ldquo;management.&rdquo;  The amendment would then read:</P>
    <P>. . . . . . . or to the internal management of any hospital or nursing organisation.</P>
    <P>The position is that these hospitals have carried on, and have carried on well, for many years, on voluntary subscriptions.  With this sweep money coming in now and with the Minister claiming the power to make certain orders in connection with the hospitals there is a genuine fear amongst certain hospitals that there will be undue interference and it is really to prevent that that I have put forward this amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I interrupt the Senator?  It is rather a pity that the Senator would not go a little farther, when I would try to meet him in this matter.  Perhaps, the House might agree to stop the amendment at the word &ldquo;organisation&rdquo; and to leave out the question of management because we are going to have the same difficulty about interpreting what &ldquo;management&rdquo; means and as to the very wide meaning that might attach to it if it became a matter of interpretation, subsequently, in a court of law.  It would save a great deal of the time of the House if the Senator could come that distance to meet me.  We do not want to interfere with the staffs at all or with the ordinary internal management, but &ldquo;management&rdquo; is capable of a very wide interpretation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelStaines" hpid="Mr. Staines Mr. Staines">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staines</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I would be prepared to accept that.  It is really what I wanted to get at.  The Minister assures us that he has no intention of interfering in the internal management and it was about the staff that I was really anxious.  It is undue interference I want to prevent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>There will be no interference, even without the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The amended amendment will then read:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Provided, however, that no conditions shall be attached to the receipt <Col N="216" /> of any such grant in any way relating to the appointment, dismissal or control of the staff of any hospital or nursing organisation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I point out that it would require a further amendment, unless it is intended to deprive the Minister of certain present powers?  It is probably a matter for lawyers, but, as the hospitals concerned include hospitals provided by local authorities, the Minister must have power to interfere with the staffs to some degree in that respect, and therefore the amendment, as amended, would require a further proviso setting out that it did not intend to restrict the powers of the Minister in respect of public authority hospitals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that that would really not be necessary.  This simply provides the conditions attaching to a grant and these would not be conditions attaching to a grant, but to the whole hospital.  The Minister will, no doubt, look into it, because Senator Johnson may be right.  I am glad that the Minister has agreed to accept this.  The last amendment was designed to enable some hospitals to stay out of the scheme and this is to enable some to stay in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Judging by previous discussions on other Bills, the Minister made grants to local hospitals on certain conditions and these conditions may involve certain administrative changes and, therefore, I think that this amendment would require a proviso setting out that it did not apply to public hospitals, that is, publicly owned hospitals of local authorities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EileenCostello" hpid="Mrs. Costello Mrs. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Minister not already got ample powers to deal with local authority hospitals under the various Local Government Acts?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I fancy he has, but it is as well to consider the point raised by Senator Johnson.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>It can be dealt with between now and the time when the Bill goes to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="217" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator who has proposed the amendment has not agreed to the Parliamentary Secretary's suggestion, I should like to ask&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>He did agree.  I will put the amended amendment, as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Provided, however, that no conditions shall be attached to the receipt of any such grant in any way relating to the appointment, dismissal or control of the staff of any hospital or nursing organisation.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Final Stage will be taken on the next sitting day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any great difficulty in taking the Final Stage now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There would be. Amendments have been passed and they have to be carefully perused to see that they are all in order.</P>
      <P>Final Stage ordered for the next sitting day.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Cement (No. 2) Bill," RHead="1933&mdash;Report Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Public Business. - Cement (No. 2) Bill, 1933&mdash;Report Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Government amendment No. 1:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 8 <i>(being the new section inserted in Committee).</i>  To delete the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Acting-Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Derrig) Acting-Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Derrig)">
      <NameTxt>Acting-Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Derrig)</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment is to delete the new section which was inserted in Committee.  It is proposed to insert the new section in a somewhat revised form.  We have the draftsman's draft further down the paper, so that the first Government amendment is to prepare the way for the insertion of the agreed amendment, and I think that it was generally agreed that this amendment might be accepted.  I should, perhaps, explain that the object of the revised amendment is to leave out the reference to importation of cement and import licences but to make it quite clear that, as regards the manufacture of cement, the Minister has to set up a standard specification, penalties to <Col N="218" /> be inflicted, accordingly, on persons holding cement manufacture licences who do not carry out the order and manufacture cement according to the standard specification laid down by the Minister.  The reference to importation of cement and import licences has been excised.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not quite sure of the effect of carrying this amendment but I presume, if carried, amendment No. 2 will not be capable of being moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that would be so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Therefore, I had better say a word on this amendment, appertaining to amendment No. 2. I felt on the previous stage that the position regarding the specification of cement to be manufactured under the general control of the Minister was fairly safe and, in any remarks I made, I laid stress on the necessity for fixing a standard quality for imported cement. Now I find that the promoters of the original amendment, presumably, are acquiescent in the deletion of the provision regarding importation.  I am not going to oppose this amendment, and therefore amendment No. 2 on the Order Paper will fall.  A case will arise on a later amendment, when I hope to persuade the House and the Minister that some further amendment is still required in this respect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>As one of those responsible for the original amendment, I might explain that the reasons for the change were that after inquiry we were satisfied considerable expense would be entailed if tests had to be made of cement coming into this country.  We believed that that expense would be quite justified if Portland cement was going to be imported for a considered time, but we received assurances that it was not the intention of the Department to allow Portland cement to be imported, as soon as cement is manufactured here.  Other authorities outside the Department assured us that there should be no difficulty in the factories here manufacturing all the Portland cement that is required. <Col N="219" /> As the amendment only dealt with Portland cement, and not with other kinds of cement it did not seem justifiable to insist on the amendment to set up a specific standard for a period of nine months or a year, and involving considerable expense.  We would not have given way if we were not satisfied that there was no likelihood of importation as far as Portland cement is concerned.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 2 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusRobinson" hpid="Mr. S. Robinson Mr. S. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 3:&mdash;</P>
      <P>New section.  Before Section 9 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>9.&mdash;(1)  The Minister shall, as soon as may be after the commencement of this Act, by order under this sub-section appoint by reference to quality the standard to which Portland cement manufactured by holders of cement manufacture licences is to conform.</P>
      <P>(2)  The Minister may from time to time by order under this sub-section amend the order made under the immediately preceding sub-section.</P>
      <P>(3)  Every order made by the Minister under this section shall be laid before each House of the Oireachtas as soon as may be after it is made, and if a resolution annulling such order is passed by either House of the Oireachtas within the next subsequent ten days on which that House has sat after such order is so laid before it, such order shall be annulled accordingly, but without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under such order.</P>
      <P>(4)  If any holder of a cement manufacture licence manufactures any Portland cement the quality of which does not conform to the standard for the time being appointed under this section, such holder shall be guilty of an offence under this section and shall be liable on summary conviction thereof to a fine not exceeding £100.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="220" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think any special question arises on this amendment. In sub-section (1) the Minister must make an order, having reference to the standard quality of Portland cement, or by any holder of a cement manufacturing licence.  By sub-section (2) the Minister may from time to time amend an order previously made.  By sub-section (3) every order made by the Minister shall be laid before each House of the Oireachtas, and within ten days may annual such order, provided such annulment will not prejudice anything previously done under the order.  Sub-section (4) imposes a penalty on persons who hold cement manufacture licences who do not conform to the standard set up.  On summary conviction they are liable to a fine not exceeding £100.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGriffith" hpid="Sir John Griffith Sir John Griffith">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Griffith</NameTxt>
      <P>The House would be wise to accept this amendment, although personally I should have liked to have some protection against imports during the intervening period.  It has been explained to me that that would involve considerable difficulty in administration and in arranging for the testing of cement in the different ports.  The House will be perfectly safe in accepting the proposals now before it.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>The following consequential amendments were agreed to:&mdash;</P>
      <P>4. Section 11, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;subject&rdquo; in line 5 to insert the words &ldquo;to the provisions of this Act relating to standard of Portland cement and&rdquo;,</P>
      <P>5.  Section 12, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;cement&rdquo; in line 9 to insert the word &ldquo;manufacture&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>6.  Section 12, sub-section (1).  To delete paragraph (h).</P>
      <P>7.  Section 12, sub-section (1). Before the word &ldquo;controlled&rdquo; in line 46 to insert the words &ldquo;to be&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 8:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 32, sub-section (1).  To add at the end of the sub-section a new paragraph as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="221" /> (d)  that the quality of the cement proposed to be imported under the licence does not conform to the standard of quality specified by the Minister.</P>
    <P>This has reference nominally to Section 32, but really to Sections 30, 31 and 32, dealing with restrictions on imports.  If this part of the Bill were only to apply between now and the date when the whole cement requirements of this country are home manufactured my argument would not apply, but it is almost certain that imports of cement will be required, even after the first factory begins to operate, and even after the second factory begins to operate, if the demand for cement increases. Certain indications have been given as to the capacity of the factories that it is intended to set up.  I am assuming that some imports will be required from the date after the first factory begins to deliver cement.  This licence provision will apply at that time.  It is set out that a person who proposes to import shall make application, and every applicant shall set out certain particulars, one of which is &ldquo;the nature and quality of the cement proposed to be imported under such licence.&rdquo;  No person shall be entitled to import without a licence, and the licence shall state that the nature and quality of cement that is imported shall conform to that quality.  That is presupposing that machinery will be set up to deal with offences under that section; that is, to see that the quality must conform to the quality defined in the licence.  Then we have Section 32, which says:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(1)  The Minister may refuse an application for an import licence on any one or more of the following grounds and on no other ground whatsoever, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  that the applicant has not complied with the provisions of the immediately preceding section, or</P>
    <P>(b)  that the applicant has been convicted of an offence under the immediately preceding section, or</P>
    <P>(c)  that, having regard to the existing stocks of cement in Saorstát Eireann and the quantity (if any) of cement about to be imported under import licences <Col N="222" /> already issued, it is not in his opinion expedient to grant such licence.</P>
    <P>The applicant makes application and states the nature and quality of the cement he proposes to import and gives certain other particulars.  If the applicant has given those particulars and has not been convicted of an offence, if there are no stocks in the Saorstát the Minister has no option but to give the import licence.  As the Bill stands, there is nothing to prevent that applicant saying that the quality he proposes to import is a quality considerably below the grade to which Irish manufacturers are going to conform.  We would have the possible position of the Department being faced with an applicant saying: &ldquo;I am going to import No. 3 grade.&rdquo;  The Minister has no right to refuse the applicant who may import a lower quality cement during the time that home manufacturers are not capable of filling Free State requirements.  Then we have the position that the consumer, say a builder, is being allowed to build houses with an inferior grade of cement and manufacturers being met in competition in the home market with an inferior grade of cement, produced probably at a low price.  To complete the scheme of the Bill it seems to me essential that the Minister should have power to insist that the standard and quality should conform to something with which he is satisfied.  At present there is a gap.  The Minister has no option but to grant the licence, provided that the nature and quality of the cement&mdash;no matter how low it may be&mdash;has been stated in the application. My amendment fills the gap.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGriffith" hpid="Sir John Griffith Sir John Griffith">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Griffith</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the amendment.  It is hardly possible to imagine that cement will not be imported. I have been assured that the Government will not allow any cement in once we are manufacturing cement here.  Contingencies may, however, arise and cement may be imported much below the standard the Government has fixed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. Guinness Mr. Guinness">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Guinness</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to support the amendment.  If there is no restriction <Col N="223" /> there will be a tendency towards importing cement of an inferior quality.  When a standard has been set up it would be a pity not to restrict the importation of inferior cement. The clause in the Bill is permissive. As it is not mandatory on the Minister to grant an application, I think he would use his common sense in the matter and he should be given this power, which I think is essential.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'Connor Mr. O'Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to support the amendment.  The quality of the cement is important for cottages and other buildings.  I use a great deal of cement.  In my opinion, cement has been of great benefit to the farming community.  It makes farmyards secure and keeps buildings free from vermin, rats and mice.  There is an element of suspicion abroad that there will be unfair competition in the cement market.  Remarks that are not complimentary are being made about cement which is dumped here at prices lower than the cost of manufacture. Stringent measures should be taken to secure that the best standard of cement is provided and a strict watch should be kept on the quality of imported cement.  If necessary, a staff of inspectors should look after imports so that those who have to use cement would have a guarantee that they are getting the genuine article. As I mentioned before, there is any amount of material in the quarries in this country suitable for the manufacture of the best quality cement.  I hope that when these cement industries are established they will be a success and of benefit to the country.  We do not want other countries to be supplying us with cement when we have an abundance of the best material at home for its manufacture.  I support the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>I was under the impression, when we got some measure of agreement in the House on this Bill, that if the position as regards the manufacture of cement were safeguarded, the House would not insist upon compelling the Minister to lay down a standard specification in regard to the importation of cement. <Col N="224" /> As Senators know, there is no definite proof that inferior cement is at present being imported in any great quantities. The position, so far as the Department of Industry and Commerce is concerned, is exactly as Senator Sir John Griffith mentioned a short time ago.  I do not know at the moment what the exact legal implications of Senator Johnson's amendment, if accepted, would be.  It is quite possible that the position that we sought to avoid, and the administrative difficulties that we thought we would get over by leaving the question of dealing with the importation of bad cement in the hands of the Minister, will be reopened again if the House accepts Senator Johnson's amendment; that, in fact, it may be necessary to take steps, let us say, to examine particular consignments.</P>
      <P>The scheme of things as laid down in the Bill is that the Minister demands from every person who seeks a licence for the importation of cement a statement as to the nature and quality of the cement proposed to be imported.  I think I can definitely assure the House that, unless the cement proposed to be imported is of a reputable and well-known quality or standard, the Minister will not grant the licence.  But, in the event of his granting a licence for the importation of a certain quality of cement named by the applicant, the applicant will not succeed in getting the licence unless he satisfies the Minister that the standard is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>On what grounds can the Minister refuse?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>The applicant cannot import cement into the Free State under Section 30 unless it is of the quality and nature specified in the licence.  Under Section 32 the Minister has only to satisfy himself that, from the existing stocks of cement, the quantity of cement about to be imported is of proper quality and can be obtained.  I take it that the Minister will, in fact, be able to satisfy himself. It is not likely that a position is going to arise in which we shall be so short of cement that the only option left to the Minister will be to give a <Col N="225" /> licence to a person to import what he definitely knows to be inferior cement. All the importers of repute in the country will be importing cement.  As I have already told the House, they have been importing cement of a well-known standard quality for many years past.  I think the Minister will have power to deal with that situation under paragraph (c).  So long as he is satisfied that cement can be got from persons holding a licence, he will not be compelled to grant a licence in a case such as Senator Johnson mentioned.  I think the position will be fully covered by the fact that the Minister will have to satisfy himself that the quality is of the right standard.</P>
      <P>The only anxiety at present is that we should not, at this stage, upset the scheme which has been laid down in the Bill: that is that the matter should be dealt with between the Minister and the licensee.  If we lay down a standard quality beforehand we will simply be raising all the administrative difficulties that I have referred to, and taking all discretion out of the hands of the Minister.  I have already appealed to the House to leave this matter in the hands of the Minister.  He gave an assurance in the Dáil, and I give a similar assurance now, that no licence will be granted for any cement that the Minister is not satisfied is of standard quality, and I think that ought to be sufficient.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. Guinness Mr. Guinness">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Guinness</NameTxt>
      <P>May I point out again that the section is not mandatory?  It is entirely permissive.  The Minister can suit his orders to what he thinks is right.  The section says &ldquo;may&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I can quite understand that the Minister will contrive to cover up the defects of the Act.  He will say: &ldquo;Well now, I have really no legal grounds for refusing this man his licence.  He is going to import No. 3 quality but I have no legal grounds for refusing him the licence.  I will make an arrangement with Tom, Dick or Harry to import No. 1 quality, and then I will refuse to grant his licence on the grounds that there is a sufficient quantity of good quality cement here.&rdquo;  I can quite understand <Col N="226" /> the Minister doing that, but that is not the way to legislate, if we can avoid it.  I quite believe that the Minister can find ways and means of fulfilling his intentions, and of securing that good quality cement is imported.  My desire was to give him power under the law to do that, but he says he would rather not have those powers.  He would rather make contrivances and agreements and, shall I say, enter into conspiracies with importers.  Very well, if he thinks so.  I am not going to force him to be a law-abiding citizen or a law-abiding law-maker.  I realise quite well, the administrative difficulties. As this Bill has to go back to the Dáil in respect to a previous amendment, I would ask the Minister to again look into the matter, and see if he cannot fill the gap that is inevitably there by virtue of the words &ldquo;on no other grounds whatsoever&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>The position is that when the Bill comes before the Dáil again the Minister himself will probably be in charge of it.  I can promise the Senator that I will recommend the Minister to look into the question, and if at all possible to accept either the amendment or the principle of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I quite admit that the amendment, in its present form, is not satisfactory.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Fifth Stage ordered for the next day on which the House meets.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Finance Bill, 1933 (Certified" RHead="Money Bill)&mdash;Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Public Business. - Finance Bill, 1933 (Certified Money Bill)&mdash;Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>The Second Reading of the Finance Bill is really the only occasion on which this House has an opportunity to review broadly the financial position of the country, and the financial policy of the Government. It has always been the custom, and I hope I shall be allowed a similar indulgence on the present occasion, to cover rather a wider field, possibly, than would be permitted if we had all the financial powers and all the details of finance before us that <Col N="227" /> the Dáil has.  First of all, I wish to refer to the great difficulties that beset any investigation of our financial position.  We have, as material, a document which is, perhaps, necessarily condensed and known as &ldquo;A White Paper.&rdquo;  It contains the &ldquo;Estimates of Receipts and Expenditure.&rdquo; Under Article 54 of the Constitution this document should be laid on the Table before the end of the financial year.  I think that has been the practice heretofore, but this year I notice that it was not laid on the Table until the 10th May, almost on the eve of the Minister's Budget speech.  That is not necessarily much inconvenience to this House, but I do think all of us here and elsewhere should have as much time as possible to study the financial position which is so very complicated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Under &ldquo;Estimate of Expenditure&rdquo; which appears as the second item on page 3 of the White Paper, I find in the second column the heading &ldquo;Actual Expenditure 1932-33.&rdquo;  The expenditure is set out in detail.  On page 5 there is given &ldquo;Total Estimate of Expenditure for 1932-33.&rdquo;  The total of that estimate is the same as the total of the item headed &ldquo;Actual Expenditure&rdquo; as regards &ldquo;B.&mdash; Supply Services.&rdquo;  On the face of it, these two descriptions are in conflict. Which is correct?  I am assuming that &ldquo;Total Estimate of Expenditure,&rdquo; agreeing as it does with the heading &ldquo;Actual Expenditure&rdquo; is the actual expenditure.  I would also ask Senators to look at Vote No. 16 in which the actual expenditure for 1932-33 on &ldquo;superannuation and retired allowances&rdquo; is set out at £1,653,245.  I want to know from the Minister was that money actually spent?  I thought that it represented some of the moneys in dispute, representing the pensions of the old R.I.C.  I thought it was not paid over to the British Government, and yet on the face of the document it appears to have been spent, and it does not appear as a receipt in any other place.  It does not appear to form part in any way of the <Col N="228" /> budgetary items.  I also notice that in the Minister's Budget speech he said that the sum of £400,000 would be necessary for special relief, and yet in the &ldquo;Details of the Estimate of Expenditure&rdquo; in the White Paper the sum of £150,00 only is set out.</P>
    <P>I presume there was not time to include this higher figure, but I am sure the Minister will agree that it is desirable, if possible, to have this document, which only appears at the last moment, as up to date as possible. An aid in examining these figures is the document known as the Finance Accounts.  Under the 17th and 18th Vic., these accounts are to be laid on the Table of the Parliament by the end of June.  I suggest that it is very important they should be in the hands of members as soon as possible. I find that, for some years past, it has been the habit to default considerably as regards the period.  I raised the question with the Minister for Finance two years ago and he told me the accounts had been laid in dummy.  I find that they have been laid in dummy again this year.  That is to say, that on the Table there is merely the title page.  It is interesting to examine the implications of the procedure of laying in dummy, because, after all, if that is adopted as a practice by the State, why should it not also be permitted to citizens? I do not suppose that the Minister for Finance would be pleased if I proposed to pay my income tax in dummy.  To extend the practice, we might have certain of these set speeches and stereotyped interjections replaced by mechanical process in the House.  I do think that it is very necessary for the Government to abide by the law just as they expect citizens so to do.  In this case we are very much hampered in the transition period in examining the financial position by the absence of the accounts for the last financial year.</P>
    <P>An item which is very difficult to follow is that of local loans.  The Estimate in respect of local loans has been increased this year by the large amount of £1,000,000, making <Col N="229" /> £2,000,000.  This is an item which is merely a sort of vote-on-account.  It represents in no way the net figure. It sets out in no way the receipts in respect of loan payments coming in every year.  It is merely the result of certain transactions which I cannot discover anywhere.  I searched the Reports of the Local Government Department, which, incidentally, are rather belated.  The latest Report for the Local Government Department is for the year 1931.  The Land Commission is more prompt.  Their Report for 1932 has been published.  Portion of these loan transactions is set out in the Report of the Local Government Department.  Other loan transactions are set out in the Report of the Public Works Department and, I believe, others are contained in the Report of the Land Commission.  I suggest to the Minister that, in view of the growing magnitude of local loans, he should consider consolidating the whole of the operations in respect of these loans in one account, preferably directly under the Department of Finance.  To scatter them about in the form of memoranda accounts in different Departments is very confusing and does not give anybody interested in these matters the information they have a right to expect.</P>
    <P>I pass now to the rather bigger question which the Minister dealt with in his speech&mdash;national indebtedness.  In his speech the Minister referred to our present indebtedness&mdash;about £38,000,000 gross.  That does not, of course, take into account any set-off for reproductive assets.  In the Finance Accounts of 1931-32&mdash;the latest accounts available&mdash;that indebtedness is shown at a standard figure of £31,000,000.  I suppose that figure has not appreciably diminished since 1931-32.  There is, however, a very substantial figure&mdash; £12,000,000&mdash;now to be added.  That is in respect of the 4½ per cent. land bonds.  Hitherto land bonds had only to be shown as a contingent liability. That position could, perhaps, be sustained inasmuch as the land bonds were financed out of the annuities. Now that half the annuities have been definitely abandoned, one half of these land bonds cease to be a contingent <Col N="230" /> liability and become a direct liability. To that extent, our national indebtedness must be increased.  On the basis of the figures which I have before me, our national indebtedness must stand now in the region of £43,000,000.  That is adding half of the issue of land bonds up to 1932.  As a matter of fact, I imagine the issue of land bonds now is somewhat greater and that we should add somewhere about £15,000,000 to our direct indebtedness.</P>
    <P>With regard to assets, I should, like to know from the Minister whether it is the custom to examine closely the realisable value of the assets set out in the Finance Accounts&mdash;for instance, whether the Minister considers that all the local loans are good in view of the increasing burden on the local councils; whether the item of £463,000&mdash;I am now quoting from the 1931-32 Finance Accounts&mdash;in respect of creameries is good; whether this item &mdash;it may have disappeared since&mdash;of £50,000 in respect of the Industrial Trust Company is good.  I should also like to know from the Minister why there is not included in these accounts an asset in respect of the equalisation account for savings certificates.  There was set up some years ago a definite fund which was ear-marked for the payment of interest on savings certificates. On page 30 of the Finance Accounts details of that amount are set out.  I should have thought that that was an asset and that it would have been definitely included as an asset in Account No. 26.</P>
    <P>In referring to the relief that the State has gained by its recent action in withholding annuities and pensions, the Minister mentioned the very large and rather startling sum of £92,000,000 as the gain to the State by Government policy.  I am not saying whether or not that figure is correct&mdash;whether it is the ultimate value of these annuities, which have to run for a number of years, and these pensions which, of course, are a wasting asset. From the point of view of actuarial calculation, the figure may be right, but we have to look at it from the point of view of relief to the Exchequer.  Some of these moneys which have been written off from the <Col N="231" /> Budgetary point of view and which have passed into the hands of the annuitants we may, I think, regard as a loss from the Exchequer point of view.  I do not think that the Minister would suggest that these remissions are increasing the taxable capacity of those who benefit from them&mdash;that the farmer who now pays only half his annuities is any more fertile a source of revenue than he was before he gained these remissions.  Looking at the matter from the point of view of relief to the Exchequer, this appears to be the position: revenue gains about £1,000,000 by non-payment of pensions, and about £1,500,000 by non-payment of annuities, representing a total of about £2,700,000.  From that has to be deducted the annuities remitted in land bonds, because these are a dead loss to the State.  Actually, the benefit to revenue of the whole transaction appears to be somewhere in the region of £2,000,000&mdash;a very different figure, when looked at in that way, from the £92,000,000 which the country is supposed to have benefited.  Against that, there is certainly some loss in moral values.  As regards the material set-off, I think it is within our knowledge that, whatever the direct gain may have been, the farming community has suffered by the reactions of the whole transaction.  I see Senator Quirke's eye upon me and he will, no doubt, tell me that we cannot have any debate here without dragging in the economic war.  So, I will leave it at that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not what brought my eye upon Senator Sir John Keane.  What brought my attention to the Senator was the fact that he was trying to convince us that the attitude of the Government in reducing the annuities on agricultural land by half did not affect the farmer in any way.  I suggest that whatever land Senator Sir John Keane has has gone up in value as a result of that remission. His land would be valued at a much greater price now than it would have been before that action was taken by the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Senator has <Col N="232" /> referred to me personally, may I say that I do not feel that my power to bear increased taxation has in any way increased because of the fact that I have had a small remission of my annuities.  That would be the opinion of most farmers.  It will be noticed that under &ldquo;Miscellaneous Revenue&rdquo; a large sum has been taken to credit. The Minister has said that, of that sum, nearly £3,000,000 is on account of the land annuities.  Could the Minister tell us up to what date the Land Commission annuities have been handed over and whether that £3,000,000, now coming into Miscellaneous Revenue, represents the total amount to the credit of the Land Purchase Fund at the date of transfer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I notice a curious transaction which the Minister referred to himself. Of the £3,000,000, land annuities, transferred to Miscellaneous Revenue, £1,600,000 was taken from the Guarantee Fund.  That suggests that this sum of £3,000,000 was not all land annuities but was made up, to the extent of over £1,000,000 by the Guarantee Fund taking the place of unpaid annuities.  Annuities were not paid.  Under the law, the Guarantee Fund had to make good the default and the Guarantee Fund, as the accounts show, did pay into the Land Purchase Fund and, ultimately, into Miscellaneous Revenue £1,600,000. Can the Minister tell us the future position of this Guarantee Fund&mdash; whether he proposes to continue it under what remains of this land purchase transaction; whether it will continue in respect of the moiety of annuities to be paid in future and whether it will continue in respect of annuities in both pre-Treaty and post-Treaty categories.  I would ask the Minister seriously to consider how unfair the whole position of this Guarantee Fund is in regard to local finances, how utterly unfair it is to make deductions from the Agricultural Grant on account of annuities which the local authorities have no power to collect themselves.  The present position, of course, is inherited from the period when these deductions were made as a form of security by an outside power.  Conditions since we <Col N="233" /> obtained our own Government are totally different and a reform of the system is long overdue.</P>
    <P>I turn now to the item of income tax.  I notice that the Minister is very informative in his speech in regard to the position of income tax.  He budgets for less income tax for the current year and from a reference in a speech on another Bill, I gather that he is of the opinion that we have reached the limit of the income taxpayers' capacity, that if we impose any more taxation we pass into the region of diminishing returns.  In his speech on the Public Services (Temporary Economies) Bill he said there was no chance of getting any more out of income tax.  That is a serious matter, affecting generally the whole elasticity and the buoyancy of our financial position. A good deal of capital has been made and a good deal of debate has centred round the question of excess profits duty and the Government have been accused of being unduly harsh in the action that they are now taking to recover excess profits that arose 15 or 16 years ago.  I think the Minister might tell us to what extent pressure was relaxed in that regard by the present Government or by its predecessors. If pressure has been continuous I do not think much hardship could arise but, if for a lengthy period the matter had been allowed to lie dormant and people had been led to believe that it has been forgotten, a pre-Treaty transaction&mdash;at one period we know that people were practically told not to pay income tax&mdash;those who are now being pressed have a justifiable sense of grievance.  There has in recent years been a big change in the value of money.  These excess profits were made at a time when prices were high, when trade was good and it is vary hard on these people unless they have been defaulting all the time, to press them to pay all the arrears now.</P>
    <P>I now come to the question of the Budget deficiency and balance.  The deficiency, as the Minister said in his speech this year, works out at the alarming figure of £5,000,000 on a total Budget, including all items, of £35,000,000.  There is a deficiency in <Col N="234" /> the actual tax and non-tax revenue of £5,000,000 in about £26,000,000.  I suggest that a deficiency of some 20 or 25 per cent. is a rather big item. The Minister takes 16 pages in his speech in leading up to the deficiency and he disposes of that deficiency in the short space of four pages.  I must say that I had to admire the facility, the financial wizardry almost and the dexterity with which the Minister disposed of that very substantial item. Incidentally, I would ask whether that is really the whole deficit.</P>
    <P>The Minister does not appear to have made provision for certain moneys that will be required, as far as one can see, under the new scheme for industrial credit.  Now we come to the manner, a very important aspect of the problem, in which that balance is effected.  We have first of all an item for over-estimation. That has been a continuous item ever since we have had our own Government.  What puzzles one is why the estimation is always over.  In ordinary life we sometimes estimate over and we sometimes estimate short. Always to estimate over is to suggest that there is some looseness or lack of close scrutiny in the preparation of the Estimates.  I do not think that that practice of over-estimation prevails in other countries.  I may be wrong, but it seems to be an entirely peculiar quality of our own.  With one's knowledge of these matters, I cannot see how it can be a continuing item always, a sort of nest-egg on which successive Ministers can draw.  Then there is a surplus.  Of course that is naturally a proper item to help either to relieve taxation or to meet increased expenditure. Then there are the &ldquo;cuts,&rdquo; of which we shall have sufficient at another time.  There is a negligible amount of fresh taxation and there is also what I think is the somewhat anxious and dubious element of borrowing.</P>
    <P>This borrowing is a growing practice, and I would suggest, although I do not want to be too doctrinaire about it, that it is a practice that requires to be approached with great caution.  There is a great element of danger in it.  It is a practice that becomes very insinuating, that holds out a great <Col N="235" /> temptation to successive Ministers to lean more and more on, and that tends to weaken the austerity and the hardness that I think sound Finance Ministers should adopt.  It was no doubt justified when it was begun.  It was justified in abnormal times when there were heavy civil war losses, but as time has gone on it is a practice that I think should have been brought under much stricter control.  I am going to suggest that perhaps the time has now come, if it is not overdue, when we should definitely force ourselves to examine it in a more critical spirit.  This year there are certain elements of borrowing which perhaps nobody can question.  There is borrowing for property losses and for the repayment of the Dáil Eireann Loan. Even there you might ask why have not the repayments of that Dáil Eireann Loan been provided out of some Sinking Fund?  There is borrowing for the Barrow drainage, borrowing which I think in view of the practice previously observed, is legitimate. Then we come to the borrowing of £1,200,000 for bounties, half the figure we propose to pay on the bounty.</P>
    <P>The Minister in his speech says that that borrowing is justified by certain assets that have been created.  I hope the Minister will be more precise on that because personally I cannot see what free assets have been created. Does he suggest that the remission of the annuities represents an increased taxable capacity which justifies this borrowing?  Does he suggest that half the annuities which are going into the Exchequer, and more than which is being spent in the Budget, represents an asset on which to borrow?  Personally I think it is a very dubious item.  It is an unsound element in our Budgetary finance.  How are we to get to grips with this question, this annual borrowing, this serious element that comes into our Budget?  It is an element that without certain justification, is dangerous on the face of it, one of which we should be very suspicious, one which tends to increase and towards which we should be very vigilant.</P>
    <P>I would suggest to the Minister <Col N="236" /> seriously to consult his officials as to the desirability of definitely dividing his Budget into two parts, that he should have a capital Budget and a revenue Budget and that he should take them at different times, in two separate, one might almost say, watertight sections.  Let him introduce his capital Budget and justify the items in it and let him at another time take his revenue Budget, set it out and balance it.  I do not believe, unless he does something of that kind, that he will ever allay the uneasy feeling that people have that there is an element of unsound manipulation in the balancing of our Budget.  I make that suggestion to him in a helpful spirit.  Let him justify our capital expenditure and the capital borrowing which it would involve, and keep that separated and in different documents in every way, from the purely recurrent revenue items.  I can see no administrative difficulty except of course certain inconvenience.  I know how unpleasant inconvenience in these matters can be to the administrative sections.  Only however by the methods which I have indicated shall we ever be able to visualise our Budget and keep a check on this very dangerous element in finance.</P>
    <P>In my closing remarks, I wish to refer to what, I feel, seemed&mdash;it is only a point of view&mdash;the rather undue and unwarranted optimism of the Minister towards our general financial condition at present and in the future. We have to note that on the figures before us we have a decline in the region of four millions in revenue taxation and an increase in expenditure of two millions.  There is a gap there of six millions.  In spite of that, the Minister seems to be quite happy, quite light-hearted and quite satisfied. We do not want him to be a doleful pessimist or to say that things are not as good as he naturally would wish them to be but in his opening speech he refers to a substantial reduction in the volume of unemployment.  I do not know what figures there are to justify that statement.  There may be a slight reduction in unemployment in the cities, but what about the terrible position of people who are dependent <Col N="237" /> on agriculture?  He refers to increased bank clearances.  There have been increased bank clearances but there has been a lot of money from the sweepstakes passing through the banks in recent years which would explain a certain amount of the increase.  He says that the sufferings in certain directions have been more than compensated for by the extraordinary expansion in our domestic commerce.  That there are sufferings is undoubted.  There has been a shrinkage in our trade of about one-third. The expansion in our domestic commerce may be capable of proof by figures but I do not think it has been felt by those living in the country.  If you talk to shopkeepers or people engaged in our basic industry, they will tell you that there is a state of stagnation. There has been a fillip given by tariffs to certain industries in towns, but I do not think that the description of &ldquo;an extraordinary expansion in our domestic commerce&rdquo; is really warranted by the facts.  It is only a straw which shows the way his mind works and I am rather concerned as to the relative values the Minister seemed to place on expenditure and revenue.  He seems rather to exalt expenditure and not to have such regard to economy.</P>
    <P>For instance, he says, in his Budget speech, that the Government will consider most sympathetically any suggestions that are made that will improve the conditions of our people and will not reject them on the narrow ground of expense.  I do not feel that, from a Finance Minister, the phrase &ldquo;the narrow ground of expense&rdquo; quite reveals the conservative state of mind that we expect.  I can understand people in the country, who are not in responsible positions, wanting money spent for everything.  I may be old-fashioned, or brought up in contact with old-fashioned beliefs, but I think that the best way to save money is not to spend it and I rather lean to the old-fashioned Minister for Finance who had to be bally-ragged into giving money. Instead of that, this year, we have the Minister seeming to indicate that there will be money for everything and that on a decreasing revenue.  At the same time, his state of mind is also revealed in his statement: &ldquo;I have now to consider <Col N="238" /> the not less important side of the account&rdquo; that is, where the money is to come from.  I suggest that the bias is wrong and that is why I am rather alarmed when I see all these grand schemes being put forward by a Government that came in pledged to economy and all these schemes by which the Government is going to go into business where, if the public will not subscribe, the Government will step in and will not be deterred on the narrow ground of expense, while the person that we rather look on as the guardian of the public purse appears to be quite happy and light-hearted. I know that it can be argued that efficient Governments can spend money and that the State can do things as well as individuals but I cannot see that that is borne out by experience. I feel that what the public should expect, in regard to central finance and in regard to those who have control of our financial policy, is the old-fashioned, conservative caution and we should not, even if our debt is small, which I admit it is, rather encourage the spirit that it is a good thing to borrow more and to spend more.  I should rather see your borrowing determined on the elasticity and buoyancy of your revenue and where the revenue is, on the Government Estimates, declining, that is the time not to borrow but rather to shorten the purse strings and let what money is wanted be found by the people and not by the State.  It is for that reason that I have dealt with this subject at rather undue length and I hope the House will forgive me.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not propose, after the very searching inquiry into the figures made by Senator Sir John Keane, to deal in detail with this measure.  There is just the one fact staring out from it and it is that, in the course of 12 months, a sum varying between £4,000,000 and £5,000,000 has been lost to the State.  We are, every day, getting reminders that there is an economic war on, and it is because of that economic war that this money has been lost.  Fortunately for the followers of the Government, they do not seem to have felt the effect of this war.  There is a Providence, apparently, <Col N="239" /> that looks after them and the burden has only fallen on those who are in Opposition.  We, of course, congratulate the Fianna Fáil farmers and business people who have felt none of the ill-effects of the loss of this £4,000,000 or £5,000,000, but I think they will excuse us if we deny that the economic war is a joke.  It is a very grim joke for a lot of us and we have seen the effect of it in all our business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>You are only beginning to feel it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>We are only beginning to feel it but we have all found it so far.  They accuse us in this matter of standing with England and that is just the point that I should like to examine.  The world recognises that England is a place in which there is commercial capacity.  In fact we are assured that John Bull's Island is entirely composed of shopkeepers and we have faced that very formidable opponent with a Government which is known as Fianna Fáil.  I do not understand Irish, I regret to say, but I am told that the translation of Fianna Fáil is &ldquo;soldiers of adventure&rdquo; or &ldquo;soldiers of fortune.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusRobinson" hpid="Mr. S. Robinson Mr. S. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>Destiny.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>Misfortune.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>I may be quite wrong but, at all events, it seems to me that we want something more.  When there is fighting to be done, soldiers are very valuable, but in an economic war, it is more essential to have hard-headed business men to fight on your side. Can anyone in this Assembly believe for a moment that English statesmen had to rely on suggestions from this side of the water as to how they would conduct their campaign?  I think they have proved to the world that, in business, at all events, they are as astute as the best.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Most of us who are not on the Government side know what this has cost Ireland.  I am going to spare you a recital of all that but what we should like to know now is what it has cost England.  I know for a fact that it has cost us a lot but I should like to hear from the Minister a detailed <Col N="240" /> account of how England has suffered in this war.  Her condition, apparently, is improving.  Her agriculture has got a distinct fillip because of this economic war.  Her unemployment is growing less and a funny thing is that when the ships that come over to the quays of Cork laden with German coal&mdash;this I cannot vouch for, but I am told by a man in the coal trade that it is a fact&mdash;leave our port, they square away for Cardiff, or another Welsh port, and load up there with coal for Germany. I suppose that means a saving to us in freight costs.</P>
    <P>We are told that this war would have ceased long since if we had stood behind the President in this quarrel.  I should like the Minister to tell me how we could have influenced the forces against us if Ireland, with one voice, had shouted out to England: &ldquo;We are all right; every step that we have taken in this warfare was a correct step,&rdquo; and England had no option but to surrender at discretion?  There is just one more word I wish to say before I sit down.  I would ask the Minister to explain to us when we have won this great contest how we are to know it?  We hear that we are winning every day but we want to know what definite fact will assure us that we have triumphed and that, once and for all, we have established our superiority over England and any other country that may come along.</P>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy of the Reeks The McGillycuddy of the Reeks">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy of the Reeks</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that, after Senator Sir John Keane's speech, what I propose to say is rather an anti-climax, but, while the Minister is in a kindly mood, I should like to come forward with a sound, constructive proposal for improving the condition of our people and I hope that he will carry out his policy of listening sympathetically, quite regardless of expense, as he assured us was his policy.  Last year, I approached him on the question of the remission of the tax on various games and sports in this country and he said, at the time, that, owing to the national emergency, he was not able to accede to my request.  I warned him of what would happen and, this year, he has met us in respect of certain games such as badminton, <Col N="241" /> boxing, tennis and, finally, rowing, but he has stopped at the point where he has made sure of a safe passage across to the other side about which I warned him last year.  I do not want him to stop here.</P>
      <P>In the course of his speech in the Dáil, he told Deputies that all the games, whether he taxed them or not, played in this country were Irish games and that they were Irish games because they were played by Irishmen in this country.  Yet he stopped short at rowing and he still discriminates between the Gaelic games and Rugby and Association.  The Gaelic games were exempted, last year, on the ground of national culture and, as they themselves admit, they are now in a very sound financial position, but the tax on Rugby and Association still remains.  The Minister said, quite rightly, that it was not only the players he was taxing but the onlookers.  The discrimination, however, still goes on and I think the games are suffering to a certain extent and, what is more, I feel that it is neither fair to the onlookers nor to the players.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>He said that he cannot give up this tax from which he receives £15,000.  I should very much like to hear the Minister elaborate those figures.  In answer to a question in the Dáil, he said that these figures could not be separated and, thereafter, we had a statement, in reply to an amendment, that actually £15,000 was produced from outdoor entertainments by those particular people who are taxed.  I took the trouble to go to the Rugby Union, and of that £15,000 the Rugby Union are finding somewhere about £3,000.  That means that £12,000 is found by the Association and other people, Rugby being quite the biggest game.  I should like to hear that elaborated and to hear if the Minister is quite sure of his figures.  Last year, we had to fight this thing right to the finish and, in actual fact, the Dáil was brought back from its holiday and, but for the Whips being put on, the tax would have been taken off by the Dáil itself.  The Minister has met us half way this year and I should like to hear him say that, if it is in any way <Col N="242" /> possible, he will remove what I regard as this very unjust tax next year.  I do not want to press this or to waste his time or the time of the Dáil by bringing it back, as we did last year, unnecessarily, because I realise his difficulties.  I do not propose to refer to why or for what reason they have been caused nor do I want to put down any unnecessary recommendation, if the Minister will give us some indication that he will deal sympathetically with my suggestion either by removing this tax altogether next year or by reducing it to a figure that will allow these clubs not only to exist but to expand as they should expand and as other games are allowed to expand in this country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been disappointed to-day because I thought Senator Colonel Moore would have risen early in this discussion to denounce the present Minister for Finance.  My reason for that is that when discussing the last Bill of the present Minister's predecessor, on 15th July, 1931, Senator Colonel Moore made use of the following words:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;As far as taxation is concerned, the great fault is that taxation is twice as high as it should be.  The opportunity to remedy that, I hope, will come one of these days when the Minister hands over his job to somebody else.  I hope the poor will get the benefit of the reduction to as great an extent as, if not greater, than the richer classes.  But the first thing is to reduce taxation wholesale.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I want to quote the Minister for Finance of that year.  Speaking in the Dáil on 6th May, 1931, in the course of his speech dealing with finances, for which the Senator denounced Mr. Blythe, he said:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The White Paper issued a week ago shows that the estimated amount required to maintain public services and to meet other necessary public charges during the year 1931-32 is in respect of Central Fund Services £4,442,677, and in respect to Supply Services £21,921,573, or an aggregate of £26,364,250.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="243" /> These are the figures Senator Colonel Moore denounced.  Speaking in the Dáil on 10th May of this year, the present Minister for Finance said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;We have now to consider the position in the present.  For that we must turn first of all to the figures for expenditure which appear in the White Paper which has just been circulated. It will be noted from the figures given therein that the total expenditure on Central Fund and Supply Services is taken at £30,654,220, of which £4,729,269 is for Central Fund Services and £25,924,951 for Supply.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The silence of the Senator can only be explained by the fact that he is absolutely stupefied and astounded that the Minister, whom he fondly expected would reduce taxation wholesale, has done quite the opposite.  I can quite understand the amazement of the Senator, and how difficult it is for him to pull himself together.  Before the discussion closes I hope he will have sufficiently recovered from the shock that he has sustained to hurl some thunderbolts at the head of the Minister for Finance like those he hurled at his predecessor.</P>
    <P>Senator Sir John Keane referred to a statement which was made by the Minister here last week and he appealed for information for which I also appeal:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I have already informed the Seanad that there has been provided this year £2,450,000 for export bounties and subsidies.  Against this expenditure, however, certain assets have been created and on the security of these assets it has been decided to borrow £1,225,000 and to use it to defray one half of the cost of the subsidies.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>It is only fair to the House that the Minister should be more precise in his disclosures.  What is the nature and what is the volume of the assets upon which he proposes to borrow?  I do not want to obscure that by further emphasising it, but I make the definite point that I want information and the Minister can deal with it when replying. What are those assets?  What is <Col N="244" /> their nature and their volume?  And if they are assets can they be considered sound assets and good security in the money market for the money it is proposed to borrow?  Until we know what these assets are and their nature, we will be in a quandary as to what the prospects really are of borrowing the money it is proposed to borrow.  We have heard from the Minister and we have seen indications that the revenue of the State is dwindling.  We are conscious of the fact that one of the reasons for that is that the sources from which revenue came had become exhausted or diminished and we come, then, to understand the alternative sources of potential revenue that have been created within the State itself.  If that is so, no one will be more gratified than myself.  On the question of economic and industrial development within the State, any really sincere and efficient effort has my full sympathy.  The one ground on which I will refrain from offering adverse criticism of the present Government is that which may be described as the zone of their economic efforts.  Unfortunately, the grounds of selection for adverse criticism independent of the zone I have referred to are so tremendous that there is really no necessity to seek for grounds of criticism of the Government in that respect.  My reference to this is not intended as adverse criticism, but rather as an inquiry.  In the debate on the Second Reading of the Public Service (Temporary Economies) Bill in the Dáil, the Minister for Industry and Commerce depicted in very glowing terms the industrial development that had ensued under the guidance of the present Ministry. Of course, the arguments were more or less in general terms and very little in the way of exact data was produced. He was replying to Deputy McGilligan and it is upon this point that I want to have an inquiry, and he said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Deputies know quite well that the revenues earned by traders and industrialists in this year will not be reflected in the public revenues until next year.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I would like to have the opinion of the <Col N="245" /> Minister if he really thinks that there are being created within this State alternative sources of revenue the fruits of which will be reflected in the Budget or the finances for next year. I would like to press this further consideration in regard to that, that I would advise the Minister not to be keen upon the effort to extract revenue from these sources in the immediate future as an alternative to sources of revenue which have been destroyed by another phase of Government policy.  The building up of industrial enterprise is difficult, arduous and a serious task.  If the Minister peremptorily endeavours to convert these industries into revenue-producing assets, it is quite possible that the force of financial circumstances may compel him to endeavour to extract the last fraction of taxation from them with the consequence that he may kill the goose that might eventually have laid golden eggs.  Whether he considers what I have said worthy of comment or not, I hope the Minister will tell us whether or not the Minister for Industry and Commerce was unduly optimistic or simply practical when he indicated that the revenue from these sources would be reflected in next year's finances.  There was one thing I missed from the Estimates this year and from the whole financial statement of the Minister.  It surprised me in view of what I read in the <i>Sunday Dispatch</i> last Sunday, that according to an interview with Senator Comyn, that the Government are on the brink of declaring their ownership of the territorial waters within the three miles limit within the whole of this island.  I should have expected that there would have been some provision or Estimate in the way of naval or sea defences in this year's finances. I hope the Minister will explain this deficiency and how it comes that a loyal, staunch and veteran supporter of his Party's policy should be misled into making such a statement if the Minister had no intention of giving effect to it.</P>
    <P>However, I think before we decide to build a navy&mdash;I do not really think there is any present urgency about <Col N="246" /> that, even though it may lead to Senator Comyn being appointed admiral of the high seas of the Free State. It is not an adequate reason for embarking on such an enterprise.  I think it is more important to build up the nation.  That is one reason why I take grave exception to the general aspect of Government policy: its failure to visualise and to grasp what are the essentials for building up the nation. In some of his arguments a favourite phrase used by the Minister for Finance has been that you cannot make an omelette without breaking eggs and, apparently, judging by the policy of the Government they believe that you cannot make a nation without breaking the people.  That is the phase that has characterised the general tendency of the activities of the Ministry.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Industry and Commerce prophesied that with the advent of Fianna Fáil there would be lighter rates and taxes and better times generally for everyone.  Can anybody say that that has emerged from the Government's policy?  Can anyone say that this country and its people are one whit better off to-day, or one inch further on the road to real progressive prosperity, or one iota free than they were on the day when the people of this State gave Fianna Fáil the reins of power?  Some people may say that it is premature to expect that yet, but those who are plain citizens of this State and have no political axe to grind, can only judge a policy by its results and, so far as those results have revealed anything, they have revealed a greater strain upon the finances of the nation; a greater strain on the resources of the people, and a greater degree of anxiety in every home in the land as well as a greater fear for the future in the hearts and minds of every citizen of this State.</P>
    <P>There is just one more query that I want to address to the Minister.  He said that &ldquo;Section 25 of the Bill gives the Revenue Commissioners power to determine the category or class to which an article belongs.&rdquo;  That is a very important section.  In connection with it, certain articles have been imported into this country in recent <Col N="247" /> times.  I would like to ask the Minister if he can give me any indication as to the particular category in which they would be classified; whether as wearing apparel, souvenirs or white elephants.  I refer to the tall hats worn by members of the Executive Council in Ottawa and Paris.  There is just one further point on that.  I would like to know if there has been any revenue derived from such importations and, if so, will it go into the Central Fund or be placed in a suspense account to be kept there until such time as Ministers learn to garb themselves as fittingly for ceremonial occasions at home as they do abroad?</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I have promised to myself this afternoon the pleasure of sitting here and listening to the various speeches that would be made on this measure.  I certainly looked forward with great pleasure to the irrelevancies which I expected from my friend, but I did not expect that his imagination would roam so far as the irrelevancy of which he has been guilty in reference to myself.  He purports to have given the House a quotation of mine, made from an English Sunday paper.  Now, one of the things that we ought to be careful of here is this: when we quote from a book, from a paper or from a speech we ought to be accurate, because we are expected to be believed.  Now, I am sorry to say that my friend, Senator Milroy, has misquoted what appeared in that Sunday paper.  I do not say that he did that deliberately, but you see he wanted that it should glide in beautifully into the period of his eloquence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now what happened in regard to these territorial waters is this: Some time ago, in the course of a debate in this House, I did state that in my opinion all the territorial waters surrounding this country were the property of the Free State.  That seemed to have come rather as a surprise to a number of people, journalists and historians. Some days ago, on the introduction of the Whip of my own Party, a historian approached me and asked me whether I would elaborate the <Col N="248" /> observation that I made in reference to territorial waters.  I did elaborate that argument.  It is rather a simple argument and a conclusive argument. I did say that the grant of Dominion status conveyed in the Treaty&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is now going away from the Bill before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>When misquoted I am entitled to correct the quotation. What I did state was this: that the grant of Dominion status to this country carried with it the grant of territorial waters surrounding the country, that the right of the inhabitants of any particular part of the country, to vote themselves out had no effect upon the grant except in so far as it related to the particular territory that voted out; that the effect of any number of people in a particular part of Ireland voting themselves out did not operate as a regrant to Great Britain of the territorial waters which they had granted to us.</P>
      <P>Now, that was a plain and simple statement of fact and I emphasised it by saying this: that a grantor cannot derogate from his grant.  That is what I said substantially, and that is what is contained in the newspaper report which was made without my being aware of it, but I repudiate nothing. I wish to correct the wrong impression which might be gathered from what my friend Senator Milroy said. I do not for one moment accuse Senator Milroy of deliberately wishing to misrepresent me, but I do think it is unfair of him to say, or to pretend to infer from what appeared in any paper, that I have any responsibility for Government policy or any knowledge of Government policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>That astonishes me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator referred to me as being an old and staunch supporter of Fianna Fáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought you were.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am an old and staunch supporter of the unity and freedom of <Col N="249" /> this country, and I have no other allegiance but that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. Jameson Mr. Jameson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jameson</NameTxt>
      <P>I had not intended to say much on this Bill.  After the very able criticism of the economic position that we had from Senator Sir John Keane, I do not think it is necessary for me to say much.  This morning I got a paper dealing with the Pig Industries Tribunal &ldquo;concerning immediate measures necessary for the control of the exports of bacon and live pigs from Saorstát Eireann in view of the steps being taken in Great Britain of regulating quantitatively the imports of these commodities to that country.&rdquo;  I have been across the water lately, and that particular report struck me as pointing to what is really a very great danger here at this moment.  Senator Crosbie talked about the economic war.  The consequences of it were revealed to us in the Budget statement.  We are spending millions in trying to keep up a trade with the other side.  We are doing that by means of bounties.  They give us no return.  They simply increase our expenditure and all that money is utterly lost.  I am not able to say whether the people who are intended to benefit from these bounties are, in fact, being benefited.  At any rate these bounties are costing this country a huge sum of money for which there is no return.  For that reason, there is not much use in criticising the Minister's Budget statement from the point of view of a country living on its own resources and doing business in the ordinary way.  The Minister is bound to spend these moneys and the taxpayers to find them. From the point of view of the economist, it is all sheer waste. We are spending a lot and we are getting nothing.  The real danger in connection with these bounties is that&mdash;there is no question whatever but this is the case&mdash;they are raising a very strong feeling against the people who are trying to export those commodities into Great Britain and Northern Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There always is, and has been as long as I remember, a very strong prejudice in every country against a <Col N="250" /> country which gives bounties to force its goods into another country.  The traders in the country affected and the people who produce the same goods are always trying to bring pressure on their Government to battle on their behalf and to place extra duties on the goods of the country which is giving the bounties. That is absolutely certain in regard to countries trading with one another. That prejudice is rising strongly in Great Britain and Northern Ireland against the exporters of agricultural produce for the Free State.  Very strong pressure is being brought to bear upon the British Government to put taxes on various imports from this country.  This practice is making them far more willing to look to all the other Dominions and, indeed, to the other countries of Europe to see if they will deal with them as we were dealing with Great Britain.  We have no representation whatever.  We have nobody sitting at the councils of the British authorities who are trying to regulate their taxation and their imports to see that we get quotas fixed favourably for this country.  We are not making a single arrangement for trade concessions with Great Britain nor, so far as I know, with any of the other Dominions.  I have already mentioned once or twice that in my own business we have been injured for the want of a concession, particularly in respect of New Zealand.  The words I used then remain true to-day.  I never heard of any concession given us by New Zealand or any effort to get one.  Even if we get the wonderful trade that is to be created in our own country and if our manufactures develop as the Government hope they will, if we have to wait for that state of affairs to mature in order to make arrangements with the country that buys practically all our surplus products, we will find that market filled up.  They will have made arrangements with every other Dominion and with all the other countries of Europe with whom they are hoping to get trade agreements.  By the time we come in, I doubt if we will be able to find any place for our goods.  The country and the Government should <Col N="251" /> look at this matter extremely seriously.  Time is going.  If we wait until some change occurs which will enable us to sit down at table with our best customers and make trade arrangements with them, our trade may be gone.  Others are pushing into the markets and getting quotas and arrangements made.  It will be no use turning round then and saying &ldquo;export.&rdquo;  Other people will have the markets.</P>
    <P>I have just come back from the other side and it gives one cause to pause and think when we have nobody that I know of sitting down and trying to get good trade arrangements made for this country.  If I am wrong, the Minister will probably tell us.  So far as I know, we have nobody negotiating for us, while the other Dominions and the other countries in Europe are negotiating.  If we have that state of affairs going on for long &mdash;things are moving very rapidly&mdash;by the time we wake up, even if we make an arrangement with Great Britain and the economic war ends, it may be of no use to us.  Our markets will have gone.  These are matters which are far beyond any Budget, but I thought I ought to refer to them, especially when we have a notice which bluntly tells us that England is now arranging her quotas, while we have nobody to assist or help in getting decent treatment for the exports from this country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>It was said that Nelson used to put his telescope to his blind eye when he was going to fight.  I think that Senator Jameson did the same thing in giving us the account he has given of the state of affairs here.  He seems to suggest that this international war is entirely on our side, that we have given these bounties and other things by way of attack rather than by way of defence. Of course, some changes have been made for trade purposes.  Other countries do that and so does Britain.  In the main, the Senator attributes the present position to some foolish idea we have had in starting this trade war.  I happened to be in London more <Col N="252" /> than a year ago when the British Government introduced a Bill to enable them to penalise the trade of Ireland on account of some financial disagreement which had nothing to do with trade.  In spite of the unreasonableness of it, that Bill was passed through Parliament to enable them to recoup themselves certain moneys we had not thought we owed them.  I am not going into the question whether we owed them or not.  That is an old tale.  The fact is that we offered everything reasonable.  We offered to give them an international tribunal to settle all these affairs.  They would not have that for certain reasons and they imposed these penal taxes to force us to pay what we did not think we owed.  They had a double purpose in that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Shortly afterwards, they said: &ldquo;If you give us some political advantages, we will take away those taxes.&rdquo;  I am only quoting from Mr. Thomas who made these statements and has been repeating them ever since, so that there is no mistake about it.  They had this double-barrelled gun against us.  On the one hand, they wanted to recover certain moneys which they said were due and, on the other hand, they wanted to secure some political advantages.  What were we to do under those circumstances?  People like Senator Jameson have been talking for some months in this indefinite way and saying that we ought to settle the business.  How are we to settle it? There are only two ways.  One is to pay the money they claim, whether we owe it or not; the other is to give them certain political advantages which they are trying to get from us.  They got various things from us in the last few hundred years by putting financial and military pressure upon us.  They are doing the same thing now and I say we are not going to sacrifice ourselves in that way for them.  We have a battle to fight as we had in 1916 and we have to fight it out.  It is very disagreeable, I agree.  It is not a nice thing to do but I see no remedy.  If Senator Jameson would tell us how to settle the business I should be very glad.  I know of no way except complete surrender to certain claims which <Col N="253" /> the British have made upon us, which, we think, are not justified.  We offered them a tribunal to establish whether we were right or wrong.  We know we are right.  Everybody on both sides has begun to admit that we were right. Even the lawyers over there have found that they were in the wrong altogether and are admitting it. People who lecture us in this way and tell us we are wrong in keeping on the war should tell us how we are going to get out of it.  If they are so wise as to be able to give us an idea how to get out of it, I dare say we will take it, but certainly not by surrender.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to say once more what I said over and over again, that this Government embarked on a policy of dishonesty and embezzlement and that they had better make up their minds how they will deal with the chickens which are coming home to roost.  It is up to them to get out of the difficulty in which they placed this country.  It is not for us to point out how this dispute should be settled.  We protested when this business of withholding the land annuities was proposed.  We told the Government what would happen.  Senator Jameson has done a very great service to the country&mdash;I am sorry there was not a bigger House here to hear him&mdash;by pointing out the imminent danger in which we are.  We are on the edge of a precipice so far as this country is concerned.  The Minister sits there as he sat in the Dáil last night with his pleasant smile, as remarked by a Deputy.  He made in the Dáil the most callous and false statement about the state of agriculture. He must be incompetent to deal with the matter.  He cannot be so blind that he does not realise that he made in the Dáil last night a thoroughly false statement as to the condition of agriculture.  He made a thoroughly callous allusion to the sufferings of the farmers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Please let us not discuss the economic war any longer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been discussed by others and I suppose I am entitled to say a few words.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="254" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I allowed the Senator to say a few words.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I want only to make a formal protest.  Senator Sir John Keane dealt with the Finance Bill. Senator Johnson has pointed out the very real and terrible danger in which the country is.  The Government indulges in the &ldquo;Rake's Progress&rdquo; in the most callous way.  I protest against that in the name of the people of the country.  I do not think I should be here if I did not protest.  I am sorry I have had to speak in this way, but things are becoming very serious. It is the business of the Government to get out of this dispute.  There was an honest way of dealing with it and they neglected it.  Now, let them settle the business.  That is their affair.  It is not our duty to tell them how to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Naturally, I was not a bit surprised at anything Senator Miss Browne said.  In fact, I was agreeably surprised she said so little and dealt in such poor fashion with the economic war.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Senator will not deal with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not propose to go into the matter at all.  It is worthy of note that the Senator never appealed to the Minister for Finance to give us back our markets.  She should not have forgotten that.  Like Senator Colonel Moore, I was amazed to hear Senator Jameson make the statement he did.  Senator Jameson and every sensible man must know that the situation existing between Canada, South Africa, or various other countries and England is not the same as the situation which exists between this country and England.  I do not want to go into the question of the economic war or the question of who started it.  We know who started it or who was responsible for starting it by encouraging other people.  We know who is responsible for the continuation of that conflict which none of us naturally want continued.  Senator Jameson pointed out, if I understood him rightly, that his objection to the <Col N="255" /> bounties on agricultural produce was that people in other countries object to the attitude of the Government in paying bounties on agricultural produce which is being exported to these countries.  I could understand people in England, representatives of the British, putting up that argument and feeling a bit sore about it, but I cannot understand anybody in this country objecting, under the circumstances that at present exist, to the Government providing bounties on agricultural produce to relieve the farmers or objecting to the extent to which they are relieved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>Who is paying the bounties?  Not the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Miss Browne claims that she represents the farmers but I have to say that she is a very poor representative.  She very seldom puts up a reasonable argument in defence of the farmers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I have done it several times.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>She never seems to appreciate anything that is done or any measure that is brought before this House for the benefit of the farmers. To take any serious notice of Senator Milroy would, I suppose, be only bringing the person who took that notice to the same level as the Senator himself, but when he stands up and makes glaringly inaccurate statements it is only right that he should be corrected.  Such statements may have the effect of convincing some people that at least some of them were correct, if they were not contradicted. Senator Milroy talks of the failure of the Government to build up the nation.  He asks the Minister&mdash;and I am sure the Minister is well able to reply himself if he will take the trouble, but he hardly will&mdash;are the people one bit more free than they were before Fianna Fáil came into power?  Senator Milroy knows perfectly well that the people are much more free than when Fianna Fáil came into power.  Several measures have been introduced&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="256" />
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask what all this has got to do with the Finance Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a pity Miss Browne is not in the Chair.  We would have great fun.  Several measures have been introduced to make the people more free than they were under the last Administration and every such measure was strenuously obstructed by Senator Milroy.  As I have often stated before, Senator Milroy is not sincere in his attitude.  Perhaps he is here now.  He generally gets behind me when I am speaking.  I should like to give a little bit of history in connection with Senator Milroy which I quoted here before.  I am quoting from <i>The Nation</i> of December 4th, 1923.  Dealing with economics, Senator Milroy wrote:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;As regards the economic aspect of policy, I have urged repeatedly in and out of the Dáil the necessity of a sound fiscal policy to be used to protect and strengthen our existing industries and for the promotion of others.  On the merits of that idea I am not going to enlarge to-day. To me the need for protective tariffs in this country is a matter outside the regions of argument.  I regard this as axiomatic.  We have this fiscal power to do what is necessary in this respect.  The question is&mdash; are we going to use them?  I know there are powerful influences at work to prevent that being done and to keep this country the bond slave of British economic interests.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;I know there are powerful influences at work.&rdquo;  If I might suggest it I would say that the most powerful influence that can be used in that respect has been used by Senator Milroy and various other Senators in this House to prevent this country from getting out of the position in which it was previously, a position in which the country was described by Senator Milroy as the bond-slave of British economic interests.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator come to the Bill now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Milroy's position <Col N="257" /> is quite inconsistent.  His speech was all froth and no beer, like every speech he makes in this House.  Before I came into this debate I met members of the Opposition in the other House and members of the Opposition in this House, and I was convinced as the result of a conversation I had with them, having read the Bill myself, that this Bill was absolutely above any reasonable criticism.  I understand that certain sections criticise various items in the Bill but I think it is absolutely ridiculous for any man to attack every item in the Bill.  It just goes to prove that members in the Opposition are convinced, or at least they pretend that they are convinced, that nothing good can come from a Fianna Fáil Government.  I did not hear any members of the Opposition admit that there was any good in the Bill.  I would ask these Senators to look at the item of £450,000 which is being provided for relief of the able-bodied unemployed.  I think that is a very good provision.  People talk about protecting the country against Communism. Most of the measures which have been introduced by Fianna Fáil are designed to prevent any such movements as Communism in this country.  Notwithstanding that, these measures are attacked in this House and no credit is given to the Government when measures of that kind are introduced.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The peat scheme is also a very fine project.  There is no necessity to go into figures but I think it is an admirable thing that the Government should take up the development of the peat industry in this country.  A sum of £100,000 has been provided for roads and drainage, £50,000 for organisation and more important, perhaps still, £25,000 for the provision of fuel for the needy poor.  These and several other provisions in the Bill will, I am certain, be welcomed by the people in the country or the majority of them. Naturally there will be a few die-hards here and there as there are in this House and in the other House who will never be pleased, at least in this world.  Perhaps they will in the next. These people are ready to take the example they get from members of the <Col N="258" /> Opposition here and in the Dáil, to criticise everything whether it is right or wrong.  Their attitude is to try to make a case against Fianna Fáil or against whatever Department puts up a Bill or against the Minister who introduces it.  At this late hour I do not propose to go into the various other parts of the Bill which to my mind are admirable and which make provision for schemes which are an absolute necessity if this country is to be rescued from that position in which it was, as described by Senator Milroy, under the late Administration, the bond slave of British economic interests.  I believe in all the circumstances that the Bill is above reasonable criticism and I support it wholeheartedly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusRobinson" hpid="Mr. S. Robinson Mr. S. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the adjournment of the debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Possibly the Senator has some reason for moving the adjournment.  We should like to hear it; otherwise I think we should go on for at least another half an hour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister will probably have to make a very long statement in reply.  It would suit his convenience if he were not called upon to do so to-night.  We can take this as the first business, possibly, next Tuesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that we ought to hear the Minister's statement to-night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister is tired and is not ready, I think that Senators might agree to adjourn now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree, if that is so, but if there are other members of the House who intend to speak, I think it right that they should be heard to-night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it understood that the Minister will not reply to-night?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister would not care to reply to-night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. Guinness Mr. Guinness">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Guinness</NameTxt>
      <P>I wanted to ask the Minister a question in connection with one of the issues of land stock.  Under <Col N="259" /> the Land Act of 1923, 4½ per cent. bonds were issued.  These bonds and the interest on them are a direct responsibility of the Irish Government. They are not in the same category as earlier bonds.  I was anxious to ascertain from the Minister where the interest on these bonds is to be found. The money must be provided out of the annuities, but half the annuities has been remitted.  These annuities have been reduced by 50 per cent. so that the interest would be short by that amount and provision would have to be made for the difference.  Is that the item to which the Minister was referring at the bottom of column 2,295 in which he is reported as saying:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Among the additional services for which provision is covered is a sum of £800,000 to meet a deficiency which arises in the Land Bond Fund&rdquo;?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the item.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. Guinness Mr. Guinness">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Guinness</NameTxt>
      <P>That refers to the 4½ per cent.  Land Bonds of 1923?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. Guinness Mr. Guinness">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Guinness</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to support Senator Sir John Keane's suggestion that in future Budgets or White Papers it might be possible to consolidate all the items connected with local loans.  At the present time they are distributed over three or four separate accounts.  They are really matters connected with the one subject and it would be very much simpler if items connected with local loans were all classified under one heading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I point out that we have a considerable amount of business to transact next week and that if we adjourn consideration of the Public Services (Temporary Economies) Bill, it will add still further to next week's business?  I suggest that if we adjourn now, we might meet again at 8.30.  I would prefer if the Minister would wind up this debate to-night if it would be convenient.  The House could sit until 7.30, or if the <Col N="260" /> House does not choose to do that, we can meet later to-night, say, at 8 o'clock.  If we do not meet at 8 o'clock, let us meet to-morrow but I think that, at any rate, we should dispose of the Second Reading of this Bill.  We had it last week and we have it this week and we have not yet disposed of the Second Reading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>May I explain why I should like the Seanad to extend to me the consideration of adjourning not later than 7 p.m.?  It happens that, by arrangement with all the Parties in the House, business for which I am responsible will be taken in the Dáil at 7.30 and I am rather anxious to have tea in the interval, but, apart altogether from that, I do not think I could reply in the space of half an hour.  Senator Sir John Keane and a number of other Senators have raised particular points which, I think, might be elucidated and, while I would be quite prepared to begin now&mdash;it is not because I lack the material but because of the circumstance I have referred to&mdash;I think that my statement would possibly gain in value if it were either to be deferred until to-morrow, when I could make a complete statement or until such other time as the Seanad may desire.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy of the Reeks The McGillycuddy of the Reeks">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy of the Reeks</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister be in a position to reply at 9 p.m. or 9.30 p.m.?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You are a late bird, Senator.  All the Senators are not, perhaps, as late birds as you are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I would suggest that, in view of the statement of the Minister, we ought to adjourn and meet on Tuesday of next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That would give us another day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I approve of the suggestion that we should meet on Tuesday but I should like to remind the House that there is a total of 21 days during which a Money Bill can be considered and, while not suggesting for a moment that the Minister has anything of the kind in view, a little more adjournment and we will <Col N="261" /> have no opportunity of making recommendations at all.  It might be better to finish the Second Stage.  It would not be stretching our procedure very much to allow the Minister to make a statement at the beginning of the Committee Stage in reply to the various points and let the members of the House put down recommendations. If we postpone the Second Stage until Tuesday and then leave four or five days for recommendations on Committee Stage, there would be no opportunity of dealing on the Report Stage with any points that arise.  That is my only objection to adjournment.  I think we should meet on Tuesday and I think we should be in a position to take the Temporary Economies Bill to which there are a good many amendments and in respect of which we shall require, I think, the whole afternoon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I pointed out to the Minister the fact that the 21 days were running out rather quickly and he is anxious to help in the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="262" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any reason why we should not meet to-morrow morning?  We could hear the Minister's statement in the morning and there are two or three minor measures that can be dealt with then.  That would leave Tuesday free for the discussion of the Temporary Economies Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That would suit me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no objection to that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no objection either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it definitely understood that the Temporary Economies Bill will not be taken until Tuesday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 6.50 p.m. until 11 a.m. on Friday, 14th July, 1933.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>