<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="10" Month="Dec" Year="1980" Vol="95" No="5" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 10 Nollaig 1980" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 10 December 1980" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="427">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="427" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 1, 2, 3 and 4 in that order and to take No. 4 not later than 7 p.m.  It is also proposed that the Second Stages of Nos. 2 and 3 be taken together.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Gas (Amendment) Bill, 1980:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Gas (Amendment) Bill, 1980: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. O'Malley) Desmond J. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. O'Malley)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill is to raise from £25 million to £30 million the limitation both on the aggregate borrowing powers of Bord Gáis Éireann for capital purposes and on the aggregate of such borrowings which may be guaranteed by the Minister for Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The current limitation of £25 million is set under the Gas Act, 1976 by section 23 in regard to the board's capital borrowings and by section 25 in regard to borrowings which may be guaranteed by the Minister for Finance.  The amendments now proposed are to enable the board to borrow in order to continue with their gas distribution projects in the Cork area.  To date the total borrowings of the board amount to about £24½ million.  This leaves an insufficient leeway for borrowings <Col N="428" /> for capital projects for the remainder of the year and leaves no scope for borrowing in 1981.</P>
    <P>As Senators know, following the discovery of natural gas off Kinsale Head, Bord Gáis Éireann were established under the Gas Act, 1976 to develop and maintain a system for the supply of natural gas.  The board have carried out with diligence their duties in the intervening years since their formation and deserve to be congratulated.  A transmission system from the offtake point at Inch to the ESB generating station at Marina was completed in 1977 ahead of time and within budget.  A spurline to supply Nítrigin Éireann Teoranta at Marino Point was also completed in 1977.</P>
    <P>In 1979 spur pipelines were constructed to the ESB generating station at Aghada and to the IDA industrial estates at Little Island and the Mahon Peninsula. Construction work on the natural gas pipeline to the Cork Gas Company works in Cork city was started by the board at the end of 1979 and completed in mid-1980.  On 14 November last initial supplies of Kinsale gas were delivered to the company.  Initially the company will supply town gas reformed from natural gas. Conversion of all consumer appliances to use natural gas directly is being planned and will be undertaken over the next four years.  The Cork Gas Company plan that by 31 December this year all gas supply to their 27,000 customers will have natural gas as the feedstock.  A further extension of the natural gas pipeline to Ringaskiddy was recently completed.  This will supply Irish Steel Ltd., and the IDA industrial estate at Ringaskiddy.  These are the hard core of projects for which capital borrowings of £24½ million were made by the board.</P>
    <P>As a result of the availability of Kinsale gas in the Cork area about 600 extra jobs have already been created.  About 652 jobs will become available arising out of industrial projects for which an allocation of natural gas has been already approved and there is the prospect of further jobs in connection with future natural gas based industries.</P>
    <P>Kinsale gas is almost pure methane.  It is virtually sulphur free and has a high <Col N="429" /> calorific value.  It is thus a highly efficient and valuable fuel source, and should not be allocated in a haphazard way.  The Town Gas Industry Review Committee concluded that, pending the implementation of a reform programme within Dublin Gas and a decision on the question of a Cork-Dublin gas grid, a restrictive policy should be adopted in regard to new allocations of Kinsale gas.  I agree with that conclusion.  I have decided that, pending a decision on the Cork-Dublin pipeline, allocations to industry by BGE should be confined to new industrial undertakings where the use of natural gas would be a premium use and where its availability would be a major consideration in the decision to set up the industry here.</P>
    <P>I think it is appropriate to emphasise at this stage that this Bill relates specifically to the raising of the board's borrowing powers to finance projects in the Cork area.  This extension of BGE's borrowing powers is independent from and is not intended to pre-empt a decision on the feasibility of building a Cork/Dublin pipeline.</P>
    <P>The Cork-Dublin pipeline project is composed of three elements.  First, Bord Gáis Éireann have been asked to undertake a detailed feasibility study in line with best commercial practice encompassing the design, routing and costing of such a pipeline.  The second element is the implementation by Dublin Gas Company of a development plan for the company.  Consumers Gas, Toronto, were commissioned by Dublin Gas to examine the company's operation and recommend a strategy for the company which would make it a suitable vehicle for the efficient distribution of natural gas.  Dublin Gas progress in achieving the performance targets set by the consultants is being monitored by my Department.  A works agreement is currently being negotiated between Dublin Gas management and unions as an essential step in the reform programme.</P>
    <P>The third element is the preparation of a financial package to enable the project to go ahead.  No decision will be taken on the supply of natural gas to Dublin Gas Company in advance of the satisfactory <Col N="430" /> conclusion of BGE's feasibility study and the demonstration by Dublin Gas Company, through the successful implementation of the reform programme, of their capability to distribute natural gas efficiently, cost-effectively and safely.  If at that stage a Government decision is taken to go ahead the necessary legislation will be introduced.</P>
    <P>Bearing in mind that to-date Bord Gáis Éireann have achieved the purposes for which they were established, I am confident that the House will support this Bill which is designed solely to enable the board to borrow for projects in the Cork area over the next few years.  I therefore recommend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Fine Gael Party will support the proposals in the Bill to increase the capital and borrowing powers of Bord Gáis.  I should like to join with the Minister in complimenting the board on their level of operations to date. There are, of course, some very great decisions to be taken with regard to the future and the Bill is a bit short on information as to the Government's thinking on these matters.</P>
      <P>One critical piece of information is how much gas there is in this field.  We have seen newspaper reports recently that the extent of the gas field is larger than first reported.  One would like to know if any hard assessment has been made or can be made as to the full extent of the field. That knowledge would appear to be a condition precedent to any plans for the future use of gas, whether in the Cork area or in a wider context.  Also it would be of critical importance in deciding whether the main thrust for the use of gas should be industrial or whether it would be permissible to make it available for domestic consumption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister devoted a fair amount of his speech to talking about the Cork-Dublin pipeline project.  It is quite clear from what he says that this is still at a very early stage of consideration.  Certain very serious and complex studies have to be carried out before any decision can be made.  Is it implicit in the results of those studies that gas is going to be made available for domestic purposes in Dublin?  Is <Col N="431" /> this not something that could be debated in a wider economic context with regard to the proper utilisation of gas, to the end product to which the gas should be put? Is this not something that would have to be decided on a macro-economic basis? If a decision were to be in a certain way, then there would be no point in feasibility studies about the cost or otherwise of bringing gas to Dublin.  If these studies come up with figures that are right as to the cost of bringing gas to Dublin, and if the Dublin Gas Company can show capacity to use it and provide it for the citizens of Dublin, and if there would be a financial package available, is it implicit that a decision has been taken that Kinsale gas will be made available for the citizens of Dublin?  Serious consideration must have been given to this fundamental question.  Implicit in the decision to proceed with these studies there must be an element of a decision: yes, if these studies are okay we will bring gas to Dublin.  We are entitled to know at this stage if the hard thoughts of the Minister are along those lines.</P>
    <P>We have been reading recently of contacts between the Minister and his counterpart from the Northern Ireland Office, obviously discussing the possibility of bringing gas from Kinsale up to the North.  These discussions have been continuing and there have been newspaper speculation and reports that the matter is being discussed in realistic terms as if it has a feasibility quality about it.  All of us would welcome such a development for more reasons than merely economic ones; for social and political reasons it would be welcomed as a tangible indication of the geographic unity of this island, something which people in some areas are inclined to ignore.  But I would like to know if it will ever be feasible.  I presume that continuing exploratory meetings between the Minister and his counterpart in Northern Ireland would not be taking place unless there is some information or thought in the background to show that something on these lines is feasible.  This goes back to the basic question of how much gas there is in the gas field, and of deciding on the priorities for <Col N="432" /> its use &mdash; domestic, domestic-cum-industrial or just industrial only.  It gets back to the basic question of the rate of use because it is a finite reserve and the future in regard to energy sources is obviously clouded and uncertain.  This is the one positive energy resource we have apart from turf.</P>
    <P>This Bill would appear to be the appropriate vehicle for the Minister's thoughts on the proper rate of extraction.  Possibly it is not technically feasible to determine with reasonable accuracy the level of the reserves in the Kinsale gas field but we would like to be told that.  If it is not technically possible to obtain this information, obviously any plans for future development of the gas system have to be very tentative indeed, so tentative that it constrains the Minister to confine the development of the grid to the Cork area so that it can be used at the first point of shore access, which would be the most economic point of use.</P>
    <P>While we agree that the extra borrowing and increase in capital for the gas board is desirable, there are many questions which remain to be answered.  In the context of the questions I have posed, the increases being proposed here by the Minister are puny and obviously are designed to enable the board to provide very limited extensions in the Cork area.</P>
    <P>Another slight criticism I would have of the Bill is that it is very short of hard information on what exactly is proposed in the Cork area.  We have been told of the developments that have taken place so far and the spur pipelines that have been constructed to the ESB, to the IDA estate and to NET.  The Minister mentioned in his speech that it is appropriate to emphasise at this stage that this Bill relates specifically to the raising of the board's borrowing powers to finance projects in the Cork area, and that this is separate from the whole Dublin issue.  I take that point but it would be useful for us to know what precisely is planned in the Cork area, what increase in volume of use is planned for the Cork area and how this relates to what I submit is the critical question, that is, the extent of the reserves.  I look forward to getting some <Col N="433" /> further information on these matters from the Minister when he replies.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FintanKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very pleased indeed to hear about the employment potential arising from the availability of Kinsale gas.  In this connection I wonder if the Minister is in the position as yet to indicate the actual industries to which the allocation of natural gas has already been approved.  In so far as new industries might be concerned, could the Minister also indicate whether it is his intention to give them preferential treatment in respect of prices and so on as an extra inducement to open up industries, especially in the Cork area?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>I also welcome this Bill and I share some of the feelings expressed by Senator Cooney.  The basic problem in any discussion of this particular resource is the extent to which the actual resource is available.  While it may not be possible to give very accurate figures, the newspaper speculation which in recent times has indicated that the Kinsale field may be considerably bigger than originally announced is something to which the Minister should refer.  Clearly one cannot be pinned down.  The reserve may be considerably bigger even than the newspaper estimates.  It is one of the crucial factors in making any decisions about the future use of the natural gas in the Kinsale field.  We want to have some idea of the reserves that are currently estimated to be under the sea.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There has been a certain amount of comment on the particular uses to which the gas is put.  Apart from the domestic use, initial industrial uses were for generation of electricity and for the NET project.  Certainly I have seen adverse comment attached to both and on the lines that neither of these projects is the most economic way to use such a resource.  I am not in a position to know one way or the other whether this is correct.  A worrying feature is the fact that the State subvention required for the NET factory seems to of a very high order indeed.  I would like the Minister to say in his reply whether he thinks that the <Col N="434" /> initial decisions to use the gas in the generation of electricity and in the production of fertiliser were the correct ones and whether this sort of policy is to continue.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. O'Malley) Desmond J. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. O'Malley)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Senators who spoke and I will endeavour as best I can to deal with the matters to which they referred.</P>
      <P>Senator Cooney inquired in particular about the reserves of gas in this field and whether any re-examination had been done that might lead to a revision of the existing estimate.  It is not easy to be accurate to any degree of fineness in regard to reserves in a gas field.  The current official estimate of the reserves is 1,000,000 million cubic feet which would envisage a take-off of 124 million cubic feet per day over 20 years.  It is no secret that a re-evaluation will take place of the estimated reserves over the next few months.  I understand that it is not an easy or a rapid proposition to make this examination because it entails pumping from all 14 wells that exist in that field in different ways at different times to measure pressure under different conditions in various parts of the field.  A very complicated mathematical sum has to be done at the end of it all to try to come up with a figure.</P>
      <P>There are prospects, certainly that the reserves may be greater than the current estimate but one would be hesitant to go beyond that.  It should be borne in mind by the House that even if the reserves prove to be greater it does not necessarily follow that the daily take-off rate would prudently be increased because it might affect the pressures and the basic structure of the field.  A bigger reserves might mean a longer life but not necessarily a greater daily take-off of gas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Kennedy inquired about which industries had a supply of natural gas in Cork.  Apart from NET, the ESB and the Cork Gas Company who have been referred to already, the other industries are Ridge Tool Company, Irish Steel, Pilmar Farm Chemicals, Duscholox Limited, Cara Partners, FMC, Cantrell and Cochrane, Foto Laboratories, <Col N="435" /> American Gauge and Machine Company, John A. Wood, Measurex and Marathon.  There are four others in respect of whom a recommendation has been made by Bord Gáis Éireann which is currently being considered by the Minister for Energy.  All of these, with the exception of Irish Steel which is in Ringaskiddy, are either in Little Island or on the Mahon Peninsula.  It is envisaged now that the pipeline has reached Ringaskiddy on the western side of the harbour that it will be available to suitable users who will be established on the very large industrial estate which runs to about 1,000 acres at Ringaskiddy.</P>
    <P>I felt it necessary about two years ago to suggest to BGE that they should run that pipeline in order that we could open up for development the western side of Cork harbour.  I am conscious of the fact that the eastern side is very heavily developed, by Irish standards, with relatively heavy industry.  The site available at Ringaskiddy was underdeveloped for a number of reasons, mainly a lack of infrastructure.  So far as port infrastructure is concerned, that defect has by and large been remedied now by the building there in the past couple of years of jetties by the Cork Harbour Commissionmers. There have been considerable improvements in the road infrastructure, but unfortunately there is still a bottleneck as one enters Cork city.  I do not think it will be finally solved until there is some very radical way of avoiding traffic from the Ringaskiddy area having to go through Cork city and that obviously is a very long-term and extremely expensive proposition.</P>
    <P>Regarding the making available of gas to future industries, one would prefer to see it used as a feedstock rather than just as an alternative form of fuel.  I emphasise that it is undoubtedly valuable as an alternative source of power but less valuable than where it is used as the feedstock.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister explain?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Rather than just for raising heat or something of that kind which can be done equally well but perhaps more expensively by electricity or <Col N="436" /> by oil.  In the glass industry for example, it would form a much more integral part of the actual manufacture of the ultimate goods produced as a result of the manufacturing process.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Making cheap ammonia.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Glass, for example, would be an ideal industry for premium use of this.  In theory the manufacture of ammonia is a premium use but we will have to leave it at that.  On the question Senator Cooney raised as to whether the usages decided on were the right ones or not, I suppose it is easy enough to be wise after the event, but there is one factor that people should bear in mind and which is not borne in mind by many commentators.  It is that we would probably never have got the gas out of the ground if two large-scale users of it were not provided from the start.  Statments are being made nowadays on the false assumption that the gas is ashore anyway and that therefore it should be diverted into other better uses.  The gas would never have got to the shore if the take-off of substantial quantities by the ESB and NET could not have been promised and arranged from the beginning of the period of negotiation for the production of the gas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is, of course, very unfortunate to see what has hapened in NET.  I am sure every one of us regrets that very bitterly and it has been a sore and sorry lesson for public enterprise in this country.  It has ended up in the appalling way that it has but I am afraid we just have to face up to the facts of the situation that exists today and try to make the best of it.  It has implications which go on a long way beyond the fertiliser industry.  Deep consideration of the basic problems that exist is by no means over.  I was informed by the chairman of NET within the last few days that their forecast losses which were given to me during the year have, unhappily once again, as is the want in this particular company, proved to be very much on the low side.  The losses this year are astronomical, being a combination of trading loss and a currency exchange loss which, in fact, is not <Col N="437" /> incurred but which must be allowed for in the current year in their accounts.</P>
    <P>It is certainly disturbing to find this situation.  If one divides the loss by the number of employees in the company one comes up with a figure that possibly would not be acceptable if it were talked about in terms of capital grants for a permanent IDA project of high technology.  That has to be accepted, apparently, as a running annual loss on the current side in a semi-State trading company.  That has many implications when we consider it.</P>
    <P>On the possibility of gas in Dublin, the Minister for Energy dealt with that fairly fully on a number of occasions recently. As I pointed out in my speech, there are three things that have to be done. Obviously BGE will have to do a full feasibility study; Dublin Gas will have to put their house in order; and some efforts will have to be made to see whether a financial package can be put together. However, it does not necessarily follow if all three of these are complied with that a decision will then be made.  The decision could not in fairness be made until the Government saw what the situation was under those three headings; likewise for example, if the Dublin Gas Company are not able to put their house in order, it does not necessarily follow from that that the possible project should fail if the Minister was able to devise some other means for the distribution of gas.  I am not personally familiar with the up-to-date situation in Dublin Gas but I have had experience of the company over a number of years and unless there has been a very radical change in recent months one would feel it necessary to say that it is a pity that the problems there cannot be faced and overcome more rapidly than has been the case in the past.</P>
    <P>On the question of a possible link with Northern Ireland, the House will know that the Minister for Energy had a meeting on 5 December with Mr. Giles Shaw, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State with responsibility for energy matters in Northern Ireland, and a statement was issued after that meeting, the relevant part of which reads as follows:</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="438" /> The Minister has had useful exchange of views during which Mr. Colley provided Mr. Shaw with more precise information about the Republic's intentions concerning the development of the Kinsale field and its plans for the distribution of the natural gas.  Mr. Shaw said this information which is new could have a bearing on his Government's policy for the gas industry in Northern Ireland, that he would obviously have to assess the implications in greater detail and this he would be doing as a matter of urgency.</P>
    <P>There are, of course, many reasons, as Senator Cooney mentioned, other than just purely economic ones why it might well be attractive for Northern Ireland and ourselves to have a gas grid extending from Cork to Belfast but at the same time, we have to be realistic about it.  We are without an electricity inter-connector for the past six years and I believe the prospects in the immediate future of its being restored are not good.  The newly-appointed chief executive designate of the ESB mentioned this yesterday.  We must bear in mind that if it is not possible to maintain an electricity inter-connector, the chances of maintaining a gas grid must be much less.  Of course, gas flowing through pipes, for the most part over the ground or very close to the surface, is far more vulnerable than electricity and the consequences of the pipeline link being blown up by terrorists are much more serious than the consequences of an electricity line being knocked down.</P>
    <P>These are most of the points that have been raised in the course of the debate. Senator Cooney mentioned that the increase proposed here is very small but, of course, that is deliberate.  It is only £5 million and it is mainly to enable further connections or spurs to this pipeline to be made to industrial estates in and around Cork.  The Minister for Energy thought it appropriate to confine the additioal moneys refered to in this Bill to that purpose alone because if substantial moneys were required afterwards in connection with the pipeline or grid to any place outside the Cork area, it is only <Col N="439" /> right that a Bill should be introduced and that both Houses should have the opportunity to discuss the policy involved.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Gas (Amendment) Bill; 1980:" RHead="Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Gas (Amendment) Bill; 1980: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 1 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>On section 1, has the Minister any idea when the board propose to draw this extra equity?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. O'Malley) Desmond J. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. O'Malley)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not equity, it is borrowings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry I misread the Bill.  I thought there was provision for extra equity as well.  When is the borrowing supposed to be taken up?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>As needed.  The first part may have to be taken up fairly shortly after the Bill is passed, I should imagine in early 1981.  It is anticipated at the moment that £1.3 million would be borrowed in 1981 and that the balance of the additional £5 million would be borrowed in following years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Do the board borrow from commercial banking sources?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Minister a question on this section which is identical to sections of this kind in all sorts of other Acts?  Has the Minister ever run into difficulties raised by people who were relying on Ministerial guarantees as <Col N="440" /> to whether at the time of the giving of the guarantee he has kept within the limit imposed by the legislation?  Something which I have talked about in relation to other Bills is that there is no provision which would enable a lender to say &ldquo;There is a statutory sentence there on which I am relying&rdquo;: in other words, that if the Minister gives a guarantee he should be deemed in the case of any borrower relying on it to have given it within the ambit of this section.  Perhaps the Minister would deal with that point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Although this is a matter I would have to check, I would imagine that in giving the guarantee, the Minister probably includes in the document a certificate to the effect that he has not exceeded the statutory limit and that this guarantee now given, together with previous outstanding guarantees, will not cumulatively exceed the statutory limit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Probably that is the best that can be done in existing legislation, but the question is there as to whether the Minister has the power to do that.  We have imposed a limit on the Minister and said he is not to guarantee more than £35 million.  The Minister in certifying that he is giving a guarantee would not help the borrower if the amount being guaranteed were in excess of the power which the Minister must get from the Houses of Parliament, or else this section would not be there at all.  It is obviously not a matter which flows to the Minister by virtue of his appointment as Minister under the Ministers and Secretaries Act.  Speaking from one experience of many years I came across a case in which they were right up to the limit but nobody thought of it and then legislation was put through to deal with it.  I have thought that the form of legislation on this point could be improved.  I am not pressing the Minister for an amendment on this particular section, but if it occurs in other Bills he might keep it in mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I suppose my Department are more involved in these matters than the Department of Energy and I will ask them to have a look at it.  We can <Col N="441" /> rejoice in the fact that the institutions which lend these large amounts of money are usually able to afford the most expensive and learned of lawyers who can prevent them falling into these pitfalls&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>And whose advice they sometimes do not take.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 3 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Irish Film Board Bill, 1979:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Irish Film Board Bill, 1979: Second Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>May I remind Senators that the House has agreed already that the Second Stages of items Nos. 2 and 3 will be taken together?</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. O'Malley) Desmond J. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. O'Malley)</NameTxt>
      <P>Because this Bill and the National Film Studios of Ireland Limited Bill both relate to the development of the film industry in Ireland, I propose for the sake of convenience to cover both Bills in this speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It may surprise a number of Senators to learn that in Ireland there is a long tradition of film making going back to the early days of this art form.  The films of Sydney Olcott and the Film Company of Ireland in the early part of the century are notable examples.  In recent years interest in film making here has centred on the shooting of many of the scenes for international feature films and the growth of Irish film making in the documentary and short feature areas.  These activities, however, have not resulted in the establishment of what might be regarded as an Irish film industry.  Many recommendations, proposals and suggestions have been made over the years for the establishment and development of such an industry.  For one reason or another none of these ideas has come to fruition.  Notwithstanding <Col N="442" /> our present economic difficulties, the Government, at my suggestion, have agreed that the time is now opportune to provide the framework within which a film industry in Ireland might develop.  Needless to say the Government themselves cannot create such an industry but hopefully can provide the necessary encouragement and incentives for those who can.</P>
    <P>By the establishment of an Irish film industry I mean not only the making of films in Ireland but also the development of Irish entrepreneurs who will take a leading part in organising the financing and production of films, of producers, directors, scriptwriters, cameramen, lighting technicians, editors, sound recordists, designers, make-up artists, craftsmen, technicians and the various people who together make up a film industry.  Such an industry would produce not only short films but feature films for world distribution, both for television and for cinema.</P>
    <P>In considering the need for an Irish film industry, account should be taken not only of the factors applicable to industrial development in general, such as creating employment and attracting foreign exchange, but also of a number of major benefits, mainly non-economic, resulting from having films made in Ireland.  These benefits include the development of artistic and technological skills, the indirect promotion of tourism, the promotion of cultural values and public relations and providing a potent means of presenting this country, its heritage and its people to the world and of keeping Irish people in touch with their distinctive environment.  It is, I think, relevant to point out that Ireland is one of the few European countries which lacks a specific scheme of inducements of one kind or another to encourage the development of film making.</P>
    <P>In 1968 the Film Industry Committee, under the chairmanship of Mr. John Heuston, the well-known film director, submitted a report to the then Minister for Industry and Commerce making recommendations for promoting the development of a native film industry in Ireland.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="443" /> The committee's main recommendations formed the basis of the principal provisions of the Film Industry Bill, 1970, which lapsed in early 1973.  The object of that Bill was to set up a board who were to have the function of furthering and encouraging the development of an Irish film industry.  The board themselves were not intended to engage in film production but were to have been empowered to make or guarantee loans for film making, subject in certain cases to prescribed financial limits.  Following the acquisition of the Ardmore Film Studios by the Government in July 1973 it was decided that the format of the Bill would have to be changed to take account of the new situation.  In any event certain sections of the 1970 Bill were contrary to the provisions of the Treaty of Rome.</P>
    <P>The Government, in July 1973 authorised the purchase of the land, premises and equipment of the former Ardmore Film Studios International (1972) Limited, Bray, County Wicklow, which were being sold at public auction by the receiver.  These assets were purchased through Radio Telefís Éireann on behalf of the then Minister for Industry and Commerce for a total of approximately £450,000, including fees.  RTE took over the studios in September 1973 and acted as caretaker-managers on behalf of the Minister for Industry and Commerce pending the establishment of permanent structures to operate the studios.</P>
    <P>I understand that the Government believed at that time that the establishment and maintenance of well-equipped film studios operating on commercial lines was an essential prerequisite for the development of a film industry in Ireland in that if the studios were to be closed permanently the emergence of an indigenous film industry producing feature films would become less likely.</P>
    <P>On 4 June 1975 the Government approved a proposal by the then Minister for Industry and Commerce to establish a company, to be known as National Film Studios of Ireland Ltd., to take over and operate the studios.  The business of NFSI is that of renting studios and other premises <Col N="444" />&mdash; offices, dressing rooms, and so on &mdash; and equipment to film producers who are making films in Ireland.  The company also make available sets, fittings and furnishings to theatrical producers.  In both cases charges are designed to cover the costs of providing these facilities and to yield a profit.  Similar facilities are provided on a commercial basis to advertising agents and firms making short commercial films for television or cinema.  A major function of NFSI to date has been to persuade film makers, both foreign and Irish, to use their facilities.</P>
    <P>Employment on a full-time basis in NFSI is being provided at present for about 60 people.  Additional employment during periods of feature film activity has been provided by the company and directly by production companies filming in Ireland.  Overall, however, the level of what could be termed significant film making projects attracted to the studios has been disappointing and has fallen far short of what would be necessary to make the operation of the studios viable and capable of ensuring a reasonable continuity of employment for Irish personnel involved in the industry.</P>
    <P>One of the main reasons why NFSI are unable to keep the studios operating at full capacity is the company's inability to offer any financial incentives to film makers.  This places the studios at a marked disadvantage as almost all the other member states of the European Communities and a number of important third countries offer varied incentives and inducements in respect of film-making. For example, in the United Kingdom the Eady Levy, based on a tax on box office receipts, is designed to attract foreign investment, since the opportunity of obtaining an additional bonus from the levy makes it financially more attractive to produce a film in Britain.  In the Federal Republic of Germany and in Denmark, national film institutes provide financial assistance to producers, exhibitors, scriptwriters and assistance in film promotion and distribution.  In Canada, the Canadian Film Development Corporation provide financial investments for feature films, loans to producers and training grants.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="445" /> Excluding the expenses incurred in the purchase of the studios, direct Exchequer grants totalling £1.5 million have been made available to date to cover principally the company's administrative expenses during periods of inactivity.  In addition, NFSI have, with ministerial approval, obtained a bank overdraft of £850,000 which has been used mainly for capital development.  A significant level of capital expenditure had to be undertaken in order to bring the studios up to the highest international standards, in the absence of which there would have been even greater difficulties in the procurement of business.  While the company have had some success in attracting film business since they commenced operations, overall the company's experience illustrates their inability to generate a satisfactory level of business without the availability of some form of financing incentives.  This is a point that NFSI made forcefully shortly after it was set up. Again early in 1977 in a proposal to the then Minister for Industry and Commerce, NFSI suggested that the proposed film industry legislation should provide for the establishment of a film financing and distribution company that would be a subsidiary of NFSI.</P>
    <P>On taking up office in July 1977 and following a re-appraisal of the overall position of film making in Ireland, including NFSI's failure to generate sufficient business to make their operations viable, I decided to seek independent advice on systems of finance for film making and on possible methods of making the studios viable.  I engaged Messrs. A. D. Little Ltd. of London, international consultants, to undertake this task and they reported to me in May 1978.  In addition to the consultancy advice, officials of my Department &mdash; and indeed I myself &mdash; had numerous meetings during 1978, 1979 and 1980 with groups and individuals involved in the film industry here. These groups included the board and management of NFSI, representatives of the trade unions and the Irish Film and Television Guild, the Association of Independent Producers of Ireland, the Arts Council, RTE and a number of independent Irish film makers.  These <Col N="446" /> meetings were normally held at the specific request of those involved.  The views of the interested groups and individuals were considered in formulating my legislative proposals in consultation with my colleagues in Government.</P>
    <P>I have adopted a pragmatic approach to the legislation and to the level of financing involved and have tried to take account of the needs of all interests involved, the NFSI, the independent Irish film makers and the technicians and artists.  It is easy to be critical of such proposals depending on where one's own interests lie but I think the time is now opportune for all the people who wish to be involved in the film industry here to work together in order to make the legislation a success.  This is a unique opportunity and, because of the many calls on the Exchequer, is likely to be the only opportunity the industry is given.  I am sure there is a substantial body of opinion in this country who will feel that the money involved in these proposals could be put to much better use in the national interest.  It will be up to those involved in the film industry to prove them wrong.</P>
    <P>I shall now deal with the Irish Film Board Bill and then with the national Film Studios of Ireland Limited Bill.</P>
    <P>The provisions of the Irish Film Board Bill are set out in the explanatory memorandum which has already been circulated.  The Bill provides for the establishment of a board which shall have overall responsibility for the promotion and development of film making in Ireland and for the operation of financial aid schemes designed to further these ends. The board will have considerable flexibility in their operations and in relation to the administration of the fund of £4.1 million.  This is a departure from the terms of the 1970 Bill which had the disadvantage of being too rigid and not allowing the board wide enough powers. Subject to such terms and conditions as they think fit, the board may invest in or make a loan, a guarantee or a grant towards the cost of the making of a film in the State.  In addition, the board may provide grants for training and provide moneys for general activities in keeping with their general functions.  I expect that <Col N="447" /> the main preoccupation of the board will be to get films made here and that the bulk of the finance available to them will go in this way.</P>
    <P>I will be looking to the board to adopt a business-like approach to prospective projects and will expect that the potential viability of each project will be a major consideration for assistance being given. Some of the projects will be international feature or television films with good employment and training potential for Irish actors and technicians, while others will be projects by Irish film makers a number of whom have shown themselves in recent years to be capable of producing works of high technical and artistic merit. I should stress, however, that the board will not be in the business of giving gratuitous handouts as this would not be of long-term benefit in an area which, the Government intend, will eventually have to be able to stand on its own feet without State support.</P>
    <P>I do not intend at this stage to indicate who might be on the film board. Obviously, particularly dedicated individuals will be required, a number of whom should be able to carry out an objective and critical assessment of both the commercial viability and artistic value of individual projects and be able to read and evaluate scripts.  It is my intention that the board would appoint a very small permanent staff and would have available to them, in whatever may be the most appropriate capacity, persons with expert knowledge and experience of the many facets of film making and distribution.</P>
    <P>Since the Bills were presented to the Dáil on 26 November 1979, I have received little in the way of concrete reaction, suggestions, proposed amendments, and so on, apart from a joint submission from the Association of Independent Producers Ireland, the Irish Film &amp; Television Guild and the Irish Transport &amp; General Workers' Union.  Perhaps on the other hand, I should interpret this as indicating general satisfaction with my proposals.</P>
    <P>I would now like to deal with the main points which have been raised in relation to the Irish Film Board Bill: firstly, that <Col N="448" /> the general functions of the board should be extended specifically to include such areas as film distribution and the establishment of a National Film Archive.</P>
    <P>I am, of course, aware of the importance of distribution in the context of film making, and I will deal with this in greater detail later.  Naturally, the board will have to devote considerable time and energy in considering this whole area. However, I do not think that it is appropriate specifically to spell this out under the proposed functions of the board as it would be rather unfair to commit the board to becoming involved on a statutory basis in this area in advance of giving them an opportunity to consider the matter in more detail.  But perhaps more importantly, there might be a temptation for some film makers to subrogate entire responsibility for distribution to the board and to blame them for the possible subsequent commercial failure of the films concerned.  There was considerable debate on this issue during the passage of the legislation in the Dáil but I was not convinced that distribution should be specifically included as part of the board's statutory functions.</P>
    <P>Again, while I recognise that the establishment of a film archive has merit and that this is another matter which the board will have to consider, I nevertheless feel that there should be no statutory obligation on the board to get involved in this area at the very start.</P>
    <P>The establishment of an archive could be fairly expensive and could present certain technical /administrative difficulties and I therefore feel that it would be more prudent to await an in-depth study of this whole question.  In my opinion, the main pre-occupation of the film board should be to get films made and if they become too deeply involved at an early stage in ancillary matters, it could have a detrimental impact on their operations.  Notwithstanding these remarks, I should say that in the course of the passage of the Film Board Bill through the Dáil, I did introduce an amendment to section 4 (1) at the specific request of certain Deputies.  This amendment puts down a marker in the legislation in relation to the establishment of an archive without placing <Col N="449" /> a specific statutory obligation on the board in this regard.</P>
    <P>A fundamental criticism that is contained in the joint submission from the AIPI/Irish Film &amp; Television Guild/IT &amp; GWU is that the Film Board Bill does not give expression to what I might refer to as an &ldquo;Irish dimension&rdquo; and linked to this is their view that not less than 80 per cent of the fund should be used to assist in the making of films by independent producers whose normal operation and residence are in Ireland.</P>
    <P>I should say at this stage that the proposed film legislation has been very carefully drafted in order to avoid possible objections from the Commission of the European Communities on the grounds of discrimination against other member states.  As I said earlier, the 1970 Bill had been discriminatory in certain respects as it included restrictions on grounds of nationality.  In fact, my Department have successfully secured the Commission's approval of the texts of the two Bills although the Commission has requested full details of the proposed method of operation of the board and the criteria for the provision of assistance as soon as the board are formally established.</P>
    <P>Nevertheless, in the course of the passage of the Film Board Bill through the Dáil, I indicated that I was prepared, if the parliamentary draftsman could come up with the appropriate words, to incorporate a non-binding reference in the Bill to give expression to an &ldquo;Irish dimension&rdquo;.  This amendment is now incorporated as section 4 (2) of the Bill and, although I have some misgivings about the need for such a subsection, it does, I hope, indicate that I am prepared to accommodate, in so far as is possible, the views of the independent Irish film makers and that I am adopting a reasonable and open-minded approach to this matter.</P>
    <P>I am not prepared to specify how the fund of £4.1 million over four years might be split between films predominantly using the facilities of the studios and film making activities by independent Irish producers.  Indeed, it would be dangerous to make such distinctions as the fund is experimental in nature and only experience <Col N="450" /> will show how it may be effectively operated.  Furthermeore, it seems to me that it would be improper to impose any statutory obligation on the board to cater for any specific group, and that it is more appropriate to leave it to the discretion of the board to decide which individual projects should be supported.</P>
    <P>However, I think it is important to make two points in this regard.  Firstly, it seems clear to me that, at least in the short-term, the National Film Studios will require a limited number of international feature films to provide sufficient work for the studios and, secondly, that notwithstanding their worthwhile efforts in recent years, the ability of the majority of independent Irish producers properly to put together, manage and control commercial films with substantially increased budgets is, as yet, unproven.</P>
    <P>In relation to section 31 of the Film Board Bill which has been the subject of some public comment, I have already said that the provisions in the Irish Film Board Bill are very broad and give the board very wide discretionary powers in relation to their general functions and the administration of the film financing fund. Indeed, this is deliberate in order to enable the board to operate in an effective and flexible manner.  I envisage that the provision enabling me to give directives to the board would only be used very infrequently and in relation to important policy issues.  I can confirm to the Seanad that there is absolutely no intention that I would interfere in the day-to-day operations of the board or in the selection or rejection of individual film projects for assistance by the board. In the course of the passage of the Film Board Bill through the Dáil, I incorporated an amendment to section 31 which excludes artistic aspects of a film from ministerial directives under this section. Furthermore, I feel that the members of the Film Board would welcome guidelines from the Minister on the general policy which might be adopted.</P>
    <P>It must not be forgotten that the Minister of the day has an obligation to the Oireachtas to ensure that the film financing fund is spent in the best possible interests of the development of the film <Col N="451" /> industry and that, given the very broad provisions in the Bill, the Minister should have the power to rectify any obvious areas where the Board might be departing from a prudent overall policy.</P>
    <P>I believe that there have also been expressions of disappointment in some quarters about the level of the fund, that is roughly £1 million a year over four years.  We are a small country and the calls on the Exchequer are many and varied.  Although the fund may be regarded as low in absolute terms and in relation to film production budgets, it is relevant to point out that in the UK, with a population 19 times our own, the National Film Finance Corporation have operated in a modest way since 1949 on a very small revolving fund.  As I said earlier, given the present difficult economic climate and the low priority which the film industry could be regarded as having, the proposed finance is well up to what can be expected.  Of course the fund, in addition to encouraging native film making, is also designed to attract international film and television projects either to be made at NFSI or on location in Ireland.  A consistent level of international projects would hopefully result in a regular flow of business for the studios which should reduce the existing burden on the Exchequer of keeping NFSI in funds.  But perhaps more importantly, such large scale projects could provide regular and valuable employment for many people in Ireland, not only for actors and actresses in major or supporting roles, but for extras, technicians, carpenters, electricians, plasterers and so on, involved in film making.</P>
    <P>Such projects also have valuable spinoff benefits in the general servicing area &mdash; for example hotels, restaurants and so on &mdash; and in the promotion of tourism. They can also be important in trainimg Irish personnel in the basic film techniques.  In the light of these benefits I am often surprised at the apparent criticism of international projects as if they were almost a discouragement to the Irish film makers.  Surely two or three of this type of project a year, if carefully selected in order to ensure viability, are to be welcomed <Col N="452" /> and could flourish in conjunction with the activities of Irish film makers.</P>
    <P>While the obvious ultimate goal would be for Irish directors, producers, script writers and so on, of international calibre to emerge.  I think it is unrealistic to expect that this can be accomplished overnight.  In any event certain international features will continue to be made in Ireland either because of our natural advantages or because of a particular Irish theme, but special financial incentives will be required in other cases.</P>
    <P>As I have said earlier, the board and the film finance fund are also designed to further native film making talent.  I accept that it is only if this section of the industry blossoms that we can have a truly Irish film industry making films that reflect the Irish way of life and with Irish themes.</P>
    <P>We have seen the emergence of a number of Irish film makers in recent years without direct State support and these people are to be congratulated on their efforts.  I know that most of these low budget films would not have been possible, however, without the indirect support of the State through RTE, the Arts Council and other State bodies who have encouraged those involved.  I would encourage these bodies, and indeed the major Irish companies and banks in the private sector, to consider supporting by sponsorship native Irish film makers in the years to come.  As a result of the efforts of these few film makers, some commentators have suggested that an Irish film industry would develop without direct State support but, I, for one, am aware that, a number of Irish film makers have put a great deal of personal savings and have gone into debt to have these films completed.  I expect, therefore that, once established, the Irish Film Board will pay particular attention to this whole area and positively encourage those involved.  A cautious approach is needed however; there are limited funds and to expect overnight miracles is foolhardy.</P>
    <P>I mentioned before the very important issue of film distribution and this was highlighted in the consultants' report to which I referred earlier.  For those involved in the industry, distribution is seen as the key to survival.  For no matter <Col N="453" /> how good a film is, if it is not shown, it can never hope to bring a return to the film maker.  Distribution is, of course, mainly controlled by the film majors who naturally give preference to their own product as part of their integrated operations.  The film board will have to devote a lot of time and energy to this question. From the point of view of assessing individual projects, either international or native, a project for which there are already guaranteed distribution arrangements would have a better chance of receiving assistance from the board than one for which no arrangements had been made.</P>
    <P>In the case of Irish film makers who would be more likely to have distribution problems because of inexperience and lack of international standing, the board would try to assist in this area perhaps by setting up a distribution office or making the necessary contacts at home or abroad.  In addition, I understand that NFSI and RTE have acquired experience in this field and might also be able to provide assistance.  Notwithstanding these remarks I feel I must stress a most important point and this is that there is no easy solution to the distribution problem and those in the industry should not assume that the film board will prove a panacea for all their ills.  In the final analysis it is essentially up to the film maker to go as far as he can in relation to negotiating a distribution deal for his own project.  Film makers cannot expect the board to provide assistance for the making of a film which will simply be deposited on the board's doorstep for distribution and for which the film maker can blame the board for its possible failure. I feel that another area which needs attention is the distribution opportunities within Ireland for Irish films and I would appeal to Irish distribution companies to be helpful here.</P>
    <P>I would now like to turn to the National Film Studios of Ireland Limited Bill.  This is a fairly standard piece of legislation and, as set out in the explanatory memorandum which has already been circulated, it is designed to give appropriate statutory backing to NFSI and regularise their position.  As I mentioned earlier, <Col N="454" /> the company were set up in 1975 in advance of enabling legislation with a nominal share capital of £1 million which has not been issued to date.  This has meant that NFSI have had to borrow the bulk of the funds needed for capital development and the consequential financing charges have been a particularly heavy burden on the company.  This burden, together with the inability of the company to attract a regular flow of film making business, has meant that the studios have been a burden on the Exchequer over the past few years.  Hopefully the two Bills when enacted will improve the situation considerably by eventually regularising the capital structure of the company and providing incentives for film makers more fully to utilise the excellent facilities at the studios.</P>
    <P>I believe that to get NFSI working on a fully profitable basis, the studios must for a few years at least depend heavily on work from international film producers, who will make films here because they can get the kind of facilities they want, and are prepared to pay for these facilities on the normal commercial scale.  A steady flow of work from such film makers will provide an income for the studios which should, hopefully, put the company in a profitable position.  It should also, and this is no less important, provide invaluable experience and training for Irish people working in the industry.</P>
    <P>Although NFSI have been severely criticised in the past, I feel I must pay tribute to the members of the board, and in particular the Chairman, Mr. John Boorman, for their efforts over the past few difficult years.  Mr. Boorman has served the Irish film industry very well and through his personal efforts has influenced the making of a number of films here, some of them by himself.</P>
    <P>In fact, a feature film with a budget of some $12 million has been completed a few months ago at NFSI.  This film &mdash; based on the Arthurian legend &mdash; was written, produced and directed by John Boorman and provided employment for a large number of Irish workers in the film industry for most of the first half of this year.  Most of the post-production work was also carried out at the studios <Col N="455" /> and it is of great significance that this film provided opportunities for young Irish trainees in all departments of the production.  Mr. Boorman's international reputation and position have contributed in no small measure to any success that has been accomplished to date by the studios and this country owes him a considerable debt.  I only hope that despite his many commitments in the future, he will continue to play a vital role at this important period in the development of the industry.</P>
    <P>While developments in the last decade in the film industry seemed to be showing a trend away from studios and concentrating more on location work, the situation seems to be turning in recent years with the trend for films with a higher studio content.  In fact, I believe that most studios around the world are quite busy at present because of the present buoyant situation in the film industry.  However, it is my personal opinion that the film industry is one that, because of its artistic and technical nature, is not particularly suited to the State sector.  The National Film Studios, nevertheless, do constitute a valuable major asset and I believe that they are regarded by people who have worked there as one of the finest of their size in the world.</P>
    <P>In conclusion I would like to stress that the overall package of proposals contained in the legislation is experimental in nature and will be reviewed by the Government after an initial period of about three to four years to assess what further role, if any, the State will play in this area.  I know that it may be too early, even at that stage, realistically to assess the impact of the board's activities but we could not continue to provide scarce State funds without reviewing their effectiveness and value to the community.  As I said before, I regard the present proposals as a great challenge to the nascent film industry in Ireland and I hope they are regarded as a measure of anticipation by the Government of the future prospects of the industry and of their expectation that those who will be involved will justify this act of faith.  With that in mind, I would hope that some of the divisions <Col N="456" /> that have existed in the past between the independent film makers and those involved in the studios will be overcome and that everybody will work together in the hope of ultimate success.</P>
    <P>I am confident that the Irish Film Board Bill will commend itself to the Seanad and I recommend the Bill for its approval.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>May I first of all thank the Minister for his comprehensive statement?  On reading the Minister's speech I got a distinct impression of an uncharacteristic tentativeness about this whole project, and possibly unexpressed doubts about it running right through the script which, in the last page, became articulated when he spoke of the venture as being an act of faith.  I do not know if that is a good enough criterion on which to ask the Parliament to provide money. From the Minister's uncharacteristically tentative approach I thought that for the purpose of this Bill he might have preferred to be over here to respond to somebody else reading that long and tentative script.</P>
      <P>Is the Bill a reaction to the persistent lobbying that appears to have been taking place in this sector for a number of years? There is no shortage of lobby groups. The fact that the Minister went to the trouble of listing all the groups with which he had to contend shows a certain amount of impatience.  He listed the board and management of the NFSI, representative trade unions and the Irish Film and Television Guild, the Association of Independent Producers of Ireland, the Arts Council, RTE and a number of independent Irish film makers.  It seems that the Minister has been bombarded by lobby interests for a number of years.  I get the distinct impression that to get rid of them we now have these two pieces of legislation and that the Minister has not really cleared his mind as to whether or not he wants an Irish film industry, or whether he is totally satisfied that the National Film Studios of Ireland should be allowed to continue or have any real hope of being a viable institution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Before we embark on setting up a semi-State company and providing taxpayers' <Col N="457" /> money which the straitened Exchequer can ill afford, we should be very clear in our minds as to whether or not we want a film industry and, if so, why.  There are a number of criteria against which we can examine whether we need such an industry.  The Minister touched on various of these but he did not expand on or analyse them so as to come down positively in favour of one or a combination of these criteria as justifying the venture now proposed in this legislation.  He raised some issues that might be reasons for establishing a film industry.  He mentioned the question of national prestige.  I always feel a little embarrassed when I talk about the State engaging in a particular enterprise for reasons of national prestige. Expressions of that kind are a visible symptom of a national inferiority complex.  Do we need, for our national prestige, to have a film industry?  Do we have to keep up with the Joneses with regard to the provision of film stars, script writers, producers and so on?  Will our authority as a sovereign nation be in any way enhanced, improved or respected in the international community, or will our prestige in any way benefit by having an Irish film industry?  Quite frankly I do not think so.</P>
    <P>Another criterion touched on by the Minister was the cultural one.  Would we in developing a film industry also consequently develop a pool of artistic expertise needed for our artistic fulfilment and for the development of native culture to its fullest extent?  I have great doubts about people in this quasi-technological cultural area being capable of contributing significantly to the expansion of our culture.  Again, the Minister thought that if this project gets off the ground it would have the effect of bringing examples of Irish culture to other parts of the world.</P>
    <P>In his speech, the Minister talks about the benefits, which include the development of artistic and technological skills and the indirect promotion of tourism. That is really groping for arguments. That this Bill will indirectly promote tourism is very marginally possible.  The promotion of cultural values and public relations, put together, is an odd combination, because the essence of cultural <Col N="458" /> values is supposed to be integrity, whereas public relations is essentially an exercise in what would be too strong to say conmanship, but it has a strong element of that &mdash; providing a potent means of presenting this country, its heritage and its people to the world and keeping Irish people in touch with their distinctive environment.  That is a most commendable objective but I suggest most strongly to the Minister that, as a commerical objective, it is a non-starter.  If that is going to be one of the reasons for starting the film industry, which he hopes will be commercially viable &mdash; and this theme goes through the Minister's speech, warning those who are coming into this scene that they will still have to stand on their own financial feet &mdash; I respectfully suggest that commercial viability is not going to be achieved.  If the films that we are going to make are to be made for the purpose of presenting this country, its heritage and its people to the world &mdash; and I would like to see these things presented &mdash; we cannot do it on a commercial basis.</P>
    <P>There was much ado recently about the feature film &ldquo;Strumpet City&rdquo; which was made by Telefís Éireann, which involved the Ardmore resources.  A lot of talk went on about the commercial prospects of that film and we were given the impression that it was a winner from the word &ldquo;go&rdquo; and that if it had not already made a vast amount of money &mdash; and it was implicit that it had done so &mdash; it was about to do so very quickly.  We have learned that the making of that film cost in excess of £800,000.  So far, all that has been recouped by RTE is £250,000, but there are hopes of selling it to more networks around the world.  Again, these are unrealised hopes as of now and I wonder is that film, in the theme it presents &mdash; which is necessarily a very interesting and very historic theme for us here &mdash; unduly narrow, not having the commerical width of approach to make it a commercial success?  I feel that it would not be to the taste of the vast majority of viewers in the English-speaking world.</P>
    <P>Technically and artistically, I am sure it is an excellent production.  I saw one or two excerpts from it and they were <Col N="459" /> impressive, but I wonder &mdash; because of the comparatively limited nature of its appeal &mdash; has it any hope of being a commercial success?  It does export to the outside world and does fulfil the criterion mentioned by the Minister of being &ldquo;a potent means of presenting this country, its heritage&rdquo; and so on, but has it real commercial possibilities?</P>
    <P>In having culture as one of the criteria for setting up a film industry, has the Minister fully cleared his mind and realised that that criterion, because of the nature of the crass world in which we live, is incompatible with commercial success?</P>
    <P>A third criterion to which the Minister referred is the provision of jobs, and that is fair enough.  If the State invests in a commercial enterprise, the one thing we want provided as a result of that investment is jobs.  Essentially when the State invests in jobs it should invest in jobs that are wealth-producing.  Jobs in the services industry &mdash; and the film industry is in that area &mdash; do make a contribution to the <i>corpus</i> of wealth in the economy, but not nearly so much as investment in jobs in a primary manufacturing area.  To some extent investing in jobs in the film sector is a form of a continuing, on-going subsidy.  Even if the film industry realised the Minister's wildest expectations for it, we have had no indication in his speech of what can be the financial return to the Exchequer.  If one of the criteria is going to be the provision of jobs, we should have all the other commercial and economic criteria that go with that.  However, one cannot complain if the investment is designed to maintain, and possibly increase, employment.</P>
    <P>Again, one wonders if the investment, as the Minister hopes, will be self-remunerating and if there will not be continual demands on the Exchequer.  I, in common with my other colleagues on the Oireachtas Joint Committee reviewing State-sponsored bodies, was depressed by the financial state of the vast majority of these bodies, their lack of capital, their excessive borrowings and their general commercial weakness and vulnerability. How sensible is it for the Minister to <Col N="460" /> come in here and propose a new industry that has all the hallmarks of going to join the rest of these commercially non-viable bodies particularly which, as I say, will not contribute basically to any increase in the <i>corpus</i> of wealth in this economy?</P>
    <P>I wonder how much attention do Governments and Departments pay to the Houses of the Oireachtas.  Are we just going through a ritual here every so often &mdash; Governments propose and Governments dispose?  The last report that I have seen of the Committee of Public Accounts &mdash; and this is supposed to be the most important committee in the Oireachtas, a committee which is getting down to the very nitty-gritty of parliamentary and other governmental responsibilities&mdash;has a paragraph under the heading &ldquo;Industry, Commerce and Energy&rdquo; on the National Film Studios of Ireland.  It is worthwhile reading to the House what this committee reported at paragraph 58&mdash;it is always a matter of regret that this committee is so far behind but, apparently, it is inescapable in our ministerial procedures:</P>
    <P>In the years 1975 to 1977 a total of £613,000 was paid from voted moneys towards the administration and general expenses of the National Film Studios of Ireland Limited, a private company which was set up in 1975 to take over the management of Ardmore Studios and which continued to experience financial difficulties during those years. The Comptroller and Auditor General told the Committee that the accounts of the company for 1977 showed a net loss of £343,000.</P>
    <P>It would have been interesting for the House to have heard from the Minister what is the current position with regard to loss or profit.  I will continue:</P>
    <P>The Accounting Officer, in evidence stated that the losses arose because the Company depends very much upon the amount of business it can procure for the studios by enticing film makers to use them.  The extent to which this can be achieved is subject to wide fluctuations.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="461" /> The Minister did say that there is demand for our studios at the moment and that the business is buoyant.  I would be interested to know has that buoyancy overflowed into demand for the Ardmore Studios.  Have they a queue of people waiting to take them up?  Have they been idle for any time this year or last year or have they been fully utilised?  With that information we would be able to pass a harder financial assessment on what is proposed to us.  The report goes on:</P>
    <P>While in the early stages the company had some success it has found it increasingly difficult to get a sufficient volume of business into the studios, mainly because of the competition from other countries which are able to offer facilities which are equally good if not better than ours.</P>
    <P>We would be glad to hear from the Minister whether he agrees with that statement as to where Ardmore ranks in the hierarchy of studio facilities because obviously its ranking is going to be very important with regard to its future prospects.  The report continues:</P>
    <P>Arising out of studies carried out by a consultant,&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>I wonder is that the Mr. Little referred to in the Minister's speech.</P>
    <P>&mdash;&mdash;further plans were being considered inter-departmentally with a view to producing additional business for the studio but, while the setting up of the studios and the provision of equipment and fittings was a relatively straightforward exercise, enticing film makers from abroad to use these facilities was a difficult task, because the film business is a very competitive one and most countries seem to be happy to lose, for prestige reasons, very considerable amounts of money on the provision of facilities for film makers.</P>
    <P>I wonder can we join in that league of losing for prestige purposes substantial amounts of money for the making of films?  I respectfully suggest to this House that we cannot.  The Minister in the debate we had on the previous Bill mentioned the situation that he is faced with <Col N="462" /> in regard to one State-sponsored company where the losses for the current year are as great as the investment made in the company; the losses per job are as great as would be the investment made in a commercial company to provide jobs on a permanent basis.  We all know and many citizens, to their pain, know that the Exchequer is straitened and that the public finances are in chaos.  Yet here we are proposing to engage in a prestige exercise in the making of films where, according to the report of the Committee of Public Accounts, other countries seem to be happy to lose money.  Are we digging here a bottomless pit for Irish money?  The Minister warned that this industry is going to have to stand on its own feet and that there will be a limit to the support given to it.  Nevertheless, once one sets up something like this and once jobs are there it is very difficult for any Minister, when representatives from that industry come in with the baby of unemployment and redundancy in their arms, to refuse more money.  It would take a very strong Minister indeed, with a very big majority in the House, to be able to refuse that and, irrespective of how big the majority is, I cannot ever see that being refused.  That is why I worry about what we are engaging in here.</P>
    <P>I will continue with report:</P>
    <P>While losses had been incurred practically every year so far and were likely to be incurred repeatedly in the future, the Accounting Officer expressed the hope that profits might be made in some years.</P>
    <P>As I mentioned earlier, we would have liked to have heard from the Minister if the position has changed since the time to which this report refers.  Has there been a profit this year or at least a diminishing loss?</P>
    <P>The report goes on:</P>
    <P>The Accounting Officer also pointed out that, had the proposed legislation been enacted as soon as the company was set up, moneys could have been provided by way of share capital but difficulties had arisen in connection with the legislation mainly because of <Col N="463" /> disagreement among the interested parties as to what the content of the legislation should be.</P>
    <P>That statement raises two points.  First, I would have to disagree with the committee here who suggest that if equity capital is given everything is all right because if equity capital is given the company then do not have to borrow and consequently do not have to pay interest on the borrowing and their financial position would be that bit better.  That implies surrender from the word &ldquo;go&rdquo;, that we do not expect any return on our equity.  I think that if a company gets capital from the State it should be in a position to remunerate that substantially and that it should not mean that it is going to be overall in a more viable financial position.  Its balance sheet may look nicer and the equity ratios and so on may be nicer but its requirement to repay the investment does not change whether the capital is equity or borrowed.  The implication in that statement, that if they got equity capital the thing would not be as bad, is a fallacy.  Investment of equity should also bring with it an obligation and recognition of the obligation that it must be remunerated.  The other point made in that last sentence which I quoted is that the legislation was delayed because of disagreement among the interested parties as to what the content of the legislation should be.  Obviously those disagreements have not been resolved and obviously one of the inspirations behind this legislation has been the wish of the Minister to get these persistent lobbies off his back; he mentioned a whole list of them in his speech.  This legislation is a compromise, patched together to get rid of them.</P>
    <P>The report then continued that the Accounting Officer:</P>
    <P>also explained to the Committee that the number of people employed by the studios varied considerably, depending on the volume of business.  The Department was seriously concerned about the losses in this enterprise, about which there had been a considerable <Col N="464" /> amount of inter-departmental debate and agonising.</P>
    <P>The Committee recognises that the business of film making is a rather volatile one but it must express its serious concern at the continuing losses suffered by the National Film Studios of Ireland Limited.  It appears to the Committee that public moneys are being spent on keeping alive a business which simply would not survive in the private commercial field.  Furthermore, since it is commonly known that studios of this kind throughout the world are closing down what is being done in this case could possibly be regarded as more in the nature of a public relations operation than the creation of a viable industry.</P>
    <P>Here one has a committee of the Dáil reporting on the financial viability of a project getting funds from the public and obviously giving it the thumbs down in no uncertain fashion.  Is this committee wasting its time?  Are we wasting our time if the Government then come in here and propose a Bill that totally ignores the recommendation of this committee of the House and propose to engage and continue on the course of action that has been very categorically condemned by this committee?</P>
    <P>The report goes on:</P>
    <P>The question which, therefore, concerns the Committee in this case is the extent to which public moneys should continue to be spent on prestige and status and it feels therefore that, because of the grave doubts as to the viability of the National Film Studios of Ireland Limited, a speedy decision must be made as to the future involvement of the State in this enterprise.</P>
    <P>Obviously, the committee's views as to whether the State should be involved or not are very clear from what went before that.  It would appear that the Minister has now decided to ignore that very explicit condemnation, that very explicit finding of the fact that the future for an Irish film industry is very much a doubtful matter.  All the signs are that it will be a <Col N="465" /> bottomless pit into which public money will continue to be poured without any substantial advantage accruing to the nation.  At least we can say with regard to the other project mentioned here that it is creating wealth, albeit expensive wealth, but it is wealth created.  In this case we are proposing to set up a service industry.  It has certain economic merit but it is doubtful indeed when it has to be subsidised.</P>
    <P>I wonder if this is a good time to be embarking on a film industry.  I understand that with the rate of technological change in the whole television area, with the provision of satellites, soon this whole scene is going to change totally.  I wonder if the facilities that we are proposing here are suitable or apt to get in with the technological changes coming in that whole general area.  Again, does the world recession that we are suffering from at the moment have any adverse effect on the prospect of a film industry? It would seem that a film industry is precisely the sort of thing that would suffer in a time of economic recession and here are we starting now in the middle of a recession to attempt to get this industry going.</P>
    <P>I find throughout the Minister's speech a certain wish to excuse himself in advance.  He is putting up warning signs all the time that this is a doubtful project. There is the element of excusing and accusing and it is there right through his speech.  At this stage, irrespective of who may be dissappointed and irrespective of how it may be presented as a climb down, and even if the Minister feels that he is going to have to face all these persistent lobbies again and endure it, I would appeal for a re-think on this whole project.  I feel it does not have any financial attraction; it does not have any significant cultural attraction for us.  So far as national prestige is concerned, I think a criterion like that has to be dismissed with contempt.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>The fact that we have these two Bills before us underlines the problems which Irish film making as opposed to, up to now, an Irish film industry, has presented.  It has been a great problem to many people engaged in film <Col N="466" /> production, to those interested in the subject and to those in the industry generally, why progress here has been so slow and fitful over so many years.  There were many traditional objections raised and excuses presented as to why we had made so little progress in establishing a permanent industry.  But many of these have fallen by the way through the passage of time and are contradicted by examples in other countries.  There was a time when it was considered that unless one had continuous Californian sunshine then one could just forget the whole question of making films.  This point of view is totally contradicted by the films that have been produced in countries that barely have daylight for three or four months of the year, let alone sunshine.</P>
      <P>There was also the necessity to have high finance in a world dominated by film moguls.  This also is contradicted by examples in other countries.  Probably one of the real, acceptable and genuine obstacles that remains out of all these various objections that were raised in the past is the problem of distribution.  Some of those problems remain to some extent. Finance and distribution certainly are problems but they are problems to be overcome.  I am sorry that I missed the beginning of Senator Cooney's speech but I got the general tone of it.  Frankly I was appalled at the philistine tone that underlines practically all his comments. If State involvement in any activity has to be based single-mindedly 100 per cent on the financial return, then I presume by his standards we ought to get rid of the Arts Council and sell our national monuments to whomever will buy them around the world and adopt a totally philistine approach to running our society.  I cannot think that is really what he meant and yet that seems to be what he was saying.  I hope that does not represent the total opinion from the opposing benches.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister has correctly indicated the necessity for financial viability resulting from the assistance which has been brought to the industry now.  Any responsible person would look for and seek to achieve that.  But the cultural objectives of this exercise have also been underlined by the Minister in his speech and in the <Col N="467" /> Bill.  It seems extraordinary that Senator Cooney's approach flies so much in the face of examples from around the world. I believe that nothing did more to retrieve and, indeed, rehabilitate the standing of Italy in the post-war era than its film industry.  It is also interesting to note that whereas many of the films produced in Italy and in many other small countries as well, were very definitely financial successes they were renowned and acknowledged cultural and artistic successes.  It is an extraordinary cynical attitude to assume, as it appears to be assumed, that if there has to be a financial criterion at all any question of a cultural dimension or evaluation has to go out the window. I do not think the world is that cynical.  I do not think even the world of finance is that cynical.  It is quite clear from films produced throughout the whole world that both objectives can be achieved. Admittedly it is also quite clear that both objectives can simultaneously fail to be achieved.  But the achievement of financial viability or an acceptable level of financial investment or return with artistic and cultural merit is possible and has been achieved in other countries.  Indeed, it has been achieved to some extent in Irish film making and it has been achieved in many other art forms as well.</P>
    <P>Let me get back to the problems and circumstances which have really prevented us from developing an Irish film industry.  Let us look at our achievements in the arts generally in comparison with other countries.  Our writers, novelists, playwrights, short story writers, actors, painters and sculptors have all achieved a standard of merit and a degree of achievement that bear comparison with other countries.  If financial acumen and business management were to be the sole criteria as suggested by Senator Cooney, then we have been as successful in those fields as they have been in other countries.  So why have we not been able to put the two together, as has been done elsewhere, on a continuing basis with the same degree of success?  I only raise the question.  I have not got the answer. Nobody seems, over perhaps two generations now, to have been able to find the <Col N="468" /> answer but it is important to recall the question because it is a question that has been fundamental to the whole problem over the years.</P>
    <P>It may be that as a nation we are individualistic.  Certainly artistic endeavour and the arts generally are a very personal thing, and it may be that the team work, the co-operation, the fusing of skills necessary in film production do not come quite as easily to us as to those in other countries.  If this is the case, then it is the responsibility of all engaged in the industry and very much so of the board to be created to see that within the industry writing skills, the directing skills, the whole range of technical skills, lighting and camera work, allied to financial management, financial expertise and distribution expertise are fused once and for all in creating the basis for a continuing vibrant movie industry.</P>
    <P>I would like to emphasise again the question of the value to the country.  By all means we have to have financial viability in Ireland, investment both from the Government and from the individual participants.  We cannot underestimate the tremendous potential for this country from a successful film industry.  I referred very briefly to the effect of Italian films and the attitude adopted throughout the world to Italy in the post-war years after the world war and after the Fascist regime.  A small country like Sweden has made an immense impact in the film industry.  The film industry has added greatly to Sweden's own stature, culturally and otherwise.  India, for example, has had a tremendously successful, and artistically successful, industry and India is a country, practically a sub-continent, which has more economic problems, of literacy and grinding poverty, than we are ever likely to find in any country in Europe.  Yet they have had the capacity artistically and every other way, including financially, to produce films that have won awards throughout the world and, much more important, audiences around the world, and have reflected very greatly to the benefit of India and the Indian people.  There are many other examples, the French film industry and many others.  To cast aside that whole potential for <Col N="469" /> this country on the basis that it is a bad time or there is going to be no financial reward seems extraordinarily shallow and extraordinarily philistine in outlook.</P>
    <P>In looking towards the development of our film industry and bearing in mind the talents we have had in the arts generally, our film makers and producers will have to be clear, no doubt they are, that success in one form does not automatically translate into success in another form. The success generally of, say, the Irish theatre will not guarantee the success of the Irish cinema, as we know from past history.  Any attempt to reproduce Irish theatre at its best in terms of cinema will turn out to be as big a disaster as if we attempted to produce on stage the techniques of film making and the cinema.  It is a separate art form; it must be allowed to develop its own character and its own personality and reflect the best of Irish talents in all the different fields in its product.</P>
    <P>As to the board and the workings of the board, generally it is known that there has been a lot of debate about how this may work out.  The existence of the film studios are a basic and huge asset in developing our film industry.  I know that there are some people who do not share that point of view.  They will point to countries that have very successful film industries but do not have that type of studio facility.  That may be true, and no doubt it is true.  But the fact that one has a studio which is equipped with the best of modern equipment and techniques is an advantage that one should not throw aside when one does have it.  In the running of the studios they will have to have a cognizance of their responsibility to the whole industry within this context.  Their major objective will be to attract foreign productions with all the problems that go with that, of being competitive, of getting them in, of being able to offer facilities which, thankfully, we have and of the necessity in most cases to offer some form of financial inducement.  The Bill provides a basis for equipping them to meet that challenge.  But in meeting it successfully they will still have to bear in mind the responsibility to the whole industry here by operating a very deliberate <Col N="470" /> and definite policy of engaging right down the line, and indeed up the line, Irish technicians and Irish craftsmen.</P>
    <P>One of the great complaints and problems which people have seen in the past is that in all cases when films have been successfully produced in Ireland by foreign producers Irish technicians have not got out of the production the level of experience which they might have got. There have been no Irish directors involved and I do not think there have been any Irish assistant directors involved.  The more we build up this talent and the more we give Irish people working in the industry here the experience and the benefit of the experience which can come from working with foreign producers the more we will build up this pool of talent and the more we will be in a position to equip ourselves to keep our own industry going.  That is the big benefit of having the studios and being in a position to attract foreign productions.  By and large the independent producers, to whom we owe a great deal for their success over the years in very difficult circumstances, are worried about this in so far as they can see the demands for money for big international productions being such that all the financial resources of the board could be swallowed up.  In making their decisions and in making their contracts the studios must bear in mind in a very definite and positive way their responsibility to the whole industry.  Also the board itself must be conscious first of the contribution which independent producers have already made here with some very successful documentary films and other films and second that if we do not provide the encouragement to the independent film producers to develop and to grow more numerous and larger, then we will not achieve the type of film industry we are talking about in the first place.  We have got to make progress on both fronts.</P>
    <P>The whole question of independent producers and the making of small films has to be analysed and examined.  Some highly successful films have been made on relatively small budgets and, if it should happen that the future of the Irish film industry is going to be in the field of <Col N="471" /> documentary films, we need look no further than the tremendous success over the years of the National Film Board of Canada, what that film board have done in projecting Canada and its recognition throughout the world.  They have done it on a basis of financial viability.  If we are bogged down with the problems and the obstacles that Senator Cooney mentioned, we should not begin at all, but I do not believe that represents the attitude of anybody engaged in the industry, remotely interested in the industry nor does it reflect the attitude of the public generally to the creation of support of this industry or any other economic or cultural activity.  The problem of distribution, to which the Minister referred at some length, is one to which both the board and the independent producers will have to give most of their time in terms of planning for the future.  The board will have a huge responsibility because, as the Minister said, if we have not got a distribution system organised, we simply do not have an industry.</P>
    <P>This has been one of the real problems of the past and one which will tend to continue in the future but it is also a problem that has been solved in many instances.  It is an area where there is great opportunity for co-operation between the board, the national studios and the independent producers, because they all have their own knowledge, experience and contacts.  The more we develop the industry at any level, make those contacts and build up our influence, the more we are going to be in a position to work out a distribution system for individual production and, possibly, for the industry generally.</P>
    <P>I want to refer to the plight of the Irish language on the question of the artistic potential in establishing our industry on cultural value.  There have been many artistically and financially successful films produced in countries where the language of those countries was not spoken on a world-wide basis.  Sweden and Italy are examples and the successes of those films in many cases have been brought about by the use of their own languages in those films.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="472" /> The whole style of direction in many Swedish films has been complemented and enriched by the use of their language and those films shown with sub-titles around the world have been highly successful.  It has always been accepted that the use of sub-titles present a barrier and yet a good production has never failed to overcome that barrier.  The films to which I referred earlier, the post-war Italian films.  Indian, Swedish and French films, were all shown initially with sub-titles and were all successful with world-wide audiences.  There is a very valuable opportunity in the use of the Irish language, working in both directions.</P>
    <P>Nothing will present our culture more authentically by definition than the use of our language and, as in the films to which I have referred, the very use of what to other people is a foreign language can contribute greatly to its success because it adds another dimension.  The use of Irish dialogue with sub-titles is perhaps a compromise but it is a compromise which has worked successfully throughout the world.  I hope this is something that can be experimented with more and more by our film makers.  I should acknowledge that some of our independent producers have already done it to some limited extent and done it with absolute success from a production and artistic point of view.</P>
    <P>The Bill forms the basis for giving the necessary and essential encouragement to the industry at this stage.  Senator Cooney says it is not a good time to be making movies.  For some people it never was and yet they managed to face up to the problem and produced films successfully from every point of view.  There are always problems.  If you are looking for circumstances which are perfect, where money is cheap and easily available, where the distribution and scripts are handed to you, you are never going to have a film industry, nor would you have anything else if you were looking for those ingredients.  It is essentially an artistic industry and they are the two words that must be taken together.  It is an industry which, because of being both industrious and artistic, will thrive in overcoming obstacles.  We have now for <Col N="473" /> the first time the opportunity to create a genuine film making community here which can provide the basis of talents going in many directions.  To those who are apprehensive that foreign productions may benefit more than Irish productions, I simply say, &ldquo;give it a chance, be sure you make your input to it in every sense&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>There was sufficient debate before the Bills were presented, and while the Bills were being presented, to know that those who are involved in the industry will watch it so carefully that there is a wonderful opportunity now, involving both the studios and, through them, the international producers and our own independent producers, once and for all, to create a genuine Irish film industry and a genuine Irish film community.  I am delighted to welcome the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá cathú orm nach raibh mé anseo nuair a bhí an bheirt Seanadóir deireannach ag caint, mar bhí orm freastal ar chruinnú.  Aontaím leis an méid atá ráite anois beag ag an Seanadóir Donnelly, is é sin, tábhacht scannáin a dhéanamh trí mheán na Gaeilge. Má táimíd chun ár saol féin a léiriú don saol mór &mdash; beidh difríocht tuairimí ann cad is brí len ár saol féin &mdash; caithfear áird a thabhairt ar an nGaeilge agus, faoi mar atá ráite ag an Seanadóir chomh maith, cuid de na scannáin ab fhearr a deineadh go dtí seo, cuirim i gcás, scannáin GhaelLinn, scannáin de chuid Louis Marcus nár a bhain díreach le Gael-Linn, is trí mheán na Gaeilge a deineadh iad agus bhí siad ar fheabhas ar fad.  Níl aon chúis ar bith nach féidir an Ghaeilge a úsáid as seo amach i gcuid de na scannáin ach go háirithe.  Aontaím leis an méid a bhí le rá aige in a thaobh sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to express my disappointment with the whole spirit of this Bill.  The House, I hope, will recognise that I do not express opposition captiously on these matters.  I am disappointed with the Minister's statement.  It seems to have been thrown at us.  It is very interesting to observe the way some Bills are introduced by Ministers in this House in an independent fashion.  It is quite obvious that they take the Bill seriously and they <Col N="474" /> take the House seriously.  They have been present at the debates in the other House and, perhaps, they have done their homework.  They come in here and introduce the Bill with a quite different speech &mdash; a refreshingly different emphasis.  I am afraid that has not been so in this case.</P>
    <P>While the Minister was reading his script I was reading the script on the Second Stage in the Dáil and it is virtually identical.  That is not good enough.  It is as much as to say that the Minister has not been listening or re-thinking at all since the Bill was introduced on the Second Stage in the Dáil.  The only difference is that the two amendments are referred to and they are not all that impressive. The one about the archives is welcome, needless to say, but, essentially, it has nothing intrinsically to do with the Bill. The business of film archives is largely an educational matter.  While it is welcome, it is not an earth shaking amendment to the Bill.</P>
    <P>The only other concession made to different opinions from the Minister's has been to include a pious reference to the desirability of having regard to the national culture, in the matter of film making generally.  It seems to be no more than a pious counsel, because it does not have any teeth and does not compel the board to do anything about this.  I regard that as a very unsatisfactory sop.</P>
    <P>Apart from being an instance of not bothering to make a fresh speech for the Seanad, the Minister's speech is also extremely condescending.  It reminds Senators that there is a long tradition of film making going back to the early days of this art form.  He said that may surprise us.  Why should that surprise us?  We know that.  What surprises us is the long tradition of neglect by Governments of the highly important business of film making in Ireland.  The Minister says &ldquo;by establishing an Irish film industry&rdquo; he means not only the development and so on but also the need to produce feature films for world distribution, both for television and for cinema.  This is typical of the vague and woolly nature of the Bill.</P>
    <P>If you think about world distribution, you will realise immediately that no one breaks into the world trade of distribution <Col N="475" /> except the large American companies.  In the realm of television distribution, the BBC has great difficulty in breaking into the lucrative market in North America.  Take a recent example, Louis Marcus's splendid series, &ldquo;Heritage of Ireland&rdquo;&mdash; the impact of which I have seen when shown on American campuses &mdash; that still is awaiting transmission on the public television service in the United States because it has not got a financial backer.  There are enormous problems relating to world distribution. Instead of talking about world distribution, we should look more modestly and nearer home for the showing of films we make here.  It is one of the illusions and self-deceptions we have about the film industry in Ireland that somehow all we need is another push and we can break into a world market.  The problem of distribution is enormous.</P>
    <P>The Minister puts all these matters in the context of industrial development.  I listened to Senator Donnelly talking about the need to see it as an art industry, a particular kind of industry which is not an industry in the accepted sense.  The terms of reference of the Bill are to see film making as almost entirely expressed in terms of industrial production.  There is great doubt as to whether the Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism is the proper person to be introducing a Bill of this kind.  Perhaps we should be talking about the Minister for Education.  I agree with criticisms that have been made elsewhere that it is nonsense to talk about a film industry promoting tourism and that kind of thing.  That is not the business of the film industry.  Neither is it presenting Ireland to the world primarily.  The proper business of film making in Ireland is to have an artist's perception of what he is doing presented to his own people in the first instance.  That is the proper business of the Irish artist, whether he is a painter, a dramatist or a poet.  He is working for himself in the first instance and for his people secondly.  He must be formed and must communicate with his own people primarily.  It is very interesting that at the moment, happily, we are witnessing a real resurgence of the Irish <Col N="476" /> drama with splendid plays from people like Leonard and Friel.  What is significant about these plays &mdash; Friel's &ldquo;Translations&rdquo; or Leonard's &ldquo;A Life&rdquo;&mdash; is that they are not concerned with presenting their vision to the outside world at all. They are talking first to their own people, and after that to the world if it wants to listen.  In fact the world does listen, because it recognises the authentic nature of productions which are, in the first place, indigenous.  In an Irish film industry, its only <i>raison d'être</i> is the presentation of an indigenous vision, and the presentation of that to the domestic people.</P>
    <P>The wrong priorities are stated in that regard.  The Minister mentioned the employment facilities, or the employment afforded by the National Film Studios of Ireland Limited.  Here we come to one of the central objections to the Bill, that whereas its prime concern should be with film making in Ireland, it is talking half the time about facilities being afforded to people who want to make films in Ireland, which is a very different thing.  In the process it exaggerates the employment facilities afforded by the NFSI.  My information is that precious few of the 60 people mentioned by the Minister have anything to do with film making.  Many of them are maintenance staff who might as well be employed in any industry.</P>
    <P>The Minister says that the studios are at a marked disadvantage as almost all the other member states of the European Communities and a number of important third countries offer varied incentives and inducements in respect of film making.  Maybe they do.  Is film making to help independent film producers?  The matter of putting a film studio at the centre of affairs is very much out of fashion at the moment.  With the exception of <i>Cine Cittá</i> in Italy, the money being poured in to the National Film Studios is not paralleled elsewhere.</P>
    <P>The Minister says that the basis of the advice he took in relation to these Bills was the engagement of a firm of consultants, Messrs. A.D. Little, and they reported to him in May 1978.  Who were the kind of people the consultants consulted <Col N="477" /> and what was the nature of their report to the Minister?</P>
    <P>Later on, the Minister said that he consulted with various groups, including the Irish Film and Television Guild and the Association of Independent Producers. These meetings were normally held at the specific request of those involved. Is that not a curious procedure for a Minister who wants to do his best for the Irish film industry, that he does not go out and seek the opinions of the people whose livelihoods are going to be affected by the measures to be introduced?</P>
    <P>I did not hear Senator Cooney but I gather that he was somewhat critical of the moneys being used in this project and that his concern was primarily for the disposal of finances.  I understand that, but I take issue with the Minister when he says:</P>
    <P>I am sure there is a substantial body of opinion in this country who will feel that the money involved in these proposals could be put to much better use in the national interest.</P>
    <P>That is like saying that the money devoted to the building up of a symphony orchestra could be put to much better use in the national interest.  It seems to be essentially an anti-intellectual and philistine viewpoint.</P>
    <P>The Minister also states:</P>
    <P>I should stress, however, that the board will not be in the business of giving gratuitous handouts, as this would not be of long-term benefit in an area which the Government intend will eventually have to be able to stand on its own feet without State support.</P>
    <P>I am all for not giving handouts if they are given in the way they have in the past, money poured down the drain in Ardmore, bits of film made here with minimum native employment, no real, not even temporary, utilisation of spending of moneys and no long-term benefits.  I deplore spending money on shoring up a film studio and begging, if you like, for foreign producers to come in and use it. On the other hand, I disagree if the Minister means that he has no intention really of putting independent producers on <Col N="478" /> their feet.  The serious feature film industry in the world rarely makes a profit.  In other words, if we want the kind of film which is authentic and good and reflects ourselves to ourselves and then to the outside world, that will certainly have to be helped at the beginning.  I do not think a phrase like gratuitous handout should be used in connection with the aid which society is obliged to make to film producers.</P>
    <P>For comic relief in a long statement, the Minister said that since the Bills were first presented he had received little in the way of concrete reaction and so on, apart from a joint submission from the Association of Independent Producers Ireland, the Irish Film and Television Guild and the Irish Transport and General Workers Union.  It is exactly like saying there was a meeting on ecumenism in Ballymascanlon which was attended only by representatives from the Roman Catholic Church, the Church of Ireland, the Presbyterian Church and the Methodist Church.</P>
    <P>There is also reference to the old chestnut &mdash; perhaps it is a relatively new chestnut &mdash; that we are prevented from doing certain things because the EEC is watching us.  I take this with a grain of salt.  The Minister talks about avoiding possible objections from the Commission of the European Communities on the ground of discrimination against other member States.  Does he mean in film making, engaging in what is, essentially, an artistic activity about ourselves, that the EEC can object to this?  If this is true, it only bears out what I have been saying about our membership of the Community since I came into this House, but I do not think it is true.  I think this does not worry other member States in the slightest.  We use it conveniently, of course, when we want to for our own sakes.</P>
    <P>The Minister says that he is not prepared to specify how the fund of £4.1 million is going to be split between films predominantly using the facilities of the studios and film making activities by independent Irish producers.  He should. It is quite true to say that there is nothing in the Bill which prevents the board from using the bulk of the money for the purpose <Col N="479" /> for which, in my opinion, it should be used &mdash; helping independent film producers.  On the other hand, there is nothing in the Bill to compel the board to do so.  If we are really talking about Irish film making and not simply a film industry in Ireland, this is what the bulk of the money in the Bill should be devoted to. The Minister says, rather condescendingly:</P>
    <P>Notwithstanding their worthwhile efforts in recent years, the ability of the majority of independent Irish producers to properly put together, manage and control commercial films with substantially increased budgets is, as yet, unproven.</P>
    <P>He is saying &ldquo;our boys cannot really get into the big time, they are not up to it&rdquo;. This question was put for comment to one of our outstanding film producers, Louis Marcus, in a very interesting interview and very relevant to this debate, in a little publication produced by the Irish film and theatre people called IFT News. It is a serious commentary of film making, and in the December 1980 issue, Kevin Rockett interviews Louis Marcus.  It is well worth reading for what Marcus has to say on these Bills.  Rockett reminds him of what the Minister said, that Irish film makers do not have the knowledge to be able to make the type of commercial features which he says foreign producers could make, and seemed to have made disparaging comments against the Irish independent film makers.  Marcus's reply is:</P>
    <P>No film makers in the world, outside the United States, have proved themselves able to make the kind of feature films that will crash the American-controlled world distribution market.</P>
    <P>It is not a question of our boys not being capable.  This is simply a problem faced by far more experienced film producers than the people we have here.  It raises the problem of beating the distribution stranglehold of the really big film makers in the United States.</P>
    <P>The Minister expresses himself as being surprised at the apparent criticism <Col N="480" /> of international projects as if they were almost a discouragement to the Irish film makers, but are they not?  Are not international projects, in the sense of big business film making, fly by night film making in Ardmore under the NFSI, not the real discouragement to Irish film makers?  Is there not an obsession with shoring up national film studios, with throwing good money after bad?  Has that not a depressing effect on Irish film makers and is it not quite simply a diversion of funds to Ardmore, with a loss to Irish film makers who need these funds very badly?</P>
    <P>I also take exception to the Minister's statement that the board and the film finance fund are &ldquo;also designed&rdquo; to further native film making talents.  They are &ldquo;also designed&rdquo;, after all these years of the wrong kind of subsidies to the wrong kind of films.  There may also be a few crumbs, he says, for our native film makers.</P>
    <P>The Minister pays gracious compliments to Mr. John Boorman who, I suspect, has been highly influential in the background shaping to this whole Bill. He said that Mr. John Boorman, the chairman of NFSI, has done great things for the Irish film industry.  He has, of course, but the Irish film industry has done good things for Mr. Boorman as well.  Ardmore and the NFSI have been good to Mr. Boorman.</P>
    <P>Towards the end of his speech the Minister made the following extraordinary statement:</P>
    <P>While developments in the last decade in the film industry seemed to be showing a trend away from studios and concentrating more on location work, the situation seems to be turning in recent years with the trend for films with a higher studio content.</P>
    <P>Neither the Minister nor I is an expert in this matter but my information is that the whole trend nowadays is towards location film making, that studios are to a large extent obsolete and that this highlights even more the irrelevance of the Ardmore adventure.</P>
    <P>I find the Minister's statement very unsatisfactory in many respects.  The <Col N="481" /> basic fault, perhaps, is the suggestion that we are talking about an industry rather than encouragement to a cultural activity.  Even if we accept the concept of industry, he is encouraging the wrong kind of industry.  He is encouraging the use of film facilities by foreign producers and the accidental aspects of film making in Ireland rather than a native film industry.  There is a wrong analogy here, too. The ideology of the economy and the multinationals is applied to the film making business.  The idea of attracting producers and offering them favourable facilities is a straight application of one of the conventional pieces of wisdom in our economy which still prevails.  Alas, like the parent model, we have the same sad results; when the going gets rough and when their business is finished, out they go and leave very little behind them. This is what has been happening with foreign producers, just as it has been happening with multinationals.</P>
    <P>I referred a while ago to the <i>IFT News.</i> In that worthwhile little paper I find the information that the season just commencing at the IFT will feature programmes once again from Iceland, New Zealand and Australia.  If Iceland, with a population of 230,000, can have an interesting and successful indigenous feature film industry, why cannot we do the same?  Icelanders do not bother to try to break into international markets or to get into the American distribution system. They simply concentrate first on their home market and their films are both a critical and a box office success in Iceland.  Because of this they are welcome in the wider world of film culture.</P>
    <P>Australia, though physically enormous, is a new and small country in the sense of not having a massive film industry.  The successful body there are the Australian Film Commission, who guarantee the money to independent film producers.  Because they are favoured by the State, business interests take up sponsorship and appear in the credit titles.  When money has to be paid back by the film producers the last people to whom they have to pay it are the Australian Film Commission.  We might well have taken <Col N="482" /> that for a model instead of throwing good money after bad.</P>
    <P>On Committee Stage I will refer to the composition of the film board.  I agree with the Minister that there have to be hard-headed businessmen on the film board and there have to be artistic individuals as well.  Of course, projects have to be worthwhile, but that does not mean that they have to be commercial in the Hollywood sense.  Why not encourage the kind of low budget, indigenous feature, costing &mdash; and the sum has been suggested to me by the independent film producers involved &mdash; an average £¼ million?  We should look for its success in Ireland first and in five or six European countries, which means it should pay for itself; any further distribution would make a handsome profit.  Economically speaking, apart from any artistic or cultural considerations, the shrewdest investment for the State would be in native film development rather than the big time American controlled entertainment market which we cannot crash.</P>
    <P>It is very significant that at the Sense of Ireland festival last spring, which was by common consent very successful, the film aspect was represented virtually entirely by the work of independent film producers.  Not one film produced by the National Film Studios of Ireland since 1975 or before then by the various managements of Ardmore Studios was included in the Sense of Ireland festival for the simple reason that not one of the Ardmore films fell within the category of an indigenous film.  If that is not a sufficiently eloquent fact, I do not know what is.  Not one film came out of Ardmore which was made in the first instance for an Irish audience.  The moral of that surely is that the £4.1 million should be earmarked clearly for the kind of people who did us proud in London last spring.</P>
    <P>Finally, I should like to remind the House that the film producers in Ireland are, first and foremost, artists.  They are not analogous to industrialists.  Of course they are out to make a living but since all of us know who they are &mdash; it is invidious to name names &mdash; I do not think we can point to any of them and say they have made a fortune out of film making.  They <Col N="483" /> are making films for the same reasons that other people paint pictures or write poems.  If it is the business of Government, and I believe it is, to extend its patronage to artists &mdash; indeed the Taoiseach has more than once pledged himself to that &mdash; then we must see the independent film producers of Ireland deserving the patronage of Government and the people, no less than her painters. In a particular way the film makers and film producers and all those associated with them are the quintessential artists of the twentieth century.  They are the chroniclers of our time in a very special way, and so they deserve much better treatment than they have got in this cynical and sloppy Bill.  They are not only the chroniclers of our time, they should also be essentially the chroniclers of our culture.  It is for them and in their interests that we should be considering this Bill, and not for a discredited and obsolete film studio.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusBrennan" hpid="Mr. Brennan Mr. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>I join my colleagues in welcoming this Bill.  Senator Cooney referred to the funds which might go into such an industry as going into a bottomless pit.  He pointed out that it is, perhaps, the wrong time to get involved in such an industry and felt that, looking at it overall, the future was far from secure.  I must confess to finding that approach to this Bill a little bit disappointing from the Leader on the other side of the House. Where is his confidence in our writers and artists?  Where is his confidence in the Irish determination to make a success of things, given a chance to do so?  I am a bit disappointed at the apparent inferiority complex which he portrays in regard to our ability as a nation to make a success of a film industry.  Starting in the fifties, through the sixties and seventies and now at the start of the eighties we have been playing around with getting a film industry started.  Let us take the reins off and get moving, because we have been playing with it for too long. We owe it to the pioneers of film making in Ireland and to our youth to give them the encouragement from this House which they need in starting an Irish film <Col N="484" /> industry.  We should not in any way hold back that encouragement or vote of confidence in our new industry which is about to be put on a formal and legal footing. While I agree with much that Senator Murphy said, there was a lot with which I did not agree.  I would charge him with having spent a lot of time rewriting the wording of the Minister's speech&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish I could.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusBrennan" hpid="Mr. Brennan Mr. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;which points to a great future, perhaps, in film scripts for Senator Murphy in the years ahead.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Or in the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusBrennan" hpid="Mr. Brennan Mr. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>He made a point, as did Senator Cooney that this is a cultural and an artistic activity and we should not put too much pressure on it to break even, to be commercial or in any way to pay its way.  I do not understand why we continually have to feel that culture or the arts are in themselves a loss-making activity.  There is no inherent reason in the long term why we have to push culture into a little box, leave it aside and say &ldquo;We all know culture loses money and let us leave it there and forget about it&rdquo;.  Of course we agree it is an artistic industry, but this House and the Government should encourage those involved in the industry to make a genuine effort at least to break even and take the responsibility off the shoulders of the taxpayers.</P>
      <P>This House should be careful about overdoing the cultural and artistic aspect of this at the expense of saying quite bluntly &mdash;&ldquo;We would ask you to make a genuine effort in your new industry to try, at least, to reach a break even situation&rdquo;.  If we do not mention that somehow we will be pulling back on the pressure, and by doing that we could be faced here in a few years time with some Minister saying that it is a cultural activity and they have to report a gigantic loss of £X million and using the excuse that it is a cultural activity and we have to pay for culture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The same argument is used in the services area, which we are not debating today.  That is another argument I would <Col N="485" /> like to dissect on some future occasion. The fact that it is culture or a service does not mean that it necessarily has to cost us the earth in the years ahead.</P>
    <P>I also want to mention another aspect of the film industry which has not been touched on.  Apart from its artistic value and the commercial nuances and so on, it is also part of an entertainment industry which is, in my view, in need of co-ordinating.  I would like to see in the years ahead some form of national entertainment organisation which would put some direction into the way in which the entertainment industry is going in this country. It is an old cliché which has been used a thousand times, that the pop group ABBA from Sweden made more in one or two particular years recently than the Volvo company of that nation.  It is no secret that the Beatles, who regrettably have been in the news recently, made a lot more for the United Kingdom in terms of revenue than many of the manufacturing industries in that country.  I mention these to highlight the enormous employment potential in the entertainment industry, of which I believe a new film industry to be a part.  With the structure of our population, which is greatly youth orientated at present, we have a responsibility to streamline the entertainment industry, and the new film industry would obviously have to take account of that.</P>
    <P>Senator Cooney referred to &ldquo;Strumpet City&rdquo; as an example of home production and how we manage to sell films abroad. That was the beginning of something which has enormous potential, but it needs to be properly structured.  RTE at present are making excellent efforts throughout the world, and particularly in the United States, to sell television films. We should look closely at the establishment of a sales company which might be attached either to the film industry or to RTE itself, but if it is attached to RTE it would certainly require some link with the film industry.  We have only scratched the surface of the kind of television material which we can sell abroad, and that is exporting every bit as much as exporting manufactured goods.</P>
    <P>Recently I have been watching the history series on BBC and it struck me that <Col N="486" /> we missed a great opportunity for our film industry.  Perhaps we should have had an opportunity in years gone by to make such a series ourselves and to sell it abroad and to use it in Ireland as well. I notice a tremendous interest in this series, particularly among young people, and it is a pity that our film makers did not approach it in the past.  I hope neither our film industry nor RTE would miss such an opportunity in the future.</P>
    <P>I am confident about this Bill because, unlike Senator Cooney, I feel that what our playwrights, actors or our world famous authors have done can be done in the same measure and with the same success and enthusiasm by Irish film writers.  We are on the threshold of an exciting new era in the Irish film industry.</P>
    <P>With regard to the financial aspect, the sponsorship of films has been mentioned. I agree with the Minister that this type of industry is not suited to the State sector in the long term because of its artistic and cultural ingredient.  Obviously the State must be involved at the commencement in order to show the way and the confidence.  Assuming that we keep this emphasis and pressure on the film industry at least to break even while carrying out their artistic profession, I can see private institutional investors, private funds and ordinary private enterprise getting involved in the production of films and this would certainly take a lot of weight off the State in the years ahead.</P>
    <P>If we are to have a film industry we need to train the film makers of the future so that we have a constant supply of trained technical professional personnel moving into the industry.  I am glad that the Minister and the Department have an open-minded approach.  There has been too much rancour between individual groups in this lead up to the establishment of an Irish film industry.  I hope that these Bills can now bring these groups closer together and start on a proper footing.  If we do not, it is the Irish film industry and the Irish people that will suffer, and I would appeal to them to try and make that effort in all our interest.</P>
    <P>The key to the success of this film Bill is marketing and distribution.  If we do not get out there and sell our television <Col N="487" /> films and full length films throughout the world, then we will not have an industry. That is where the circle has to start.  We have all sorts of marketing boards and Córas Tráchtála and I would advise the new board to look seriously at the establishment of a marketing subsidiary.  If we are not successful in achieving our markets throughout the world there is no points in making films to lie on the shelf.</P>
    <P>Senator Murphy pointed out that it is very difficult to break into the world markets, particularly as the United States distributors have it all tied up.  I accept that it is difficult but we have to start somewhere and we should try to break into the American market straight away. All our exports down the years have been hard to sell and it has been a long hard slog to try and sell them to the Americans and others, but we succeeded in great measure in convincing them that the Irish product was successful.  I would hope that in no less measure we can get out there and convince the other countries that the product from our film industry is of a high quality and that they should buy it.</P>
    <P>I would like to wish this film industry well in its early days.  Marketing is the key, and as soon as we achieve some progress in it then we can get down to establishing a proper film industry in Ireland.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>The most important feature of the film world is enthusiasm.  I am glad the Minister is back and I hope he will not take exception to what I am going to say.  I believe that if John Huston as a director, John Boorman as a producer, Maureen O'Hara as an actress or even Barry Fitzgerald &mdash; all Irish associated names &mdash; were to have seen the Minister in his presentation of this Bill today, they would have given him a very low marking as regards enthusiastic support for the launching of this Bill.  The very basis of the movie business is one of enthusiasm and confidence that everything will be right and that the product will be the best product that was ever created.  Similarly in the launching of the Irish Film Board and in putting the National Film Studios <Col N="488" /> on a new footing I believe that confidence and enthusiasm for the future are preeminent factors.  Perhaps the Minister is not a movie-goer, and that is the important point.  If one is an activist in any particular sport or art one can be a real afficionado.  If one is not, one can look upon it sometimes as one looks upon abstract art, in a rather dismissive way. I may have misunderstood the Minister. I would have preferred him to have launched this Bill with more enthusiasm.</P>
      <P>Whether we recognise it or not, cinema is recognised internationally as an art form.  The important question that Ireland has to face is whether Ireland has anything to contribute to this art form.  If it has, how does it do so and in what manner?  They are the important questions.  The launching of a film board is important and having our own film studios is also important, but they are nothing really unless that art form is seen as a true Irish art form.  It does not mean in any way that it portrays Irish scenery or does a PR job for the Irish Tourist Board or for any other aspect of Irish life.  The Irish character in all his passions and emotions, even eccentricities, must be pre-eminent features in what comes finally on the screen.  Earlier speakers referred to Sean O'Casey's plays, and one Senator said that it might not be possible to have the same success on the screen as on the stage.  Only an Irishman can bring to the screen, as an Irishman brought to the stage, the characteristics of Ireland and the Irish character.  One day we may well have a film which will be screened internationally and confronted with the characters on that screen we will see for the first time something which is on a par with what Sean O'Casey put on the stage.  I am confident that that will happen, but it will only happen if an Irishman is behind the camera, an Irishman is in the director's seat and, perhaps, if possible in the producer's armchair.  It cannot be left to foreigners to do it because we can only end up with the pseudo characters we have had in the past in the depiction of Irish people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In launching a film board we are taking an important step.  I am in favour of it, but I must express some reservations <Col N="489" /> about the manner in which it is being launched, principally in regard to the amount of funds which it is being given. A figure of £1 million per annum over three or four years is only chicken feed in a business which is renowned internationally for high costs.  What an Irish film board will be able to do with £1 million per annum I am not too sure.  I hope the people who are given that responsibility will be able to allocate it proportionate to both home product and foreign product.  It prompts the question as to whether there is a need at all for Government involvement if the amount of money entrusted is so little.  Could the private sector not be approached to come up with moneys of the scale envisaged in this Bill? In most other countries the private sector has very successful film studios and film industries.  However, the Minister may have decided to operate a compromise in this case.</P>
    <P>In every country today the film industry is very much a high risk business, and there are two facts of life associated with that high risk business.  One is the escalating costs which I already mentioned. Recently I read of a film which cost something like $34 million, approximately £20 million &mdash; one of the costliest ever &mdash; and it has received the thumbs down sign from all the critics.</P>
    <P>Another fact of life is the ratio of success to failure.  If film studios have one successful film out of ten produced they are doing very well.  That single success may well determine whether they act on a profit or loss basis for that year.  Film studios such as United Artists or Columbia have had a situation where one success has seen them through one year and has given them a very profitable situation but in the following year they may have loss after loss and find themselves practically in liquidation.  So we are entering into a very high risk business with a small sum of money.  Perhaps the Minister has decided it is the best way to approach this, to tread very carefully.  If so, we will see what happens in three or four years time.</P>
    <P>He has given emphasis to the work content and the PR aspect of films produced under the jurisdiction of the Irish Film Board.  I believe these are only part <Col N="490" /> of the objectives of an Irish film board or the Irish film studios.  The objective should be to inculcate in young Irish people a sense of the art of cinema and to develop the talents they may then find they have in that particular field.  It does not mean in any sense an emphasis on Irish scenery or even Irish history.  We know of many instances throughout the world of countries that have built up a very reputable film industry and in no case did they depend either on their scenery or their history to show what they had contributed to this art form.  It is a question of bringing to the screen characteristics of the race of people who have produced that film.  That is what is important.  It is not a question of bringing the stage Irishman onto the screen.  It is bringing to the screen a sense of genuine Irish passion, emotion and character.</P>
    <P>The Minister referred to the problem of film distribution.  There is no doubt cartels have always operated in this field, people who have cornered the market, who have been very careful about who gets which films, when they get them and for how long.  We had a case in the past couple of years where the Restrictive Practices Commission had some work in this regard and uncovered some very unsavoury details about what went on in this country in regard to the distribution of films.  There have been cinemas in provincial areas of Ireland particularly who have had to wait and wait until a film was no longer the big success it had been on first issue.</P>
    <P>It is interesting to note here the submission made by the Irish Film and Television Guild that the Film Board should set up a distribution office.  They referred to the fact that 30 per cent of the cost of a film has to go on distribution and promotion.  That is a very hefty sum to budget for, and it all goes for naught if the film does not end up in the cinemas. Selling a film is just as important as the production, or even more important, because unless the customer sees it there is no point in producing it.</P>
    <P>Although the Minister has made some amendments in the Bill I still think there is a certain amount of undue ministerial surveillance.  Section 25 deals with the <Col N="491" /> profits that may emanate from films. Hopefully there will be profits.  He could well have decided to leave to the judgment and discretion of the people on the Film Board the decision about what to do with any profits.  I am quite certain they would plough them all back without having to look over their shoulder at what the Minister might decide should be done with the profits.</P>
    <P>Section 31 refers to the Minister giving general directives.  He has emphasised that they will not be in regard to the artistic elements of a film.  It was good to see that amendment brought into the Bill.  However, right through the Bill there is provision for referral back to the Minister in regard to many matters.  This could have been left out, particularly in a business in which there is a very small financial commitment initially, whatever happens in the long term.  It is a business which depends tremendously on the judgment of the people concerned.  The people who will be on the Film Board will be persons with skill, knowledge and experience of the film industry, but more importantly with judgment as to what will be successful on the screen.</P>
    <P>There is no doubt the Film Board should help the Ardmore Studios.  They have had a very dismal history.  Senators are inclined to differ on the point as to whether the trend in the cinema world today is to work in or out of the studios. At the present time with the special effects in the cinema, where there is such a great need for concentrated work and the magnifying of that work to create special effects on the screen such as we saw in &ldquo;Close Encounters of the Third Kind&rdquo; and &ldquo;Alien&rdquo; and all sorts of things, possibly the studios are the &ldquo;in thing&rdquo;. That is not to say they will continue to be so.  Undoubtedly the Film Board should help the studios.</P>
    <P>The Irish Film and Television Guild have made an appeal that there should be some levy on admission prices to augment the finances available to the Film Board for investment purposes.  One would like to say there should be, but admission prices to anything nowadays seem to be escalating all the time.  It is <Col N="492" /> something which will have to be borne in mind, because I have no doubt that the initial investment of £4 million is completely inadequate and will have to be augmented considerably if we are to make a success of Irish film art.</P>
    <P>There will be great responsibility on the people given the task of producing and directing films in Ireland because most films are judged on a number of important matters &mdash; casting, the screenplay, the script and even the running time of the film.  If one of these is wrong the whole film can collapse.  It is going to call not only for experience and knowledge but for judgment.  I could not anticipate success in the near future in regard to the production of an Irish film which will meet all those criteria.  It will only come through time.  It will only come through young Irish people being inculcated with a sense of the art form of the cinema, being given the help and encouragement to devote their talents to it.  Finally we may produce a film which can stand on a par with what O'Casey produced even though it may not be on the same theme at all.  But it will bring to the front that characteristic of the Irish people, and it is only an Irish person who can do that.</P>
    <P>Those are the few comments I have to make on this Bill.  I welcome it.  The funding is completely inadequate.  I do not know if the Minister is a film-goer or not.  I think that can determine the amount of money he is prepared to put up in this matter.  Hopefully it will be a success and if it is a success I have no doubt that further financing will be provided.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CLambert" hpid="Mr. Lambert Mr. Lambert">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lambert</NameTxt>
      <P>I also am very glad to welcome these two Bills.  I do not see them as initiating a film industry but as enabling legislation in the promotion, and I hope the co-ordination, of the existing film industry.  I am also glad that they have been taken together, because the delay in introducing the legislation has aggravated the competing factions within the industry.  Unfortunately there has been too much controversy and disagreement regarding the priority for claims on financing.  I hope that the Film Board will be appointed as soon as possible.  I share <Col N="493" /> the Minister's concern that all those who are working in the film industry will now make it their objective to see that this legislation works and to see that in the initial stages the finance which is being provided will lead to revolving finance. Once the community see the finance revolving due to the success of the initial film making, it can lead to an encouragement of sponsorship from private enterprise and investment which, in turn, can lead to a return on equity, as someone mentioned, for the State.</P>
      <P>Having read the Dáil debates and listened to the Minister's introduction, I take a very different view from Senator Murphy as to the Minister's involvement. I feel he has approached this with a great deal of thoroughness in the advice he has taken, obviously obtaining the maximum information and weighing up the views and ideas of a number of groups with fairness and honesty.</P>
      <P>I was at the relaunching of the National Film Studios some years ago when it was expected that legislation would be introduced.  This was in the time of another Government and obviously Ardmore was seen by the board and the management in this context.  There was a great deal of optimism at the time.  However, the company were not capitalised and this meant they had to borrow from the commercial banks to remedy inherited ills.  We must remember that the Government subsidies included a great deal of inflated interest rates.</P>
      <P>I have visited the studios from time to time.  In fact, we held our radio and television awards function there in 1978 and I can speak with personal experience of the enthusiasm and total commitment of Séamus Smith and his staff.  Very few companies can boast of such an understanding and good working relationship between chairman and managing director.  It is a pity that Members of the Oireachtas do not use to a greater extent the opportunity to visit State bodies before they run into criticism and try to learn some of their problems so that before debating them they will have some experience of all the various aspects of the problems that affect any State body.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In spite of all the drawbacks, the <Col N="494" /> National Film Studios have been instrumental in bringing to the screen 29 cinema and television features, some made wholly and some made partly in Ireland. These films have brought some £10 million in foreign earnings into the Irish economy.  Because of the nature of the industry such earnings entail minimum outlay in the importation of equipment and raw materials.  Unfortunately, these benefits are not reflected in the annual accounts of the National Film Studios, a disadvantage shared by many other creative institutions which attract wide-scale participation.  Another instance is the Dublin Theatre Festival which is in a similar category.  From my information, the studios received £1.466 million in Government subsidies over a period of five-and-a-half years which represents approximately only £260,000 per annum. However, leaving aside the benefits to our economy which I have already mentioned, this expenditure is well offset now by the inflated value of one of the most modern and efficient studios in Europe in &ldquo;a garden of Ireland&rdquo; setting.</P>
    <P>It is interesting to note that when the studios went public they got the support of the unions who played a major role in persuading the Government to purchase them.  I think they have been proved right.  We heard earlier in the debate that employment has been quite high this year on the filming and shooting of &ldquo;Knights&rdquo; where there were 220 Irish technicians, construction crew, actors and drivers employed.  In addition, an average of 260 Irish extras were employed for a 15-week period and from this film alone the economy benefited to the tune of some £3½ million.</P>
    <P>The ordinary man in the street reading about the conflict between the film studios and the independent film makers does not seem to realise that the film studios have given assistance to many of the independent films that have been made in this country and which have been widely acclaimed abroad.  There is Bob Quinn's &ldquo;Poteen&rdquo;, Kieran Hickey's &ldquo;Exposure&rdquo;, and Cíarín Scott's award winning film.  &ldquo;Rosc, the Poetry of Vision&rdquo;.  With regard to this last mentioned film, I had the privilege of arranging <Col N="495" /> a showing in New York recently for the International Council of the Museum of Modern Art.  This film is a classic recording of the highlights of modern international art in the past ten years.  In company with ancient treasures, Celtic craftsmanship and the period of the Vikings in Ireland, it cleverly blends the work of ancient and modern together with Irish nature in a fascinating way with music and without commentary.  To my view it is a work of art in itself.</P>
    <P>The reason I am specially mentioning this film is that it provides an excellent example of what an Irish film producer and director can do when given the opportunities.  I mention it in particular having read the criticism in the Dáil debates that the Bill was not going far enough to make the film board responsible for promoting Irish culture or an Irish dimension.  Here is a film that has all those qualities, which can be admired internationally, without having terms of reference imposed on the producer.  The acclamation in New York was quite overwhelming and as there were numerous requests for further showings I left the film with the Irish Consulate.  It brought home to me what has been mentioned in this debate, namely, the difficulty of distribution, because so many people have to see the film before the enthusiasm and demand increases.  There is no doubt that CTT and our foreign affairs service can help enormously in getting initial showings, particularly of documentary films, and thus get an opportunity to attract a wider interest.</P>
    <P>Although the National Film Studios have had to mark time much has been achieved.  I hope the capitalisation now will enable them to progress in the way they have been trying to do, in having incentives to offer film producers, both national and international.  We must remember that a film has to be made for an audience.  As we have a small population it is very difficult to get a good financial return from only showing the film in this country and that is why we have to look at it from an international aspect.</P>
    <P>I remember the classic film of all time <Col N="496" /> made in Ireland which was, of course &ldquo;The Quiet Man&rdquo;, which I believe ran in Paris for 20 consecutive years in one cinema or another, proving beyond doubt that an audience does not necessarily have to be English-speaking to appreciate the film or, for that matter, Irish speaking.  When I saw the film in Paris it was sub-titled.</P>
    <P>It was said in the debate that films need not necessarily be dubbed, that they can be shown with the sub-titles if they have the qualities that appeal to the general public.  &ldquo;The Quiet Man&rdquo; captured the imagination and empathy of the whole world, and that brings to mind an obvious name which I strongly recommend to the Minister for appointment to the film board, and that is Maureen O'Hara.  She has had 40 years in every facet of film making all over the world; she has contacts with those who can influence international distribution and she also has a very strong business head.  She could bring immediate international standing to the new board.  In the past we have been quite remiss at honouring our famous sons and daughters in their lifetime, and I feel that here is an opportunity to honour one of our own who has received so many awards abroad.  Indeed I was delighted to see she received one at last in Cork at their recent Film Festival.</P>
    <P>I would also like to suggest members from Northern Ireland.  I know that on the Arts Council of Northern Ireland there is a film director and a film committee who are offering money subsidies to produce films and who are enthusing the whole community in Northern Ireland to look at film making for the future. I can let the Minister have some names in due course.  There is such involvement in the film making up there that I would like to see a member on the Film Board here.  I suppose there should be representation from the studios and from the independents.  We have Kieran Hickey, an outstanding film maker who has all the qualifications, who has travelled abroad, who knows what the international distributors need in a film coming from Ireland. He has already acknowledged the benefits he has received from CTT in travel grants in enabling him to go to America.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="497" /> I think his experience would be very valuable to the new Film Board.</P>
    <P>We have talked about culture and artistic element, but little has been said about the creativity of making films.  This is the key.  It is not just culture and art, it is the whole creative, imaginative flair which, quite frankly, I feel is now happening in this country in people who need employment and do not want to live on charity. The opportunity here for these Bills to give the creative population an opportunity to express themselves is unlimited. We can benefit greatly from the output and scale of films to be produced.  I hope that the Film Board, with their initial finance will look at the opportunities to provide the revolving finance, and then I think we will have the basis of a very successful film industry in the future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GemmaHussey" hpid="Mrs. Hussey Mrs. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>I just have a few very brief words to say on this Bill.  I am very glad so many Senators have spoken on it and have given it such a welcome.  Indeed it is customary more often than not in this House that we stand up and we say &ldquo;I welcome this Bill&rdquo;, Ministers look gratified and we proceed on that basis.  I particularly want to say that I welcome this Bill because I get the distinct impression that the Minister does not.  I think it is quite important that it be established that some of us do welcome it.</P>
      <P>I feel that the tone of the introduction of this Bill was quite different this time from the usual occurrence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Donnelly addressed some remarks to Senator Cooney, chastising him for a negative approach.  I think his remarks might have been more properly addressed to the Minister.  It is no wonder that Senator Cooney would take from the Minister's statement such a very negative attitude.  What worries me about the way this Bill has been approached is that we are talking about creative people, we are talking about an industry which has certainly a most significant technological input but which also depends totally in the long run on its creative people.  If I were involved in trying to get this industry off the ground in Ireland, I must say I would be extremely discouraged by what I have heard today.  I would leave <Col N="498" /> the reading of this debate in rather a depressed state, feeling, to quote Patrick Kavanagh &mdash; he used the words in a different area &mdash;&ldquo;that something that was struck so foul a blow so early in life had little chance of success&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>It seemed to me that the Minister was reluctantly bringing this Bill before us.  I did not get the impression that he had much of an opinion either of films or film makers or the possible contribution they could make to Irish society.  When I say that, of course, I am aware that at difficult times &mdash; and the Minister did stress so often in his statement that times were difficult, money was short and money might be short for the film industry &mdash; the arts in general and things in that area suffer.  I would only say to the people involved in the film industry, take comfort from that, they are among the people who do suffer when times are hard.</P>
    <P>I hope I do not exaggerate the negative qualities of the provisions of this Bill. We had threats thrown out about this being the only opportunity there would be, about how there would be a review to see how things were getting on, and that really there was a very short fuse to the Minister's patience with this industry. In fact, I felt the whole thing was rather in the line of throwing a bone to a dog who was condemned to be put down quite soon anyway.  It has been mentioned in the Minister's statement and by several other people that we are almost alone in the EEC countries in not giving major inducements and incentives to film makers.  We should stop to think why these other countries see fit to give substantial moneys to film makers, because if we examine the reasons why they do it it is quite clear why we should do it too.  In passing, I would like to say that I hope we will not have films like &ldquo;The Quiet Man&rdquo; in the next few years while the film industry survives, although I hope it will survive much longer.</P>
    <P>The countries which subsidise their film makers heavily have appreciated the potential of film making as part of an enormous media and communications industry which is developing so rapidly in the world that every possible aspect of it must be used to strengthen a country's <Col N="499" /> standing in the world and to establish a country's identity.  Never could it be more important for a very small country like this to join in that effort in using this new technology.  I see a situation before very long that somebody in Los Angeles or Hong Kong could press a button in their sittingroom and conjure up a film from Ireland about Ireland, that we will not be dependent on having to distribute the films in the way that we think of it now but that we will be part of an enormous technological revolution which has started and will gather impetus.  Rather than be reluctant, or penny-pinching, on this matter, we should realise that we may miss a very fast-moving boat indeed, if we do not give positive incentives and much more definite encouragement to this industry.</P>
    <P>I had the honour of working as a member of the board of directors of the Abbey Theatre for four years, and it is not easy to work with artistic people, in the field of theatre and in the creative field.  That it is not easy should not make us impatient with, or dismissive of them.  No really creative person, no genius, is ever easy to live with, or is ever a totally rounded person in every other area.  People involved in the creative side of this industry need a lot more consideration than they have got.  We have, in the Abbey Theatre, an absolutely superb group of actors who have already demonstrated their abilities in film making, in films like &ldquo;Strumpet City&rdquo;.  I hope that the establishment of this industry will give their talents a far greater range than they have at the moment.</P>
    <P>I am very interested in the subject of the National Film Studios because I grew up on the road on which the studios are located.  I very much hope that, despite the reluctance displayed in getting this Bill off the ground, this Bill will give the National Film Studios a new lease of life. They are on a par with the very best in the world.  They stand up to comparisons with excellent studios in the United States, for example, and give extremely badly needed employment in an area which could be improved beyond all <Col N="500" /> imaginings if we approach this business positively, and if we can, by this debate convey our encouragement to the people who are starting this industry and that we wish them well.  I conclude by saying that I welcome these two Bills.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. O'Malley) Desmond J. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. O'Malley)</NameTxt>
      <P>A great variety of points were made.  I do not know if it is feasible for me to reply to them all in detail, because of their diversity.  It is interesting to contrast the very strong speech made by Senator Cooney after I had introduced the Bill with what was said afterwards, particularly on his own side of the House.  I was accused by a number of Senators of a lack of enthusiasm, which some of them described as an uncharacteristic lack of enthusiasm.  If I were unenthusiastic in some of what I had to say, I would like to contrast that with the total hostility to the whole idea that is contained in this Bill on the part of Senator Cooney, who is one of the leaders of the Opposition here.  It was a very strong speech, well argued and well researched.  His use of the quotations from the Committee on Public Accounts was effective and, in many respects, compelling.  I assume that that report was signed by a member of the Opposition as chairman of the Committee concerned, Deputy O'Toole.  My Department were accused of ignoring the strictures of the Committee of Public Accounts.  There are many strong, detailed criticisms which the committee made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Before I begin to defend myself against those on the same side of the House as Senator Cooney who attacked me from the directly opposite direction in defence of what Senator Cooney said, in criticism of me &mdash; that I brought forward these Bills and ignored the Committee of Public Accounts, whose advice could generally be summarised to the effect that we should forget about film studios in this country, certainly at the public expense &mdash; it is only right to point out that this particular studio company was never capitalised in the normally commercially accepted sense of the word.  As I understand it the money for the original purchase was put up but there appears to <Col N="501" /> have been no injection of equity capital and to have been fairly heavy borrowing.</P>
    <P>A further factor that one must take into account is, of course, that there was no system of direct financial incentives in this country, so far as film making was concerned.  Everybody here who said that there was none at all, is wrong.  There was a very valuable incentive in terms of export tax relief, the benefit of which went to film makers and indeed, to manufacturers of goods.  Apart from that there was not available, hitherto, a system whereby direct grants, or loans or equity investments in a film, could be made by a board or fund established for that purpose.  We were certainly at a disadvantage in that respect.</P>
    <P>Endeavouring to defend myself against the strong criticism of Senator Cooney for having brought in these Bills, I have to do a quick mental switch and defend myself against the criticisms of his colleagues for not having introduced them sooner, or shown greater enthusiasm or optimism in regard to them.</P>
    <P>The first thing I would like to say is that I am the first Minister for Industry and Commerce in ten years who has done anything, in legislative terms, about the film industry.  It is a little disappointing that, when one does take the plunge into this slightly contentious area &mdash; which seems to be made up of a lot of very fractious people &mdash; you are immediately rounded on, first by those who think you should have done nothing and then by those who think you should have done a lot more and done it a lot sooner.  It is a no-win situation, without question.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister cannot win.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Markey seemed to believe that my commitment, or otherwise to the film industry was in direct proportion or ratio to the number of films which I view every year, and I think he suspects that I never see any.  I am happy to be able to tell him that I probably see more films than anyone else in this House at present.  In fact, I was trying to work it out, roughly speaking, I calculate that I see about 20 films a year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="502" />
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that all?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Every one of them somewhere between 30,000 and 40,000 feet up and every one of them involuntarily.  I do not know if films they show in aeroplanes are the same as those they show on the ground, but if they are, and if the terrestrial films are as bad as those shown in the air, it is easy to understand why the film industry finds itself in difficulties, in this and in other countries.  The standard seems to be pretty poor to say the least of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>That means that the Minister does not go to the movies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I go involuntarily, because I am unable to sleep and because these films are inflicted on you.  You are not allowed to read.  Unfortunately, you have no option but to look at them at that stage.  It is bad enough when you have to look at one on a particular trip, but when you have to look at three of them your enthusiasm would, quite naturally, wane.</P>
      <P>On the question of reported losses and so on encountered by the National Film Studios of Ireland Limited in recent years, there are some conflicting figures in this respect.  For that reason, it is better that I set out the actual losses that the studio has incurred in each of the past four years.  In the year 1977 £470,566, in 1978 £497,041, in 1979 £523,295 and in 1980 &mdash; of course, the year is not yet over &mdash; I understand that the estimated loss is about £500,000.  It cannot be suggested that these are minor losses which are more than made up for by the amount of business that is generated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is worth drawing the attention of Senators to the fact that this year was one of the more successful years, in terms of business, at the studio &mdash; almost entirely due to Mr. Boorman's film &ldquo;Knights&rdquo; in which there was a very high content of employment of Irish people, thanks to Mr. Boorman and to his generally helpful attitude towards the studio and the country which I referred to in my opening speech.  There have been, of course, other films made by Mr. Boorman and, <Col N="503" /> indeed, other films made by other Irish people, including &ldquo;Cry of the Innocent&rdquo;, where a very high proportion of Irish people was used in its making.  There are some producers, certainly, who are willing to give substantial help in this respect.</P>
    <P>If it is felt that I am less than enthusiastic about some aspects of this, it is not unnatural that I should be apprehensive, in the light of the kind of losses that have been sustained and in the light of my experience of some trading semi-State companies in recent years and the belief that because the State owns a company it does not really matter tuppence whether it ever succeeds or fails.  It is a handy place where people can get permanent jobs without any of the unpleasant commercial constraints that the real world imposes on private sector companies.  It would be in the general, overall interest of this country if we could get away from this belief which seems to be so deeply prevalent and if we could get away from a situation of taking it as fact, utterly for granted, that the situation of a company which loses £½ million a year for four consecutive years, when its original assets cost less than £½ million, is no problem and that such a company should be allowed to continue at the expense of the Irish taxpayer for all time.  I do not share that view of this or any other State company.  They should face up to and be encouraged to face up to commercial reality.  In so far as they do not, perhaps I am less enthusiastic.  Some people may feel that I should be.</P>
    <P>Senator Murphy complained about the similarity between the speech I delivered here and the speech I delivered in the Dáil.  I accept that criticism, except that I would put it to him that the main one of these two Bills only passed in the Dáil last evening and there was not very much opportunity to rethink an entirely different approach, as between five or six o'clock last night and 2.30 p.m. today. Senator Murphy pleaded that I should say here and now that it is my opinion that the bulk of the money which is being made available through the Film Board should go to independent film producers. He should contemplate the consequences <Col N="504" /> of his asking me to say that.  If I do say it, it means that overnight we close down the National Film Studios of Ireland.  In spite of the criticism which I have made, I am not prepared to do that.  Senator Murphy and people like him cannot have it both ways.</P>
    <P>A number of Senators made the point that the expression of Irish culture and the expression of it abroad in particular, is of paramount importance in regard to films.  It is certainly one important factor, but I recall the debate in the Dáil where I was rounded on by Deputy Kelly, who vehemently objected at quite some length to my saying that.  To some extent, Senator Cooney is saying much the same today.  He talks about the question of the prestige of this country and it betokens in his view &mdash; and may well be right &mdash; a national inferiority complex to feel that we should be concerned about our prestige, or that we should try to build it up through an economically troubled industry like the film industry.</P>
    <P>Senator Murphy expressed himself as being against any of the money proposed in these Bills being spent on foreign productions coming in here.  If he is, he knows that the consequences are that we can close down the film studio in the morning.</P>
    <P>Senator Brennan quite rightly made the point that the key to much of the success in film making is the whole question of distribution and asked me in that respect to look at the possibility of a marketing board.  He also suggested an entertainment industry board to streamline the entertainment industry, and suggested that a sales company attach to RTE and the film industry.  I do not disagree with the principle of what he suggests, but wonder if the formation of two further quangos is the right way to go about it.  Do we not have enough of this breed at the moment in this country? There is no doubt that distribution and marketing of films is of absolute importance.  If you are guaranteed in advance that your film will be shown in 1,000, 1,500 or 2,000 cinemas in the United States, at the very worst you will not lose a lot of money on the making of the film. If your film production company is <Col N="505" /> attached to one of these cartel or multinational operations you have an enormous advantage.</P>
    <P>I expressed in my opening speech, and in the Dáil, my unwillingness to tie on to the Film Board statutory obligations to market or distribute films because they will simply have films of varying degrees of talent and varying degrees of commercialisation dumped on their desk.  If they fail to sell, they will be blamed for the failure of what would otherwise have been, technically and artistically, a great film.  I do not think they should be forced into that position.  If they can develop, over the years, some distribution expertise &mdash; and I hope that they might be able to do it in conjunction with the film studio and with RTE, and that all three of them might operate together for that purpose &mdash; then they may be able to build up a worthwhile network.  It is a daunting prospect &mdash; and let us remember this &mdash; for an Irish State-owned operation to break into a market or a system of distribution which is dominated by multinational companies who have all kinds of incestuous relationships with one another and who have dominated this whole scene for a very long time.  I would certainly give them every encouragement because I regard it, as Senator Brennan does, as the key to the success of film making here by Irish people but it would be unfair and unrealistic to expect them to achieve overnight success.</P>
    <P>I have not mentioned by name the sort of people one would like to see on this board.  Senator Lambert was good enough to make one or two suggestions. The lady to whom he referred would seem to me to be eminently suitable, if she were prepared and available to serve. One of the difficulties I want to avoid in a board of this kind is appointing a representative board where everyone is representing some particular group or action and where everyone sees himself or herself on the board as just fighting for the narrow sectional interests of his or her particular part of the industry.  Too many of our boards, in my view, are dominated by people who are there in a representative capacity and whose ability, therefore, <Col N="506" /> to make a positive contribution on a broader plane is very much limited because they are all the time reporting back to their constituents whom, they allegedly represent on particular boards. The more successful type of board, in my experience, is one where individual members are not under heavy daily pressure from sectors in the industry concerned and are able to take a broader and perhaps a longer-term view, and are not answerable to particular groups.  That is fairer to board members also, because it gives them a better opportunity to work in a more positive fashion for the greater public interest.</P>
    <P>I hope that I have dealt with the main points that have been made, but if the Senators have any further queries which I might have inadvertently overlooked, I would be glad to reply to those on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Irish Film Board Bill, 1979:" RHead="Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Irish Film Board Bill, 1979: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 to 3, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 4</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 4 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>Since so much emphasis has been placed on the sale of films and the distribution problems that will be involved, would the Minister not consider writing into the section the word &ldquo;distribution&rdquo; so that the first line of page 4 would read: &ldquo;The development of an industry in the State for the making and distribution of films&rdquo;?  It would give a greater emphasis as to its importance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. O'Malley) Desmond J. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. O'Malley)</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no doubt that the broad way in which section 4 is drawn gives ample power to the board to engage in the distribution of films.  The point was made in the other House that it should be written in as a statutory obligation on them from day one.  I found <Col N="507" /> it necessary to resist that, because I do not think they can succeed from day one. They would find themselves in great difficulty in being forced to distribute films that were landed on their desk.  The expertise, the knowledge and the contacts which are necessary in film distribution will have to be built up by the board, in conjunction with the two other bodies I have mentioned over and above the period of a year, two years, three years or whatever.  When they feel that they have built up sufficient expertise to venture into that area, they would then become involved in a more active way. Of course, under the Bill they are free to do that.  In setting up the board, and in giving them general guidelines, I will certainly make clear to them that this is one of the areas in which they can be most helpful when they have acquired that expertise.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 5 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 6</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 6 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>One of the purposes of the Film Board is to create work in Ireland through all the different technical jobs that will be involved.  An effort should be made to, perhaps, screw down more of the film which must be made here rather than just having a vague definition that part of the film should be made here, because that could mean as little as 1 per cent or it could be only one quarter of one of the four reels of a film, if there are four reels.  The suggestion is that perhaps the word &ldquo;mostly&rdquo; could be substituted for the word &ldquo;partly&rdquo; or some suitable substitution of that kind be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The first point that I would make in reply to the Senator is that there is virtually no film at all which is wholly made in the State, because there are some aspects of technicalities that go into the making of a film that cannot be <Col N="508" /> done here.  For that reason probably no film can be actually 100 per cent made here, although a very high percentage can be done here.  In practice, in any event, most films are only partly made here.  I do not think it would be feasible to confine it to those that are wholly made here.  It would probably mean in practice that only the small short films were being made here.  I do not think it would be technically possible to make every possible aspect of a major feature film here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not dwelling on the word &ldquo;wholly&rdquo; at all.  I do accept that there might be some editing part which has to be done perhaps in America.  I am just dwelling on the word &ldquo;partly&rdquo;.  I am suggesting that the section should read &ldquo;the making of a film wholly or mostly&rdquo; or include some suitable word like &ldquo;mostly&rdquo;.  We could try and screw down a very&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I will put it this way. There is no doubt whatever that the degree of assistance that the board would render would be, to a great extent, in proportion to the amount of the film that was made here and to the amount of money that the company concerned was prepared to spend here.  Obviously a film, only 10 per cent of which is made here, could not expect the same degree of support as one which is 90 per cent made here.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 7 to 11, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 12.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 12 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems that section 15 determines a quorum for a meeting as being three.  Now the film business is a rather dirty business when it comes to control and distribution and so on.  A quorum of three is a very small number to make policy decisions in regard to such an important field as films.  It is my suggestion that perhaps the number of members <Col N="509" /> on the Film Board should be bigger so that the quorum itself will be proportionately greater.  So in section 12 I would suggest that we should have, instead of seven, say, nine or 11 or some figure like that, to get over this problem &mdash; and it can be a very important point &mdash; of a small section of the board, if that is all that is present, being able to make policy decisions.  Three members appears to me to be rather a small number to make important policy decisions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I deplore the fact that Committee Stage has been taken this evening, and some of us who were at a meeting were quite taken aback to discover that this was being done.  In these two important measures which we have been considering, we should have been given the opportunity to defer Committee Stage until next week.</P>
      <P>On section 12, it has been suggested, and very wisely I think, that the board should include not only people of artistic qualifications, people who know about filming, but hard-headed businessmen, if hard-headed businessmen is not a tautology.  I agree with that, but I think that the Bill should make specific provision to exclude the kind of businessman who has other film interests, who may very well be involved as a shareholder, or whatever, in a profit-making film company either inside or outside the State.  Here there would be a grave matter of the private interest conflicting with the public good and I do not see why section 12 should not have included such a proviso.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. P. Reynolds) Acting Chairman (Mr. P. Reynolds)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. P. Reynolds)</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the Minister replies to Senator Murphy, I came into the Chair at a given time and there was no objection to taking all Stages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not intend my remarks as being any reflection on the Chair, Sir, but on those who are responsible for arranging the Business of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="510" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>It was arranged here by the Members of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>On the question of the quorum I would point out to Senator Markey that it is not fixed inflexibly at three.  Under subsection (7) of section 15 it can be a higher number, if I so direct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>It is unlikely, considering that the basic number is seven members anyway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  I am looking at a list of State company boards which have seven members which is one of the most usual, NEB, BGE, RTE, IIRS, NET, and the quorum in respect of all of those is three.  In the 1970 Bill which was the rather distant progenitor of this one, the quorum is fixed at two, and section 134 of the Companies Act, 1963 states that in the case of a private company two members shall constitute a quorum.  So I think it is a usual provision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I ask the Minister to make a comment on my point, which was that somebody specifically having a film interest should be disqualified from membership?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not accept that at all.  The very contrary is constantly being urged on me, that there should be people who have film interests, because if they have some connection with the industry and they are to be disqualified I think one goes to the other extreme.  I was talking in my reply to the Second Stage about the undesirability, as I saw it, of having a board where everybody was there in a representative capacity, representing some identifiable sector of the film industry to which he or she was going to be held responsible.  The suggestion had been urged on me that we should, for example, have a much bigger board and that every little sub-group that exists within virtually every sector of the industry should have a representative.  I think that is going too far in one direction, and I said that I thought that people who did not have a great deal of vested interest, or who were not answerable to <Col N="511" /> others, were obviously more satisfactory members of a board because they were able to take a broader view.  What Senator Murphy is urging is really the direct opposite, that anybody with any connection with the industry be ineligible, and that would do as much damage as the proposition that every particular interest should be represented.  I think the truth and the best solution lies in the middle and that one has a mixture of such people.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 13 to 16, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 17.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 17 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>This is in consequence of the point raised by Senator Murphy.  If the Minister is not willing to exclude a person who has an interest in some aspect of the film business from membership of the board perhaps he would add to section 17 a prohibition on him from taking part in any decision taking.  According to section 13 he has to disclose his interest before the matter is discussed but it still does not prevent him from taking part in the decision taking.  Perhaps the Minister would consider this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>In practice the usual procedure is that where somebody makes such a disclosure he withdraws from the remainder of the meeting which discusses such a matter.  It is a matter for the chairman of the board, under the normal procedures for the running of boards and board meetings, to request the person concerned to withdraw.  I think he has power to do that under the general law anyway.  He does not need to be given power to ask the person to withdraw. This statute does something which would not, perhaps, necessarily be part of the general law, in providing that a disclosure would have to be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have difficulty in understanding how such a member can <Col N="512" /> be compelled to state his interest if he is not so inclined to do.  Are there sanctions in that regard?  It is provided that a member shall disclose his interest to the board, but who is to compel him to do so?  If he does not do so are there conditions for expelling him?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am advised that this is a standard section used in similar terms in many other Bills.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>So it is, but that does not answer the question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not answer the question.  In other Bills, at times, that point may well be covered by a general offence section towards the end of the Bill.  But there is none in this Bill.  I suppose it is contemplated, in spite of Senator Markey's views, that nobody in this delightful industry would be capable of committing an offence.  The Senator has a good point.  Section 17 seems to be a moral exhortation rather than a substitute of law in the circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>It also includes my point that there is no obligation on a person to withdraw and there is no obligation on the chairman to request such a person to withdraw.  The chairman himself may have an interest in a particular aspect of the business.  So there are two points there where we are depending on moral obligations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not an expert on the Companies Acts but I think the chairman of the board would probably be able to exercise the powers that a chairman of a company could exercise under the Companies Acts.  I would imagine that those powers accrue to him except in so far as they are excluded by this Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know.  I wonder if we could have some advice on that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been suggested to me that the sanction may be section 12 (6) which says that the Minister, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, may <Col N="513" /> at any time remove a member of the board from office.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I see no organic connection between section 12 (6) and&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no organic connection but there may be a very practical connection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>But section 12 (6) does not state the reason for which the Minister may remove a member from the board, and certainly not specifically for not disclosing his interest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>He can remove him for any reason that to him seems proper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think section 17 should have more teeth than it has.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 18 to 24, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 25.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 25 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>Let me suggest that the Minister throw out this section of the Bill altogether.  If the people, as we are told, are going to have such a moral commitment and a moral obligation on their part to act wisely and judiciously under sections 17 and 18, I think they can be entrusted with any profits from such a high risk business like film making.  Whatever profits there may be, and I do not expect they will be considerable or even large in the early years in any case, the decision can be left to those people to decide what to do with that money which, in all probability will probably be to plough it back into the business.  That section could well have been left out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I would go so far with the Senator as to say that I regard the section as fairly academic.  If it does not achieve anything, at least it does no <Col N="514" /> harm.  It might aid employment for some printer for a couple of months in printing the last four lines of it.  Outside of that its value is limited.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 26 to 28, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 29.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 29 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>There may be something to be said for the Minister's principle that one of the features of drafting legislation is giving employment to printers.  Nevertheless, I would like to query section 29.  I think it should be dropped from Bills generally.  The Minister said apropos of section 17, that it is a stock feature of most Bills.  That is precisely my point.  As a newcomer I think a lot of legislation goes through and a lot of legislation is drafted by just repeating slabs because it has been there all the time.  There is a story told about a soldier standing guard in St. Petersburg over a spot which apparently marked nothing and the bureaucrats began to get curious about why one sentry after another there was appointed to guard a blank piece of earth.  It was discovered in the archives that long, long ago Catherine the Great had planted a particular flower there which she was very fond of and which had long since withered.  I suspect that many clauses in Bills are there simply because no one ever bothers to question their presence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In regard to section 29 I still have to find a satisfactory answer to the question of why should a Member of the Oireachtas be excluded, <i>ex officio</i>, from membership of such boards?  I put the question last week to the Minister for Education and he more or less, within the constraints of party propriety, told me I was right.  Why should I, for example, who have no film interests, no oil interests, or whatever, be excluded from a board of this kind?  There may be other reasons why I should be excluded, but I should <Col N="515" /> not be excluded because I am a Member of the House.</P>
    <P>It seems extraordinary that this provision is put in, but the other one, that someone with what may very well be self-interested motives as a businessman is allowed to sit on the board.  Obviously I am not asking the Minister to change section 29.  It is a stock feature of legislation.  But I would ask Members in general to consider whether in fact there is any real wisdom behind this.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>This type of section, which is on all fours with dozens of similar ones in other Bills of this kind, has appeared now for the last ten years or so in all these Bills.  I cannot really remember what the reasoning behind it was, but I suppose it was thought at the time that there was a certain impropriety in a Minister putting Members of the Oireachtas on certain types of boards.  Maybe there were some celebrated cases of that nature in the past.  It was the kind of thing that used to excite people a few decades ago. I do not know whether the members of this board get paid, but even if they do I can assure the House that they are not going to acquire much material benefit from their membership.</P>
      <P>The Senator rightly says that he is not, of course, asking me to take it out, because I cannot.  I cannot remember why it was ever put in in the first place. But I know the Department of Finance or of the Public Service or somebody insist that this section goes into all Bills because they want uniformity between all these bodies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>Subsection (5) of this section reads to me &mdash; correct me if I am wrong &mdash; that if an employee of the Film Board is elected to either House of the Oireachtas he is thereby disqualified from reckoning the period of membership in the Oireachtas for any superannuation benefits.  Does that mean that if there is a superannuation scheme within the Film Board he cannot continue paying towards the superannuation scheme of the Film Board?  Does it also mean that his term of membership of the Oireachtas is not reckoned as part of his <Col N="516" /> service in the Film Board for superannuation purposes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand the Senator to ask if somebody who is employed by the board, rather than on the board, is elected to the Oireachtas, does he lose his pension rights from the board in respect of the period.  As far as I can see the answer is that he does lose his pension.  On the other hand he does not lose his right to re-employment.  He just stands seconded, or whatever, from the board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>I think this is different. There are other pieces of legislation relative to other semi-State bodies where a person can continue paying towards the superannuation scheme of his ex-semi-State employer and thereby does not break his service for superannuation benefits even while he is a Member of the Houses of the Oireachtas.  So there is a difference here.  I think it is a bit unfair. It could well give him the same opportunities that exist in other cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Although this does not repair the principle, if the principle is wrong &mdash; and I am not positive I know whether it is or not &mdash; there will be very few employees on this board.  It is a purely administrative board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>Even if there are only one or two, it can still be unfair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not repair the principle of it if the principle is wrong but&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister could be keeping down good talent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I would recommend to people who view a career in the Oireachtas as a possibility that they would not apply for employment to this board if they want to keep their superannuation right.  Enthusiastic young people never worry about their pensions anyway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CLambert" hpid="Mr. Lambert Mr. Lambert">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lambert</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know of any other State body where a member of the <Col N="517" /> board has the benefit of a pension.  I know if one is a member of the board and joins the Oireachtas one has to resign before one actually joins the Oireachtas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a member of the board.  It is an employee, or officer or servant of the board, which is a different matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GemmaHussey" hpid="Mrs. Hussey Mrs. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>On section 29 I do not share Senator Murphy's reservations about this membership of boards by Oireachtas Members.  It is perfectly correct that the Members of the Oireachtas should not be members of semi-State boards.  Whether the principle was established ten years ago or not, it was a very good principle.  I would like to go on record as supporting that principle and I would hate to see it being departed from. I am sure other Members of this House might have been in the position that I was in when I was elected to this House when I was a member of another board and was about to resign from it when my term was up; unfortunately just before I put in my resignation the Minister fired me anyway.  But, as a matter of principle, notwithstanding the flower of Catherine the Great, this principle is a good one, and I am glad to see it in this Bill and I hope that it will remain in all such Bills.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 30 to 35, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to address the Minister because when I was making my contribution the Minister of State was present.  I would like to have brought in amendments but it would be pointless in the circumstances.  Now that the Bill is about to be passed, my reservations, briefly, are that public money has been <Col N="518" /> thrown away on film studios and that independent film producers are not people out for loot, by and large.  They are people who want to make a living in their own country, doing their own thing.  They are deserving of public support, and the fact that it was their work and not anything out of Ardmore that was displayed and won acclaim at the &ldquo;Sense of Ireland&rdquo; speaks for itself.  I respectfully ask the Minister while he is in Government and in this office to bear these points in mind.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="National Film Studios of Ireland" RHead="Limited Bill, 1979: All Stages">
    <Title>National Film Studios of Ireland Limited Bill, 1979: All Stages.</Title>
    <P>Agreed to take all Stages today.</P>
    <P>Bill read a Second Time, put through Committee, reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Sale of Irish Goods:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Sale of Irish Goods: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamHyland" hpid="Mr. Hyland Mr. Hyland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hyland</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann calls for immediate and sustained backing for the efforts of the Government and the Irish Goods Council in promoting the sale of Irish goods.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the opportunity of addressing the House.  In debating this issue we are supporting and adding our voice to a matter which, because of its very nature, is of basic and fundamental importance to our economic development.  I welcome the opportunity too of recognising at this level the very significant contribution made by the body entrusted with the task of promoting the concept of buying guaranteed Irish.  I compliment the chairman of the Irish Goods Council, Mr. Tom Hardiman, and the Chief Executive Officer, Mr. Vivian Murray, on their success in the campaign to date.  The dedication and enthusiasm they have displayed far exceeds the call of duty.  I also welcome the Minister of State.  If he pursues this portfolio with the same vigour and determination he displayed in <Col N="519" /> his previous Ministerial position this section of the Department is in very capable hands.</P>
    <P>I should like to express my thanks to the many voluntary organisations throughout the country who have, down through the years, supported the efforts of the Irish Goods Council in this important national matter.  It is clearly an area of activity where all of us can share a common platform in the national interest.  I do not wish to make this debate heavily laden with statistics.  The cost to the country in terms of large scale imports is widely known.  Its very serious effect on the economy is clearly on record.  Perhaps the most telling record of all is reflected in the thousands of homes throughout the country where husbands and wives, sons and daughters, are unable to enjoy the basic right of securing a job and earning their livelihood in their own country.  The creation of full employment has been the aim of successive governments, and this national priority has been restated on many occasions.  When the Government embarked on a very deliberate policy of job creation, there can be no doubt about its initial success. It is, however disappointing to note that the very welcome trend has been reversed and that unemployment is again on the increase.  I do not propose to analyse the many reasons for this undesirable trend, which is due to a number of varying economic circumstances.</P>
    <P>One does not have to be an economist to understand that one of the most important factors in increasing and maintaining employment is the market for Irish produce.  The most important and most economically favourable market for any country is the home market.  In this context the debate is relevant, and I hope our deliberations will jolt the public mind and the public conscience into realising that we all have a very serious responsibility in this regard.</P>
    <P>We are a developing economy and we spend thousands of pounds in exploring new markets abroad and we have had considerable success.  We welcome the recently announced new markets which Coras Tráchtála have been successful in <Col N="520" /> negotiating abroad.  Our products are universally accepted as being goods of quality and value, particularly when they carry the guaranteed, easily recognisable, Irish symbol.</P>
    <P>Does it make sense then that our success in export markets is being undermined at home by our failure to support the industries and to purchase the products which are manufactured in them? Many reasons have been put forward for this attitude.  My own view is that it is due to a large extent to complacency and a lack of thought on the part of the customer and, in many cases, to the failure of the shop to stock and put on display the produce of our industries.  I realise that in some cases there is a genuine price and, perhaps, quality difference.  I also appreciate that, particularly for those on low incomes, this is a very important consideration.  I do not deny the right of such families to get the best possible value and return from their weekly pay packet.  We cannot expect, and I am sure the Irish Goods Council do not expect, people to purchase goods which are substandard or which are not comparable in value with imported products.  We are, however, entitled to expect, all things being equal, particularly at this difficult time, that our shops and our supermarkets should give prominence to Irish made goods of quality and value.</P>
    <P>I am pleased to note that there has been a positive response from many of our stores to the recent request from the Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism to promote Irish goods and to the efforts also of the Irish Goods Council.  One of the great problems in the past is that this effort has not been sustained. It is here that the customer can exert his influence, by continuing to ask for the home produced product.  Another important issue is the influence of multinational combines on the Irish market.  We all know that the small shopkeeper is under considerable pressure, and I regret very much the disappearance of the traditional family grocer.  They provided a personal service and, at times, a social service.</P>
    <P>In the economic environment in which they now operate, many of them are forced to sell the imported product if it is <Col N="521" /> more attractively priced.  Multinational syndicates have a serious obligation to our country in ensuring that they do not use their vast resources to undermine this important aspect of our economy.  I have strong reservations about the long-term effect and benefit of such multinationals on our commercial life.</P>
    <P>We are all genuinely interested in economic development.  Our programmes succeed or fail for various reasons.  Many of our policies are difficult to implement. Could it be that what we are discussing here is too simple a solution to the problem?  It does not, for instance, require massive borrowing, there is no element of compulsion about it, its success is completely dependent on the voluntary decision of each and every one of us.  If so, it reflects lack of concern on our part for our future.  If we are lucky to be in secure employment it reflects a degree of selfishness and a lack of concern for those who are less fortunate.  These may be strong words, they may be provocative words, but strong words are needed at this time to stir the public conscience.</P>
    <P>Every factory that closes, every man and woman who loses a job, every school leaver who fails to get work, will cost the Exchequer and the individual many thousands of pounds.  We are all familiar with the increasing costs of financing government policies.  We complain about the growing volume of taxation necessary for this purpose and, yet by our own actions, we seriously undermine one very important aspect of economic development. The so-called imaginary savings of cheaper imported goods is outweighed by the increase in taxation which is necessary to meet that situation.</P>
    <P>The retail sector is a very crucial link between industry and the consumer, and the Irish Goods Council have been correct in aiming their programme to influence the retail sector into thinking positively about promoting and selling Irish made products.  They must be made to realise that a depressed manufacturing sector means a reduction in consumer expenditure and a loss of retailing profits and, therefore, what may seem to them to be a short-term gain can, in the long <Col N="522" /> term be a substantial loss.  The success of this campaign is an educational process. Young people who, in the long term, will be the real beneficiaries have a very important role to play.  The long-term necessity of supporting Irish products should be promulgated through our schools, and I would like to see a situation where our teachers, who have been to the forefront in community leadership down through the years, taking on this important national role of trying to encourage and promote in the schools the importance of purchasing and supporting Irish industry.  The influence of our young people in shaping our destiny and our future is very important and they have a very significant contribution to make.</P>
    <P>We must ensure that our teachers and our students alike understand the economic necessity to support the &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo; campaign.  One area of organisation within this country which is largely untapped and which has a very important role to play is the trade union movement. I was very pleased during the week to read their official magazine <i>Liberty</i> and to find that the editorial comment called on trade unionists all over the country to recognise the serious situation prevailing and that they should, in the national and in their own interest, support the campaign.</P>
    <P>If the trade union movement put its full weight and its full support behind this campaign, they would achieve tremendous results.  I call for a very definite and positive commitment from all aspects of the trade union movement at this time for all Irish workers to support the actions and the campaigns of the Irish Goods Council.  It is in their own interests that they should do this.</P>
    <P>There are other areas where there is scope for further promotion of Irish made products.  Purchasing officers in State bodies are not always conscious, as they should be, of the need to buy Irish products.  There has been an improvement in this respect in recent years.  It is only fair to say that very many of them now recognise the importance of buying Irish. There is no excuse for any purchasing officer in any public body to buy an <Col N="523" /> imported product if a similar product of quality is available.</P>
    <P>There is room for further improvement and further expansion.  We all know and recognise the important contribution which the Industrial Development Authority has made in relation to the establishment of new industries.  In recent years they have been successful in their import substitution drive.  There is tremendous scope for the manufacturer of numerous small items which are at present being imported.  I hope the drive, which was so successful over the last couple of years, will continue and that we will eventually reach the stage where every component which is imported into this country, if it is possible, can be manufactured here.  It is laudable and desirable to do so.</P>
    <P>As a farmer, it annoys me considerably to see the very high food import bills.  We are an agricultural economy.  We have a soil and a climate which is capable of producing a very wide range of agricultural products.  We should be able to process all those products in our factories to the betterment of our agricultural industry and the workers of this country. Yet, for some strange reason, we find it necessary to continue to import massive amounts of foodstuffs from abroad which could and should be produced and processed in this country.  There is a lack of organisation, endeavour and seriousness. I hope that this is one aspect of economic activity which could be developed and improved in the future.</P>
    <P>I know we will get constructive comments and that the motion will be supported by Members from all sides of the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I second this motion and congratulate the people who tabled the motion, Senators Hyland and Mulcahy. Unfortunately, Senator Mulcahy is away and unable to be here today.  This is one of the most important items that we have discussed for some time.  It is particularly relevant between now and the few days before Christmas, when millions of pounds will be spent by Irish shoppers buying gifts for their children, that we should devote some time to urging the <Col N="524" /> community, every section of it, to spend more money on home produced products.  In so doing we are not urging people to buy goods of an inferior quality.  Neither are we urging them to buy goods that are more expensive, but thanks to the efforts of the IDA, through the assistance of the Irish Goods Council, Irish products are available and they are up to the standards of imported products and just as cheap.  Because of the efforts of Córas Tráchtála in promoting our goods abroad Irish products are now available at cheaper prices than goods that are imported.  I join Senator Hyland in congratulating the Irish Goods Council, their Chairman, Tom Hardiman and their Chief Executive, Vivian Murray, for the work they have done on our behalf in promoting the &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo; campaign. They have ensured that many thousands of Irish people remain in jobs and that many of our young people will have jobs that they might not otherwise have had.</P>
      <P>We are told that if 3 per cent of the consumer bill switched from imported goods with a similar switch in industrial standing to home produced goods, 10,000 jobs could be created in this country. Earlier this year the Taoiseach made a very special plea to all shoppers when he asked them to spend £1 more per week on home produced goods.  By so doing, they would be helping in the development of our economy and making sure that more jobs are available to all Irish people, particularly to yound people.  We are now witnessing the effects of a world recession.  We have had a 30,000 increase in the unemployment figures in the past year.  What better way for us to help control the unemployment figures than by going out and buying Irish goods that are available?  President Kennedy once said &ldquo;Ask not what your country can do for you but rather what you can do for your country&rdquo;.  The best possible thing that any Irish patriot could do would be to look for and purchase Irish goods.  If those goods are not easily available, there is nothing wrong in asking the shop assistant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like here to pay tribute to many of the big stores in the Dublin area who over the Christmas season have placed <Col N="525" /> an assistant on their information desk to advise customers of the range of Irish goods available and in what part of the shops they are to be found.  I had a case recently of going to purchase something and I had actually to ask were there any Irish goods available.  I was told there were and the assistants went back behind the counter and came back out with the Irish goods.  People in the retail business have a vital role to play in making sure that their staff are aware of what exactly the Irish goods are and of making sure they bring these to the attention of all shoppers.  It would be a useful exercise if more and more of our department stores engaged in seminars or information classes which I know the Irish Goods Council have arranged from time to time to make sure that all shop assistants are aware of the important function they have.  They are ambassadors for Irish trade, and when people go into a shop they will not be able to buy Irish goods unless they are available to them and unless they know they are there.</P>
    <P>This is an important motion from another point of view.  Very often in this country we suffered from an inferiority complex when it came to anything that was Irish.  We were told it was not available in the same quality or it was much more expensive.  As a nation we have a very big role to play in changing attitudes to our own home produced goods and in making sure that we support our own people and our own manufacturers.  The media have a role to play, in particular RTE.  There are very many morning programmes which have a tremendous impact, especially on the housewives of the country.  There is a programme every morning hosted by Gay Byrne and people like this have a role to play in urging shoppers, housewives in particular, to look for Irish goods and to buy them.  We must make sure that we do not have this apologetic inferior attitude to our own people and our own manufacturers.</P>
    <P>It is also important not only in the buying of goods of a material nature but goods like services that we promote our own industries.  Again I would refer to the role of Radio Telefís Éireann in the <Col N="526" /> playing and promotion of Irish music and Irish records.  I am not just talking about traditional Irish music; there is Irish popular music too and many of our artists are suffering the effects of the recession.  If it were not for the fact that they have other vehicles like dance halls and so on many of them would never be in existence. RTE could play a role by playing more Irish records, by promoting more Irish artists, as they did in Sweden when they promoted ABBA and they did in Canada when they promoted Anne Murray to be international world stars.  This is all part and parcel of the &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo; support campaign which we are all trying to encourage.</P>
    <P>I was delighted to read recently of an EEC survey publication which showed that the Irish people were improving their attitudes to their own goods and industries.  It showed that the percentage of people who felt that Irish goods were of a similar or superior quality to foreign goods had increased in the years 1975 to 1978 from 63 per cent to 71 per cent.  It is not a big increase but it is significant that at last our own people are going to have faith in our own industries.  It is extremely important that we encourage that.</P>
    <P>Senator Hyland referred extensively to the work of the Irish Goods Council, and they on behalf of the community and the Government are promoting a very extensive Buy Irish campaign.  At the moment they have under way the biggest promotion ever launched in this country.  The sum of £¼ million was spent in the preChristmas promotion to encourage people through advertisements, seminars, slides of the council's activities, to think Irish and to buy Irish.  It is very important in organising events of this nature, any sort of promotional work, that we involve school children, because people at a very early age now are spending quite an amount of money.  If they get into the pattern of thinking in terms of buying Irish from an early age when they first start to shop for very small things, they will continue along that path.  I would like to see many more schools, teachers and principals encouraging this type of activity and encouraging their children to <Col N="527" /> be involved in the many competitions and promotional efforts being made by the Irish Goods Council.</P>
    <P>The Irish Goods Council, too, help manufacturers and retailers.  They do not just make information available to consumers and urge them to buy.  Obviously they will not be in a position to buy the goods if the goods are not available.  I am delighted to see that 1,000 Irish companies are now registered under the Guaranteed Irish sign.  If a consumer buys something that carries the Guaranteed Irish sign, he is not just buying something that is made in Ireland but is also getting the guarantee that he will have after sales service.  This is very important.  If a person buys a faulty item or something that does not conform to the stated quality, he has some redress.  The Irish Goods Council, through their Guaranteed Irish campaign, have guaranteed that if the consumer does not get satisfaction when he brings faulty goods back to the retailer they will take up the case on his behalf. It is a very important fact that must get home to people, that they have after sales service and that they are being guaranteed that the goods will be of a certain quality.  Of course the recent passing of the Sale of Goods Act will also help here in giving consumers more power when it comes to purchasing items.</P>
    <P>Senator Hyland also referred to the role of the semi-State bodies in the promotion of the Buy Irish campaign.  It is essential that they too play their full part and also all the Government Departments.  I recently travelled on a CIE train and I was horrified to see that the little carton of jam they serve was a British product.  I know it is available here because it is made in Drumshanbo, County Leitrim.  That is a shame.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>The EEC is the cause of that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDeBrun" hpid="Acting Chairman (Séamus de Brún) Acting Chairman (Séamus de Brún)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Séamus de Brún)</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Harney to continue, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but CIE could purchase Irish-produced jam.  I would like to join with Senator Hyland in urging all the <Col N="528" /> people involved in the purchasing sections of all our semi-State bodies and all our Government Departments to make sure wherever possible that if the goods are available, made in Ireland, they be purchased and made available to the Irish people.</P>
      <P>Our marketing system in Ireland, particularly in our big shops and in the retail industry generally, has not always been up to the standards that one would like. Very often, as Senator Hyland said, you go into a shop and you just cannot see the Irish goods because they are not clearly on display.  Very recently there was a promotion by many of the big department stores where they had an all Irish section or an all Irish week.  It is important they they would have the Irish goods to the forefront and that they would be clearly identified as having been made in Ireland.  If Irish people can see their own home made goods they will be prepared to buy them once they are sure that the goods are of the same quality&mdash;as in most cases they already are&mdash;as the imported goods.  In many cases they are of a far higher standard.  Many Irish fashion designers and fashion manufacturers have won world prizes in recent years, and I would like to see more women when they go out to buy fashion thinking in terms of buying Irish coats or Irish dresses because they are available and they are of a very high quality.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The future of our country depends in a very real way on how we respond to the efforts of the Government through the Irish Goods Council in their current promotional campaign.  We are going through a recession.  We are going through a very difficult time for employment, and not only will more jobs he created as a result of our buying more Irish goods but the current jobs which are under threat&mdash;there are many Irish firms now on a three-day week&mdash;will be secured and they will be back to a full working week if all of us play our part by doing as the Taoiseach said&mdash;spending £1 more per week, and that is not a lot, on Irish goods.  If we do this we will, in a very real way, help our community and our economy and we will make sure that our young people have some future in <Col N="529" /> Ireland with some chance of employment.  We will be the patriots of the future, because patriotism now does not involve dying or anything like that.  All it involves is supporting everything Irish and promoting, in our own way, through the various clubs and organisations we belong to, Irish goods and Irish manufacturers.</P>
    <P>All of us involved in public life have a role to play at whatever meetings we attend of our own political parties or of other organisations in the next two weeks in urging people, as they go out to shop in the tremendous bonanza that takes place before Christmas, to buy more Irish goods.</P>
    <P>I would like to second this motion and in so doing pay tribute to the Government and the Irish Goods Council for the tremendous work they have done.  I ask them to continue urging the people, in particular the shoppers, our young people through the schools, our ladies through various ladies clubs and the ICA and all the various powerful organisations in the country, to play their role not only in the next two weeks but throughout the coming years, and to make sure that everything Irish is supported and that we play our part in the development of the Irish economy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondGoverney" hpid="Mr. Governey Mr. Governey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Governey</NameTxt>
      <P>I take this opportunity of welcoming the Minister of State on his first appearance in this House in his new role and I wish him well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am very pleased to have the opportunity to add my few words in support of this motion tabled by Senator Hyland and Senator Mulcahy.  I, too, should like to congratulate and pay tribute to the members of the Irish Goods Council for their terrific involvement, their dedication and the work they are doing in promoting the sale of guaranteed Irish goods.  It is especially important at this time of the year when the country is on a shopping spree.  It is a particularly good time when we, as public representatives, should voice our opinions and encourage the public to support Irish produce and guaranteed Irish goods.  I should like to join in the appeal to all section of the <Col N="530" /> community to play their part, not alone during the coming few weeks, but in the future to see that they ask for and get Irish goods when they go shopping. Under the Guaranteed Irish sign or label one is assured of quality and value.</P>
    <P>At the present time, this appeal rings a special chord for me because we are all fully aware in this House of the present recession in which we find ourselves.  We know of the unemployment figures published yesterday of 115,000.  I am convinced that we must spell out that these figures can be reduced if everybody plays his part in supporting Irish goods and Irish industry.  We have the workers, the expertise and the goods; that only leaves us to get the purchasers for these goods. It is here that the Irish Goods Council are certainly playing an excellent role. We must make this appeal on the lines that by supporting our Irish industries we are protecting jobs.  Too often today we see businesses in difficulties which could be helped by the support of the Irish public and Irish shoppers to keep people in employment.  With many businesses and firms in what I could only describe as serious difficulties, it was never more necessary that we should support and purchase the products of these Irish firms.</P>
    <P>No matter what we say here or no matter how industry and the Irish Goods Council play their part, it can be all to no avail unless we get the message across to the public in general what they are protecting when they insist on getting Irish goods.  I am happy to say that I am one who always insists on Irish gods if I go shopping.  Generally in the retail trade now we find that Irish goods are produced more freely than perhaps 15 or 20 years ago.  This is all to the betterment of the economy, the betterment of our workers and of the country in general.</P>
    <P>One of the previous speakers mentioned the question of displaying goods of Irish manufacture.  In the shops at the moment, while we would like to see more, there is a fair display of Irish products.  If there are some still who are inclined to leave our Irish products in the back end of the shelf or in the dark corner of the shop, they should bring them forwar and let them be seen.  We can stand <Col N="531" /> over anything that is produced in this country, especially when it has a guaranteed Irish sign on it.</P>
    <P>Earlier this evening I was reading through the Irish Goods Council News No. 3 and regarding the participation of the Irish Goods Council at the winter fair in the RDS I quote the following:</P>
    <P>Commenting on the Irish Goods Council's decision to back the food exhibition, Ms. O'Sullivan pointed out that there is tremendous concern about our food import bill of which over £100 million constitutes competing imports.</P>
    <P>That is a frightening figure to me and deals purely with food imports.  Why that alarming figure should be there is beyond my imagination.  I know that it is correct and we have increasing food imports. Increasing quantities of vegetables are being imported into the country; carrots are being imported from Italy and France in the early season and in the main season we have onions, cauliflowers and carrots from places such as the United Kingdom. Apart from our home market, with our natural advantages for vegetable production, we should be expanding in the fresh vegetable export business.  There is a considerable opportunity in this type of business for this country.</P>
    <P>In my own town of Carlow, the board of the Irish Sugar Company decided on a closure of Erin Foods, their processing company.  The reason I cannot fully understand, when we think of the import bill this country is facing I am convinced that there is considerably opportunity, even at this late stage; for Erin Foods in a combined fresh and processed vegetable enterprise.  An immediate and comprehensive examination of this potential is required without delay because while we are promoting Irish goods the closure of this firm is to take place next June.</P>
    <P>If there are no contracts for vegetables for the coming spring.  it might be very hard to get the people who have been so loyal over the years in growing vegetables for that firm to come back again after a lapse of a year.  In that respect I have a certain concern, and I have spoken to the Minister for the Department of Agriculture <Col N="532" />&mdash; I know it is not the direct responsibility of the Department of Industry and Commerce &mdash; and I have left some questions with him which he said he would have answered for me.  The <i>Irish Independent</i> on 10 December has a headline &ldquo;Buy Irish for £11 million Extra&rdquo;.  It is a frightening heading when you read it at first, but in fairness I could not stand here tonight and ask people to buy Irish if I were to be critical of the step that was taken in that case.  I do not understand, and I would not be an expert of course, why there is such a big difference between the price of a ship produced here and one imported.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would remind the Senator that his time has just expired.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondGoverney" hpid="Mr. Governey Mr. Governey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Governey</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government are taking the decision to subsidise the difference in the price.  In the interest of Irish industry and promoting the Buy Irish campaign I would suggest that in the case of Erin Foods the Government should decide to subsidise that industry, if necessary, to keep it going for another 12 months and see what comes out then of the investigations I have suggested.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am happy wholeheartedly to support this motion and I will always be glad to support motions of this kind.  That is why I made such a plea for the interests of native filmmakers earlier in the day.  It seems to me that it all hangs together, as Senator Harney suggested, and that the &ldquo;support Irish&rdquo; motif runs across the whole field of business and culture.  In a sense this is a non-contentious motion.  It is rather like being against sin in the days when sin was sin.</P>
      <P>I note that this is the second time Seanad Éireann has addressed itself to this topic in the current session.  On 26 April 1978 we had a similar motion brought by the same team that brought you tonight's motion, except that on that occasion Senator Mulcahy proposed the motion.  Senator Harney was a very able understudy indeed, and I must apologise to her for unthinkingly ruminating out loud when she mentioned the presence of foreign preserves in CIE.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="533" /> We had that debate and I think it is unusual that we should be having virtually the same debate two years afterwards.  Apart perhaps from Nothern Ireland and thecustomary debates on EEC reports I do not think we return to the same topic after such a brief interval.  It underlines its importance but it also raises obvious questions.  Why should it be necessary for us to debate this again and say the same things?  Why should it be necessary to spend in the present phase of the campaign £250,000 on a promotional campaign to buy guaranteed Irish goods?  It certainly raises all kinds of questions as to why people are not buying Irish.  Has any survey been made on this topic?  It is now customary to undertake surveys at the drop of a hat on all kinds of topics.  Perhaps Senator Hyland or Senator Harney could inform me whether the Irish Goods Council or a similar body are acting in the dark or are they aware of popular attitudes on this matter?  Certainly there is something very wrong, given our history, national aspirations and given the assumption that political independence would mean economic prosperity.  It is quite extraordinary that people apparently will not buy Irish in sufficient numbers to make an economic difference.</P>
    <P>The Fianna Fáil pre-election manifesto made a definite statement that if we could switch three pence in the pound of spending to Irish products in three years it would yield 10,000 extra jobs.  I never understood then, nor do I understand now, how this figure was arrived at.  However, I accepted the general principle that buying Irish would reduce unemployment somewhat.  My point is that it is very curious that for some reason people simply cannot be led, induced, bribed or threatened to buy Irish or to buy it in a sufficiently important manner.  It may be our history.  Our history would have left a residue of servility and of the slave complex as well; people even in 1980 will tell you, or perhaps will only half tell you because they are half ashamed, that &ldquo;You cannot really trust the Irish product.&rdquo; After all the promotional campaign there is still a popular resistance which should <Col N="534" /> be scientifically investigated.</P>
    <P>I make no secret about repeating some of the ideas I expressed here on the last occasion.  I want to point out also that the notion of supporting Irish manufactured products is, of course, one that did not happen today or yesterday.  It has a long ancestry and we might call it by the shorthand of economic nationalism or patriotism.  It is a long time since in the early 18th Century Swift wrote his proposal for the universal use of Irish manufactures. What is interesting about that is that Swift's plea &mdash; although he would not have meant by Irish what we understand by Irish &mdash; fell on deaf ears.  It would seem that a plea like that made in isolation has little effect.</P>
    <P>It is significant that only when there was the patriotic and the political fervour of the Volunteer movement at the end of the 1770's was there a great popular rush to buy Irish.  In that day and age the phrase was non-importation.  Grattan's Volunteers themselves made a great play of buying native cloth for their uniforms. At the beginning of this century the Gaelic League, in that whole ferment of nationalist fervour, had as one of its main planks the economic objective that people should buy Irish goods.  It should never be forgotten for the Gaelic League that it was one of the economic props on which the national movement was founded, as well as being a cultural base. <i>An Claidheamh Solais</i> pointed out in 1901 that jobs could be saved and emigration lessened by buying home-manufactured goods.  The economic message was accepted in an age of patriotic conviction and patriotic fervour, a fervour which endured in a way into the 1930s and 1940s when there was an intermittent but lengthy campaign to buy Irish goods. The slogan at that time was &ldquo;Buy Irish, be Irish.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>My question is, can we really ask people to buy Irish now because they are Irish?  Do we have anything like the same patriotic fervour that we had even in the thirties?  I suggest we do not, because in those days people believed, maybe naively, but there was some substance in their belief, that you could have control over the national economy, that you <Col N="535" /> could actually in your own State make effective laws to improve economic matters.  I do not think people believe that any more.  They have been listening for ten years or more to EEC propoganda which has half suggested to them &mdash; and I got it in this House from people over there who are no longer with us, happily &mdash; who more or less suggested when I put forward a patriotic line that I was &ldquo;old hat&rdquo; and not with it and that to be patriotic today was to be European.  That kind of propaganda has been having bad results in that people will say to themselves &ldquo;What is the difference between buying Italian shoes and buying Irish shoes if we are all in the same Community?&rdquo;  Even the word &ldquo;Community&rdquo; is pregnant with the idea of family.  Their attitude will be: &ldquo;Why should I buy the product of Ireland rather than that of Italy, whose people are our brothers, after all?&rdquo; I am putting this forward in all seriousness.  The EEC propaganda has diminished our commitment to buying Irish.  We have not the control over the economy anymore.  We either have multinationals who pull out when it no longer suits them to stay or we have a commission in Brussels issuing directives to us that a particular line is overproduced and, therefore, should be cut down on. In these circumstances people might well ask, what is the point of supporting Irish products if we are no longer sure how long they are going to be with us or if the control of the economy is no longer our own?</P>
    <P>Apart from that general point, it may well be objectively that a campaign like this is alien to the spirit, if not to the actual letter, of the European Economic Community.  I come back to the point I made when I was apologising to Senator Harney.  I, too, noticed the fact that our semi-State company, Córas Iompair Éireann, offers non-Irish jams and preserves.  My understanding is that under EEC regulations they may not withdraw these British preserves.  I do not know if that is correct but I would like the experts to make a comment on that.  I remember sitting in on a Dáil Question Time not so long after having that debate in April <Col N="536" /> 1978 and I remember a Minister answering rather ruefully along those lines to that very question of why Irish products were not being pushed by CIE.</P>
    <P>Having expressed these reservations, having wondered perhaps whether it is not rather too late to be pushing this campaign, nevertheless I support it.  I am glad also to pay tribute to the excellent work done by the Irish Goods Council. I note that in its most recent issue there is no reference whatsoever to membership of the Community.  You might ask why.  If you are talking about pushing Irish manufactured goods particularly, it seems like Hamlet without the Prince to ignore the fact that much of our unemployment, and much of the decline particularly of our industrial goods, has been due simply and clearly to EEC membership.</P>
    <P>Although I suspect that it is rather too late, and although I suspect that even if people took the campaign seriously it would be like a drop in the ocean, I am still glad to be able to support it.  Like Senator Governey, I also am always anxious to ask for the Irish product when I go shopping, I hope all Members are like that.  I hope that if there were an inspection of our personal apparel from top to toe we would not be discovered wearing Conte suits.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to add my voice to the voice of the other Senators in support of this particular motion.  I often think that the term itself &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo; is far too simple.  There is quite a lot more to it than has been expressed here.  I feel that what we do today may affect the product of tomorrow and that in a cost-conscious society the product of tomorrow emanates from action taken today. Earlier today, as chairman of the Fianna Fáil trade union group, I had the opportunity of visiting Bee Line, a textile factory in Ballyfermot, where they produce garments of a very high-class nature.  The workers are working under excellent conditions in an excellent factory, with superior technical know-how, with efficient management and efficient training.  All these factors go hand in hand with the production of items for the future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="537" /> I believe that if production units do not keep abreast of modern technical development and are concerned about just producing for a particular period or a particular season they are going to be lost in the markets of the future.  The Government will have to ensure that we keep abreast of developments in relation to the microchip and other forms of modern technology to meet the competition of the future.  It has been rightly pointed out that we are a member of the EEC and that business is more competitive now than it has been in the past.</P>
    <P>I want to support the motion fully. Many young people are employed in the factory I mentioned.  They are being trained and are guaranteed in some way job opportunities in the future because this concern has kept abreast of technological developments and are dealing with the question of future costs.  They have done the necessary surveys.  It is essential that factories carry out extensive surveys and studies if they are to compete successfully in markets.</P>
    <P>The whole matter of the &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo; campaign rests at the moment on the shoulders of the trade union movement. Their members are affected in many cases but they neglect to enforce their viewpoint on their own members.  They could in a very real way ensure that a greater emphasis is put on the &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo; campaign.  I do not think it is enough to print in one of their magazines an indication that they support the &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo; campaign.  I think something more imaginative and more forceful should come from the trade unions.  They should ensure that their own members are fully protected by the directives or by the support that they could give.  Indeed, housewives must realise, too, that their husbands' jobs are at stake, as is the future of their children.  The community as a whole must feel they have a collective rather than an individual part to play. What is required is a concentrated effort across the board rather than individual groups making pleas on particular occasions.  That stimulus must come from the trade union movement, on the point that the jobs of their members and of their <Col N="538" /> sons and daughters will be protected if all members of families purchase Irish goods.  It is far too simplistic just to say &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Mention has been made of the Italian shoes, French perfumes, Scotch whisky and Dutch cheese: all these are sometimes regarded as the &ldquo;in&rdquo; thing, but the quality is often inferior to our own.  Members of both Houses have a role to play in encouraging people to buy Irish.  I think our voice should be directed to the organisations that can best get to the ears of the workers concerned and so ensure that the voice comes across loud and clear.  I am disappointed that members of the Labour Party have not seen fit to add their voice to this very important motion. It may be an indication of their interest and that of the trade unions in the &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo; campaign.  I would have hoped on an important motion like this that every Member of this House would add his or her voice loud and clear to the &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo; campaign to ensure that jobs are protected.</P>
    <P>It is rather regrettable that we have sections of the Oireachtas who show no concern on this particular occasion in relation to this very real and pressing problem.  Without the representatives of the trade union movement it is going to be difficult for Members of this House to penetrate the trade union movement.  I am quite certain that the trade union movement will listen to their own leaders and their own elected representatives, but when they fail to respond here, then we see the great difficulties we are faced with in the Oireachtas and indeed in society in getting through to people.</P>
    <P>We can keep abreast only by updating ourselves on the matter of modern technology.  The Government have done much to ensure that the necessary aids are available.  Where industries are really concerned about continuity of production and about producing products in a cost-conscious society, they should be fully and effectively supported.</P>
    <P>I had an opportunity today, together with other Members of the Oireachtas, to visit a factory and we were pleased to find the great depth of research that had been done in relation to the market and <Col N="539" /> the product.  I should like to pay a compliment to the management of Beehive for the manner in which they are conditioning the workers to the technical developments and technical aids that are all so important for the future.  In addition the conditions under which they are working indicate their desire to ensure that the workers will be happy.  A happy worker will respond not only to the voice of Members of this House or members of the trade union movement but indeed to any patriotic suggestion that would ensure not alone the continuity of his own job but also that of his neighbour.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to congratulate the movers of this motion.  It is a very useful exercise.  I was not aware until I heard Senator Murphy say so that we debated this subject two years ago.  I would also like to pay a compliment to the Irish Goods Council.  That goes without saying because it is very important in all our interests that this campaign be successful.</P>
      <P>There are a few aspects of this that I would like to take up.  I would have to say that despite the best efforts of the Irish Goods Council, and I will assume that they would be the first to agree, their present campaign to date has not been as successful as they would like.  I am not talking about the financial input.  What I am talking about is the actual response in the purchase of Irish goods by Irish people.  It has been mentioned already here this evening that we are talking about a tremendous number of jobs lost because ordinary Irish folk will not buy Irish products.  Some 10,000 prople are currently on the dole because we do not care as an Irish society to support Irish goods.</P>
      <P>It is true to say that our country, in keeping with many other countries in Europe, is gripped by materialism.  As Senator Murphy said, the days of patriotism, in the way we would like to interpret it, are certainly gone.  Some of the so-called patriots who have the answer to all our problems would appear to overshoot the runway when it comes down to how best we can be Irishmen.  I will not labour the point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It must be said that the various types <Col N="540" /> of promotional work carried out by the Irish Goods Council have not been successful.  Perhaps we have come to the point where we have to provide more favourable incentives to purchase Irish goods.  There are a number of important points in the chain of the sale of a product that maybe the Irish Goods Council should take up.  We have arrived at a situation where very few people will do anything now other than when it suits them or when there is something out of it, and I mean financially.</P>
    <P>Perhaps the Irish Goods Council should consider paying people who are engaged in important areas in the chain of distribution from the manufacturer until the product meets the consumer. The time might now be ripe for it.  Let us consider the role of the shop assistant.  I am not talking about a direct subsidy because I quite understand that is not on at the moment, but perhaps that asaistant might be encouraged to realise it is in her own best interests to make sure that every customer who comes through the door is first shown the best of the Irish products. We will all have to be realistic and accept that if a customer says he or she will have nothing to do with an Irish product there is nothing that can be done, but that is not the case.  From my own experience I believe that a great percentage of people have a reasonably open mind about products.  Perhaps the Irish Goods Council could come up with a scheme on the basis that there would be some type of a prize, award or recognition for a shop to increase its sale of Irish goods and eventually there could be across the country people engaged in promoting the purchase of Irish goods.  I realise this will cost money but if we can put 10,000 extra people in jobs we are talking about millions of pounds.</P>
    <P>No longer do we have a patriotic attitude with regard to the &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo; campaign.  In provincial centres and small towns, perhaps, the local town development associations could organise a scheme similar to the Bord Fáilte Tidy Towns Competition, involving the traders of the town in a promotion to buy Irish.  The ordinary folk behind the counter and the shopowners must be <Col N="541" /> involved to that extent, where they firmly believe on one hand that they are getting something financially out of it and also that they are doing a good day's work for Ireland.  That special relationship that will be built up will be very important. One has to have doubts about television and radio advertising.  However all the polls will show that it is the only way to get an instant message across to a community.</P>
    <P>We are quite well aware that advertising comes into the homes of nearly everybody at one stage or another during a given night.  The multiplicity of the types of advertising has made people very hazy about the whole thing and a situation has almost arrived where many do not really believe what they see on the advertisements.  Any people involved in advertising can make a great case that this is the only way to advertise, and I will accept that.  However, its usefulness over the years is not increasing and a lull is coming, because it is one firm competing against another, with glossy, JR-type situations.  We saw fit to bring JR over for a Department of Agriculture advertisement.  If that is the answer to the problem, you would merely need to bring over the entire gang from Southfork and the Irish Goods Council would have no problem, but it is not that simple.</P>
    <P>As Senator Dowling said, the trade union movement obviously have a very big say in all this as, indeed, the farming co-operatives have.  I will not detain the House too long, but in the activity about which I know most, it is true to say that some of our bigger farming co-operatives are promoting items like Findus Foods on the same basis as, or even at times more so than Irish products.  When you consider that the Irish co-operative movement is the heartbeat of rural Ireland and has been over the years, somewhere or another there must be some reason for this particular type of promotion where equal shelf space and display are given to imported and Irish products. Let me be clear about this, any Irishman or woman should not buy an Irish product which is inferior, or is dearer.  We have problems in industry, and in agriculture <Col N="542" /> for that matter, from the point of view of quality control, but that is subject for another debate at another time.  I am quite certain that there is a tremendous number of Irish products that can take their place beside anything that comes into this country, but they are not getting a fair crack of the whip.</P>
    <P>I suggest that we are arriving at a very dangerous stage because of our European involvement.  Our big co-operatives in certain parts of the country at least, are beginning to be taken over now by multi-nationals and, indeed, we would want to be careful of the big supermarket chain stores as well.  It is a well known fact that big business can be a dramatic thing from a purchasing power point of view, and we will soon arrive at a situation where even a national Government has little control over the actual goings on in that particular state <i>vis-àvis</i> big business.</P>
    <P>I would certainly hope that our laws would always ensure that there is a fair chance for people in business in a smallish way.  We had some talk recently about supermarkets, how big they should be and what have you, and RGDATA are very concerned about this.  All those things are inter-related, but if the Irish Goods Council do nothing other than what they are doing at the moment, however impressive it might be &mdash; and it is impressive and, indeed, they are to be congratulated on the quality of their advertising, particularly of late &mdash; we shall not get anywhere.  It takes a long time to change attitudes, and unless there is something in it for the people we hope to influence, we will not get very far.</P>
    <P>I have a sneaking suspicion, but cannot prove it, that a tremendous number of items imported into this country are being sold to the retailers &mdash; and, in fact, to the wholesalers &mdash; at prices that would be regarded as of a dumping nature. There was a craze a few years ago when every woman in Ireland went wild about Italian shoes.  Now I understand that they have a fairly good name, but it is true to say that many of the shoes bought under an Italian label let their manufacturers down very badly.  We should have some monitoring system whereby we would <Col N="543" /> know that the products that came on the Irish market came at a realistic price. Wholesalers and retailers sometimes get a great rake-off on some of those products, and that would be one reason why they would go all out to ensure that these were sold.  If we are ever to counteract our problems with the Buy Irish campaign then there must be something in it for the people who count, those nearer the front line, the people who actually meet the consumers.  They are the people who are working on our behalf.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I remind the Seanad that there is only about a minute and a half before the Adjournment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GemmaHussey" hpid="Mrs. Hussey Mrs. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no way in which one can convey a message in a minute and a half unless with high-powered advertising on television, which is <Col N="544" /> extremely relevant to this debate because we are talking about consumer spending. The debate is timely, because we are talking about consumer spending as we are coming up to Christmas, as was mentioned earlier on.  We should remember that out of every £100 spent here on consumer goods £80 is spent by women, so we are talking about directing this campaign at the people who are actually there at the point of sale.  That is something that should be tackled by the Irish Goods Council and by this House if we are really serious in the wording of this motion, which is to support the efforts of the Irish Goods Council to encourage people to buy Irish goods.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.30 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 17 December 1980.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>