<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="20" Month="Feb" Year="1980" Vol="93" No="10" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 20 Feabhra 1980" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 20 February 1980" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1061">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1061" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 1 and 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MylesStaunton" hpid="Mr. Staunton Mr. Staunton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staunton</NameTxt>
      <P>When we last met a number of Senators from this side of the House, from my party, from the Labour Party and some university Senators, sought a debate urgently on No. 17 regarding the Government's foreign policy in the light of recent events in Iran and Afghanistan and I had thought from the tone of the leader of the House on that occasion that he was receptive to the view that a debate should take place and should take place fairly urgently.  I would like to ask what the position is about the proposal to have a debate on that motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to support what Senator Staunton has said. The Leader of the House used the phrase &ldquo;the near future&rdquo; on that occasion, so, perhaps, he would like to define that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I did discuss that matter with the Minister for Foreign Affairs and the position is that either today or some day this week the EEC Committee of Foreign Ministers will discuss that subject and decide what attitude they will adopt in regard to Afghanistan.  He said he was quite prepared to come in and to take part in a debate on that motion <Col N="1062" /> but not until the EEC have adopted a view about it.  That will be adopted, I imagine, this week and I think he will be quite willing to come in within the next week or two.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MylesStaunton" hpid="Mr. Staunton Mr. Staunton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staunton</NameTxt>
      <P>That seems reasonable if we have an assurance that that debate will take place next week, if at all possible, if the Minister is in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Soon, anyhow.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Sale of Goods and Supply of Services" RHead="Bill, 1978: Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Sale of Goods and Supply of Services Bill, 1978: Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ValentineJago" hpid="Mr. Jago Mr. Jago">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jago</NameTxt>
      <P>I also would like to welcome this Bill in that it updates legislation that has fallen behind in our ever-changing society.  It brings into the field the area of services and hire-purchase: it deals with unsolicited sales and directory entries.  But also there is one very important area and that is the exclusion clauses.  However, in the absence of legislation in this field, to a certain extent the public over the years have taken remedies into their own hands. How many times have we been given, if we are buying a car or a washing machine, a form to sign and when it is returned we will be given a guarantee? How many of us have completely ignored signing the forms but still we have had the warranty on the goods that we bought?  Also, the public have found that in many of these cases publicity has been the answer because the one thing a producer or a retailer-distributor fears is adverse publicity and, in fact, certain people have found the publicity on the &ldquo;Gay Byrne Hour&rdquo; has been very effective in the absence of legislation.  I welcome the fact that we will now have legislation governing these exclusion clauses.  There is one fear that I have, and we can keep this in mind on Committee Stage, and that is that if the penalties are made too severe in certain <Col N="1063" /> cases this could react on the consumer in that the producer or the distributor may, finding the penalties severe, stop supply or it could mean increased cost for the goods in covering himself in such cases.</P>
      <P>There is one section that I would particularly like to refer to&mdash;it has been referred to already by some Senators&mdash;and that is section 13, I feel that the motor traders have acted very responsibly in their approach to this in that they have sent their views to the Members of the Oireachtas.  Latterly, we have had a habit of people making protests and doing things the wrong way and because I received, as well as other Senators, the views of the motor traders I have looked into this section far more deeply than probably I would have otherwise.  I have already had correspondence with the former Minister, that is the Minister for the Gaeltacht at present, and also with the Minister of State who is here today, on this subject.  The point I would like to make and which I have made already is that in a Bill which is for consumer protection subsection (2) appears to be sufficient in that you have already implied that a vehicle being sold is being sold in a safe condition.  I do not like the aspect of bringing the criminal element into civil legislation.  Among other things it could develop and at present if a person puts in a car for general service to a reputable garage he gets a certificate back as to what has been examined and what has been dealt with, in other words a certificate to say that these points are now right.  I would hate to think that at any future date there would be a fear that we would not be able to say that we were getting a genuine report without the costs going up on the garage to give that report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If, also, safety on the road is the aim in this then, to a certain extent, it is not doing the job 100 per cent because only those cars sold by the dealers will get a certificate and the cars sold privately will not get a certificate.  That is not making any advance towards safety in a certain number of the cars sold.  If safety is the aim I feel it should be under different <Col N="1064" /> legislation&mdash;road traffic legislation which will cover all cars&mdash;because today driving on the road shows that the more dangerous aspects are things like the focussing of lights which if one is driving at night can be, to say the least of it, pretty bad and dangerous.</P>
    <P>It could also be introduced in relation to the insurance of cars, that cars over a certain age would have to have a certificate. I fear that there could be a case of discrimination in this.  In other words, we have one section of the community selling who have to supply a certificate and another section selling who have not and therefore there is discrimination.  In view of certain proceedings in some of our courts one could not tell the result of an action brought under such a heading. Recently, we had the case of the working wife.  Equally a case of discrimination could have been brought by the working husband because he did not get a working allowance so you could not tell what cases could be put and nobody could forecast the result.</P>
    <P>On this obligatory certificate, if the time comes when I want to trade in my car or buy a new car I will probably find that I will have a better chance of selling it now privately because the dealer would probably protect himself against the cost of a certificate and therefore he would give me less.  That means on this safety procedure you are putting more cards on to the side that will not have certificates than on the side that has.  The Minister should have another look at this section and possibly amend some of it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill in general terms because it will increase the protection of the consumer in Ireland. Before looking at what it will do and before criticising some aspects of it I would like to preface my remarks by the general comment which was echoed by other Senators who spoke, that it is a pity that Senators approach a Bill of this sort by a general debate on the floor of the House on the principles of it.  If this was a draft directive on the sale of goods and supply of services, the way in which the Oireachtas would examine it is infinitely <Col N="1065" /> better and preferable and more authoritative than the kind of debate we can have here this afternoon and the kind of debate that took place recently in the other House, because we would sit in Committee and have the benefit not only of the views of the Government through the kind of speech which the Minister made in introducing the Bill but also we would have an opportunity for both written and oral representations from the various interests&mdash;from the consumer interests and from the sectors which are particularly affected.</P>
      <P>As it happened Senators have received the assistance of lobbying from some of these sectors&mdash;in my view a perfectly legitimate and indeed helpful exercise of letting Senators know what the views and concerns of particular sectors are&mdash;but that is very <i>ad hoc</i> and random. I have received representations from the motor industry, as I know other Senators have, from the finance houses and from one or two lawyers who wanted to draw certain parts of it to my attention as a fellow lawyer but I have not had the rounded, balanced covering of interests that I would have liked.  I would get that perhaps by spending a lot of time going and seeking the views of the Consumers Association and the various other bodies and groups affected.  This is a reproach to the way in which we approach a Bill of this sort because it is a technical Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is an extremely important Bill and a very far reaching Bill.  I do not believe, even though we may spend some time in examining it, that we are sufficiently in a position to give it the consideration which it warrants.  I am disappointed that the representations that were made to have a Select Committee of this House appointed to consider the Bill were not acceptable or did not meet with any support and enthusiasm from the Government side.  It is regrettable because it is going to reveal the difficulties under which Senators must operate in considering the terms of the Bill.  Reference has already been made to the debate in the other House and it reveals strikingly the difficulty of Dáil <Col N="1066" /> Deputies trying to examine a Bill of this sort without an adequate opportunity to be briefed on the implications it has for various sectors and on the overall considerations of the Bill.</P>
    <P>Having made those remarks about the deficiencies of this House in considering the Bill&mdash;which is part of my longstanding campaign for reform of the Oireachtas&mdash;I want to make it very clear that I extend a welcome to what I regard as a long overdue Bill.  I also appreciate the fact that the Minister in introducing it made it clear that it is a Bill that has been in process for some time and the principle of which was agreed by the previous Government.  When we look at the kind of representations that are being made about the effects that the Bill could have on certain sectors, it is worth reminding ourselves that it is substantially amending an Act dating from 1893, The Sale of Goods Act, 1893, and that virtually since that Act was enacted it has been possible to avoid some of the clear protections that that Act was intended to afford to consumers.  Because consumers are individuals, because as a group they are not strongly represented&mdash;and they are not sufficiently strongly represented still in this country&mdash;this imbalance in the 1893 Act, this unintended development by exclusionary clauses which removed the protections of the 1893 Act has been allowed to continue right up until 1980.  That is worth bearing in mind, that the interests of consumers have not been protected because they did not have an effective voice.  We have been slow to follow the kind of developments that have taken place in other countries in relation to control over misrepresentations and the kind of prohibition of exclusionary clauses which this Bill will now bring into Irish law.  It is worth reflecting on the lack of protection that there has been for the consumer under the existing law and how slow we have been to take account of that.</P>
    <P>While dealing with this aspect of it, I would like to say that I do not believe that this Bill is by a long shot the end of the road in the protection of the consumer. <Col N="1067" /> It is necessary to give the consumer access to a reasonable and easy forum to resolve disputes.  In other words, we need the small clains court so that a consumer has a ready place to go to complain or to pursue some of the legal rights which he will now have under this legislation.  One of the great deterrents to the ordinary person at the moment is the comparative inaccessibility of our ordinary courts.  This will not be corrected to any great extent by the civil legal aid scheme which the Government have committed themselves to introducing, because it looks as though the kind of claim which will be the most common will be excluded from that scheme.  Perhaps the Minister might comment on that but it seems to me that the kind of actions most likely to arise would not be included in the Civil Legal Aid Scheme, actions for small debts, when the consumer wanted to pursue a remedy under this Bill.  When we are improving the law and when we are improving the protection extended to consumers we have to follow it through and have the kind of small claims court procedure which operates in many other countries and is considered an essential part of the protection of the consumer. In principle I welcome this Bill, but I hope that it is not going to be the last word on the protection of the consumer. I hope it will be followed up by ensuring access to a small claims court when it is necessary to avail of the improved protection and remedies open to the consumer.</P>
    <P>A great deal more should be done to ensure that adequate information is made available to the consumer.  Here I appreciate that we have had the Consumer Information Act and that we have a Director of Consumer Affairs.  I would hope that this will mean over the next few years that there will be a greater attempt made to ensure that the ordinary person is made more aware of what to look for, that school children are made more aware of what to look for when they become adults, in credit schemes and hire purchase schemes, what their <Col N="1068" /> rights are and how they can enforce them.  This is an area, where despite the efforts on a voluntary basis of the Consumers Association, they have not had the resources.  We are not a consumer-conscious nation and that, I believe, contributes a little bit to the very high prices and inflationary spiral that we are in.  It is much easier to raise prices when you have not got an alert, conscious and resourceful public.  Apart from improving the legal protection we also need, very dramatically, to increase the awareness by the consumer of his and her rights; to begin with the very young consumer, to begin with the child in school, the young adult, to ensure that they have the knowledge of their rights and they do not become inadvertent victims who might possibly have a remedy but the enforcement of that remedy is so remote from them that they just have to cut their losses and forget about it, even if technically through this Bill they would in fact have a remedy.</P>
    <P>Having affirmed very strongly my support for the idea of getting away from the <i>laissez faire</i> approach of the 1893 Sale of Goods Act, with its potential for exclusionary clauses which denies the consumer many of the protections intended by that Act, and my support for the approach in this Bill of greatly improving that protection and of ruling out exclusionary clauses, I now have to say that, as a lawyer, there are a number of aspects of this Bill which would worry me and on which I would like to have an opportunity for a detailed Committee Stage debate so that we can be very clear on what the terms of the Bill mean and so that, where necessary, it will be possible to introduce amendments.</P>
    <P>A number of the points that I would like to make in this context have been made by other Senators on both sides of the House, so, perhaps, I would indicate them at this stage.  They are very substantially Committee points: they are ones on which we will have to have a very full discussion on Committee Stage. The first relates to the question of definition of the consumer.  There is reference in section 3 to dealing as a consumer and <Col N="1069" /> there are a number of questions arising out of that, even questions arising out of the approach of not defining consumer&mdash;as has been done in the European Community directive and in the legislation of other countries.  I would very much welcome some indication in the Minister's reply as to why he has chosen in this Bill not to have a precise definition of consumer but to have the provisions of section 3, which we will examine on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>I would also very much like to know, because it is a most important point in trying to understand this Bill, why it has excluded leasing.  There are very substantial, very far reaching provisions of liability of finance houses in hire purchase agreements, but none of these legal provisions extends, if I understand the Bill, to leasing arrangements.</P>
    <P>It is a clear fact of life that in business and in the professions a great deal of plant or equipment or office furniture, filing cabinets&mdash;anything&mdash;is being leased at the moment rather than being bought outright or bought under hire purchase arrangements.  It seems to me that this Bill as it stands could have a very distorting effect.  We are dealing with finance houses who presumably have a great capacity to adapt and if we impose on finance houses through hire purchase arrangements a co-liability with the seller for the condition of the goods and we give an option to the consumer either to sue the seller or the finance house which extended the credit to the consumer, then if the finance houses can provide a facility where they do not risk the same kind of liability, in other words, if they can say from now on we are not going to enter into hire purchase agreements but we will enter into leasing arrangements; surely that is the way in which they would move and they would not have the same kind of liability.  It is not just a question of why did the Minister appear in this Bill not to extend the same arrangements to leasing but would this not have a completely distorting effect?  It could in fact have a very harmful effect if my assessment is correct, because it could mean that it <Col N="1070" /> would be much harder for the consumer to get hire purchase facilities, to get credit facilities, and this could seriously hurt a consumer who would not have the cash or the capital and who needs these hire purchase facilities.  So, in seeking to protect the consumer and in seeking to extend a potential liability I think that we have to be very careful either not to close off a facility that is there at the moment or have the result of a major switch from hire purchase to leasing arrangements which would escape some of the proposed safeguards of the Bill.</P>
    <P>Another section which will obviously have to be dealt with in detail on Committee Stage is section 13 relating to the car industry.  I think there has been a very substantial reference to this by other Senators in their contributions and I certainly feel that the introduction of a certificate accompanied by criminal penalties is a very different kind of provision from the other measures in this Bill. I am very much in favour of the implied condition in section 13, I think that this in itself is very much part of what the Bill intends to do; I think it should extend to the motor industry and I think that it would have favourable consequences if it did, but I do not think that the criminal certificate has any real significance.  I am persuaded by the representations which have been made by the motor industry that it would be much better to introduce in a completely different context the provisions for compulsory vehicle testing and, if necessary, to accompany that by criminal penalties under the criminal law, but the approach here seems to me possibly to postpone that kind of compulsory vehicle testing and not to achieve its objective.</P>
    <P>I have also been very impressed on this point, not so much by the formal representations made, and referred to by other Senators, by the motor industry, but by small traders both in my constituency and elsewhere in Dublin, very small men who are doing the business which they have been doing all their lives who see a very real danger.  They see the very real danger that operators will get around the provisions of section 13 by <Col N="1071" /> advertising in the evening papers that they have a car for sale, not as motor traders, but in a so-called private capacity and avoiding all the safeguards. There will be the rogue dealers, as the small traders would call them, operating in a situation which is really created by the terms of section 13.  This is something which can be discussed in great detail on the wording of section 13 on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>It is a matter of real importance how we strike the balance in giving the consumer more protection than the present law does, but is not creating such a concern for motor traders in their business than it either gives a field day to the existing rogue dealers or encourages others to avoid the terms of the section and to enter into private relationships for resale of secondhand cars, where there is no protection for the consumer and where none of these provisions of the section apply.  I endorse what a number of other Senators have said on this point.  I welcome the fact that the Minister in introducing the Bill appeared to be prepared to give consideration to the representations made by the motor industry and to the views of Senators on this point.  This is a section which ought to be amended on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>Another section which certainly needs to be clarified and which if left as it is at the moment could have a distorting effect is section 14, creating for finance houses the same liability as that of the seller of goods and giving, apparently, the consumer who has bought on credit the option either of bringing proceedings against the seller or against the finance house.  There seem to be one or two possible difficulties about that section. First, it appears to place the consumer who finances the purchase of goods on credit in a much better position than the consumer who pays cash; this is because obviously a finance house would presumably be a good mark in almost all circumstances.  I do not know whether we want to deter purchases on the basis of cash in favour of almost all purchases being on the basis of credit, because you <Col N="1072" /> have the additional advantage there of the possibility of bringing an action against the finance house, in the circumstances. Also, in trying to achieve something which I would very much support&mdash;the protection of the consumer&mdash;there is a possible danger that if there is no limit to the liability of a finance house in those circumstances, either, as I said earlier, finance houses would be very reluctant to give hire purchase facilities and will move substantially towards leasing to avoid the provisions of the Bill, or, if they do give hire-purchase facilities, these may be on very onerous terms, in order that the finance house can secure itself against any actions that may be taken.</P>
    <P>For example, as I read section 14 it is hard to understand the scope of the liability.  If the goods in question cost a substantial amount of money and were sold in a defective condition, about which the finance house was ignorant not having examined the goods, but just providing the facility, if the financing was for only a small part of the transaction, is the finance house fully liable, or liable to the extent of the amount advanced? If fully liable&mdash;which seems to be the way section 14 reads&mdash;again, what effect would this have on hire purchase transactions?  Perhaps the Minister would give some indication as to whether the provisions of section 14 if unaltered would, in the Minister's estimation, have an effect on access to hire purchase and on hire purchase rates. Does he anticipate that this would have an effect on hire purchase rates themselves? This is something which could be taken up on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>Another point, which may be dealt with by way of an amendment on Committee Stage, is the fact that although this Bill will make a very significant change in the area of commercial transactions and although there must be a very significant number of contracts and documents based on the existing law under which people are operating at the moment, there is not, in this Bill, any provision that it would come into effect, for example, on 1 June or 1 May, nor is <Col N="1073" /> there any provision&mdash;which would be an alternative way of doing it&mdash;for the Minister, by order, to say when the Bill would come into effect.  This could be very disruptive of existing commercial transactions and relationships and is something which, again, could potentially cause unnecessary litigation, if I could put it that way.  It is right, after a very long delay&mdash;and I have already criticised the delay&mdash;to protect the consumer and to secure more fully the protection of the consumer.  It would, however, be more orderly and, indeed, less likely to give rise to either vexatious litigation or to problems in present commercial transactions, if there were to be some period after the passing of this Bill&mdash;not necessarily a long period, but some reasonable period&mdash;in order that those who are engaged, for example, either in providing hire purchase or credit facilities, or those involved in standard form contracts under existing law and which therefore, have exclusionary clauses, could bring their contracts into line with the new legislation.</P>
    <P>I am aware, and glad, that this Bill has received a great deal of public comment. It is not that people can say that they are unaware of its existence.  Yet, as many Senators have said, it is a very technical Bill.  As far as lawyers are concerned, it makes a very dramatic difference in the law&mdash;in the law of contract; in the law relating to conditions and warranties; in the prohibition of exclusionary clauses, where these are standard things in standard form contracts.  It would be desirable to have some gap between the passing of this Bill and its coming into operation, to ensure that the message is got home all right and that future commercial transactions reflect the law as it will be and to ensure that there is not, in the interim, a disruption of commercial transactions and some vexatious litigation which would be better avoided in the interests of everybody except the lawyers briefed in the matter.  I have not stooped to the stage, as yet, of saying that all litigation is good litigation.</P>
    <P>Those are my remarks on this Bill on Second Stage, As Senator FitzGerald, I <Col N="1074" /> think, and various other Senators have said, it is basically and, very importantly, a Committee Stage Bill and therefore I ask that we be given sufficient time to discuss it in this House.  It is clear from contributions made by other Senators that we appreciate the significant changes which this Bill will bring about and that we are concerned to ensure that when it passes through this House it will have satisfied the various queries and will be the best possible Bill for the protection of the consumer.  I ask that we be given an opportunity in this House to have the kind of Committee Stage which I believe&mdash;and which I know some other Senators believe&mdash;will be necessary in order to carry out that task.  I certainly welcome, at long last, a greater legal protection of the consumer.</P>
    <P>This Bill tries to do, in one measure, what other countries, for example, the United Kingdom&mdash;in a similar situation have done in several different Bills.  In some instances we go further than British legislation and in others we do not go as far.  We need to be extremely careful that the end result is the best one and the best balance for all purposes and not only genuinely increases the legal protection of the consumer but also does not have undesired potential side effects which would not be to the benefit of the consumer.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mícheál Cranitch Mícheál Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>Táimse ar aon tuairim leis na Seanadóirí a labhair ar an mBille seo.  Fáiltim go croiúil roimh an mBille agus sílim go bhfuil an-mholadh ar fad ag dul do na daoine a ullmhaigh an Bille agus a chuir os ár gcómhair é.</P>
      <P>This Bill is to amend and extend the provisions of the Sale of Goods Act, 1893.  Certainly it does that and is all the more welcome because if we compare the date of 1893 and the date of this Bill&mdash;which is 1978&mdash;we will see that there has been a lapse of 85 years.  Much has happened in those 85 years.  Many business practices, some desireable, some undesirable, have come into existence since the 1893 Act was passed.  I happily welcome the Bill and hope it will give every satisfaction to the public in general; they deserve it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1075" /> A number of suggestions were made to the Minister regarding various sections. I make a suggestion regarding one. It is section 12, particularly the part which reads:</P>
    <P>In a contract for the sale of goods of a class to which this section applies there shall be an implied warranty that spare parts and an adequate after-sale service will be provided by the seller for such period and in such circumstances as are stated in an offer, description or advertisement by the seller on behalf of the manufacturer or on his own behalf.</P>
    <P>I have had personal experience of grave disappointment in this regard, and so have many others who have spoken to me about it.  The best thing would be to give an example of what I have in mind.  I know of a man who some time ago went into a shop and bought an electric razor.  He kept the razor very well, kept it cleaned, got it serviced and so on. The motor and everything else in the razor were working perfectly.  He got one or two renewals of the main movable parts, that is, the cutters in the razor. Quite recently he went in to get a new supply of cutters and the shop assistant said that he did not seem to have the size.  He kept on trying but came back to my friend, the customer, and said that he had no parts and that the machine was obsolete.  An argument ensued; my friend declared that the machine could not possibly be obsolete, that it was as good then as it was when he bought it five or six years earlier or less.  He got no satisfaction.  His excellent razor was now useless; he could get no more spare parts for it.</P>
    <P>It is very important when one gets a machine or instrument with moving parts that are subject to wear, that spare parts be available for such a machine for a reasonable period after the purchase is made.  The question then arises&mdash;what is a reasonable period?  I shall not detain the House but I hope the Minister when replying will refer to this section; I do not really understand these sections and their implications in law.  Perhaps he <Col N="1076" /> could explain what exactly is involved in section 12(2).  I am sure the public would be very happy if they knew that a firm selling an article, such as I described, would guarantee to the customers that spare parts would be available for a period of X years.  The customer would then know where he stood and would not be subjected to the disappointment he would experience if after three, four or five years, an excellent machine was rendered obsolete, not by reason of the fact that the machine failed to work but simply because he could not get the spare parts for it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>It is with a certain amount of trepidation and lack of confidence that I speak on this Bill because I hear lawyers and members of the legal profession themselves expressing difficulty in understanding the technical complexities of such a Bill.  I pity what many consumers will face in trying to understand the contents of this Bill.  After all, it is for the consumers themselves that this Bill and its benefits are intended. There is no doubt that the Bill does bear witness, in its complex terms, to the rather sophisticated and complex nature of the market place today.  So complex and sophisticated is that field that I should have thought that any legislation to meet the difficulties inherent in that market place would tend to be simple in its definition and in spelling out what it intends to do rather than being confusing in its contents.  Perhaps the best thing would have been to repeal all prior and existing pieces of legislation and to bring in one codified piece so that anybody who wishes to avail of the benefits would have to peruse only one piece of legislation rather than many pieces.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have always been a believer in the old dictum of <i>caveat emptor</i> as being sufficient guidance for anybody trying to hold his head solidly on his shoulders in regard to any purchase transaction, but I must admit&mdash;in the face of the various pieces of legislation that I have seen go through in the past couple of years, such as the Occasional Trading Bill and community bills like the Bill dealing with roadside trading and the Consumer Information <Col N="1077" /> Bill&mdash;that there certainly must be many people who have difficulty in the matter of a purchasing transaction.  It has already been stated that this Bill weighs somewhat in favour of the buyer and to this extent it is different from the Sale of Goods Act, 1893.  Examples of this lie in the exclusion clauses that are prohibited, for instance, &ldquo;no refund&rdquo; notices will now be allowed and credit purchasers who have no rights now will have certain rights under the new legislation.</P>
    <P>If these benefits, as they are, are contained in this Bill and other benefits, the Bill must raise certain questions as regards whether it will be availed of by the people whom it is intended to benefit. Will a cost be the consequence of this legislation going through, a cost which may well be added to the actual price of the goods?  If it is weighed any way in favour of the buyer is it, therefore, weighed too much against the seller and is there equity in all of this?</P>
    <P>As a member of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges some months past I alerted this House and the Government to the fact that this House has within its Standing Orders certain rights as regards conveying a Bill of such complex nature to a select or special committee where it could receive really positive and very close attention, and that such a committee would have been the ideal forum and vehicle for dealing with Bills of this nature.  Perhaps it is too late at this stage; perhaps there has been some agreement in regard to giving more leisurely and more positive treatment on Committee Stage and a more orderly treatment regarding the various sections. It would certainly have suited the stature of this House and of the Bill itself if it had been referred to a special or select committee.  I wonder if the protections contained in this Bill will result in some hidden cost in the eventual price of the goods.  We have experienced hidden costs in legislation before.  In regard to labour legislation, some employers have, as a result of various Acts such as the Unfair Dismissals Act setting out minimum terms of notice of dismissal <Col N="1078" /> been reluctant, to an extent, to taking on additional labour, even when additional labour was warranted by the extent of their manufacturing enterprise at a particular time, because they saw in it certain difficulty in terminating employment. There is a hidden cost in legislation in that context.  I wonder whether there is not also a hidden cost in this legislation.</P>
    <P>I can think of no better forum than the Seanad, with so many of its Members in the legal profession, but if it is confusing and complex to them and difficult to understand in certain aspects, how difficult will it be for the people whom it is supposed to benefit?  Will they avail of the Bill at all?  Will they understand anything about it?  Certainly, if people who are dealing in large volumes and large quantities of goods, for instance, people who buy wholesale in large quantities and retailers who buy in large quantities, feel a grievance as a result of a purchase transaction they will be in a position to avail of the contents of this Bill.  Will the small purchaser, however&mdash;or the small businessman who does not buy in very big quantities&mdash;consider the cost of having to seek legal advice in trying to understand what exactly is available to help him in this Bill?  Will he bother doing anything at all about it?  On the other hand, if the seller of the goods feels that he may be subject to court cases at the end of the road, will he not add a certain little item of cost on top of the price of the goods?  It is very difficult to see whether these hidden costs will, or will not, result from the passing of legislation like this.</P>
    <P>The small buyer will probably find it difficult to understand his rights under this Bill and perhaps there should be a small tribunal or some forum which could consider that small buyer's rights and perhaps be established on a permanent basis to give advice on these matters. We should consider that on Committee Stage.  There is no doubt that legal and court processes will have to be simplified for small purchasers involved as a result of this legislation.  They should know, with confidence, that there is somewhere in which they can pursue their <Col N="1079" /> rights and that the whole matter will not be completely prohibited to them.  What has been the experience since the Consumer Information Act was passed in 1978?  Has that Act shown up instances where small consumers were able to understand the rights that were available to them?  Have they been able to act upon them?  I am sure the Department concerned have some information and some feedback in regard to this and it would give an indication as to how a Bill, such as we have here, will work out in practice.</P>
    <P>Certain speakers have already raised the matter of defective vehicles, particularly where a person other than the buyer will come under the scope of this Bill.  This will present certain difficulties and will provide great scope and a great field-day to all lawyers and solicitors trying to disentangle where and when a vehicle passed from one person to another and the condition in which it passed in its stages and so on, and where exactly the person in charge of the vehicle at the time stands in regard to the enforcement of the penalty clauses in this Bill.  If we are speaking of danger to life and limb and road safety in general, then perhaps the Road Traffic Act is far more appropriate legislation than the Sale of Goods Bill for pursuing the matter of defective vehicles.  In drawing up this Bill, and in teasing out all its implications, all the pros and cons of its various sections, and the possible inherent difficulties in its enforcement that have been pointed out on Second Stage, what answers have the Minister's officials come up with, in trying to close any loopholes that may well arise in those situations?</P>
    <P>Other speakers have referred to the question of leasing not being covered; I wonder why leasing is not covered in this Bill.  Does it mean that we will have before us another Bill at some future stage in regard to that?  Advantage will have to be taken of the period between this Bill's final passing through the Houses of the Oireachtas and actually coming into operation, which should be <Col N="1080" /> sufficiently long to enable all the individuals concerned to be educated on the contents of this Bill.  It should not just be left for the event to happen, where the person feels a grievance as a result of some transaction and has to face up to the question of whether he should or should not obtain legal advice in regard to taking action under this Bill. There should be an adequate transitional period whereby the Department concerned can educate and inform the public in general on the contents of this Bill.  Small businesses, particularly, are going to be in a rather difficult situation.  Their very structure hinders understanding of what exactly is contained in this legislation.</P>
    <P>This Bill seems to make offences of many happenings and incidences in sale and buying transactions which I believe will always be present.  For instance, ordinary human fallibility means that there will always be mistakes made, that accidents will always happen in documentation or whatever processes are laid down in this Bill, even in recording documents, in the recording of defective vehicles&mdash;of when they came into a premises, when they left and what work was carried out on them.  It is a bit like the imposition on farmers of requiring them to keep accounts when their whole psychology, attitude and make-up are not geared to such an imposition being made on them rather suddenly.  Perhaps this Bill is going a little bit too far in making offences of many incidences in the actual sale and purchase transactions, which will present difficulty.</P>
    <P>Having made those few comments, I believe that the Bill does contain benefits, as no doubt it was intended to. If the Department officials have gone into all the pros and cons and the implications of the various sections, and seen the difficulties that may well be there, could the Minister tell the Seanad whether or not they are satisfied that the Bill can cover any loopholes?</P>
    <Speaker pid="CLambert" hpid="Mr. Lambert Mr. Lambert">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lambert</NameTxt>
      <P>In welcoming this Bill I pay tribute to a wide cross-section of the public who have contributed to the various reports of the National Prices <Col N="1081" /> Commission and the Consumer Advisory Council over the years since Professor Whincup's report in 1970.  We are inclined to forget the amount of work behind the formulation of this legislation. As Senator Robinson has pointed out, when enacted it will only bring us into conformity with legislation pertaining to other EEC countries.  I should point out, on behalf of the private sector, that most Irish manufacturers, particularly those with export trade, as a matter of principle have adhered to the various factors contained in this Bill and, indeed, have to date been doing so on a voluntary basis.</P>
      <P>We have heard a lot about the motor industry and I have every sympathy with their submission, but we must take into account the number of accidents and the dramatic statistics which are recorded regularly, Every citizen will applaud a clause being included in this Bill which will pertain to a certificate of roadworthiness, or some warranty that will prevent accidents.  I am very interested in the prevention of accidents and I feel that, in the effective administration of the Bill, the insurance companies could co-operate in ensuring that they have sight of any certificate that is decided upon before they issue cover.  This might encourage them to take on more motor insurance at more appropriate rates.  I should like to see the insurance institute and the motor industry play a more active part in the prevention of accidents and anything that this Bill can do to help the ordinary citizen in avoiding such accidents should be taken into consideration.  It would also save on expensive claims in insurance and, perhaps, a certain amount of Garda time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have a particular interest as a consumer and as someone interested in security because quite recently my Ford Granada Ghia car was stolen twice in four days from private car parks.  I should like some guidance from the Minister as to what liability might arise under this new Bill.  In the first instance I parked it in the RIAC car park when I was going to a dinner.  I locked it but when I came back it had been stolen.  It <Col N="1082" /> had been taken for a joy ride and vandalised. I was lucky to get it back.  In the case of the club, I pay an annual subscription that covers car parking facilities but the club maintains it has no liability and that the car is parked at the owner's risk.  Under this Bill will the club be liable, despite their disclaimer, since I have paid my subscription towards car parking facilities which are supposed to be supervised?  I was so distressed I took taxis for a few days.  I had a meeting in Trinity College and when I drove in there I was stopped at the barrier and questioned very severely as to my reasons for wanting to park within the confines of the college.  I was allowed to park there.  I went to a meeting and after two hours when I came out, I found my car had been stolen.  I had it locked and the steering lock was on and so on.  In that case I did not pay a subscription but on the other hand are the owners of that car park liable where the entrance facilities are strictly controlled?</P>
    <P>I mention this in the interests of the public generally, because it raises the question of the responsibility of car manufacturers.  There has been comment recently over the easy accessibility to Ford cars in Northern Ireland, there seem to be so many duplicate keys available that some research should be done by the motor industry as to how safe a locked parked car is and what are the chances of it being stolen.  I felt, from my experience, perturbed about the complacent attitude of the motor industry particulary when one thinks of the situation in Northern Ireland where cars are easily stolen and used for crimes which we all abhor.  I hope that this Bill will help both the motor industry and the insurance companies to play a more active part in the prevention of accidents and the prevention of crimes which lead to the destruction of property and life generally.</P>
    <P>In the Dáil debate the Minister answered the question of danger associated with the sale of inferior imported electrical goods and stated that regulations are constantly policed by the Department in conjunction with the <Col N="1083" /> IIRS.  I mention this because there does not seem to be the same protection where food imports are concerned.  Home manufacturers have to adhere to certain standards of hygiene because there are regular visits from inspectors.  Access of foreign imports into this country, as I have said in previous debates, is the easiest within the EEC.  I should like to draw the Minister's attention to this aspect of consumer protection and consumer rights.  There should be similar regulations imposed on imports of food as there are for defective electrical and other equipment.</P>
    <P>I should like to raise another point which at first may appear somewhat unusual. The practice of newspaper and magazine articles appearing under <i>noms de plume</i> or pseudonyms is on the increase and the styles range from &ldquo;a Special Correspondent&rdquo; to the use of fictitious names or titles, in many cases misleading the reader.  Where these are unsigned are they taken as the editorial view of the paper?  It seems to distance whoever the writer is from the contents of such pieces.  The use of pseudonyms creates in the reader's mind the impression that an author with the same name exists and that he is prepared to stand over the article.  This occurs more often in the gossip columns and produces two distasteful after effects.  First, spurious legitimacy is conferred on the contents of such articles and the reader can be misled.  For better or worse people tend to believe what is written in the newspapers.  Secondly, those who are singled out for comment can suffer and apologies rarely take the same space or position is the offending article.</P>
    <P>Journalism in Ireland has rightly been commended for the general responsibility and objectivity of its practitioners. Many senior journalists have expressed their resentment to me about the use of pseudonyms and fictitious titles since this can lower the tone of the profession.  Perhaps the Minister could guide me as to whether the consumer who purchases a newspaper has adequate rights of protection under this Bill <Col N="1084" /> and the Consumer Information Act, the right to expect proper information regarding a journalist's identification particularly if an article refers, favourably or unfavourably, to a reader who has purchased the newspaper or magazine.  I welcome the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill.  It goes a long way towards introducing a means by which the protective services of the State in this field can be utilised and better availed of by people who feel aggrieved.  To a great extent it gives them a permanent structure through which they can act.  It goes some way towards giving the community as consumers access to the centre of power.  I say some way because I do not mean all of the way, but it is a step on the way.</P>
      <P>I am not suggesting, while I welcome the Bill, that it satisfies all that is needed to protect consumers.  It is something that is on its way to better things and that is what generates my interest and welcome.  It is clearly up to the politicians and other people involved in the consumer protection area to see that advances on this Bill follow.  It is incumbent on interested parties in consumer affairs to keep a watchful eye on developments because this lays the basis for good development.</P>
      <P>Speaking as a layman, I found difficulty in understanding everything that was contained in the Bill.  It looked to me after a while, getting a little bit bored reading it, like a long legal document. The evidence of that has been shown here because the people who got the best out of the debate are those who have some legal background and knowledge or who have some training and experience in this area.  Those who are sellers are consumers in some other respects, I am as interested in their welfare as I am in that of the people I would be more or less talking about.  My main concern lies in being ever vigilant on behalf of consumers.  I say that largely in respect of the individual consumer. I say it also in respect of the means by which he can get both redress for his complaint and compensation.  I cannot stress that enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1085" /> Although the Bill does not deal with compensation arising out of a claim the question of redress is still there in that consumers can, through the director of consumer affairs, get at the people whom they say have cheated or misguided them and they can bring prosecutions. They have to adopt a separate procedure if they want to get compensation if they feel very aggrieved.  It could be argued that the ideal would be to have the two situations linked together in one Bill.  I am not too sure that that type of legislation would work unless there were other bodies in existence which be more effective than the present national consumer authority.  Something on the lines of a Ministry of Consumer Affairs would be needed to back up that kind of Bill.  In present circumstances, I feel it is not on. These are areas that can be debated in the future.  The Bill has laid the foundation for that and I look forward to further developments.  It could well be argued that a Minister for Consumer Affairs, if such were to be contemplated, might not work for the consumer.  He might, in fact, in some cases work against the consumer.  I am not being adamant about this matter but it is an area where there is scope for a lot more debate.</P>
    <P>While I expressed a great deal of satisfaction with the Bill there is need to widen the discussion and deal with the best means of protecting consumers' interests. I mentioned the National Consumer Authority but they do not have teeth.  Would a more effective one be helpful with similar powers to a Ministry or is that a practical proposition?  Would it be realistic?  On the other hand perhaps a type of local provision by local government for consumer protection might be more beneficial to supplememt what exists at present.  In other words, what can we do to improve the scope, control and operation of consumer protection and the relationship with private groups that are involved?  Is there room for the argument that small clains for compensation should be dealt with through separate courts to avoid the delay and expense of going through the ordinary courts, and so on?  We are <Col N="1086" /> heading in those directions.  A fuller debate on those areas would be very beneficial to bring about the real consumer protection that is needed to give the consumer a real share in the economy.</P>
    <P>In fairness, the Bill tries for a unified trading standard but it misses out in some fields, for example, in that of weights and measures.  Perhaps in the type of debate I suggested those arguments could be used helpfully to advance the legislation.  Again there is scope on the question of surveillance and advertising. As regards advertising, there is a statutory code of advertising practice.  I wonder how effective it is as regards consumer protection.  I do not know how far they can go to test advertising claims or to sponsor the testing of claims made by certain advertisers.  The consensus of opinion on consumer matters would support the idea of a stronger Government agency with powers and facilities for large scale testing.  That is called for in a lot of cases.  It would need scope for adequate publicity for its reports, for dealing with consumer complaints and for acting as a channel for devising new regulations and enforcing them.  These are the practical methods necessary to be pursued.  I am not saying that there are none of them in the Bill.  What I am saying is that there is scope for advancement to bring the consumer more into the scene as part of the economy rather than being just a consumer.  They should have the right to know what competition is about and how they can make an effective input. Prices were mentioned earlier on and this is one way that we could deal with that question.</P>
    <P>I mentioned local government and so on.  What is wrong with information services being available on the high streets? What is wrong with a grant being given to the corporation to put up a site where consumer protection and consumer advice could be given?  These are areas where there is scope for further development. The Bill has given that scope to the Minister who introduced it.</P>
    <P>As socialists we are aware of the increasing deterioration in living and working conditions not only in Ireland <Col N="1087" /> but in the whole of Europe where the capitalist system obtains.  Consequently I see&mdash;whether it is a bias or not I do not know&mdash;the consumer being the person who is losing out in the widening gap between the producer and consumer.  I am not putting forward anything to suggest that the seller has not got any rights, because he is a consumer in another instance.  Of course he has rights.  What I am saying is that the actual producer as distinct from the person who runs a monoply with no registered offices in this country is very far away from the consumer.  That gap is widening and the power of the consumer is diminishing.</P>
    <P>We, as socialists, would like to see a situation developing where some kind of action could be taken by a social-economic group to enable the protection of consumers' interests to be developed much more strongly.  We could go that far and are extremely interested in seeing that consumer information is unbiassed. We are very concerned that consumer protection against misleading advertising is pursued.  In this respect I propose to outline where some of the abuses lie in the hope that I can highlight the need to create an island of consumers and not solely an island of big business, because the consumer is part of the economy and should not be seen just as a consumer.</P>
    <P>The Bill is encouraging and lays the foundation for more effective legislation. Consumers should be brought into the community through a much more permanent structure than they have through the Bill.  We would like to see them in a position where they could organise properly as a social-economic group and be given access through the courts for both compensation and prosecution.  I know they can bring prosecutions through the Director of Consumer Affairs but I am talking about the social-economic group having power to go to court themselves.  That sounds a little radical but it is not all that radical in the final analysis.</P>
    <P>The Bill, good as it is, will not wipe out illegal agreements and the dominant <Col N="1088" /> positions of certain people but it is a genuine endeavour to do so.  If money could be advanced through the budget, for example to strengthen the staff of the consumer authority so as to move on from there to the creation of a consumer network it would be a further step.  I say this particularly since the monopolistic tendencies of multinationals who are very far removed from us in not having registered offices in Ireland or, for that matter, maybe not even in Europe, damage the rights of consumers.  The consumer dealing with those people is not in a position to demand the right to competition.  Consumers should not be left to take up defensive policy positions but should, with State aid, be able positively to promote their interests with emphasis on preventive measures and recognition of their rights.  Consumers are not only purchasers, they should be full partners in the whole economic process.</P>
    <P>On the question of advertisements, surveillance, vigilance and the right to tests, it is very serious when harmful substances, used frequently in foodstuffs. cleaning materials, cosmetics, pharmaceutical products and so on are advertised through the media.  The consumer does not know what the properties are, only that they have some chemical name or else they are generally described as colourants.  This is not good enough.  Apart from the harmful effects on society from the consumers point of view, and the damage it may do to health, it is wrong that they can be advertised without somebody being able to test them.  The onus must be put on the producer to provide prior proof of the harmlessness of anything that he is going to advertise or put on the market.</P>
    <P>There is also the question of harmonisation of laboratory standards.  In some European countries research has taken place only after numerous complaints and there has been evidence that some of the substances are of a harmful nature.  This does not help to put the onus of proof on the person who is advertising. Something stronger than that is needed.  Instead of the consumer being <Col N="1089" /> on the defensive he should be in a position where he can put the onus on industrialists or producers to prove that the product they are producing and putting on the market or advertising is harmless.  Very often there was no widespread publication of the findings of the research carried out in Europe.  The administrative and professional side of it were very secretive.  If we become involved in that, and we should, the results of tests should be publicised widely.  We should also know about the administration and professionalism involved in it.</P>
    <P>I said earlier that the seller was also a consumer.  Sometimes people might think that I do not recognise this fact.  I have dwelt on the word &ldquo;consumer&rdquo; much more so than on the word &ldquo;seller&rdquo;. I believe that the disadvantage lies with the consumer.  There has been a great emphasis in this debate on the legal aspects.  I have no quarrel with that. Business people are better geared, better structured, better legally advised and can afford to make greater use of much more effective organisations than the consumer can.  The consumer has not the same effect and his power over the years has been diminishing.</P>
    <P>I mentioned in the course of winding up on the Appropriation Bill that an imbalance existed between the powers of the consumer and those of the manufacturer and supplier. I attributed this to the fact that there was a concentration on mass production.  This is one of the factors that has contributed to a widening of the gap between the consumer and the seller or producer.  That imbalabce will be remedied to some extent by this Bill but there is a long way to go.  I am not suggesting that producers should gang together and create a great plot.  Not only is there need for strong mechanisms, and we have a few in the Bill, to deal with consumer protection, there is need for constant and effective policing of how those mechanisms are doing in the light of the rate and pace of change arising from the spread of technology.  The need for consumer protection arises from other activities <Col N="1090" /> of the consumer society.  I mentioned the mass media earlier.  Through the mass media and by large-scale advertising people, in increasing numbers, are influenced to buy.  Maybe this is the manufacturers' way of getting the most out of their plants and their workers, but it does not end there.  I want to see plenty of work for the workers and plenty of advertising to keep jobs alive, but it does not rest there.  The dishonesty commences when the producer, manufacturer, advertiser or agent for the producer has stimulated people into buying in increasing numbers.</P>
    <P>This is not sufficient in itself and a campaign gets going, the little trick called &ldquo;re-consuming&rdquo;.  There is misleading advertising. The belief is promoted by subtle means that the product is the greatest in the world.  It is suggested that last year's product should be thrown away and this year's product should be purchased.</P>
    <P>The psychology is clear.  It is not a question of advertising to try to sell people what they need.  It is the psychology of creating a scrambling selfish system, and the vicious circle continues.  In circumstances like this the consumers must be protected.  They must be protected against aggressive and misleading publicity about goods which are detrimental to health.  The manufacturer's logic is understandable.  Naturally he tells the advertising people that his campaign must be geared in the first instance towards persuading consumers that a certain product is good and then getting them to throw it away, or to change from it to the latest product advertised. The procedure creates dissatisfaction with existing products.  That is understandable but it is not beneficial to the consumer.  Manufacturers and sellers have problems but that system is not very satisfactory to the poor and the lowly paid who will be the greatest sufferers. Legislation must be geared to protect their interests to the full.</P>
    <P>In effect I am saying that through the mass media, manufacturers and advertisers co-operating and in collusion with each other, trick and cheat, using the <Col N="1091" /> system that is legally open to them to do so.  Because the consumer has so little power there is no way of taking them to task and having a full scale examination of what is advertised on the mass media. In the final analysis, no matter how we argue this, no matter what legal argument is put forward, the consumer is the most vulnerable person and his power is continually diminishing.  If he is not given the fullest possible protection, with regular enforcement of all the consumer protection that is in existence and all the legislative mechanisms that are available to him, and if there is not a regular updating of those mechanisms, further technological developments, an increase in the size of manufacturing units, the spread of the multinational corporations will continue to diminish the consumer's power.</P>
    <P>We in this House and Deputies in the Dáil have the greatest responsibility to the consumer.  There is a physical and mental gulf between the manufacturer and the consumer and, if we are not vigilant, if we do not bring in more legislation and enforce it, the little bit of power and protection the consumer has will diminish.  Many of the things I am saying are an unpleasant reality.  I do not make any apologies for saying them, and I do not make any apologies for placing great emphasis on the need for continual vigilance.  These tricks are completely undesirable.  The consumer has not got access to the mass media and other forms of advertising to try to redress the balance.  The consumers who get the rawest deal are the poor, the ill-educated and the elderly.  These people should be the concern of every one of us and certainly they are the concern of the Labour Party.  We must give priority to their needs.  We are interested in the seller, the manufacturer, the producer, and so on, because he produces jobs but, as a socialist party, we make no excuse and no apologies for laying emphasis on the protection of the poor, the ill-educated and the elderly.  They are of particular interest and concern to us.</P>
    <P>Earlier I made reference to the tendency <Col N="1092" /> for a physical and mental gulf to grow between the manufacturer and the consumer and I mentioned tricks built into the system.  I should have stressed that there is no evidence to show that the manufacturer is not concerned about bridging the physical and mental gulf, possibly because it would not benefit him very much.  Since it is well-nigh impossible for the consumer to bridge that gap, the onus is on this House to bring in the strongest legislation possible to protect the consumer.  I am not saying the manufacturer does it with the idea of trampling the consumers into the ground, but he does not see it as his responsibility to bridge that gap.  He gets his advice through the various organisations, through the legal bodies, and so on, and as long as he is just about right he is happy enough.  The onus is on us to provide more consumer protection through properly organised bodies and agencies.</P>
    <P>It is the Minsiter's responsibility, it is the responsibility of both Houses of the Oireachtas, to campaign as hard as we can to see that the consumer gets the best possible protection, to see that the situation does not deteriorate to the point where in fact it has deteriorated&mdash;there is the &ldquo;re-consume&rdquo; trick&mdash;and to see that people do not start producing goods of a lower quality in order to stimulate the need for replacement.</P>
    <P>This is the Sale of Goods and Supply of Services Bill.  If you are going to produce inferior goods and if you want to take advantage of the mass media to get people to &ldquo;re-consume&rdquo;, if the goods thrown away need a service, why should you bother too much about providing too good a service?  You would defeat the &ldquo;re-consume&rdquo; trick and you would not be too happy with some obstinate consumer who was looking for services in an abundance of stocks, spare parts, and so on.  I could not see manufacturers going overboard to see that stocks, spare parts, services, and so on, were there in abundance.  They will do as much as is necessary to get by, or to satisfy people to some degree.  If I am right in my argument <Col N="1093" /> about manufacturers trying to get people to throw away last year's goods. and using the media to do that then it would be a terrible contradiction where goods need a service, to start producing too good a service for those goods.</P>
    <P>It seems to me that inherent in the whole question of the sale of goods and supply of services is whether it is in the best interest of manufacturers who employ agents to advertise for them to give the best possible service.  Some give a good service, but that does not apply across the board.  Certainly in many cases, if you did not give a good service you would not be too long in business. There are areas where a good service is not given.  This is where the consumer is vulnerable and needs protection.  If the mass-media can be used by manufacturers and their advertising agencies, and so on, to trick and cheat people into buying goods, there is no reason why the State should not use the mass-media to ensure that the consumer knows all his rights.  There are one or two programmes on television and radio which do this, but the State should tell the consumer: &ldquo;The Sale of Goods and Supply of Services Bill, 1978, has gone through both Houses of the Oireachtas.  We want you to get to know your rights under thar Bill.  This is the agency to which you go.&rdquo; Why cannot we advertise to procect the consumer?  The consumer is not just a buyer of goods.  He is part of the whole economic situation.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill.  It is a step forward. If we are really serious about this matter we should continue to introduce consumer protection legislation.  We should examine it at regular intervals.  We should encourage socio-economic groups to get involved.  We should encourage local government to set up advisory services and, if necessary, we should ensure that free legal, aid is available, or that a grant is given to the free legal aid services to set up a special sector to investigate the question of consumers' interests, not only to advise on them, but to represent the people's interests arising out of complaints under the existing legislation.  We should encourage <Col N="1094" /> the free legal aid people to show where the legislation is not having an effect.</P>
    <P>I feel strongly about this subject. There is more scope for consumer protection.  I am not worried about the big business people.  They have plenty of legal aid, plenty of well-organised bodies, plenty of resources to fall back on, and plenty of know how and expertise to give them all the protection they need.  The consumer is the person who needs our help and the onus lies on both Houses of the Oireachtas to provide that help and I urge the Minister to bear that in mind.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelMulcahy" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom fáilte a chur riomh an mBille seo.  Ceapaim gur céim mhór ar aghaidh é chun go mheadh an gnáth dhuine sa tír seo sásta le pé earraí a bheadh á gceannach aige.  Tá a fhios againn go léir go bhfuil an-staidéar ar siúl san Eorap; san mBruiseal, le déanaí ag leagadh amach polasaí den tsaghas seo.  Is mór an áthas atá ormsa go bhfuil beirt Éireannaigh i bhfeighil an polasaí sin a leagadh amach, duine amháin acu mar Choimisinéar agus an duine eile mar stiúrthóir ar an Roinn atá i gceannas an taobh sin de.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Bill.  It is another step in dealing with one of the great problems in Irish society which is what I call the &ldquo;Ah, sure it will do&rdquo; complex.  The Irishman tends to give in fairly easily when it comes to quality of product.  I should like to change the nature of the debate on the Second Stage of the Bill by putting some emphasis on the quality aspect; I see this Bill as providing the sanctions which will encourage the producer to use the methods of modern quality control to ensure that the product is in a fit state for consumption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The future of this country depends on industrial development.  We have mentioned this many times in this House.  To be successful in a modern competitive society, industrial development must imcorporate the best of the management techniques developed under the heading of quality control.  We see examples of that in other countries.  Japan, which <Col N="1095" /> some decades ago was seen as an industrial society producing secondhand goods and copying other people's output, is now probably in the leading position in the world in the production of quality goods.  This did not happen overnight. It happened because a conscious effort was made by the Japanese to develop the methods of quality control and to put them to work in their factories. An &ldquo;ah, sure it will do&rdquo; complex was not accepted.  In fact, the motto developed there was &ldquo;the zero-defect programme&rdquo;.  To that extent, the tendency to say &ldquo;Sure you will always have problems&rdquo;, or even, as Senator Markey said, paper work can go wrong and we must understand that, are relics of an attitude I should like to see disappearing. We must not accept secondhand work: &ldquo;zero-defect&rdquo; is the motto and &ldquo;zero-defect&rdquo; it will have to be.</P>
    <P>I will try to illustrate that.  I am sure every Senator in the House is happy about the fact that the best methods of quality control and the best &ldquo;zero-defect&rdquo; programmes are used when they sit in an aeroplane and are flying at 30,000 feet at 600 miles an hour.  They hope that the manager of quality control in the factory which produced the fasteners holding on the wings operated those schemes.  They are not willing to say: &ldquo;Ah, sure the paper work could have gone wrong.&rdquo;  I am not saying Senator Markey actually said this, but I am building a little on what he said.  That is an attitude that gets into industry and it was the attitude in Irish industry two and a half decades ago.  Two decades ago, in 1960, I worked as a quality control manager.  At that time I was the only person in the country who was a member of the American Society of Quality Control.  Now there are many members. I believe a new Quality Control Institute is being set up, with staff and is to be opened at the end of next month, possibly by the Minister.  This is great progress.</P>
    <P>I see the Bill as the sanction, the systematic way that is being put in the hands of the consumer to enable him to <Col N="1096" /> throw pressure back on the producer to employ these techniques.  If they are employed there will be some added value. You do not get them for nothing.  We have talked about costs.  Will there be extra costs involved?  Of course there will be extra costs involved, but it is a matter of balancing the costs with the benefit, the benefit of the improved quality.  This Bill is a major contribution in this area.  I hope some positive approach will be taken which will be an encouragement to producers to adopt quality control procedures and that even though they have sanctions hanging over them, that they will be motivated by a positive viewpoint internally to set up these procedures.</P>
    <P>I agree with the Senators who spoke about the way this Bill applies to the motor trade.  I will not elaborate on it.  I agree that applying a criminal sanction is probably not appropriate under this Bill: it might be appropriate elsewhere.  At the same time, I would, make the point to the motor industry that it is up to them to employ the best of modern management quality control techniques to ensure that vehicles being passed over to consumers are roadworthy.  I should not like to see us getting to the stage where a Ralph Nader would be needed in Irish society to ensure that this Bill is fully implemented. The positive aspect I am trying to emphasise is important; the positive aspect of the producer of the product, the person who is cutting the tool to size, the person who is assembling the machine, the person who is producing the motor, or whatever else it is.  You cannot inspect quality into a product; you can only build it in and a stitch in time saves nine.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasWhitaker" hpid="Dr. Whitaker Dr. Whitaker">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Whitaker</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I should like to express a general welcome for the provisions of this Bill.  Like some other Senators I do not understand why its scope does not extend to leasing.  Secondly, I should like to support those Senators who have expressed misgivings about the introduction into section 13 of a criminal responsibility for the issue of an incorrect certificate by a motor trader.  I hope that on reconsideration the <Col N="1097" /> Minister will decide to rely entirely on civil liability which should be as severe as is necessary in terms of potential damages.  Thirdly, I should like to take this opportunity to say that I do not understand fully the reasoning behind section 14.  Section 14 is the section which deems a finance house to be a party to a particular kind of sale and makes it jointly and severally liable to the buyer for breach of contract of sale and&mdash;I understand this is new&mdash;for any misrepresentations made by the seller with respect to the goods.  The section as it now stands was welcomed in the Dáil as being very enlightened and as being beneficial to the consumer.  I recognise that protection of the consumer is necessary and desirable and that abuses can arise if finance houses are too liberal in financing sales or enabling sellers to push their wares.  But I am not persuaded that the imposition of joint and several responsibility on the finance house is altogether fair and reasonable, even though it may have been done in Britain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Perhaps I should make it clear that I have not been asked by the finance houses to make any representations on their behalf.  I am raising this matter entirely on my own initiative.  The question is why a finance house should be liable in particular cases, while the provider of finance is not liable at all in other cases. For example, if I pay for a car by overdrawing my current account in a bank, no liability attaches to the bank in connection with the transaction.  If anything goes wrong, my only recourse is against the supplier.  It would be utterly unreasonable to involve the bank.  Even if I borrow from a finance house myself on a hire purchase or credit sale contract and pay the supplier with the proceeds, no liability attaches to the finance house which has provided me with the money if there is anything wrong with the goods. Again, this seems right.  But if the finance house acquires title temporarily to a car because it pays the supplier direct, and then collects the money from me on a hire purchase or credit sale agreement, section 14 makes the finance house jointly and severally liable with the supplier, <Col N="1098" /> if the supplier has misrepresented the quality or roadworthiness of the car.  I do not quite follow the logic of this.  I may be told that the legal difference, the passing of title to the finance house, justifies involving it in some liability.  I would be prepared to accept that.</P>
    <P>It may be argued further that there can be a social problem if credit sales are made too automatic and easy.  I do not deny this.  But surely the Central Bank can do something to make sure that finance houses cannot extend credit too liberally for any particular purpose, and can even make it a condition of their banking licence that they do not buy too much from any supplier for resale on hire purchase or credit terms.</P>
    <P>I am really asking are there adequate social grounds for differentiating as much as this section does between one form of finance and another?  In any case, surely the supplier should bear the principal liability and the finance house be liable only in a secondary and limited way, not going, perhaps, beyond its original financial input.  I should very much like to hear the Minister's views on the questions I have raised on this section.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. Kiely Mr. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill.  The Minister, in his opening remarks, said that this Bill in a number of respects complements the Consumer Information Act, 1978, which was designed to ensure that the consumer would have protection against misleading advertising and descriptions of goods and services.  What I am concerned with is my own occupation, farming, in respect of which I should like to point out that in the sale of pedigree cattle the dams are recorded.  In some of the advertising in catalogues the records are fictitious.  When cows are recorded and certified by the Department they must carry a Department reference number.  I have seen animals sold bearing no reference number quoted in the catalogue, with a definitely fictitious record for the dam of the animal, the purpose being to render the animal more valuable than it should be.  This is something I should like to see protected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1099" /> There should be an onus on auctioneers who are paid by the purchaser at the rate of 5 per cent.  They should give correct figures, ensuring that when they are cataloguing animals like this the Department's reference number be appended. Indeed, there should be some penalty imposed on any farmer or breeder who would resort to such low tactics as those to which I have referred in order to make unjustifiable profits.</P>
    <P>Sufficient has been said already about the controversial section 13.  While the consumer should be protected I should not like to see a reputable dealer subjected to such convictions as are imposed in section 13, which would, perhaps, be to the detriment of the reputable dealer leaving the &ldquo;cowboys&rdquo; or people who advertise under box numbers to gain therefrom.  Anyone advertising goods should do so in his own name; he should not be ashamed to do so and should not advertise under a box number.  This is something that should be investigated.</P>
    <P>I would not mind if there was some system whereby all vehicles would be tested.  I was delighted to note from the Minister's opening remarks that he would be prepared to meet the Society of the Irish Motor Industry to discuss this controversial subject.  Perhaps thereafter the motor industry would be satisfied with all of the provisions of this Bill.  I welcome the Bill and I hope it will afford the consumer adequate protection.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AndyOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I join in the general welcome of this Bill.  Indeed, it is overdue. The Bill provides the basis for further legislation in this field, when it is seen how effective its provisions will be or perhaps when the need for further amendments become obvious.  In so far as its provisions are directed at protecting the right of the consumer or the buyer the Bill is very welcome.  The existing legislation dating back to the end of the last century tended more to protect the seller.  Therefore, this new approach of protecting the consumer or the buyer is to be heartily welcomed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are cases that come to mind <Col N="1100" /> which will not occur with such ease to the perpetrators of such unjust practices in the future, as happened in the past.  I think, for example, of the sale of defective cars and so on.  It is most desirable that the provisions of the Bill prevent the buyer or consumer from being tricked or codded in any shape or form.  In so far as its provisions deter those who sell these articles, or goods of other kinds, from bringing off such smart moves on an inexperienced customer then they are to be highly welcomed.</P>
    <P>I hope that when the Bill becomes law, which will be in the near future, a reasonable time will elapse in which to enable everybody to become aware of its provisions.  I should not like there to be a persecution of small business people and others of that calibre who, for one reason or another, might not be fully aware of its provisions and land themselves in serious trouble mainly through lack of information.  With that reservation I welcome the Bill and hope it will prove to be as effective as Senators hope.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to make one or two points on this Bill.  I welcome the introduction of this Bill and compliment the Minister on so doing.  We have had a very wide-ranging debate.  Practically every point has been made. Nevertheless I hope that Irish products will reflect a greater spirit of pride in the finished fruits of Irish endeavour so that we will not need this Bill, although I believe it is certainly no harm to have it on the Statute Book.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Reading through the Bill&mdash;which appears to be quite complicated&mdash;I note that &ldquo;goods&rdquo; or indeed &ldquo;services&rdquo; have not been defined in section 2.  I suppose that means that the Bill covers a very wide field.  I do not know if it is intended that the Bill's provisions should cover the sale of livestock.  It deals fairly well with services.  I might mention one type of service in passing.  I listen at least once a week to a service provided by Telefis Éireann, a report on livestock marts throughout the country.  If one were to keep a note each week of the remarks of the gentleman announcing increases of <Col N="1101" /> so much per kilo, one would be lead to believe that cattle were more expensive than gold.</P>
    <P>If a semi-State organisation, like Telefís Éireann, purport to give that service the announcer should be exact in the numbers exhibited and in the prices.  Certainly at present it misleads the public and, in many cases, prompts people to put their goods or cattle on sale when possibly&mdash;if they knew the exact situation of the market&mdash;they might not be so tempted.</P>
    <P>I should like sincerely to endorse the case made by Senator Whitaker, and indeed by many others, on section 13.  I support those views, not just because the Irish motor traders are very perturbed about it but since it has been clearly pointed out that this section will not cover quite a significant number of sales of vehicles.  Therefore, it is a little unfair. I hope the Minister will be able to introduce some amendments on Committee Stage in order to improve the Bill in this regard, ensuring that all sections are treated in the same way.</P>
    <P>In an era of increased prices and increased costs of services the consuming public are entitled to the greatest possible protection.  I hope that the Minister will bear this aspect in mind&mdash;even though this Bill is bridging a considerable span of time&mdash;and that by its implementation he will be able to amend existing legislation.  In the main the services supplied and the quality of goods supplied here and produced by our people are second to none.  Nevertheless there are some people who appear to get by very comfortably on short-dealing the public.  This practice must be tackled and I wish the Department and the Minister every success in so doing.  I am sure that he will have the full support of the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. R. Burke) Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. R. Burke)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. R. Burke)</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to thank the many Senators who spoke on the Bill for the constructive way they approached this debate.  As I said in my opening remarks, it is a Bill which is overdue.  I <Col N="1102" /> agree that, having waited this long, the Bill should&mdash;when it leaves this House&mdash; be as good and as effective as possible.  Certainly this will be my approach during the Committee and other Stages.</P>
      <P>Many points were made by Senators during the debate.  While I am satisfied that in many respects the Bill is as it should be, nevertheless, I appreciate the merit of many of the points made and I will be considering them carefully before the next Stage.</P>
      <P>Turning to a number of the points made, I shall refer first to the last speaker, Senator McDonald, who spoke of RTE and their services.  RTE are not providing a service under contract.  Consequently, that is not covered by this Bill. The term &ldquo;goods&rdquo; is defined already in the Principal Act.</P>
      <P>We had a number of Senators from all sides raising the question of bailment and leasing.  There were Senator McGuinness, Senator Whitaker and a number of others.  The general question of bailment is a separate area of law in its own right.  As such, it was not tackled in general terms in the Bill.  Furthermore, I am advised that an extensive study of this whole area would be required if that law were to be substantially changed. Secondly, while Part IV of the Bill&mdash;dealing with the supply of services&mdash;did not set out to cover bailment situations specifically it does cover them in so far as they are contracts for the supply of a service.  My Department have not received any volume of complaints which might suggest that the bailment area needs to be substantially overhauled at present.  Should there be a drift to leasing envisaged by the various Senators, I would be prepared to have this area of leasing examined in depth with a view to establishing what needs to be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the question of consolidation of the sale of goods legislation, Senators Molony and McGuinness said they would like to see all the legislation consolidated into one Act.  While I appreciate that this would be of benefit to <Col N="1103" /> consumers, traders and lawyers alike, it is not a practical proposition at this stage.  All we set out to do in Part II of the Bill&mdash;which deals with the sale of goods&mdash;was to amend certain provisions of the Sale of Goods Act, 1893 in order to bring the balance of legal responsibility between consumers and traders more into line with modern circumstances. We did not set out to overhaul the 1893 Act as a whole.  In any event, we are creating new statute law in this Bill in such areas as services generally, directory entries and so on. Therefore if we took the approach of consolidating the law on the sale of goods it would mean that it would not be possible to legislate in these other areas as well.</P>
    <P>Several Senators also mentioned misrepresentation and maintained that this was not the appropriate Bill by which to amend the law on this subject.  I appreciate that the United Kingdom Misrepresentation Act, 1967&mdash;on which sections 40 to 43 of this Bill are based&mdash;has more widespread application than I am proposing.  Indeed, I agree that it might be a good idea to amend the law in general relating to misrepresentation. However, the Bill relates only to the areas of sale of goods, hire purchase and supply of services.  I am satisfied that it is reasonable to use this opportunity to amend the law on misrepresentation as it applied in these areas only.  Senator Kiely mentioned misrepresentation in the livestock industry.  This would be covered by the misrepresentation section in this Bill.</P>
    <P>There was substantial discussion of the provisions of section 13, dealing with motor vehicles.  Practically every Senator who spoke referred to this section.  In particular they referred to the requirement on motor dealers to issue roadworthiness certificates in respect of the cars they sell.  I explained to the House on the last occasion that I intended to meet the Society of the Irish Motor Industry before we reached Committee Stage.  I met representatives of the SIMI last week and I am arranging for <Col N="1104" /> further dialogue with them with a view, perhaps, to restructuring somewhat the extent and scope of the section as a whole.</P>
    <P>Regarding the criminal offence element of this section, many of the Senators who spoke, and indeed the SIMI representatives I met were of the opinion that while the implied condition in subsection (2) was a welcome innovation the exposure of motor dealers to the risk of criminal prosecution for failure to issue a correct roadworthiness certificate could not be justified.  I should say that this Bill is unashamedly designed to provide the maxium protection for consumers. However, I do not feel that their interests will be protected by creating a criminal offence in this instance. Therefore, I have been convinced of the justice of the arguments of the Senators and of the representatives of the industry and on Committee Stage I will be introducing an amendment removing the criminal element.</P>
    <P>Senator Molony felt it was not appropriate to have any criminal offences included in a Bill of this nature.  While I agree that the main thrust of the Bill is in the area of civil law, I would maintain that we are concerned in a wider context with protecting ordinary people and their rights.  Section 11, for example, provides among other things that any person in the course of business who puts up a notice to the effect that the implied rights being given in Part II do not apply will be committing an offence.  I am not suggesting that retailers would try to &ldquo;con&rdquo; the public in this way into believing that they had no rights, but I am satisfied that nevertheless there should be a deterrent in the form of criminal sanctions.</P>
    <P>Senator McGuinness raised the question of the Director of Consumer Affairs and the staff and financial resources available to him.  At the outset I should say that I am conscious of and respect the director's independence in carrying out his functions.  I am, of course, far from satisfied that he has the staff necessary to carry out these functions as he would wish.  I have already had discussions <Col N="1105" /> with the director and have taken action to remove his staffing problem, which I hope will be sorted out in the very near future.</P>
    <P>Senator Lanigan while referring to section 13 like many other Senators, mentioned the cost-effectiveness of consumer legislation, the fact that certain interests in other countries are beginning to question whether the protection the consumer is getting is worth its cost.  I would suggest that this argument is not completely relevant to this country since we all would admit that consumer legislation here has not extended to areas of protection reached elsewhere and that we would have much farther to go before it would be legitimate to question the cost element.  In any event, in essence what we are doing in this Bill is providing the consumer with a right to expect, and get, a certain level of satisfaction from the goods and services he buys or are supplied to him.</P>
    <P>Senator Markey questioned whether the cost of implementing the legislation would push up consumer prices.  This may well happen to an extent; we do not know.  I feel that consumers are entitled to expect satisfaction from the goods and services they buy.  I feel that the National Prices Commission would hesitate to approve price increases allegedly applied for as a result of this Bill.</P>
    <P>Many specific points also were raised by various speakers and I shall try to deal with these.  For example, several Senators saw a problem in the definition of &ldquo;consumer&rdquo; contained in section 3. Senator FitzGerald made quite a long and very helpful contribution on this point.  My approach here is that, in simple terms, a consumer is a private citizen buying a product from a business seller for his own private use and consumption. The Senators who spoke on this question had the same general approach. I do take the point, however, that the definition in the Bill might pose certain problems.  I propose, before Committee Stage, to see if anything can be done to improve and tighten it up.</P>
    <P>Senators FitzGerald and Lambert, <Col N="1106" /> speaking about sections 15 to 19 dealing with guarantees, suggested that a retailer should not be able to exempt himself from liability under a guarantee if he is also the importer of the goods involved. My officials have been discussing this and related issues on guarantees with the Confederation of Irish Industry and with our own legal advisers.  Arising from these discussions we will be looking at the provisions relating to guarantees on the basis that they may need to be tidied up to a certain extent.  No legislation we introduce should give an unfair advantage to the importer rather than our home industry.  Anything I can do to tighten up the situation will be done to give equal, if not greater, protection to our home manufacturers.</P>
    <P>Senator FitzGerald also maintained that it would be unfair to the business community if the provisions of the Bill were to take effect immediately on signature by the President.  I agree that, as the Senator suggested, a breathing space should be afforded all those in the business of selling to enable them to revise their documentation and so on.  Indeed, such a move would be beneficial to buyers and sellers alike as it would cut down potential confusion and allow both sides of trade to familiarise themselves with what is in the Bill.  Accordingly I shall introduce an amendment on Committee Stage providing that the Bill will not come into effect until three months after its signature by the President.</P>
    <P>A number of Senators raised the issue of informal courts for dealing with small claims.  Although the Department are currently examining this area no firm decisions have been taken.  Nonetheless it is crucial to my legislative programme aimed at improving the position of the consumer that quick, effective and inexpensive redress be available to aggrieved consumers.  Indeed, the NCAC, when they reported on the question of small claims, said that unless justice is truly accessible consumer law will remain in the realms of pure theory.  I find no reason to disagree with this view. Nevertheless, it is an extremely complex issue and this Bill is not the most suitable <Col N="1107" /> instrument for dealing with informal redress procedures.</P>
    <P>Senator FitzGerald wondered whether section 33 of the Bill would make the hire purchase company liable for the supply of spare parts under section 12 and for guarantees under sections 15 to 19.  The effect of section 33 is to make the dealer liable in such circumstances since it refers to the person by whom the &ldquo;antecedent negotiations&rdquo; were conducted. In fact the dealer is the party intended to be covered by the expression &ldquo;antecedent negotiator&rdquo;.  The hire purchase company would not, therefore, be liable in such cases.</P>
    <P>Senator FitzGerald also suggested that the Bill should contain a provision to the effect that a contract which is in breach of the Consumer Information Act, 1978, will be void.  However, the Consumer Information Act contains an exactly contrary provision.  Section 25 of that Act provides that a contract for the supply of any goods or services shall not be void or unenforceable by reason only of a contravention of any provision of the Act.  The purpose of this provision is to ensure that a seller or supplier, when pressed to enter into a contract, could not evade or avoid doing so merely by showing that he had breached a provision of the Act.  It is intended that, notwithstanding this, the contract should on such grounds remain unaffected.  A purchaser injured, or at a loss, as a result of falsely described goods, has, of course, an action for damages.  Further, if he could show that misdescription affected the essence of the contract, he might succeed in having it set aside.  But the mere fact of misdescription does not in itself invalidate the contract.</P>
    <P>Senator Robinson, referring to section 14, made a point.  Section 14 does not apply to hire-purchase transactions.  It applies where a finance house cooperates with a seller in providing the cash necessary for the purchase of the product.  In such cases the finance house does more than merely providing the cash.  It encourages the consumer to make the particular purchase.  The buyer <Col N="1108" /> might not have been in a position to buy the goods but for the availability of the finance house facility.  Therefore it is fair that the finance house should bear a certain amount of liability for the goods bought.</P>
    <P>Senator Cranitch asked what is the position in regard to section 12.  Section 12 provides merely that, if a seller says he will carry spare parts for a certain period, he will be obliged to do so.  It does not set out to force all sellers to carry spare parts for everything they sell. In my view such a provision would not be wise commercially or economically. What we have done is to introduce a compromise in this section.</P>
    <P>Senator Lambert questioned whether the Bill protected consumers against misleading journalistic matter.  The Bill does not attempt to control journalistic comment, which of its nature would be an attempt to interfere with the freedom of expression. I have no desire or intention in this Bill or in any other Bill I will introduce to become involved in that sphere.  We, as a Government, have no desire to interfere with freedom of expression. The Bill deals with contractual rights and matters immediately relating thereto.</P>
    <P>Senator Lambert in the course of his contribution told us of the unfortunate incidents with regard to his car over the past couple of weeks, when it was stolen on two occasions.  I extend my sympathy to him in that regard.  My interpretation of the position is, and I am advised, that if there is a contract of service there can be no exclusion.  Therefore, the authorities of the car park mentioned would be liable in the case outlined by Senator Lambert.</P>
    <P>Senator Harte described the NCAC as having no teeth and can they be given more powers.  The NCAC are an advisory body representative of trade, consumer and a general interest.  Their primary function is to advice the Minister for Industry, Commerce and Tourism on legislation in the consumer field and on EEC proposals in that area.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1109" /> A number of other points were made by various Senators.  They will excuse me if I do not reply to each and every one of them at this stage but I will deal with them all on Committee Stage. When I mentioned the Committee Stage, there was an argument advanced by a number of Senators for a special or select committee.  I have indicated my intention to introduce amendments which will meet some of the main objections the Senators have expressed in this Second Stage debate, in particular the most contentious element with regard to section 13 which I feel would have taken most of the time on Committee Stage and will still take some considerable time when we get to it.  However, in view of the fact that I have come forward with the agreement to alter this contentious section and also the other points that I have indicated and my willingness to include amendments in Committee Stage in my own name, I feel that the Committee Stage could proceed in the normal way through the House.</P>
    <P>One thing that I would like to mention on this Stage of the Bill is that Senator Harte, amongst other Senators, mentioned the fact that he hopes that this Bill will not be the end of the legislative road for consumers.  I would like to assure this House that it is not the end of the road. Indeed that is one of the main reasons why we changed the Title of this Bill from the Consumer Protection Bill to the Sale of Goods and Supply of Services Bill in case anybody might think that when we put this Bill through we were going to put consumer legislation on the shelf for the next 90 years, as it had been for the previous period.  Besides this fact, the second EEC consumer action programme is coming forward and this contains all sorts of proposals which when sorted out will give increased protection to consumers in such areas as health, safety, education and information. So, by no means have we reached the end of the road in consumer protection legislation.  I see this as an on-going situation in the years ahead.</P>
    <P>Finally, I would like once again to thank the Members of the Seanad for the <Col N="1110" /> warm welcome that they gave to this Bill.  I look forward to a constructive Committee Stage debate.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Mr. R. Burke Mr. R. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>About three weeks at a minimum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask what does &ldquo;a minimum&rdquo; mean?  Not before?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Mr. R. Burke Mr. R. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Not before.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 12 March 1980.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Seventh Report of" RHead="Committee of Selection">
    <Title>Seventh Report of Committee of Selection.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>
      </P>
      <P>The Committee of Selection reports that it has nominated Senator Pierce Butler to serve on the Committee on Procedure and Privileges to fill the vacancy occasioned by the election to Dáil Éireann of Senator Liam Burke.</P>
      <P>I move: That the Report be laid before the Seanad.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Road Development Plan:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Road Development Plan: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann welcomes the &ldquo;Road Development Plan for the 1980s&rdquo; prepared by the Minister for the Environment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Before I go on to the motion it gives me great pleasure to welcome the Minister to the Seanad for the first time during this period.  I am sure he has been here on other occasions but this is the first since his appointment as Minister of State.  I wish him well and many, many years of success in his Department.  I have no doubt he has the capabilities and the background in local authority administration to give us the right leadership in that Department, together <Col N="1111" /> with his Minister and the other Minister of State, Deputy Connolly.</P>
    <P>Let me say at the very outset that this, I suppose, is a history-making motion.  It is the first time, I believe, over a number of decades&mdash;I think the last one was in 1926 or 1927&mdash;when any Department or Minister prepared a programme on a ten-year basis.  I think it was prepared on the previous occasion as a result of the 1916-1922 period to try to update bridges and roads damaged during that period.  I think the Minister must be complimented for his foresight in making a plan available to the Government and to the nation that gives, first of all, projections of works to be carried out in that decade and the financial backing that is necessary to carry them out.  That projection has been clearly spelt out in the plan and indeed I am grateful to have the opportunity of moving this unique and history-making motion in the Seanad today.</P>
    <P>The growth rate of traffic over the last number of years no doubt was responsible for bringing such a plan before us here&mdash;the ever increasing number of heavy and articulated commercial trucks that have increased so much in number over the years plus the great number of motor cars and other traffic on our roads now that we did not see in the thirties and the forties.  We also have the EEC haulage.  Our roads are now used by European hauliers who have to carry heavy payloads and high tonnage so that it is necessary to update our roads and at least give our national primary network two-laned roads with hard shoulders in order to carry this traffic which we have seen travelling up and down the country over the last few years.  Our roads were not constructed for the type of tonnage that they have to carry today.  A great input of capital is necessary to maintain the existing roads.  In my view the first priority is to maintain our existing standards at the highest levels.  The projections in the plan for further development must be realised so that this type of traffic can move easily and speedily through <Col N="1112" /> our country as through any EEC member country.</P>
    <P>I want to refer specifically to the by-passes. This is of great importance.  They should come into operation right away because every provincial town today has the problems of trying to get articulated trucks through the narrow streets.  It is necessary that this type of traffic be diverted as soon as possible because it is creating great chaos in those provincial towns and also for the truck operators.  It is important for them to get to their destinations as fast as possible.  When I speak of by-passes, I see in the plan that there are some towns where it is not indicated that there will be by-passes in the sketches proposed for this decade, the eighties.  I suggest to the Minister that pedestrian crossings, overhead crossings, or vehicular tunnel crossings such as that in Maynooth would be used in towns where we are unable geographically to provide a suitable bypass otherwise.  I suggest that recognition be given to pedestrian overhead passes and vehicular or underground passes to take the normal local vehicular traffic within the provincial towns where by-passes are not indicated in the plan.</P>
    <P>People forget that as a result of road widening farmers along the route often have their farms split in two.  I can envisage that the day is fast coming when livestock will no longer be safe travelling on foot on the roads and I would suggest that the Department officials look into the possibility of providing underground livestock passes from one part of a farm to another.  This does not create a big problem apart from drainage; you can do it quite easily in the same way as you construct culverts.</P>
    <P>There is the problem today where a farmer, his wife and his kids have to police their cows from their milking parlours across to their pastures because of the ever-increasing traffic.  That is one point I would like the Minister to consider.</P>
    <P>I am very conscious of the value of the non-skid surfaces.  That is a matter of first concern.  Many people have lost <Col N="1113" /> their lives on a slippery surface as a result of the wrong type or size of chips being used, often with too much tarmac mixture through the chips.  I would like to see the elimination of these black surfaces. This would also give greater vision at night and a better background to lights.  We have one of these black stretches leaving Limerick on to Shannon. It is a deadly surface because vision there is almost nil.  That should be eliminated.  The &ldquo;black spot&rdquo; signs are only put up by the county council for one purpose&mdash;to safeguard them against damages and insurance: it is an insurance regulation to put up a &ldquo;black spot&rdquo; sign where many accidents happen throughout the different counties.  I should like to see these &ldquo;black spot&rdquo; signs removed immediately and the necessary work of realignment and surfacing taking place in that particular area so that these signs could be removed and further accidents would not take place.  Putting up a &ldquo;black spot&rdquo; sign does not necessarily mean that you are going to keep people safe because it does not always result in reduced speed and for that reason you have deaths continuing to take place.</P>
    <P>I would also like to see proper definition of crossings, whether by roundabouts or white lines.  Tourists or people from Europe and the States find no indication as to who should stop.  I would like to see more definition on major crossings whether it be a roundabout or whatever other means.  This is very important, as is sign posting.  It is all right for people who know the country well and can get around, but for our visitors the sign-posting programme should be accelerated as fast as possible.</P>
    <P>Lay-bys properly constructed on main roads are a necessity for the heavy articulated trucks we have today.  Only out at Enfield do I see a lay-by with proper catering facilities provided&mdash;and, indeed, it took an Englishman to find out that there was a living to be made by setting up a catering unit at a properly defined lay-by.  Anybody who passes along that route to Enfield will identify what I am talking about.  It is a patch lay-by where <Col N="1114" /> the heavy vehicular traffic can pull in at times when they may not be able to pull in at hotels or restaurants in towns. These lay-bys should be provided and there should be some incentive for the provision of catering facilities.</P>
    <P>I welcome especially the introduction of the national primary route from Dublin to Kinnegad.  That takes most of the western, midland, north western Galway traffic to the west.  You can leave the west and be held up for an hour-and-a-half coming from Kinnegad into the centre of the city here in Dublin. I am glad that is outlined in the national primary plan as a dual-carriageway.  I welcome also the proposed routes from Naas to Portlaoise, Limerick to Ennis, Collooney to Sligo, Mallow to Cork, and various other routes.  I am delighted that they are defined in the plan here for the eighties and I would like the development to be tackled right away.</P>
    <P>From the tourist point of view the hedges along our main roads, tourist roads and country roads are a disgrace, choked with briars and all types of weeds, and I would welcome an arrangement whereby, by agreement with the farming community, by a grant from the Department of the Environment or, failing either, a compulsory order would be made by the Minister to ensure that no hedge reaches more than four feet high along our main and national primary, secondary or regional roads.  We are lacking in that respect and much good work could be done in ventilating our roads by the removal of these hedges. This would give better visibility for the lovely countryside that we have here in Ireland, especially from the tourist point of view.  Bridges are hard to negotiate with these large vehicles and I would hope that any of the old sores we have on our roads, bridges that have been there since the thirties and which are now outdated, would be immediately dealt with when we are tackling this problem in the programme outlined here.</P>
    <P>I suppose it would not be right for me as a Mayoman to let this occasion pass without mentioning first of all the problem we have down in Mayo.  The <Col N="1115" /> main urgency is the acquisition of land, the realignment and improvement of our national routes.  Indeed, if you look at the road from Ballinlough border at Roscommon into Mayo you will see that the Department officials at one time decided that the Mayo people could accept a lower standard of road for their national primary and secondary than in every other county.  I still maintain that the roads in Mayo are as important as any other roads in Ireland.  We have the greatest road network in the whole of this country; we have one-eighth of the whole country's roads in national secondary. The reduction of the hard shoulder that was implemented from Ballinlough into Ballyhaunis was a reduction of standard from that of Roscommon, Sligo and Galway.  I resent that very much.  It was a decision by the Department officials on that occasion.  While traffic volumes are not as high as in Dublin, Cork and various other large centres, there are large sections or unimproved national primary roads in Mayo still to be developed.  For example, the road from the county boundary at Roscommon right through Charlestown, Swinford to Castlebar, is one of our national primary roads.  I can say here to the Minister that we have acquired land, a four-mile stretch on that particular road, and we intend to pursue that acquisition policy in order that the 28 kilometres of that national primary road will be completed within the decade of this programme that is now before us.  That road work is essential.  The road is joined at Swinford by the Ballina road which is going into the very important town of Ballina.  It is essential that work would start this year on the four miles of road for which we have land being acquired and plans designed.  I hope that a substantial grant will be made available, something over £650,000 to £750,000 for that type of work on that national primary.</P>
    <P>We have also the national primary road that runs from the Sligo border right through Charlestown, Knock and into Ballindine on the Galway side.  I <Col N="1116" /> want to compliment the Minister for the heavy injection of capital he gave to us over the last two years for the provision of the road for the centenary year at Knock.  He must be congratulated for bringing that about and enabling the access road on the national primary to Knock to be dealt with.  We hope that the deficient portions of that road will also be brought up to national standards. I am glad to say that in the light of the expected grants for the 1980s we will be able to continue that great progress in design and acquisition in respect of our national primary and secondary roads. As I said earlier, we have one-eighth of the national secondary network of roads in Mayo and that area should be dealt with and the necessary capital brought into Mayo.</P>
    <P>As regards our regional roads, by Ministerial decision a block grant was introduced some few years back.  That gave authority to each local authority to allocate from national primary and secondary a portion of whatever amount of capital they had in the block grant to whatever schemes they wished.  In Mayo we were unfortunate again because at that time, at the introduction of the block grant which was preceded by a 100 per cent grant from the Department for the taking over of sand roads for tarring, we had something around 1,500 miles of non-tarred roads in our county and we had to subsidise work to the extent of 75 per cent out of rates in order to bring up our black topping to its present state with roughly 70 per cent of sand roads tarred in the county.  I think it was unconstitutional to ask the people of Mayo to do that but because our county road programme was so far behind&mdash;as is our national primary and national secondary now&mdash;we had to dip into the rates of the county to bring about the 70 per cent tarring programme on county roads that we have at the moment.  We shall pursue that policy until we have at least 95 per cent of the roads in Mayo tarred.</P>
    <P>In order to give effect to our regional road and to our county road programme an injection of about £1 million in 1980 is necessary.  We got £618,000 last year <Col N="1117" /> but with inflation and the increased cost of tar products&mdash;the oil brings it all about&mdash;we would need that type of money in order to keep abreast of our road problem in Mayo.</P>
    <P>Prior to that block grant we had a grant known as a tourist grant.  That, of course, affects most of the coastal counties in this country and indeed some of the inland counties where they have waterways and various other tourist amenities.  That was scrubbed in transit as a result of the introduction of the block grant and while it may not have been a major contribution&mdash;I think the contribution we got in the sixties was around £55,000 in Mayo and that was when we could get some work done for £55,000&mdash;it was of great help.  That was knocked on the head and there is no such specific grant now while we have many, many counties throughout this island with great tourist potential.  I believe that the tourist board should make some moneys available for this type of purpose, identify a type of road and classify roads as real tourist roads that do not come under national primary, or secondary and some of them, not under regional classification, but which could give great access to beaches and lakes, and to shooting and fishing facilities.  A great portion of that money could be allotted to the tourist areas of the various counties.</P>
    <P>I welcome the plan, for which we have waited a long time.  I am delighted that the Minister has to Ministers of State on whom he can call in the implementation of this plan.  I know that there is a financial projection in this development which will be accelerated or retarded according to the financial climatic conditions of every year in that decade.  There is no reason to believe that it may not be pursued because of financial difficulties, but there is also no reason to believe that it will be completed if we get the necessary moneys.</P>
    <P>Approaches for long-term loans should be made and, I am sure, will be made to the World Bank to put this programme into operation.  If our internal financial commitments are to be curtailed <Col N="1118" /> we should go ahead with a major loan for this type of work because inflation will beat you every year you delay in implementing these proposals.  Until we get our own oil offshore and our own tar at a much reduced price, it will be necessary to get a major loan from the World Bank for this necessary type of development.  I have no doubt that with the energy of the three Ministers behind it it will be completed within the ten years.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. Kiely Mr. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AndyOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with Senator O'Toole in extending a welcome to the new Minister and in wishing him success in his term of office.</P>
      <P>It is a good thing to have this motion on the Order Paper, to give Members an opportunity of discussing the road programme for the eighties; it has been on the Order Paper for some time.  When it was left for so long it is a pity that the discussion was not left over for another week or so, when we would know the position as regards provision for road development in the budget.  The Book of Estimates arrived only this morning.  We did not have time to look into it and see what moneys are being allocated for road development.  It is obvious, from what Senator O'Toole said, that he has a very wide knowledge of the road problem, coming, no doubt, from his long experience as a member of a local authority.  He made a great number of very valid points.  I join with him in expressing the hope that what he wants to see done will be done in the reasonable future, not just in the part of the country to which he specifically referred, but in other parts, including my own.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It should be said at the outset that this is a well-prepared booklet which gives members of local authorities and others very valuable information as to how the Road Fund is financed, what the powers of local authorities are and the road design for the next ten years.  In so far as it does all that, it is a very valuable document and I am glad to have it.  I have some reservations about the plan, as <Col N="1119" /> drawn up, for road development in my own part of the country but I shall deal with that at a later stage.</P>
    <P>The hopes expressed in this booklet and the statements of policy in the target years of 1983&mdash;4&mdash;5, on up to 1989, for the finalisation of some of these schemes are very laudable, but we must examine the policy against the background of the restriction being placed on local authorities.  Local authorities are confined, by order of the Minister, to an expenditure not greater than 10 per cent more than that incurred last year.  I am a member of Cavan County Council and our experience is that the amount of money allocated to our council last year was inadequate for the work that had to be done.  An increase of 10 per cent on a sum that was inadequate last year is even more inadequate this year, because of the increases in wages and in the cost of road materials.</P>
    <P>There is a very substantial wage increase for road workers from 1 January 1979 to what it will be by the end of the current year.  If my figures are correct, road workers' wages at 1 January 1979 were about £48 or £49, something under £50.  Because of increases in the national understanding and so on, I understand that the wages by the end of this year will be in the region of £70; that is a very substantial increase.  I do not begrudge it to that section of the community, but it is a very substantial increase and when we take that into account how will a county council who are restricted to an increase of 10 per cent on last year's expenditure be able to carry out anything like the same amount of work which was done last year and which in many cases was inadequate and did not meet the needs of the county?</P>
    <P>If we compare the prices tendered for the supply of those materials for this year with those prices tendered 12 months ago, there is a very substantial increase in the cost of these road materials, very much in excess of 10 per cent.  A factual appraisal of the situation confronting local authorities shows that <Col N="1120" /> if the present restriction of a 10 per cent increase is enforced throughout the year these authorities will not be in a position to maintain roads to the desired standard.</P>
    <P>At present, there is a very serious deterioration in our roads.  It is a matter of grave concern to public authorities, engineers and county managers all over the country.  This deterioration is due to a number of factors.  It is due to inadequate supplies of money over the past few years and, indeed, further back if one examines it deeply; it is due to an increase in traffic, especially to a very great increase in heavy vehicles.  The actual weight of some of the vehicles using our roads today is far beyond what the roads were ever intended to carry.  It is the opinion of engineers involved in road maintenance that expenditure on some roads in an effort to maintain them is little better than a stop-gap policy; the foundation structure of these roads is not adequate for the heavy traffic they must carry.  The maintenance work is less than effective; it cracks, rain gets into it, frost further interferes and we are not getting good value for money spent.</P>
    <P>In my opinion, based on a good number of years' experience as a county councillor, a lot of the maintenance work being done is not effective for the simple reason that the engineers are not able to get down and tackle the major problem of building roads suitable for the volume and weight of traffic which they have to carry.  I realise that that would entail colossal expenditure but there are areas where the building and maintenance of roads is a major problem because of the nature of the soil and because of the high road mileage in some counties as compared with others, due to the contour of lakes and bogs and so on.  These areas would need very great injections of capital to build up the roads properly and should get larger grants through the EEC fund.</P>
    <P>Very special attention should be paid to our areas without a rail service&mdash;almost all of County Cavan is without rail service.  That applies also, to a degree, to Leitrim and to an area of <Col N="1121" /> Monaghan.  Because these areas are without a proper road service or structure and have no rail service, they need extra expenditure on road building.  On page 21 of <i>Road Development Plan for the 1980s</i> it is stated that 10 per cent of our road network carries 60 per cent of the traffic.  That is a fact which I do not dispute, but it is true that other areas are restricted in development because of inadequate road structure.  We might have a greater development of industry and a greater spread of population in parts that are not now developing because the road structure is not there.  I would not be unduly influenced by that figure of 10 per cent of the network carrying 60 per cent of the traffic.</P>
    <P>I draw attention to the map on page 20 of this booklet.  My point is better illustrated by reference to map No. 1 on page 12, where you have a big blank area stretching from road N55 over to N16 and N4.  That is the area that covers a part of west Cavan, the whole of County Leitrim and a large part of County Sligo.  According to these maps, there is no indication of the building of roads in that area and unless there is an intention to service that area with a helicopter fleet, then it is obvious that that area will be neglected.  The policy of restricting the development or the maintenance of county roads owing to the shortage of capital will in years to come mean that an ever increasing amount of money will have to go to road maintenance. There will be nothing for improvements, the removal of dangerous bends, blind corners, dangerous hillocks on roadways that restrict road vision and the erection of minor bridges.  This policy of road cuts will lead on to road ruts.  It is an unwise policy and will leave the country in a greater difficulty with regard to providing an adéquate road structure in the times immediately ahead.</P>
    <P>Everybody knows that the traffic in Dublin city is a cause of great frustration and annoyance to people.  It will have to be firmly tackled in the immediate future.  It is possible that the suggestion made by Senator O'Toole with regard to underground tunnels for pedestrian traffic <Col N="1122" /> in different parts of the country could certainly be applied with great benefit to Dublin.  I am sorry that in all these projections there is no mention of development of the road from Clonee to Dublin. That is the section of the main arterial road from Dublin to Enniskillen which serves County Cavan, part of Monaghan, part of Leitrim and Fermanagh which is, unforturately, outside our jurisdiction for the time being.  While it is possible to travel from Cavan to Clonee at a moderate speed in one-and-a-half hours or less, it often takes most of an hour to get into the city centre.  I can see no indication of any plans for the improvement of that bottleneck approach to Dublin city using the road which serves our end of the country.  As long as that situation persists it will slow down or hinder the industrial development of counties which that arterial road is meant to serve.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has one minute of his time left.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AndyOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a lot to say in one minute.  I am astonished that there is no provision for an improvement of the Cavan-Granard road&mdash;a road which carries very heavy traffic, as figures on the map indicate and which is in a very bad state.  It is quite common for lorries to go off the road into the fields.  Quite recently a cattle lorry went off that road because of the breakaway in the road edging and 18 cattle were lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is another road to which I want to draw attention because of the area's potential for development.  Killeshandra is a developing industrial town in Cavan, with a great creamery and a milk powder plant.  It is on the perimeter of the most undeveloped area in west Cavan and is quite convenient to Leitrim.  The road from Cavan town to Killeshandra meanders its way and is a cause of very great difficulty to truck and lorry drivers who are constantly complaining about it.  It is a source of great disappointment to me&mdash;and it will be to the people of Cavan&mdash;to see that there is no hope of that road being improved in the immediate future.  It is not listed anywhere <Col N="1123" /> that I can see in the programme, right up to 1989.</P>
    <P>I could, if I had the time, draw attention to the need for developing the port of Greenore and providing proper adequate road approaches to it to serve that north-east corner of the country; that is a suggestion that was made by the North-Eastern Regional Development Organisation.  I cannot see anything in this book that would indicate that it will be tackled in the immediate future or indeed in the present decade.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a good road to finish on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AndyOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>Have I any time left?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You have stolen a minute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AndyOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a reference somewhere in this book which says that the local authority have some function with regard to the development of tourist amenities and so on.</P>
      <P>There is great potential for tourist development in the coarse fishing areas of Monaghan, Cavan, Leitrim, part of Roscommon, part of Meath, Westmeath and Longford; it is the greatest coarse fishing area in Europe.  The potential is not being realised because of inadequate approach roads to the places of interest to thousands of fishermen who come across here from Britain and Europe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a good road to finish on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardConroy" hpid="Professor Conroy Professor Conroy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Conroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I join in the welcome for the Minister of State, and in praise of the Minister for the Environment for his foresight and enterprise in putting forward this plan, which is a very necessary and very useful initiative.  I thank Senators O'Toole and Kiely for introducing this motion and giving us a chance to talk about a very important subject, particularly in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In general, we take roads for granted. We assume that they will be there, provided for us, will be adequate for all <Col N="1124" /> our needs.  We, perhaps, do not tend to assume this in regard to the railways, yet, in a sense, they are a very important part of our infrastructure.  Roads are particularly important to Ireland because, as this booklet points out, we carry a higher percentage, both of passenger traffic and of freight traffic, than any other country in Europe.  We do not fully appreciate the enormous use made of roads in this country, the extent to which we are dependent on them.  We are used to thinking in terms of the motorways in Britain, the autobahns in Germany and so on and do not really realise that our roads play a bigger role than in those other countries.  At the same time, we have an enormous land area in relation to our very small population; thus we have a very considerable mileage of roads to try to provide. Senator O'Toole has pointed to some of the problems which arise in Mayo and these are seen all over the country.  We are faced with an enormous expenditure, something in the region of nearly £100 million in 1978&mdash;an expenditure which, as Senator O'Toole has pointed out, is tending to escalate.  Yet it is a very essential burden that we must try to carry if we want to continue developing our industries; if we want to continue attracting industry, if we want to have a country that is pleasant to live in as well as attracting this industry, then, difficult and financially painful though we may find it, we must give very considerable priority to our roads infrastructure.</P>
    <P>We do not fully appreciate the enormous increase in traffic that has taken place over a few years; some of the figures are given here for it.  We had 60,-000 private cars in 1948; we have over 640,000 private cars now.  There are similar increases in goods vehicles and in all other road vehicles.</P>
    <P>Another aspect&mdash;a very much sadder one&mdash;over which we have grown all too callous, taking it virtually for granted, is the death and casualty rate on our roads. All too often it just merits a small paragraph in the papers, perhaps a sad photograph.  All these deaths on the roads are totally unnecessary deaths.  We <Col N="1125" /> have a very considerable responsibility here to make our roads as fit as is feasible and practical.  I wholeheartedly concur with Senator O'Toole in his suggestions regarding road safety, in such matters as overhead crossings where necessary, underways, well marked pedestrian crossings and more effective road signs, in such very simple and tremendously helpful matters as having a proper camber on the roads and keeping the hedges cut low.  We are all very familiar with country roads with all sorts of zig-zag bends on them.  They would be perfectly safe if only the hedges were cut, yet how often are there head-on collisions, or pedestrians struck at night time on this sort of road&mdash;all unnecessary?</P>
    <P>When we talk about modernised roads we think in terms of the autobahns and motorways, and, undoubtedly, we have some need in this country for some such routes, perhaps not as much as elsewhere because their population is so spread out, but this is something we must gradually aim towards.  Otherwise, we are going to be very much left behind in relation to our road capacity and performance as compared with those of the other EEC countries.  Inevitably, the vehicles developed for these countries take for granted that such types of roads will exist and if we do not have something similar&mdash;quite apart from the many other advantages and occasionally, indeed, disadvantages of such roads&mdash;we shall find that our non-motorway highways will crumble under the weight of juggernaut type vehicles and other road vehicles which are primarily designed for very heavy surfaced autobahn-type motorways.</P>
    <P>I should like particularly to address myself to the problems of our suburban roads.  We have, in the Dublin area alone, almost one million people.  The problems which we see in Dublin are duplicated elsewhere in Cork, Limerick and other urban areas.  We are a much more urbanised society than we were. We have tended, unfortunately, to neglect our urban roads.  We have already mentioned the juggernauts.  For those of us who have experienced, as I <Col N="1126" /> have in my own area, these massive juggernauts coming across from Dun Laoghaire, cutting across through suburban roads that are really only designed for very light passenger vehicle traffic, they are terrifying, dangerous and enormously expensive and destructive.  This is a problem we really must look at much more intensely than we have already.  Additionally, we are still basically geared in Dublin to the idea of the old horse traffic.  There is virtual total congestion, through goods vehicles alone, if you try to travel up and down towards the Dublin docks.  This is something we must do something about.</P>
    <P>There are also the actual problems of commuter traffic.  I do not think that we have faced up to what we are going to do in relation to cars and buses.  It is very easy to say, &ldquo;We will ban the private car from the roads&rdquo;.  If you are living in many suburban areas of Dublin, you would find it extremely difficult, indeed, to get to your work in any sort of reasonable time if private cars were banned from the roads.  Additionally, very many families, for all sorts of very good reasons depend on their cars for their immediate transport.  This is something we must take into consideration and perhaps we should consider making the centre of Dublin a non-vehicular area, unless perhaps for buses, but there is no way in which we can simply say that we will ban passenger cars.  It is not on; it is foolish to even consider it, other than in a very limited sense.  What we must try to do is to accommodate to this reality of life that most people today, for good reasons, are going to travel in their private cars, encourage them to do so and provide the roads that will enable them to do so, whilst, at the same time, keeping the centre of the city free and having adequate roadways so that the centre of the city can be by-passed where necessary, both by goods traffic and by passenger vehicles.  We must also consider this question of safety which, alas, too often we neglect.</P>
    <P>I am delighted to see that in the Dublin area, there are listed on Table 1, page 37, no fewer than 22 major developments. <Col N="1127" /> I am not happy that they are enough.  A lot more will be needed, but at least they are listed and there is some form of a coherent approach and plan now towards Dublin traffic.  In my own area I notice particularly the Templeogue, Tallaght, south-west ring routes, the Belgard Road and my own road, Grange Road.</P>
    <P>Let us not ignore the fact that building new roads in suburban and urban areas brings its own problems.  I am trying to balance the very necessary traffic needs we have just been looking at with the considerable social, financial and environmental complications of attempting to build any kind of urban motorways. There are a lot of different aspects that will have to be balanced.  If I had a criticism of this road development plan it would be that it does not take fully into account the difficulties involved and also it is looking at road development in isolation.  It has to be considered in the context of railways as well.  One cannot just take one and ignore the other.  It is an essential part of our infrastructure.  In speaking about regional development aids some people mentioned EEC funding.  This is an area where we have an unanswerable case with the EEC for funding and it is one which we must press very strongly.  I welcome and support the motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>I notice that the &ldquo;Road Development Plan for the 1980s&rdquo; was published last May.  I wonder to what extent it would be different if the report was being formulated at present in the wake of the very bad road conditions we have all experienced during the winter months.  The road plan is quite informative, and helpful in regard to certain statistics which it brings out.  It is not saying anything which we did not already know when it points out certain figures, such as that the number of passenger cars have gone up tenfold in the past 30 years, the number of goods vehicles have trebled in the same 30 years and that the position has been worsened by the very large number of large <Col N="1128" /> articulated trucks which have come on the roads.</P>
      <P>It refers to the work done by An Foras Forbartha in the early seventies in the compilation of some reports on our road network position.  Foras Forbartha, at that time, said that one-third of national primary routes and one-quarter of national secondary routes&mdash;these are the major primary roads in the country&mdash;were below a satisfactory standard. The road plan states that there has been considerable deterioration in the position since then.  That we can all vouch for.</P>
      <P>Consideration of this motion is particularly relevant in the context of the publication of the public services figures for 1980.  If I could see any ray of sunlight or hope in those figures that the position and condition of our road network would be considerably improved in the next 12 months I would say so.  As regards an increase in money terms of 9 or 10 per cent, after taking into consideration inflation rates of 16 or 17 per cent, and the ever-increasing cost of raw materials used in the road network and so on, we see an actual deterioration in real money terms for 1980 projected.  This means that we cannot see the inception of the considerable road improvement works which were scheduled in this road plan.  We would have expected some start to be made on a number of the major road improvements projected in the plan.  I notice from table 4 that a number of road improvements on national primary routes were projected to start in 1980.  The Minister should take advantage of this debate to give an indication of whether this work is going to start in 1980 or not. There is no point in people compiling road development plans, and putting a lot of work into them and proposing certain time schedules for what are very necessary works if those time schedules are not going to be met.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We all know that the Road Fund was done away with in 1978.  With hindsight, we wonder whether that was wise or not. We know there were abuses and that there were various raids on that Road Fund over past decades.  That is not to <Col N="1129" /> say that those raids could have been prevented.  We might well have to consider starting a Road Fund which will be devoted solely to road improvements.</P>
    <P>The most outstanding aspect of deterioration of our road network over the past winter has been the difference in the standards that have resulted from that deterioration from county to county.  The Department should have uniformity in the specifications which they insist on every local authority conforming to in their road maintenance and road improvements.  Some county roads have deteriorated at a much quicker and worsening rate than other county roads. To pass from one county to a neighbouring county can be a rather hazardous experience at present.</P>
    <P>The manner of the execution of road works has always rested with the local authority.  They were the sole determining authority as regards the way they would carry out the work, the standard of the work and the extent to which they wanted to put materials into a job.  The employment potential of the project was a factor in their final decision.  It is high time for the Department to insist on a uniformity of road work specifications.</P>
    <P>The road plan refers to the energy situation and to the consideration it may play in determining whether we should go ahead with road improvements to our networks as envisaged in the plan.  At the same time it does not hesitate in stating on page 26:</P>
    <P>Any uncertainties there may be about the future of energy supply would not in themselves provide sufficient justification for holding in further abeyance a roads programme which is geared to a considerable extent towards removing existing deficiencies.</P>
    <P>In other words, our present system of road network is so bad that no consideration should be allowed to interfere with bringing it up to what is necessary as a modern standard.</P>
    <P>The plan does not provide for any motorway system and in this, of all the EEC countries, we are unique.  In the light of the capital funding figures for <Col N="1130" /> 1980 the possibility of a motorway system will be put further into the future.</P>
    <P>There is always need for extensive and long-term advance preparation for any road network improvement because it takes so long to buy land and design the various schemes necessary.  It is necessary, therefore, that we should have a very definite programme laid out in advance. We cannot operate, if we want to have a satisfactory road network system, with a stop-go system.  It is important from the funding requirement that there should be a continuing, uniform level of funds pumped into improving our road network.</P>
    <P>In table 5 of the plan a figure in the region of £57 million is estimated as being necessary for road improvements in 1980.  In the light of the capital figures presented today we are very far away from achieving that kind of investment by the State.  The Minister should tell us whether the plan to start some of the road network improvements in 1980 and continue each year up to 1985 will be adhered to by the Government.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasWhitaker" hpid="Dr. Whitaker Dr. Whitaker">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Whitaker</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to thank the Minister and the Department for this useful publication.  The extent and the speed with which the Road Development Plan can be carried out is, of course, unpredictable. It will depend essentially on the success of succeeding Governments in strengthening our public finances.  I have no doubt that our borrowing potential should be applied far more to the improvement of roads and telecommunications and far less to financing current budget deficits.  In that way we would be ensuring that our scarce borrowing potential is devoted to the best purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wish to make three points, in particular, about this subject.  The first concerns responsibility for roads policy.  As this booklet explains, at present the Minister for the Environment is the Minister of Government in whom is vested responsibility for national policy, legislation and financial arrangements in relation to roads and road traffic.  Recently the Taoiseach announced&mdash;and I applaud the decision&mdash;his intention to set <Col N="1131" /> up a Department of Transport and Communications. I suggest that national policy, at least in relation to national routes, should be vested in that Department. In that way a coherent and comprehensive view could be taken of transport needs and of how best roads, railways, airways and sea transport could complement each other to the national advantage.  This suggestion does not in any way mean that the execution of Government policy in relation to all roads should not continue to be carried out by local authorities.</P>
    <P>The second point I want to make concerns the urgent need for easier exit from and access to Dublin&mdash;for new radial routes particularly to the west, the north-west and the north.  This is extremely important for the development of the midlands and the remoter parts of the west and north-west.  Not only would expenditure for this purpose be an appropriate use of EEC regional and investment funds but of our own national funds.  I recognise it might be difficult to persuade everyone in the west to agree on the concentration of expenditure on road improvements in the vicinity of Dublin, but I have no doubt that, together with the improvement of telephone communications, the improvement of access to and exit from Dublin would do a tremendous amount for the economic and social development of the west.</P>
    <P>My third point concerns maintenance. This document mentions on page 17 that deficiencies in the road system have arisen through insufficient maintenance to meet the wear caused by weather and traffic.  It goes on to say that the losses caused by road deficiencies may be measured in terms of time-waste, wear and tear of vehicles, fuel consumption and road accidents.  Recent journeying to Galway, and through Clare, Kerry, Cork and Limerick has convinced me that there is an appalling neglect of maintenance everywhere, especially in towns and indeed in cities as well.  One sees deepening and widening holes and ruts.  We seem to have forgotten that a <Col N="1132" /> stitch in time saves nine.  Have we become so used to lavish public expenditure that we interpose nothing whatever between total neglect and the expensive perfectionism of the motorway?</P>
    <P>One thing we should concentrate on, particularly in this time of financial stringency, is the timely repair and maintenance of roads.  All local authorities should have small flying squads of what I would call &ldquo;make do and mend men&rdquo; to fill the holes and smoothen the ruts as they arise, thus safeguarding lives and saving a lot of damage to vehicles and expenditure of unnecessary money and time.  That is something I would urge as being urgent.  I should like to join Senator O'Toole in his recommendation that there should be compulsory lopping of hedges to a certain maximum height, particularly in beautiful counties like Mayo.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKilbride" hpid="Mr. Kilbride Mr. Kilbride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kilbride</NameTxt>
      <P>Much of what I should like to say has already been said by Senators O'Brien, O'Toole and Whitaker.  I see the matter of road structure and maintenance at present in the context of the use of roads for commercial purposes by huge juggernaut vehicles that come in here with 25 and 30 tonne loads and go out with similar loads.  These vehicles cross what we termed as adequate main roads in the past. They were never built for this kind of load.  The surfacing and maintenance applied by county council workmen on the roads is very much a lost exercise, and an expensive loss at that.  The material which is put on to carpet or blanket the road as a topping is collapsing.  Damage is done and the roadway gets lower, out of alignment and into a very bad condition with high speed vehicles of the calibre I have referred to crossing them. The work is completely lost and cannot stand up even for a week to the demands made on it by these heavy vehicles.  We have a road structure which serves to bring the people into the larger towns and into Dublin from all directions.  These roads are occasionally used for the haulage of vehicle loads of 15 or 20 tons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1133" /> Senators will remember occasions when they saw 20-ton sand lorries going on very minor roads.  Some roads are of such a width that the vehicle is compelled to go on the verge and this churns up the verge side.  When a car meets another vehicle there, they invariably get stuck because they cannot get out of this ploughed-up verge.  In this weather this is a usual experience no matter which direction one travels in.  We should have an infrastructure of main roads sufficient to ensure that the materials that are put on them would last and the roads should be of such a width that vehicles could safely pass each other.  As far as local populations are concerned, there should be roads which the drivers of heavy sand lorries or ordinary trucks that would have loads of seven, eight or nine tons would know would be easy ones for them to traverse, even if they were parallel to the main road to some extent and were linked by country roads to another main road.  That kind of road should be constructed and maintained if we are to have a road structure that will enable people to have services locally.</P>
    <P>The scenic beauty of the midlands and of the Cavan-Longford border at Lough Gowna, for instance, is regarded as the Killarney of the midlands.  It is a poor commentary that from the town of Granard to Lough Gowna and across through north Longford to Aghnacliffe, which is the beauty of the area, the roads are both narrow and bendy and in a very serious condition as far as safety for the traveller is concerned.  If we set value on bringing tourists into these areas and providing accommodation for them, we should ensure easy access and safe transport, which would attract them to come back again.</P>
    <P>Longford is in the hub of Ireland. Senator O'Toole referred to the róad to Dublin going through Lanesborough and Termonbarry, into Longford and on to Edgeworthstown, Rathowen and Mullingar. That road is carrying more traffic in the midlands than any other.  It is the road that is the most dangerous one to traverse even with the best lights at night.  It has been the scene of serious accidents. <Col N="1134" /> Whatever we are going to do by way of road improvements or however acceptable this plan may be&mdash;and I welcome it&mdash;it is virtually important that more than planning is done and that schemes be implemented to whatever extent possible within the financial scope of the Government.  They should apply that sort of effort in the areas that give service to the local community, to commercial interests and to scenic areas where tourists visit and from whom we expect to draw financial gain.</P>
    <P>The road from Athlone crosses this road to Dublin at Edgeworthstown and goes on to Cavan.  Senator O'Brien referred to this.  It is a road that is carrying more traffic than it ever was intended to.  There is a bog rampart on it that makes it entirely unrealistic to try to maintain it under the very heavy juggernaut vehicle traffic that is traversing it.  It is vitally important for that reason that our council get enough finance to upgrade that road as soon as possible.  I referred to this a year ago in a debate on a roads estimate.  The upgrading of that road is of vital importance.</P>
    <P>County roads are to a great extent the charge of local authorities, and county councils this year will have the experience of minor roads being allowed to deteriorate for want of finance and attention. Provision should be made in the coming year's estimate to enable them to redeem their debts, so to speak.  People in rural Ireland would be able to have the same accommodation as their friends from accross the water have.  In the area I represent one has only to go up any bohereen or <i>cul-de-sac</i> and one will find a channel inside which the wheels of a car run and a high ridge of grass and soil that was churned in from the sides.  In the summer time two, three or four inches of grass grew and rotted down and the next year more grew.  That is a characteristic of every one of these minor roads.</P>
    <P>These are the roads that the people who contribute to industry and agriculture have to traverse.  People are crying out to the county councils to come back and resurface these roads. <Col N="1135" /> Our county engineer told us that he was not in a position to do it, that it all depends on what is provided in the rates. We are inhibited in striking more than a 10 per cent increase in what we gave for roads last year.  We are lucky that so far this year there has not been a heavy frost.  These roads will be in such a condition and will have deteriorated so far that the same kind of effort will have to be made again to bring them up to a proper condition; whereas, as Senator Whitaker said, they could have been saved by a stitch in time.  If people looked after the roads in the way that traffic load demands we would be saving money and the amount of money allocated could go a very considerable way towards keeping maintenance at a very moderate level.</P>
    <P>I do not want to have to plead for grace like Senator O'Brien, but, if the Government do not take major steps to alleviate the difficulties on the various road structures to which I have referred, they will find themselves involved in more expense and the country will lose considerably more.  I welcome the Minister to the House but I believe he is confronted with a problem of some magnitude.  When he has conquered this problem it will be a feather in his cap.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackieFahey" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Fahey) Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Fahey)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Fahey)</NameTxt>
      <P>It might be as well for me to say a few words at this stage.  I should like to thank the Senators who welcomed me to this House this evening.  Words of welcome always make me feel at ease and I lose some of my nervous tension.  I should also like to thank Senators for the constructive manner in which they have spoken on the motion.  This motion is well worthwhile.  I have no intention of endeavouring to reply to the various points made so far, but I assure Senators that I have been listening attentively to them and I have noted what they said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am delighted to have the opportunity of speaking to Senators about this plan for the eighties.  For some years past, and particularly since our accession to <Col N="1136" /> the European Community, there has been a growing awareness of the deficiencies in the country's road system and of the cost which these deficiencies impose on the agricultural, industrial, commercial and social life of the community. The country is highly dependent on the public road system for physical communication and movement.  In fact, the proportion of passenger and freight traffic carried on the road system in Ireland is higher than in any other country in Europe.  The growth in road traffic, both private and commercial, has been continuous since the end of the second world war.</P>
    <P>Against this background and in anticipation of the demands likely to be put on the road system in the decade ahead, the Government's road development plan for the eighties was prepared.  This was an ambitious undertaking, not least because of the fact that it is the first road development plan of its type since the foundation of the State.  The plan demonstrates the Government's commitment, unprecedented in its time span and format, to tackle the deficiencies in the road system in a positive and practical way.  The Government are, of course, very much aware of the problems involved in developing a ten-year programme of the kind put forward in the road development plan.  Its progress will depend very much on planning and land acquisition at local level.</P>
    <P>We believe, however, that it is essential that the strategy to be followed should be clearly spelled out, giving a firm indication of the priorities and of the Government's commitment, so that road authorities can proceed with confidence with their planning and land acquisition and the civil engineering and construction industry can gear itself to the work ahead.  The plan will provide a positive basis for action by the road authorities in the years ahead.  I am confident that they will play their full role in achieving its aims.</P>
    <P>The plan provides that priority in State investment in the eighties will be given to the more important major urban and inter-urban roads, access routes to <Col N="1137" /> the principal seaports and airports and to relief roads and internal circulation roads in Dublin, Cork, and other important commercial centres.  The plan provides for two-fold action.  First, there is a substantial programme for what are termed normal improvement works designed to bring all sections of the national primary routes and significant sections of the national secondary routes up to a specified minimum standard and will include road realignment, road-widening and the eradication of accident black spots.  Secondly, there is a special programme of major improvement projects, including dual carriageways, bridges, relief roads and by-passes in urban centres and on the principal inter-urban routes.</P>
    <P>The overall programme of work is derived from analysis of deficiencies identified in the system of national routes by studies carried out by An Foras Forbartha and from land use, transportation and traffic studies carried out in Dublin, Cork, Limerick, Waterford and other areas and also from the development plans of the local authorities and regional development organisations.  The standard of road generally envisaged is an all-purpose road but this does not preclude the adoption of motorway standard by road authorities in any instance where they may consider the higher level of service is warranted.</P>
    <P>The plan assigns particular importance to road maintenance to ensure continued benefit from previous investment in roads and the continuation of a satisfactory level of service to local communities generally.  The road development plan affords special consideration to the role of road words in the preservation and creation of employment.</P>
    <P>Expenditure on road works is a generator of widely distributed direct employment in quarrying, plant, machinery and other related industries. The greater part by far of the investment is spent on Irish labour, professional, skilled and unskilled and on material and equipment of Irish origin and manufacture. Further employment is generated as a result of expenditure of direct and <Col N="1138" /> indirect incomes which arise as a result of road works.</P>
    <P>By settling on a broad programme of achievements, rather than on a restricted list of optimum improvement projects, one of the more important objectives of the plan was to ensure that the permanent work force of the road authorities and the suppliers and contractors who served them would be protected.</P>
    <P>I do not propose on this occasion to review the major schemes envisaged in the plan.  I should like to make the point, however, that there is a danger that people looking at the plan will tend to concentrate on the major schemes which are listed and not take sufficient note of the extensive programme of other improvement works which are provided for and which will be carried out in all parts of the country.  The major improvement schemes are additional to the normal improvement programme which has already been expanded significantly in recent years.  I should like also to make it clear that the time scales indicated for the various major schemes are flexible, having regard to the availability of finance and the preparedness of road authorities to undertake or continue particular projects at a particular time.</P>
    <P>In relation to the question of finance, I am happy to be able to record that the road development plan has been accepted by the European Investment Bank as the basis for work programmes to be included in applications by the Minister for Finance for loan facilities.  In addition, a substantial programme of major improvement works selected from the plan for construction over the next three years has been accepted for grants from the European Regional Development Fund.</P>
    <P>Finally, I am satisfied that the road development plan is realistic and capable of making significant improvements in the country's transport infrastructure.  It provides a positive basis for action by the road authorities in the decade ahead and constitutes a determined initial step in the programmed development of a public road network for the eighties and beyond.</P>
    <Col N="1139" />
    <Speaker pid="MylesStaunton" hpid="Mr. Staunton Mr. Staunton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staunton</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to welcome the Minister of State to this House.  It is the first time he has been in this Chamber and I wish him well in his appointment.  The Seanad is a useful forum in which to discuss a road development plan because of the singular capacity of its Members to appreciate the problems of the roads of this island. Most of us have a background of county council membership for a long number of years and many of us have gone through the process of being elected to the Seanad through tramping the 26 Counties.  In addition, others of us have had experience in large parts of this country as European candidates.</P>
      <P>This document is very useful for a number of reasons.  In the long term, it spells out what the priorities are.  This is important for many reasons, particularly since we became a member of the European Economic Community.  Governments are now going to the EEC to seek assistance by way of grants or loans for road programmes.  A long-term plan over a ten-year period is a very useful background document against which to discuss these applications.  The setting out of a long-term plan over a ten-year period is useful in another sense.  I have felt for a number of years that we should be constructing a far higher proportion of main roads under a contract system. The background to this plan illustrates the dimensions of the problem.  To a colossal extent work on main roads is carried out by county councils and the percentage of main roads being constructed under contract is at the extremely low level of 6 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As a member of a local authority for a number of years and as somebody who has driven through most of the country and particularly on the roads from the west to Dublin, I see major weaknesses in the present system under which we do not have contracts.  I see a great deal of merit in the suggestion made by Senator Whitaker that, perhaps, a wider authority with responsibility for a much wider network of roads on primary routes is the type of authority that should be in the decision-making area <Col N="1140" /> where main roads are being constructed. This is necessary for consistency of materials and consistency of construction and possibly for cost factor as well. There are many examples where road works done under contract have been singularly successful over short stretches of road.  In many cases the system breaks down when you leave the contract system.  In a small country such as ours, the piecemeal building of roads by different counties, each constructing them according to their own lights leads to inconsistency.  The development of a plan such as this, which sets out long-term objectives and approximate cost of plans, might supply the incentive to private contractors.</P>
    <P>I agree completely with the plan in so far as the Dublin area is concerned.  It might seem strange for somebody coming from County Mayo to talk about the necessity to improve the roads in Dublin but, as the plan itself states, basic access is the primary function of all transportation systems.  In rural Ireland we have problems about roads and we have deficiencies in the funding of them.  A large county like Mayo has a huge proportion of our total road network and we are terribly backward in the development of county roads.  The deficiency has not been in the county councils or in the county engineers.  It has been one of funding&mdash;the lack of adequate funding by Governments.  Despite the problems we have, at least we have basic access. Regardless of how bad our roads are, one can drive from Louisburg to Achill or from Achill to Belmullet, or from there to Castlerea.</P>
    <P>The most appalling access situation exists in examples in Europe today so far as road transportation is concerned.  The deficiencies in the road system in Dublin are infinitely worse than they are in many cities such as Los Angeles, London, New York, cities with ten or 20 times our population.  In many of these larger cities expenditure on roads was geared to the development in population. There is a bursting at the seams in the city of Dublin without a corresponding investment in the road system.  This affects  <Col N="1141" /> not just the people of Dublin but all the people of the country.</P>
    <P>Returning to the question of basic access, on a drive from Westport to Dublin, one runs into the single largest problem at Kilcock or Maynooth and the run in from Kilcock.  If you want to tell somebody how long it will take you to drive from Westport to Dublin the only area you cannot quantify is this crazy 30 or 40 miles into the City of Dublin where there is a totally inadequate road system, narrow roads, bends. This is the major artery to all the West of Ireland where there is major movement of goods by cement trucks, large articulated vehicles and where, literally, you can be caught behind these kinds of trucks for five, six, seven miles at a time. This is the single, most appalling road deficiency in the country, where there is not basic access, because of this bottleneck. We have had a bottleneck in the city for the past two or three days also. So, from the point of view of the countryman as much as the Dublin person, in terms of overall national development and of providing adequate incentives for people in industry and elsewhere to establish major developments in the west and other parts of the country, this is the major deficiency which has to be overcome.</P>
    <P>I welcome the report and the emphasis it puts on the Dublin problem.  As a Member of the Seanad, in so far as it is a movement to provide funds for improving the Dublin situation, I am completely behind it.</P>
    <P>I want to make a few comments about the road from the west to Dublin.  I agree with the concept of a motorway at some stage.  I do not know where we will get funds, or when it will come, but certainly the provision of a motorway from Dublin, say, to Galway, with branches and arteries making connections with areas 50 or 60 or 70 miles to the north or south, to the north-east or the northwest, could revolutionise development in the country by providing access and eliminating bottlenecks.  It could lead to very substantial developments in many ways and give much employment.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1142" /> So far as the present trunk roads are concerned, there have been major improvements on the main road from the west, from the Westport-Castlebar area to Dublin, but there are still major deficiencies.  In his useful contribution Senator O'Toole referred in particular to the bottleneck in the Castlebar-Swinford area.  The county council have been purchasing land with a view to widening that road.  That section from Castlebar to Swinford is the most deficient primary route in Ireland and it will take a long number of years before it reaches an adequate standard.</P>
    <P>The problem we have in driving to Dublin from west Mayo really amounts to this.  The sensible route to take is the primary route by Longford, but the big weakness in that route is that you are on the most appalling imaginable road from the town of Castlebar to the town of Swinford.  It is a considerable distance on a hopelessly inadequate, narrow and dangerous road.  Alternatively, if you take the other route, if you take the better road in the west through Castlebar, Claremorris, Ballyhaunis and Castlerea, you end up going through Lanesborough and Ballymahon and while it is straight, is it a very dangerous road because it is much too narrow, there are far too many blind hills, and it is very dangerous at night.</P>
    <P>I have a small proposal I should like to put to the Minister and his officials in the Department.  If you look at the map you see the better road in the west from west Mayo towards Dublin, is the Westport, Castlebar, Claremorris, Ballyhaunis, Castlerea road.  When you get up to the east of the country by far the better road for travelling into Dublin is the Longford road, the road from Tulsk, Ballaghaderreen, Frenchpark, Edgeworthstown, on the route to Mullingar. If you want to envisage a better system, there is a short stretch of road from the village of Tulsk to the town of Castlerea.  If you are driving from here to Castlebar, or Westport, or Louisburg, you take the Longford route, the main Tulsk road as far as Tulsk and, on the map, the straight road would be to drive <Col N="1143" /> from Tulsk into the town of Castlerea and from the town of Castlerea driving west, you have the perfect main western road for Castlerea into Ballyhaunis, into Claremorris, into Castlebar into Westport.</P>
    <P>The point I want to make is the very commonsense point that, if you want to develop a major route which gives you the best road to the west, the best road to the east, all that is required is an upgrading of the road from Tulsk to Castlerea.  I think we are talking about a distance of about 11 miles or so.  It is something of that order.  I would seriously say to the Minister that he should get his engineers to look at that small stretch of road and see the commonsense and practicality involved in upgrading it.  It would be a very useful exercise and would be of benefit to us.</P>
    <P>The report has very little to say about issues concerning safety, and safety is a very important factor.  One safety matter about which I have very serious concern is this.  Because of the enormous deficiencies in the road system all over the country, with different standards of roads, realistically it will take a generation or perhaps two generations before we have an adequate road system.  It will take at least a generation before we have a road system comparable with that of more developed countries.  For that reason, we have to pay particular attention to safety matters to a proportionately greater extent than many other countries.  We are running the same types of motor cars at the same kinds of speed on roads that are absolutely inadequate.</P>
    <P>The point I want to make about safety is that major investment in the road system with the provision of white lines and cats' eyes at corners would make a great deal of sense.  Driving on narrow roads in some countries I have noticed bright white paint on bad bends and corners. This is a great help in guiding motorists at night and at other times.  I believe it to be a major safety factor. Realistically we cannot achieve a desirable roads system for a generation and, therefore, a corresponding higher <Col N="1144" /> investment in that area is very important.</P>
    <P>I want to make one or two other points.  In another area there has been the most scandalous neglect by this Government and, let me hasten to add, by the previous Government.  I am not scoring a political point.  There have been two or three successive energy crises with the most dramatic increases in the price of oil.  We have a bog resource in this country which, at the last estimate, despite the vociferousness of the demand for energy, has not been developed.  If our bogs were developed at this stage they would provide enough energy for about 40 or 50 years.  It is criminal that there are no State funds to build roads into our bogs.  In theory they are supposed to be helped through the local improvements scheme but in practice it does not happen because there are inadequate funds.  This is madness in a county like Mayo where there are thousands of acres of bog and yet the tractors, or the trailers, or the small trucks cannot even get into the bogs.</P>
    <P>While all this is happening we are burning oil, importing coal and using other sources of energy the use of which could be reduced dramatically if there was a policy in that area.  The employment which would be given by the opening up of the bogs and the use of native fuel is a very important point.  It may be somewhat outside the scope of a major road development plan but if we are talking about roads a matter like that should be looked into and something should be done in that area.</P>
    <P>I want to thank you, Sir, for your indulgence. On reading that registrations of passenger cars increased from 60,000 in 1948 to 640,000 in 1978 we realise we have a big problem which will need a lot of money to solve.  What is in this report is very sensible.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>My brief remarks will relate mainly to Dublin.  There are few cities in the world of the size of Dublin without a ring road.  As a consequence, the bulk of traffic, including lorries and other heavy vehicles, go through the centre of the city.  This, in <Col N="1145" /> turn, leads to acute traffic congestion which was highlighted dramatically as recently as two days ago when it took buses 20 minutes to get from one end of O'Connell Street to the other.  Admittedly, the problem was compounded on that occasion by road works nearby. The rigorous enforcement of parking and traffic by-laws will go some way towards meeting the problem.  Another aspect worthy of close examination, however, by way of remedial action, is that of flexi-time.  I suggest the Government could give a lead by investigating the possibilities of extending flexi-time in the public service.</P>
      <P>We live in a pressure-group democracy and road development can and does affect various groups and interests. It can involve property acquisition and demolition, and disturbance of business, industry and, of course, neighbourhoods.  However, the situation will become intolerable in Dublin shortly unless remedial action continues to be pursued and unless various interests, including local communities and environmentalists, are prepared to compromise so that the intolerable situation which is developing rapidly can be avoided.  I should like to make a call for co-ordination on rail and road systems in Dublin.  At present there is no coordinating mechanism for examining alternative systems of transport.  Such a co-ordinating mechanism is crucial, not least because of the huge financial investment required.</P>
      <P>Several Members of this House are members of local authorities and, lest it be overlooked, it is worth drawing attention to a circular sent by the Department of the Environment to all local authorities last August, enclosing a copy of a specification for road works.  It prescribes standards for materials and workmanship and it should lead to the adoption of a uniform, scientifically-based standard of road construction over the country as a whole, and should also facilitate the preparation of contract documents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In conclusion, I should like to join with other Senators in extending a <Col N="1146" /> welcome to Deputy Fahey to the Seanad and to congratulate him warmly on his appointment as Minister of State.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. Kiely Mr. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I formally second this motion and in so doing I welcome the Minister of State on his first appearance in the House and congratulate him on his appointment as Minister of State at the Department of the Environment.  I know he has had previous experience at that level.  I am sure the Department will benefit therefrom and that he will prove successful.</P>
      <P>I should also like to compliment the Minister and his Department for producing this booklet entitled &ldquo;Road Development Plan for the 1980s,&rdquo; a very detailed publication which I am sure is very welcome.  Ireland, because of its structure, being an island, is very dependent on roads for transport.  We have railways and air transport but it must be recognised that 95 per cent of passenger and 85 per cent of freight traffic is carried on our national roadways. Therefore, it is most important that we should have a definite development plan for roads for the eighties.  The increase in motor vehicles from 1948 to 1978, as has already been pointed out, was tenford and in respect of all vehicles eightfold.  This constitutes a vast increase placing tremendous pressure on our roads system.  Last year there was an increase of 26 per cent over the previous year, in the registered number of vehicles , an increase of 48 per cent over 1976. That increase highlights traffic congestion. I remember travelling to Dublin to an All-Ireland Football Final in 1961.  I travelled that day in fairly record time. Yet, on the first day I attended the Seanad my journey home took me longer than that trip in 1961.  That is yet another illustration of the congestion there is on roads at present.  As all Senators know, time is a very precious commodity in the life of business people and all others on this island.  The real costs entailed in the congestion on national and secondary roads, in economic and social terms, are very significant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1147" /> There is tremendous need for a good roads system on which Ireland is so dependent for physical communication and movement.  In this respect transport conditions and considerations often dictate stock turnover and holdings and siting of factories and of depots is very important.  Efficient distribution affords producers much tighter control over the timing and reliability of final deliveries of goods.  Losses caused by road deficiencies may be measured in terms of time and wear and tear on vehicles&mdash;as Senator Whitaker pointed out earlier&mdash;where roads are not properly maintained.  Road accidents can also cause loss of time and money.  Here again traffic congestion can be the cause. Traffic congestion is also detrimental to the commercial, industrial and farming life of the country.  Sometimes traffic moves at the rate of six miles per hour in cities which causes terrible delay with presumably loss of finance to business people and those involved in the transport business.</P>
    <P>National and county roads comprising 90 per cent of the entire roads system are of vital importance to agriculture. They must be maintained and repaired to meet the needs of agriculture and other social needs.  That is the real importance of the production of this road plan for the eighties with which I am sure everyone will agree.  Its implementation will also give employment.  Indeed, in Ireland, the employment potential of roadworks is well recognised, affording wide distribution of direct employment on and off the site, using Irish skilled and unskilled labour, material and equipment. In this context I might mention that roads in foreign countries were built with much Irish labour.  If our people were prepared to build roads in foreign countries then it is logical to assume they would work equally well on road construction here, providing us with a road system of which we can be justly proud and which would be the envy of anyone visiting the country.  According to this booklet, in 1977 the monthly average number of road workers was 9,540.  As a <Col N="1148" /> result of an allocation in July 1977 of an additional grant of £500 million and some other additional grants, the monthly average for 1978 was increased to 10,088.  I am sure that when the development plan gets under way there will be a further increase in employment and one of the objectives of the manifesto will have been achieved.</P>
    <P>It is important to provide dual carriageways to ease congestion, with major bridges especially across rivers in towns.  Here I am thinking of Limerick City where the construction of a third bridge is necessary across the Shannon to ease the congestion there and to facilitate the flow of traffic.  I was delighted to read in the Press that a subcommittee of Dublin Corporation decided to provide an east ring road around Dublin.  Senator Hillery spoke about it already.  Senator Conroy said it would ease traffic congestion in the city especially bearing in mind the present volume of articulated truck traffic plying between various EEC countries.  Ring roads are necessary in other towns especially in Limerick.  Naas is a glaring example.  Also lay-bys are necessary on these main roads, as was mentioned by Senator O'Toole, where restaurant facilities might be provided.  Such facilities should be included in the plan so that people travelling long journeys could have something to eat without having to enter large towns or hotels where they may have to wait a considerable time.</P>
    <P>It is most important also to make roads safe which could be achieved by the erection of proper sign-posts and warning signs where roads may be accident blackspots and so on.  The tourist industry could benefit from this road plan also.  As Senator O'Toole mentioned, there is need to have hedges cut and maintained at a certain height.  Indiscriminate dumping on roadsides is an environmental hazard.  I passed through a town yesterday near Charleville where there was a lorryload of refuse dumped at the side of the road.  This problem should be tackled and people dumping refuse should be subject to heavy fines. <Col N="1149" /> Such dumping does not project a good image of our country.</P>
    <P>In regard to the national primary network, I am delighted to note that there will be a dual carriageway from Dublin to Portlaoise with a by-pass in Naas.  The Dublin to Portlaoise road is the busiest road in the country carrying all traffic from Dublin to the south&mdash;Limerick, Waterford, Cork and so on.</P>
    <P>I am pleased to note also that the Cork to Mallow road will be reconstructed and that it will be a dual carriageway.  It is a busy road.  At present there is terrible congestion on this road especially during the beet harvesting season.  One can be delayed behind a line of traffic for ten miles or so travelling at 15 or 20 miles an hour, whereas on other such roads into towns of similar population in other parts of the country traffic could travel at 60 miles an hour.  The Limerick to Ennis road is another road carrying a lot of traffic and I am glad to see it included on the map also.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Brien was disappointed that there is a vacant space in his county.  I was looking at the map to which he was referring and there are vacant spaces in many other parts of the country also.  I am sure that all these vacant areas will be taken care of in time. The Department and the Minister had their priorities in order in tackling now roads most in need of reconstruction.  I am glad also to hear that there will be no hold-up in finance, that the European Investment Bank has recognised this plan, and also that there will be grants coming from the EEC Development Fund. Senator O'Brien referred also to inadequate finance.  There must have been inadequate finance prior to 1977 also because I remember coming to Dublin when the construction of the dual carriageway from Newbridge to Naas was at a complete standstill.  Since the end of 1977 continuous work has been taking place on it and progress is being made.  In July, 1977, there was an allocation for selected improvement projects and an increase in the overall allocation <Col N="1150" /> of grants in 1978 to £37.548 million. This is something that must be borne in mind.  Certainly, this Government could not be accused of not providing adequate finance for road development.</P>
    <P>Senator Markey thought that we had not a definite programme.  This road plan constitutes a definite programme and I am sure that the Minister for the Environment, with the assistance of his two Ministers of State, will ensure that this programme is brought to fruition.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelMulcahy" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall not detain the House long.  There are one or two points I want to raise.  We have a ten-year plan. My information is that the EEC have had a look at the plan and are happy with it and that is a good thing.  The Minister may have mentioned this fact but I was not present when he spoke. The EEC see it as a contribution to regional and economic development in Ireland.  The one thing that is not so good at present is that the Regional Fund of the EEC is still being spent in about half of the territories of Europe, covering approximately 40 per cent of its population and cannot in any way be dealing with the real problems of regional imbalance.  There is no doubt that the entire road system is a problem for us now.  At least, it can be brought in as a problem of imbalance.  Just to inform the House, I should say that two of the sub-committees of the Joint Oireachtas Committee on Secondary Legislation of the EEC are having a look at what is going on in the Commission in relation to the policy for the Regional Fund.  Some discussion documents are in existence.  We have had access to them. We are hopeful that we will be bringing out a report on this matter shortly, making some recommendations which might be of general use.  The fact that this committee is a Joint Committee means that we will have reached some sort of concensus on our ideas which I am sure the Minister will find of interest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I decided, on looking at the facts which are available, not to talk about any of the principles or suggestions, but the facts that periodically we talk about, <Col N="1151" /> making more use of railways and taking the pressure off the roads.  I did not appreciate that 85 per cent of the freight carried in this country is carried on the roads and that 90 per cent, approximately, of passenger traffic is carried on the roads.  This is an indication of the level of the problem.  People's daily economic behaviour is not going to shift&mdash;to reduce the problem for us.  A possible exception would be the immediate area around the Dublin urban conurbation.  Another review has got to be ready by January 1981.</P>
    <P>Therefore, the Minister is to be congratulated that his Department have produced a ten-year projection of our needs.  I would see this projection as a guideline.  We should not rest at that.  If, through ingluencing the EEC we can get more funds, then we can speed up progress and projection dates of completion of various road sections can be brought forward.</P>
    <P>I do not know if it has been mentioned in the House that Mr. Donovan of the Confederation of Irish Industry made a point in public recently that many of these projects, as listed in the ten-year plan, were shown to be sharting around 1985 and finishing in 1990.  He made a lot of mileage out of the fact&mdash;no pun intended&mdash;that five years to build a section of road of a certain length was much too long and, by implication, that the Public Service were falling down.  When I examined the matter I found that the expenditure projected in the plan is about 50 per cent up on the average expenditure over the last few years.  That is a notable increase.  Also some of the bottleneck areas, for instance, the road from Heuston Station to the west is projected to be finished between 1980 and 1981. There are some immediate commitments to bottlenecks.  As far as the road network is concerned we have a massive problem.  Of the total moneys involved in the ten-year plan, something like £550 million allocated&mdash;I cannot be more exact&mdash;is for improvement of the existing network, excluding Euro routes.  There is a big problem.  Even after the implementation <Col N="1152" /> of the plan we will be the only country in the EEC that will not have a motorway because a motorway is not included.</P>
    <P>One would hope that the EEC would see their way in the future&mdash;hopefully that the &ldquo;own resource&rdquo; budget would open up and more funds would be available&mdash;to speed up the plan and would recognise that Ireland, at the estern tip of Europe, is one of the regional areas needing a massive injection of help.  We are not dependent on the Regional Fund alone; we have the Ortoli facility and the new investment fund but most of that comes by way of loan.  Even if there are through the EMS arrangement some interest subsidies, nevertheless it means national borrowing and adds to the problem which we all know so well and about which we have been talking over the last few weeks.</P>
    <P>I would hope that phase two of this ten-year plan would be &ldquo;operation speed up&rdquo;.  An &ldquo;operation speed up&rdquo; is a way of getting more resources.  This is probably the right time to say to Deputy Fahey, the Minister of State in this area: &ldquo;Rath Dé ar an obair.  Look for as much as you can get because we need it all.&rdquo;  I welcome the Minister to the House and wish him the best.</P>
    <P>As in the case of everybody else I have one localised point to make, which is this: even thought I would probably be the first to advocate comprehensive, integrated planning of the networks even though you complete only sections of the road, according to availability of resources, where it would be possible to show that provision of a section of road would eliminate a bottleneck I would not hold up the provision of that road until such time as the total plan is agreed.  To that extent I am quite concerned that the approach being taken now by Dublin Corporation in relation to motorways and routes being discussed at present is a sort of comprehensive one and, therefore, some parts of the programme which could be implemented without a lot of fuss may have to wait.  I am thinking in particular of the roadway which is being considered to by-pass the Clontarf <Col N="1153" /> Road on the East Wall side, what is now known as the Fairview embankment road.  The Fairview embankment road is not a big deal.  It is a £350,000 investment. I would hate to see people who come from north Dublin along the coast road sitting in their cars in the North Strand when a £350,000 road would provide them with a by-pass.  I am all for integrated, comprehensive planning and everything I have ever written or what I have said in this House would prove that.  Nevertheless, if it can be shown that a section can be implemented without having to go through built-up areas, where house demolition problems arise, work should proceed.  A by-pass would lead to the development of a sports complex, of playing pitches alongside.  Therefore, I would advocate that.  There must be other examples of that kind across the country.  I just happen to know about that one.</P>
    <P>My message would be: an excellent ten-year plan.  I am delighted to see it.  It constitutes a 50 per cent increase in expenditure on roadways and phase two should be &ldquo;operation speed-up&rdquo;, get more money from the EEC.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>Like those who have spoken I should like to welcome the new Minister of State to the Seanad and wish him the best of luck in this very important Department.  As a man who travels frequently from Clonmel to Dublin I am sure he is every bit as aware of the problems we have with our roads system as is everybody else.</P>
      <P>It is a good thing that we are discussing this very important road development plan for the eighties as we begin the decade.  As our economy develops, as more and more industries come into the country, as we decentralise, as people travel more, live further away from their places of employment, roads will play a major role and more and more money must be invested in the provision of accessible roads, that are easy to travel on and which facilitate traffic from A to B.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We must realise that as housing accommodation becomes more and more expensive in Dublin city, and people <Col N="1154" /> begin to move 20 or 30 miles out of the city, they will have to travel into work. We must provide transport that will allow them to get from their homes to their places of employment fairly fast.  At present that is not possible.  For example we do not have bus lanes in Dublin city. Neither do we have&mdash;at a time when we are trying to conserve energy&mdash;bicycle lanes.  These are two important aspects that we must consider.  As a start we could consider the provision of those two types of lane in the Dublin area.</P>
    <P>Another aspect of this report to which I would like to draw attention is the section devoted to the sign-posting of roads. We need to pay particular attention to this.  It is not important only from a tourist point of view.  Very many of us who live in Dublin, who know Dublin particularly well, still find it very difficult to find our way from one part of the city to the other.  Within the city itself signposting is almost negligible.  Going from Dublin to other parts of the country, unless on the main routes, it is very difficult to know the places at which to turn off and so on.  The Minister could, through his Department, advise the various local authorities to co-operate with one another in ensuring efficient and clear signposting.  That would help to solve the many problems caused by congestion and so on.</P>
    <P>Being a small island country, and given the fact that, as the report says, 95 per cent of passenger travel and 85 per cent of freight travel is done by road, it is important not only that the Department of the Environment should pay special attention to the infrastructure and to investment in roads but that local authorities, through this Department, should co-ordinate their plans and ensure that roads are properly maintained. We have a very high unemployment rate.  I cannot see why many people who at present get money for doing nothing could not be usefully employed in improving and maintaining the roads.  This money should be spent for the benefit of the community and the economy.</P>
    <P>I welcome this report.  It is an important one and will become more and more <Col N="1155" /> important.  We are trying to conserve energy.  Given, as the report says, that 20 per cent of all energy consumed in Ireland is by cars, trucks or other vehicular traffic, it is important that we examine the most efficient way of using energy for the transportation of people. In this respect is is deplorable to see people coming into work in the cities every morning, one to a car.</P>
    <P>I should like the Minister and his Department to pay particular attention to the provision of bus lanes and bicycle lanes.  These ideas have been mooted by others.  They are very important.  As we progress into the eighties, as energy becomes more and more a problem, as people have to travel longer distances, particularly to their places of employment, these matters should be examined thoroughly, and this is possibly the opportune time to do so.</P>
    <P>I should like to thank the Minister for coming into the House for the debate on this report.  Sometimes it is difficult to get Ministers into the House to consider reports but the fact that this new Minister has done so today indicates his concern for and his interest in the provision of a better infrastructure and a more efficient roads system for our community.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to join other Senators in welcoming the new Minister of State.  I welcome also the opportunity provided for this discussion. This is a very wide subject and the plan is on a national vasis.  Purely because of the constraints of time which exist in this type of debate I would like to confine my remarks to the urban areas and in particular to the Dublin situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Road construction gives rise to very understandable anxieties with many people, both as to the cost of the undertaking and also the possible effect on communities by disruption in areas through which traffic has not previously flowed. In order to get the problem in perspective you really have to get down to analysing what the costs and the benefits are of a co-ordinated and well-thoughtout <Col N="1156" /> programme, as indicated in this plan, and the cost of going on as we are.  Some Senators have rightly pointed to the cost of inadequately kept roads and inadequately maintained roads.  In addition to that I would like to make the point that there are very direct and unnecessary costs arising even when roads are properly kept but where the transport system to which the road network is allied is basically inadequate.  There is the problem of congestion which is bringing not only traffic in Dublin to a halt but is having a serious and fundamental impact on life in the city.</P>
    <P>The problem of energy which has been high-lighted in this debate is accentuated and multiplied out of all proportion by traffic which is snarled up and which simply cannot flow freely.  The difference in the rate of consumption of petrol and other fuels in vehicles when the traffic flows smoothly and when it does not and when it is continually slowed or stopped is enormous.  That is a pretty direct cost which hangs around the neck of every citizen in the country, particularly now with the impact which fuel is having on our imports and on our balance of payments and the cost of paying for it.  There is also the direct cost of wear and tear which has also being mentioned but which still arises even when roads are well maintained but where the system itself is inadequate.  The average life of a car alters greatly between when it runs efficiently and smoothly through most of its life and when it is normally engaged in snarled up and chaotic traffic conditions.</P>
    <P>There are also some important indirect expenses that it is important to bear in mind when we consider the overall cost/benefit of road construction. There is the time factor which has already been referred to; the loss of production, the loss of service.  The loss of output which arises from delays in transport and in travel is enormous and incalculable.  It is a very definite cost and even though it may be, to a great extent, hidden.  So great is the problem becoming that it is perhaps less and less hidden.</P>
    <P>In relation to the useful life of a vehicle, <Col N="1157" /> to which I have already referred, there is another point which is of some importance.  If vehicles are driven in traffic conditions and on road systems that are efficient, the useful life of that vehicle will be lengthened, the cost of maintaining it will be reduced and the time when it is replaced will be that much further away.  That in the long run will have an important and a very considerable benefit in reducing our imports in so far as it will give us a permanent saving in imports if our vehicles remain longer in use.</P>
    <P>The inefficiency to which Senator Kiely has referred in lost time and fatigue is perhaps one of the most important of the indirect costs.  It is of very great social concern to people.  It is daily becoming a greater problem and one which is causing the height of aggravation. The ordeal facing workers, be they using public transport or private transport, in spending two or three or perhaps more hours per day in simply getting from their homes to their work is something which I do not think anybody would seek to defend regardless of the circumstances.  It is an appalling loss of time; it is an appalling intrusion into the time they have for family and social life. The hours spent by people going to work, queueing for buses or simply sitting in buses or cars that are going nowhere is a problem which will have to be tackled almost regardless of the cost.</P>
    <P>On the question of cost generally, I agree that it is heartening to hear the contribution of the Minister particularly in regard to the qualification of the plan set out for assistance from the European Investment Bank and also, for grant purposes, from the European Development Fund.  Those two factors alone help to put the overall cost which we are undertaking in this type of plan very much into perspective.</P>
    <P>I would like to refer to the effect on health generally of the present road system in urban areas and particularly the Dublin area.  The effects of inpossible traffic conditions in terms of stress over long periods are of fundamental importance and must, in many cases, place a <Col N="1158" /> very great strain on and do a great deal of damage to the average citizens' health.  Travelling through congested traffic conditions day after day driving against the clock under stress is obviously an extremely unhealthy occupation and one which it is in everybody's interest to eliminate as quickly as we can.</P>
    <P>There is also, of course, the direct problem of pollution.  Surveys have shown clearly that the incidence of pollution&mdash;in the case of petrol driven cars, carbon monoxide and lead and other substances&mdash;grows tremendously in cases of congested traffic as compared with free flowing traffic.  Also, in a highly built-up area, such as Dublin and in many other areas throughout the country, over a long period of time obviously that has a very serious effect of the health of the community.  The whole range of respiratory ailments; heart conditions and all that allied to the stress to which I have referred highlight another immense cost, perhaps a hidden cost but one that is very real and one which everybody is in favour of tackling. Looked at in those ways, the problems and costs of road construction do fall into perspective and perhaps this may help us to reach decisions which in some ways may be unpopular but when viewed against the background of these problems are seen to be very necessary.</P>
    <P>Road construction in the Dublin area, to which the plan refers, will play an immense part in relieving some of the problems to which I have referred. Nevertheless there will be very understandable worries and doubts about it, doubts with which most of us will have a great deal of sympathy.  It must be remembered also that whereas, road canstruction may in many cases disrupt communities&mdash;traditional, longstanding communities&mdash;the present situation if we do not tackle the problem is also very disruptive to communities.  So great is the problem and the pressure now that many motorists are availing of side roads which were never intended for through traffic, but which are now being used because of the snarled-up, congested <Col N="1159" /> position on the main thoroughfares.</P>
    <P>This I believe is known to those who study this very carefully as &ldquo;rat running&rdquo; and it conveys something of the nature of the problem.  It is extremely dangerous in so far as it brings heavy continuous traffic on to roads that were never intended to take them: it can damage the houses on the roads in question: it is obviously a danger to children because the roads were not constructed to safeguard children against continuous, flowing traffic. The point I make, therefore, is that the cost to communities of doing nothing can be much greater in terms of disruption and other matters than the cost of actually getting down to this problem and constructing, where necessary, the type of motorways envisaged in the plan. There should, of course, naturally, be precautions which take sensitivity into account, the anxieties of people who live in certain areas where traditional communities have existed.  We obviously have to preserve, as far as we can, traditional character and traditional amenities.  Indeed, some forms of road construction in urban areas will present an opportunity to add to the amenities. Screening, in the form of trees, or even in the construction of new houses, should obviously be taken into account to mitigate the worst effects of pollution which may arise and which may increase as a result of the new roadway construction.</P>
    <P>Finally, I would like to say again specifically in relation to Dublin that, whereas I very much welcome this report prepared by the Minister and his Department, one comment made by the Minister for Transport in the past week was, perhaps, the most refreshing comment I have heard on the Dublin traffic and road situation for a very long time. The Minister, Deputy Reynolds, clearly pointed out to Dublin Corporation that they have at least as much responsibility in the matter of solving the road and traffic problem in Dublin as anybody else.  It was a breath of fresh air: it was lively and imaginative comment, comment <Col N="1160" /> which will do a great deal of good and may stimulate a lot of new ideas.  I would support this whole idea of taking a fresh approach and using some imagination in this matter because whereas I support the road construction plans as set out in the plan, nevertheless, road construction itself is not the whole answer by any means.  Experimenting with bus lanes, experimenting with cycle lanes, as Senator Harney has suggested, is something which should be tackled. We can learn an immense amount from this.  If public transport was enabled to run efficiently and smoothly by means of bus lanes or other means, that would obviously greatly reduce the number of private cars being brought into congested urban areas and so we would have a dual benefit.</P>
    <P>There are many related aspects of the immediate problem.  Road construction is fundamental to the problem, but is not the whole problem.  The construction of car parks to relieve congestion on the roads is something that has to be tackled.  I accept that Dublin Corporation do provide car parks, but clearly not enough.  The construction of high level car parks should be considered in an environmental context as well as everything else.  It is clearly unfair to penalise and fine motorists for illegal parking when there are simply no reasonable facilities for them to park legally.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondGoverney" hpid="Mr. Governey Mr. Governey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Governey</NameTxt>
      <P>I rise to add my voice to what has already been said here today. This is an excellent, correct and precise report.  We note from it the development for the eighties, and I only hope that with the lists of works that are included in it the finance will be readily available and that we will finish on target.  There is one particular point I want to mention, the question of by-passes. We have the situation&mdash;perhaps it was already mentioned in the House today&mdash;within my own neighbouring county, South Kildare, where you have from Dublin to Naas a beautiful dual carriageway but any evening of the week, when you get as far as Naas you can have a traffic jam back as far as the <Col N="1161" /> Dublin side of the racecourse.  It can take you anything from half an hour to three-quarters of an hour to get through the town of Naas.  I know there are plans under way for a by-pass.  I am not quite certain if all the legal aspects as regards acquisition of land and so on have been completed.  I think this is a very urgent job because of the hold-up that you have just at that particular point.  Perhaps this is something that has died out now, but I know that some years back, there was a certain amount of misapprehension about by-passes.  I want to say to anyone who might have doubts&mdash;perhaps we are so modern in my own town of Carlow that we are ahead of everybody else&mdash;that I remember many years ago being at meetings at which the question of a by-pass was discussed and it was the general feeling at that time of the people present that this would be a terrible thing for the town: there would be a loss of business: it would become a ghost town.  To those who have doubts like that I would say that if we had not gone ahead at that time with that project it would now be impossible to get through the town of Carlow.  We now have, as I am sure the Minister is probably aware, living not too far away from it, a by-pass of the town and yet business has survived and not alone survived but has prospered over the years.  We have got additional industry and were it not for the by-pass and the people who thought of it at that time, it would be impossible actually to get through the town today. To anybody who has doubts about a by-pass, I say I do not think it will have any detrimental effect on business in a town.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The other matter I want to mention is that while it is grand to have a plan and to work to it we must not neglect, while we are thinking of, and working in the eighties, something that is very important, and that is the maintenance and the up-keep of existing roads.  I am a member of the local authority where at times at estimate meetings&mdash;indeed it happened all over the years; it is not something that happens under one particular Government or another&mdash;you have cutbacks on estimates, and you are leaving over maintenance of roads which should <Col N="1162" /> be done in a particular year.  It is left over to the following year.  We know that with rising costs today this is not good economics.  If roads are not kept up to standard and parts are left over for the following year, it is fair to say that costs in the following year will be much greater.  I would suggest to the Minister that as far as possible, with the funds available to him, he should pay special attention to having funds available for the maintenance of our present roads.</P>
    <P>I should like also to refer to the section on signposting and in particular to the marking of white lines on the roads.  I think it is terribly important that these should be kept up to date so that when a road is re-tarmacadamed the white lines would be immediately replaced.  It is also very important&mdash;I think we have made progress over the years in this regard&mdash;that accident &ldquo;black spots&rdquo; should be signposted.  I am sorry that there is need for so many of them but at least they give one warning in advance of the danger spots one is close to.</P>
    <P>My final point is that whatever sums are available for roads and road maintenance, I believe that to keep on the employment force of the county councils and even to add to that force is working in the right direction, because we have at the moment people who, through no fault of their own, cannot find work and are unemployed.  If employment could be found for these people in order to increase our work force with the councils they would at least be getting a decent standard of living; we would be saving money on social welfare.  This is something which the councils and the Minister for the Environment should have a look at.  I am not being critical of people who are unemployed; I am talking about people who are unemployed and just cannot get work.  I think it would be good economics; you would be giving them employment, a better standard of living and at the same time you would be saving a certain percentage in social welfare benefits.  In conclusion, I would like to join with the other Senators who have spoken here in welcoming the Minister to the House today for his first time.</P>
    <Col N="1163" />
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>First of all, I want to thank the seconder of this motion, Senator Kiely, and all the speakers who contributed to a constructive debate.  Indeed, I want to pay a special tribute to the other side of the House.  While the motion came from this side of the House, there was no question of politics involved.  I want to commend them for that and say that it only goes to show me that everybody is treating this as an important issue, above politics.  We all live in this country and we all want to have better communications and better roads. I just want to say to Senator O'Brien that indeed the 10 per cent regulation by the Minister in no way curbs the development of this programme and I would welcome greater EEC grants as he suggested.  He may have misunderstood me when he said that pedestrian traffic would go underground rather than overground.  I did say that for pedestrian traffic I would welcome by-passes overhead and for vehicular and livestock traffic a tunnel underneath.</P>
      <P>As regards the other speakers, I want to thank Senators Conroy and Markey and also Senator Whitaker for his comments on my county, and its beauty.  I welcome him to it as often as he can come.  I know he is a regular visitor there and he will always be welcome.  I know that Senator Kilbride is very much worried about the maintenance of the roads we have and the big problem facing us.  It is indeed a big problem. Senator Staunton spoke about the reclassification of the tourist road on the other national primary, across into Castlerea for a distance of about eight or ten miles to bring us into the Ballyhaunis, Ballinlough, Claremorris area.  It would, of course, need reclassification of our national primary to bring in that road.  It may be possible, I do not know what the Department officials and the Minister may think of that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I agree wholeheartedly with him about bog development and I can assure him that my party have already discussed this in the light of the energy crisis and I have no doubt that some improvements <Col N="1164" /> or breakthroughs in bog development and in bog roads will be in the pipeline in the not-too-distant future.  Senator Hillery spoke about the standardisation of construction.  I think it is necessary that we have a standardisation of construction throughout the whole of the country, rather than have a county identified as having a lower standard than another county.</P>
    <P>Senator Kiely made a case about debris and unused vehicles and machinery strewn along our national primary network.  I think that is a disgrace, I think some law should be brought in to enforce the removal of this junk.  People tend, outside rural garages, to do all their parking on the roads approaching those garages.  That is also something that we should tackle; it is unsightly from the tourist point of view and I would like something to be done in that connection.</P>
    <P>I thank Senators Mulcahy, Harney and Donnelly for their mention of congestion. City congestion is damaging to health and so is the pollution in the air, which no doubt will have its effect on the human beings of every city where you have cars ticking over.  Excess use of fuel will give that type of pollution that is highly dangerous to health.  I might say to the people who are worried that this programme might might outdate our existing road programme that such is not the case.  It is an addition and indeed it is not an alternative to the road programme we have in the various counties. It will not in fact dilute or devalue what we know of at the moment and what we have on stream in the various counties.  That type of development and road construction that we have from the block grant will continue as usual.  The only thing I see wrong with acquisition is that the terms agreed by the landowner and the local authorities might become outdated if construction work does not take place immediately after the terms of acquisition are brought into force.  I think that is a major problem when you have to go back and you have objections to the terms of acquisition where works are not completed in the shortest possible <Col N="1165" /> time.  The main thing that I see wrong not only in respect of construction of roads and the county council's administrative side and the engineering side and the carrying out of the work, is that we have a lower production on our roads for the amount of money spent than any other country.</P>
    <P>Many people have suggested that we should let our roads programme out on contract.  That was something we could have done in the past but with the present cost of the necessary machinery, for any individual contractor, group of contractors or company to purchase sufficient machinery to go into road construction today, the capital investment involved would be far beyond the guarantees that might be forthcoming from local authorities.  For that reason I cannot see the contract system working while I should like it done on a trial basis on a certain section of a road where some contractor may have the necessary machinery for doing this type of work.  I cannot see any contractor, or any group of contractors having the capital investment necessary to compete with a county council.  The county council have an organisation set up; they have purchased their machinery.  That machinery would, of course, become obsolete if you brought in the contract system, but I would like to see it on a &ldquo;once off&rdquo; basis on some section of a road to see how the cost per mile would compare and to have a watchdog in the Department watching the return for the <Col N="1166" /> moneys spent within the various counties.</P>
    <P>I did mention the World Bank when I was speaking&mdash;I should have said the European Investment Bank.  However, I do not mind which bank&mdash;you can call it the World Bank or the European Investment Bank&mdash;but we must get loans for this programme.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I sincerely thank the engineering staff of the Department of the Environment.  This might be a small document when you look at it from the outside, but one must acknowledge the amount of energy, time and work that was put into the compiling of this document by our engineering staff, in the first instance, and by the co-operation of the engineering staff of every local authority within the State.  Months and months of hard work has gone into this document and I compliment the engineering staff sincerely for its production and the administration staff within the Department of the Environment for its presentation. It is properly presented; it is easy to read; it is easy to know what they are about in the document and they must be highly commended for its production.</P>
    <P>Finally, let me thank the speakers, the Minister, and the Minister of State for the very alert way he listened to every comment that was made here in connection with this document.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.05 p.m., <i>sine die.</i></P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>