<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="4" Month="Jun" Year="1980" Vol="94" No="6" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 4 Meitheamh 1980" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 4 June 1980" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="569">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="569" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator West that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The unsatisfactory composition and functioning of the Irish National Commission for UNESCO.</P>
      <P>I regard the matter as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and it will be taken from 8 p.m. to 8.30 p.m. or earlier if the business ordered is concluded.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Cooney of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The awarding of a contract for a new national school at Ballinahown, County Westmeath.</P>
      <P>This matter also is suitable for the Adjournment but the Standing Order does not envisage discussion on more than one matter.  I have selected the earlier matter for today's Adjournment and Senator Cooney may give notice for another day of the matter he wishes to raise.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 1, 4, 5 and 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Leader of the House indicate to us the plans for next <Col N="570" /> week's sitting?  I have heard that there may not be a sitting next week and that instead there may be a three-day sitting the following week.  If that is the case, if I have heard correctly, I would like to enter a protest at the uneven flow of business coming to the House.  It is a great waste of our time that we are not called upon at all next week and then have to sit for three days the following week.  I would like to make that protest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we have the comments of the Leader of the House on that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>At the moment the position is that it does not look as though there is going to be anything available for next week.  I regret that.  It is unfortunate that we should not have business next week but these things happen.  At the moment it does not look as though we are going to have any business from the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Turf Development Bill&mdash;could that not be taken next week? It has been on the Order Paper for the past three or four weeks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Mr. P. Reynolds Mr. P. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>And the Agricultural Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We could take that.  It probably would not take more than an hour.  It seems to be hardly worthwhile to meet for that Bill alone.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Mr. P. Reynolds Mr. P. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>And the Agricultural Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Agricultural Bill dealing with rates, the change in the rating position, will take more than an hour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It has not gone through the other House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PierceButler" hpid="Mr. Butler Mr. Butler">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Butler</NameTxt>
      <P>If the agricultural rates Bill goes through the House next Tuesday, could we sit on next Wednesday?  I have a contribution to make on that Bill. I will not be here next Wednesday week. I am a good attender in the Seanad, and <Col N="571" /> I never miss a sitting, but that is one special day on which I shall be missing and I want to contribute.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Report of Committee" RHead="of Selection">
    <Title>Report of Committee of Selection.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee of Selection reports that it has discharged Senator Hanafin from membership of the Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies at his own request and has appointed Senator Hillery in substitution for him.</P>
      <P>I move: That the Report be laid before the Seanad.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Packaged Goods (Quantity Control)" RHead="Bill, 1980: Second Stage">
    <Title>Packaged Goods (Quantity Control) Bill, 1980: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. Meaney) Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. Meaney)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. Meaney)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill, as its name implies, is to update methods of control of the contents of packages&mdash;not only the methods employed by packers and importers but also those of the State. This will be achieved by legalising the average system of quantity declaration on packages by requiring that packers and importers who have not already done so introduce statistical quantity control procedures and by setting up a specially trained departmental inspectorate to oversee the practical operation of these procedures.  It should not, however, be thought that the new system will consequently penalise and adversely affect packers.  In fact, the opposite is true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>By the introduction of tighter control procedures packers will benefit in that under the principles of the average system they will be able to take full advantage of modern high-speed filling equipment and discontinue the practice off &ldquo;over filling&rdquo; which is necessary so as to ensure compliance with present <Col N="572" />&ldquo;minimum contents&rdquo; law.  The consumer too will benefit from these proposals as a result of the increased surveillance at factory and import levels.  Importers will be under the same obligation as packers to ensure that packages meet the requirements of the law.  They will, however, to a large extent be able to meet this obligation by obtaining documentation from their suppliers abroad.</P>
    <P>These proposals bear strong similarities to those being adopted elsewhere in the European Community in that they are based on two directives of the Community, Nos. 75/106/EEC and 76/211/EEC, the aim of which is to ensure free circulation within the Community of packages which have been made up and are marked in accordance with the directives.  However, this is not to say that our proposals are limited to implementing these two EEC directives. In fact they go beyond the scope of the directives in that they embrace all prepacked goods over five grams or five millilitres in quantity whereas the EEC measures place an upper ceiling of 10 kg/10 litres&mdash;five litres in some cases&mdash;on the quantity and, in the case of some products, confine the benefits to certain specified sizes.  I am also taking the precaution of providing certain powers in the Bill to expand or contract the scope of the legislation so as to enable us to keep pace with future developments in Community planning or the requirements of international trade.</P>
    <P>The Bill has been welcomed by packers and manufacturers generally, because of the advantages already mentioned which will accrue from the introduction of the average system of quantity declaration and which will help to increase their competitiveness on both home and foreign markets.  It is of particular interest to exporters of products which come within the scope of the two directives mentioned as it will enable them to use the symbol for which the directives provide&mdash;the &ldquo;e-mark&rdquo;.  This symbol acts as a metrological passport within the Community in that it means that the Government of the member state in whose territory it was applied <Col N="573" /> guarantees that the quantity declared on the package is correct within the tolerances laid down in the directives.  In time I expect that the &ldquo;e-mark&rdquo; will in practice become recognised as a guarantee of accuracy in export markets other than those within the Community and this should further increase the acceptability of Irish produce abroad.</P>
    <P>The Bill is comparatively simple in concept in that it sets out to provide the broad parameters for the new control system.  The detailed requirements will be contained in regulations to be made by the Minister and in two guidance manuals, one for packers and importers and the other for inspectors, to be published.  Two teams of consultants have been engaged by my Department to draw up these guidance manuals and industry was provided with a first draft of a manual for packers and importers for consultation purposes some months ago.</P>
    <P>The response given it and the advice and comments generated have been of great assistance in preparing for the introduction of this Bill and the drafting of the necessary regulations which is currently under way.  I should mention that my Department are also deeply indebted to the members of the Consultative Committee on Prepackaging. This committee, which was set up by the Minister in 1977 to advise on the implementation of the directives, comprises representatives of industry, packers, consumers and trade interests as well as representatives of the weights and measures authorities.  Its advice and assistance are still available to the Department in connection with the preparation of the regulations and manuals and are of inestimable value.</P>
    <P>I would like to expand on a number of details contained in the provisions, specifically, certain exclusions from the Act, including special arrangements in respect of small packers, the role of the departmental inspectorate, marking requirements and certain temporary derogations which may be granted.  I should say initially that I intend excluding certain types of packages from the scope of the proposals, specifically, <Col N="574" /> so called &ldquo;random&rdquo; or &ldquo;catch&rdquo; weights. These comprise random weight made-up packages such as are quite common in the bacon and dairy processing industry which, being so made up, are difficult if not impossible to monitor using the proposed methods of statistical sampling. Accordingly, it has been decided that they will continue to be subject to existing &ldquo;minimum contents&rdquo; requirements.</P>
    <P>This, in turn, bring me to the one group of packers which I propose exempting from statistical control procedures and record keeping. Specifically these are very small packers or packers of short runs where each package is manually filled and weighed on non- or semi-automatic weighing equipment and is filled to minimum contents requirements, thus ensuring that no package contains less than the declared quantity.</P>
    <P>I should now like to expand on the proposed role of the inspectorate to be established to oversee the implementation of the proposals.  Although the proposals include provisions for prosecution and relatively stiff penalty clauses, it is my intention that the inspectorate and back-up staff of my Department will act in an advisory and supportive manner and I hope that they will not be seen by industry as an investigatory force whose primary purpose is to ferret out infringements.  Rather, it is in the interests of all concerned to co-operate to ensure that the new scheme is adopted as smoothly and efficiently as possible so as to maximise its advantages.</P>
    <P>I would like to emphasise that this Bill deals only with packaged goods which are sold by weight or volume.  It is concerned only with the way in which the weight or volume is expressed on such packages, the extent to which this expression of quantity may vary from the exact quantity included in the package and the steps which must be taken by packers and importers to ensure that any variation in quantity which may occur is in accordance with the law.</P>
    <P>Where the Bill and the regulations to be made under it refer to markings on <Col N="575" /> packages, other than the &ldquo;e-mark&rdquo; which is provided for in the EEC Directives, the markings in question are the declaration of quantity and the identification mark of the packer or importer, the latter mark being necessary to enable an inspector to trace the source of the package.</P>
    <P>Other markings such as listing of ingredients, showing of unit price, marking of latest date for use or consumption of the product, are the subject of two directives which were adopted recently by the European Community and which will be implemented in Ireland by other legislation, possibly later this year.</P>
    <P>I am aware that there are also compulsory markings in relation to drugs, dangerous substances, agricultural produce and so on which are the responsibility of other Ministers.  I have been in touch with the Departments concerned with a view to ensuring that there will be no conflict between their regulations and those which it is proposed to make under this Bill when enacted.  Matters other than marking&mdash;for example, prescribing of products which must be sold by weight, volume or count, prescribing of sizes of packages in which certain products must be sold, indication of country of origin of a foreign product&mdash;are at present dealt with, and will continue to be dealt with, under the Merchandise Marks Acts, 1887 to 1978, although some minor modifications of these Acts will be necessary because of the legalisation of the average system of quantity declaration.  These modifications are provided for in sections 12 and 20 of the Bill.</P>
    <P>I do not, of course, expect that all industry will be able to switch over to the new system overnight and accordingly have made provisions for the issuing in certain circumstances of temporary derogations.  While the outside limit of derogation laid down in the Act is 31 December, 1985, it is expected that the majority of temporary derogations from the Act will be for periods of months rather than years.  They will be granted primarily to enable packers to use up existing <Col N="576" /> stocks of labels and containers. Derogations may, however, be granted, in exceptional circumstances, for longer periods and from other requirements of the Bill&mdash;for example, the requirement to use approved equipment or to make checks at prescribed periods.  Their primary purpose is to enable the Bill to be brought into operation within a reasonably short period after its enactment, thus facilitating those manufacturers who are already in a position to comply with its requirements and who feel that their competitiveness, particularly on export markets, is adversely affected by the present requirement to pack to the &ldquo;minimum&rdquo; rather than the &ldquo;average&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>I am confident that when adopted and fully operative the new control system will increase the efficiency and competitiveness of our packers and will provide Irish consumers with a comprehensive protection against substandard packages.  I therefore commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MylesStaunton" hpid="Mr. Staunton Mr. Staunton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staunton</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not opposing this Bill which is obviously necessary in this age of gimmicks and high powered marketing.  We are not in the age when a pound of tea was simply a pound of tea, or two pounds of sugar were two pounds of sugar.  With the sophistication of present marketing it is obviously necessary that there should be controls to protect society and to protect consumers. For that reason in broad terms we welcome the Bill.  It is necessary as well so that we should comply with EEC requirements under Directive 75/106 which deals with liquids and Directive 76/211 which deals with laws of member states relating to the making up by weight or by volume of certain prepackaged products.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is necessary as well to help the export industry in this country in the prepackaging area so that the legislation harmonises with international standards and of course the tighter control is in the interest of the consumer.  It is interesting that this Bill has been welcomed by those in manufacturing industry because very <Col N="577" /> often governments introduce legislation which for different reasons is seen to be unduly restrictive by that section of the community which it affects.  It is not so in this case.  By the introduction of this measure the packaging and manufacturing people will benefit under the average system which will allow them to be more competitive with the full advantage of high speed filling equipment.</P>
    <P>The very small manufacturer is being looked after by the exception that is being made and to which the Minister has referred.  The retail trade for a number of years has been faced with a variety of inspectorates from the Department, for all types of purposes, and this has aggravated the retailing community.</P>
    <P>I support fully the notion contained within this Bill, that the responsibility for compliance with this Bill is to be transferred from the point of sale from the retail store or supermarket to the manufacturer, or the packer, or to whatever one would choose to describe as the source of packaging the goods in question.  Sometimes it seems to be a little unfair to the retail community that they are so totally held responsible for all types of goods and services which they provide and some areas of which are quite outside their control.  This is an area where if a package does not contain what it should the retailer is held responsible and that to me seems unfair.  I welcome the fact that now it is traced back along the line to its source.</P>
    <P>I suspect that the Department in the implementation of this Bill will have difficulty with the extent of surveying and monitoring that will be necessary.  I wish them well in doing so.  I hope that when it is being implemented the purpose of the Bill itself is not lost on the consumer because this Bill is obviously in the interest of the consumer.  Governments may get very excited about introducing legislation in broad objective terms which is desirable but at the end of the day unless the message gets through to the consumer that this Bill is in his or her interest and that the contents of the various packages and liquids are as specified, which is the purpose of this <Col N="578" /> Bill, the whole effect of this will be lost on the consumer.</P>
    <P>It seems to me to be very important that what is written on these packages and on these bottles is in simple terms and is legible to the housewife or to the man who is shopping.  If we get lost in the jargon of EEC directives and all that goes with it and the minutiae that one gets on the pharmaceutical preparations, for example, and if this is the type of script that is going to appear on packets of custard and such items the whole point will be missed and the effect and the objective will have been lost.  I would ask the Minister to ensure that his team of consultants and others in his Department in their liaison with the packers and the manufacturers do what they can to see that simple language in legible script which is not tiny print, is used.</P>
    <P>I have nothing more to say on this Bill which is non-contentious.  In broad terms we readily accept it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EileenCassidy" hpid="Mrs. Cassidy Mrs. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister of State said that the Bill has been welcomed by packers and manufacturers generally.  I feel it will be of great benefit to the housewife if it ensures that greater control will be exercised over what manufacturers actually put in their packages.  We are not doing anything serious about quantity control until we tackle the problem of unit pricing.  I know that unit pricing is not common in EEC countries and only in West Germany is it compulsory for packets to have the price per unit marked clearly on them.  I do not know why this is so.  Perhaps it may be for the reason that our Joint Committee on Secondary Legislation, in their report on unit pricing in April of 1978, while they agreed with unit pricing in principle felt the cost would inevitably be passed on to the consumer, in this case, the housewife.  With all due respect, they did not convince me as a housewife that that was necessarily so or even if it were so, that it would not be worth it in the long run.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The housewife when she goes to shop today is confronted with a bewildering array of sizes and shapes in packages. <Col N="579" /> There is a small size, a medium size, a large size, a giant size and there is now a euro size.  By the time she reads the small print and converts the measurements in kilograms down to ounces, with which she is probably more familiar, and then to pounds and pence, at the same time trying to control a couple of toddlers who are trying to come to terms with the bacon slicer, she is completely bewildered.  Modern shopping, especially supermarket shopping is not geared to this sort of thing, so that unit pricing is a &ldquo;must&rdquo; for housewives.  It would, too, make it very much easier to compare the cost of living in the various EEC countries.</P>
    <P>I was glad to hear the Minister's comment that the showing of unit price is the subject of two directives which will be implemented in Ireland by other legislation, possibly later this year.  I welcome this very much and I look forward to that legislation coming before the House. There is also a great need for manufacturers to be persuaded to produce a small size product for people who shop for one person only.</P>
    <P>My reaction on reading the Bill for the first time was one of disappointment.  I read it quickly and I thought we were concerned with quality control rather than quantity control.  I feel that quality control is a very much neglected area. Where fruit and vegetables, particularly, are concerned, we should have a very rigorous system, possibly under weights and measures legislation, to ensure a better system of quality control.  This will be a very formidable task as long as the Dublin Corporation Fruit and Vegetable Market is operating in its present unhygienic and inefficient manner, but it is very necessary.</P>
    <P>Another item which is very necessary in quality control is that where nutrients have been removed from food during processing this should be clearly stated. Manufacturers always state what they add to food but they very rarely state what is taken out in processing.  We could do a lot worse than look at legislation in other countries, such as they have <Col N="580" /> in Canada, where this is looked after under the Food and Drugs Act, 1950 and which was updated in 1972.  They have most useful regulations to ensure that dangerous cleaning substances such as chlorine which is very common&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair would like to intervene.  The Chair is aware that this Bill deals with quantity rather than quality and feels that the Senator is straying more towards the quality side rather than the quantity side.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EileenCassidy" hpid="Mrs. Cassidy Mrs. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept the ruling of the Chair, but I do feel as regards quality and quantity that we might have stricter compliance with standards.</P>
      <P>I have confined my remarks on the Bill to the housewife's position because I feel the housewife's position in the consumer society is a very important one. We have only to look at the recent battle of the multi-national giants who were trying to gain control of the retail food industry here.  The housewife is a very important part of the consumer society. She is also subject to a great deal of psychological pressure when she shops, the sort of pressure that is designed to part her from her money without any reference to her budget or to her needs.</P>
      <P>I would like to conclude by wishing the Minister well in this very responsible portfolio of consumer affairs.  The concept of the consumer is a new one and although Ireland and Italy are regarded generally as being at the bottom of the league as regards consumer protection legislation I think that recently our record is good; we have passed the Consumer Information Act; the Sale of Goods and Supply of Services Act; the Occasional Trading Act and I look forward to the further legislation which the Minister mentioned in his speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Cassidy about the importance of the area we are discussing which is fundamentally the area of consumer protection. In my time as Minister for Industry and Commerce I had some experience and indeed some involvement in the <Col N="581" /> preparation of some of the legislation which has been passed by the present Government, and on the basis of that experience I want to say two contrasting things.  First, I think that this piece of legislation is a very small piece.  It is part of a useful progression of Bills in the area of consumer protection.  I think we can look on that as a modest plus, but we have a very long way to go.  We are in the circumstances that, as Senator Cassidy said, Italy and Ireland are the most backward places in the Community in regard to consumer protection.</P>
      <P>We have a very poorly-developed consumer sense and we have a number of people who are working admirably in the consumer protection area, but they are quite few and they do not enjoy nearly enough public support.  So let us not think that a Bill like this, which is a very small one does much in the consumer protection area.  It is worth noting also that what we are doing is putting into national legislation a couple of directives that date from 1975 and 1976.  It is for a reason like that, that the protestations of the distribution interests, wholesale and retail, that they have to have some extra time to use up the labelling and the packing which they have, ring a bit hollow.</P>
      <P>I was very struck in my time as Minister at the extremely elaborate defences in depth, and which sounded plausible, which came from the packaging and wholesale section of distribution and which in fact when looked at closely were not so plausible.  They were a passionate, skilful and well-organised rearguard action, but did they not know five years ago that this was going to have to become the law of Ireland?  Did they not know four years ago?  Who can claim with the faintest shred of justification that they were taken by surprise? They cannot make that claim.  However, the Labour Party are certainly not going to contest the Bill.  We are glad that this enactment is coming forward but we see it as something rather small.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like to make a few points of a more specific kind.  The Minister will <Col N="582" /> forgive me if I have misread the Bill&mdash;in fact, I hope I have&mdash;but, as far as I understand it, it is entirely metric.  I should like to ask the Minister if that is correct because a lot of what I have to say in the next few paragraphs depends on whether it is right or not.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>Almost entirely, but there would be still other imperial ones.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not completely clear.  I read it to be in reality entirely metric with some loopholes.  I wonder if that is the best way to describe it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>That is correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>In that case let me try to characterise what has happened since we joined the Community.  I believe in harmonisation, in the idea of the Bill and I believe passionately in the metric system.  I greatly regret the confrontation between Britain and France 200 years ago that made us lock ourselves to a disgusting method of measuring and debauched generations of school children for a couple of hundred years when the metric system existed.  I am totally pro-metric and, yet, the reality of what is happening in the transfer from imperial to metric is that the ordinary housewife, indeed why single out the housewife, the ordinary citizen does not understand a kilo, a litre, or the difference between an ml and a cc and so on.  Why should they?  I do not say that in any sense of reproach.  What is happening is that the real information conveyed to the present generation of purchasers is, in fact, diminishing and not increasing.  I say that with regret&mdash;it is nobody's fault&mdash;but that is the way it is.  It will be better in the next generation. Would it not be a good thought in our legislation, if we genuinely want, first, to convey information and, secondly, to make people in their everyday life more familiar with the inter-relation of metric and imperial measure, to say both must be put on the packet?  In fact, by saying that people could read whichever they were familiar with but by reading on an <Col N="583" /> object, a packet of sugar or a carton of milk or what not, both things simultaneously they would continuously be getting a little education as to the relationship between the number of mls and half a pint and between the number of grammes and half a pound.  Those are things we need to see lots of times so that we can become familiar with them.  I would like to see imperial and metric printed.</P>
      <P>I echo the plea for legibility.  I support what Senator Cassidy said on the question of unit pricing.  There was a mention of unit pricing by the Minister on the basis of an exclusion, but since he made a brief reference to it I take it I am in order in doing the same.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>A brief mention is in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be brief and what I have to say is germaine.  In the April 1978 Report of the Joint Committee on the Secondary Legislation of the European Communities there was approval in principle of the idea of unit pricing.  The argument, the basis of an exclusion in the Bill, which could come forward, for example, from people dealing in bacon saying, &ldquo;Yes, it is a lovely idea but it is too difficult&rdquo;, is not true with modern electronic machinery for weighing and stamping labels, What was genuinely difficult 20 years ago, to work out an exact weight and then the unit price corresponding or whatever is not so now.  Nowadays there is machinery with electronic innards that will print labels in a number of weights and of prices simultaneously and at almost no extra cost.  Those machines can be seen in supermarkets.  Certain supermarkets have the wit to market their products in a quite sophisticated way in regard to price.  A battery of very skilful people are involved.  At the one end motivation researchers get into the shape of a pack, even the shape, then the colours on the pack, then how to make something that, in fact, contains five-and-three-quarter ounces look as if it contains nine-and-one-quarter ounces.  They are getting <Col N="584" /> psychologists to work on that.  They have heavy law to circumvent all the mechanisms for the protection of the public.  That being the case we know how dishonest and misleading packaging is. We know the packaging industry, just as we know the layout of a supermarket, is a mechanism for getting people into impulse buying of an irrational kind.  I will not use a sharper phrase than that but that is sharp enough.</P>
      <P>In what we know to be that circumstance then we are entitled to say that the arguments against the unit pricing are adequate for the thirties or forties and, indeed, for the days of mechanical cash registers but in the days of electronic cash registers, electronic label printing machines and electronic calculation of price in relation to weight, they are simply bogus and covering for another intention.  The other intention, as usual in this matter, is to give advantage to the seller in the eternal tug-of-war between the seller and the buyer.  My own conviction is that in that tug-of-war the State ought to be on the side of the buyer, who is less organised and often less well informed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is a useful small piece of progress which we certainly will not obstruct but in my view it could have been made stronger quite easily in a few ways.  We do not have to trot behind the Community all the time four or five years late.  We might occasionally anticipate it as the consumer legislation of some countries has done.  When we do find ourselves coming into line with Community directives we might use the opportunity to strengthen the consumer as against the packager.  This is not really dealing with the shops, this is dealing with the packagers and they are fewer in number than the retail outlets.  They are easier to police.  In that eternal battle the use of metric and imperial simultaneously would have been a useful thing to do and it could have been easily done. Those inter-conversions presented daunting arithmetic 20 years ago but are now so easy when people can get pocket calculators for £10.  Little print-out labelling machines can be got for substantially <Col N="585" /> more, but still for a small amount in regard to the total cost of a retailing enterprise, or a wholesale or packaging enterprise.  For those reasons this Bill might have been a little stronger.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiBrugha" hpid="Ruairí Brugha Ruairí Brugha">
      <NameTxt>Ruairí Brugha</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a relatively simple measure which does not call for a lot of debate.  It should be stressed that it is purely a quantity proposal providing for the publishing or printing of the quantity of the article or goods contained in the package.  We should not think it goes any further.  Senator Keating has made a point which is worth following through.  We are largely, as a community, relatively uneducated in relation to new methods of measuring quantity.  Most people do not know what a gramme or a kilogram is or, indeed, litres.  Although it is simpler in relation to our own measurement they still confuse people.</P>
      <P>If the suggestion Senator Keating made was possible for the time being, that the package would contain both measurements or both weights, it would help.  Perhaps the Minister might consider providing a chart for each supermarket or store showing the relative difference. That would help people.  A lot of people do not understand the metric system.  It is completely new.  They did not learn about it at school and even those who learned about it recently are not very up to date on it.  The aim of the Bill is to provide information and I suggest to the Minister that there might be additional ways to ensure that the customer will know what these quantities mean such as those put forward by Senator Keating, or by way of the Department providing charts for retailers, at least for the next ten to 20 years, setting out the comparatives between the different weights and measures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Mr. P. Reynolds Mr. P. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>While Senator Brugha was speaking I thought that if he was in the retail business now he would find that there are ample charts around without adding another one.  Paints manufactured within the Republic carry the metric weight while imported paints carry both.  It is a must that imperial and <Col N="586" /> metric are displayed on the container. Packets which contain raisins or currants on the outside state 12 ounces but there is no indication whether that is net or gross.  It is completely misleading. Such packages should clearly indicate to the consumer whether the weight is net or gross.  It is easy to do that because of the small number of people involved.  It is not like in the retail business.  One is only dealing with importers and manufacturers.</P>
      <P>The Minister made reference to some temporary exemptions.  I should like to know why there are exemptions.  If one firm who are geared to deal with this find that somebody who is in competition with them is exempt, that firm will have a grievance.  There are other exemptions also.  I am curious to know the reason for those exemptions.  I welcome this Bill.  It is a move in the right direction and like Senator Staunton, I am delighted this matter is being dealt with at the import and manufacture level and not at the retail stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CLambert" hpid="Mr. Lambert Mr. Lambert">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lambert</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill which enables the Minister to issue regulations on a directive that is overdue. It is mainly concerned with the averaging directive which the Irish food industry has been operating since the beginning of the year.  With the help of the weights and measures inspectors, who have provided certificates, they have been able to retain their position in the export market.  We are grateful to the Department for this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On Senator Keating's point about the electronic equipment, we have been warned to be very careful in buying weighing equipment.  This will come under another directive, the weights and measures directive.  It is possible that this will be explained in the publicity manual which will be issued so that manufacturers or businesses should not rush into buying machines which may not be acceptable to the factory inspectors.  We are proceeding to metrication but, as we have heard, dual marking, metric and imperial, will be allowed until 1985. There are certain products, such as <Col N="587" /> biscuits, which have dual marking and one will find both ounces and grammes illustrated on the packet.  The tendency as we move to metrication is to enlarge the metric weight and make the imperial weight smaller.</P>
    <P>The Minister has explained that there are many other Bills imminent to comply with legislation under the EEC directions on packaged goods, weights and measures, unit pricing, article numbering and, most important, food labelling.  This is of the utmost importance to us because the UK issued their draft proposals in February this year and it is unlikely that the Irish law will be introduced for some time&mdash;I was not quite sure whether this was one of the Bills which would be introduced later this year.  The labelling directive will, of course, cover Senator Cassidy's point because the proper ingredients will have to be displayed on the packet and if the ingredients are not pure the scientific people will not allow it through.</P>
    <P>Whilst we are very anxious for Community harmonisation, and the need not to offend others, or be undiplomatic to the UK in particular, I should like to draw attention to the fact that there was a great deal of consumer legislation in the past year, the Consumer Information Bill, the Sale of Goods and Supply of Services Bill, the Safety in Industry Bill and now this Bill.  All this recent legislation means that Irish factories are expected to comply with a multitude of disciplines. In general, Irish manufacturing industries are only too willing and happy to do so but we are concerned that competitors from other EEC countries, particularly from the UK which is now suffering from a depression and unloading a great deal of imports here, comply with all these disciplines which are embodied in that legislation.  As I have said in an earlier debate, Ireland is one of the easiest countries in which to import food.  If Government policy is opposed to anything but full compliance with Community proposals and if consumer interests must reign supreme then we should investigate all pragmatic steps to <Col N="588" /> ensure that our competitive manufacturers who are importing here are complying with all the legislation with which Irish manufacturers are adhering to.</P>
    <P>I hope the Minister will spur on the Director of Consumer Affairs and other people involved in the administration of the directives now being made law to ensure that importers comply with that legislation and urgently raise such matters with offending parties.  One instance which struck me under the Safety in Industry Bill is that inspectors of factories have power to inspect every part of the factory day or night; they may require the production of registers and while inspectors pay a great deal of attention to the hygiene&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair feels that the Senator seems to be broadening the scope of the debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CLambert" hpid="Mr. Lambert Mr. Lambert">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lambert</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to illustrate the point that under this legislation connected with packaged goods Irish manufacturers are adhering to the legislation but I am not sufficiently satisfied that we are paying the same attention to our imports. In other words, I welcome the Bill and all others which improve the harmonisation of product exchange between countries but I appeal for a more effective watch-dog on imports to see that they comply with such legislation.  I wish the Minister well in his onerous position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AndyOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to join in the welcome extended to the Bill.  I believe it will go a long way to improving conditions for consumers and manufacturers alike.  I support the view put forward that some people will have great difficulty, or still have great difficulty in translating the weights and measures from one system to the other.  The point made by Senator Brugha about producing charts to show the relative value of each weight or measure has a good deal of merit in it.  It was very effective in schools and the younger generation do not experience very much difficulty in translating one to the other.  I have seen that.  It is true that older people have the greatest difficulty in translating and <Col N="589" /> suggest that during the transition period weights and measures in addition to being given in the metric system should also be given in the system to which people were accustomed.  Otherwise they will have great difficulty.</P>
      <P>I am aware that since the introduction of the decimalisation of our currency older people still think in terms of 240 pence in the pound.  That emphasises the need for making the transition from one system to another in a gradual way and relating the new system being introduced with the one people were accustomed to for a little time.  The Minister should consider seriously having a relation between the two weights or measures for the transition period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ValentineJago" hpid="Mr. Jago Mr. Jago">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jago</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill.  I agree with Senator Keating that it is all part of legislation to protect the consumer but I do not think this Bill is to protect the housewife against a packer who is out to take advantage of her.  It will give the housewife the advantage of the use of modern machinery by the packager to reduce cost.  Naturally, modern machinery works faster and there is less cost.  Under present legislation where an employer has to give a minimum weight the packer has to give excess weight to make sure he is right.  In some legislation there is the impossible position that packers have to give the exact weight.  In other words, if they are over the weight then in accordance with the law they are breaking the law just as they are if they give under the weight.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill puts the matter right and if the average weight is given, within limits, the packer will be able to give the advantage of cost saving to the consumer.  The Bill puts an onus on the importer.  The Minister suggests that this may be done by documentation or failing that it means that the importer will have to weigh all produce coming in before he re-sells to make sure it has the fair average weight.  A lot will depend on the regulations made under the Bill.  One part of the Bill states that goods can be ordered by the inspectorate to be held for a certain period, presumably as <Col N="590" /> evidence.  In that case the regulations will be important as to what is exempt and what it not because certain goods change with time.  For example, packaged bread will lose weight with age.  I presume there will be something in the regulations to cover this.  Generally, I welcome the Bill because it will enable the Minister by regulation to put many things right which are troublesome in the packaging field.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. Meaney) Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. Meaney)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. Meaney)</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to thank all Senators who contributed for their kind remarks and for what they said on the Bill.  There was a general welcome which I very much appreciate.  As I said at the outset this Bill is not wide-ranging, it is just another piece of legislation concerning the consumer and consumer protection. There will be a lot more legislation within the next 12 months and we hope to get it through the House without any great delays.  The Bill deals with the situation where there is high-power packaging and, as Senator Keating said, advancing technology.  It concerns the &ldquo;e-mark&rdquo; on packaging with very fast packaging.  We are replacing the minimum system with the average system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Staunton was worried that what would be written on the packages should be legible.  That is a natural worry to have.  He wanted it written in simple language.  I should like to refer the Senator to section 10 (1) (d) which provides that markings be easily read without opening the package.  That should satisfy Senator Staunton's worry. Senator Cassidy suggested that manufacturers put products on the markets in smaller sizes to suit people on very limited income, mainly those on social welfare, old age pensioners and so on.  I am aware of the need for this but I doubt if it has been brought to the notice of the manufacturers.  If the market exists I cannot see why the manufacturers will not have to comply with it.  Of course, manufacturers have to see what is profitable.  I know of one product that is sold in the old 2lb. measure but a person <Col N="591" /> living alone would have sufficient in ½ lb.  It would be in the interest of the manufacturer to come in line with that.  I wonder if they carried out any research on that.</P>
    <P>Senator Cassidy also mentioned quality control for fruit and vegetables. The matters raised by the Senator in that regard are appropriate to the Departments of Agriculture and Health.</P>
    <P>Senator Keating was worried about the delay.  I know that he has experience in this field as he was Minister for Industry and Commerce.  When the Senator was Minister, legislation was starting and directives were coming from the EEC.  Senator Keating is very well aware of what they contain.  We will check it out because we always check everything in our office.  Some of the other EEC member states have only recently implemented the directives, for example, the Netherlands, Belgium, the UK and Luxembourg.  It would not really be a great advantage to Ireland to implement them before 1980.</P>
    <P>We have a long way to go in consumer protection.  There is a lot to be done in that field.  I look forward to being deeply involved in it and hope to bring more legislation here as time goes on. The metric system versus the imperial system was also mentioned.  Senator Brugha mentioned that and he also mentioned charts.  Under the legislation programme charts have been available in retail outlets for some time.  I do not know if people have become fully aware of what is involved.  I exhort people to become more involved in the metric system as it is something we will have to face in the future.  The metric system is used in directives but there is nothing to stop any firm, manufacturer or packager also using the imperial system side by side.  We are not legislating on it.  Many people have come to me and have said they would like all packaging to be plain and clear and have as little as possible on it with very little small print.  There is nothing to stop any manufacturer or packager from putting on the weights and the volumes under the two systems.</P>
    <Col N="592" />
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>But the Minister will not require them to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  It is something that will be going out in a short time.  We will have the &ldquo;e-mark&rdquo; as well and it will carry its own right throughout the EEC. I appreciate that many housewives will be buying imported goods and we would not have control over these.  The &ldquo;e-mark&rdquo; is very much involved in this legislation.  It is an Irish E.  Somebody asked what size the &ldquo;e&rdquo; would be.  The mark &ldquo;e&rdquo; will be in a legible size in proportion to the package or the volume of goods that is packaged.  One could not ask for an &ldquo;E&rdquo; to be carried on a small package.  The provisions of the Bill will apply equally to Irish import firms.  It will be a strict Bill.  It is carrying the &ldquo;e-mark&rdquo; which will have to come from other countries and that carries authority to go through the other member states.</P>
      <P>Some Senators mentioned labelling legislation.  That is very important legislation and the Department are very much involved with it at present.  I never like to put a time limit on when any legislation will come in.  I hope, all going well, to have that legislation within 12 months.  We have a lot of other legislation coming before the summer and we have already arranged for Bills to come in in the autumn.</P>
      <P>Senator Reynolds spoke about exemptions and said that one firm would be geared up and another would not be.  The Bill will be to the advantage of the firm which has advanced and geared itself, and has bought sophisticated machinery for high power packaging.  The other firm may still have the minimum contents regulations which means that every package will have to have X number of items which, in many many cases, will lead to an over-fill.  I said earlier that the advantage will be to the firms who have advanced, spent a lot of money on a modern, sophisticated machinery, technology and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Jago mentioned the inspectorate and its operation on behalf of the housewife will give her an increased assurance that the package contains the <Col N="593" /> legal quantity.  Once the package contains a certain mark on it, the housewife can be guaranteed that the legal quantity is OK and that she is protected. Somebody said that it was a good Bill because it did not put any more onus on the retailers.  That was a fair comment because it is at the point of packaging that the inspectorate will be working. They will have access to packers and the way they work.  Anyone who has studied the directives will see the standards required and the allowances that are made for mistakes.  I should like to thank everybody who contributed to the debate.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the next Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>I made a request to the Minister in regard to simultaneous metrication and imperial labelling which was supported both by Senator Brugha for the Government and the other parties in the House.  I should like an opportunity to move an amendment on this because it is an important issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not hear the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>I want an opportunity, since it seemed the suggestion I made in regard to labelling had the support of all three parties, to move an amendment which would also furnish us with a method of protecting Irish packages against overseas competition. It is important for the housewife and the packager.  I am not willing to have the next Stage taken now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it not be possible for the Senator to put one in later this afternoon?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>It could be included by ministerial regulation.  I do not mind having a look at it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="594" />
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>My wish is that for the protection of the consumer it should be obligatory to mark it both in imperial measure and in metric measure.  The advantage of that is that some countries doing very big runs which are entirely metric would not take the trouble to put in imperial measure as well.  We would be saving our packagers from a little bit of overseas competition as well as protecting the consumer.  I want to see the requirement that both the metric and the imperial number be put on.  I take the point about not having undue complexity but that is simple to do and would be advantageous to all sides.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>How will we arrange it with importers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>Importers from Britain?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>From member EEC states.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>We would have a way, with a perfect legitimate reason, of protecting our consumer from ignorance and our packager from overseas competition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot have a debate on the substance of an amendment that has not yet been tabled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is no harm to tease it out.  On this EEC directive, we have no control over ensuring that companies within other EEC countries will put down anything except metric and work under the metric system.  We are asking Irish packagers, industries and manufacturers to put down a specific set of markings which will carry them through the EEC but it is something that other countries are not asking their manufacturers or packagers to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>We had a suggestion from the Leader of the House that if I could table something later on in the afternoon, it might be possible to meet the situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="595" />
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, if the Senator would do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>As a matter of procedure, I want to contribute on the next item on the agenda, but immediately I have done that I will draft something.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that the question of when the next Stage is taken can be considered after the next item.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>We will facilitate the Senator at any hour and he could have a chat with the Department before putting the amendments down.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The debate on the Order for the next Stage of this Bill is now adjourned and we move on to item No. 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>When will we resume on this?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>On the conclusion of item No. 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Protection of Young Persons (Employment)" RHead="(Section 4) Order, 1980: Motion">
    <Title>Protection of Young Persons (Employment) (Section 4) Order, 1980: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Eireann approves the following Order in draft:</P>
      <P>Protection of Young Persons (Employment) (Section 4) Order, 1980,</P>
      <P>a copy of which Order in draft was laid before Seanad Éireann on 21 May, 1980.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Labour (Mr. Daly) Minister of State at the Department of Labour (Mr. Daly)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Labour (Mr. Daly)</NameTxt>
      <P>The motion now introduced seeks the approval of Seanad Eireann for a draft order to continue in force, for a further period of 12 months from 4 July 1980, subsection (3) of section 4 of the Protection of Young Persons (Employment) Act, 1977.  A similar motion was approved by the Dáil on last Wednesday, 28 May 1980.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="596" /> The Act provides that section 4 (3) was to remain in force for two years only from the date of commencement of the Act unless continued in force by an affirmative order.  This two-year time limit expired an 4 July 1979 and with the approval of the Dáil and Seanad last year an order extending the section for a further 12 months was made.  Since then, a full-scale review of the Act, with a view to its amendment, has been taking place in my Department.  It was not possible, however, to complete the review before the expiry of the existing order in July of this year.  I am satisfied that the <i>status quo</i> should be maintained until the Houses of the Oireachtas have an opportunity to consider amendments of the Act in more detail.  Accordingly, I am seeking approval of this draft order which would continue section 4 (3) on force until July 1981.</P>
    <P>The employment of children under the school leaving age, which is at present 15 years, is generally prohibited under the 1977 Act.  However, the effect of subsections (2), (3) and (4) of section 4 is to permit children under 15, but over 14, years of age to be employed in light nonindustrial work for limited periods outside school hours provided that the work is not harmful to their health or normal development or that it does not affect their capacity to benefit from education and their attendance at school.</P>
    <P>The Act also imposes other obligations on employers in regard to the employment of young people, including those between 14 and 15 years of age. Before employing a young person an employer must require the production of a birth certificate or other satisfactory evidence of age.  The written permission of a parent or guardian must also be obtained. An employer is required to maintain a register or other satisfactory record showing the name, date of birth, times of starting and finishing work each day, the rate and the total amount of wages paid.  The employer is also required to display an approved abstract of the Act at the principal entrances to the place of employment in such a way that it may easily be read by the young people employed by him.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="597" /> We all have an obligation to ensure that young people are given every opportunity to benefit fully from their attendance at school and that their education is not disrupted in any way.  I can well understand the viewpoint of those who maintain that there should be a total ban on the employment of children under 15 years of age during the school term and I accept that their concern is for the health, education and moral welfare of young people.  However, the experience of my Department in the enforcement of the Act since it came into operation almost three years ago, has not revealed evidence of any significant degree of exploitation of children in employment during school term or at any other time. On the other hand, there is some evidence that the withdrawal of the right to engage in employment without the strict limits laid down in subsection (3) of section 4 of the Act could be contrary to the wishes of many parents who consider that a limited period of work outside school hours can be a useful experience for young people in the process of deciding on careers.</P>
    <P>I can assure Senators, however, that I have no intention of going soft on the enforcement of the Act.  There is an inspection system operating on a countrywide basis, and there have been successful prosecutions and others are being considered. This is not to say, however, that there are no difficulties in regard to enforcement. I am hopeful that the review being carried out will indicate what should be done to ensure more effective enforcement.  I intend to introduce amending proposals, if possible, during the next session.</P>
    <P>While the original intention, was that section 4 (3) would lapse after two years unless kept in force by affirmative order, I am advised that the legal position appears to be that in the absence of section 4 (3), children under 15 years of age would be allowed to work during the school term but without the protection which section 4 (3) provides by way of limitation of their hours of work.  For this reason, it is necessary to keep section 4 (3) in force.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="598" /> As I have said already, the Members of the Oireachtas will have an opportunity to consider fully the future long-term position when the proposed amendment of the Act comes before the Oireachtas following the completion of the current review of the Act by my Department.  Meanwhile, I would ask the Seanad to approve the making of an order to continue in force for a further 12 months from 4 July 1980, subsection (3) of section 4 of the Protection of Young Persons (Employment) Act, 1977.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>It is good to hear the Minister say that there is a comprehensive review under way in the Department in regard to the employment of young people, particularly school children and young persons as they are defined under the Act.  Whenever an amendment to the Act comes in, it will be necessary to have a more strict interpretation of what is meant by &ldquo;young person&rdquo; in that Act. Within the terms of the Protection of Young Persons (Employment) Act, 1977, it can apply to schoolchildren of 14 years of age.  The Act draws a distinction between a young person and a child. It will be necessary to make that distinction far more explicit in any amendments that come before the Oireachtas.</P>
      <P>Employment for young people can be very positive but it can also have its negative aspects as well.  It can be very positive and desirable in that it can inculcate a sense of work habit among young persons.  It can give them practical experience of employment and what they will face when they will finish their schoolgoing days and also what their service to the community at large can often involve.  The negative aspect can be a very harsh experience for young persons in regard to employment particularly where it is in an environment which is not the most satisfactory or desirable or where it arises from pressures within the family for economic or other reasons and even from pressures that apply from children themselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>For example, children feel that because other children in their class are working they should go out and obtain a <Col N="599" /> position.  Sometimes they go out and obtain the first position that comes to hand and the environment, circumstances and conditions may not be suitable at all and may leave a certain stamp on their attitude towards work for the rest of their lives.</P>
    <P>We have to be very careful about providing employment for young persons and particularly school-goers.  In 1974 when this Bill was debated by this House and came into operation, I said I had the gravest reservations about school-going children being given employment on school days, whatever about weekends.  During school terms there is a certain danger which must be faced in employment being taken up by school-going children.  The Act puts a limitation of two hours on it during school days.  It is perhaps fortuitous that a survey which was done by the Dublin youth committee of the ITGWU arrived in our post today.  It mentions a number of points in regard to employment for young persons and school children which are rather frightening.  It is a fact of life that the major source of employment for young persons lies in lounge bars, in fish and chip shops and in restaurants.  We see a lot of these young people employed in lounge bars late at night.  I have always had the gravest reservations and doubts that the two-hour limitation period applies at all in those instances.  We know that these lounge bars function until 10 o'clock or 11 o'clock.  We know that it can be 10.30 p.m. or 11.30 p.m. by the time the place is closed up for the night.  All the cleaning up and so on is done after normal closing hours.  We know that young people are seen there for a number of hours on any night and it would appear that the two-hour limitation period has not been enforced at all.  The obligation is on the Department of Labour to enforce this, whatever about the obligation on employers to ensure that they provide work for only a two-hour period.  The Department of Labour, being the Department that brought in this legislation, must be seen to insist on it and to take necessary prosecutions as they arise <Col N="600" /> where this limitation period has been exceeded.</P>
    <P>Employment for young people is very desirable.  It can give them a sense of work habit which is very good.  It is not so good when it arises from pressures within the family, pressures to go out and earn a few pounds extra in the week or pressures that can arise within the classroom from seeing other children going out and obtaining work at night time and at weekends.  The Act states that such employment should only be condoned where it does not hinder or affect in any way the capacity of the school-going child to benefit from the instructions in his class.  I cannot think of any instance in which a couple of hours working at night would not hinder the capacity of any school child to improve his education.  School can finish at 4 o'clock or 3.30 p.m.  It is necessary that there be a few hours recreation period for any school-going child.  He must then do certain home exercise.  It is rather difficult and is asking too much of a child with the travel involved going home from school, having an hour or two at home to do his home exercise and then travelling to get to a place of employment, which can take up to an hour or a half an hour in certain instances, and then going home from that place of employment, perhaps as late as 10.30 p.m., 11 o'clock, 11.30 p.m. or even later.  In no instance can I think of where those kind of conditions would not take away from the capacity of any school-goer.</P>
    <P>The reservations which I had five or six years ago when the Bill was first introduced in regard to school children still continue as far as I am concerned.  We have had a number of surveys since.  At the time the Bill was debated in 1974-75, a survey was done in the town of Drogheda which produced rather shattering figures as regards exploitation of young persons in regard to employment. A survey was taken recently in Westport in regard to this matter.  The survey which arrived today is also shattering in the information which it gives in regard to this matter.  The Department will have to bring in certain modifications and <Col N="601" /> amendments to this legislation if the public at large are to be satisfied that young persons are not being exploited.</P>
    <P>When we look at the survey of the ITGWU youth committee we find there may well be a case for having a minimum wage introduced.  If we take an example of a 13 year old working four days per week as a milkman's helper for £5, in no instance could we accept that as a reasonable remuneration for any school-goer.  The survey gives other examples of where there is blatant exploitation of young persons.  This can be done with the families condoning the situation, but where it affects the education of the school children there is an obligation on the State to look very closely at the matter. We hope that in 12 months time the Minister will not be seeking a further extension of this section.  We hope that he will be bringing in substantial amendments to this Act.</P>
    <P>Employment for young people is desirable if it is controlled but it must be monitored very carefully and the final responsibility rests with the State authorities to ensure that school children are not exploited in any sense.  From the surveys that have been carried out by bodies ranging from junior chambers of commerce, the schools and the ITGWU, there is ample evidence that there has been exploitation.  Perhaps it is a sad reflection on the state of society in Ireland today that the places which seem to present the greatest evidence of this exploitation are themselves the greatest evidence of a decline of standards.  There is a lot of money spent on alcohol and beverages for many hours and there are extensions until 12.30 a.m. and 1.30 in the morning in these places.  Perhaps that is a reflection on the State as a whole but we must remember that children, particularly school children, are innocent in this whole matter.  The pressures are on them to go out and seek employment.  If it was left to themselves they would far prefer to be out kicking a football around the streets perhaps.  It is up to the State to ensure that if there is employment for young persons it is monitored and scrutinised continuously.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="602" /> As regards the inspectorate which the Minister mentioned, I should like him to give some information in his reply on the success or otherwise of the inspectorate in pursuing blatant exploitation of school children in regard to employment.  If there have been prosecutions, how many, how often and what are the findings of the inspectors in regard to the number of young people working during the day and working late at night?  What has been the experience of the inspectorate regarding the wages given in these instances?  All these matters are covered comprehensively in existing legislation. The employer is supposed to put in a prominent permanent place an extract from the Act.  He is supposed to keep a register giving all the information which I have mentioned, namely the ages of the school children, the wages they have received and the hours they have worked.</P>
    <P>All that information should be available to the Department.  Perhaps the Minister will give some information in his reply as to what information he had compiled by his inspectorate in regard to these matters.  A vote of gratitude is due to the bodies who have done surveys over the past number of years, starting with that survey that was carried out in Drogheda six years ago.  It will be necessary to have a continuing monitoring of what is happening under this legislation.  There is no point in putting legislation on to the Statute Book if we are not going to see it enforced and applied. Young employed persons, right down through history&mdash;indeed it was chronicled by famous novelists such as Charles Dickens&mdash;have been most prone to exploitation.  It is necessary that the State should scrutinise this matter very closely.  I welcome the surveys that have been done by the various bodies.  I would ask them to continue such surveys in the next 12 months so that when the Minister comes to have this legislation modified in 1981 we will have up to date information available that will enable us, perhaps, to bring in certain amendments which will keep a strict eye on what is <Col N="603" /> happening regarding the employment of young people.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>What is revealed when one looks at the real situation about the employment of young people in Ireland is obscene.  Senator Markey has done us a service in referring to previous surveys carried out by different bodies.  We have all received, in the very recent past, a survey carried out by the Dublin District Council Youth Committee of the Irish Transport and General Workers' Union.  We are vastly in their debt for the work they have done and on which I am going to spend a little time putting it on to the record of the House. The sort of initiative that they have shown and the sort of information that they have provided is exceedingly valuable.  Historically, exploitation is always sharpest on those least able to defend themselves: historically, they have been women and children.  We are acquainted, as Senator Markey said, with the polemic writings of Dickens and others more than a century ago on the question of the exploitation of children.</P>
      <P>I find it nauseating, in a country with the ready profession of Christianity that we find on all sides here that the exploitation of children seems to have diminished very little in its ruthlessness. While I do not attempt to apportion blame in this regard to individual administrations or individual Ministers, I think that we have really shattering complacency on the part of the Minister of State and on the part of his Minister.</P>
      <P>On 13 June last year we were discussing the extension of this order for a further year.  The following sentence occurs. I want to read it in full because I want to compare it with what the Minister of State has read out to us now. On 13 June 1979, the Minister, Deputy Gene Fitzgerald said:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>However, my Department's experience in the enforcement of the Act since it came into operation almost two years ago has not revealed evidence of any significant degree of <Col N="604" /> exploitation of children in employment during school term.</P>
    <P>But the Minister of State said to us a few minutes ago&mdash;it is interesting to see the little bits of fiddling with the text that civil servants do at times, I wonder why they fiddle in the way they do&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>However, the experience of my Department in the enforcement of the Act since it came into operation almost three years ago, has not revealed evidence of any significant degree of exploitation of children in employment during school term or at any other time.</P>
    <P>There is one version at the beginning. There is the addition of &ldquo;any other time&rdquo; at the end of the sentence and there is the substitution of &ldquo;three&rdquo; for &ldquo;two&rdquo;.  We are all a year older and neither the Minister of State nor, apparently, the Minister or his servants, have learned anything in that year.</P>
    <P>The real situation is known to many people and is so scandalous and so public that it was in the early autumn of last year&mdash;even though we have only received the ITGWU Youth Committee report within recent days&mdash;that these investigations were undertaken into a situation which surely every public representative knows happens on a large and scandalous scale.  I utter those words in anger but they are not carelessly chosen.  It happens on a large and scandalous scale and every public representative knows it.  That I affirm.  Those who wrote the Minister's speech apparently do not know it.  I do not mean to pillory them as individuals.  They cannot defend themselves.  Perhaps their Minister will do it for them.</P>
    <P>What the people in the transport union did was something that, apparently, the Minister's inspectors cannot do. Senator Markey asked the Minister of State for figures of investigations, inspections and prosecutions.  I have figures which perhaps the Minister would either confirm, amplify or deny that in the last three years there have been approximately 1,500 inspections, an approximate rate of 500 a year, two successful <Col N="605" /> prosecutions and four pending.  I do not know how big the inspectorate is or how many hours a year they give to this.  It would be interesting to know because the exploitation of children is an important social issue.  There is no putting that aside.  What they did was simply to look, by means of questionnaire, at two schools in south County Dublin, both boys' schools in working class areas, a total of 310 students offering for group intermediate and leaving certificates.  I am not going to put a lot of statistics on the record.  They emphasise properly, and we must emphasise, that this is an extremely limited survey and it does not claim to be comprehensive or rigorous. The figures in it are no more than a guide, but they are so appalling that they at least tell us the approximate nature of the problem.  In my view, they confirm what every public representative knows. Of the people questioned in that survey, 77 per cent&mdash;I will round off the per centages&mdash;never heard of the Protection Act of which we are now extending a section, 90 per cent had never seen a notice of the Act, although that is a statutory requirement, 77 per cent had never been asked for a parent's permission, and 75 per cent had never been asked for a birth certificate.  That corresponds with many people's experience.</P>
    <P>How does that compare with the statement of June 1979 which I read on to the record that experience did not reveal evidence of any significant degree of exploitation?  How does it compare with the situation a year later?  What are these inspectors doing?  We know, from our own experience, that there is a real problem.</P>
    <P>A survey done in this way revealed that there is a problem in very specific and concise terms.  The number of relevant people was only 310.  It is revealed that the great majority worked in lounge bars.  This is a part of our society and our life and we can have our private opinions as to whether an appropriate percentage of people's incomes is spent on drink and is spent specifically in pubs. We are entitled to ask if the hours worked are excessive, if the time the <Col N="606" /> hours are worked is in school term, that the times at which those hours are worked are not permissible hours under the law for people under 15 and older people.  If we know that that is the situation, what do we think it does to those 14 and 15 year olds to experience the atmosphere in many lounge bars at that time of the night?</P>
    <P>I believe passionately that school children ought to work, the earlier they are introduced to the habit of work the better.  The separation of school and work is bad.  Since there is no minimum wage we are not choosing the work which has an educational benefit for these people, we are letting them be used as cheap labour, in work which is exceedingly bad for them.  We are being asked to extend this order for another year.  The employment of people under 15 in a whole category of employments, including employments associated with the serving of drink, should not happen at all.</P>
    <P>There are many forms of occupation where young people could and would find work, and there would be persons anxious to employ them, where it would be beneficial&mdash;almost everything in the countryside relating to farming, fishing and a whole number of craft industries, all magnificient things for school children to do which they would love to do and benefit from doing.  Since there is no minimum remuneration for these children they are simply used as cheap labour, in the jobs that are dullest and are morally worst for them and that are most inclined to switch them off in regard to work and to their prospects in life.  What we are, in fact, doing is setting up a machine to create&mdash;it is a tribute to their homes that it works in so few cases&mdash;the sort of delinquents who will cost the State a great deal of money later on.  It is not even intelligent economically, however wicked it is, because it is creating further charges in further sectors, in further times of the individual's life.</P>
    <P>It is appalling.  No words that we would utter are strong enough for the scandal that this constitutes in our <Col N="607" /> society.  While I note the reservations&mdash;I am glad to see them&mdash;I note with pleasure the promise of a revision.  I think it appalling that there was firstly a two year period, 1977 to 1979, and then a year ago we had the Minister for Labour saying &ldquo;May I have one more year?&rdquo;  Now we have the Minister of State saying &ldquo;May I have one more year&rdquo;? The fact is shocking, but we need not be surprised if we know the history of what one would politely call private enterprise. If it is possible to exploit a defenceless group in society, private enterprise exploits them.  That is the norm of the society we live in with its attitudes and morals.  That is not surprising, however disgusting it may be.</P>
    <P>It is surprising and it is shocking that there is a statement repeated a year later, initially made in the face of a fairly large amount of evidence to the contrary, that the Minister and the Minister's servants were simply not aware of any significant degree of exploitation of children.  That is what the Minister said again today.  I find that complacent and flying in the face of experience and indeed flying in the face of a certain amount of imprecise documentation.  I find that shocking and distressing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDowling" hpid="Mr. Dowling Mr. Dowling">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowling</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to add my voice to the voice of other Senators in relation to this legislation.  It is very important and sensitive legislation.  It is necessary and desirable to update legislation.  A survey of widespread variety is important from the department's point of view.  We are dealing with the weakest section of the community. I applaud the trade unions who carry out surveys into the conditions of young people and many trade unionists themselves are working in places of employment where young people are being exploited.  The terrible tragedy is that the trade unionists at that particular stage are prepared to deal with the problems that affect adults, while these people are unorganised to a large degree and are being exploited.  They continue to allow them to be exploited.  The trade unions as a whole have a responsibility to ensure <Col N="608" /> that young people who are not members of trade unions get some protection at their place of employment from the trade unions.  Trade unionists, whether in pubs or workshops or elsewhere, have a very grave responsibility to ensure that where the workforce is being exploited they take appropriate steps.  While surveys and reports are all very fine, the place to stop the rot is at the job centre.</P>
      <P>I hope that the trade unions will take the same type of interest that has been taken here in relation to the compiling of a report and that they will not rely just on a report but that appropriate action will be taken against unscrupulous employers. Many employers, if they had their way, would participate in this baby farming racket that has gone on for many and many a day in many a centre. Baby farming has become a way of life with some employers, cheap labour and exploitation of the young.</P>
      <P>Every effort is made by the Act to protect, in so far as the conditions are laid down: having a birth certificate, obtaining the written permission of the parents or guardian, starting and stopping times and the wages paid.  Responsible employers will meet that situation, but unscrupulous employers will not conform.  They are the most difficult to get at, the ones that give them a few bob here and a few bob there, where there is no set wage, and take advantage because of the geographical location or because of other factors.  In many cases young children have stayed away from school because unscrupulous employers had attracted them in such a way that there was no record and they just get a few bob.  While lounge bars have been mentioned, a particular section who were very concerned when this Act was brought in were the jam factories where it is traditional that during the summer holidays young persons under the age of 15 are employed to pick fruit.  They put forward a very good case to show how young people are employed, the conditions under which they are employed, the pay rate and how they conform with the regulations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Unfortunately it is the unscrupulous <Col N="609" /> employer who the factory inspector will almost find it impossible to get at, because he is hidden away, insulated and safeguarded, and it is he who has been exploiting the young people all along.  I would ask the Minister to take into consideration, quite apart altogether from the responsible employer, that the greatest exploitation takes place outside the area where there is free access by factory inspectors or by other personnel. The trade unions should give a lead here and take up their case, just as they take up the cases of persons who are in a position to pay union dues.  As trade unionists, we have a responsibility to ensure that exploitation does not take place in our area of employment.  We have a very important responsibility to ensure that every single sector of the employment area is sealed off to some degree.</P>
    <P>Irresponsible employers cover up accidents and at no stage do they meet the requirements of the Act.  What Senator Keating said is quite true, that there are people who continue to exploit, and I hope that the Minister will now expedite the revision of this legislation and take into consideration the factors that have been raised here.  It certainly is the most difficult one to detect, and where this difficulty exists there will have to be new thinking in relation to this type of exploitation.</P>
    <P>I hope that in the re-assessment of the Act that is taking place that due regard will be taken of the people who remove themselves so far that they cannot be detected.  I am sure the Department are aware that there are employers who entice young people from school, sometimes in remote areas and sometimes in less remote areas.  If more inspectors are required, or a deeper study is required, that deeper study should take place at this stage.  It would be wrong to come back in a year's time and look for additional extensions.  The Minister must act now and further amendments can take place in the light of the situation as it develops.</P>
    <P>I urge the Minister, as other Senators have urged him, to ensure that the Department, at the earliest possible moment, <Col N="610" /> will produce something that will alleviate the distress that is being caused by the unscrupulous section of the community. I hope that shortly the Minister will be in a position to come forward with legislation that will bring relief and that will give the inspectors a greater degree of freedom to ensure that we track down the people who are exploiting the young.  There is no doubt that this is happening and surveys have indicated that it is happening.  It is a fairly broad situation and every aspect has to be examined.  Consultation with school teachers and the principals of schools in various areas is a factor that should be considered, to get their view.  I am quite sure that many of the school principals know of the enticement and will be able, maybe to a much greater degree than the inspectors, to throw some light on a problem that is a very serious one.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity of contributing to the discussion on this motion which is dealing with the protection of young people in employment. Let me say, before I go on to discuss it, that it is my first occasion to speak in the presence of the Minister in this House, and I would like to welcome him here and wish him well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the matter we are discussing, I would like to make this comment.  The discussions we have had quite rightly put the emphasis on conditions and on the exploitation that exists in places of employment for young people.  It is proper that the emphasis should be put there, but equally I feel that it is important that we would also discuss and give a certain relevance to the conditions that create the situation which push young people on to the labour market.  There are a number of reasons for this.  There is, first of all, in the consumer society in which we live, the pressure that can be put on people even of tender years to earn pocket money, and the pressure to obtain finance to purchase the things they desire to have and which their parents cannot afford to give them.  There is a certain encouragement on the part of <Col N="611" /> parents to have their children seek part-time employment at an early age.</P>
    <P>I feel that some parents view the question of children doing part-time work at an early age as having a duel advantage. It means that part of the earnings, small as they can be, is returned to the parents and makes a contribution to the family budget.  There is also the fact that the remainder of that money which is earned by the young person, which will be used as pocket money, eliminates the necessity of the parent having to provide that money.  Therefore, we should not ignore that some parents encourage their children to go out and seek part-time jobs.</P>
    <P>There is also the fact, of course, that we are unique in the situation that a very high proportion of our population are young people and, that being so, the tendency of young people to seek part-time jobs is a situation which is going to be with us for some time.  Therefore, I support the call that has been made to ensure that the legislation is directed wherever possible, and whenever possible, to ensure that young people in part-time employment are not in a situation where they can be exploited.</P>
    <P>One of the other reasons that creates pressure on young people to work is the society we live in.  High-powered advertising through the media focuses on certain articles, be it clothing, records, or something like that, and creates a desire on the part of the young person to have a particular article.  Perhaps, coming from a home where the family budget cannot enable the young person to have the money for that, you have the pressure to go out and get part-time jobs. You have also the long summer holidays. I have heard it said that children at secondary school find it difficult to face the monotony of a three months holiday. I think it is a peculiar attitude of mind but nonetheless it is there.  In relation to that particular bracket of young people the pressure is there to find something to relieve what they regard as the monotony and they are again on the <Col N="612" /> market and they are seeking these part-time jobs.</P>
    <P>I want to tie in with that an attitude that I have heard described by parents which to a certain extent disturbs me: it is that they would find it difficult to put up with their children being continually around the house for a three-month period.  It is an attitude that certainly disturbs me, and it probably raises the moral question that as a society we have failed.  We have failed these young people by not providing and by not seeking to establish the facilities at the outset that would occupy the leisure time of these young students.</P>
    <P>The question has been raised also in relation to part-time employment of young people as to whether young people should be allowed to work on school days.  My attitude to that is quite simple: I do not believe they should.  I believe that going to secondary school, indeed while going to any school, the teenagers have their hours that they must spend at school; they need a few hours of recreation and they need a few hours of study, and unless their education is going to be interfered with quite severely they cannot afford to engage in a part-time job at the same time. Therefore, as far as I am concerned part-time jobs during school days or school evenings, are something that I disapprove of and I do not think they should in fact be tolerated.  A number of studies have been referred to but I have found interesting this particular one that we received in the post this morning from the Dublin District Council Youth Committee of the Transport and General Workers Union&mdash;School Survey Report.</P>
    <P>In the short time available to me to look through it, I have found it to be an interesting document, and I want in particular to refer to what the survey has described as the extreme examples of the wages that they have found being paid to young people in part-time employment. And, as far as I am concerned, a wage or a figure of 37p per hour, a weekend for £6, another weekend as a milk round helper at £5 and a 14-year-old working at 65p an hour is without question exploitation. <Col N="613" /> These are scandalous wages to offer to any youth or young person.  I believe that there is a need to look very closely at the question of a minimum wage because even though, as the survey has indicated, these are extreme cases, nonetheless they do exist and it is scandalous exploitation to offer that kind of wages for the hours and the weekend to any young persons.</P>
    <P>I noticed with interest the jobs and employment available, according to the survey, to young people, listed under eight headings.  Somewhere, somebody else commented that going to work at an early age would be an advantage to young people in deciding their career of the future, but quite honestly I do not think that working as a lounge boy, as a garage helper or petrol pump attendant, in a chip shop or in a restaurant, as a milk roundsman, a glass-washer or a packer in a supermarket&mdash;which are the top six categories identified here&mdash;would help a young person to gain useful experience. I doubt if they would receive much encouragement to regard any of these occupations as a future career.</P>
    <P>A Senator referred earlier here to the fact of young people under 15 years being employed in lounges.  The fact, of course, is that they should not be so employed on two grounds: if they are employed as lounge boys during the hours that lounges normally operate they are operating beyond the hours which are permitted under the legislation we are talking about for young persons, and secondly, as far as the licensing laws are concerned no person under 15 years of age may be in a lounge bar or a public house.  Under both these headings it is illegal that young people should be employed in loung bars at the hours when they are employed, or employed at all if they are under 15 years of age.</P>
    <P>I hope that the Minister, when he returns in the reasonably near future equipped with the outcome of the surveys and deliberations that are going on in his Department, will be in a position to put a comprehensive package before the Oireachtas which will be of benefit to <Col N="614" /> the categories of people that we are seeking to protect.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasWhitaker" hpid="Dr. Whitaker Dr. Whitaker">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Whitaker</NameTxt>
      <P>I merely want to register myself amongst those who would prefer that there should be a total ban on the employment of children under 15 years of age during the school term&mdash;at least during the school term.  I find it very difficult to believe that in our now largely urbanised society the employment of children of between 14 and 15 years even for limited periods is not likely to be inimical to their health, education and moral welfare.  Like Senator Howard I find it very hard to believe in this alleged wish of parents for the availability of a limited period of work outside school hours during school term, as a way of providing useful experience for young people in the process of deciding on careers.  That does not make any impact whatever on me, and particularly so in view of the disturbing indications in the ITGWU Dublin Youth Committee Survey of how in fact these children are largely employed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Howard has already spoken with proper disparagement of the likelihood of experience as a lounge boy and in other blind alley occupations being of any help in a worthwhile future career.  Also, I think that if employment of young people were of any real necessity as a means of adding to family income even in the poorest families, that point would have been brought out in the survey by the Dublin District Council Youth Committee of the ITGWU, but no such point is made.  In fact, the clear inference to be drawn from this survey is that only a fraction of the below-market earnings of these youngsters goes back to their parents and most of it is spent by way of addition to pocket money.  Some of it, unfortunately, even at that early age, is spent on drink.  I hope that when the survey which the Minister referred to is completed we will be prepared to take a more restrictive view about employment of young people.  I would urge that work should not be available at all for children under 15 years of age during school term.  If I understand correctly what the Minister said in his speech, <Col N="615" /> however, it appears that through some legal quirk we cannot actually oppose this order because if we do so we make the situation even worse because the limitation that applies at present on the number of hours that young people of 14 to 15 may work would disappear entirely. This is a Catch 22 situation which I hope will not last even another year.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to join in the strong criticism expressed by a number of Senators of the Government's approach to the protection of young employees and to the approach apparently adopted by the Minister for Labour in this House last year and the Minister of State here today.  Senator Keating has already referred to the almost identical texts the Minister used today and in June last year to renew by order subsection (3) of section 4 of the 1977 Act.  I would like to refer to some of the things said by the Minister in that debate a year ago. They are echoed here today but we have made no advance.  I think we have to look at the statements made to see where in the order of priority of the Government is the question of protection of young persons and specifically the protection of children against exploitation and abuse.  In the debate in this House last year&mdash;and I quote from Volume 92 of the Seanad Official Report, column 393&mdash;the Minister for Labour in his brief speech introducing the motion said:</P>
      <P>I should also mention that I intend during the coming 12 months to review this legislation, particularly in regard to a possible drafting defect in section 4.  An important point is that I have been advised that the lapse of section 4 (3) would not, in fact, result in a prohibition of the employment of children under 15 during school term as was apparently originally intended, but would allow such employment in work which fulfils the conditions set out in subsection (2)&mdash;the earlier ones to which I referred&mdash;but without any definite restrictions as to hours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="616" /> That is the legal quirk to which Senator Whitaker referred.  It was well known to the Minister a year ago when he referred to it in this House.  It is a minor drafting point.  Having read the section carefully, I think I agree that there is a minor drafting problem there but it is not one that poses any difficulties or need cause delay.  It is one that could have been amended without any difficulty if the political will had been there.  It appears that the Minister had some sense of priority at that time because in concluding at column 406 the Minister said:</P>
    <P>Finally, as I said in my opening contribution, I intend during the coming 12 months to review this legislation, particularly in regard to a possible drafting defect in section 4.  The lapse of the section would result now in no definite restriction applying in the case of hours.  This is important. We will obviously give the Seanad the opportunity of discussing this within the coming year.</P>
    <P>However obvious it may have been at that time to the Minister, we did not get the opportunity and apparently we are not going to get much opportunity today, because despite the fact that the Minister of State here today mentioned that a review has been taking place, he has given this House absolutely no details about the nature of that review. This is regrettable, because the only practical survey that Senators have at their disposal is a small but valuable survey carried out by the Dublin District Council Youth Committee of the Irish Transport and General Workers' Union.</P>
    <P>This survey has been referred to by I think every Senator who spoke because we all recognise the value of empirical research of that sort.  I think it is not adequate or sufficient that we discuss a motion to extend by order the operation of that section for a further year, having been told last year that a survey was going to be carried out by the Government, having been told this year that the survey is being carried out but being told absolutely nothing else.  If the survey has been genuinely carried out during the last year then the Minister must have <Col N="617" /> preliminary results from it and he can at least tell us what shape the survey is taking, which matters are being surveyed, where the areas of concentration are, how it is being approached and so on.  If this survey of the youth committee of the Transport Union can, by examining the position of boys in two schools in south Dublin, come up with as detailed a response and as adequate information as this then I think we deserve information from the Minister here in this House.</P>
    <P>We deserve it because in a press release following the submission to the Government of this survey by the transport union youth committee, the Minister did give some information&mdash;he gave more information than he has given here this afternoon&mdash;of the inspections that have been carried out.  In a press release issued by the Government, dated 28 May 1980 and referring specifically to this survey, it was stated and I quote:</P>
    <P>Commenting today on a survey of young people at work carried out by the Dublin District Youth Council of the ITGWU, the Department of Labour said there had been more than 1,500 inspections in connection with the Protection of Young Persons (Employment) Act since it came into force three years ago.  In addition, the Department's inspectors in the course of their countrywide inspections under the general worker protection legislation also investigated the position in regard to the Act.  There have been two successful prosecutions under the Act and papers have been sent to the Chief State Solicitor in four further cases while prosecutions are being considered in a number of other cases.</P>
    <P>The statement goes on:</P>
    <P>The Act was widely publicised at its coming into operation and a special poster was distributed to schools and youth organisations.</P>
    <P>It is quite clear from the survey carried out by the Youth Committee of the Irish Transport and General Workers' Union that the publication at the present time and as of September/October of last year when the survey was carried out is <Col N="618" /> totally inadequate.  That is one of the main conclusions which Senators have referred to arising out of this survey.  I will refer to the table at the end of that survey where the figures were that 77 per cent had never heard of the Protection Act, 90 per cent had never seen notice of the Act, 77 per cent were never asked for their parents' permission and 75 per cent were never asked for a birth certificate. We are not talking about a minority of the children and young persons who are to be protected by this legislation; we are talking about three-quarters of them, and in some cases over three-quarters of them in this particular survey did not know of the provisions of the Act and obviously it was not being brought to their attention and they were not getting the protection that they should have been receiving.</P>
    <P>Since we are caught in the cleft stick of not being able to oppose this order on this occasion because of the technical drafting defect that has been known to the Minister and his Government for well over a year, if not earlier, all we can do, and it is important to do it, is to hope that the Minister in his reply will give us much more information about the survey that has been carried out by the Department in the last 12 months.</P>
    <P>First of all, in relation to the 1,500 inspections carried out under the Act, how many of these inspections were carried out after 8 p.m.?  One of the important protections which is intended to be afforded by this legislation is that children under the age of 16 do not work and may not be employed after 8 p.m.  In the case of children from 16 to 18 they may not be employed after 10 p.m.  Yet, we see from the survey that one of the main types of employment of the children and young persons interviewed in this particular survey was in lounge bars and similar places.  In the appendix dealing with this, Appendix No. 3 of the survey, dealing with the protections of the Act, it refers to the fact that children under 15 may not work after 8 p.m. but of the 27 children under 15 years who were working and who were interviewed in this survey all worked after 8 p.m.  That is the <Col N="619" /> first point I would make, that it is extremely important that both the inspectorate of the Department and the survey of the Act by the Department place a great deal of emphasis on checking the enforcement of the Act after 8 p.m.  In the case of those aged between 16 and 18, where the Act provides that they may not be employed after 10 p.m., all those who were working and who responded to the survey worked after 10 p.m.  In the case of the under 18-year-olds who may not work on Saturday and Sunday, 21 of the under-18-year-olds, 21 of the 27, worked on both Saturday and Sunday.  In the case of the under-15-year-olds working during term, where the Act says that they may not be employed for more than two hours a day, the average hours worked were four-and-a-half hours per day.</P>
    <P>We are not talking about a small handful within this survey of cases where there were transgressions of the Act.  We are talking about a blatant disregard for the protection of the Act and we are talking about the majority of children and young people covered by the survey who were working in conditions which were in fact in breach of the statutes, where the employers were in theory at least committing offences and where there appears to have been no adequate follow-up.</P>
    <P>Like Senator Keating, I find it very hard to believe that the Minister last year and with almost identical wording this year can come in and say that his Department have not become aware of any evidence of substantial breaches of the Act in so far as it protects children under 15 or young persons in their employment. Like him, I do not need a survey although it is very helpful to have a survey giving the empirical research; like him I know of cases where particularly in lounge bars and public houses children under 15 are working late hours and in particular young persons under 18 are working after 10 p.m.  We all know that and yet there is not enforcement of the legislation.</P>
    <P>The Minister, to say the least, does <Col N="620" /> not come with clean hands in seeking a further extension of this order; he does not give us any more information than the Minister for Labour gave here a year ago.  He does not give us any details of this survey which is being carried out by the Department.  We hope he will give us some details in his response.  He does not really convey the kind of concern for those involved, for children who are undoubtedly being exploited.  They are being exploited because there is not any minimum wage; they are being exploited because there is not enforcement of the hours; they are being exploited because they are working at night time after the hours when the Act prohibits them from being employed, and they are being exploited because they are working on both Saturday and Sunday on average although this is prohibited by the Act.  This is a very grave indictment, and when laws are enacted and so flagrantly violated then they not only fail to achieve the purpose of the legislation but respect for the law and respect for the purposes of legislation is undermined.</P>
    <P>I would agree with Senator Whitaker: I think that the survey produced by the Irish Transport and General Workers Union is very interesting in the evidence that it gives of both the wages received and how the money was spent.  It seems, looking at this, that the main pressure on the youngsters has been a consumer pressure.  The survey shows that although the students of the schools spent their earnings in a fairly varied way, only a small number gave any significant amount of their earnings to their parents and that most of them spent the money on clothes, records and drink.  It was very much consumer-orientated, very much representative of the pressure on the kind of society we live in, the pressure of advertising, the pressure to have the pocket money to buy these things.  This counters whatever purpose there may have been in allowing children, particularly children under school leaving age, under 15, a very low school leaving age, to work in school term, and there is no evidence of the kind of training and work experience which <Col N="621" /> many parents would welcome, which I think is now very much part of a broader approach to the education of young people which will help to equip them for adult life and for employment and for coping with the stresses and strains of seeking employment and adapting to work.</P>
    <P>This is not what is evidenced by this survey or what appears to be resulting from the provisions of this Act.  It is not tending to encourage the provision of useful work experience and training for youngsters.  It is tending to allow them to be exploited, exploited both in the very minimal wages they are getting and in the kind of dead-end and, as many Senators have said, inappropriate work which they are doing.  I note from the Act itself, the 1977 Act, from section 4, that it is open to the Minister to make an order.  Under section 4 subsection (8) it is provided that the Minister may by order declare any form of work specified in the order to be work which is not light, nonindustrial work, and any work which stands so declared shall be deemed for the purpose of this section to be work to do which a child cannot be employed.  In other words the Minister has it in his power to make an order excluding certain types of work even under the existing provisions of the Act.</P>
    <P>I would like to ask the Minister whether this has been contemplated, whether this aspect of the potential safeguards of the Act forms part of the survey and whether we can expect a definite commitment from him and from the Department that legislation will be brought in within this year.  There is a credibility gap; we were told last year that we were likely to see legislation within this current year; we have not seen it; are we going to see it, or only in the form of a further order next year?  If that is to be the case, certainly the Labour group would have to think very seriously about either a Private Members' Bill or, alternatively, opposing any further extension under the terms which we have seen at the moment.  It was not the original purpose of the legislation.  The legislation is clearly drafted in such a <Col N="622" /> way that the provision for allowing employment of under-15-year-olds during school hours was only to be a temporary provision and it is clear from the text of section 4 that it was intended to be phased out.  It was intended to lapse after two years unless renewed.  It was renewed once last year and it is coming up for second renewal this year.</P>
    <P>This is going in the face of what was a legislative attempt at the time; we are doing it without any adequate knowledge, without any evidence of the Government's survey and unfortunately with considerable evidence of flagrant abuse, of lack of enforcement of protective controls and of exploitation of the children involved.  This is a very serious matter, and I am glad that so much criticism has been expressed by different Senators and, as I say, I hope the Minister will take the opportunity to put much more factual material on the record of the House in his reply by telling us exactly what kind of survey his Department have been carrying out, what is the scope of it, what are the preliminary results of it and when he will be in a position to publish it, because if the Minister for Labour was already talking about it last year then something must have been done in the intervening 12 months.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Míchéal Cranitch Míchéal Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Míchéal Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think I would have spoken at all but for the constant repetition of so-called evidence regarding exploitation of our youth on a large scale.  It seems to be based mainly on a survey entitled &ldquo;Dublin District Council Youth Committee ITGWU School Survey Report&rdquo;.  Interestingly enough, that report concludes:</P>
      <P>As outlined in the introduction this is a very limited survey.  However, even the statistics from these two schools alone show many disquieting features....</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Those two schools in the city of Dublin were the basis to slate the Minister, the Government and all concerned. We are all against exploitation no matter where it takes place or against whom. <Col N="623" /> Exploitation does take place, it always did and always will.  Never in our history has there been so much exploitation as there is presently of adults and children. The travelling public are being exploited and not long ago during bus disputes they were exploited.  More recently the sick and aged in hospitals and elsewhere were being exploited.</P>
    <P>The Minister has been adversely criticised for not bringing the report of the Government survey into existence before now.  In my view no Minister in the Government has been working harder and for longer hours trying to prevent exploitation on a huge scale right across the human spectrum than the Minister for Labour.  Every Member is against the exploitation of children. Where there is evidence of children being exploited it should be brought to the attention of the proper authorities and acted upon immediately.  I have no doubt that it would be acted upon.  Is it the view of many of the speakers that there is something against children working at all?  From my own experience of life&mdash;I have been dealing with children and their parents in a close way&mdash;the sooner children learn to work and love work the better.  That should not be lost sight of.  I know of many children in my area who work at home, on their land, and help neighbours and enjoy it.  Apart from whatever small monetary reward they get for that they have an experience of life and a love of work that will stand to them forever.  Those children when they grow up will be the better for their experience of work and less inclined to depend on drugs and so on that so many people who are not used to work have to fall back on.</P>
    <P>This discussion could be interesting and useful, but a proper balance should be kept right through.  The sooner we begin to love work the better.  On the other hand, exploitation, where it occurs, should be made known to the authorities and acted upon effectively.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AndyOBrien" hpid="Mr. O'Brien Mr. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>The motion seeks permission to continue in force for a further period of 12 months section 4 (3) of the <Col N="624" /> Protection of Young Persons (Employment) Act, 1977.  The fact that it is for a brief period of 12 months means that I support it, but that support is given only because a full scale review of the Act with a view to its amendment is taking place in the Minister's Department.  I hope we can be certain that the results of that review will be made known as soon as possible and that the Minister will then set about introducing a Bill that will clear up the situation that exists with regard to the employment of youth at present.</P>
      <P>There is material in this limited survey carried out by the Dublin District Council Youth Committee of the ITGWU that should cause great concern to the Minister and Members of this House.  I am sure we can take many of the statements as accurate.  That report states:</P>
      <P>The most staggering indication which arose from the survey was the general lack of knowledge of the Act and blatant breaches of it.</P>
      <P>The report substantiated that statement by figures in an appendix.  These figures should be a matter of great concern to us all.  The vast majority of our citizens would be opposed to the ages of those involved in working, the hours they work, the situation they work in such as lounge bars and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is most essential that the review being carried out is wide-ranging and that people with experience of dealing with youth are given every opportunity to put their views forward.  What are the views of teachers and social workers about the contribution young people at work make to the drop-out rates in schools?  There has been for a considerable time a disturbing drop-out rate in vocational schools, and a relatively small percentage of those who enrol finish their five years.  I should like to know, on the best authority that can be found, the contribution youth at work make to this drop-out rate from schools.  I should like to have the opinion of teachers and others concerned with youth as to the rate of progress being made by students who do not drop off but continue at <Col N="625" /> school in a part-time fashion and keep a job at the same time.  What is the opinion of teachers with regard to the number of pupils who are engaged in youth employment but fail to reach their potential in their second level course?  Those are matters of grave concern, and for that reason I hope the review will be thorough and very wide-ranging.</P>
    <P>As a result of recommendations made by that ITGWU committee, or as a result of the opinions put forward or the facts given by them I hope we will be in a position next year, or earlier, if possible to deal with this problem as it should be dealt with.  I agree partly with what Senator Cranitch said about work, in certain circumstances, doing children good.  We all know that on the family farm or in the family business the young people contribute to the work done.  It does them good, gives them an interest in life and an awareness of the need to contribute their share.  That is completely different from taking young people out of their own homes, away from parental supervision and putting them in to work in lounge bars, chip shops, hotels or places like that.</P>
    <P>It is disturbing to think that in many cases those young people work very late hours.  That is injurious to their health and it denies them an opportunity of pursuing their studies.  In addition, it has them spending too many hours during a very formative period of their lives in the wrong atmosphere.  Those points deserve close examination.  I hope that the Minister will see to it that the review body will take this study on a very broad base, that it will be examined carefully and in great depth.  The opinions of people who by their business or profession are in a special position to know a good deal about this problem should be sought.  I think we will be given an opportunity of enacting legislation that will cater in an advanced way for this problem of young people at work in the near future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ValentineJago" hpid="Mr. Jago Mr. Jago">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jago</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Keating quoted the Minister and the Minister of State as saying that there was no great indication <Col N="626" /> of exploitation.  He also said that practically every Member of the Oireachtas should be aware of the exploitation.  I am not aware of it.  The only area I can talk about it Cork city.  I have been in several lounge bars but I have not seen any boys or glass-washers there.  I have seen milk lorries going around, and while in the old days one always saw a boy helping the milkman one does not see any boys doing that work today.  I am associated with the bakery trade and I am aware that any boys employed by the trade in Cork city in a recognised bakery are covered by agreements with the Irish Transport and General Workers' Union and they work in conditions governed by legislation.  I have seen boys working at petrol pumps but from my experience I could not say there is great exploitation.</P>
      <P>I may be wrong, but generally, how does one get a complaint if there is something wrong?  If a consumer is overcharged or gets less weight than he should, that consumer complains.  The report of the Dublin District Council Youth Committee does not tell us who sought the job.  Was it the employer who advertised a vacancy, looking for somebody to do the work?  Was it the young people who persuaded employers to take them on so that they could earn some money for clothes, entertainment, drink and sweets or records?  The report does not tell us that or whether parents influenced children to ask for a job.  Only three people were concerned.  When there appear to be no complaints coming what can one say?  In many cases it appears to be young people looking for pocket money who seek jobs.  They do not know what they are entitled to and it is probable that the employer in the case is not giving them full-time pay for the number of hours they work.  I do not think from the evidence we have, even with this report, that any Member can say there is great exploitation throughout the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Having read this report and from learning what young people spend their money on, I agree with Senator Whitaker that there may be a case that <Col N="627" /> people under 15 years of age should not be allowed to work at all.  There may be a case for a general review.  That would be very difficult to legislate for.  Out of school there are jobs, for instance, at fruit picking for jam-making, in good weather.  That is good for children. Should we stop that by legislation?  Is there something wrong with children doing that when on holidays?  I cannot see great exploitation.  The Minister has said there will be a review and I agree with that decision.  There should be a review because there may be certain things that require changing but I do not think that this report gives us any evidence because it is not comprehensive enough and has not asked all the right questions.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardConroy" hpid="Professor Conroy Professor Conroy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Conroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to associate myself with Senator Jago's words.  While we are not specifically discussing this report one must congratulate the ITGWU for a very responsible report.  However, it is one which they indicate was on a limited sample and very much on a pilot basis.  It is excellent to see a trade union producing such a responsible and worthwhile report on such an important topic.  I regret to hear some of my colleagues extrapolating that into the most astonishing comments about exploitation. One would think we were back in the Victorian days.  This is not the case. Undoubtedly, there are some areas where there is some degree of exploitation. This is very much to be deplored and I am glad the Minister is to take steps in this respect.  Any legislation introduced should be in a manner which takes the whole situation into account and should not be unduly restrictive.  The object of such legislation should be the genuine protection, welfare and good of young people and our society as a whole. It is all too easy to bring in restrictions, congratulate ourselves and be very righteous about it, not realising that by being so restrictive we are preventing young people, who would be far better off doing a worthwhile job in appropriate conditions of protection and with appropriate and good remuneration, <Col N="628" /> from undertaking work and employers from employing them.  If we are unduly restrictive we then comdemn those children to a life on the streets, into a state of lawlessness and idleness which we are so quick to condemn in other respects.</P>
      <P>While supporting this legislation and congratulating the ITGWU on their excellent work on this report, I nonetheless strongly urge the Minister and the Minister of State, to take a broad and balanced view when further legislation is introduced.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Labour (Mr. Daly) Minister of State at the Department of Labour (Mr. Daly)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Labour (Mr. Daly)</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to express my thanks to the Senators who contributed in a constructive way to this debate.  I will ensure that the remarks made are brought to the notice of the committee at present reviewing the operation of the Act.  The Act came into operation in July 1977.  Initially, it was necessary to publicise its provisions in the media and by posters and advise employers, parents, schools and organisations concerned with young people of its main terms.  It was necessary to exhort them to ensure that young people taking up employment did not do so in breach of those provisions.  We circulated to all schools, primary and post-primary, and youth clubs documentation in relation to the provisions.  I will arrange to have this documentation in connection with provisions of the Act circulated to Deputies and Senators so that they will be more fully aware of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that documentation be sent also to local authority representatives.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  I was surprised to hear the remarks of Senator Keating who spoke of shattering complacency and exploitation on a large and scandalous scale.  If the Senator, who was supported by Senator Robinson on this, was aware of this situation he should have brought it to our attention.  If people know of this exploitation they should tell us about it. We do not want to evade our responsibility in this regard.  It is important to <Col N="629" /> record that there was only one official complaint from a public representative in relation to this Act.</P>
      <P>Questions were raised by Senator Markey about the definition of a young person and of a child.  A child is defined as being under 15 years of age, the school leaving age and a young person is described as being over 15 years of age and under 18.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that that calls for a change in the title of the Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>I will bring the Senator's views to the notice of those who are reviewing it.  The Act defines a young person and a child.  I was asked about the number of inspections.  In the course of their inspections in connection with general worker protection legislation, which are on a countrywise basis, the general inspectorate also investigate the position in regard to the Act.  In addition, they carry out specific inspections under the Act investigating complaints.  There are 17 general inspectors.  The industrial inspectorate in the course of routine inspections under the Factories Acts also investigate the position in regard to the Act dealing with young persons where young person are employed.  There are 47 industrial inspectors and the inspections are on a countrywide basis.</P>
      <P>When moving a similar motion last year to extend section 4 (3) the Minister said that it was his intention to review the Act during the subsequent 12 months.  This review has indicated other areas of possible amendment in the Act, apart from section 4 (3) such as the difficulty sometimes experienced by the inspectorate in obtaining proof of the age of a young person or the training of apprentices outside the hours prescribed by the Act.  It was considered that more experience of the operation of the Act would be necessary before decisions could be made as to amendments which should be carried out.  It was decided, therefore, to extend section 4 (3) for a further 12 months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Since the Act came into operation three years ago&mdash;Senator Markey <Col N="630" /> referred to this&mdash;about 240 breaches of the Act were dealt with.  Of these about 180 were as a result of investigations by Department inspectors and the balance resulted from complaints made to the Department.  Many were for minor breaches of the Act, non-display of the abstract, and when, on further investigations, the employer was found to be complying with the Act no further action was taken.  In other cases a subsequent inspection revealed that the employee had left the employment, had reached 18 years of age, or that the employer was complying with the Act.  There have been two successful prosecutions and in four other cases the papers have been sent to the Chief State Solicitor.  Further investigations are being carried out in a number of other cases.  Areas which are being considered by the committee at present&mdash;this is not a survey as Senator Robinson seems to think but a review of legislation, including section 4 (3)&mdash;include better enforcement, records, double employment, conflict between apprentice training and the Act and the display of the abstract.  We have no definite figures for inspections after 8 p.m. but there were at least a few hundred.  There would have been many more involving other legislation.  I welcome the suggestions put forward.  We expect the review to be completed soon and dealt with in the next session of the Dáil.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Packaged Goods (Quantity Control)" RHead="Bill, 1980: Order for Committee Stage">
    <Title>Packaged Goods (Quantity Control) Bill, 1980: Order for Committee Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are resuming debate on the question: &ldquo;That the Committee Stage be taken today&rdquo;.  Is it agreed to take Committee Stage now?</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Packaged Goods (Quantity Control) Bill," RHead="1980: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Packaged Goods (Quantity Control) Bill, 1980: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand apart of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Col N="631" />
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>The interpretation of the word &ldquo;container&rdquo; includes a bag, bottle, box, case, carton, envelope, net, sack or wrapper and also an inner container.  Is the Minister satisfied that this would cover the use of aerosol containers which can sometimes be used on their own without any outer packing or outer container?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Minister of State of the Department of Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. Meaney) Minister of State of the Department of Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. Meaney)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State of the Department of Industry, Commerce and Tourism (Mr. Meaney)</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the point the Senator is making?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the word &ldquo;container&rdquo; and its interpretation as outlined cover the use of an aerosol container which would not have an outer packing or an outer container?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>I would say yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>According to the section the word &ldquo;packer&rdquo; means, in relation to a package, the person who in the course of carrying on a business placed or caused to be placed in the container included in the package the goods so included and I should like to know if the Minister is satisfied that this interpretation would exempt a worker or employee on a factory premises.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  I am completely satisfied.  As a result of a discussion we had in the Dáil we went to extreme lengths to bring in an amendment to ensure that the worker on the floor, or the packer, would not be involved if there was any negligence found or criminal proceedings.  Our concern was to ensure that the worker, or the packer on the floor, would not be the person who could be prosecuted in any circumstances. That is why we introduced an amendment on those lines.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>From the wording it is not too clear that the worker or employee will be excluded from any responsibility or obligation.  The section states that &ldquo;the person who in the course of carrying on a business placed or caused to be placed in the container included in <Col N="632" /> the package the goods so included&rdquo;. What was the original wording?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>The original wording meant placing in the package.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>Were the words &ldquo;carrying on a business&rdquo; added?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>We wanted to indicate that the person carrying on the business, the proprietor of the package industry, was the one responsible.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 3 to 9, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 10.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 10 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to the points raised by Senators Keating, Brugha and others in relation to the dual marking of packages with metric and imperial quantities, I should like to inform the House that it will be in the regulations to be made under the Bill that the system to be used will be prescribed.  I promised to look into that and am prepared to give full consideration to the matter between now and when the regulations are made and to contact interested parties to see if, notwithstanding the reservations I expressed earlier, the points can be met.  I appreciate the co-operation of Senator Keating in facilitating the taking of Committee Stage today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>This section raises a query in regard to packing which I have seen displayed in shops in a language other than English or Irish.  There are a lot of imported articles from France, for instance.  One item&mdash;without identifying it&mdash;is totally and solely in French.  Is the Minister satisfied that this Bill gets over that sort of problem which can confront the consumer?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill is tied up with EEC directives to which I have alluded several times.  If Senators read them they will see how the points raised are <Col N="633" /> covered and what the definitions are under the directive.  As Senators probably are aware when the &ldquo;e-mark&rdquo; comes in it will give a right to sell goods throughout Europe.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 11 to 18, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 19.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 19 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>As regards the size and amount of the fines in the case of offences, £1,000 and in the case of a second and subsequent offence a fine not exceeding £10,000, these would appear to be large, and I wonder on what the Minister has based the size of the fine and what association there might be between the amount in this Bill and the amount of the fines in, for instance, the Act dealing with consumer information?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>As regards size, the maximum penalty of £10,000 on conviction and indictment, which really applies in a case of a second or subsequent offence, is the same as the maximum penalty provided in the Consumer Information Act, 1978.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>The same amount?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>The £1,000?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>The inspectors will act mostly in an advisory capacity, but if they meet a firm or a packer who is not anxious to co-operate and who will not co-operate then the crunch will come.</P>
      <P>The penalties have to be stiff all the way because by the time that would happen we would have given them a very fair hearing and given them every chance to rectify the situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>It says in the case of a first offence, if the inspectors call into a premises and see that the Act is not being complied with that is an offence.  In <Col N="634" /> that instance it appears to me that the inspectors have little option.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should not get mixed up between an offence and a prosecution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiBrugha" hpid="Mr. Brugha Mr. Brugha">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brugha</NameTxt>
      <P>What is intended there is that the inspector will give due notice of an infringement rather than prosecute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJVMeaney" hpid="Mr. Meaney Mr. Meaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meaney</NameTxt>
      <P>The inspectors will mostly be acting in an advisory capacity. They will point out the faults or defects and if there is no co-operation they will prosecute.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 20 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Agriculture (Amendment) Bill 1979:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Agriculture (Amendment) Bill 1979: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="LorcanAllen" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture (Mr. Allen) Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture (Mr. Allen)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture (Mr. Allen)</NameTxt>
      <P>The provisions of section 42 of the National Agriculture Advisory, Education and Research Authority Act, 1977, which were designed to introduce a system whereby 60 per cent of each county committee of agriculture would be members of the county council and the remaining 40 per cent chosen by voluntary rural organisations active in the county were found to be unworkable.  The section was amended by section 26 of the Agriculture (An Chomhairle Oiliúna Talmhaíochta) Act, 1979 which became law on 22 May 1979.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The reason section 42 of the 1977 Act was unworkable was already explained to this House during the passage of the 1979 Act.  Briefly, this was because the law provided that the total number of members of a committee of agriculture <Col N="635" /> could vary between three times and four times the number of county electoral areas.  This made it impossible for the Minister to designate in advance the number of members to be nominated by the various rural organisations.  The 1979 Act determined precisely that the number of members of a committee of agriculture would be four times the number of county electoral areas.</P>
    <P>Older legislation requires that the members of county committees must be appointed at the first meeting of each county council following a local election. Because of the late date on which the 1979 Act was passed and the very short interval between that date and the holding of the local elections on 7 June 1979, and the then current postal strike, there was not enough time to put the new arrangements into operation.  The result was that county committees of agriculture had to be appointed last June on the old basis and the new arrangements provided for in the 1979 Act would not be used until after the next local elections in five years time.  The Minister, however, announced at that time that the Government had decided to prepare legislation to enable the provisions of the 1977 and 1979 Acts to be brought into effect as soon as possible, thereby avoiding the delay of five years. He announced this on 15 June 1979 so that county councils, in nominating county committees of agriculture under the old system, would be aware that those committees would only have a short life and would be replaced by new committees when the legislation now before this Houss is enacted.</P>
    <P>In the context of An Chomhairle Oiliúna Talmhaíochta, which has now been set up, the functions of county committees of agriculture will be altered.  They will no longer have a direct involvement with the staffing aspects of the advisory or training services.  The committees will, however, have other important functions. They will retain responsibility for operating livestock improvement and certain other schemes for the assistance of farmers.  They will also have the function <Col N="636" /> of preparing, in conjunction with the chief agricultural officer, an annual county advisory and training programme.  Committees will also have the task of ensuring that An Chomhairle, as a national service, is also responsive to the needs of the agricultural community at local level.  With this altered involvement and responsibility of county committees, the inclusion of representatives nominated directly by voluntary rural organisations in each county will provide a necessary broadening of the spectrum of interests, knowledge and expertise of the members.</P>
    <P>This new Bill, therefore, provides for early reconstitution of committees of agriculture on the new 60-40 basis and, as a corollary, for the termination of the term of office of existing committee members.  The change will take effect in each county on the occasion of the first ordinary meeting of the county council after a date to be designated by the Minister when this Bill is enacted.</P>
    <P>I commend this Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>In giving the Bill a guarded welcome, I take the opportunity to welcome the Minister of State.  It is the first time that I have been involved in a discussion in his presence and I wish him well in his new post.</P>
      <P>This Bill is long overdue.  It is high time that the farming community, through the voluntary organisations, were given a say in the membership of the county committees of agriculture. The Bill has a certain number of defects but at this stage a reasonable Bill is better than no Bill at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the involvement and expertise of farmers who have to make a living from farming.  There is no doubt that any full-time farmer who has to go through the rigours of making a living from the land, is entitled to be a member of a county committee of agriculture.  It is a far cry from the days when we had all kinds of people who had not the slightest interest in agriculture and, while some of them made a contribution, others had no interest in it other than being on various <Col N="637" /> committees with all the attending possibilities they might have, for example, through expenses and so on.  Over the years the county committees of agriculture&mdash;I happen to be a member of one in Galway&mdash;have outlived their usefulness in the sense that the rate of progress in farming seems to have outpaced them.  At budget time in the committees of agriculture, one would have to get the go-ahead from Dublin to purchase a biro even though the committees are established by statute.  Through the Department of Finance, the activities of the county committees of agriculture have been very much curtailed.</P>
    <P>There is great potential for the new type of county committees envisaged here.  There are a certain number of politicians who would argue that 40 per cent is too great a percentage of people from voluntary organisations.  I do not agree with that.  I believe that there has to be a platform for people who are leaders in their own particular walks of life.  I hope they will make good use of it.</P>
    <P>There are a number of questions this Bill raises.  I read the passage of the Bill through the Dáil.  This was involved in the setting up of AnCOT some time ago. Who will define the number and kind of organisations that will be entitled to be on the board?  Who is to say that the 40 per cent would be drawn in a certain manner one way or another?  When the Bill was passing through the Dáil that question was not answered.  It is easy enough to create a situation where the fly-by-night organisations that mushroom up could be cut out.  What type of mechanism is there to ensure that a particular organisation does not decide to have the whole lot?  If there are a number of organisations that would like to be on this and if by allowing a member from each organisation on it it goes above 40 per cent, who decides to leave the one or two out?</P>
    <P>I sincerely hope, for the benefit of every farmer, that the new county committee of agriculture, under AnCOT and under the structure that is now taking shape, will have a more important role. It is true to say, if one wanted to be <Col N="638" /> cynical, that they are now only an advisory body.  If one looks at the legislation one will see that it is basically in an advisory capacity that they operate. Words like &ldquo;responsive to the needs of the local community&rdquo; could fall on very deaf ears if the bureaucracy that was involved begins to raise its ugly head again under the new director of AnCOT, for whom I have the highest personal regard.  I hope that he will not be hand-tripped by all types of bueaucracy of one type or another and that the obvious flare he has for Irish agriculture which he showed in the Agricultural Institute, will show through in the agricultural advisory service and all the training services that are so vitally important.</P>
    <P>Whatever else happens, the central and regional directors should be given a reasonably free hand, because there is a power of work to be done in the whole area of agricultural advisory work and agricultural education.  It is tragic that the Bill does not incorporate the Agricultural Institute under the one roof. I am amazed that the research wing of this important organisation will be left out.  I know that it is water under the bridge and there is nothing we can do about it here this evening, but I place on record my absolute regret that the institute is left out from under this umbrella.</P>
    <P>The stage has been reached where AnCOT will have a tremendous job to rejuvenate the framework and services that work for them on behalf of Irish farming. It is true to say that, despite the best efforts of all involved there was a certain sense of decay and frustration right through even down to the local agricultural adviser.  We have to hand it to them that, over the years, they have been an important factor in our agriculture advancement.  There is a certain degree of cynicism at this stage right through the various services.  I hope that the AnCOT people, who are now charged with the responsibility for them, will be in a position to get fire back into their bellies.</P>
    <P>Not many years ago a lot of people who worked in rural Ireland were not too worried about a 5 o'clock finish in <Col N="639" /> the evening or about overtime for lectures or whatever.  I know that times have changed and that one has to treat the farming folk in the same light as anybody else nowadays with the advent of television and so on.  But the time has come for people with enthusiasm and ambition, who are in the services, to be recognised and given various positions of trust.  If we are unable to get new entrants into agriculture trained to a certain degree of proficiency, there is no point in the world in talking about Irish farmers being able to compete with any farmers in Europe or anywhere else.  We are making reasonable progress but we are absolutely miles behind.</P>
    <P>I hope that the new county committees of agriculture will play a 100 per cent greater role in the activities of farming, in solving problems that beset all farmers and that reasonable note will be taken of what they have to say.  There is nothing so frustrating as to sit around a table for two or three hours one day a month&mdash;and there are many people listening to me today who are in a similar position&mdash;to be told that there are certain rules that govern particular situations or that there is no money for this, that or the other.  If 20 committed people in a county like Galway, or any other county, think that a certain line of action is good for the farmers of County Galway, it is only right and fair that people in higher authority would listen to what they have to say.  For the ten or 12 months that I have been on the Galway Committee of Agriculture I could not say that our views were listened to because we seem to be hitting our heads off a stone wall most of the time.  I am making that special appeal.  I welcome the Bill as far as it goes.  I will be delighted to see 40 per cent of the membership coming from the farming organisations.  I hope that they will accept the responsibility, do a good job and knit in nicely with the elected representatives.  From the point of view of the committee of agriculture, I hope all will be working for and on behalf of the particular county.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="640" /> Reference was made in the Minister's speech to the fact that one of the functions of the new county committees will be to draw up a plan of activity for the year for both training and advisory work.  The new AnCOT authority should not alone hope that this would happen, but should make sure that every committee of agriculture has a plan of action for the advisory service for that year.  There should be certain goals to be achieved and certain questions asked at the end of a period of time if they were not achieved.  The time has now come in this competitive age when all things can be measured to some degree or other.  A plan of action should be followed and, at the end of the day, the AnCOT authorities should have a full appraisal of the situation.  In any county that is not pulling its weight, no matter in what section, somebody should do some hard talking.</P>
    <P>I hope that the change means that the county committees of agriculture will mean far more in the future to farmers than they have in the past.  I am sorry that the institute are not involved and are not under the umbrella of the AnCOT authority.  Perhaps where the institute people are on the ground they might be given one of the seats on the committees of agriculture so that at least we would have a link with them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not commend the remarks of Senator Connaughton in connection with past members of committees of agriculture throughout the country.  I represent County Mayo and am a member of that committee for over 20 years.  I should like to pay tribute to the members of my committee for the work and talented effort they have put into the working of the Mayo Committee of Agriculture through the years.  We have embarked on many programmes, and I am delighted that our CAO at present, Mr. Paddy Brennan, has been selected as one of the regional managers under the new AnCOT Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Many people of different shades of political affiliation have represented the committee and given worthwhile service <Col N="641" /> in Mayo and worthwhile time to the agricultural industry.  Our pig producing programme, milk programmes and five year development plan for increasing livestock units are a major success and on stream and on target.  I should like to pay the highest tribute to the outgoing members of the old committees of agriculture.  I understand quite well that the Minister's delay in finalising this section is because of the reason mentioned in his opening speech.  I welcome the Minister and wish him every success in his Department.</P>
    <P>As regards the system of selection in the past, in Mayo at any rate it may have been done by the political parties.  I assure Senator Connaughton, who is very new in the field of activity of any committee, that the political parties in Mayo always selected men of the highest integrity and knowledge of agriculture in their own field who made a worthwhile contribution.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>They would all be Fianna Fáil?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I can answer that if the Senator likes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair would prefer if all Senators confined their remarks to the Bill before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a measure of doubt that the same will apply in the selection of the 40 per cent in the new AnCOT Bill.  If one gets a county council where there is a political majority and one picks 60 per cent of them from a party and the rural organisations pick another 40 per cent, possibly orientated to the same political party, then one will have, under the new AnCOT Bill, a political committee of agriculture. Whatever might be said about the old committees they were fairly distributed throughout the county and fairly representative of the whole community. They served a very useful role up to now.  We have only to await the results of the new committees and the production that we will receive from them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="642" /> I want to ask the Minister in connection with&mdash;I think I mentioned this before&mdash;rural organisations that will have membership of the various committees. While you take western committees such as those in Galway, Donegal, Sligo, Mayo, part of Kerry and Waterford, you have people who have their own county hill sheep organisations and are carrying out a great portion of the work of the committees of agriculture in the various counties I mentioned.  I would welcome especially people with high intensification of hill sheep farming who are representing that section of the agricultural sector who would be considered for membership in the 40 per cent mentioned under the Bill.</P>
    <P>I think that there are certain sections in the horse industry who are not nationally represented.  I feel that these people may not have access to the committees unless they are picked by political parties to represent them on the new AnCOT committees.  I would especially welcome the hill sheep farmers being represented and I feel that much useful work could be achieved for that section of the community.  They are going through a very lean time at the moment and have gone through a lean time in the past.  They should have a voice and I appeal to the Minister to give them a voice on the committees where there is a heavy concentration of hill farming, along the coast.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill, according to the Minister, is to broaden the membership spectrum of committees of agriculture, so that people outside the public representative sphere will have an interest and an investment in the functioning of the committees of agriculture.  It is also an attempt to depoliticise the membership content of committees of agriculture and to give them that broader spectrum of interests with which I agree.  There are certain committees of agriculture who have adopted a system which the Minister is now exhorting in the legislation.  For instance, my own county of Louth has had since 1967 a system whereby <Col N="643" /> specific voluntary organisations were encouraged to nominate a number of members to the Louth/County Committee of Agriculture.  As far back as 1967 Louth County Council indicated that they would give membership on the committee of agriculture to the IFA, to the small farmers' association and to Macra na Tuaithe.  That has been adhered to in the past 13 years and it has operated very successfully.  We were not sinful in any regard in this matter of de-politicising the membership of the committees of agriculture.  The net outcome of it all has been, with the operation of these new regulations, that Louth County Committee of Agriculture will pay a price for exercising their virtue rather than for sinning, because of the 16 members on the committee of agriculture which has now divided on a basis of 12 public representatives and four for rural voluntary organisations, that will now have to change under the new arrangement to ten elected representatives and six for rural voluntary organisations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Louth County Committee of Agriculture, immediately after the local elections in 1979, sought agreement from the Minister and his Department to an extension of the numbers of the membership of committees of agriculture in particular instances, if not on a general basis, from 16 to 20.  This would have allowed the new percentage allocation of 60 per cent and 40 per cent to operate on the basis whereby the existing 12 public representatives could continue in their positions and would give an increase in the allocation for rural voluntary organisations from their present four up to eight.  Louth County Committee of Agriculture exhorted the Minister to do this but, unfortunately, in the past month our reasonable request was rejected.  It will mean that certain members will have to drop off committees of agriculture.  It will also mean that the representation which has been available to certain voluntary organisations by certain counties will have to be adjusted and that may well result in a situation whereby certain voluntary organisations, who have had membership on committees of <Col N="644" /> agriculture up to now, may well find themselves, under the new regulations, not having any membership content at all.</P>
    <P>To that extent these regulations are unfair to the committees of agriculture which have operated in accordance with the principle which the Minister is himself advocating.  Even at this late stage, I suggest to the Minister that he should have another look at this.  It may involve a statutory amendment to allow flexibility in regard to the number of members on committees of agriculture <i>vis-a-vis</i> the number of electoral areas there are in each county, but that is only a statutory amendment which can be adjusted. It could well be a very profitable exercise to amend it, if it means the retention of members of the present committees of agriculture rather than ejecting them from their positions, and it could be a very profitable and beneficial exercise if it allows those committees which have operated with this principle over the past decade or so extend the membership from rural organisations. Having made that point, I exhort the Minister, even at this late stage, to think again about the membership content of committees of agriculture.</P>
    <P>The delay in the Bill being implemented is going to produce and present certain technical difficulties for the committees of agriculture, namely in regard to the holding of their annual general meetings and the appointment of new chairmen.  The Minister stated that he will designate a date which will determine when the new committees of agriculture will come into operation.  I would ask the Minister to let us know, since we are nearly at the 12th hour before the implementation of this legislation, when he expects that date will be announced and what that date will be, because very many county councils are holding their annual general meetings this month.  They will be followed very shortly by the annual general meetings of committees of agriculture because they are tied to holding them within a certain limited period, varying from one year to the next, within 14 days from when they held their AGM the previous <Col N="645" /> year.</P>
    <P>It is imperative for the Minister to indicate very promptly when the new committees are to be set up.  Will it mean that if there is any delay the present committees must continue as they are?  Can they hold their annual general meeting which should, perhaps, in certain instances be held no later than the third or fourth week of June?  I would like the Minister to give his opinion on that point.</P>
    <P>AnCOT is a crucial development in the agricultural sphere and it is unfortunate that it is starting off in possibly one of the worst financial circumstances and financially unfavourable times for the establishment of such an important body.  The estimates which the committees of agriculture submitted to the Department at the end of 1979 for 1980, have been cut back in a shameful manner by the Department.  Whichever officials were responsible for the pruning of those estimates they have not done a worthy service to agriculture.  We have found in Louth that the estimates for 1980 were based on the money actually spent at the end of 1979, notwithstanding a commitment that may well have been given in the course of 1979 to further expenditure.  That commitment had to be met and was met, and yet the actual money was not paid out until 1980.</P>
    <P>The officials of the Department, in drawing up what would be the estimates applicable for 1980, disregarded a commitment by the committees of agriculture to expenditure for the remaining part of 1979.  Because the moneys were not paid out and because the cheques were not signed before the end of 1979, there was a disgraceful cutoff point.  That sort of pruning by the Department, allied to the very unfavourable financial circumstances of the present time and to the depressed air of confidence in the agricultural community, is not the most favourable and not the most optimistic sign for the establishment of such an important body as AnCOT.  I request the Minister to look at the finance that will be available for the establishment of AnCOT and for the running costs and operations of all <Col N="646" /> the committees of agriculture in 1980.</P>
    <P>The scholarship schemes that have been operated by the committees of agriculture in recent years have been very successful.  They are attended by an ever-increasing number of young people. Ten years ago, in many county committees of agriculture, they could not get enough applicants to take up the scholarships that were available.  Now we find that there are far too many looking for far too few places.  It is not a realistic sign for any farmer or anybody interested in the agricultural sphere to find in that environment that the estimates available for scholarships in 1980 have been so radically cut.</P>
    <P>In my own county we have been operating on this basis for the past 13 years and it is not new to that extent except that we are going to have to ask a few public representatives to take themselves elsewhere.  We are going to throw into the melting pot the making up of the voluntary organisations and even the identification of the rural voluntary organisations as regards making up the balanced membership of the Committee of Agriculture.  There is no guarantee in my county that a body such as the small farmers' association or Macra could be one of those favoured bodies.  I would like the Minister to give some indication as to how the identification of these bodies, their listing for allocation of the 40 per cent allocation, is going to be determined.  Will he do it solely on his own judgment?  Will he do it in consultation with the committees of agriculture in each county?  Will he do it in consultation with all the voluntary organisations that are applicable and operating in each committee?  I suggest that he seek the opinion of the committees of agriculture in each county on this important matter before he makes his decision.</P>
    <P>Again, I exhort the Minister to have another look at the estimates that have been approved for the committees of agriculture for 1980.  It is a wrong basis on which to start a new agricultural environment in this country.  A lot of work, advice and research has gone into the establishment of AnCOT.  It would be a pity if they were to start their operation <Col N="647" /> on such a short shoestring as has been presented by the Minister.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamHyland" hpid="Mr. Hyland Mr. Hyland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hyland</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill which is the final step in bringing to fruition the long awaited An Chomhairle Oiliúna Talmhaíochta.  It is a Bill which has received a lot of lip service, some of which was deliberately obstructive and was responsible for the long delay in having the Bill finalised.  Some Senators have already expressed their regret in relation to the delay.  However, there has been much relevant and constructive comment, and the fact that it has generated such discussion is good and reflects the importance of agriculture to the economy.  Even those who expressed sincerely held reservations about aspects of the Bill would agree that the final draft, which is very little changed from the original, provides the base on which agriculture in this country can develop and expand to meet the challenge of the future.  It is obvious&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Mr. P. Reynolds Mr. P. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, last week we had a complaint from the benches to say that they could not hear what was being said.  I suggest that they get a quorum now that they can hear.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Notice taken that 12 Members were not present; House counted and 12 Members being present,</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamHyland" hpid="Mr. Hyland Mr. Hyland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hyland</NameTxt>
      <P>As I was saying, it is obvious that the Bill gives more power and greater flexibilty to the committees of agriculture, and it was on this one point that most concern was expressed.  This is as it should be, because committees of agriculture have played a very significant role in the development of agriculture over the years.  At the time when agricultural education was not as acceptable as it is today, committees of agriculture with their dedicated staffs, brought agricultural education to the farmers in rural schools.  If the Leas-Chathaoirleach and myself could privately reminisce we both have very happy memories and recollections of such agricultural classes and we remember <Col N="648" /> with affection the agricultural instructor in Abbeyleix, Tom Casey, who did a wonderful job at that particular time.  I apologise to the House if the Leas-Chathaoirleach and myself indulged in that little exercise.</P>
      <P>These classes and the improved farming techniques emanating from them paved the way for a farming revolution which gave birth to our farming organisations and laid the foundation stone for the production of many excellent farm leaders.  It is relevant, in relation to any debate on the Bill, that we should, for a moment, pay a tribute to the members of county committees of agriculture in every county in Ireland who, down through the years, gave of their time so generously to the promotion of agricultural services in the county.</P>
      <P>Regardless of what people may say about politicians and political representation on county committees of agriculture, I am glad to say that, in my own county of Laois, all political parties are represented.  They are genuinely interested in and concerned about the progress and development of agriculture. Politicians and political representatives on these committees have always done a good job.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This brings me to the composition of the new committees of agriculture&mdash;60 per cent elected members and 40 per cent representing our rural organisations. I am very pleased that the Minister is giving recognition in the Bill to the rural organisations, Macra na Feirme, the Irish Farmers' Association and other organisations which have done such a good job through the years in relation to agricultural development.  In Laois, this is nothing new as we have had that kind of representation, 40 per cent organisation representation, on our county committees of agriculture for the last ten years.  I can vouch for the credibility of the members who represent those organisations, for the genuine and constructive contribution which they made in relation to agricultural development in my county.  I say to any Member here who has any reservation about such <Col N="649" /> nominations that he can be sure that these organisations will nominate people who will do a good job on behalf of the farming community.</P>
    <P>The Bíll comes at a time when farming has reached a cross-roads.  We have benefited considerably from EEC membership. It should go on record that Irish farmers, with the full backing and support of the Government and the advisory services, availed to the maximum of those benefits and used them to consolidate the base for the modernisation of the industry from which both they and the economy in general benefited.  It would be a disaster for those farmers, for the industry and the economy in general, if we allowed anything to interfere with or hamper that progress.  Farmers are now suffering a severe decline in income and the falling off in farm expenditure on development is reflecting itself throughout the economy.  Everyone should recognise this important point.  It should be clearly understood that the increased income, and much more along with it, was spent by farmers on the development of the industry.  I want to emphasise the word &ldquo;spent&rdquo; because when agriculture is going well, the economy is going well.  We must, therefore, be realistic and face facts. Price increases in the future are going to be strongly resisted and hard fought and the Minister for Agriculture will have an extremely difficult task negotiating increased incomes for our farmers.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair very reluctant to interrupt the Senator but it would be preferable if he would relate his remarks to the Bill which has only a few sections in it dealing solely with agriculture committees and appointments to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamHyland" hpid="Mr. Hyland Mr. Hyland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hyland</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry if I strayed.  I want to make the point, with the indulgence of the Chair, that in future the emphasis on efficiency and production is going to be made the main means by which farming income is going to be increased and, to that extent, the committees of agriculture and the new Authority have a very important role to play.  I <Col N="650" /> look forward to the day when every farmer will be working to a farm development plan administered by the county committees of agriculture.  It is only in that way that individual farmers, the industry in general, and the economy in general, can benefit to the maximum from our greatest industry.</P>
      <P>I join with the previous speakers in welcoming the Minister of State.  I know he will do a good job in his Department.</P>
      <P>Previous speakers on the far side of the House have said it is important that we make sufficient money available to the new Authority and through the county committees to ensure not only have we a general development plan for agriculture from farm level to national level, but that we also have the resources to employ sufficient instructors to service and to monitor the development plans.  I do not know of any other profession, although I am sure there are many, where a greater return would be achieved from investment than in the recruiting of agricultural instructors to prepare and to service farm development plans.  I hope that the Minister of State will convey that point of view to his Minister and to the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One of the most encouraging aspects of this Bill is that it clearly defines the role of the county committees in the preparation of annual advisory and training programmes.  These programmes can be geared to the needs of individual counties.  To that extent, committees of agriculture will become development agencies for the county and, as such, they have a very important role to play, because the pattern of agriculture varies from county to county.  One of the great tasks facing county committees of agriculture under the new legislation is the identification of needs for individual counties.  One has only to drive throughout the countryside to observe the vast amount of undeveloped agricultural land that we have. I should like to see the new Authority and the committees giving more thought and more time to resolving and bringing into production, in so far as they can within the resources of the Bill, the great <Col N="651" /> vast national resource which is undeveloped. The members of committees of agriculture and the members of the new Authority will be anxious and willing to do that, provided sufficient resources are available.</P>
    <P>I would like to say how pleased I am that Dr. Walsh has been put in charge of the new Authority.  He is a man who has won the widespread admiration and respect of every farmer and I have no doubt that, under his guidance the Authority will progress and that farming here will progress along with it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PierceButler" hpid="Mr. Butler Mr. Butler">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Butler</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a few points to make on the Bill before us today.  I am not very enthusiastic about this new setup that is going to take place at county committee level.  I am not enthusiastic because I feel that people who have given long service to agriculture&mdash;and this has been said by Senator Martin O'Toole and I would agree with him&mdash;will now have to vacate their positions within the county committees of agriculture.  I do think that the county committees of agriculture have played their part over a long period in the development of agriculture at county levels.  The counties that I know best are Tipperary and Waterford.  I know the county committees of agriculture over a long period of years.  I was working in Waterford in the agricultural sector and I had communication with the people who were representing us on the county committees of agriculture there.  When I came to Tipperary I kept up my contacts with those in Waterford and also made contact with the representatives of the county committees in South Tipperary.  I can assure everybody that I had no difficulties in communicating with them on agricultural problems.  They had no difficulty in communicating with me.  I am deeply involved in agriculture and especially in the milk sector of agriculture. I am one of the management team of Mitchelstown creameries and therefore I would have had contact with the county committees of agriculture in Waterford and in south Tipperary and in Cork also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="652" /> I feel that because of the change you are letting down some of those people who have given the best service to agriculture.  They are now going to be eliminated from the county committees of agriculture.  They are going to be replaced by members nominated by the farming organisations.  I have nothing against any of the farming organisations but I see a difficulty here.  While it may not be political in the sense we know it, I think you are going to have a canvass by the committees themselves because the number of agricultural committees in counties can be as high as 12 or 13. When you have that number of committees of agriculture opting to have representations on the county committee then you are going to have trouble within the farming organisations as such.  Some of those people will be members of a number of committees involved in agriculture such as the IFA, the ICA, Muintir na Tire, ICMSA, the Land League, Small Farmers Association and even the Irish Creamery Managers Association, who I think should have the right to a place on county committees of agriculture.  They have a part to play there and they should be able to give some of their knowledge in that area to those county committees of agriculture. In that sense, we are going to have problems.  Perhaps the problems that will arise are worse than the problems that have been there up to now.</P>
    <P>Another thing that worries me is how the Minister or AnCOT will regulate the 40 per cent that will be drawn from the farming organisations.  With four times the number of county electoral areas, how are you going to nominate the numbers from each electoral area?  Will some electoral areas have only one representative from the farming organisations and other electoral areas have two or three?  Forty per cent of the total number has to be a certain figure.  The representation on the county committees of agriculture will have to be a certain number representing the 40 per cent, with the number of electoral areas in a county&mdash;and there are five in my county&mdash;I do not know how you will come up with an even 40 per cent and an even 60 per <Col N="653" /> cent.  That will create difficulties within the farming organisations and with the old membership.</P>
    <P>The development of agriculture requires a good deal of education.  There must be educational development.  I am a little bit worried that the farming organisations may, like the political organisations, go for the person who might have the time to go to those meetings but who may not be the best person to be nominated by those organisations.  You will have a position within those farming organisations where you will have young people who, naturally, will be interested in political life.  When people become involved in organisations they develop an interest in political life.  You will have that type of development taking place because you are putting them into a political area by putting them into county committees of agriculture.  When you put them into that type of atmosphere where 60 per cent of the membership will be nominated by political bodies&mdash;there is no doubt at all about that&mdash;you will have competition for votes of the people who are nominated by the agricultural committees. You will have promises from those bodies&mdash;&ldquo;We will think of you at the next election and maybe nominate you as a candidate for the next election if you support us&rdquo;, or &ldquo;We will nominate you as a candidate for the Seanad election. We would guarantee you so many votes in the next Seanad election&rdquo;.  That problem is there.  We all went through it: we know what is it all about.  That problem will arise.</P>
    <P>Personally, I do not think this is the be-all and end-all of the development of agriculture.  I accept that something had to be done.  If the county committees of agriculture, as they were, came under the control of AnCOT, as it is now, then you might have better county committees of agriculture; you might have better advice coming to them from the top and you would get a better commitment I think from the people who have been involved on county committees of agriculture up to now.  I am not enthusiastic about the Bill.  I am a little worried about it and <Col N="654" /> about what may happen once these county committees are set up.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JustinKeating" hpid="Professor Keating Professor Keating">
      <NameTxt>Professor Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>It was listening to Senator Butler that moved me to speak at all.  I want to address myself to the 40 per cent who are not coming forward to the county committees from the traditional political process.  I am not too enthusiastic about the Bill either.  In fact, I will say it some other time in detail and in a more appropriate place.  I am not too enthusiastic about all of our new structures in the whole advisory/educational sector.</P>
      <P>I wanted to talk about the county committees, following what I thought was a very interesting thought of Senator Butler.  He very politely and gently characterised a certain type of person who finds himself on committees in Ireland, &ldquo;the person who might have the time&rdquo;.  I am afraid that the voluntary organisations in agriculture have many such persons.  My conviction is that the good times and the easy times in farming are over; they were very brief.  I would like to see the county committees as engines for technical innovation for the increase of productivity, the increase of production, the streamlining of marketing, the highest possible added value, the highest possible quality in our produce, and so on; highly technical and efficiently generating and growth generating organisations.  I think we have politicised agriculture too much and we have politicised the county committees too much.</P>
      <P>All I wanted to say is that the 60 per cent will come out of the political process anyway and they will carry on the political process that they are accustomed to in the county committees of agriculture, as they do in local authorities and wherever else they can.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In Ireland we are in love with politics, not in an idealogical sense about policies and things we want to do, but we are in love and we see this when we compare our emigrants in the United States and Australia with the emigrants from other countries; we are in love not with idealogical politics but with press-the-flesh, <Col N="655" /> fix-it sort of politics.  The people who are golden to me in the Irish countryside are not those people; they are not the people who have time to sit on all the committees; neither are they the advisory service.  The people that are really golden are the people who have done it better right at the point of production, the really good farmers, and I would add to that the people in agri-business, the people who have done something about distribution and processing: it is the really efficient people themselves who know the hardships who possess the skills, who are the innovators.  My wish is that their passion and their managerial skills and their knowledge be fed into the processes of the county committee so that it would spread back more widely through the whole county.</P>
    <P>Therefore, I would end with one plea. I do not think 40 per cent is enough for the non-political people.  I would like to see it much more, but we have the bit of legislation and that is the way it has been decided.  My plea is a plea that I will record anyway, without a very great hope of it being listened to.  When the voluntary farming bodies came to knock out among themselves who should go, it ought not be the person who lobbies too much because they want a place there for its own sake.  It ought to be almost diametrically the opposite; they should look at the whole spectrum of their county and say who is the best in the county, and that is often a person who would not touch politics with a barge pole, any of our parties, who does not think much of the political process.  It is often a person who is so busy that he does not have time to sit on a plethora of committees and is not seeking committees to sit on.  They are the precious people, the golden people and the people who are good at things.  I would say to the voluntary organisations not to send forward to the county committees the most vociferous lobbyists who are in search of a committee, but to think of people who may not be in any voluntary organisations, not necessarily their own members who might be too busy; think <Col N="656" /> of people who might be too busy and who are really good, really technically brilliant and put them in.  If we are to get the growth that we all agree to be necessary, if there is to be a golden age for our agriculture, it has to come not from price hikes but from increasing efficiency; it has to come from an absolute whirlwind blowing through the country, improving our technology, improving our efficiency, improving the amount that we do as well as the quality of application with which we do it.  The better the quality of our actions the more production we will get.  We will be able to push the farming over the mountains.</P>
    <P>Without much hope of being listened to, I say let us leave politics out of this business and let us leave the place of the committee lobbyist out of it as much as possible.  I am begging the voluntary organisations through the House, at least in some instances, to seek out the really superb producers and organisers and managers in their counties, in their areas, and if they have no current involvement in voluntary activities to beg them to sit on county committees of agriculture in the hope that their expertise and their management and their breadth of vision would be passed on to their own areas.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad that this Bill is before the House this evening.  I think there has been too much of a time lag and too much uncertainty in the committee system and with the entire AnCOT question.  It is nice to start afresh to let the people tackle the different problems that face the industry at the present time.  I regret that the new committees will have fewer statutory powers than those that functioned under the system that they are replacing.  I have had the honour of serving on a committee for 24 years and I have had the experience of seeing the services expand and give the leadership, the assistance and the service that so many farmers of all categories have benefited from.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>During the past decade many farmers could be described as being in God's pocket, but I think He has been superseded by the banks.  It is unlikely that organised farmers will complain too <Col N="657" /> loudly at the extraordinarily high interest rates and so on and, therefore, we need a strong, agricultural advisory service in order to equip the farming industry with the ways and the means of getting through the bleak and the difficult period that faces the entire agricultural industry at the present time.</P>
    <P>It is important that this piece of legislation should go through; that the people who will be affected by it will have the task of settling down and working the new system and providing the services.  Like many other Senators, I would hope that there would be the very fullest co-operation between all the people serving and working in agriculture.  I hope that there will be a new <i>esprit de corps</i> between the new AnCOT services and An Foras Talúntais, and the Minister's Department.  I hope that the co-operative movement and the processors in the various ancillary services will be able to work closer together to be able to provide the people at all levels in the industry with better living and working conditions.</P>
    <P>Agriculture is facing a rather difficult period.  The new committees will be expected to give a lead.  It is one industry where there is always change and there must always be change especially with legislation moving through the Oireachtas, perhaps some of it prompted by directives or regulations from the EEC where standards are being laid down as we had today in packaging or quantity control.  This calls for a greater input of education so that people will be helped and facilitated in providing the kind of products, in providing the high standard of products that the greatly educated consumer demands and insists on getting.  This is going to be an increasingly difficult role.  I hope that the new committees will be able to meet that challenge.</P>
    <P>As I said, I think it will be difficult for them.  They are starting in an era when more and more people are clamouring for and in many cases getting decentralisation. I think the central authority is taking too much control, and nothing stymies enthusiasm more than the inability <Col N="658" /> of people who serve on committees to make a decision.  Unless the new authority at county level is given an opportunity of really being part of an organisation where their voices are listened to and acted upon you will not have dedicated service.  People become clockwatchers and the service deteriorates.  This would be a pity.  In my own community in Laois the last three of four committees have been representative of voluntary farming organisations as well as the nominees of the county council: we have had the 40 per cent.  It has been an outstanding success. We have been able to ensure through that that we had direct access, as it were, to the organised younger farmers and the classes and the demonstrations.  I think we are assured of a very ready audience and attendance.  In addition, the meetings were in the main very business-minded and only on very rare occasions did party politics enter in.  I am a politician who certainly would offer no apologies for being or declaring that I was a member of a political party.  After all, this is a democracy.  Why does everybody want to apologise for being a member of and supporting a political party?  Anyone who has the interest of the country at heart, who has any spirit of nationalism, if he or she has the guts to stand up and declare in favour of a registered or recognised political party, cannot in a democracy be anything that people should be ashamed of.  I am amazed that when you go into some voluntary organisation you find that you should almost apologise for showing up and showing an interest in your own profession or in your own work.  We should get away from that.</P>
    <P>The members of the main political parties in this country have done a good job on a voluntary basis at local level; they have done a thankless job.  They have contributed in a very unselfish way to the building up of the various agricultural industries and ancillary service industries.  I hope that they will continue to do so.  At least the people who represent the county council have to render an account every five years to the people who put them on these committees <Col N="659" /> and boards, and I think that that in itself is a good thing.</P>
    <P>It is good that people should be accountable. If you look at the committees of the House here, the Joint Committee on semi-State Bodies or the Committee of Public Accounts, the fact that semi-State bodies have become directly accountable to or at least answer to a committee of the House has improved the flow of knowledge from one to the other and there has been greater understanding and I think less suspicion. All in all, I think the public tend to get a better service at the end of the day, and that is what we should be interested in and worried about when it comes to the expenditure of public money.  While I am glad that this legislation is coming to a conclusion and going on to the Statute Book, nevertheless, I regret that the Government deemed it necessary that the new committees should have less statutory power and therefore, will I believe be hindered to some degree in guiding the educational structures, that they in their own expert local knowledge would regard as most suitable for the people in their own areas.  I hope that the central authority will rely heavily on the views and the wishes of the county committees in the future.  Indeed, I think they have always given them a very diligent ear in the past.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. Kiely Mr. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to welcome the Minister of State for Agriculture on his first official visit to this House.  I wish him well and I am confident he will be a good Minister.  In the short time since his appointment he has proved to be an able, talented and reliable Minister.</P>
      <P>This Bill came about as a result of the AnCOT Bill to provide farming or voluntary organisations who will be electing or nominating 40 per cent of members of county committees of agriculture.  Heretofore, the county committees of agriculture were appointed annually by the county council.  It was generally the elected members of the council that comprised county committees of agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="660" /> I would like to pay a tribute to those members who served heretofore as elected members and who were described as politicians.  I think that they did a good job and I doubt if the representatives from the farming organisations will be as good as some of those people they will be replacing.  Senator Connaughton said that some of those appointed previously or elected previously as representatives on the committees of agriculture were not suitable.  I wonder will the farming organisation appoint suitable people.  I can see where co-ops or even meat factories are controlled by farming organisations, farmers being a little disappointed with the way they are going.  I see that down in Limerick&mdash;and I am sure Senator Butler knows all about it&mdash;we have a milk war at present, probably through bad management by co-ops that are controlled by farming organisations.</P>
    <P>I would not like to see the major farming organisations monopolising 40 per cent of the seats that will be allocated to them through this Bill.  You have farming organisations, as was already mentioned by Senator O'Toole probably in the west&mdash;sheep farmers probably&mdash;and in other areas you have the beef growers and you have breed societies in areas where cattle and especially pedigree cattle are being bred.</P>
    <P>I would also like to see the societies responsible for organising agricultural shows being considered for the right to nominate members to county committees of agriculture.  It might be a hard thing to do but I am sure the Minister will take all types of farming in different counties into consideration.  I am sure he will consider organisations representing different types of farming.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill with some reservations. I was disappointed to see that members of county committees of agriculture who have given great service and have contributed successfully to the improvement of agriculture will probably be vacating their seats to farming organisations.  Farming organisations have done a good job in their own way.  I <Col N="661" /> know one farming organisation who made a rule that anyone affiliated to any political party would not be eligible for officership in that organisation.  Now, some political members of these committees will have to vacate their seats to make room for members of voluntary organisations.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKilbride" hpid="Mr. Kilbride Mr. Kilbride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kilbride</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not have any desire to speak at any length on this matter. Having been a member of a county committee of agriculture for 28 years I have a very extensive knowledge of what is involved in the administration of the agricultural advisory services in my county.  Some people have some misgivings and others have welcomed the new departure in regard to representation from agricultural organisations on county committees of agriculture.  Under the old system before one got the right to deliberate at a county committee of agriculture one had first to go before the electorate and win support at the ballot box.  One then had to face one's colleagues on the county council who had knowledge of one's ability as a political operator or as a farmer, as the case might be.  In my county after a local election those with the least interest in agriculture stepped down and left the membership of the agricultural committee to the farmers.  That system was to be recommended to the exclusion of any other system.  The politicians in their wisdom put the best farmers elected by the people in control of the agricultural affairs of the county.  I do not believe there can be any improvement on that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the innovation where agricultural organisations will have an opportunity to have representatives on committees since this new system has been adopted.  It will be possible for people with new ideas, experience and the educational qualifications to put their view across during deliberations of committees of agriculture.  When a question of policy is being decided at committee level it is important that the best opinions are available.  I doubt if the opinions of committees of agriculture will have much influence on what is pursued in any county.  The new organisation, administratively, <Col N="662" /> should ensure that the most appropriate line is pursued in any county.  That should be laid down as a matter of policy by committees of agriculture.  The younger elements we are expecting to be appointed to the committees of agriculture by their contributions, their ideas of modern administration and systems will have a lot to contribute.</P>
    <P>County committees of agriculture have never had a great amount of power. They had no great authority to make any alteration in regard to the work that should be pursued in a county.  That is why I feel the new system may have the effect of creating a better image, at least a more hopeful image.  It was usual to go to monthly meetings and pursue certain functions such as the allocation of premium bulls, premium boars, and approve winter agricultural classes and so on.  Those decisions merely amounted to rubber stamping a policy that was already decided.  If there is an improvement on that it will be welcome.</P>
    <P>I do not think agriculture will be in any way enhanced by opportunists anxious to be vociferous and place any organisation in the farming community to the forefront.  They may be able to talk a lot but I do not think they will be anything better than the person who was elected by the people.  To qualify for representation the organisations concerned should insist that people know about good farming in the county.  It will be vitally important that this is researched to the extent that opportunists are not allowed to jump on the bandwagon and replace somebody considered better.  It will be difficult for a member of a committee of agriculture, even a shopkeeper, to have to stand down in the middle of a term.  It will be a serious jolt to those who put a lot of effort into this and dedicated their services over many years to the interests of agriculture.  I hope for a better system.  If that does not happen let us hope it will be altered.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelMulcahy" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>When I first became a Member of this House in 1977 I spoke on agricultural policy and one of the <Col N="663" /> points I made was about the productivity of agriculture.  From recent figures it appears that we are not making much progress in the dimension of milk yield.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill relates to the appointment of county committees and we cannot have a general debate on agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelMulcahy" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>In fairness, the Chair came in very quickly on me.  I see these committees as being central in helping to promote the activity, the husbandry and the management required.  One of the points mentioned by the Minister was that they would be responsible for the development of livestock.  It seems that agricultural output at present is limited by that very dimension, the yield per cow.  In 1977 I made the point that we needed more advisers.  I am not an expert on agriculture and I am sure my friends down the country will want to know why I am talking about agriculture and will suggest I stick to industry.  However, the figures have a stark realism for me.  It seems that until output goes from 600 gallons per cow up to 800 or 900 gallons on average we will not be making progress.  I hope that the reorganised committees will move forward and encourage the progress required to achieve those levels.  The industry of Ireland depends on the farmer of Ireland.  Effective committees of this kind can contribute tremendously in that regard.</P>
      <P>I should like to join with my colleagues in welcoming the new Minister of State to the House and assure him of our support in the future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LorcanAllen" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture (Mr. Allen) Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture (Mr. Allen)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture (Mr. Allen)</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not propose to answer all questions raised many of which are totally irrelevant to the legislation before the House. However, I should like to comment on a number of matters that were raised. Before doing that I should like to refer to Senator Connaughton's remarks about members of committees of agriculture. For a member of a county committee of <Col N="664" /> agriculture to say that such people only became members, in many instances, to collect expenses was the lowest remark I have ever heard as a politician.  He must be referring to members of his own committee because from my knowledge of members throughout the country, I have nothing but the highest respect for such people, I am sure members in Galway will remind him of his remarks.</P>
      <P>Senator Connaughton asked who will determine the organisations.  The Minister will determine the organisations in each county.  Section 24 of the AnCOT Act states that:</P>
      <P>Every person appointed to be a member of the committee of agriculture shall be chosen or nominated for appointment by reason of attainment in the practice of farming, the development of agriculture, promotion of agriculture or rural home advice or education or by reason of a practical, commercial or technical knowledge of agriculture or a special local knowledge of agricultural matters.</P>
      <P>That is very important.  It is possible that Senator Connaughton was referring to people not included in those categories. It is possible that in future we will have people of the proper calibre from Fine Gael on such committees.</P>
      <P>Senator O'Toole mentioned sheep farmers and I have no doubt that they and the horse industry will get every consideration. Senator Markey asked about increasing the number of members at county committee level.  I should like to state that the number of counties where members of county councils will have to leave committees of agriculture is 12 out of a total of 27 committees.  Senator Markey's neighbouring county man, Deputy Tully, when Minister for Local Government, reduced the number of electoral areas in Louth from five to four.  That meant that the membership of the county committee of agriculture in Louth was automatically reduced.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not the point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LorcanAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>It is.  The Senator wanted the membership increased.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="665" />
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister of State has missed the point.  I made the point that membership should be increased on the basis of what is there at present and the practice in each county at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LorcanAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>I was returning to the situation as it obtained up to the change of Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>It has nothing got to do with the point I made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LorcanAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>It has.  There would be greater representation on Louth County Committee of Agriculture if County Louth had been left with five electoral areas rather than the four to which it was reduced.  To increase the size of committees of agriculture any more than they are would make them unworkable. A number of Senators mentioned the delay in bringing this legislation forward. This legislation took seven months to get through the Dáil because of opposition to it.  That was the cause of the delay. Because of the delays we have to bring in this amending legislation to put the matter right in so far as county committees are concerned.</P>
      <P>A lot of people have been under the impression that the Minister is the person who will determine who will be nominated by rural organisations.  The Minister will not have any say.  He will designate the organisations who will have the right to nominate in any county.  It would be most unfair to cover the country entirely.  It will have to be done on a county by county basis because some counties have the ICMSA while others do not.  I am just taking that organisation as an example.  I can promise Senator Hyland and others, who mentioned the question of adequate finance for AnCOT that we will make all the necessary finances available to ensure that it gets off the ground.  I was delighted to hear so many people mention Dr. Tom Walsh, a county man of my own.  It is true to say that when he was in the Agricultural Institute he did an excellent job and I have no doubt he will get AnCOT off the ground and moving.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="666" /> Senator Keating was not satisfied with the 40 per cent for rural organisations. There is nothing to stop any county switching it the other way round if they wish and giving the 40 per cent to elected members and 60 per cent to rural organisations.  That will not be a rigid situation, but a minimum of 40 per cent have to be selected members.  Any county council wishing to extend the 40 per cent rural organisation representation to 60 per cent con do so.  The previous Minister for Agriculture, prior to the election of the present committees, said that he intended bringing in amending legislation to ensure that rural organisations would be appointed to those committees. This is in a new ball game. County councils will appoint 60 per cent of the membership and they will be notified, in due course, when the Minister has taken the decision on the rural organisations to be nominated.  I expect that will be in the next month to six weeks.  There will not be much delay, possibly a month.  Some counties&mdash;my own, for example&mdash;when electing the previous committee decided that the 60 per cent would be appointed from the existing membership.  They know that when the Bill becomes law they will have to go.  That will not happen in every county.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Agriculture (Amendment) Bill, 1979:" RHead="Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Agriculture (Amendment) Bill, 1979: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to refer the Minister to his remarks in regard to the change-over date.  A number of committees of agriculture will have their annual meeting within the next three or four weeks.  Some of them will have their meeting between the third week of June <Col N="667" /> and the second week of July.  If the Minister has not designated the date in accordance with section 2 can he give some guidance as to what those committees of agriculture are to do as regards their annual meetings?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LorcanAllen" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture (Mr. Allen) Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture (Mr. Allen)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture (Mr. Allen)</NameTxt>
      <P>The legislation does not affect the annual meetings of the committees.  The annual meetings can proceed after the committees are reappointed. If a change is necessary the new committee can make such a change.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that, but it puts the county council in a position where they may feel obliged to hold the annual meeting of the committee on a certain date.  The Minister may say there is no reference in the Bill as to when they hold their annual meeting and it does not matter, in other words, when the county council hold it or, accordingly, when the county committee of agriculture hold their annual meeting.  Will we want the ridiculous situation where a committee of agriculture in accordange with the present law hold their annual meeting in the second week in July and then three weeks later have to hold a completely new meeting which amounts to another annual meeting?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LorcanAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>When this becomes law and the order is made for a county committee to change the old committee is suspended and you start afresh.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>I see no reason why the Minister should not designate the date within the next week or two.  It would get county committees out of a ridiculous situation if they feel obliged to hold their annual meeting in three weeks' time.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister say <Col N="668" /> what is in section 26 (2) of the AnCOT Act which bears reference to paragraph (b) of subsection (3) of this Act?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LorcanAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 26 (1) of the AnCOT Act makes changes to the Second Schedule of the 1931 Act and provides a new format of committee. Section 26 (2) provides that section 26 (1) will have effect in respect of each county council as from its annual meeting in the next election year after the commencement of the Act.  The other provision of section 3 (b), the amendment of the principal Act set out in section 26 (1) of the AnCOT Act, would not come into operation until after the next local elections in June 1984.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>I wanted to confirm that the words &ldquo;election year&rdquo; were in that subsection of the 1979 Act.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before proceeding to the next item could we have an indication as to when the Seanad will meet again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusBrennan" hpid="Mr. Brennan Mr. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>Tuesday, 17 June at 2.30 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matter. - Irish" RHead="National Commission for UNESCO">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter. - Irish National Commission for UNESCO.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>Ireland joined UNESCO in 1961 and UNESCO is the United Nations educational, scientific and cultural organisation.  Its function is to contribute to peace and security by promoting collaboration among the nations through education, science and culture in order to further universal respect for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamental freedoms which are affirmed for the peoples of the world <Col N="669" /> without distinction of race, sex, language or religion by the charter of the United Nations.</P>
      <P>Given our history, tradition and interest in education, science and culture and our contribution to education in the developing world, UNESCO is a body in which we should have a special interest. The importance of UNESCO was well illustrated in the past week when the Pope, on his visit to France, devoted the whole of one of his addresses towards UNESCO personnel.  It was clear from what he said in that address that he regards the role that UNESCO play as one of the utmost importance.  I have worked with, not under, UNESCO in the development of universities in Africa. The project in which I was representing the international Mathematical Union was successful and resulted in the formation of a mathematical organisation in Africa to stimulate the study of mathematics in African universities right through the continent and the formation of an institute funded by UNESCO with a branch in Nice in France and a branch in Africa to stimulate, co-ordinate and develop mathematics in Africa.  That is only one small illustration of what UNESCO does.  It is a body to which we should have a major input and from which this country should derive major benefits.</P>
      <P>The link between Ireland and UNESCO is the Irish National Commission for UNESCO, and this is the channel through which information from UNESCO should flow to us, through which the benefits of membership of UNESCO should accrue and through which we should make our input to that important organisation.  The national commission is supposed to act as the centre to which the national intellectual resources can be associated with the work of the organisation, thus assuring their participation in evaluation of UNESCO's programme as well as international intellectual co-operation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The reason I raised this matter on the Adjournment is that I feel we have failed to take advantage of our membership of <Col N="670" /> UNESCO and have failed to realise the importance to this country of UNESCO. We have failed to realise how important a role Ireland can play in UNESCO and in the development of its activities, and we have failed to make an impact on the workings of that organisation.  That failure is fairly and squarely our own fault.  It can be put down to a great extent to the failure of the national commission to set to work in the appropriate way and in the correct spirit.</P>
    <P>I wish to refer to the composition of this body.  There are representatives from a range of organisations, but the obvious body to me to be asked to nominate to the national commission for UNESCO is the Royal Irish Academy, which is our senior academic body and which fulfils the sort of functions in relation to the other international organisations that this commission is fulfilling, or supposedly fulfilling, <i>vis-a-vis</i> UNESCO. The national scientific organisations have adhering committees in Ireland which are sub-committees of the academy.  The academy, more than any other body, is fitted to make an input as our senior educational, scientific and cultural organisation and it should be represented.  However, that is a small point.  My main contention is that the commission as a whole has failed to make an impact.  It has failed in its duty to make sure that there is a specific Irish input to UNESCO and it has failed to ensure that we acquire the benefits from that organisation, and that really reflects the fact that we have not treated membership of UNESCO sufficiently seriously.</P>
    <P>The function of the Government is to provide for the servicing of the national commission and to provide the premises and the financial resources necessary to allow the commission to carry out its functions.  The Department of Education undertakes this task.  It provides servicing for the commission, a certain membership for it and the resources with which the commission is supposed to operate.  So few people have ever heard of this commission or ever realised what the commission is about or is supposed to be doing, that one must question <Col N="671" /> whether really anything at all has been achieved by our national commission.  It is of some interest that every Senator I spoke to about this or who asked me what I was raising on the adjournment this evening asked me what was the national commission for UNESCO. They all heard of UNESCO but they had never heard of our national commission. There has been a failure to provide information about the activities of UNESCO in this country.  The national commission is the channel through which this information should be disseminated to the public.  What UNESCO is doing is of great interest to the public and of particular relevance.</P>
    <P>Given our tradition and given our involvement in the developing world, UNESCO is one of the bodies that is doing the most.  It is the international body that is placed and designed to assist in educational development, particularly in the Third World.  It does not restrict its activities to the Third World by any means.  There should be a considerable interest in what UNESCO is doing and yet we never find any publicity in the media or any information coming through about its activities.  It is a closed book as far as the Irish are concerned, and that is the fault of the national commission.</P>
    <P>To illustrate the failure to appreciate what UNESCO is about on the commission's behalf, I refer to an important questionnaire sent out to all the national commissions of the adhering countries.  This questionnaire was sent out in April 1978 and in October 1978 the replies to it were collated and the report was circulated to the member countries.  The questionnaire was precisely on the topic which I am discussing: the organisation, structure, composition, role and activities of national commissions for UNESCO in the various countries.  It was asking the national commission to report on its activities. Perhaps, because we did not have many activities to report on, Ireland was not one of the 85 countries that replied to the questionnaire.  The <Col N="672" /> countries that replied were Bahrain, Bangladesh, Barbados, Bolivia, Brazil, Bulgaria, Cameroon, Chile, Columbia, Congo and so on but Ireland significantly is not in the list of the 85 countries. The commission has a reputation for not replying to correspondence.  It attends the annual UNESCO conference but the input is minimal.  I made some inquiries among members of the present commission who have recently been appointed and one of them told me that the philosophy that the civil servants who were in charge of the delegation impressed on him was &ldquo;when in doubt say nothing&rdquo;.  If one takes that attitude to international organisations, we will not get anywhere.  What I am asking the Minister to do&mdash;I am not blaming him for this failing, I am just pointing it out&mdash;is to take steps to change our attitude and import an entrepreneurial spirit into the workings of this commission. He should upgrade our approach to UNESCO through the national commission and see that, first of all, we get the information and documentation necessary for us to appreciate what UNESCO is doing so that, from our considerable educational and cultural resources, we can make a proper input to UNESCO, which we are not doing at present.</P>
    <P>Organisations such as UNESCO, FAO and the World Health Organisation are of tremendous importance because they are non-political in a sense in which the United Nations, of course, is not.  They are not forums for great political debate.  Political issues do colour their discussions but they are basically organisations with non-political aims.  In the case of UNESCO its aims and functions are so much in line with the tradition of which this country is proud&mdash;a missionary tradition and a tradition of education in the less privileged areas of the world&mdash;that it is a great pity that we do not play a vital role in ensuring that this important work goes on and ensuring our views and specific expertise is known, appreciated and used and is at the service of UNESCO.  Only in that way will we get the benefits that accrue.  I know, having <Col N="673" /> been a member of one of those international organisations, that it is much better to get up and say something in which one is taking a bit of a chance than to have the poor mouth approach. If one does not get up and take a chance nobody will know anything about one or realise that one has a particular contribution. As we have such a tremendous contribution to make to an organisation like UNESCO, I appeal to the Minister to change the attitude and operations of the national commission and ensure that we make our proper impact in this essential organisation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnPWilson" hpid="Minister for Education (Mr. Wilson) John P. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Education (Mr. Wilson)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator West for giving me an opportunity of saying a few words on UNESCO and the commission.  I take the Senator's point that UNESCO is an important organisation of the United Nations.  This is underlined by the fact that the Pope thought it was important that he should address it on his recent visit to Paris.  I congratulate the Senator also on the important work that he did in the realm of mathematical studies in Africa and his interest in the organisation, the purpose of which is to stimulate the study of mathematics in that continent.</P>
      <P>I should like to comment on what the Senator said about an alleged policy adopted by our representatives in UNESCO &ldquo;when in doubt, say nothing&rdquo;. I do not think that that ever has been or ever will be the policy of anybody from the Department of Education at any international gathering.  I reject that statement from whatever source it came.  As regards the point made by the Senator about UNESCO not being a political organisation, as such it is not but the activities of UNESCO were very heavily politicised as time went on.  The Department of Foreign Affairs feel it should have an interest in the activities of UNESCO for this very reason.  They attend various meetings of UNESCO as well as representatives from the Department of Education.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I take the opportunity to bring to the notice of the Seanad the major contribution which has been made over the last <Col N="674" /> two decades by individuals who have given their time and commitment to serve on various Irish national commissions for UNESCO.  I am in complete disagreement with the view put forward by the Senator but, at the same time, I am glad to have the opportunity to advise of the many and varied facets of the UNESCO programme which Irish national commissions have catered for through the expertise and wide-ranging interests of their members.</P>
    <P>The Senator touched lightly on the composition when he mentioned one group that was not represented.  I was rather disappointed that he did not spend more time examining the composition and telling me where he thinks improvement could be made.  He concentrated his speech mainly on the functioning. The Irish National Commission for UNESCO came into being in the following way.  The Irish Government in December 1960 authorised the then Minister for External Affairs to have a motion moved in Dáil Éireann for a resolution assenting to acceptance of the obligations contained in the Constitution of the United Nations Educational Scientific and Cultural Organisation, recommending the taking of steps with a view to Ireland's admission to membership of the organisation.  The formalities in connection with Ireland's entry were completed in October 1961 and in December 1961 our Ambassador in Paris presented his credentials as a permanent delegate to UNESCO.  Subsequently it was decided to set up an Irish National Commission for UNESCO under the Minister for Education.</P>
    <P>The first meeting of the Irish National Commission for UNESCO which took place in September 1962 was addressed by the then Minister for Education, Dr. Patrick Hillery, in the following terms:</P>
    <P>Perhaps the most important function of a national commission is its role in making known the aims of the organisation and associating with its programmes and objects all the appropriate bodies in the country which are concerned with education, science and culture.  These programmes and <Col N="675" /> projects have many facets involving the free flow of ideas and information across national frontiers and outside the narrower official channels.</P>
    <P>Article VII of the UNESCO Constitution provides that each member state shall make such arrangements as suit its particular conditions for the purpose of associating its principal bodies interested in educational, scientific and cultural matters with the work of the organisation, preferably by the formation of a national commission broadly representative of the Government and such bodies.  In the nomination of members for the first Irish National Commission referred to, the Government ensured that the membership of not more than 22 individuals was fully representative of all of the bodies concerned with education, science and culture.  Members were drawn from the teachers' unions, the Irish Congress of Trade Unions and the school managerial associations, lay and clerical.  Universities were represented by members drawn from a variety of facilities from arts to engineering.  A representative from the Irish language movement was included, also a member from the broadcasting authority and the agricultural sector.  The chairman and secretary were Department of Education officials while the Department of Foreign Affairs was also represented.</P>
    <P>The first major task of the new commission was to participate in the general conference of UNESCO in 1962 in Paris.  The task of this, and of every general conference held at two-yearly intervals since then, was to prepare a programme and budget for the following two years.  The first Irish National Commission participated fully in the general conference of 1962 and 1964 and the second and third Irish National Commissions which followed on in 1966, 1968 and 1970 were equally active in successive conferences as well as in all other areas of UNESCO programmes until 1973.</P>
    <P>The fourth Irish National Commission which was appointed in 1977, and is <Col N="676" /> currently in office, has carried on the tradition of being broadly representative of the principal bodies interested in educational, scientific and cultural matters. The educational interests are covered by men and women teachers and administrators who have made and are making significant contributions to the educational field, individuals whose range of interests focuses on the highly topical areas of equality, youth, language teaching and educational research.  The scientific interest is well catered for by representatives from different university faculties of engineering and chemistry.  For the cultural side, there is representation from the Arts Council, the Royal Hibernian Academy, the arts department of the universities and one of the Irish language organisations. The area of communications is covered by the fact that two members of the commission served on the RTE authority.  The tradition of involving the agricultural sector and the trade unions has been maintained by including in the membership of the national commission an agricultural advisor and a representative of the Irish Congress of Trade Unions.</P>
    <P>I have already mentioned that the Irish National Commission has participated in the general conference of UNESCO which is held every two years and at which the biennial programme and budget is discussed and approved.  A full plenary session of the entire national commission is held at least twice a year in the course of which meetings many projects receive consideration, motions are put forward in relation to the proposed programme and budget and activities which will further the aims of UNESCO are initiated.  The functions of the national commission are to advise the Minister for Education on matters relating to UNESCO; to co-operate by all suitable means in the implementation of the programme of UNESCO in Ireland; to foster interest in the promotion of international collaboration through education, culture and sport.</P>
    <P>The Irish National Commission decided at the outset that in order to fully execute its functions an executive <Col N="677" /> committee should be set up which would meet on a regular basis.  An executive committee which comprises six members of the national commission, the Chairman being the secretary to the national commission, has met regularly during the terms of office of each national commission. It has always been the aim that the executive committee would be also broadly representative of the educational, scientific and cultural interests in the country and the present executive committee can be regarded as meeting these requirements.</P>
    <P>Since the fourth Irish National Commission was established, five plenary sessions of the full commission have been held, the last of which took place at the end of May.  The executive committee has met on seven occasions.  As to participation in the other committees of UNESCO, I may say that delegations participated in 1979 in conferences on sport and education, on the question of the international recognition of studies, diplomas and degrees in higher education. More recently still an Irish delegation attended an international conference <Col N="678" /> on the status of the artist.  Furthermore, in regard to projects, fellowships, competitions and so on which are organised under the UNESCO programme, the Irish National Commission have diligently aided Irish participation whenever possible.</P>
    <P>I think I have said enough to cover most of the areas mentioned by the Senator.  One point did strike me.  He said that there was not the flow of information which there might be and people were not perhaps as well informed as they might be of the activities of UNESCO and the Irish National Commission in particular.  I will have a look at that situation to see if anything can be done about it.  I maintain the position that the Irish National Commission is representative and that since it was revived in 1977 it has been functioning effectively.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister never got the questionnaire?</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 17 June 1980.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>