<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Thu" Date="21" Month="Sep" Year="1944" Vol="94" No="11" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 21 Mean Fómhair 1944" DateEnglish="Thursday, 21 September 1944" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1793">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1793" /> Do chuaidh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Petrol Ration for Medical Profession">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Petrol Ration for Medical Profession.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Supplies if he proposes to increase the petrol ration to members of the medical profession at an early date, and if he is aware of the immediate necessity for an increase.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Minister for Supplies (Mr. Lemass) Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Supplies (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>The ration of petrol allowed to members of the medical profession will be reviewed periodically in relation to the supply position and will be increased if, and when, conditions so permit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the supply position at present not warrant an increase to the medical profession?  There are rumours that there is plenty of petrol in the country.  If that be so, the medical profession should get a share of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The allowance now given is the maximum which can be allowed in the present supply position.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Sugar for Jam Manufacture">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Sugar for Jam Manufacture.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Supplies whether, in view of the shortage of butter, he proposes to make sugar available to private persons for the manufacture of jam.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Having regard to the limited stocks of sugar held, it is not possible to make a special allocation of sugar to private persons for jam-making. It was found possible, however, to allot special allowances of <Col N="1794" /> sugar to the principal jam manufacturers and, in consequence, substantially increased supplies of jam are available to the public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it possible for the Minister to consider a modification of his decision in respect, for instance, of religious institutions where boarders are housed and which experience difficulty in procuring adequate supplies of butter for their boarders?  These institutions have apple crops available with which to manufacture jam.  If an allowance were made to them, it would ensure that a certain limited number of persons would benefit&mdash;a type of person over whom there would be effective control and in respect of whom there would be little likelihood of abuse in regard to the allowance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a separate question, but I think that, for the time being, we must limit sugar supplies to those who are licensed as manufacturers of jam.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister not consider that it is national waste if the apples are available and there is no sugar to convert them into jam?  I understand that jam manufacturers are not disposed to take all the apples available this year.  Will the Minister undertake to consider the matter sympathetically if the case is put to him?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The quantity of jam to be made is determined by the supply of sugar available and not by the supply of fruit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister not aware that those apples must go to waste if no sugar is available?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>We propose to allow jam manufacturers sufficient sugar to justify them in buying all the fruit offered to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Supplies of Cement">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Supplies of Cement.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he will state when it is expected that supplies of cement will be available for purchase without a permit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1795" />
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJMurphy" hpid="Tadhg O Murchadha Tadhg O Murchadha">
      <NameTxt>Tadhg O Murchadha</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce whether he can indicate how soon increased supplies of cement required for various works, and in the absence of which large numbers of artisans are idle, will be available to the general public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass) Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>I will answer questions Nos. 3 and 4 together.</P>
      <P>It is not at present possible to state when circumstances may permit of the removal of the restrictions on the purchase and sale of cement.  Recently, however, the supply position has eased somewhat and permits for the purchase of cement are being issued more freely than was possible heretofore.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it possible for the persons in question to get supplies for artisans now, even in limited quantity?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It is possible to get supplies now.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Price of Children's Boots and Clothing">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Price of Children's Boots and Clothing.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government and Public Health if he is aware that children's boots and clothing are too costly for many thousands of children of necessitous parents and if it is now proposed to make any concessions for those unable to provide them from their own inadequate resources.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Dr. Ward) Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Dr. Ward)">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Dr. Ward)</NameTxt>
      <P>I would refer the Deputy to the reply given to his question on the 20th June last in which it was stated that the provision of boots and clothing which may be required by those in receipt of public assistance is a matter for the public assistance authority.  A scheme for the distribution of footwear at reduced rates to children of persons with low weekly incomes is likely to be brought into operation in November.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Parliamentary Secretary say on what terms the poorer people and people on low rates <Col N="1796" /> of pay will be able to provide boots or clothes for their children, even if they are not on home assistance?  It is very difficult for people with small wages to get on home assistance.  What are they to do if they require boots, shoes or clothing for their children, many of whom are almost naked?  If the Parliamentary Secretary would come with me for a ten-minute walk from this House&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has not asked a supplementary question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>On what conditions are poor people who are not on home assistance to get boots and clothes for their children?  Let the Government subsidise them and give them a chance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>It is quite clear that the Deputy was not paying the slightest attention to the reply which I gave to his question.  I stated in the reply: &ldquo;A scheme for the distribution of footwear at reduced rates to children of persons with low weekly incomes is likely to be brought into operation in November.&rdquo;  I might as well have been talking to the wall as talking to the Deputy when I made that reply. He wants his little bit of window-dressing here at the expense of the poor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I object to the cheap jibes of the Parliamentary Secretary. He referred to the previous reply given in respect of the children of parents on home assistance.  I want to know if the children of parents who are not on home assistance will be included in the scheme.  I do not want cheap jibes from the Parliamentary Secretary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrFCWard" hpid="Dr. Ward Dr. Ward">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ward</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has not paid the slightest attention to the reply which I gave him.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="An Tánaiste Seán T. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>An Tánaiste</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take items 1 and 4 on the Order Paper, No. 4 to be interrupted from 6 o'clock to 7 o'clock in order to complete the discussion on No. 7.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1797" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesHughes" hpid="Mr. Hughes Mr. Hughes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hughes</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it proposed to sit to-morrow?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="An Tánaiste Seán T. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>An Tánaiste</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHughes" hpid="Mr. Hughes Mr. Hughes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hughes</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to meet next week?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="An Tánaiste Seán T. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>An Tánaiste</NameTxt>
      <P>Normally, we would sit on Wednesday, Thursday and Friday but, on account of the strenuous work which has to be done in connection with the Transport Bill, it is proposed to sit on Tuesday of next week, in addition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephWilliamMongan" hpid="Seosamh Ó Mongáin Seosamh Ó Mongáin">
      <NameTxt>Seosamh Ó Mongáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Cathfimid fanacht anseo amáireach ag déanamh bolg le gréin agus gan aon ghnótha le déanamh againn.  Níl aon bhealach againn le dhul abhaile ach, ós rud é go gceapann na daoine móra i mBaile Átha Cliath go bhfuil siad marbh tar éis bheith ag obair ar feadh trí lá, caithfidh na Teachtaí ón tuaith dhá lá a chailleadh an tseachtain seo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="An Tánaiste Seán T. O'Kelly">
      <NameTxt>An Tánaiste</NameTxt>
      <P>Is dóigh liom go raibh duine de Pháirtí an Teachta i láthair nuair a deineadh an socrú.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephWilliamMongan" hpid="Seosamh Ó Mongáin Seosamh Ó Mongáin">
      <NameTxt>Seosamh Ó Mongáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Níor chuala mé focal faoi agus ba chóir dúinn obair mhuintir na tíre a dhéanamh gan bheith ag smaoineamh, mar atá na daoine móra i mBaile Átha Cliath ag smaoineamh, go bhfuilimid marbh tar éis bheith ag obair cúpla lá.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá obair na tíre ghá dhéanamh.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Local Government and Public Health Provisional Orders" RHead="Confirmation Bill, 1944&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Local Government and Public Health Provisional Orders Confirmation Bill, 1944&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Bill passed through Committee without amendment.</P>
    <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Transport (No. 2) Bill, 1944&mdash;Committee" RHead="(Resumed&mdash;Amendment No. 18)">
    <Title>Transport (No. 2) Bill, 1944&mdash;Committee (Resumed&mdash;Amendment No. 18).</Title>
    <Col N="1798" />
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>There was some discussion last night as to the number of decisions that could be given on the series of amendments Nos. 18 to 27a which with the exception of Nos. 21 and 24, which are out of order, deal with a major issue. If amendment No. 18, which was formally moved last night, were withdrawn, it would simplify matters. Amendments Nos. 19 and 20 are alternatives to the &ldquo;establishment date&rdquo; proposed in the Bill.  They might be discussed together, but only one question could be put which would dispose of the operative date.  Amendments Nos. 22, 23 and 25 are interrelated and will all be governed by the decision on No. 22.  If this amendment is defeated, amendments Nos. 26 and 27 cannot be moved, as they are consequential on Nos. 19 and 22.  As there is a separate point on amendment No. 27a it may be moved, though it would, if adopted, require to be redrafted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask leave to withdraw amendment No. 18, which was moved last night.  The discussion on that matter can be taken later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It will emerge on amendment No. 22.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 19:</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), paragraph (a), lines 18 and 19, and in paragraph (b), lines 32 and 33, to delete the words &ldquo;establishment date is&rdquo; and substitute therefor the words and figures &ldquo;6th day of February, 1942, was&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The purpose of amendments Nos. 19 and 20 is that there should be recognition of the fact that at some date, either in 1942 or 1943, notice should have been given to the stockholders of the Great Southern Railways that proposals for the introduction of legislation in regard to the company had reached such a stage that they would be advised, either by the chairman of the company, or possibly by the <Col N="1799" /> Government, that they should be careful in disposing of their stock.  In my opinion, they should have been advised as to withholding any selling of their stock, on the ground that the Government were contemplating certain changes with regard to the company's financial foundation, and until it was clear what these proposals were, they should not be influenced by suggestions or by rumours that might have been abroad at that time.  There were certain dates on which the Government should have given such notice.</P>
    <P>On February 17th, 1942, the Government issued an Emergency Order taking complete charge of the railway company.  From February 24th they wiped out the old board of directors and put in a chairman to whom extraordinary emergency powers were given.  They made him practically a dictator of the whole railway company and its machinery.  They deprived the previous directors of office and appointed a chairman.  No meeting of the board could be held unless the chairman was present, and no decision could be arrived at by the board without his concurrence.  They decided that the chairman would be paid out of the revenue of the company, and that his remuneration would be a matter for the Government to decide. Generally, the regular conduct of the affairs of the company was left in his hands.  The action of the Government at that particular time had implications, and while the Minister and others may argue that it was too soon to make any statement, as the intention with regard to legislation may not have been clear, nevertheless, in the particular circumstances under which the chairman was appointed, there were implications there, from the Government point of view, and from the chairman's point of view that, in my opinion, warranted the shareholders being advised to hold their stock until the Government had made a pronouncement of one kind or another regarding the railway company. If it is thought that February, 1942, was too early, then we come to February, 1943.  In the evidence given before the <Col N="1800" /> tribunal of inquiry into stock transactions and in the report now issued, it was shown that, on 6th February, 1943, a memorandum was addressed to the Minister by the chairman of the company in which he pointed out, among other things, that a seven-year plan should be adopted and a statutory company formed with a capital of not more than £10,000,000, with only one kind of stock bearing a low rate of interest, which would buy out the existing shares, with the general idea that ultimately all public transport would come under the control of the new company.  The report discloses on page 26 that the Minister lost no time in considering the memorandum submitted by the chairman of the company, and, on 27th February, 1943, he issued a memorandum with certain tentative conclusions at which he had arrived as to the lines of investigation into the proposals.  These conclusions suggested the formation of a company of £10,000,000, the acquiring of the Great Southern Railways and the Dublin United Transport Company and that, during a seven-year period, the additional capital required by the company to accomplish the reorganisation of the concern and to modernise and standardise equipment should be guaranteed as to principal and interest by the Government.</P>
    <P>In February, 1943, if not in February, 1942, there was a strong case for the holders of Great Southern stock having been advised by the Government to hold their stock, pending further and complete disclosure by the Government of its attitude.  The memorandum of February, 1943, also asked that the company should be given power to raise their rates, or at any rate the Minister was asked by the chairman at the end of February, or the beginning of March, 1943, for permission to increase the rates.  It was suggested that these rates ought to be increased by at least 20 per cent.  The view of the chairman was that an increase of 20 per cent. in railway rates was necessary and in his report to the shareholders on 3rd March, 1943, at the general meeting the chairman stated:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;You cannot now provide out of <Col N="1801" /> future revenue the money necessary to make good the failure to provide for renewals in the past, and there is no reason to think that the railways can&mdash;no matter how much you ask for the services rendered&mdash;pay dividends on existing capital.  There therefore must be a reconstruction of the capital, and what is ultimately agreed to be the value of the stockholders interest should rank equally with, and carry whatever guarantees are given to those subscribing new capital.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>At that time, we had the Minister coming to the conclusion, with the chairman, that reformation of the capital was necessary and certain values should be assigned to the then existing stock.  We had the chairman making a speech which might indicate to the shareholders that their stock was not very valuable, so that, if not in February, 1943, when the Minister was coming to these conclusions, in March or May, 1943, when the Minister gave permission for the increase in rates looked for, there should have been a statement such as I suggest.</P>
    <P>If it did not come in May, I submit that there is evidence in the report that it should have come in July.  If the Minister was not clear enough in his mind in May that he should make such a statement to the shareholders, the Department were becoming clearer in their minds with regard to their intention to do something with the financial side of the company by June.  On page 27 of the report, it is stated that to the memorandum which was passed to the assistant secretary the secretary added a further memorandum, dated 14th July, 1943, in which he discussed the possibility of offering the existing shareholders bonds in the new company, or, as an alternative, cash, which would avoid any suggestion of confiscation and recalled the reduction of capital in 1933 and the reaction to it.  But the secretary came to the conclusion that compulsory conversion was inevitable.  That memorandum was submitted to the Minister on the same day, July 14th, 1943.</P>
    <P>If they were not clear in July that a warning ought to be issued to the <Col N="1802" /> stockholders, there is another date, 30th September, 1943.  On page 29, the report says that the assistant secretary again met Mr. Reynolds on 30th September, when there was some discussion as to the amount of proposed capital which the assistant secretary thought too high.  Finally, a figure of £20,000,000 was suggested and provisionally accepted by Mr. Reynolds, who, it was agreed, should go away and draft a scheme for reconstruction. This was the first time the figure of £20,000,000 was suggested as the capital of the new company.</P>
    <P>Further down the page, the report shows that on the 7th October, 1943, the Minister approved of the scheme for submission to the Government, subject to the assent of the Department of Finance.  If we turn to the schedule issued with the report of the amount of purchasing which went on, we find that for the four weeks following the week ended 25th September, which are included in the ten weeks' period shown separately on page 13, the amount of stock bought per week, definite proposals having been made public on October 25th, went higher than it ever went before.</P>
    <P>In two of these weeks, 13,565 ordinary shares were purchased, and in the weeks ended 9th and 23rd, the number purchased was 14,203.  The total of preference stock purchased in the weeks ended 9th, 16th and 23rd October was, respectively, 22,004, 25,240 and 25,794 and of guaranteed preference in the same weeks, 40,239, 20,382 and 25,061.  For debenture stock in the same three weeks, the figures were 35,900, 48,877 and 58,011, so that in the weeks immediately following the decisions which appear to have been taken in the Department on 30th September, there was very substantial buying of stock, and when it was apparent that, over the period from the end of August, there was substantial buying, it ought to have been impressed on the Government that something was happening in the way of rumour or suggestion of one kind or another among the public that something was proposed with regard to the railway company and its finances, and they ought to have intervened to save <Col N="1803" /> the stockholders, about whom they express so much concern at other times and in other ways, from being jockeyed by rumour, fright or anxiety into disposing of stock which definitely, as must have been known to the Department and to the chairman at the time, was to be secured in a substantial way by Government proposals.</P>
    <P>We feel that a very serious injustice will be done to people who parted with their stock in circumstances which we consider were avoidable.  I have not got the increases for the various months, but when we hear of the increases that have taken place, say, from the early part of 1942 up to now, as a result of the publication of the proposals of the Government, we realise that a substantial wrong has been done to a large number of stockholders who parted in ignorance and perhaps fright with the stock they had.</P>
    <P>I, therefore, move that the people who should be given any compensation or should be given any stock in the new company should be the people who possessed stock at the time the Emergency Order was issued by the Government which wiped out the old board and put a Government-nominated chairman in control of the company.  I suggest it must have been in the Government's mind that they were going to follow up that by action with regard to the railway company somewhat along the lines they are now proposing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesLarkin1943" hpid="Mr. Larkin Mr. Larkin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Larkin</NameTxt>
      <P>I think, in view of the many remarks made by the Minister expressing concern with the ordinary shareholders, that some consideration along the lines set out by Deputy Mulcahy should, even at this late hour, be given them.  The Minister suggested yesterday that I did not seem to pay due regard to the interests of the shareholders.  I do not profess to have any particular regard for shareholders as a general body, but it would seem to me that whatever lack of concern I may have for ordinary shareholders, the Minister has set a pace that even I cannot keep up with.  His record started off in 1933 when he slashed the interests of the ordinary shareholders <Col N="1804" /> by 90 per cent. and now, following upon the activities of last year, he has left them helpless and derelict in face of the tremendous change which has taken place in the concern in which their interests lie.</P>
      <P>There are more than financial questions involved in this issue.  One of the things I would like to have placed before the House, in addition to a statement of the actual capital of the companies, is a statement indicating their effective ownership.  We have a habit of taking it for granted, when we speak of the shareholders of companies such as the Dublin United Transport Company and the Great Southern Railways Company, that we speak of a large body of persons who, in a democratic way, are effectively able to control the concern in which they have money invested.  Anyone who has followed the activities of a large industrial concern knows that that is not so, and that the effective control lies in the hands of a small group.  My feeling is that, despite the report of the committee of inquiry, what has been taking place during recent years in our State is a consolidation, a tightening of the grip, of a small financial group over our two main systems of transport, the Dublin system and the national system, as embodied in the Great Southern Railways Company, both road and rail sections.  I am fearful that what we are giving effect to in this Bill is not merely a technical or a financial reorganisation of transport, but we are clamping down in an effective manner a monopoly on the whole transport system and that monopoly will be in the hands of a very small group.  That may not be the position, but we have very few figures to lead us to a contrary view.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It would have been helpful if, in the course of his submissions to the House, the Minister had indicated exactly in whom he has vested control of the Great Southern Railways and what has been the effect, as regards that ownership, of the transactions in stocks and shares that have taken place since January, 1943.  If we did discover that the small shareholders, over whom tears of blood have been wept by the <Col N="1805" /> Minister, have lost whatever control and power they had previously, and that this power and this control are being exercised by a small group, then I think not only in the interests of the shareholders, but in the national interest, we would have to take a more serious view of the position.  Although the actual turnover of stocks and shares, according to the report of the committee of inquiry, was only 10 per cent. of the nominal value, that, added to what these groups already possess, guarantees them the effective control and enjoyment of all that we propose to give them in this Bill.</P>
    <P>As we know from experience of limited companies, there is no need for a group to control 51 per cent. of any company in order to be the dominant and deciding factor.  Very often, by a process of arrangement and understanding and proxy, a holding of 20 or 25 or 30 per cent. is sufficient.  When we have, in addition to that, a turnover of 10 per cent., then we have got to the position where the control has become cast-iron and we are dealing no longer with a body of small shareholders, but with a group of very powerful individuals who will reap the benefit of any legislation we pass here.</P>
    <P>The argument may be advanced that it would be a complicated and difficult matter to rectify what has happened, but when we take into account the dates set down by the committee of inquiry, such as the date of the speech of the chairman of the company, 3rd March, 1943, and the dates of the replies made by the Minister in this House to questions addressed to him, coupled with a history of the activities behind the scene between the officers of the Department and the railway company, we can see that on some particular date, if the interests and the welfare of the shareholders were any concern of the Minister or the Government, then on that date some warning should have been given to them that they should pause and not enter into any dealings to get rid of their interests in the railway company, but to wait and see what developments would take place.  I do not think that would be an exceptional thing to expect of any Government that professes <Col N="1806" /> to have an interest in the welfare of these men and women.</P>
    <P>We are told that one of the bases for the financial structure and the system of control by directors is concern for the shareholders and their financial interests.  We are, therefore, entitled to ask why was not that concern shown in a more effective manner so as to preserve what little interest these shareholders had in the company and prevent it being taken away from them by people who seem to have a wider knowledge and experience of how to make money on the stock exchange?  I am aware that, during this period that has been the subject of inquiry, many of the ordinary shareholders suffered a grievous financial loss.  Perhaps they were foolish in getting rid of their interests.  Perhaps they had not the ability and wisdom to draw the conclusions which other gentlemen seem to have been so facile in drawing.  At any rate, they unloaded whatever interest they had at a very considerable loss.  If we are, as we are supposed to be, concerned not with the large, well-protected, financially powerful group of individuals, but with the ordinary man and woman who have invested their small life savings in this company, and who, according to the Minister, have experienced a very bad period when they had no return on their investments and another period when the nominal value of their investments was cut by 90 per cent. now, when the sun is starting to shine, the least we might have done was to see that it shone on those who had gone through the hard period and not on those who had taken advantage of the rapid change in the circumstances of the company, and of the change in the policy of the Government towards the future of that company.</P>
    <P>I feel that this whole group of amendments here does embody a very important principle, and, as an ordinary matter of equity, the small shareholder should have been given some indication which would have protected him against this tidal wave that has over-swept him.  Even now, we should try to find machinery that would set a <Col N="1807" /> limit behind which those men and women could be protected.  In so far as those who invested in the stocks and shares are concerned, their particular interests could be dealt with in the form set down in some of the amendments, namely, through consideration by the High Court or some other judicial tribunal, which would estimate what financial interest they may have in the shares, and what loss they would suffer if the effective ownership were transferred to the original owners at an earlier date, before those pessimistic speeches of the chairman of the company upset their hopes.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>On the group of amendments which I presume are open for discussion at this moment&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 19 and 20 are open for discussion. The other points will arise in discussion on Nos. 22, 23, 25, 26 and 27. Nos. 19 and 20 deal with the question of date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>On the question of date, this resolves itself into a question as to who are to be regarded as registered holders for purposes of stock in the new company or for purposes that they themselves have described on various occassions as compensation for holdings that at one time were owned by certain people and are now owned by certain others in this company.  I put down March, 1943, because that is prior to the date on which the chairman made that speech.  It is to be noted that the tribunal of inquiry which was set up has definitely found that there was abnormal buying, and their comment on that is that prior to the chairman's speech at the annual meeting on March 3rd there was very little movement in those stocks.  The judicial report then continues:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;This speech was generally regarded as gloomy and had a very depressing effect on the market. Some holders proceeded to get rid of of their stocks and this occasioned some activity and a sharp fall in prices.  On the 24th March, Mr. Davin in Dáil Eireann addressed a <Col N="1808" /> question to the Minister arising out of the chairman's speech and, following the Minister's reply, which was non-committal, prices again fell slightly.  There was little activity or fluctuation for some weeks, but prices recovered somewhat in May. On the 26th May the Minister spoke on the Estimate for his Department and, following his speech, which was not regarded as encouraging, prices fell again and the market remained slack for some time.  We were informed by some of the stockbroker witnesses that during this period, the precise date being left in uncertainty, the stock exchange considered suspending all dealings in the company's stocks until the position became clearer.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>As a result of this long inquiry, we find in the narrative matter which leads up to the decision that purchases were abnormal in the period under consideration, and it is put down, first of all, to the chairman's speech on 3rd March, 1943, and to a few statements made by the Minister.  Each of those things caused prices to fall slightly, and then we are told that the stock exchange considered suspending all dealings in the company's stocks until the position became clearer.  Over the page, in the report, the other side of the picture is presented:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;From August onwards the dealings in the company's stocks were described to us as &lsquo;absolutely abnormal&rsquo;, &lsquo;a boom&rsquo;, &lsquo;absolutely hectic&rsquo;, &lsquo;inexplicable&rsquo;, and such seems to have been the general opinion on the stock exchange.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>It then goes on to say that stockbrokers suspected each other of having information.  In any event, there was a definite inflationary boom period, in which certain people, who might now be proprietors of what appeared to be very sound holdings, sold some of them at a very low price and others at fairly high prices considering the earlier levels that had been maintained.  The Minister was called upon to answer in regard to this matter, and his answer as given here in the report&mdash;a particular phrase to which I call attention &mdash;is that the dealings in the stocks <Col N="1809" /> were neither extensive nor abnormal. All the witnesses from the stock exchange flatly denied that, and there is a rather long-winded reference to the matter on page 12 of the report, which winds up with the particularly good descriptive phrase that&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;the figures supplied to the Minister as to the comparative volume of business done in 1942 and 1943 upon which he based his reply to Mr. Cole's question appear to have been compiled under a complete misapprehension as to the true significance of the particulars from which they were prepared and to have little or no relation to the actualities of the situation.  They were described by some of the broker witnesses as &lsquo;completely illusory&rsquo;&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>In any event, whatever the public had to go on, those remarks of the Minister and the chairman&mdash;two people who would have been expected to be in the know; two people who, as people of responsibility, would have been expected to advise the stockholders as to the exact position of their holdings&mdash;came much later in the year. We find the Minister's reply to a Parliamentary question, about which the most extreme <i>bona fides</i> is expected, criticised in that fashion&mdash;that it had little or no relation to the actualities of the situation, and that his figures, as described by some of the broker witnesses, were &ldquo;completely illusory&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>In the course of the inquiry, when two members of the stock exchange were called upon to give their evidence, the chairman, whose evidence came first, was asked as to whether it would not have been possible, following the statement made by the chairman to the meeting, when negotiations with regard to an approach to the Government were in progress, to have a warning issued by the chairman of the company, who was in the know, to the stockholders, asking them to retain their holdings as negotiations were in progress, the outcome of which, of course, could not be prophesied.</P>
    <P>The chairman of the stock exchange said he thought that could be done, but it might be unusual.  When the secretary was called upon to give <Col N="1810" /> evidence afterwards, the opening question to him was as to whether he had heard his colleague's statement, and whether he wished to take away from or add anything to it before giving special evidence of his own.  He said there were two matters to which he wished to refer.  One was the particular description his colleague had given of the boom period, which he described simply as &ldquo;abnormal&rdquo;. The secretary put on a few descriptive adverbs to that&mdash;&ldquo;absolutely exceptional&rdquo;, I think he said.  What he said regarding the second suggestion&mdash; which he wanted to disagree with&mdash;was that it can be described as unusual in normal circumstances for the chairman of a board to advise his shareholders to retain their holdings because it was certainly unusual in practice, but he said there were no such unusual circumstances as that.  For instance, I think he gave this example.  When there were two companies amalgamated, or a company reconstructing its financial background, or in particular approaching a Government for aid, then it was not unusual, but perfectly usual and normal, for a member of the board to warn stockholders that they should not part with their holdings, or at least give some idea of the value that should be put on them.</P>
    <P>In this country there is a significant example, not so many years ago, where that practice was followed.  There was a time here when considerable speculation occurred in D.W.D. shares and the chairman of the meeting on one occasion told his shareholders that the price of their shares was, ruling by the market of a particular date, in the region of 3/-.  He said, in fact, they had large stocks of whiskey and had obtained an actuarial calculation as to the value of the shares then ranking at 3/- if the market appreciated, and the actuarial calculation was 13/-.  The chairman then announced that, of course, there were other developments about which he could not prophesy, but if they eventuated successfully there would be a further rise in the share values.  At any rate, there was a clear hint by the chairman of that company to the shareholders that the shares that would appear from the <Col N="1811" /> market quotation to be worth only 3/- were worth 13/-.  I am giving the figures to the best of my memory and they may be very far removed from the actual figures, but the gap is a significant matter and it was at least as big a gap as I have indicated.  He told these people they should hold on, and at least any person who sold in the interim sold with a warning by the chairman of the company based on the actuarial calculations that the shares were at least worth a good deal more than they would appear to be worth in the market.</P>
    <P>What was the procedure adopted in connection with this company?  The chairman opened the ball on the 3rd March, 1943, in a long speech from which I propose to quote some extracts. If they are not sufficient, I will try to supply any gap, if my attention is drawn to the matter.  After asking how the railways could be operated efficiently he said:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Do you realise that for every two miles run by a steam engine, it was necessary to run one mile in marshalling and shunting?&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>That was the greatest joke ever made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The chairman continued:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Do you know that trains were running on inferior fuel and were hours behind and that they lost many more hours because they were operated over a large section of single track lines?  Very often turf had to be handled twice because trains could not, for technical reasons, be run on another section of the system.  The rolling stock is largely obsolete and the real problem during the year was to meet the transport needs of the community at any cost.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>He then went into the matter of labour and said:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;In the days when the railway served the community with that high standard of efficiency which is always necessary to produce profits, wages were low and the cost-of-living index figure was unknown.  To-day the wage <Col N="1812" /> content is so high that even if railways were modernised the country could not afford a transport system which needs some 15,000 workers to operate it.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>He then went on to pass a few further comments which certainly would not arouse any enthusiasm in the shareholders. With regard to trade union restrictions, imposed on this body of 15,000 operators, or some parts of them, he then said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The 1943 revenue is already considerably down.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I want to mark that phrase:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The 1943 revenue is already considerably down.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>He was speaking on the 3rd March, 1943, and dealing with part of the revenue of the year, two months of which had gone by.  He continued:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The position in 1943 will be that for every £ of gross revenue earned the workers will receive 13/-.  That is an impossible position and although the trade unions have been warned they have decided to take all they can get at the moment, even though by so doing they will disemploy hundreds and as time goes on, thousands of their fellow workers.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There was a definite hint there with regard to the rolling stock being obsolete and the railway workers were gouging whatever they could out of the depleted revenue, with the warning that, if this went on, not merely hundreds but thousands of the employees would lose their employment. He said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I hope I have succeeded in making it clear that obsolescence and the excessive number of workers required to operate the system have brought the railways to a time in the history of transport in Ireland when they can no longer compete with road services.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There was this chilling phrase:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I do not suggest that the country can do without railway services altogether.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I should say that shareholders listening <Col N="1813" /> to his speech at that point would have thought about selling for whatever they could get, because it looked as if the chairman contemplated the disappearance of the railways as a system of transport over the country to a considerable extent.  He says then:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;There must be a reorganisation and whatever portion of the railway remains as part of a transport system must be modernised and efficient.  Rail and road services must be co-ordinated so as to give the community what is best and most suitable in each for its needs.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>A little later, he spoke of the point that railway companies do not make allowance for depreciation:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;It is not the practice of the railways to provide for depreciation.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>When we in this House discuss this phrase, we are apt to leave it at that &mdash;&ldquo;do not provide for depreciation&rdquo;. Mr. Reynolds gave the other side of the picture and stated what is allowed instead&mdash;a system of renewals:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;When, after amalgamation, intensive competition from road services, very often unfair, had to be met, the company found itself unable to earn enough to provide for renewals and this has resulted in the obsolescent state in which the railways find themselves to-day.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>We did definitely say they never had allowed for depreciation&mdash;that is not railway practice&mdash;but there is the other matter, the renewals, to be attended to in lieu of depreciation, and that minimum of renewals could not be done by this company because of the intensive competition and as a result they are in the obsolescent state in which we find them to-day.  Here is another chilling phrase:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;You cannot now provide out of future revenue the money necessary to make good the failure to provide for renewals in the past and there is no reason to think that the railway can&mdash;no matter how much you ask for the services rendered&mdash;pay dividends on existing capital.  There must, therefore, be a reconstruction <Col N="1814" /> of the capital of the company and what is ultimately agreed to be the value of the stockholders' interest should rank equally with and carry whatever guarantees are given to those subscribing new capital.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That again was a definite indication to any shareholder that his capital was going to be very drastically and very largely written down.  Then there was the amazing phrase that &ldquo;no matter what is charged for the services rendered, no matter how much you ask, there is no reason to think the railways can pay dividends on the existing capital.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>At a later point, he said that he was going to ask for an Emergency Powers Order allowing them to increase rail rates and charges.  Ordinarily, that would be done before the Railway Tribunal, but this time he was simply going to apply to the Minister for an Order and hoped to get it.  Then, lest any shareholder might get one little heartbeat of comfort from his speech, he said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Unless there is a decided improvement in the supplies position, this will do no more than enable us to make ends meet, the future payment of dividends depending entirely on the success of the proposals for reorganisation.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That was his opening remark on this whole matter.  The next in the field was the Minister.  He is referred to in the report of the Tribunal of Inquiry, page 10.  When Mr. Davin addressed a question to the Minister in Dáil Eireann arising out of the chairman's speech the Minister's reply was noncommittal and prices again fell slightly. It goes on:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;There was little activity or fluctuation for some weeks, but prices recovered somewhat in May.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There is then a reference to the Minister's speech in May on the Department Estimate, and it says:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Following his speech, which was not regarded as encouraging, prices fell again and the market remained slack for some time.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1815" /> In May what the Minister did say was this:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The railway company is making a loss now and the anticipated revenue of the company for the present year will not meet its working costs.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Mr. Reynolds spoke in March and referred to the couple of months of the railway revenue, the records of which he was able to see, and said it was down in comparison with the previous year.  The Minister's speeches in May, and presumably his reference to the loss, must have some relation to a later period than that to which Mr. Reynolds referred in March.  But in May, whatever date the Minister's mind was fixed on, he said the railway company was making a loss and that &ldquo;its anticipated revenue for the present year would not meet its working costs&rdquo;.  In a speech during the election at Inchicore, in June, the statement was, if anything, worse.  He said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The Great Southern present earnings, even during the war, are insufficient to pay the working expenses.  Even the increased rates will not cover the deficiency in full.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That is June.  I presume that during all this time the Minister, who is a responsible man, was getting information from the railway company as to how their revenue was going and that these remarks were founded upon some information supplied to him by the railway company.  But certainly, up to June, the situation is that even the increased rates &ldquo;will not cover the deficiency&rdquo;, the deficiency being the inability of the railway company to meet its working expenses.</P>
    <P>Finally, we come to the point when in October, in a famous circular, Mr. Reynolds again addressed the shareholders and once more declared that the company's rolling-stock was obsolete.  He added to it this precise phrase: &ldquo;New buildings, plant and machinery will be needed.&rdquo; He said: &ldquo;The reorganisation of the permanent way, the stations and the yards will call for the expenditure of large sums <Col N="1816" /> of money.&rdquo; Here again is a reference to the state of the physical assets, the property of the shareholders, certainly of the debenture holders in the company. Up to that point, Mr. Reynolds has certainly said the rolling-stock was obsolete and later on he declared that the permanent way, new buildings, stations and yards were all requiring expenditure of large sums of money. Mr. Reynolds also talked about the revenue being deficient in comparison with the year before.  The Minister in his speech, both in May and June, simply said, this railway cannot go on; it is not making enough to meet working expenses.  And, lest anybody should have taken comfort from the new Order giving power to charge increased rates and fares, Mr. Reynolds said he did not believe, no matter what was asked, that the service that was to be rendered would earn sufficient to pay dividends and the Minister said that the anticipated revenue would not meet the working costs.  In June, he said that the increased rates would not cover the deficiency in full.  It all wound up with the circular addressed to the shareholders on the 25th October, Mr. Reynolds simply confessing to the shareholders, in this vivid phrase, &ldquo;we want new money.&rdquo; He said there was no reason to believe that the public would subscribe it.  In fact he put it positively&mdash;&ldquo;The public will not subscribe the additional capital required.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Remember, that is October.  Say, possibly, there was a lag of a month; say that no revenue for October was before the chairman of the company when he made that announcement on the 25th and that the October, November and December revenue still had to come in.  He, at least, had nine months of the railway working and he had three months of the working with the increased fares.  What do we find? At the end of the year the 1943 accounts disclosed that the amount provided for renewals and maintenance exceeded the average of the previous five years by about £600,000 and that after providing for that extra maintenance the profits of the company amounted to over £600,000.  The man who said to his shareholders that there <Col N="1817" /> was no reason to expect, no matter what was asked, that the railway can pay dividends on its existing capital, succeeded in the year in which he made that statement in paying a dividend in every class of the capital.</P>
    <P>There might be some excuse for a man speaking in March, not knowing how the railway system was going to work out.  There might even be some excuse for a Minister, speaking in this House on an Estimate, when less than half the year had gone, saying the deficiencies in the working expenses will not be met in full.  There might even be some excuse for a Minister, in the middle of an election, addressing a crowd at Inchicore, telling the workers that their livelihood was in jeopardy and that even the new rates would not enable the deficiency to be met.  But what excuse is there for a man who has all the controls and all the information through his office, on the 25th October, telling his shareholders nothing except that large sums were going to be required for permanent way, stations, yards, locomotives, and winding up with this phrase: &ldquo;The public will not subscribe the extra money we want?&rdquo; Without any extra money&mdash;because there has been no extra money put into this concern&mdash;we find that the next year, but based on the revenue for the year 1943, a dividend is paid in every class of stock with, I think, some arrears, the amount provided for renewals and maintenance is over the average provided for the previous five years by £600,000.  When that is done, there is £600,000 left for the provision of this dividend.</P>
    <P>The way in which company directors address their boards and the way in which prospectuses are framed has been the subject of inquiry in the courts in many cases.  The most notable one has been the Royal Mail Steam Packet Company case in which Lord Kylsant was sent to jail for including in a prospectus a statement that was found in the end to be false in a material particular.  In a foreword to an account of that case this statement occurs:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;A man who issues a prospectus is <Col N="1818" /> endeavouring to sell an interest in his own concern to the public and no salesman traditionally cries &lsquo;stinking fish&rsquo;.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>What were these statements except a cry of &ldquo;stinking fish&rdquo;, four times repeated, and made by the two people who were at the heart of this concern. They said &ldquo;this concern has no future, we cannot even make our working expenses, and even the increased rates will not allow it to be done,&rdquo; and persisted in that cry of &ldquo;stinking fish&rdquo; until the 25th October, and then, two or three months later, they solemnly declare a dividend in every class of the stock, while providing £600,000 for renewals and maintenance more than had been provided in the average of six or seven years previously.</P>
    <P>Taking the Minister's phrase the other day that he wants to be fair to the shareholders, let us be fair to them.  Let us be fair to the real shareholders. Are we going to give this guarantee or Government pledge of finding them their money, if the company cannot find it out of revenue, to the people who, oppressed by these statements, made by these two responsible and knowledgeable people, sold their shares and after they had sold, or while in process of selling, there emerged a situation which has been described by witnesses and set down in this guarded report of the judicial inquiry as &ldquo;absolutely abnormal,&rdquo;&ldquo;a boom,&rdquo;&ldquo;absolutely hectic,&rdquo;&ldquo;inexplicable&rdquo;?  Some months later, the Minister on the best advice he can get, on the compilation of figures given to him, tells this House that dealings in stock which were described by witnesses in that way, were neither abnormal nor extensive. Stockbroker witnesses said that these statements of the Minister were definitely illusory.</P>
    <P>What was happening during all this time?  Did the Minister know that there was an improvement in the company's revenue?  I should imagine, if he did, he would have told all about that.  Did the chairman know?  The chairman made a very distinct statement in March.  He said the revenue was down for a couple of months in comparison with the corresponding <Col N="1819" /> couple of months in the previous period.  Surely the public can certainly see that one-tenth of the shareholders were jockeyed out of their holdings&mdash; their property&mdash;when that circular was issued on the 25th October, as late a date as almost the end of the tenth month in the year in which, eventually, all classes of stock got a dividend, while a bigger provision was made for renewals and maintenance than ever was made before.  Surely, the possessors of that property, who sold at that particular period, are entitled to some explanation.  I wonder if there was not a greater number of such people involved in those days than those described in the tribunal report as one-tenth.  At any rate, they did it, and I think that these people are entitled to an explanation.</P>
    <P>Now, when it comes to the question of shares, I have to turn to another aspect of this matter.  There is another and rather peculiar side to the picture that has been presented here.  The Minister, in the last couple of days, on at least a few occasions, said that whether the assets are wasted or wasting is not a pivotal matter: that even with wasted or wasting assets you can make revenue, and that there were things in the background of the organisation which would give hope to the railways.  Where is that hope held out to the shareholders?  I can find no single remark there which conveys to the shareholders that, although their stocks are a bit out of date, and so on, it may be possible to do something for them because they have a really good company in the background.  I can only describe that as a mortuary card notice.  It is heavily ringed with black, and there is not gleam shining through. All these people have been referred to, in effect, as not being able to help us to make our working expenses.  There is, however, a change in the House now, dealing with the same thing, and again I want to refer to the words of a famous economist, known as Mr. Hartley Withers, who wrote a book called <i>Stocks and Shares.</i> One part of that book has often been quoted by people in connection with the floating of companies.  He said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1820" />&ldquo;All prospectuses should be scanned in a spirit of jaundiced criticism and with the most pessimistic readiness to believe that they are speciously alluring traps laid by some designing financier to relieve the reader of some of his money.  No allowance should be made, and the benefit of the doubt should never be given to the prospectus.  In fact, a large number of them are quite reasonable propositions put forward by quite honest men, but when they are of this kind they will, or ought to, stand the most sceptical scrutiny, and when they are not it is a service to the community at large to put them as quickly as possible in the wastepaper basket.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>And this is a phrase to which I want to direct the Minister's attention, as being in some degree descriptive of this company which was described, in the year 1943, as lying prostrate:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;When they arrive by post, or thrust themselves on your attention in the columns of your newspaper, your first instinctive thought should be that here is somebody wanting your money, and that he may be a descendant of Dick Turpin throwing back to his distinguished ancestor and practising brigandage in a more modern and much less attractive form.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The Minister comes into this House in the last couple of days and is now presenting the rosy side of the whole picture: We should give money to these shareholders; we should give the moneys that he wants us to give to the Great Southern Railways Company and to the Transport Company because, as he said formerly, the company was in a hopeless condition.  But look at what has happened in the meantime.  I want the House to consider the attitude of the Minister in his present mood as being what has been described by Mr. Withers as practising brigandage on the public.  Whatever the case may be, however, I want to ensure that there will be some method of calculation as to value.  Whatever the sum may be&mdash;and I am not speaking now of the type of people who were <Col N="1821" /> referred to yesterday as &ldquo;fly-boys&rdquo; who make money on stock exchange transactions; I am speaking of people who owned these shares, people who were, and who must have been, swayed by the statements that were made-I want to ensure that there should be some proper method of calculation as to the value of these shares at the time.  Other statements were made besides those to which I have referred, but there certainly were not statements made which were calculated to lighten the gloom of the statements I have quoted.  I certainly think that the stockholders who have been done out of their shares will have reason to complain that this House has no sense of justice, having heard a responsible Minister make the statements that he has twice made, and also having heard the statement that the Minister's nominee made to the railway company at that particular time&mdash;the statements he made carrying his pessimism as late as up to the 25th October of that particular year.  These stockholders will say that this House has no sense of justice if, having considered these matters, we proceed to deal with the whole question as if the Minister and Mr. Reynolds never spoke on the matter.</P>
    <P>I say that we have responsibilities&mdash; that this House has a responsibility&mdash; because the Minister, speaking as a Minister of this House, did tell these shareholders that their property was nearly gone, even as he told the railwaymen themselves that their livelihoods were in jeopardy; and his nominee, in even more detailed terms, carried on these very gloomy prophecies up to as late as 25th October, 1943.  I have mentioned the end of March.  Operations were carried on up to that period, but I take it that March, being the end of the financial year, would be the last period.  In view of what I have said, I think that we should reinstate those people in the position they were holding. I am sure that the point will be made to me that these people got money and, therefore, what do I propose to do about them?  I propose to let them have it.  I am not in a position to suggest what would be completely equitable from the point of <Col N="1822" /> view of these people, but, judging from the number of people who have written to me, I know that, in addition to the reduced purchase price which the majority of these people got for their shares, through selling at that particular time, they have also lost by not holding on in respect of the shares that they did not hold on to up to the end of October, 1943.  It appears to me that if those people were to be allowed to keep the money that they got by selling on the stock exchange, and be allowed to get the dividends accruing, it would be found that they have not gained anything at all, but rather that they have lost.  I have not calculated the amount over a sufficient number of cases to enable me to give a real example, but that is the best number I can get, and in such cases I suggest that these people should be dealt with in the way I have suggested.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The speech made by Deputy McGilligan was designed to divert the attention of the Dáil from the real issue arising from these amendments.  The proposal put forward by Deputy Mulcahy, linked with the proposal of Deputy McGilligan, is a direct consequence of the allegations that were made here in the past: that certain people, who had engaged in transactions concerning stocks of the Great Southern Railways Company, had indulged in these transactions because they were aware beforehand of the Government's intentions in regard to the reorganisation of the company.  I think these amendments were framed at a time when the Party opposite were hoping or expecting that the report of the tribunal would be different from what it was. Now that the tribunal has reported, and reported in the most emphatic manner, that there was no foundation for the allegations made by Deputies opposite, surely it is time that this campaign stopped.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Am I to take it that Deputies opposite are not accepting the report of the tribunal?  That is the implication to be read into these amendments and into Deputy McGilligan's speech.  Not merely were these allegations made in the Dáil but they were <Col N="1823" /> made throughout the country, made in the most flagrant manner at public meetings during the general election. Many people heard these allegations made.  People were no doubt influenced by these allegations, people who will never learn that the tribunal which investigated the allegations and before which these Deputies were brought on oath, reported that not a single one of them was able to depose to any fact which constituted direct evidence of any disclosure of information. There are many people who will never know that that was the tribunal's report, that that was the result of the evidence of these Deputies who made these allegations so glibly in the past in the Dáil and during the election campaign throughout the country.</P>
    <P>It is true these allegations were made.  It is true that a campaign which was a disgrace to the political life of this country was carried on by many Deputies and ex-Deputies of this House.  Is one of them going to apologise, now that their allegations have been completely exploded?  Surely honesty and public decency require some withdrawal from some one of these Deputies or some representative of these Deputies?  The tribunal's report was as specific as a report could be.  They do not merely say that the allegations were not proven.  They do not merely advert to the inability of the Deputies who made the allegations to produce evidence to support them. They report that they had fully investigated every single aspect of the matter and found, as a fact, that there was no disclosure of information, no improper use of information, that no person purchased shares of the Great Southern Railways Company by reason of information improperly used or improperly disclosed.  That is now the fact as established by a judicial tribunal which carried out an exhaustive investigation.  Is that fact going to be accepted or are we going to have a continuation in another form of the rotten allegations which were bandied about so frequently during the election campaign?  I suggest that it is now the duty of the Deputies who were associated with that campaign to express <Col N="1824" /> their regret for having participated in it and to withdraw the insinuations they made, which affect the honour of individuals, and if they are not going to discharge that duty, I suggest their retirement from public life is overdue.</P>
    <P>Having established as a fact that no person purchased shares of the Great Southern Railways Company by reason of any improper use or improper disclosure of information, is there a case now for amending this Bill in the manner suggested for the purpose of penalising persons who acquired these shares during the past two years or during the past year according to the form the amendments take?  Many people acquired shares of the Great Southern Railways Company during that time&mdash;some by purchase, some by gift, some by inheritance, some perhaps on the surrender of securities for loans.  In a multitude of ways the shares passed from hand to hand. People bought these shares as an investment and still hold them.  It is these people who purchased these shares as an investment, who acquired the shares by inheritance, who acquired the shares in legitimate ways, whom the Deputies opposite are proposing to penalise.  If there were speculators, people who purchased the shares in order to secure an appreciation of the capital value when the market price of these shares rose, they have sold out and they are not affected by the amendment.  The enactment of this amendment will not cause them to lose any of their gains and would in no way diminish the profit they made.  It is those who did not speculate, those who purchased for investment purposes, those who acquired the shares by inheritance during this period, whom Deputies opposite are trying to penalise, not because they wish to penalise them but because they hope to keep alive the rotten campaign with which they were associated during the last three or four months.</P>
    <P>I hope Deputies will read the report of the tribunal and read it very carefully. I hope they will not be misled by the distorted versions of the report which appeared in some newspapers. I want to express particularly my contempt <Col N="1825" /> of the tactics of the <i>Irish Times</i> and of the manner in which it presented that report to the public. Nobody reading the headlines in that paper or the sub-editor's observations on the contents of the report could have possibly understood the full significance of the tribunal's decision. These Yellow Press tactics will not commend themselves, I know, to the readers of that paper and I hope that Deputies will not be misled by them, that they will read the report for themselves and see the specific and unambiguous nature of the verdict of the tribunal.</P>
    <P>Deputy Mulcahy says that there was an obligation on the Government and on the Minister for Industry and Commerce to tell the shareholders of the Great Southern Railways Company in February of last year that legislation affecting their interests was in contemplation. He knows, by reason of the evidence produced before the tribunal, the various developments in the plans for transport reorganisation. If he had studied them carefully he would have realised that in February, 1943, I contemplated a scheme of reorganisation which involved compressing the capital of the Great Southern Railways Company and the Dublin United Transport Company within a figure of £10,000,000.  That plan would involve a further reduction in the nominal value of the stocks of these shareholders.  If that plan had been proceeded with, and if I had done what Deputy Mulcahy says now we should have done, and if I had told the shareholders not to part with their shares, is there any Deputy who does not feel that Deputy Mulcahy and his colleagues would have made the welkin ring in denouncing my action? In fact, the plan which was on the books in February, 1943, was not the one which found expression in a draft Bill, that plan was modified, and modified in consequence of the examination which was given to it when it was drafted and presented to the Government.</P>
    <P>Deputy Mulcahy quoted very carefully from the report of the tribunal or some of the quotations contained in the report.  Some of these quotations <Col N="1826" /> are from statements made by me and made by the chairman, which are contained in the report, but I presume he knows he left out the most significant quotation in order to maintain his case that I was in default in not intimating to the shareholders that legislation was in contemplation.  He deliberately ignored various statements that are contained in that report.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>What are the statements?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>On page 22 of the report there is an extract from a statement made by me in the Dáil on the 26th May, 1943.  I quote from the statement:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;It is necessary, in my opinion, that the process of reorganisation should be begun earlier.  As Mr. Reynolds intimated to the company at the annual meeting reorganisation proposals are at present being worked out and will, in due course, be completed.  If it should be my function they will be prepared in the form of legislation for submission to the Dáil.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That intimation to the Dáil and to the public, that legislation affecting the Great Southern Railways Company was in course of preparation, was made on the 26th May, 1943.  On the 16th June, 1943, in a statement made on behalf of the Government Party then contesting a general election, a statement that received considerable publicity in the newspapers, I stated that &ldquo;the framing of the necessary legislation has begun, and if the present Government is re-elected it is expected that the general framework of the measure will be completed at an early date and the drafting of the necessary Bill put in hands.&rdquo;  These specific declarations, that legislation was being prepared and that it was the intention of the Government to introduce it, were available to members of the public and to the shareholders of the company in May and June, 1943, and the fact that many shareholders noted these declarations, and appreciated their significance, was brought out in evidence before the tribunal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1827" /> Deputy McGilligan referred to the speech made by the chairman of the Great Southern Railways Company at the annual meeting of that company in 1943.  He read extracts from it, and represented it as a speech deliberately designed to discourage the shareholders of that company as to their future prospects.  He represented the chairman of the company as describing the undertaking as &ldquo;stinking fish&rdquo;.  I think these were the words he used. I do not know whether Deputy McGilligan was deliberately trying to misrepresent the speech of the chairman of the company on that occasion, but certainly the extracts from that speech which he read did not give the full purport of the speech or the meaning which the speaker intended to convey. Shareholders of the company went before the tribunal and testified that, as a result of that speech, they decided to increase their investments in the shares of the company.  One of the shareholders, according to the report of the tribunal, described that speech as the best intimation that he had ever got.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>He said it was a straight tip.  A lot of other witnesses were asked did they regard it as such, and not one of them supported him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a matter of personal opinion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Only one man said that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The fact is that the speech was obviously capable of another interpretation than that which Deputy McGilligan put on it, and other people did, in fact, put another interpretation on it.  It is true that in March, 1943, the company had at that time earned less than in the corresponding period of the previous year. It is quite true that up to May, 1943, it appeared that the company was not going to earn sufficient to cover its working expenses.  It is also quite true that in May, 1943, it became urgently necessary to increase the rates that the company could charge, and these rates were increased.  When <Col N="1828" /> Mr. Reynolds and I discussed the position in the earlier months of that year, I did not think and he did not think that the reorganisation which he was bringing into effect would produce results as quickly as they did.  We certainly had no idea that they would permit of a dividend being paid at the end of that financial year.  It was not until June, 1943, that Mr. Reynolds came to see me and told me that the financial results of the company's working were proving to be better than he anticipated, and it was not until much later in the year that it became obvious that the reorganisation brought into force was producing results on a far more substantial scale and much more rapidly than had been originally thought possible.</P>
      <P>The Dáil has been asked to consider the position of a lot of shareholders who, according to Deputy McGilligan, were &ldquo;jockeyed&rdquo; out of their holdings. I do not know if Deputy McGilligan used that word for the purpose of conveying the idea that somebody deliberately planned and executed the business of depriving these shareholders of their holdings, but I think that is what he intended to convey by the use of that term.  We know that, despite the interpretation which Deputy McGilligan has put upon the speech of the chairman of the company and the various statements made by himself, 90 per cent. of the shareholders in the company did not part with their shares: that in respect of 90 per cent. of the total holdings of stock there were no stock exchange transactions at all.  To whatever extent shareholders may have been misled, or may have misrepresented the facts of the situation, not more than 10 per cent. of them decided that they should take action to the extent of disposing of their holdings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Let us be quite clear as to what was, in fact, the position of these shareholders.  Most of the holders of the ordinary and preference stocks in the Great Southern Railways Company had been in the position described by a stock exchange witness before the tribunal when he said that they could not sell their stock.  One witness said that if you wanted to sell <Col N="1829" /> Great Southern Railways stock you had to go out and look for somebody to buy it, and, no doubt, many of the stockholders would, in the months before 1943, have been glad of an opportunity to realise their holdings if they could, but were unable to do it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>The banks would not do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>What does the Deputy read into that fact?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>That they control most of the shareholders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>A number probably regarded it as being to their advantage that the market became active in Great Southern Railway shares and that they had an opportunity of disposing of their holdings for cash without difficulty.  In any event, there is nothing which transpired in that period which would justify us now in abusing our power of legislation in order deliberately to penalise people who quite legally and with no suggestion of any irregularity came into the possession of Great Southern Railways shares during the period prior to the publication of the circular and the introduction of the Bill.  I think that for the Dáil to accept these amendments would be an abuse of its power which would be completely indefensible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy Larkin appears to think that we should endeavour to secure that the benefits of the reorganisation scheme, which we are now attempting to bring into effect, should be secured not merely for the shareholders who held shares in March, 1943, or the shareholders who held shares in February, 1942, as Deputy Mulcahy proposes, but for all those who held shares in 1933. The Deputy wants us to go back over the past 11 years and eliminate from whatever benefits may be conferred by the Bill all those shareholders in the company who acquired shares since the Act of 1933 was passed, the Act which cut the value of Great Southern Railways stocks.  I think that is a preposterous proposal.  The Act of 1933 was justified by the circumstances of 1933. During the intervening period, there <Col N="1830" /> have been many transactions in the shares of that company, and it would be almost impossible to secure now that the benefit of the improved conditions, if there are to be improved conditions following the enactment of this Bill, should be diverted exclusively to those who happened to be holders of Great Southern Railways stocks more than ten years ago.  I do not think that the suggestion was seriously intended. Presumably, it was just as seriously intended as the one put forward by Deputy Mulcahy or Deputy McGilligan.</P>
    <P>The tribunal reported that there were abnormal dealings in the stocks of the Great Southern Railways during the ten weeks prior to the publication of the company's circular.  I confess that when I was questioned in the Dáil before the establishment of the tribunal I stated that as far as the information available to me showed, there were no abnormal dealings in these stocks.  The only source of information that I had were the company's books.  The tribunal pointed out that the transactions recorded in the company's books were not necessarily an indication of the number of transactions in the stock.  It is obvious, when one considers it, that there may be many transactions in the shares of a company before the ultimate change becomes recorded in the company's books.  On that occasion I had no source of information open to me except the company's register, and on the date on which I arranged to have it examined it justified the conclusion that I had reached.  In any event the facts upon which that conclusion was based, are given in the reply, and these facts are accurate.</P>
    <P>It is necessary for Deputies to make, in their own minds, the distinction which the chairman of the company made in his speech between the railway undertaking of the Great Southern Railways Company and the company itself.  It is quite true that, in the financial year 1942, the railway undertaking did not earn sufficient to pay all the working expenses and charges associated with that undertaking, taking debenture interest as a charge <Col N="1831" /> upon the revenue.  The company's road undertaking did earn revenue which, added to the total revenue derived from the railway undertaking, permitted of the payment of the debenture interest, even though it was not possible, as the chairman said, to make a proper appropriation for maintenance and renewal of the company's assets.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Did he, in his speech, say: &ldquo;We have road resources on which we can rely.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I think he did.  It is quite obvious that there is a distinction between the railway undertaking and the road undertaking.  This is not merely a railway undertaking; it is a transport undertaking.  It provides road passenger transport, road haulage services and ancillary services some, or all, of which are revenue-producing. The road transport services are extremely profitable.  There were periods in the company's history in which the profits of the road undertaking were helping to maintain the railway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister allow me to quote from the speech the reference to the road services?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that there is anything in that speech which affects what I say, but I have no objection to the Deputy reading it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>After giving figures, the speech proceeds:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;There was a very serious shortage of fuel, tyres and spare parts and services must be restricted at once.  The fuel position was such that road services might have to be suspended at very short notice.  The payment of debenture interest for last year was only possible because of the net revenue derived from road services and, as they could not depend on this source for anything like the same net income as was forthcoming last year, they were left with no option but to increase rail rates and charges.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1832" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>A perfectly accurate statement of the circumstances then existing.  He told them that the payment of debenture interest was only made possible by the revenue derived from the road services.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>And that they could not depend on receiving anything like the same amount as before.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Was that revealing any secret?  Was it revealing anything which any Deputy did not know?  As the responsible Minister, I went to the broadcasting station to warn the country about the transport position. Restrictions were imposed on the road transport services operated by private traders and licensed hauliers.  We brought a scheme into operation in the western counties, which we extended over a large part of the country, with a view to carrying on essential services, despite diminishing supplies of petrol, tyres and parts.  Was it the duty of the chairman of the company to draw the attention of his shareholders to the fact?  Are we not now entitled to congratulate ourselves that the crisis which we then anticipated did not prove to be as bad as it might have been?  Are we not entitled to congratulate ourselves on the fact that the problem has now eased considerably and that, instead of contracting the services of the company, we are able, to a limited extent, to arrange for their expansion?  It is still true that the extent to which expansion can take place is limited by the reduced supplies of tyres and equipment but the fact that expansion has taken place is a source of congratulation not merely to members of the Dáil and the public but also to members of the company, the revenue mainstay of which was furnished by the road services.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I urge the Dáil to reject these amendments.  I think that it would be iniquitous for the Dáil seriously to consider passing these amendments.  I say that there is no justification whatever for them except to try to support the discreditable campaign undertaken by certain Deputies during the past three or four months.  I hope that the Dáil will, by rejecting these amendments <Col N="1833" /> emphatically, show what it thinks of the campaign.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to leave aside the little red herring the Minister has drawn across this proposal and also to leave aside the <i>Irish Times.</i> Let us come back to the proposal before the House.  The proposal is that the House take into consideration the neglect on the part of the Minister and the chairman of the Great Southern Railways Company to warn the holders of stock that proposals were in contemplation as between the chairman and the Government and that definite decisions were being set that would substantially enhance the value of their holdings.  Quotations for the stock over a period were set out in a reply to a Parliamentary Question put by me on Tuesday.  The highest quotations in the last week in June in certain years were given in that reply. In the year 1939&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Why commence with 1939?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall come along to 1940 and 1941.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Why not go back to 1937?  The Deputy got the figures from 1937.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall give all the figures that I have here, although I intended to commence with 1939.  For ordinary stock, the figures were: 1937, £34½; 1938, £20; 1939, £9?; 1940, £8; 1941, £8.  No quotations were avail able, so far as the Government was concerned, for 1942 or 1943, but, in 1944, the quotation was £51.  For the preference shares, the quotations were from 1937 onwards to 1944: £46, £20, £13¼, £9½, £9, £18, £14, £51.  For the guaranteed preference shares, the quotations were in the same years: £72½, £50, £30, £20?, £28, £38½, £28½, £70.  For debenture stock, the quotations were: £88¾, £70, £52, £44, £51?, £63, £54, £93?.  The appreciation that took place in the stock from 1939, when the tribunal inquired into the railway position, up to the present is shown by these figures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1834" /> From then there has been a very substantial increase in the valuation of the stock.  There was a particular rise in the value of the stock between the period which we are discussing and the period during which the information got to those with their ears to the ground.  Government action in relation to the railways, the statement of the Minister and the statement of the chairman of the company all created contradictory effects in the minds of certain people.  Some were clever enough to read into them that appreciation was going to take place but others were not able to read the news in that way.  We get into a rather interesting period in Ireland if the Irish Stock Exchange, as far as it caters for Irish industry, is going to become a place for speculation. Normally, what we want a stock exchange for in relation to industry here is, so it would be possible for our people to put their money into industry, and yet have machinery by which, if they required money in particular circumstances, they would be able to liquefy it.  In the circumstances we are now coming to, with Government interference likely to be of considerable importance in industry, if our stock exchange is going to have this effect, that people with sharp ears are able to manipulate transactions and make a living, while other people are going to lose, we should be very careful before we subscribe to that policy.</P>
    <P>The Government cannot deal with industry in such a way as to change substantially the value of an industry and do so without any regard for the interests of those who hold stock.  The Minister stated that certain pages of the report were left unquoted.  There was no intention to misrepresent.  We simply made a case with certain facts and asked the House to decide.  If the Minister wants to go back over various statements that were quoted from the report he can do so, but he should not misrepresent things.  He quoted from a statement made on page 22 of the report, where he stated that it was necessary that reorganisation should begin early.  That followed a statement made on May 26th, 1943, in which he said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;However, the position is, as I <Col N="1835" /> think the employees of the railway company must know, that the whole organisation upon which they are dependent for a livelihood is in jeopardy.  There is no useful purpose to be served by concealing the fact from them, that the organisation cannot be carried on indefinitely at a loss.  It is making a loss and it will continue to make a loss unless the general reorganisation which the Government contemplates, and to which Mr. Reynolds referred at the annual meeting, is successfully carried out....&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That statement of the Minister did not do anything to relieve the gloom.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The tribunal refer to that in the preface.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I quoted that speech in reply to Deputy Mulcahy, when he said that no intimation was given to the shareholders that legislation was contemplated.  In that speech it was definitely stated that legislation was contemplated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not accepting, in such gloomy terms, that legislation was pending.  What I contend is that, having reached the conclusion gradually reached, and particularly as early as July, 1943, a definite warning ought to have been issued by the Government to stockholders to hold on to their stock.  The facts of the situation are plain, and no claims of misrepresentation of any kind here, or on the part of the Minister, should be taken.  Persons have by the general circumstances, and by the general atmosphere of that time, been deprived of wealth that they were entitled to hold.  The Minister said that some people got in, and some got out, making profits in that way.  That is no reason why one part of the problem could not be dealt with satisfactorily. We are asked to decide whether, in circumstances due entirely to Government actions, persons who were able to read the signs made a substantial amount of money, while others who could not read the signs so well lost. It is a reflection on the whole way in which the Government conducted the <Col N="1836" /> business, and it is for this House to try to secure that people will get fair play from Parliament when dealing with business matters.  This is a beginning, I suggest, of acceptance by the Government that they are completely dispensed from giving any kind of hint to stockholders of particular companies in respect of which the Government takes action affecting value.  I do not think we can accept that position and that this is a clear case to which Parliament should direct attention, and make up its mind to make good the losses in some other way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is one of the most eloquent speakers on the Ministerial Bench, and he sometimes succeeds in convincing the House that his case is a better one than any made by his opponents.  In the speech he has just delivered, he tried to create the impression that the stockholders were all ordinary people, whereas the fact is&mdash;and I am sure he knows it as well as anybody else&mdash;that the big bulk of the ordinary shares, the preference and the guaranteed preference shares are held by the principal banks, particularly by the Bank of Ireland.  If any evidence of that statement is needed it can be found on page 35 of the report of the Judges' Tribunal.  As a result of his evidence before the tribunal the chairman of the company was reprimanded and censured by the Judges' Tribunal for selecting special people to whom to give advance information regarding his capital reorganisation proposals. He admitted in his evidence that he conveyed to His Grace the Archbishop of Dublin, information on a certain date previous to the publication of the reorganisation proposals, and that he made arrangements, which did not work out in accordance with his wishes, for the same information to be given about the same time to the Secretary of the Representative Church Body and to the Secretary of the Bank of Ireland.  Can the Minister tell us the percentage of ordinary, preference and guaranteed preference shares held by these three representatives?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>In so far as they are trustees, none.  As trustees I think, <Col N="1837" /> they can only invest in debenture stock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that a positive statement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The only stock they can invest in is debenture stock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Anybody in close touch with the working of the railway system knows that the power to appoint directors is held, in the main, by the banks, and particularly by the Bank of Ireland.  I would not mind gambling that the stockholders' directors are selected mainly by the banks, and particularly by the Bank of Ireland.  Surely if that is so, they must represent a big holding of ordinary and preference shares, and particularly ordinary shares, in this company. In the return on page 13 of this report, we have some very valuable information.  The figures there disclose that there was an increase of 34 per cent. in the amount of shares exchanged, or, if you like, sold and bought, for the ten weeks ending October 23rd as compared with the period from January 9th to August 14th, inclusive.  Can the Minister give the House any information as to what percentage of the shares sold during that period were sold by the banks as compared with those sold by individual stockholders?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no information on the subject except what is in the report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it not be very interesting for the Minister to inquire and satisfy himself on the point?  If he does so, he will find that it was the individual stockholders who were caught out and who lost in this gambling which went on.  The banks have their nominees on the Board of the Great Southern Railways and these nominees are neither deaf nor blind. They can hear and see, and their job in the ordinary course would be to advise those whom they represent, the banks, not to sell at a period when they knew they would be committing financial suicide.  If that is true, the majority of those who sold during that ten weeks' period were the individual <Col N="1838" /> stockholders who are certainly not people who would have any inside or reliable information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the very reverse was the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>These are the very people who could be fooled by the rather conflicting statements made by the chairman and the Minister in the early part of 1943.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy will be relieved to know that the reverse was the case, so far as the indications go.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister had no information half a minute ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Nor have I information as to what shares held by the banks were sold.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister now has any information, I think it should be put on record.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I am putting it on record.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister then put on record the percentage of the shares exchanged during the ten weeks' period I referred to which were sold by the banks as compared with those sold by individual stockholders?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not got that information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not be sorry for the banks if they lost during that period, but I have great sympathy with the individual stockholders, ordinary and preference, who had held these shares for a long period and who, for the past 12 years, got no dividends of any kind.  I have intimate family friends who, under the terms of wills, were handed over Great Southern Railway shares at as high a value as £100 and asked to distribute the assets to different members of the families on the basis of that value.  Some of these people got a rude shock when the value went down to £10.  That is fairly common with country traders <Col N="1839" /> and certain classes of farmers.  When the value of the shares went down, many of these people had to transfer the shares to the banks.  The banks hold the voting rights and are thereby able to put their nominees on the board of the company as against the collective influence of the individual stockholders.</P>
      <P>I was appointed a member of a select committee set up a number of years ago under the chairmanship of the then Ceann Comhairle for the purpose of revising the old charter of the Bank of Ireland.  During my short period of membership, I asked for and got a good deal of information and a good deal of education regarding the inside control of the Bank of Ireland, the principal bank of this country.  The same applies to a lesser extent to the other banks.  When the Minister talks about shareholders' directors, I cannot help thinking that he is worrying about the interests of the banks who put these people on the board and who are the people who will eventually become the owners of the property of the two companies now being amalgamated.  I am anxious to get, and should be greatly obliged if the Minister would give, the information I am asking for. If the notice is too short, I hope the Minister will get the figures and put them on the records during the later discussion of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to try to get this matter down to a question of an objective type, on the basis of statements made without any imputation of motive whatever.  I protest against, and characterise as completely wrong and inaccurate, the Minister's reference to my latest speech in which he said that I described the chairman's speech as a speech deliberately designed to do certain things.  I do not think I used any such phrase.  I certainly never intended to use any such phrase.  I want to get clear away from the motives and background of anybody who spoke.  I want simply to give what was said and to base my own judgment on the natural reaction of that on the people who listened to and heard these various statements.  I am <Col N="1840" /> not saying one word about what were the motives, good, bad or indifferent, of the people who made them.</P>
      <P>I am inclined to query, and I think I am entitled to query, the basis of information on which these speeches were founded; to ask whether that information was in fact accurate or not and if it was then accurate but has since turned out to be inaccurate, what were the changes and at what stage could the changes have been observed. The Minister has said with regard to his statement made in answer to Deputy Cole about dealings in stocks and shares that it was based on wrong information, but again let it be remembered that the phrase put upon that outside was that it was illusory.</P>
      <P>I want to say one other thing in that connection.  The Minister not merely made a reference in which he said there were no abnormal buyings and gave figures on which he based that statement&mdash;figures which have now been described as completely illusory and, I think, accepted by the Minister as such&mdash;but he went on to say there was no evidence of leakage.  I think the <i>bona fides</i> required from a Minister answering a Parliamentary Question would have involved the revelation to this House that about a fortnight before he made that statement, he had asked for the resignation of a civil servant in this connection.  The House was not told that.  It is the duty of the person asking a Parliamentary Question to see that the Minister will not evade, but if there are things peculiarly within the knowledge of a Minister which seem to be called for by a question, it seems to me they should be given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The statement was quite accurate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, yes; it can be put quite accurately&mdash;there was no evidence of this, that or the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>That possibility was investigated at the time, and I satisfied myself with regard to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a fact which I think might have been brought to the notice of the House&mdash;that the Minister <Col N="1841" /> himself had caused the resignation of a civil servant to be put in because of his association with these matters. In any event, the House was not told that; we heard it later in the course of the evidence given before the tribunal. Just consider how the House was treated by the non-disclosure of that. The Minister may say he was not bound to disclose it; possibly he was not, but it emerged afterwards, and it does not do the Parliamentary system any good to find that a relevant fact like that was not disclosed and no hint of it was given.  It has been accepted that it was based on information &ldquo;which had no relation to the actualities of the situation&rdquo; and was of a &ldquo;completely illusory&rdquo; nature.  That can be said without imputing any motive to the Minister.  I never said he wanted to mislead the House.  The point is that a question was put here and it was not answered in accordance with the &ldquo;actualities of the situation&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I want to get back to the chairman's statement and the Minister's references, and I want to get back to them in the atmosphere that the judges found there was no improper leakage.  That does not end this matter.  If there was an improper leakage you would have much more to do on the other side of this question with regard to those who were involved.  I am leaving those out of consideration now.  I am dealing with the people who were the proprietors and who would now be the proprietors if it were not for the bit of boom speculation that emerged.  I do not care how it occurred.  I am not concerned with the people anxious to buy, but I am concerned with the people who were induced to sell by the depressing statement that was made, and who possibly would not have sold if this depressing statement had not been made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think the dates are significant.  The months rolled on&mdash;March, May, June, late October&mdash;and in those four months there were statements made which could only have a depressing effect on the stock market.  The Minister says it is wrong to say that there was no reference to the reorganisation.  I did not say that.  I say that whatever <Col N="1842" /> references there were, were couched in the terms that they were going to try to reorganise a completely derelict institution, and in the meantime they were going to bolster it up by charging increased rates and fares which, as they pointed out, they did not believe would pay their working expenses.  If the Minister held the view that the reorganisation proposals were going to bring about prosperity for the stockholders, I think some hint of that should have been given to them&mdash;not merely to say that there were reorganisation proposals, but to point out that &ldquo;despite what we have told you about the bad condition to which the railway has drifted, there is a good future ahead of you.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I want to find out a phrase which the Minister will point to in which the shareholders were advised to hold on to their stocks.  I suggest I have given many phrases which would induce the people who were shareholders to part with their shares.  The Minister said that a distorted version was given of two of his speeches.  Let me draw attention to the narrative way in which the tribunal expressed themselves in their opening remarks.  The chairman's speech was made in March, 1943, and, quoting from the report, this is what was said about it: &ldquo;This speech was generally regarded as gloomy and had a very depressing effect on the market.&rdquo;  That is the speech which may have made reference to the reorganisation, but it was &ldquo;generally regarded as gloomy and had a very depressing effect on the market.&rdquo;  The quotation goes on: &ldquo;Some stockholders proceeded to get rid of their stocks and there was a sharp fall in prices.&rdquo;  The tribunal is not imputing motive; they simply indicate what was said and set out the consequences.</P>
    <P>A question was asked in the House by Deputy Davin and, in regard to it, we have this observation: &ldquo;Following the Minister's reply, which was non-committal, prices again fell slightly.&rdquo; I read that as meaning that when Deputy Davin asked his question, and there was no hint of optimism in the Minister's reply, prices fell slightly. And remember, this was after they had fallen sharply and after it was <Col N="1843" /> stated that the market had been depressed. On the 28th May, the Minister spoke in relation to his Department. The portion of that speech on page 23 is not the whole speech and it does leave out the part I have already read here, and which is very significant. The report gives in full the statement with regard to the great reorganisation.  As the speech was given in the <i>Irish Times</i> on the 27th May, it read: &ldquo;The present financial position of the company is very serious. The anticipated revenue of the company in the present year would not meet its working expenses.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The tribunal quote other parts of the speech and pay full attention to the Minister's statement about re-organisation. They say about it: &ldquo;Following his speech, which was not regarded as encouraging, prices fell again.&rdquo;  The report indicates that the chairman's speech was regarded as gloomy and had the effect of depressing the market.  Some people got rid of their stocks and there was a sharp fall in prices.  The Minister was questioned and, being non-committal, prices again fell slightly.  There was then a speech on the Estimate for the Department and it was not regarded as encouraging and prices fell again.  The Minister did go further on the 17th June, when he said that earnings, even during the war, were insufficient to pay working expenses and even the increased rates would not meet the expenses in full. When the Minister was addressing the House in May we were informed that the company was approaching a situation when it could not meet the wages of employees, the cost of fuel and other expenses.  There was going to be a deficiency and even increased rates would not cover that in full.</P>
    <P>Again the Minister told us: &ldquo;We must take this organisation as a whole. It is not a railway business; it is a transport business, with rail and road services.&rdquo;  If all the road services are going to be such an immense benefit, was it not up to the chairman so to inform the shareholders, and was it not the duty of the Minister to say: &ldquo;I am talking only about the railway, but there are road services as <Col N="1844" /> well, and they are making good&rdquo;? I wish to put on record again what I interrupted the Minister to read.  The chairman's speech on the 3rd March&mdash; the speech regarded as gloomy, and which had a depressing effect on the market&mdash;had a certain importance. I produce it because the Minister tries to make the point that the gloomy statement referred only to the railway. There is a statistical reference with regard to the number of passengers carried by the road services.  The chairman talks about shortages of tyres and spare parts, and he also speaks on the fuel position.  He goes on to point out: &ldquo;As I have shown, the payment of debenture interest for the last half-year was only possible because of the good revenue derived from the road services.  We cannot depend this year from this source for anything like the same income as last year, and we are left with no option but to increase rail rates and charges.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Does the Minister seriously suggest that was a hint to the shareholders to put out of their heads all he had said about the bad state of the railways? Did he mean to convey that the road services would make good all the deficiency?  He goes on, in the next part of the same sentence, to say: &ldquo;Normally to-day this is a case which would have to be made to the Railway Tribunal, but in the present state of things we are seeking from the responsible Minister an Emergency Powers Order allowing us to increase railway rates and fares.&rdquo;  That is because the road traffic would not bring them in as much as before, and having said that they were going to get the railway rates and fares increased, he then says: &ldquo;Unless there is a decided improvement in the supplies position, it will do no more than enable us to make ends meet, the future payment of dividends depending entirely on the success of the proposed reorganisation.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The Minister, I know, referred to that speech, and referred to his own speech in the Dáil here in May, and referred to his own speech at Inchicore in June, but he never made one reference to the chairman's circular of 27th October, and I want to get back again to that. <Col N="1845" /> Without saying that the chairman was deliberately misleading or anything of that kind, I simply want an explanation. On 27th October, the chairman issues this circular about reorganisation. He made great play with the large amount of money that would be required for the permanent way, for the yards, for the stations, for equipment and so on.  I have given the phrase before; I am emphasising it now.  He said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;New buildings, plant and machinery will be needed.  The company's rolling stock is obsolete.  The reorganisation of the permanent way, stations and goods yards will call for the expenditure of large sums of money.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>He winds up by saying that the public will not subscribe the capital.</P>
    <P>The 27th October is an amazing date, because the year had at least three-quarters, call it ten-twelfths, run by that time, and when the revenue for the year was disclosed it was found possible to pay a dividend on every class of stock, and to set aside this amazing sum, over £600,000 in excess of the average for renewals and maintenance. Is it possible that on 26th October the chairman did not know of the good prospects before the railway company arising out of the revenue for that year?</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Where is that in the circular?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what I want to know.  Is there a hint of it in the circular?  Is there a hint that a good situation has developed?  I am asking the question, because if it is there I want to have it pointed out to me. If it is there, I am seriously in error.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I think from the point of view of the chairman it is lucky that there was no such reference, because it would only accentuate the suggestion that he was boosting the stock at the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Either there is or there is not some reference to the good position of the company.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1846" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Why should there be? The statement that the public would not subscribe capital was true, and it is still true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>There was no reference to the amazing revenue that was coming into the company at that time, unless of course we assume that all the earnings were made in the last couple of months.  That is a possibility, but I do not regard it as a likelihood.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The bulk of the earnings is made in the last half of the year, anyway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that an explanation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>No, but it is true, as the Deputy knows.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Was there observable an amazing tendency towards better conditions when that circular was sent out?  The whole insistence in that circular is on the deplorable state of the buildings, the plant, the machinery, the permanent way, the stations, the yards, the rolling stock. I do not know what more in the way of depreciation could have been said about the company than was hinted at in that circular.  Yet, as I say, within a few months it was found that the situation was so easy that all those moneys could be paid.  I have got no explanation of that circular.  While a big amount of those holders were jockeyed out of their shares&mdash;I use the phrase again: I use it as meaning that they were induced to sell; I am not talking about people wanting to induce them; they were in fact induced to sell, because of those depressing statements&mdash;as between August 21st and October 23rd, remember that a considerable further amount of the property changed hands in the period from October 30th to November 20th, which is the last date up to which this account is made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not think the Minister will disagree with me when I say that anybody selling or buying at that time, would have had regard to that circular of October.  I suggest that we have a duty to those people who were made to sell; that there was no <Col N="1847" /> explanation given of the pessimism which was displayed.  There was nothing in the way of optimism.  The people were simply told that there were reorganisation proposals on but there was no hint as to whether they might be successful or as to the revenue that would be derived if they were successful.</P>
    <P>The whole burden of complaint at the time was: we require new capital, and that new capital we cannot get. We require that new capital for the stations, the yards, the rolling stock, and all the rest of it.  No new capital was found, and yet we have had those results.  Up to date, no new capital has been subscribed.  For months after this Bill goes through, no new capital will be subscribed.  The whole demand there was for new capital, and the complaint was: the public will not give us the money; therefore, we must, so to speak, look to this shuffle and change-over, and then we will get a Government guarantee.  Meanwhile, without a penny having been advanced on foot of a Government guarantee, the situation apparently has changed. I think the public as a whole are entitled to some sort of clarification of that position.  Certainly, the unfortunate people who were in possession of those stocks and who sold them up to the 25th October are much more entitled to some explanation.</P>
    <P>Would the Minister just put himself in the position of the ordinary individual, subject to ordinary human emotions, who read those statements, and who held some of those shares.  He goes into conference perhaps with some other members of his family who hold shares, and they read the speech of the chairman in March.  Then they get one very much later in the year, one which could disclose some change in the company's position if a change had occurred, and they put both together. They look at where the chairman, in the earlier speech, said that no matter what they ask for the services rendered they cannot pay dividends on the capital.  Then they look through the October circular for some phrase to counter that, and I suggest that they find none.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1848" /> Looking at those statements from the man at the heart of affairs, who would not have sold under those circumstances? Certainly, who would not have sold when there is a brisk bit of buying going?  A whole lot of people were in the market to buy at the time. Would not the Minister confess that he would be subject to very definite feelings of rage, feelings that he had been tricked out of property, if within four or five months he found that every share held by anybody in the company was getting its due reward, and that what the chairman said could not be done&mdash;to make up out of future revenue the money to make good the failure to provide for renewals in the past&mdash;was to some extent being done? I think if the Minister were the owner of those stocks, and he were asked whether it was equitable to give him back the old holding or let his position be taken by somebody who would buy, I think his answer would be that he was not defending a case here in the House.  I am speaking from the angle of those people who regarded themselves as having certain rights.  What was the effect of those statements on any balanced mind?  It was such as would make them sell.  The Minister is the one person who says the chairman's speech of March could be regarded as highly satisfactory.  One man said he regarded it as a direct tip to buy and after he had left the witness box the other witnesses were questioned until the judges were tired as to whether each particular witness would agree with that interpretation; and nobody was found, as far as I can remember, to back that statement.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy McGilligan is representing the position of these shareholders as that of people continually watching the stock market prices of their shares.  He goes further: he endeavours to create in our minds a picture of shares that were of steady value and that suddenly began to fall in value and then appreciated again.  I think the fact which must be made clear is that nine out of ten of the shareholders of the Great Southern Railways, so far as statistics show, have no interest in stock market values at all.  They bought their shares <Col N="1849" /> for the interest and dividends they would get on them.  They hold those shares irrespective of fluctuations in market values, and no appreciation in values induces them to sell and no fall in values forces them in panic to get rid of their holdings.  That is what the statistics show.</P>
      <P>Even in the period of 1943 following the increased activity in the shares prior to the publication of the circular, and even subsequent to its publication when the full terms of the proposed reorganisation scheme were known to everybody, nine out of ten of the shareholders showed no interest.  Only 10 per cent. were concerned with stock market transactions.  It is also necessary to remember that the market values in Great Southern Railway shares have fluctuated considerably in the course of the past ten years.  In the case of one class of stock&mdash;the guaranteed preference&mdash;the highest point reached in 1944 was lower than the highest point reached for those shares in 1937, when there was no question of a Government reorganisation scheme.  It was merely a matter of the public's appreciation of the possibility of the company continuing to pay the guaranteed interest.  The ordinary shares which in 1937 were valued at £34 fell in something like four years to £8.  Again there was no question of legislation.  It is true that the company had paid no dividends; it is true that the directors were very perturbed at the possibility of their concern never paying any dividend and that the Government were making inquiries into the situation and contemplating legislation; but these fluctuations in value may have induced some shareholders to dispose of their shares and may have induced other people to buy shares.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not think there is any obligation on us to take cognisance of the fact that some sold and others bought. Each makes a different appreciation of what the future of the company may be.  We have Deputy McGilligan asking to-day that we write down the stock to suit one class of the people, those who considered it better business to sell the shares, and to penalise those who came to the conclusion <Col N="1850" /> that it was better business to buy shares.  On every occasion since 1937 that shares were sold, somebody bought them.  In 1937 somebody bought the shares of the Great Southern Railways at £34 per share. Three or four years later, they found that those shares for which they had paid £34, had a stock market value of £8.  Are we going to compensate those people for miscalculations as to the possibilities of the company?  In 1937 somebody sold shares at £34 and, four years later, when the market price was £8, they congratulated themselves on their astuteness and judgment in getting out of the stocks a few years previously.  Are we now going to make up to them the loss that they incurred by not holding on to those shares longer, by selling in 1937 instead of 1944?</P>
    <P>I think it is obvious that we cannot attempt to deal with matters of that kind.  People will use their judgment in the purchase of stocks and shares, just as they do in the purchase of cattle, clothes and other commodities. Some people buy cattle at the wrong time of the year, and others sell at the right time of the year.  While we sometimes have had, in the past, suggestions from members of the Dáil that individuals should be compensated for their lack of judgment or errors in calculation, we have never accepted that plea, and I do not think we should accept it in relation to shares of the Great Southern Railways.</P>
    <P>I want to disabuse the minds of Deputies completely as to the history of the finances of the Great Southern Railways in 1943&mdash;certainly to remove any impression that the statements made concerning the financial position of that company at any time in that year were in the least bit misleading. When the chairman spoke at the annual meeting in March, 1943, the company was in a very serious financial position.  Its revenue for the two and a half months of the year which had passed was below the revenue for the corresponding months of the previous year.  Its financial outlook was that it had paid debenture interest, not out of the earnings of the railway system but out of the profits of the <Col N="1851" /> road undertaking.  It seemed improbable that the road undertaking could be maintained on the same basis during that year.  In fact, if my recollection serves me aright, in April, 1943, all the long distance buses had to be withdrawn, and road goods services were seriously curtailed.  They were restored within a matter of three or four weeks, fortunately; but the fact was that the fears of the chairman in March, 1943, were fully realised in a matter of a few weeks.  In May, 1943, when the question of the increase in fares was under consideration, it was also true that the company, on the basis of its experience up to that date, did not appear likely to earn its working expenses during the course of the financial year.  Subsequently, however, the conditions improved.</P>
    <P>It is true, of course, in any year, that the bulk of the company's revenue comes in the second half.  Deputy McGilligan appears to query that, but everybody knows that the passenger traffic is at its peak during the holiday season&mdash;July, August and September&mdash;and the goods traffic is at its heaviest after the harvest, when the grain and beet&mdash;and the turf, under present conditions&mdash;have to be moved. In fact, it is at this time of the year that the priority regulations made by the Government in relation to goods traffic on the railways become operative, and that the company is unable to provide wagons and other equipment to carry all the traffic offered to it.</P>
    <P>Arising out of the increase in traffic in that year, arising out of the reorganisation which had been effected under the new management and which had become effective after that year, there was a very substantial increase in the company's revenue and a very substantial increase in the net revenue, which permitted of the allocation for depreciation to which Deputy McGilligan referred, and which permitted of dividends on the junior stocks.</P>
    <P>Deputy McGilligan appears to think that that matter should have been referred to in the circular regarding the reorganisation scheme.  I do not think <Col N="1852" /> it should.  Certainly, at that time in October, 1943, nobody could have forecast that a dividend on the ordinary shares would have been possible.  I do not know at what stage the board of the company came to the conclusion that a dividend should be paid.  On the date on which it did come to the opinion that a dividend was possible, it announced that fact, announced it in advance of the annual meeting.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>On the 25th October, nobody could have believed that it would be paid?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Although I presume a proportionate increase in the last three months of the year in comparison to the others is pretty well kept.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I would say so.  I am speaking from recollection.  It was after the general election of 1943, probably early in July, 1943, that the chairman, in the course of conversation with me in my office, informed me that the financial position was proving to be less serious than feared, that the revenue was increasing and that the gloomier picture which he had painted for me in May, when discussing the question of increased fares, was not likely to prove as bad as anticipated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>So that a statement could have been made in July to shareholders to hold their shares.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is now talking after the event.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am only asking if it could have been made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>At any time in the second half of that year, rail traffic might have ceased altogether, or road services might have ceased altogether. There was no certainty that we would be able to maintain a supply of coal for the railways or a supply of petrol for the buses.  Nobody could forecast that services would be maintained uninterruptedly to the end of that year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Any statement as to the probable results of the year's working at that time would be mere guess work, and I certainly say that the chairman would <Col N="1853" /> have been completely wrong to have attempted to forecast at that time what the result of the year's working was likely to be.  It is easy to be wise after the event.  The Deputy is criticising the chairman because he was not wise before the event.  He knows now that there was no interruption of service.  He knows now that the railways were able to take nearly all the traffic offered to them and carried it successfully, but he could not have known in advance.  In respect of the present year the situation is similar. He does not at the moment know what the result of the present year's working will be.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Put yourself in the position of the chairman who has committed himself to a statement in March that, no matter what you charge for the service, there is no reason to think the railway can pay dividends. In July that situation had changed completely.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  I say that by July the chairman told me the financial position of the company was not likely to be as bad as he had feared in the beginning of the year.  That is not &ldquo;changed completely&rdquo;.  That is an exaggeration of what I said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMcMenamin" hpid="Mr. McMenamin Mr. McMenamin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McMenamin</NameTxt>
      <P>He knew definitely on the 25th October that a dividend would be paid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>He did not know and could not know.  Nobody knew in October that dividends would be paid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMcMenamin" hpid="Mr. McMenamin Mr. McMenamin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McMenamin</NameTxt>
      <P>In the last week of October&mdash;the tenth month of trading?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Or in November, for that matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Even taking the line of other years, you could not announce it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Even taking the line of other years.  In so far as the circular is concerned, it is not correct to say that the circular merely declared that the public would not subscribe the capital. The circular said:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;The considered opinion of your <Col N="1854" /> directors is that the public would not subscribe the additional capital required at economic interest rates, even on a debenture secured by new assets, and if ranking <i>pari passu</i> with the existing debenture stock, the new stock would not be subscribed for unless it was also covered by independent guarantees&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is worse.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not worse but it is certainly different from the quotation given by the Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;Secured by new assets.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The point I want to bring out is that the circular did not say that the public would not subscribe the additional capital required but would not subscribe it at economic interest rates and I do not think that would be due entirely to the financial position of the company, but would be due to the financial history of the company.  Anybody going to the public for money for railway shares would certainly have the difficulty of the public remembrance of the fact that in 1933 we had cut the nominal value of Great Southern Railways stocks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly; and that a tribunal set up in 1939 also faced the fact that any new capital secured for the Great Southern Railways Company would have to have a Government guarantee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister know that one witness said that the phrase &ldquo;reorganisation&rdquo; used in connection with railway matters created shudders&mdash;I think it was?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It may.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It was a phrase of unhappy memory.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It may not be the next time.  The point I want to make is that I think it is entirely wrong to assume that there is any obligation upon the House, in framing legislation of this kind, to have regard to fluctuations <Col N="1855" /> in the market value of shares. There have been fluctuations in the market value of Great Southern Railways shares over periods equal to if not far more definite than those that occurred in the year 1943 and nobody is going to suggest that we should attempt either to compensate or penalise those who bought or sold shares in the previous years because their judgment proved either right or wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with the Minister's statement, adding this only &mdash;except where interpositions in this House or statements made by members of this House had brought about the fluctuations.  Then I think we have a duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>There was one substantial fluctuation in the shares of the Great Southern Railways following an announcement about the electrification of the main-line.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand&rdquo;&mdash;put and declared carried.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 20 and 21 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnONeill" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Eamonn O'Neill">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 22, 23 and 25 cover practically the same ground.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 22:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), lines 25 and 26, and 38 and 39, to delete the words &ldquo;the amount set out in column (4) of the said Part I at the said reference number&rdquo; and to substitute therefore the words &ldquo;such amount&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is an entirely different point from the last.  What I suggest by amendments Nos. 22, 23 and 25 is that, instead of giving the exchange of stock that is suggested in the Bill, we should have a proper value put upon the assets or upon the earning capacity or upon anything that can be regarded as giving a value to the shares of this company.  I suggest, in amendment No. 26, that various matters should be taken into consideration by a judicial tribunal with assessors which determines <Col N="1856" /> this matter.  In putting down that amendment and in asking that the value should be determined by the High Court, I was moved, to some extent, by a circular which was sent out by the Stockholders' Protection Association in which they ask distinctly that a proper value should be put upon the whole property of the railways.  They ask that the value of the property of the Great Southern Railways Company should be ascertained, not by arbitration, but by an independent expert judicial tribunal. In a second memorandum they suggest that the tribunal should be presided over either by the Chief Justice or the President of the High Court, assisted by a railway engineer and rail constructor who could be recommended by the chairman of any of the railway companies nearest to us&mdash;the English railway companies. Seeing the High Court was mentioned in this, and the possibility of assessors being brought into High Court adjudication for certain purposes, I took this opportunity of asking that the High Court should be asked to put some value on these shares.  I ask in amendment No. 26 that they should take into consideration a variety of things.  First of all, as to how value is to be ascertained. I think it is the practice in this country in any dealings with property to have the value ascertained. If the value to be set upon property cannot be arrived at by agreement between the parties, that is, the party acquiring the property and the party from whom the property is taken, there is always provision for some independent arbitration or arbitration board to assess the value.  The courts are constantly engaged in assessing the value to be given to people for various losses or in substitution for various properties.  Under the Electricity Supply Act, where companies of particular types were acquired&mdash;ordinary private companies can only be acquired by agreement&mdash;there was provision in certain respects made that if there was dispute about certain things there was resort to arbitration.  There is legislation in this country which aimed at one time&mdash;although the aim has not been very well met&mdash;at wiping out a certain number of what were called redundant <Col N="1857" /> public houses.  The proposition was enveloped in a piece of legislation which provided that if there was to be any such redundancy declared and the licences confiscated, then there was to be a value assessed upon these by a particular type of method, which was a judicial method.  It is well known that when citizens' property in this country is destroyed in ways that bring it under the Acts of Criminal Damage or Malicious Damage, the value is assessed in the ordinary way through the courts, and in such remarkable instances as, say, when members of the police force in this country lose their lives in ways that bring them inside these Acts, the amount of compensation to be given to the dependents is assessed by the courts.</P>
    <P>In addition, the fact is that the ordinary negligence case in the country resolves itself, at least in some part in every case, and in the whole part in many cases, to a question of what is the value to be assessed on certain disabilities, pain, or suffering as a result of an accident.  The courts are very well practised in assessing compensation, and there is no question as to what they can do in such cases.  In this case, the people concerned have agreed beforehand, under peculiar circumstances, as to what they can get, and we are being asked now to back up these people in their claims. I could give a variety of phrases that were used in connection with this matter, but I shall confine myself to a few.  Last night, I quoted from statements made by Mr. Wylie and Mr. Tweedy on this question of the exchange of transport stock.  They indicated that the proposed figure was higher than any arbitrator would give. Mr. Wylie indicated that the proposal was to pay £14 10s. in stocks of the new company for every £10 stock of the Dublin United Transport Company, and he gave it as his opinion that if an arbitrator were brought in, the shareholders would not get par value or anything like it.  I am not sure of the exact phrase, but I think that Mr. Wylie said that no arbitrator would give these people what they wanted. Speaking from recollection, I think that one of the directors, Mr. <Col N="1858" /> MacMahon, said that when he saw the proposal, he embraced it with enthusiasm. There is the situation.  We are asked to build up this company in a particular way.  The building up of it entails a Government guarantee, which attaches to the Bill the repayment of the principal money as well as the interest, and whether the taxpayer has to meet the 3 per cent., as well as the payment of these debentures, is a matter that the future will have to disclose.  Either the Government or the taxpayer, or those who are the users of the railway, will have to pay it.  Everybody is entitled to fair play, and all I want to see is that everybody gets fair play.  We do not want to see people getting more than fair play.  We do not expect that anything lavish should be provided, but in the interests of transport as well as in the interests of the ordinary taxpayer, I think we should see that a deficit should not be allowed to occur just because there is a public purse in the background which can be drawn on in a certain, indifferent way.</P>
    <P>I am asked, in effect, not to bother my head about the physical assets of the company or about the revenue earned by it.  I am asked to focus my gaze only on the earnings of the company for the last year, or the last couple of years.  That is not a fair way to regard such matters.  Members of a Party may believe that the judgment of their leaders is wonderful, but I am sure that nobody in the country is going to believe that what happened in 1943 or 1944 represents the actualities of the situation.  There is a situation existing at the moment, the result of which is that people cannot travel except by whatever means the transport company provides, and therefore the public are at the mercy of those who adjudicate on what the charges may be.</P>
    <P>In that connection, take, for instance, the meeting of the sugar beet company which was held on the 28th July of this year, where the chairman adverted to the amazing position in regard to the fortunes of that company, arising out of transport charges. Dealing with the accounts of the company, he said that at the end of this <Col N="1859" /> year there was a trading loss amounting to £33,407, and he went on to say that by drawing on reserves, and as a result of a variety of things, they were able to extinguish the trading loss and to pay interest on the debenture stock. The chairman, Mr. Williams, further said:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;This year, it will, unfortunately, be impossible for the company to pay an ordinary dividend, which, in effect, means that the Minister for Finance will receive no return on his very considerable investment in the ordinary shares of the company.  The disability which he will suffer by losing the dividend on this shareholding is a direct loss to Exchequer funds and those of the taxpayer.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Accordingly, the taxpayer may get it doubly in the neck through these proposals because, if there are other things to be considered, and if, despite the amazingly high transport charges, the company is not able to pay the Minister for Finance, then the taxpayer suffers.  Later on, the chairman said:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;You will notice, from the profit and loss account, that the company has withdrawn from general reserve the sum of £65,000 to enable the trading loss of £33,407 to be extinguished, and to provide interest on the company's debenture stock and dividend on the 6 per cent. cumulative preference shares of the company for the half-year to 30th April, 1944.  When these items for interest and dividends have been provided, the carry-forward to the next accounts of the company will amount to the small sum of £2,212.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That is a very small carry-over.  Incidentally, he remarks that the net total tonnage of sugar beet washed into the company's factories was 698,901 tons, for which the growers received £2,750,000.  He then goes on to speak of freights and the freight subsidy.  He says:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Each year, the sum which has to be found by the company to meet the subsidy on freight shows a definite increase, and during the financial year under review a subsidy of over <Col N="1860" /> £70,000 was paid by the company in case of freight charges on farmers. The directors of the company take the view that the charge for hauling sugar beet to the factories should be brought into a more strict relation with the real value to the producer of the commodity hauled, and that there are features in connection with this traffic which call for the strictest application of a policy of reasonable freight rates.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Now, £70,000 is the rate of subsidy paid to the company, and if they had not been paid that, they would not have been able to meet the Minister for Finance's little bit.  The Minister for Finance was also represented at that meeting, and the Secretary of the Department of Finance spoke&mdash;he was one of the few who spoke at this meeting&mdash;and this is his comment, which is rather good:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Another feature that one finds rather upsetting in the accounts is the heavy increase in freight charges on beet.  This increase, especially in the case of a comparatively low-grade article like sugar beet, is certainly very distressing to notice and, as the chairman says, it may strike a blow at the heart of the industry unless some method is found to reduce the freight costs which, on the figures given in the statement, amount to nearly £650,000 in the year to which the accounts relate.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>A calculation was made by one of the newspapers the next day, from which it would appear that that was equal, approximately, to 24 per cent. of the price to the producers, and that in the areas under beet it represented £8 an acre.  I give that as a sample of the amazing effects of overcharging and of those increased freights.  Of course, I understand that there are other increases pending in regard to other commodities.  Earlier in the year there was a meeting of Fuel Importers, Limited, and the Turf Development Board, where it was indicated that further changes were impending.</P>
    <P>There is a further statement, not from a judicial tribunal, but one made by counsel to the effect that the freight on turf had been increased <Col N="1861" /> from 13/5 to 15/9, and on firewood 17/3 to 19/8.  That is in connection with something which according to the <i>Statistical Abstract</i>, brings the farmer £2 per ton on the bog, which is sold here at something over 60/- per ton and which involves even then a subsidy of nearly 30/-.  Yet the freight is going to be raised on that commodity which cannot be sold or produced at anything near an economic rate.  I move to report progress.</P>
    <P>Progress reported, Committee to sit again.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Deputies' Business. - Local Government" RHead="Administration&mdash;Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>Private Deputies' Business. - Local Government Administration&mdash;Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel as a public representative, as chairman of an urban council, and as a member of other local bodies that I cannot let the present opportunity pass without giving expression to what I think, and what the majority of the people think, of the County Management Act. Strange to say, when the Fianna Fáil Party held a majority on the county councils there was no need for a County Management Act, but in the elections of 1942 prominent speakers of the Fianna Fáil Party said in my own town, when they knew that the ground was slipping from under them, that no matter who would be elected, the county manager would be the boss. We hear a lot of talk about corruption but, as far as I see, this County Management Act was introduced solely to give the supporters of Fianna Fáil big jobs at the expense of the ratepayers. There are some members who agree with the County Management Act, like Deputy Dr. O'Higgins, who is a medical officer of health, and who is under the whip of the county manager.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That does not arise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>Those people will agree with the Act.  The Fine Gael Party voted with the Government for the Act and, therefore, they cannot condemn it, but we who represent the <Col N="1862" /> working-class people know well enough that the people are handicapped and that public representatives are handicapped to a very large extent by the Act.  Take the case of the mental hospital committee in my own town.  What happens there?  The meeting is held on a fair day.  The farmer members on that day come into town, sell their cattle, go down to the mental hospital, have their tea and a smoke, go home and get their travelling allowances.  That is going on month after month.  If, on the other hand, you look for home assistance for people whom you know to be genuine cases, when you go to the home assistance officer he says: &ldquo;That must be submitted to the county manager.&rdquo; These poor people must go without assistance until the county manager thinks well to consider their cases a fortnight or a month afterwards.  That is what the people I represent are getting under the County Management Act.</P>
      <P>Again, the allocation of cottages in Wexford under the managerial system has been a scandal.  Cottages in rural areas that were built for agricultural labourers were given to people in an urban area who were not agricultural labourers at all, simply because they were supporters of the Fianna Fáil Party.  When I brought the matter up at the county council I was told that I had no voice in the matter, that it was an executive function.  If a councillor raises a question of the wages paid to quarry workers or road workers under the county council the county manager says: &ldquo;That is an executive function; you have no voice in it.&rdquo;  I suggest to the Minister that if the Act is not scrapped&mdash;and I would not be satisfied with any amendment of it; I think it should be completely scrapped&mdash;he should scrap all committees, county councils, urban councils, visiting committees to mental hospitals and all other such committees, so as to save the ratepayers the expense of paying travelling allowances of members who have nothing to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Parliamentary Secretary said last night that some local bodies were greatly in favour of the Act.  Who are they?  They are <Col N="1863" /> supporters of the Fianna Fáil Party.  Take County Wexford, for instance.  The county manager during the emergency, when many people were greatly in need of home assistance, came along with a scheme to sow apple trees along the public road and the Fianna Fáil members said it was a grand scheme.  Under that scheme it was proposed to spend £500 of the ratepayers' money for ten years to sow apple trees along the public road.  At the same time I was fighting the county manager to give back to people who had no other means, relief that was taken from them.  I say that that can be proved by the reports in the local papers of the debates at the Enniscorthy Urban Council and the county council.  I say if there was any corruption, the corruption was carried out when Fianna Fáil had a majority on the urban councils and the county councils, because no one got jobs except members of Fianna Fáil clubs. Nobody else need apply.</P>
    <P>I would ask the Minister when did the people give him a mandate to appoint county managers at big salaries? After the local elections of 1942 everyone in Wexford knew who the county manager was going to be, and in other counties as well.  The jobs were already made.  When the administration was carried on without any county manager everything was all right, but when the Fianna Fáil term of office had expired they said there was need for a manager.  Why?  Because they were a corrupt Party.  They gave members of their own Party all the jobs that were going.  If a member of the committee goes down to the mental hospital in Enniscorthy he cannot interview an attendant, man or woman, but he can talk as much as he likes to the patients.  You can talk to them about their complaints but dare you interview the attendants employed there. That is a question for the manager.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaSnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I happen to be a chairman of a mental hospital committee and we act as a visiting committee.  We can make any inquiry we like from any individual regarding the running of the institution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1864" />
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the Deputy's point of order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaSnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>My point is that I cannot sit here and listen to statements that are falsehoods.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is not obliged to stay and listen.  It is not a function of the Chair to judge the accuracy of every statement made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaSnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is making a silly statement.  He does not know what he is talking about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>I know well what I am talking about.  The Deputy is like every other member of his Party.  He can see only one side of the picture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaSnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>I see the whole picture. I know something about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>I am a member of a public body.  The chairman of the Wexford County Council is sitting near you, and he knows well that I am telling the truth.  He will not get up and second me and say that I am doing right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaSnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>That is because what you are saying is not right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>I am right.  At the local elections in Wexford we put up six men and got in five.  On the night before the election a Senator and Deputy Allen said no matter who got in the county manager would be the boss.  They knew who the county manager was going to be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That has no bearing on the motion before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>I know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>And the Deputy will act accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>I am telling them to their faces here in the House.  I do not go to Wexford and Enniscorthy to condemn the County Management Act. I want to condemn it here where the people sent me, and to tell the House that under the Act the people have no power.  My friend opposite talks about visiting committees.  I want to ask him what good are they doing.  A few farmers may visit the hospital farm and write a report, or they may <Col N="1865" /> go around with the doctor and be shown where some painting work has been done.  But under this Act the members of the committee cannot do anything on behalf of the people employed there.  Does the Deputy deny that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaSnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>I do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>You may be getting privileges from your county manager.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy should address the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1943" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Local Government and Public Health knows Enniscorthy as well as I do.  He spent some time there years ago.  We have a sanatorium there.  A doctor, rather than live near the institution, left the town to take, we were told, a bigger job in England.  I believe he left because we were compelling him, through the Minister, to live near the institution.  You have that kind of thing happening.  When I go to Wexford I report cottages that are in need of repairs.  We have a whole crowd of engineers there, and now we have got another one to mark out the additional half-acres for cottages.  Day after day and week after week the members of the county council are getting letters complaining of the state of the cottages and making other complaints as well.  Nothing is being done.  We were told that under the County Management Act there would be great savings.  I say there would have been great savings if the Act had never been put into force, because then the £20 or £25 that is going to the manager could have been given to the poor people who are being cut off home assistance.  One can go to the relieving officer, but if you are not a Fianna Fáil member you will get no &ldquo;say&rdquo;.  He will tell you &ldquo;Oh, I cannot do anything about that, I will have to report it to the manager and to the superintending home assistance officer.&rdquo;  The people who are giving out home assistance in the County Wexford can get sheep dipping jobs; they are warble fly inspectors and all the rest, even though they cannot wait on the poor people they are paid to look after.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1866" /> This Act should be scrapped.  If not, there will be no local elections next year.  Why spend money on local elections and bring people to the polling booths if, when they are elected and ask that something be done, they are told &ldquo;that is an executive function&rdquo;?  Every member of a local body present in the House knows that is true.  Members of local bodies have no power under the County Management Act.  Why did Fianna Fáil bring in this Act in 1942?  Why did they not bring it in when they had a majority on the county councils and the county boards of health?  For years they looked on and everything was all right.</P>
    <P>It was only in 1942 that the Minister appointed his county managers and put big expense on the ratepayers.  I say: &ldquo;If you want to do justice to the people that we represent, scrap us, save what goes in travelling expenses, and give it to the people who need it.&rdquo; I would prefer that any day to what we have at present.  I do not care who the county manager is, he cannot get to know the needs of the people as well as local representatives.  If you are not going to scrap this Act and give back to the people the power that they had, then there is no use in having local elections next year.  I ask that to be done in the interests of the plain people.  Why fool the people by asking them to vote for any Party at the local elections when the elected representatives can afterwards be told by the county manager that such and such a thing is an executive function? That happens.  Members of local bodies are told that they have no powers. When a member asks that something be done, and is told that, he is laughed at by some members of the council who agree with the County Management Act.  I do not care what the Parliamentary Secretary said last night, I cannot find anyone in touch with local affairs who is in favour of this Act. Why have all this unnecessary expense of county managers?  It was said here last night that they are great savers. They would want to save a lot to make their own salaries.  I refused to sign the rate books in Enniscorthy when the county manager did not appear. That is the one time when he should <Col N="1867" /> be there, and that is the only time&mdash; the striking of the rate&mdash;that we have any power.  After you strike the rate you have no more power.  The county managers can spend the money then any way they like.</P>
    <P>I am sure Deputies read the reports in the newspapers of what took place in the City Hail last week.  All Parties were represented there.  At that meeting there, Fianna Fáil members admitted that they would not have voted for this Act if they knew at the time that they could not do various things.  They found that out too late. The Fine Gael Party, of course, will back up this Act.  I do not mind Deputy O'Higgins or any other member of that Party backing it up, because they voted for it.  They want now to give it another trial.  Will the Minister put on the Table something to show what saving there has been since this Act was passed, or what improvement there has been in the conditions of the people?  In conclusion, I ask the Minister to scrap this Act, or if not, to scrap all the public bodies.  He has already dissolved some because, I suppose, they did not agree with this Act. I ask the Minister on behalf of the people that I represent&mdash;the working-class people and ratepayers in County Wexford&mdash;to save the rates and scrap all the public bodies in the County Wexford, because we are of no further use to the people that we represent.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. MacEntee) Seán MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>I had not intended to intervene at this stage of the debate because, after the excellent and thoughtful speech of the Parliamentary Secretary last night, it did not seem to me that it was necessary that I should say more than a very few words, but the Deputy who has just sat down has made one or two statements which, I think, I should deal with now when they are fresh in the minds of Deputies.  He has stated that there was no thought of introducing county management when Fianna Fáil had a majority on the county councils.  I suppose most of the members of the House were in public life in 1934.  I suppose Deputy O'Leary himself was in public life at that time. The Deputy will remember that, at the <Col N="1868" /> local elections on that occasion, the Fianna Fáil Party practically swept the boards.  The councils which were elected then remained in office until 1942.  There was a reason for that.  A general election took place in 1937 at which, amongst other issues, the Constitution under which we now live was put before the people.  It has been the custom&mdash;I think it is wise procedure&mdash; not to hold local government elections in a year in which a general election is plainly inevitable.  It happened that the statutory term of the councils elected in 1934 expired in 1937.  The elections should have been held that year but, apart from the consideration that a general election was to take place in that year, there was the fact that the Government was contemplating the application of the managerial principle to county administration. The elections were, accordingly, postponed. In 1938, the elections were again postponed and, on this occasion, the ground for the postponement definitely was that the Government had in contemplation the introduction of the managerial principle to county administration. It was considered undesirable that the elections should be held before the Dáil had an opportunity of considering the proposals of the Government in that regard.</P>
      <P>In due course, those proposals were submitted to the Dáil.  If my recollection does not mislead me, the Bill was introduced in the year 1939 and became law in 1940.  Every member of the county councils in 1940 knew that the management principle was to be applied to local authorities, generally, throughout the country.  It had already been applied to the county boroughs and, at least, to one borough. The members of the county councils were not ignorant that the county management principle was about to be introduced.  I am sure that members of local authorities who were also members of the Dáil took advantage of the discussion of the Bill in the House to elicit the views and opinions of their colleagues upon local bodies who were not members of the Dáil.  I have no doubt that they made proper representations here in respect of those views.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That was the position.  Yet, Deputy O'Leary, in the ill-considered speech <Col N="1869" /> to which we have just listened&mdash;I am sorry I have to describe the speech in those terms&mdash;said that there was no thought of introducing county management until the Government Party had lost its majority on the county councils. When he considers all the facts which I have put before him, I am sure the Deputy will admit that his speech was ill-founded and ill-considered.</P>
    <P>If what I have said does not carry conviction to Deputy O'Leary's mind, I remind him that one of the reasons why I held that it was desirable to hold the elections, even in the circumstances which prevailed, in 1942, was that I was anxious to give effect to the County Management Act, which had become law and the operation of which had been suspended while we were drafting the necessary regulations and making the necessary preparations. When the elections were announced, everybody knew that, simultaneously with the coming into office of the new bodies, the remaining provisions of the County Management Act, which had been held up pending those elections, would be put in force and that the whole corpus of the statute would be applied to the local authorities, generally.  Those are the facts.  Yet, with those facts in mind, Deputy O'Leary has made the type of speech to which we have just listened.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>He was told that four years ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The type of speech made by Deputy O'Leary is not going to help us.  Neither will it help us to suggest, as the Deputy has suggested, that, in some way or other, the present county manager in Wexford secured his appointment because he was supposed to be friendly to the Government. I do not know what the gentleman's politics are.  I know that he has been a good nationalist.  He was a colleague of mine in Richmond Prison in 1916.  Beyond that, I have no idea of what his political views are. I do know that the Dáil, because, amongst other things, of the difficulty of finding men capable of taking the posts and because county secretaries and other senior officials of the local authorities had claims in equity to <Col N="1870" /> prior consideration in the appointment of county managers, decided that existing county secretaries and secretaries of boards of health would secure the appointments if the Local Appointments Commission&mdash;not the Minister&mdash;considered them to be qualified and suitable.  It is because the Local Appointments Commission&mdash;a body independent of the Minister&mdash; decided that this gentleman in Wexford&mdash;who, I think everybody admits, is an excellent official&mdash;was qualified and suitable for the post that he was made county manager.  Those are two serious mis-statements for which Deputy O'Leary was responsible and, when he reads what I have said just now, I think that he will be sorry he made the type of speech he did make. It was not a helpful or useful contribution.</P>
      <P>In this matter of local administration we are faced with a very difficult problem and I endorse what the Parliamentary Secretary has said to the House regarding it.  We, in the Government&mdash;and I, particularly, as Minister for Local Government&mdash;are approaching this problem in an experimental frame of mind.  While we are prepared to say that we are not rigidly tied down to every detail of the County Management Act, as it stands at the moment, we have the firm conviction that it is not in the local interest nor in the national interest that we should revert to the position which obtained prior to the introduction of that Act&mdash; a position which was very well described in the debates here by an old and experienced ex-member of this House who had served here for ten or 12 years and who had served, I think, as chairman of a county council for some time.  I refer to Mr. Michael Brennan, who was formerly a member of the Opposition. Here is what he said in 1939 on the Second Stage of the County Management Act:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;What I have always felt about the position is that at the present time local authorities are hopelessly overloaded with work.  I do not think that the Bill that is before the House is going to be ideal.  I do not think that it is going to be perfect.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>None of us contends that it is either <Col N="1871" /> ideal or perfect but we say that it is an honest attempt to find a solution for a very difficult problem.  We think that it offers the fairest prospect for a solution, and that the solution, when it is found, will differ only in accidents, and not in essence, from the one we have embodied in the Act.  He continued:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I do not think that the Bill that is before the House is going to be ideal.  I do not think that it is going to be perfect, but I do think it is going to give us a better and more efficient machine for dealing with local government.  I do not at all agree that the Bill is taking away local government.  As far as I am concerned, I have not any desire to appoint officials.  I would be very glad to see somebody attending to the work, determining what shall be paid to the officials and where they shall be put in their particular offices.  I do not want to do it and I think I have as much and as close experience of local authority work as any member in this House.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Any person who has been in the unfortunate position of having had to decide which one of nine or ten individuals is to get a particular appointment will feel exactly the same as ex-Deputy Brennan felt in regard to this matter.  He proceeded:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;In regard to the board of health, I am a member of the board of health in Roscommon.  Deputy Murphy has mentioned certain matters that ought to be attended to by the Department of Local Government, such as more attention to the poor, the segregation of different parties and so on.  I entirely agree with Deputy Murphy in that. That ought to be done, and that is one of the reasons why I am backing the Bill.  We cannot do it.  Ten laymen, meeting once a fortnight to consider 40, 50 or 60 items in four or five hours on a Saturday afternoon, are not able to do that.  We try as best we can to do it.  In order to finish the work, when it comes to seven or eight o'clock in the evening, after sitting possibly for six or seven hours, I have often seen the work <Col N="1872" /> being parcelled out to members. That is not efficient administration. You cannot have efficiency in that way.  If Deputy Norton or the Labour Party believe that this Bill is taking away all the democratic principles we had in local authorities, they have not shown it.  Nobody has shown it.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>We approach this problem with the conviction that the position which ex-Deputy Brennan described, and which we all know to have existed in every local body, cannot be allowed to obtain again.  Local government has become so complex and so vast that we had to find some way of ensuring that local services, which are so costly, not only to local ratepayers but also to the State, would be administered expeditiously, effectively, and efficiently. We have tried to do that.  We have tried to secure efficient administration and, at the same time, to safeguard democratic principles.  We have done it by means that are very similar to those which have been evolved in the administration of national affairs.  We have taken pains in the County Management Act to ensure that the elected bodies will be the policy-making authorities in local affairs, within, of course, the limits that the general law of the land allows.  We have made certain that within the limits imposed by law upon the elected body, they will be the paramount financial authority. We have generally imposed on the elected body the duty of supervising the actions and the administration of county managers.  That is why we have embodied in the Act a provision so that the elected body can, by a majority, require a county manager to make a full report, and a full disclosure of all information and all facts in his possession relating to any transaction of a local authority by which he is engaged.</P>
    <P>Of course we have been very careful to ensure that the county manager's authority over the officers and employees of local authorities remains unchallenged. That is because we feel that unless a man is able to deal with his subordinates in a way which appears to be just and reasonable&mdash;there being also an appeal to the Minister&mdash;which <Col N="1873" /> will ensure that they will fulfil their duties and obligations, we could not hold him responsible for the general administration of local affairs.  Now I felt originally I had to intervene to-night because I listened with some astonishment to a statement made by Deputy O'Sullivan when moving this resolution.  He said that the system of local government is doing more harm than good, that the practice of making a report to the council had disappeared entirely; and that the whole system of local administration was an absolute failure.  The statement, particularly that about making a report to the council, was so striking that I had the matter investigated. I do not know whether Deputy O'Sullivan and I talk the same language, but I have here a very full report made to the Housing Committee of Dublin Corporation, which happens to be signed by Deputy James Larkin as chairman.  That report consists of 21 paragraphs, and contains information supplied by the city manager.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>Will a vote be taken before 7 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>At 7 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to be granted the indulgence of another couple of minutes to deal with this matter.  I have here another report addressed to the chairman and members of the general purposes committee.  This one is signed by the city manager, and in view of what has been said here as to the futility and powerlessness of members of elected bodies, I think it right to read one paragraph:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;I have to refer to the following motion passed by the city council on the 7th February, 1944, viz.:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That the city manager be requested to furnish to the council particulars of schemes that have been considered or decided upon as suitable for carrying out in the difficult post-war period, and how these are to be financed.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a resolution passed by the Corporation of Dublin, the elected body in this case, asking the city manager to report.  He gives a very full report, and much detailed information. No doubt the corporation could <Col N="1874" /> have had more information if they asked for it.  The council accepted the report, and made no further comment except to congratulate the city manager on it.</P>
    <P>Having received that report and having considered it, they could have expressed dissatisfaction if they felt it was necessary to do so.  They could have asked for further information, for further details about any one of these schemes, and if they had been dissatisfied with the conduct of the manager in relation to it, they could have passed a resolution and could have drawn the attention of the Minister to it.  If necessary, they could have gone further and, in the last resort, could have passed a resolution suspending the manager.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MartinOSullivan" hpid="Mr. M. O'Sullivan Mr. M. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I interrupt the Minister at this stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister gives way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinOSullivan" hpid="Mr. M. O'Sullivan Mr. M. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister can refer to my point in the Official Debates. I was referring to the ordinary city manager's monthly report which was a feature of the meetings of the Dublin Corporation since 1960.  It was initiated by the first city manager in a volume of six pages, giving details of all his transactions, major and minor, for the month preceeding the meeting and up to about 12 months ago that practice continued.  The report then dwindled in size to two or three pages and finally disappeared, and no longer appears on the monthly agenda of the Dublin Corporation.  I repeat that statement now as a statement of fact.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy O'Sullivan, as Lord Mayor, knows what his rights under the Act are.  If he required this report, would it not have been furnished?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinOSullivan" hpid="Mr. M. O'Sullivan Mr. M. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>It was asked for and we were presented, as we are presented elsewhere, with a volume of Orders on the Table.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like Deputy O'Sullivan to give me more precise particulars, because I cannot see&mdash;I may be very dense in this matter&mdash;how, if the corporation can require a report <Col N="1875" /> upon a comprehensive matter like this by simple resolution and if, that resolution having been passed, the manager is bound to submit that report, the corporation could not arrange, if they so desired, to have this monthly report to which Deputy O'Sullivan attaches so much importance.</P>
      <P>But perhaps there may be a reason why we do not get these reports now. I have before me some account of the matters considered at meetings of the various committees which the Dublin Corporation has set up to deal with its business.  There is a General Purposes Committee, a Housing Committee and a Finance Sub-Committee and I have seen some of the matters considered by the General Purposes Committee.  These matters are considered in detail by that committee and a report is furnished to the corporation which, in due course, considers it. Looking at some of the agenda of meetings of the Dublin Corporation, I find that they are very comprehensive. Not merely are there reports of the corporation committees there, but I find numerous resolutions and if these resolutions which are put down by members of the corporation and to which, presumably, those who put them down attach very great importance, are to be considered at all, I do not see how any very extensive report from the city manager could be considered on the same evening.  However, I have trespassed far enough on Deputy Corish's time.  I am grateful to him for the few extra minutes he has given me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>We have listened to a very interesting debate on the County Management Act, and I am rather glad that both the Minister and the Parliamentary Secretary took part in it. May I say without disrespect that I think the statements of both the Minister and the Parliamentary Secretary were rather of an academic nature. They made no effort to examine the position as it confronts the country to-day, and especially the members of local authorities.  The Minister, in answer to Deputy O'Leary, said that the County Management Act became <Col N="1876" /> law in 1940 and that all councillors knew that.  They certainly knew the Act had become law, but I venture to suggest that not one of those who offered themselves for election two years ago was aware of the drastic provisions of the Act.  I must confess that I sat in the House during the whole period when the Bill was going through and with my Party fought every line of it.  We moved a large number of amendments, but I myself was not aware that the provisions of the Act were so drastic until after the elections were held in 1942.  I have met men, members of this House, who voted for the Bill who have confessed to me that they were not aware of its drastic provisions when it was going through.</P>
      <P>The Minister has had an altercation with the mover of the resolution, Deputy O'Sullivan, in connection with the matter of reports submitted to the Dublin Corporation.  I should like to ask the Minister of what use are these reports?  The reports made to the various councils, when county managers do submit reports, are reports of matters which might be considered to be <i>faits accomplis.</i>  The action is already done and the council have no control, good, bad or indifferent, over the actions of the manager, with the result that, where reports are submitted, in a great many cases very little notice is taken of them, because the moment anybody questions them, as Deputy O'Leary says, the chairman tells him it is a function of the county manager and he has no right either to discuss or deal with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like to ask the Minister if it is right, from the point of view of absolute democracy, that one person should have the right of veto over the elected representatives of the people, because that is the position?  We are told that we have control over the finances of the council, and we are told that we have the right to strike the rate for the ensuing year.  We have, but I suggest that we have not got complete control so far as finance and the striking of the rate are concerned.  If the manager submits an estimate and the members of a council argue that, <Col N="1877" /> in their opinion, so much money should not be spent on such a thing, and if the county manager remains adamant, he appeals to the Minister, and in every case since the County Management Act came into operation the Minister has threatened <i>mandamus</i> proceedings against the council concerned, if it will not agree to strike the necessary rate.</P>
    <P>I have to refer only to the case of the Roscommon County Council.  I am not concerned at the moment with why they wanted to cut the amount down; I am speaking merely of the fact. During the debate on the Minister's Estimate, the Minister went so far as to say that in the future, if anything like that happened, he will not set up machinery for an inquiry, but, under the Emergency Powers Act, will immediately proceed to abolish the council.  There, to my mind, are the powers which county councils and urban councils have.</P>
    <P>I listened with very great interest and very carefully to the Parliamentary Secretary, and, again, without disrespect, I want to say it was quite obvious to everybody that he had no knowledge whatever of the work of public bodies, that he had not the slightest idea of what he was talking about so far as the activities of public bodies are concerned.  It was, to my mind, a speech similar to one which might have been made by a Conservative member of the British House of Commons when the Irish Parliamentary Party were looking for Home Rule.  He said he took exception to the phraseology of the motion moved by Deputy O'Sullivan.  He disagreed with the terms of the motion where it says: &ldquo;...reveal a distinct departure from democratic principles.&rdquo;  I want to emphasise that particular phrase in the motion that stands in the names of members of the Labour Party.</P>
    <P>He stated that it was only in the year 1897&mdash;I think it was 1898, as a matter of fact&mdash;that democracy, in so far as elections to county councils and other local authorities were concerned, came to this country; that it was only then county councils were elected on a purely democratic franchise. <Col N="1878" /> That may be so&mdash;it is so, as a matter of fact.  I think it is a rather unfortunate thing to find that that democracy, which was given to us by an alien government, with a king at its head, was taken from us by a Government which calls itself a Republican Government.  I want to be quite calm in this matter and I am not saying that in any disrespectful way or for a political purpose; but really is the situation not Gilbertian, to say the least of it, when we remember all the outbursts from the Fianna Fáil Party about democracy?  I remember well, when the Limerick City Management Bill was going through the House, some members now on the Government Front Bench getting into a white heat in condemnation of that Bill.  I remember well the strong words used by the present Minister for Finance against the anti-democratic policy of the Government of the time.  I venture to say that the present Minister for Finance knows more about local government than any other individual on the Government Front Bench, and I cannot understand what brought about the change.</P>
    <P>The Parliamentary Secretary mentioned that I was a member of the Greater Dublin Commission.  I was, and I signed a minority report.  I remember well during the sittings of that commission when the question of management was mentioned that what the members, so far as I can recollect, visualised was a manager elected by the council with the same relationship existing between them as between a board of directors and their managing director.  I certainly visualised a manager handling the day-to-day routine matters of the council and consulting the council regularly with regard to matters of policy and being guided and advised by the council.</P>
    <P>No matter what the Minister or the Parliamentary Secretary may say, there is very little in public life to-day to interest members, especially the younger members.  The time of county councils and corporations and urban councils at the moment is taken up by resolutions dealing with matters extraneous to the work of local authorities. Time and time again at county council and urban council meetings we <Col N="1879" /> have resolutions calling for an increase in old age pensions or reductions in the price of turf, and matters of that kind. These resolutions are introduced in order to create an interest at the meeting of a particular county council or corporation.</P>
    <P>The Parliamentary Secretary said yesterday that we had a right to deal with housing, the erection of bridges, and sanitation.  I do not think we have.  We may have the right to say to the county manager: &ldquo;We believe that you should proceed with the erection of so many houses in a certain place,&rdquo; but when we say that and ask the manager to initiate a scheme, there we stop.  We are not permitted to have anything further to do with the housing scheme.  We are not permitted to examine the tenders that come in; we are not permitted, when the houses are built, to fix the rent.  As the Minister knows, in the old days when houses were built and when it was found that the rent would be too high, councils were in favour of giving, and usually did give, a subsidy in order to reduce the rent to an economic level, but under the present conditions we are not permitted even to discuss that aspect.  We tell the manager to initiate a housing scheme, the manager proceeds to get plans and request tenders, the tenders are examined by him and he, in his wisdom or otherwise, accepts the lowest tender and we hear nothing more about that scheme.</P>
    <P>So far as sanitation is concerned, it was always very interesting at a public board to receive a sanitary officer's complaint about cases in particular areas.  Now a council does not know a blessed thing about what is going on so far as sanitation is concerned. Surely it is not too much to ask that matters of that kind ought to be the function of a local authority?  The position is that a person sends in a complaint to the council and it is sent to the county manager.  The ordinary member of the council does not know a blessed thing about it.  He may be met by an individual in the street and asked about the matter and he has to confess that he has not seen the letter and does not know anything about it, <Col N="1880" /> even though it is a major matter so far as a particular district is concerned. If a decision is arrived at by the county manager, a letter is sent out to the person or firm concerned, as the case may be, in these terms: &ldquo;I am directed by the corporation (or the county council, as the case may be) to refer to your letter ...&rdquo;  He is not directed by any corporation or county council, unless the county manager is to be called the county council or the corporation, for the purpose of the Act. These are the things we are up against.</P>
    <P>As regards home help, is it suggested that one person, and that person the relieving officer, even though there is a county manager there, is the person to determine whether an unfortunate individual has to get home help or not?  We all know the care taken by the county health boards to investigate cases that come before them.  I wonder would it be too much to ask the House to allow me another five minutes in which to conclude my speech?</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>No objection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy may continue until five minutes past seven o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>All those cases were examined very carefully by county health boards and care was taken to secure that the proper people were given home help.  Now it is left to one person to determine whether an applicant is or is not entitled to home help.  In a great many cases the applicant is not treated fairly.  I think anybody who is a member of a county council will have to agree with that. Deputy O'Leary knows that our county council has asked on three or four occasions since the County Management Act came into operation that the county manager should agree to set up a committee to deal with home help applicants, and up to the present we have not been successful.  If the manager is a sensible man he ought to agree to a proposal of that kind, even if the committee were only to act in an advisory capacity.  I am satisfied that no interest whatever will be taken in local authorities in the future <Col N="1881" /> unless the powers are given back to the county councils.</P>
      <P>Reference has been made to the letting of houses.  Again, I say that no one person, no matter what his capabilities are, is capable all the time of determining who is best entitled to a house.  In the old days, members of county councils and corporations got more annoyance from the letting of houses than from anything else. Nevertheless, they were prepared to put up with it.  They tried to do their best, and to give the houses to the most deserving people.  There is dissatisfaction at the present moment because of the method of letting houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Up to the time of the County Management Act, the borough surveyor was always present at meetings of the corporation to which I belong.  Since the passing of the Act, he has not been present at one meeting.  I suggest that that is a very serious matter, and that no work can be done properly unless the officials concerned attend the meetings of their various councils.  If a complaint is raised about something connected with the borough surveyor's work, the town clerk will take a note of it; he will submit it to the county manager; he in turn will have a &ldquo;confab&rdquo; with the borough surveyor, who will give him a kind of an answer, and the matter will come back again to the council.  Weeks and weeks are lost before anything is done, whereas, if the borough surveyor had attended the meeting, heard the views of the council and got the work done immediately, time and perhaps a <Col N="1882" /> good deal of money would be saved, because when necessary repairs are delayed deterioration is bound to result.</P>
    <P>I suggest to the Minister that the whole system of local government ought to be examined.  There is not a bit of use in talking about allowing a further period in which to see how the County Management Act works.  It is apparent to everybody now that it is not working properly; that it is not working in the interests of democracy; that it is not working in the interests of the people who elected the councils to do their work.  I am perfectly satisfied that nobody will offer themselves as candidates in the next election.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. MacEntee) Seán MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy offer himself?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>I will.  I definitely will.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, the Deputy is somebody.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, I will fight as long as I can.  Of course, there are people who say that the County Management Act is all right, but I think it will be found that they are people of this type: they are either people who tried to be councillors, time and time again, and who have been rejected by the public; or they are people who have been in county councils and corporations and got &ldquo;fired&rdquo;; or they are people who have certain axes to grind, and do not want to see the plain people govern in this country.</P>
      <P>Question put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Dáil divided:&mdash;Tá, 16; Níl, 70.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Blowick, Joseph.<br />Cafferky, Dominick.<br />Cogan, Patrick.<br />Corish, Richard.<br />Davin, William.<br />Donnellan, Michael.<br />Everett, James.<br />Flanagan, Oliver J.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Halliden, Patrick J.<br />Keyes, Michael.<br />Norton, William.<br />O'Donnell, William F.<br />O'Leary, John.<br />O'Sullivan, Martin.<br />Sheldon, William A.W.<br />Spring, Daniel.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Aiken, Frank.<br />Allen, Denis.<br />Bartley, Gerald.
<Col N="1883" />Boland, Patrick.<br />Brady, Brian.<br />Brady, Seán.<br />Breen, Daniel.<br />Brennan, Thomas.<br />Breslin, Cormac.<br />Briscoe, Robert.<br />Burke, Patrick (Co. Dublin).<br />Butler, Bernard.<br />Carter, Thomas.<br />Childers, Erskine H.<br />Colbert, Michael.<br />Colley, Harry.<br />Corry, Martin J.<br />Cosgrave, Liam.<br />Crowley, Fred H.<br />Daly, Francis J.<br />Derrig, Thomas.<br />de Valera, Eamon.<br />Flynn, Stephen.<br />Fogarty, Andrew.<br />Friel, John.<br />Furlong, Walter.<br />Giles, Patrick.<br />Gorry, Patrick J.<br />Hilliard, Michael.<br />Humphreys, Francis.<br />Keating, John.<br />Kennedy, Michael J.<br />Killilea, Mark.<br />Kilroy, James.<br />Kissane, Eamon.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Beegan, Patrick.<br />Blaney, Neal.<br />Boland, Gerald.
<Col N="1884" />Lemass, Seán F.<br />Little, Patrick J.<br />Loughman, Frank.<br />Lydon, Michael F.<br />Lynch, Finian.<br />Lynch, James B.<br />McCann, John.<br />McCarthy, Seán.<br />McEllistrim, Thomas.<br />MacEntee, Seán.<br />McGilligan, Patrick.<br />Moran, Michael.<br />Morrissey, Michael.<br />Mulcahy, Richard.<br />O Briain, Donnchadh.<br />O Ceallaigh, Seán T.<br />O'Connor, John S.<br />O'Grady, Seán.<br />O'Higgins, Thomas F.<br />O'Loghlen, Peter J.<br />O'Reilly, Matthew.<br />O'Rourke, Daniel.<br />Rice, Bridget M.<br />Ryan, James.<br />Ryan, Mary B.<br />Ryan, Robert.<br />Sheridan, Michael.<br />Skinner, Leo B.<br />Traynor, Oscar.<br />Walsh, Laurence.<br />Walsh, Richard.<br />Ward, Conn.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers:&mdash;Tá: Deputies Keyes and Corish; Níl: Deputies Kissane and Kennedy.</P>
    <P>Motion declared lost.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Deputies' Business. - Transport (No." RHead="2) Bill, 1944&mdash;Committee (Resumed)">
    <Title>Private Deputies' Business. - Transport (No. 2) Bill, 1944&mdash;Committee (Resumed).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>At the adjournment I was speaking on the group of amendments on the Order Paper in my name. I had indicated my view that it would be better to have some reasonable valuation set upon the holdings of the stockholders in these two companies before the House committed itself to giving the amounts that are set out in the Bill.  I had indicated that the courts are quite capable of discharging this function of assessing a value on this type of property.  They do it frequently and in all sorts of more extraordinary circumstances than they would be faced with in this case.  I had also indicated that, as far as one could see, the directors of the two boards not merely felt that the amount offered was much more than they had expected, but had also indicated their view, in precise terms so far as the Dublin United Transport Company is concerned, and in a rather vague phrase so far as the Great Southern Railways Company is concerned, that they were getting much more than any arbitrator could be expected to give them.  I had said that I thought we should act on the basis of being fair to these people, but should not, of course, levy on the public purse or on the industrial user or the ordinary passenger, afterwards, in order to make up for the extravagant suggestions that are made in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I indicated that, while an answer might be made to me that if you leave all the past years behind and simply contemplate the last years, you might say that the Great Southern Railways Company was in a much better position and that, consequently, the terms offered were not so very extravagant as might appear from an examination of the earlier years.  On that, I had discussed this matter of the charges in so far as they affected a couple of things in the country.  I took two in a selective way.  I do not think they are unfair commodities to take.  I said that the Chairman of the Irish Sugar Company <Col N="1885" /> had indicated at their meeting that they had made a trading loss, that the amount they had withdrawn from general reserve to cover that trading loss, which was £65,000, included a subsidy for freight of £70,000. In other words, if the particular subsidy had not been paid, they would have been able to pay interest on their debenture stock.  I had referred, further, to the amazing statement made by the representative of the Ministry of Finance at that meeting when he talked of the heavy increase in freight charges on beet.  He said: &ldquo;The increase, especially in the case of a comparatively low-grade article like sugar beet, is certainly very distressing to notice and, as the chairman says, it may strike a blow at the heart of the industry unless some method is found to reduce the freight costs which, on the figures given in the statement, amount to nearly £650,000 in the year to which the accounts relate.&rdquo; I quoted from an <i>Irish Independent</i> editorial of August 1st to give a better picture.  It showed that the charge for transport of sugar beet to the factories amounted to 24 per cent. of the price paid to the producers and that, taking it as a levy on the acreage under beet, the freight charges represented £8 per acre.</P>
    <P>The amazing thing in respect to that is that the Great Southern Railways Company issued a statement to the Press, the day after that editorial appeared, in which they said&mdash;why they confined themselves to road haulage I do not know-that road haulage of beet by the company involved a loss of over £6,000.  So that the Sugar Beet Company find this levy put upon them of 24 per cent. of what is paid to the grower, representing £8 an acre, so far as acreage is concerned; the freight subsidy of £70,000 involved the company in what was called a trading loss for the year under review and yet, on the whole, when the Great Southern Railways Company issued their statement counter to the <i>Irish Independent</i> editorial, the main thing was that they lost £6,000.</P>
    <P>The second thing I called attention to was the objection taken by Fuel <Col N="1886" /> Importers (Eire) Limited against increases in the charge for turf and timber by the Great Southern Railways Company.  That has reference to the present year.  The case was opened on the 13th April this year.  A short report of the statement of the case on behalf of Fuel Importers (Eire) Limited appeared the next day.  It was claimed that the effect of the new rates had been to increase the average freight for turf from 13/5 per ton to 15/9, and for firewood, from 17/3 to 19/8. Take turf alone.  The freight is going up by 2/4 on 13/5.  According to the agricultural returns, turf is counted as an agricultural output, and it is supposed to bring in a return to the producer of about £2 per ton.  In Dublin we know the price ruling for a long time was 63/-, and it was asserted that there had to be a Government subsidy of, I think, 25/-.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>28/10.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That makes the price 91/-.  Turf which is sold here at 63/- requires 28/- subsidy, although it is produced at the bogs at £2 a ton, and I understand from people who know more about this than I do that that £2 a ton is a fictitious figure, that the return is much less than that. Notwithstanding all that, the Great Southern Railways Company propose to increase the freight charges by 2/4 a ton, and we are supposed to regard that as something normal and on which to assess the basis of the return to these people for the last couple of years.</P>
      <P>In amendment No. 26, I have asked that, in considering the case, the High Court.</P>
      <P>&ldquo;shall pay attention to all the circumstances of the dissolved railway company,&rdquo;</P>
      <P>&mdash;that is a phrase taken from the 1924 Railway Act which, of course, dealt with a situation in which there were entirely different matters to be reviewed with regard to the companies that were to be absorbed or amalgamated. Still the phrase does quite well for this purpose&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1887" />&ldquo;the dissolved transport company and the Company and in particular the value on a net revenue earning basis on the 1st day of March, 1943, of the dissolved railway company and of the dissolved transport company and the estimated value on a net revenue earning basis of the Company under the provisions of this Act, the depreciation as on the 1st day of March, 1943, in the wasting assets of the dissolved railway company and of the dissolved transport company not provided for by reserves, the amount of capital required to make good such depreciation and the aggregate amount of such dividends if any, paid to stockholders of the dissolved railway company and of the dissolved transport company as were drawn from reserves, subventions, or other non-recurrent sources and were not paid out of what I may call ordinary trading revenue.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I put that in in order to cover the ground that the Minister had covered in his statement of May of this year.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;That statement of May this year was only in line with the statement made by the chairman of the Great Southern Railways Company previously and the statement made by the Minister on the two occasions I have referred to&mdash;the May and June statements of 1943.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>In that connection I want to call attention to the Royal Mail Steam Packet Company case.  In that case the allegation against the chairman of the board who issued a prospectus was that he misled the public, that he issued in the prospectus a statement which was false in some material particular and in that way got new money under what amounted to false pretences. What he did was, having certain subsidiary companies which were earning moneys, and seeing that these moneys were not going to be earned much longer, and where he got an adjustment in his tax charges and where he had certain other secret reserves, he drew on these and put <Col N="1888" /> them into a balance sheet, as it was alleged, to show a trading profit where in fact there was a trading loss.  The whole case was analysed from the point of view as to what should be shown in the accounts.  It was alleged that the accounts showed trading profits which were not earned, that there were certain things drawn from reserves and what were called adjusted profits.  A phrase used by one of the counsel in the case is, I think, particularly appropriate, with a little difference, to the situation of the Great Southern Railways Company.  One of the counsel said: &ldquo;The trouble in this case was that this old gentleman's business was not making money, that the old gentleman was living on the savings of his prudent middle age.&rdquo; That might have been said for the Royal Mail Steam Packet Company.</P>
    <P>It is not so for the Great Southern Railways Company, at least, if we consider that its middle age had been reached and passed by, say, the year 1924, because from the year 1924 on, if one looks at the tables given in the report of the tribunal of 1939&mdash;I think it is at page 139&mdash;one will see that this company was for years paying dividends when, for a number of years it was not making as much profit as it paid out in dividends and, from 1931 onwards was paying dividends when, instead of making profits it was making losses.  Of course, what it was digging into was (1) the money which was handed over by the British Government at the end of the last war for renewal of track, rolling stock, permanent-way and everything like that, and (2) the money they got, of a non-recurrent type, under the 1924 Act, the moneys that were in subvention to them in respect of the baronially guaranteed railways.  They had certain obligations to meet in connection with the same matter.  For the rest of the period, from 1931 onward, what they were doing, as was confessed afterwards, was letting that renewals item go.  The official who was present at the 1939 tribunal said that they were satisfied that not enough money was being put into renewals at all, and that they estimated that £600,000 on each of two sets of estimates was the <Col N="1889" /> amount required, and they estimated the amount set up by the two tribunals should be based on that.</P>
    <P>Accordingly, it would appear that up to 1931 the company, for a long time, was making some profit and paying, out of that profit, certain dividends, and that from 1932 to 1938 they were making, in the main, losses.  They made a small profit in one or two years, on an adjusted account, but in the main they were making losses, which amounted to well over £500,000.  From 1932 to 1938 they paid for renewals, having made a deficit of £639,000, and in those years they paid a dividend amounting to almost £1,500,000.  The situation in the previous years was not too good.  They had a net profit amounting to £815,000, and paid out dividends amounting to over £2,000,000. That, of course, was from reserves resulting from the terminating Railways Act of 1924, but taking the years from 1938 onwards, on the whole, they paid out in dividends far more than they had got in profits, and the way that that was done was by letting the wasting assets waste, with the result that they arrived at the stage that the Minister described, when introducing the original Transport Bill last May, when he said, as reported in column 1793 of the Official Report:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The provision of cheap and efficient transport facilities in our circumstances involves, so far as railway transport is concerned at any rate, over the greater part of the State, an almost complete scrapping of existing transport equipment.  The railway equipment which Córas lompair Eireann&mdash;the corporation which it is proposed to establish under this Bill&mdash;will acquire from the Great Southern Railways Company is very largely obsolete.  Not merely is it largely obsolete, but it is to an entirely uneconomic extent unstandardised. It will be necessary, at the earliest moment, for whatever organisation we set up, to take over the responsibility of transport operation, to replace the existing equipment with new equipment...&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There was the situation, and now <Col N="1890" /> we are asked to pay these people&mdash;to give them, in return for the stocks they hold in the two companies&mdash;I am dealing with the Great Southern Railways Company at the moment&mdash;the amount that they put in.  I want this thing to be dealt with from 1924, dividing it up in whatever way you like.  I say that something more than a bare calculation on that sum should be given to these people.  I say that for this reason: that, in my opinion, up to 1931 there was a net profit, although it was very small, but that from 1931 onwards there was nothing but losses, and it must be remembered that the losses were accrued to them, as the tribunal pointed out, mainly on account of the economic war.  That economic war was not their business, and I do not think it is right to saddle them with the unfortunate consequences of it.  I think that an examination of the accounts will show that an amazing amount was paid out when it was not earned.  It was not resulting from the savings of the old gentlemen or the middle-aged gentlemen. They had no savings, whether they were young, middle-aged or old.  Whatever came to them was as a result of subventions of various kinds, and the result was the shocking situation in which the company found itself.  When you add to the deplorable situation in which the company found themselves, the fact that Mr. MacMahon said that when he heard of the proposals he was delighted and received them with enthusiasm, and when you also take into account that Mr. Wylie and Mr. Tweedy said that for £14 10s., they were to get £10 I think there is a case to be made for an examination into the whole matter, and the Stockholders' Protection Association have asked for it.</P>
    <P>The last point that I wish to deal with is this.  I have dealt with stockholders all together, but there are different classes of stockholders in the companies, and the various proposals are known to the House.  There is a proposal that there shall be two classes of stock: one the redeemable stocks, and the other the ordinary stocks; but it seems to me that the day after this Bill is passed the Minister can pay off all these debentures in one &ldquo;go&rdquo;, and establish new conditions of repayment.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1891" /> However, I hope that at a later stage we shall get an explanation as to the actual proposal in this: whether it is to put a value upon the numerous classes in the two companies, to divide them and give certain equivalent holdings of other debenture stock or common stock in the two companies.  During the course of the tribunal hearings, some witnesses were asked whether they could put a value on the stocks of the railway company, as such.  As far as I remember, two of them said that the scrap value of the railway would not bring in, or might just bring in, the value of the debenture stock last year.  The sum of £4,000,000 was mentioned as being the then value of the debentures.  One witness said that he thought they might be more, and a gentleman engaged in the buying of scrap said that, as scrap, it might be worth slightly more than £4,000,000. At any rate, nobody put a higher valuation on it, and yet we have this position now.  I ask that it be determined what value is to be put, not merely on the present holdings of the stockholders but then to go on and equate that to what is the corresponding amount they should get in the new company, and I would give the new company power to determine whether they will give that debenture or common stock, mainly because, when this matter was under discussion in the courts nobody suggested that the Great Southern Railways' property, either rail or road, had any value to anybody other than the debenture stockholders, and that if these debentures were paid, nobody else would have any claim to anything.  The debentures must be first paid and, if they were paid, there would be nothing left for anybody else.  Under the old Acts, if they could not work except for the scrap value, then when people realised that the property was going to scrap, the value put upon it would be very much less than the value put upon it by the courts.</P>
    <P>The suggestion in the measure is that we should come to the assistance of the debenture holders and get rid of them after a period&mdash;get rid of them <Col N="1892" /> at least by 1960.  When that is finished, what are we going to do?  We are going to hand over this refurbished company to the common stockholders. They are people who, if maintenance and renewals had been properly attended to, would be far down the line for any dividend at all.  With the exception of the last few years, it is many years since they saw a dividend. If maintenance and renewals, according to the report of the Transport Tribunal, had been attended to, the interest on the debentures could not be paid up to 1938 and it is doubtful if it could be paid with ordinary charges since.  Yet it is proposed that we should clear out the debentures with the aid of the taxpayer's money or by piling on costs to the railway users. When it is all finished we are going to make these other people, who were never believed to have any real profit-earning assets, owners and proprietors of the new transport system.  There will be transferred to them at that time the assets of the old railway company and some good assets of the Dublin United Transport Company.  There are no transfers of shares from the Dublin United Transport Company to the common stock of the new company. They are going into the debentures.  I think that has been already stated.  I wonder if an option were given to some of these shareholders, particularly with the version of the new company as now paraded by the Minister, would they choose to become common stockholders or would they go into the debenture class subject to redemption? I think these are matters that should be left to a judicial determination, where everything can be examined, all sorts of witnesses called and calculations can be put before people well skilled in valuing these things.</P>
    <P>It may be said that to do that would hold up the Bill.  It would not; this measure and the reorganisation can go through.  We have been told in the circular of the 26th October that new capital was required but no new capital was got since up to this month. Yet we are told a remarkable transformation has taken place.  It is learned from the reading of the report <Col N="1893" /> that the old certificate of the engineer that the line was unsafe has been changed to a new certificate that the line has been made safe without any new capital.  This is certainly a miraculous transformation, the full implications of which are not yet clear to the people.  In any event that is the situation.  I do not know how long it will be until the new material required for the replacement of rolling-stock and for the carrying out of necessary repairs can be procured but it will obviously take some time.  The suggestion in the Bill is that by changing the name of the Great Southern Railways Company and the Dublin United Transport Company to Córas Iompair Eireann we are going to get immediately a magnificent development and that new capital will be provided by what is proposed in the section.  The new capital will be got later but I should imagine that it will be some time before that capital will be required, in the sense that it will be a long time before that capital can be expended.  The scheme of reorganisation can meanwhile go on but there should be a judicial determination on this matter which would leave people satisfied.  A lot of them are asking for it and as far as the rest are concerned they have indicated that they are doing very well at the public expense.  Eventually it is at the expense of the taxpaying public or the railway users&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Or the workers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The chairman indicated some time ago that a number of workers might have to walk the plank. That statement has since been modified to some extent.  That means that the sacrifices that are going to be imposed on the workers will be postponed and that discharges will be subject to the compensation clauses that will be embodied in the scheme as amended.  Unless we are going to contemplate the continuance of charges, which incidentally the chairman states he considers are too high, with such adverse results on the carriage of such things as beet and <Col N="1894" /> turf then the result will be that either the taxpayer or the travelling section of the community will have to pay.  I suggest that before we impose these burdens on them we ought to be satisfied and the public ought to know how the valuation is to be arrived at.  Let them know what is to be brought into consideration.  Let them be satisfied that what has been done is fair on the whole to the shareholders while being fair to the future transport users and passengers of the company.  There is nothing that can be objected to in that scheme.  There is no question of any imputation brought into this thing. This an attempt to get a determination, and the Minister has not given us the basis of his calculation.  He has told us certain things, but he does not indicate how it is possible to have this determination arrived at.  I look with suspicion on this determination, welcomed as it was by the representatives of the shareholders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The absorption and the amalgamation of companies are not unusual, but it is true to say that they far more frequently occur on the basis of agreed terms than on terms determined by arbitration.  In this case we are proposing to effect the amalgamation of two companies to constitute the new corporation.  The State comes in as the instrument by which amalgamation is effected.  We are proposing to proceed on the basis of an agreement with the two existing companies. Deputy McGilligan says that we should not proceed on the basis of an agreement but on the basis of arbitration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the case of the amalgamation of two private companies, joined together because the owners or directors of these companies consider that amalgamation is desirable in both their interests, even if they are unable to agree on terms and decide to resort to arbitration, they usually endeavour to get agreement on the terms of arbitration. Deputy McGilligan proposes that we should not proceed to get agreement on the terms of arbitration, but that we should endeavour to get the basis and the terms decided by the Dáil, the terms recommended by him and set out <Col N="1895" /> in his amendment.  These terms are obviously designed by him to secure that the shareholders of the Great Southern Railways Company will get the least possible compensation for their existing stocks.</P>
    <P>Let me say at this stage that Deputy McGilligan's remarks concerning the failure of the Great Southern Railways Company to provide adequately for maintenance and renewals appeared to me to be entirely beside the point. Whatever assets there are at the moment as security for the debentures held by the Great Southern Railways Company debenture holders will still be the assets of the new company on which the debentures of the new company will be secured.  They will have the additional security of a Government guarantee, in consideration of which the debenture holders have agreed to surrender 1 per cent. in interest. Whatever the earning power of the old company, in other words, whatever the value of the ordinary stock, will still be the earning power of the new company, subject to the extent to which, as a result of amalgamation and better management, the earning power may be increased.</P>
    <P>It seems to me, if it is true, that there has been default on the part of the company to the extent mentioned in maintaining its equipment and permanent way, and if that default has to be made good by new capital expenditure in the future, that is a factor which vitally affects the value of the shares which we are proposing to give to the shareholders of the existing company, because if there has to be new capital expenditure financed out of new borrowing it means more interest and, consequently, a diminution of the company's ability to pay a dividend on the ordinary stock.  The proposal, therefore, to give stock in the new company&mdash;£1 per £1&mdash;in return for stock in the old company is a fair one, and avoids the difficulty of determining whether the company has made adequate provision for maintenance and renewal, or the extent to which there has been default in such maintenance, as default there undoubtedly has been.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1896" /> Deputy McGilligan says that we will not seek agreement.  So far as the Government is concerned, we are determined to proceed on the basis of agreement.  The proposals, that are contained in the Bill were put before the shareholders of the Great Southern Railways Company and before the shareholders of the Dublin United Transport Company, and were accepted by a majority in each case, and the Government is bound to go through with the contract that is implied in that procedure.  But Deputy McGilligan says that we will not proceed on the basis of agreement at all, but on the basis of arbitration, on arbitration designed to secure that these shareholders will get the lowest possible amount that we can arrange.  In order to do that, he says, he proposes the arbitrator shall be instructed to value the undertaking, not upon its basis to-day, not upon its basis before the war but on the basis of the worst point in the company's history.  Why should we do that?  Why pick the 1st March, 1943, and determine the value of the undertaking on that date?  On that particular date the Company was in the worst period in its history.  The full effects of the war had not been felt on its revenues, the benefits resulting from better management had not yet begun to accrue.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Take 1939.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the case for 1939?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>What date did the Minister take?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I say that we did not take any date.  We proceeded on a different basis entirely.  If you try to determine the compensation by arbitration you will run into all these difficulties: of trying to lay down the terms of reference for the arbitrator.  Mind you, we could lay down terms of reference for an arbitrator which would enable us to say in advance what the compensation was going to be.  If an arbitrator were instructed to proceed on the basis of net revenue-earning <Col N="1897" /> capacity only and ten years' purchase, any mathematician could work out in half an hour what the compensation would be.  If you proceed on the basis of the fixed assets&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>What is their value?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Someone has said that the railways have a scrap value of £4,000,000.  I doubt that very much. What is the scrap value of the permanent-way from Dublin to Cork if it is not carrying railway tracks?  It has none.  It is an obstruction.  The building of that permanent-way cost a great deal of money, but unless it is carrying railway tracks it is worth nothing. Why, even to put it back into grazing land would involve capital expenditure far beyond what the land would be worth as grazing land.  But, as a permanent-way carrying a railway, it is worth something unless we can do without railways altogether.  If that permanent-way were not there we would have to built it.  If we had, how much would it cost?  Far more than it is valued at in the company's books. The same applies to stations, stores, and to great deal of the fixed equipment. When we talk about obsolete stock, we refer mainly to rolling stock. It is true that many of the stations are ill-designed for modern traffic and would have to be reconstructed.  A great many of the assets of the company were not earning revenue but are earning revenue now, so that if we were to proceed on the basis of their replacement value, we would find ourselves paying the shareholders of the company far more than we propose in the Bill.  If you were to proceed on the basis of arbitration you would run into all these difficulties.  Is it not much better, therefore, to proceed on the basis of agreement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If Deputies want to know what the case is for proceeding on the basis of agreement instead of arbitrarily determining ourselves the value that we put on the stock of the company, they should read the speeches delivered by the members of the Fine Gael Party on the 1933 Act.  On that occasion I <Col N="1898" /> did not proceed by way of agreement. I decided myself that it was obvious that a large part of the capital which had been invested in the railways of the country was lost and should be written-off in a completely arbitrary manner.  We determined the extent to which the nominal values of the different classes of stock should be written-down, and we legislated to write them down.  We did not consult the shareholders of the railway company, and certainly did not get their consent.  The members of the Fine Gael Party strongly objected to that procedure and urged that we should proceed by way of agreement.  I think experience has shown that agreement, if possible, is the preferable method.  I think that the difficulty which the Great Southern Railways Company had in raising new capital when it required it, and when there was no Government guarantee, was due to the impression created by the 1933 Act. But we had to proceed in 1933 as we did because neither the directors nor the shareholders of the Great Southern Railways Company had at that time awakened to a realisation of their position, and there was no hope of getting agreement on any reasonable basis of valuation of their capital.</P>
    <P>It is true that the directors of both companies recommended the terms of this Bill to their shareholders.  It may be that these directors were relieved to find that we were proposing to proceed by way of agreement on this occasion instead of following the method pursued in 1933.  It may be also that the terms were slightly more favourable than could possibly have been secured, and that the agreement of the shareholders was due to that fact.  I do not know.  In any event, the terms, on the face of them, are fair.  We are giving to the shareholders of the Great Southern Railways Company new stock of the same nominal value as they have at present.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Suppose the directors had rejected agreement the alternative was the threat of arbitration?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>In the case of the <Col N="1899" /> Dublin United Transport Company, yes.  I was very pleased that we got agreement, and I suggest that the Dáil should be pleased, too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister threatened them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I told the companies that the Government regarded the amalgamation of both companies as an essential part of its transport reorganisation plans, that we wanted to get that amalgamation by way of agreement, and offered them these terms which we were prepared to defend in the Dáil, and indicated that if they were not accepted we would have to get them by&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Arbitration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  I say that we are proceeding in a much better and fairer manner.  We do not have to wrangle about the basis of the value of the concern.  We do not have to decide whether its failure to earn sufficient revenue in the past was due to circumstances outside its control.  Deputy McGilligan has suggested that it cannot in the future hope to earn more substantial revenue than in the past. In any event we are giving to each shareholder the same nominal value in stock.  The debenture holders are going to get 1 per cent. less in interest, but in consideration of that we will give them the certainty, instead of the probability, of getting their interest. To the ordinary stockholders we guarantee no interest at all.  Their interest will depend entirely on the earning power of the company.  It is clear that the capacity to earn a profit sufficient to secure the payment of a dividend on the ordinary stock is improved by reason of the amalgamation and particularly by reason of the reduction in the interest payable on the debentures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the case of the Dublin United Transport Company, it was in a different position because, while, on <Col N="1900" /> the one hand, there was a general recognition that something had to be done, that a reorganisation of some kind had to be carried out, on the other hand you had a company which was not merely earning substantial revenues but that obviously was capable of earning substantial revenues in the future.  In their case, the offer took account of the revenue-earning capacity of the company, making due allowance for the fact that the interest on the new stock would be Government guaranteed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>You did not take the easy method of saying &ldquo;£ for £&rdquo; in that case?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>No, because, obviously, an offer of £ for £ would be unfair to the shareholders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>But it was fair to say &ldquo;£ for £&rdquo; to the Great Southern Railways shareholders?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It was the easier way, and that was the reason it was done?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>This was the fairest way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Why was it fair?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Because it left those shareholders with the same property as they had in the past&mdash;that was the case so far as the debenture holders were concerned at any rate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>What has the Minister said?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has been confusing this issue by his references to the past history of the Great Southern Railways Company.  Whatever the undertaking is worth, whether <Col N="1901" /> from the point of view of its fixed assets or its revenue-earning capacity, it is being transferred as a unit to the new organisation.  We are transferring with that unit the same capital liability as attaches to it at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you stopping there?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that all you are doing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that it is a fair arrangement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you not guaranteeing 3 per cent., no matter what they earn?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>We guarantee the debenture holders 3 per cent. on their investment.  In consideration of that guarantee, they are surrendering 1 per cent. interest.  We are giving that assistance to the company to enable it to effect a reduction in its interest charges and to facilitate the reorganisation and development which we believe to be possible.  This device of utilising State credit to get money more cheaply for the company than we think it could get it itself is justifiable in relation to such an important matter as transport, while it might not be justifiable in relation to other economic activities, even activities in which the Government would be interested. The Minister for Finance is, naturally, perturbed at the increase in the contingent liabilities of the State and various provisions were inserted in this Bill to ensure that the contingent liabilities undertaken by the State would be limited in time and extent. But we do come here to defend the proposal that State credit should be made available in order to reduce the interest which the company has to pay on its loan capital.  Is that clear to the Deputy?  The Deputy got himself involved in a discussion on existing freight charges.  Let me start off by saying that the present freight charges of the Great Southern Railways Company <Col N="1902" /> are in no case, so far as I know, above the standard charges fixed by the Railway Tribunal in 1929.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>And never operated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>In so far as the Railway Tribunal in 1929 determined reasonable charges for transport, those charges have not been exceeded, despite increased costs since the emergency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The new rates fixed after the cutting down of the stocks in 1933 have never been applied either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It is true that the company was not able to make those 1929 charges effective, by reason of the competition which developed on the roads, which competition forced the company to cut its charges in order to get business.  The matter to which the Deputy referred&mdash;the failure of the company to make profits in that period and its inability to make proper provision for maintenance and renewals&mdash; was due to the fact that, owing to the development of this competition, they were unable to make effective the standard charges of 1929.  Those standard charges are in force now.  It was contemplated by the 1924 Act that a transport service would be provided which would be capable of operating on a remunerative basis, but it was also contemplated that that transport organisation would have rates for traffic no lower than those now in operation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy McGilligan spoke at some length on the subject of the transport charges to the sugar company.  He misinterpreted the figure given by the chairman of the sugar company at the annual meeting but I may say this for him&mdash;he finds himself in what he may regard as good company.  The writer of the leading article in the <i>Irish Independent</i> and the Secretary of the Department of Finance also, obviously, misunderstood the figure given.  The £600,000, odd, which the sugar company paid for transport was not paid for the transport of beet only.  That <Col N="1903" /> figure represented all the transport charges incurred by the company in that year&mdash;the charges for the transport of beet, beet pulp, sugar, which is now sold carriage-paid in all parts of the country, coal, machinery, spare parts, limestone and all the other raw materials of the sugar industry.  Some part of the money was paid to the Great Northern Railway Company and a very large part of it was paid to private licensed hauliers.  Not much more than half of the sum was paid to the Great Southern Railways Company. Deputy McGilligan referred to the high proportion of the total cost of beet represented by freight charges. In fact, freight charges are a much smaller part of the price of beet now than they were before the war, due entirely to the increase in the price of beet, which has been far more substantial than the increase in the cost of transport.  In the 1943-44 campaign, the Great Southern Railways Company lost a sum of, approximately, £7,000 on the transportation of beet by road.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>They say £6,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy also misunderstands the significance of the freight subsidy.  The freight subsidy has nothing to do with the cost of freight.  It represents the decision by the sugar company to pay the entire cost of freight over 8/- per ton.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it included in the £600,000 figure?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Clearly, the amount of subsidy payable by the company under that arrangement depends on the number of growers of beet who are at a considerable distance from the factories. During the war, the company encouraged the production of beet in all areas of the country, whereas, in ordinary circumstances, they would have endeavoured to secure the full supply from the areas nearest to the factories.  The amount of that subsidy is no indication of whether freight charges are reasonable or unreasonable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1904" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am also in good company in that case&mdash;in the company of the chairman of the sugar company, who relates that to the charge for hauling beet to the factory.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The cost of hauling sugar beet to the factory depends far more on the cost of hired lorries from licensed hauliers than on the railway company's charges.  One of the considerations put up when the question of increase in the freight charges arose this year as between the railway company and the sugar company was that they could not guarantee to get transport to haul the beet unless they could offer increased rate charges to the licensed hauliers.</P>
      <P>In circumstances such as exist, when licensed hauliers can get far more business than they can undertake, it is difficult to ensure that their full services will be available for the transportation of beet when required, unless they get what they regard as reasonable remuneration. That factor more than anything else determines the cost of bringing freight to the factory.  The figure Deputy McGilligan quoted includes not merely the cost of bringing beet, but coal, limestone, spare parts as well as taking sugar manufactured in the factory and delivering it in all parts of the country.  The company has incurred increased cost in that regard, because, in order to make it possible to have a national fixed maximum price for sugar, the company was required by the Minister for Supplies to depart from the usual practice and to sell sugar on a carriage prepaid basis in Eire.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The same consideration arises in the case of turf.  It is not correct to refer to the turf rate as something that is normal which, I think, was the expression used by Deputy McGilligan. Clearly it is an entirely abnormal feature of the company's activities. Not merely is turf required to be carried to a far greater extent than ever before, not merely is suitable equipment difficult to get for that, but the company is required by Government Order to carry turf in priority to other <Col N="1905" /> traffic.  If the company could accept or reject traffic as it thought fit, or what was best suited to its commercial interests, it could obtain a great deal of traffic that would be far more remunerative than turf.  It is required by Government Order to carry turf in priority to other traffic which would be more remunerative to it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that the position at present?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the position. The company is operating under a Priority Order, and is required to give definite preference to turf over any other commodity.  If turf is offered the company must carry it, even though other traffic is available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is turf classified under &ldquo;minerals&rdquo; in railway charges?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Turf would be under &ldquo;other minerals&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I notice that the rate has gone up from 5/8 pre-war to 10/5.  That is nearly double.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The special rates which were in operation in 1943 have been increased.  They were not increased by a uniform amount.  There was an all over increase of 20 per cent.  In no case did that bring the amount over the standard rates fixed.  I should point out that the length of the haul has increased immensely, as well as the amount of other minerals dealt with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not a fact that hundreds of turf wagons have been withdrawn from the haulage of turf?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.  Not only turf but grain and beet had also to be dealt with.  We cannot continue the delivery of turf only.  I ask the Dáil to reject the amendment, not merely because of the date mentioned, but because I think it is unfair to the <Col N="1906" /> shareholders of the Great Southern Railways that we, at this stage, should say that we are going to take their property and give them new stock determined in accordance with the proposals in the amendment.  This amendment was designed to ensure that they would get the worst possible terms.  I think that would be unjustifiable.  I recommend the Dáil that, instead of determining by arbitration what the exchange of stock terms should be, the process adopted by the Government, that of proceeding by way of agreement, is one that should be upheld by the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot understand why the Minister is so opposed to arbitration in a matter of this kind, particularly when we have regard to his original scheme of securing some kind of agreement or scheme of valuation of the Dublin United Transport Company.  In that case the Minister offered the shareholders of the company approximately £145 for every £100 of stock in the tramways company. He said to the shareholders: &ldquo;If you do not like £145 for every £100 of stock, then we will go to arbitration.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I did not offer £145 of stock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not obvious that that is what was in the Minister's mind?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>In the long run that is what they are to get.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>They are to get stock in the new company to the nominal value of £145 bearing interest at 3 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>For £100 of stock in the old company they are to get £145 worth of 3 per cent. redeemable stock in the new company.  If the shareholders of the Dublin United Transport <Col N="1907" /> Company had taken the view that that was an unfair offer on the part of the Minister or that his proposals were not equitable, they could have said &ldquo;All right, we will not take your proposals; we do not think them fair,&rdquo; and in that case the Minister would have to go to arbitration to ascertain the value of the shares in the Dublin United Transport Company.  Apparently the Minister was not terribly upset at the prospect of going to arbitration, because that was the alternative to acceptance of his proposal by the shareholders.  If he had to go to arbitration it is obvious that terms of arbitration would have to be agreed upon.  If terms of arbitration could be devised to ascertain the value of stock in the transport company, is there any insuperable difficulty in devising terms of arbitration to ascertain the value of stock in the Great Southern Railways?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It was to avoid difficulty in having to devise terms of arbitration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Had the Minister no terms of reference when deciding?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>From what the Minister says and from the point of view of his sense of financial tidiness a catastrophe was avoided only because the directors recommended the shareholders to take his good offer.  If the directors had taken the other line and said to the shareholders: &ldquo;Look here, lads, hold out, and you will get more by arbitration,&rdquo; the Minister would be forced to adopt other methods if the shareholders were irascibly minded on the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Of course, the shareholders, knowing a good thing when they saw it, said it was &ldquo;O.K.&rdquo;  If there were no terms, the chairman could say to the shareholders: &ldquo;Look here, boys, there is as much jam on this bread as we are going to get.  This is the best thing that is going this year.  Take it while it is going.  We will never get a better offer as the Minister threatens arbitration if we do not take it.&rdquo;  Supposing the directors said: &ldquo;Hold out, as the Minister is committed to the <Col N="1908" /> principle of reorganisation, he may be willing to ladle out more jam.  If he is not, we will go to arbitration.&rdquo;  If the directors had done that, the Minister would have had to go to arbitration, and if so, he would have fixed terms of reference to ascertain the value of the shares.  What is the difficulty in doing the same thing in respect of the rather amazing financial vicissitudes that the Great Southern Railways have passed through in the last 15 years?</P>
    <P>I think Deputy McGilligan's amendment is a reasonable one, because it says in respect of certain stock that there is some doubt as to the value of the shares, and, having regard to all the circumstances, suggests that a body like the High Court should have jurisdiction to determine the amount of substituted stock to be allowed to each stockholder.  It also suggests that, when valuing the amount of stock to be allocated, the court should take into consideration all the circumstances of the dissolved railway company, and bear in mind the atmosphere in which it operated.  The amount might be increased, having regard to the difficulties under which the company operated in that period.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not what is there.  Let the Deputy read on.  It continues: &ldquo;and in particular...&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;In particular,&rdquo; yes; in other words, the value on a net revenue earning basis on that date. But surely it did not exclude taking into consideration all the circumstances of the dissolved railway company. Obviously, you must have some regard to what the value of the assets was, but you were not tied down to the value of the assets.  You had a right to take into consideration, too, all the circumstances of the dissolved railway company.  The amendment, therefore, does not tie the High Court down to valuing the shares on a purely accountancy basis, but enables the High Court to take into consideration certain other circumstances which might induce them to increase the normal value of the shares on the particular <Col N="1909" /> valuation date.  I cannot see why the Minister will not permit a body such as the High Court to express an opinion on the value of these shares, having regard to the rather chequered history of the finances of the Great Southern Railways.</P>
      <P>I do not know whether the Minister's endeavour to convince us that this whole scheme of substituted stock is so simple is not just a device on his part to cover up something which, in my opinion, is much more than simplicity. He says: &ldquo;In the case of the railway company, what we did was to take £ for £.  We gave the debenture holders in the Great Southern Railways £100 3 per cent. guaranteed redeemable stock in the new company for £100 stock in the other company. The only difference was that, in the new company, we reduced their prospect of a dividend from 4 per cent. to 3 per cent.&rdquo;  But when it came to the tramway company, it was not £100 for £100, but £145 for £100.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>£145 of 3 per cent. stock for £100 of 6 per cent. stock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>£145 of State guaranteed 3 per cent. redeemable stock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>For £100 of 6 per cent. stock which had never missed a dividend, in the case of the preference.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>And the chairman said the shareholders would not be paid at par or anything like it, if it went to arbitration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Nevertheless, the amount the shareholders will get in interest and dividend is reduced by £20,000 per year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it not be fair to give them a chance of showing that to a tribunal?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>On what basis of arbitration?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>We can easily argue the basis of arbitration.  The Minister must have had some basis in his mind when he gave these terms.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1910" />
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us hear Deputy Norton.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>My main complaint against this whole scheme of finance is that we are throwing the public credit in to buttress up a transport company on valuation terms which I think are extravagantly generous to certain shareholders.  The Minister, in justification for throwing in the State credit to this private monopoly, said he did so because of the fact that he is reducing the interest on the redeemable stock from 4 per cent. to 3 per cent.  That is his justification for throwing in the State credit.  Would the Minister consider leaving the redeemable stock at 4 per cent. and taking away the State credit, because from the point of view of the State and of the community, it will pay less if that credit is withdrawn than it will have to pay if the company have to go out and raise capital on the basis of 4 per cent. redeemable stock?</P>
      <P>My fear is that this transport company will not earn anything like a revenue capable of paying 3 per cent., and that, year after year, the transport company, through its debenture holders, will put its hand down into the public purse and the community will be taxed in order to pay the guaranteed 3 per cent. dividend to a private monopoly of this kind.  The Minister knows perfectly well that this company could not get capital on the open market to-morrow at 3 per cent. or 4 per cent.  The suggestion that the State credit is thrown in in justification for the reduction of the interest from 4 to 3 per cent. does not deceive me, or, I think, anybody else.  The Minister knows perfectly well that the State guarantee is thrown in for two reasons, (1) to get this private monopoly money which it could not get itself, and (2) to buttress up and asphalt the road for the amalgamation of the two companies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My complaint is that the public have to pay for this in the long run.  They may have to pay later in the form of higher transport charges.  Workers may have to pay in the form of lost employment or contenting themselves <Col N="1911" /> with rates of wages and conditions of employment which do not provide them with an adequate return for their services, and the travelling and trading public may be mulcted in order to maintain this private monopoly, overvalued as I believe it is to-day, and even when all these people have made sacrifices of a kind, the community in taxation through the Minister for Finance may have to dole out annually a sum of money in order to pay the debenture holders the guaranteed interest which is provided for in the Bill.</P>
    <P>I do not think the Minister has made any case why the High Court should not be permitted to adjudicate on the value of stock and the value of substituted stock as from the date suggested in the amendment.  The High Court is an eminently reasonable body.  It is capable of administering arbitration proceedings on as equitable a basis as the Minister could ever have contemplated when he had in mind the application of the principle of arbitration to the value of the shares of the Dublin United Transport Company, and even now the Minister ought to say to the public: &ldquo;If you are to foot the bill for this private monopoly by providing 3 per cent. interest for them, whether they make a profit or not, you are at least entitled to know what the High Court thinks of the value of the shares you are being asked to guarantee.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has rather emphasised the point that the amendment proposed in Deputy McGilligan's name would mean that the stockholders of the company would get the least possible value in substituted stock; in other words, that a definite injustice would be planned for them. That is the Minister's exaggerated way of putting it.  The suggestion in the amendment is that they would get reasonable justice, but there is another side of this justice aspect to be taken into consideration, that is, justice to the people of the country as a whole, the people who will have to depend upon proper transport services <Col N="1912" /> if they are to maintain their present economy, if they are to increase their production and if we are to deal with the cost of living, the maintenance of our people and the problem of competitive trading abroad.</P>
      <P>On page 50 of the report, information is given that one particular buyer of stock, realising, when the charges were increased in July, that he had to pay in respect of his company a sum of £4,500, together with an additional £700, making in all £5,200 a year, because of the withdrawal of certain privileged rates from his company, thought it worth while to invest in £30,000 worth of stock, nominal value, on the ground that the Great Southern Railways had been given power by the Minister to squeeze more money in transport costs out of the people, even to the extent, in the case of this particular company alone, of taking £5,200 annually from them.  The key to the whole change in the Minister's mind with regard to the financing of this company, and the main point to be borne in mind by the House in dealing not only with the stock proposals, but with the general proposals of the Bill, is that very much higher transport costs than should be taken from the people will be taken from them in the future.  As I emphasised before, that will operate at a time when, in the general interests of the economy of the country, we should be reducing our transport costs to a minimum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the question of compensation&mdash;I will call it compensation, or I will take any other word the Minister would prefer to use&mdash;of the stockholders, on the 6th February, 1943, the chairman of the Great Southern Railways Company thought it would be reasonable to form a statutory company with a capital of not more than £10,000,000, bearing a low rate of interest, with which to buy out the existing stockholders. That was the proposal of the chairman of the Great Southern Railways Company who had been in his dictatorship position in the company for 12 months.  According ing to him, a statutory company ought to be formed, with a capital of £10,000,000, that would buy out the existing stockholders.  As I indicated, if you pay off the holders at their full <Col N="1913" /> valuation, it would leave about £65 per £100 for the other stockholders.  That was the chairman's idea.</P>
    <P>On the 27th February the Minister followed up that with the formation of an idea of his own.  According to the Minister then, a statutory company with a capital of £10,000,000 should buy up not only the Great Southern Railways Company, but the Dublin Transport Company as well.  That was the second estimate that we find of what might be done.  Later on, on the 14th July, the Secretary of the Department of Industry and Commerce, according to a memorandum, or an addition to a memorandum, furnished by him at that time, having come to the conclusion that compulsory conversion was inevitable, pointed out the difficulty of deciding what would be fair and proper conversion terms and suggested that Mr. Reynolds should be asked to state his idea of a fair and proper basis for the scheme.  The secretary annexed a number of calculations of the cost of conversion, based on market quotations, designed to bring the required new capital under or within the range of the £10,000,000 mentioned in the Minister's minute. As late as 14th July, 1943, the Minister and the Department were still thinking in terms of £10,000,000 that would buy up the two companies.</P>
    <P>From 1st July the railway company had been given authority to increase the rates.  It was not until the increase in the rates had been able to operate for a while that the bigger and wider and more generous ideas began to show themselves.  On 2nd September we first come up against the idea that the chairman of the Great Southern Railways Company contemplated a fixed capital of £5,000,000 in common stock, with a Government guarantee of a dividend of not less than 2½ per cent. for seven years and his total capital would be brought up by redeemable bonds to £25,000,000. Finally, on the 7th October we get the present scheme; that is, we get the present scheme after three months had shown what could be squeezed out of the users of transport in the country.</P>
    <P>I ask Deputies to examine their own <Col N="1914" /> minds on this particular matter and I ask what can be the explanation of the change, except that they saw what they were able to squeeze out of the transport users and they saw there were people in the country who were able to swallow an additional £5,200 a year being put on their transport costs without making any grumble about it. Under the emergency conditions they bludgeoned people's minds with regard to costs and expenditure of all kinds and this has been done in such a way as to give the Minister some hope that he can still continue to do with transport charges in the country after the emergency what he is doing now.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>He would be a foolish man who would try to decide on the basis of war-time experiences what should be a permanent policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is basing the Bill on this idea, that he will find the people as unresponsive to oppression in peace-time as under the conditions brought about by the emergency here, and that is where the Minister is wrong.  That is where we see a danger in the future.  We see people now being given a definite Government guaranteed interest in a particular company.  The people will find themselves saddled by a Government guarantee and Government commitments at a time when they will be no longer able to bear them.</P>
      <P>There is evidence through this report, too, that the chairman of the Great Southern Railways Company hopes to be able, in respect of the amalgamated company, to do what he has done in the City of Dublin, and that is by the charges he is able to put upon the people to pay off any substantial lump sums of the temporary capital provided in such a large volume here.  The Minister is simply taking people, whose initiative and energy and vigour are impaired by emergency conditions, and he is prepared to squeeze £9,000,000 out of them, within the next few years, more than the transport system here should cost, and give all that in a newly built-up company to the people whom, in February, 1943, he was going to buy out for £10,000,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1915" /> The key to the whole business is the high rates.  Those who control the company have had a taste of the higher transport rates from July to September in 1943, and the change of mind that is indicated in this report and that is enshrined in this particular Bill is the result.  The proposal that is before the country is based on the experience of the increased charges the Minister allowed the railway company to impose under emergency conditions since last July.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to support the amendments on the broad principle that where the State sets out to acquire property or bring about a compulsory conversion of property, as in this case, it is the duty of the State to acquire that property at a fair valuation and compensate the owners fairly.  There are two fundamental ways in which the State may err in regard to compensation to owners of property.  First they may pay an excessive rate for the property&mdash;they may give excessive compensation&mdash;and in the second place they may provide inadequate compensation.  In order to avoid inflicting an injustice either upon the owners of property or upon the citizens of the State, the taxpayers and the travelling public, it is absolutely essential that there should be an impartial tribunal set up to decide what is adequate compensation.  That is simply what this amendment seeks to provide.  I confess that I did intend submitting an amendment somewhat on those lines, but I found it difficult to draft anything which would meet the situation fully.  The proposal in this amendment to submit the case to the High Court appears to be a most equitable method of overcoming the difficulty.  I feel that if the complicated issues raised in this transfer or compulsory conversion of stock are submitted to a judicial tribunal, the High Court in this case justice will be done first of all to the shareholders, large and small, and secondly to the general taxpayers in the country who have to foot the bill, and to the travelling public who must share in the cost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1916" /> No reasonable case has been put forward by the Minister in opposition to this amendment.  A sound principle, which should obtain in all cases where the property of individual citizens is being interfered with by the State, is that an impartial tribunal should be set up to decide the value of the property. When the tribunal gives its decision, that decision should be accepted.  To adopt any other line is to open the way to injustice; it is to open the way to pressure being brought to bear upon the Minister and his Department by the people who own property.  If, for example, the Minister were to consider acquiring possession of my farm, I would feel very happy if the decision were to acquire that farm by agreement.  In all probability, I would then be in a position to secure a price far in excess of its value. Having regard to the fact that in a matter of this kind the Minister is the custodian of the people's interests, the custodian of the people's money, I do not think the State has any right to approach the question in that way. The only fair and just method of settling the question is by submitting it to a tribunal which cannot be &ldquo;pulled&rdquo; or coerced in any way.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister said that it was wrong to bring in matters like the obsolete plant or equipment of the railway, or anything like that.  If that is wrong, why did he spend so much time on 2nd May telling us about the obsolete state of the railway?  Why was his talk about the railway and its parlous condition based on the almost complete scrapping of the equipment? Why did the chairman, in his speech of March, 1943, go to such pains to remind the people that the rolling stock was obsolete, and that that obsolescence as well as the inordinate number of workers employed had brought the railway to its present position?  Why did he say that the system of renewals which should have been adopted and was not adopted had brought the railways into the obsolescent state in which they find themselves to-day?  Eventually, in October, when addressing the shareholders by circular and telling them about the condition of the railway, <Col N="1917" /> why did he spend so much of his time dealing with the new buildings, plant and machinery that would be needed, in dealing with the fact that the rolling stock was obsolete, and with the fact that reorganisation of the permanent way, the stations and yards would call for the expenditure of large sums of money?  Why, having said that, did he add that the public would not subscribe a shilling to it?  Those things must be of some account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister says that he finds it difficult to draft terms of reference.  I can see points here and there in most terms of reference that are bad.  In quite a gay manner, the Minister said to this House that he really had very simple proposals for the Great Southern Railways&mdash;pound for pound. It was not so simple to say &ldquo;pound for pound&rdquo; in regard to the transport company; he had to go into some calculation. Some calculation had to be made to obviate the adoption of the easy method of pound for pound. &ldquo;Pound for pound&rdquo; is a simple thing to say.  Whether or not that is a fair basic calculation apparently does not enter into the Minister's mind.  It is pound for pound in one case and £145 for £100 in the other.  Why the distinction? There was some calculation made.  It was a distinction between the two companies on their past revenue earnings.  The position of the two companies is read from that angle.  The Minister decided pound for pound in the one case.  It was not as if he went into a room with some other person and said: &ldquo;You think of a number and I will agree with it.&rdquo; The Minister went in charged with figures and, I am sure, full of arguments about the company, arguments about the position of its rolling stock, the fact that there had not been dividends earned at the time they were paid, the fact that renewals had not been kept up, and that the result of paying out dividends which were not earned was that the position of the company was deplorable.  Now, the Minister wants to forget all this nonsense about calculations and evaluations and thinks that the simplest thing is to say &ldquo;pound for pound&rdquo;.  But it is not pound for pound; the £100 in <Col N="1918" /> any event used to bear 4 per cent. interest and it is being changed to 3 per cent.</P>
    <P>In addition, there is the fact to which Deputy Norton has referred, but which apparently the Minister does not consider important, that whether the company earns a shilling or not the 3 per cent. debentures will have 3 per cent. paid on them; in some way or another there is to be a debenture fund built up; whether it is built up or not, in some way or other, under the provisions of the Bill, the company has to redeem £16,000,000 debentures by 1960. Of course, there is one way in which it can be done, and that is by leaning very heavily upon the shoulders of the taxpayers, or else by dividing the weight between the transport users and the taxpayers.  We want to find out whether it is equitable to give them pound for pound, with the substitution of the 3 per cent. for 4 per cent., with the addition of the Government guarantee, and, in the case of the transport company, £145 for £100.</P>
    <P>Again I want to stress the reference in this memorandum by the Railway Shareholders' Protection Association. They refer to the fact that the Hon. James MacMahon said he &ldquo;embraced the proposal with enthusiasm&rdquo;, and add the comment: &ldquo;Love at first sight&rdquo;.  He took it at the first gulp.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>He was not consulted by the managing director.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>One would be suspicious of that type of offer which was accepted so readily.  Take the other rather deliberate phrases used by the other two gentlemen: &ldquo;Sure, shareholders would not be paid at par or anything like it,&rdquo; which was Mr. Wylie's observation, while Mr. Tweedy's is rather a little better&mdash;or a little worse&mdash;&ldquo;At an average, each of the £10 shares would have to be written down to considerably below £10, and we are asked to give £14 10s. for them.&rdquo;  They might easily have adopted the phrase of the other gentleman&mdash;that they &ldquo;embraced this proposal with enthusiasm.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1919" /> We ask, instead of that, that some consideration be shown for the future of the transport industry in this country.  This is going to saddle the taxpayers or the users of transport with a very heavy burden.  I do not know if the Minister has made a calculation as to what that burden will be.  I asked a question regarding that, on the basis of redemption by annual instalments, and on the basis of the redemption money having to be found out of the taxed profits&mdash;profits provided out of taxes in the ordinary way &mdash;as to what it would come to.  I got a figure which I could not understand, and I asked the Minister if it was without taking in taxation, and he said that it was not.  If I take the figure of £16,000,000 and divide it over the period, there is something in the neighbourhood of £500,000 to be found each year, on an equal instalment basis.  It is a rather rough calculation and I did not go into the smaller points.  At 7/6 in the £1 interest, some figure has to be found which will reduce it by three-eighths.  The 7/6 will show £500,000, so that figure is somewhere in the neighbourhood of £800,000.</P>
    <P>It would, therefore, appear that to repay the debenture&mdash;I am taking the first year&mdash;and to pay interest on the taxed profits out of which that money must be found, it would require £800,000.  The payment of the debentures themselves will take £250,000. That comes up to a total of £1,050,000. It may be that the value of some of the stock is wholy illusory, but if the company is going to earn all this and has to find the money for the debentures, they should be able to find the 6 per cent. for the stockholders.  That is another £200,000.  All told, it is somewhere in the region of £1,250,000. That has to be found, after providing for proper renewals.  The sum that was suggested before the tribunal previously was £1,200,000.  I take the amounts set out on page 139 of the Transport Tribunal Report.  It only gives statistics up to 1938, but if I add on figures that I have elsewhere for the years 1939 to 1942, I do not think the railway company, after meeting <Col N="1920" /> its working expenses, has shown a net income for, distribution of anything higher than £400,000, on the average.</P>
    <P>On the situation as I give it, therefore, they will have to make three times that.  How is that going to be done?  The easy way is to say: &ldquo;Well, we can easily call on the taxpayers for part of that&mdash;the redemption money&mdash; and that will be a decreasing sum, because a certain amount will be wiped off each year.&rdquo;  But take the year in which we have to start.  Even in the years talked about here, the highest figure they ever reached, before they made higher charges, was 1929, when they made £879,000.  That was the best year by far&mdash;the averages do not come at all to half that&mdash;and they made only £879,000.  Yet, on these proposals, they will have to make something like £1,000,000 or £1,250,000.  That figure was reached in 1942, on a scale of charges which the chairman said were too high.</P>
    <P>I have shown the repercussion of these charges on the sugar company. Some point can be made that that £650,000 is not Great Southern Railways charges.  The Great Southern Railways issued a statement the next day, after the <i>Irish Independent</i> editorial.  The Great Southern Railways statement did not say the same things as the Minister is saying now&mdash; but it did say:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Growers have the option of utilising the railway service of road haulage to railheads or using their own transport, or alternatively, utilising a direct road transport service&rdquo;</P>
    <P>and it adds:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;On the basis of last year's working, more than 70 per cent. of the growers will avail of the rail-road&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>That last word may mean the rail and its subsidiary road services, but certainly does not mean that they are going to avail of outside services. Take 70 per cent. of £650,000.  It is a very big sum.  The chairman of the company said it ought to be brought <Col N="1921" /> more in relation to the value of the crop to the producer.  The Minister for Finance said &ldquo;it was striking a blow at the heart of the industry&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>I do not know what excuse or justification can be made for the turf charges.  All I know is that an article is sold here at 64/- a ton, requiring a subsidy that brings, according to the statement given to us, the economic cost up to 80/-; and yet the railway company decided to increase the freight this year by 2/4, from 13/5 to 15/9.  I have compared the rates for this type of traffic in the years 1938 and 1939&mdash;the years in which it was only really proper to pay a dividend out of earnings, and I have taken the rates charged on certain goods, dividing the classes of goods carried as minerals into coal, coke, other minerals&mdash;and taking it that the &ldquo;other minerals&rdquo; includes turf.  Probably the greatest increase is in turf.  The amount rose from 300,000 tons to 1,000,000 tons.  The average rates of the railway company rose from 5/8 to 10/5, and it is proposed to increase that, on the basis of these charges.  People may say that it will probably be possible then to meet these debenture charges and interest charges, but that is not consistent with the promises the Minister gave here that we would have both efficient and cheap transport services.</P>
    <P>I do suggest that we ought to look with very definite suspicion on the readiness with which these shareholders came to the conclusion to accept those terms.  I personally had the feeling, when I saw the terms first, that the transport company people were not being treated properly; but when I saw the way it was recommended to them by these two gentlemen who spoke, I began to feel&mdash;they knew more about the inside workings than I did&mdash;that, if they were going to accept those terms, it was not for me to cavil about them.  At the same time, if any member of the shareholders feels he may have got a bad deal out of the £145 for every £100, he should be able to make a case before a judicial tribunal.  As far as the Great Southern Railways is concerned, I do <Col N="1922" /> not think anybody has any doubt that those in that company are being paid and overpaid, on the sheer merit of the proposal as a transport business. That is why I brought in this phrase about considering &ldquo;all the circumstances of the dissolved railway company&rdquo;, to suggest that something more than bare justice might be done them, because of the way in which their concern has been thrown about in past years.  They did not get exactly the best chance.  It can be said, of course, that the shareholders were responsible for what the board did.  But we know the way boards are run and the way in which proxies were used by the directors of the railway company to get a body of people put in power over many years.</P>
    <P>It is hard to blame the unfortunate shareholders because they did not take a livelier interest in these later years. The shareholders probably did not know the background that has now been revealed.  Otherwise, some of them might not have been content to receive a dividend, if they had information that that dividend was being paid out at the expense of the property of the company, which is what was happening.  They did not know anything, except that their dividends were coming along to them, and it would take someone who could read the accounts&mdash;someone instructed in accountancy or methods of finance&mdash; to explain what was happening in the company or to make them realise it. That is why I mention &ldquo;the circumstances of the case&rdquo; and suggest they get consideration.</P>
    <P>I think Deputy Norton was right in saying that the value of the revenue earning basis on 1st March, 1943, does not tie anybody to that date.  If anybody looks into this matter they may possibly point a finger and say it was normal up to that date and if it is realised, as the Minister says, that it was the worst date, I wonder if he would say what was the best date.  Would he say it was the end of the year 1943?  Would it be the best date so far?  I would be prepared &mdash;and will on a future occasion&mdash;put <Col N="1923" /> this amendment down again and change that date from the 1st March, 1943, to allow the Dáil to consider whether some judicial tribunal may back up the case on a one to ten year basis, and ask the Dáil to reject the <Col N="1924" /> section, or provide another amendment. I move to report progress.</P>
    <P>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</P>
    <P>The Dáil adjourned at 9 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Tuesday, the 26th September, 1944.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>