<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="3" Month="Feb" Year="1988" Vol="118" No="7" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 3 Feabhra 1988" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 3 February 1988" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="951">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="951" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Patrick Kennedy that, on the Motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The closure of Barrington's Hospital, Limerick.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator John Connor of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The possibility of siting the administrative headquarters of the proposed National Forestry Authority in Castlerea, County Roscommon, as part of the Government's decentralisation policy.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator David Norris of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The condition of the paintings in the possession of the National Gallery of Ireland.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Joe Doyle of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The urgent need for the Minister for Energy to implement in full the recommendations of the Cremer and Warner report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="952" /> I also received notice from Senator Paul Bradford of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The need for the Minister for Agriculture and Food to expedite the processing of applications by farmers throughout the north Cork region for inclusion in the Disadvantaged Areas Scheme.</P>
    <P>I also received notice from Senator Patrick McGowan of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The need to restructure Bord Fáilte on a regional basis in view of the upturn in the tourist industry.</P>
    <P>I regard the matters raised by Senators Kennedy, Connor, Norris, Doyle and Bradford as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected Senator Kennedy's motion and it will be taken at the conclusion of business.  Senators Connor, Norris, Doyle and Bradford may give notice for another day of the matters they wish to raise.</P>
    <P>I regret that the matter raised by Senator McGowan is too wide to be dealt with under the half-hour Adjournment procedure.  I regret I have to rule the matter raised is not suitable for discussion on the Adjournment of this House.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamRyan" hpid="Mr. W. Ryan Mr. W. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Items Nos. 1, 2 and 3.  We will take all stages of Item No. 1 and the Worker Participation (State Enterprises) Bill will follow.  If that Bill is concluded before 6.30 p.m. the House will break for tea. In any event we will take the Labour Party motion at 6.30 p.m.  I propose that, notwithstanding the Order of the House of 4 November 1987, the speech of the proposer of Item No. 3 shall not exceed 15 minutes and the speech of any other Senator shall not exceed ten minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Order of Business, I would like to refer the Deputy Leader of the House to Item No. 15 on the Order Paper, the amendment to the 1987 Extradition Act.  I would like to <Col N="953" /> propose that it should be taken today as the first Item of business and to remind him and the House that I got a clear undertaking from the Leader of the House, Senator Lanigan, last October that this matter would be addressed and would be taken on Second Stage at a later time.  First, we have seen enough over the last period of time to indicate the urgency of this matter and to indicate that, as a House of the Oireachtas with a clear commitment and responsibility and duty to our citizens, we have a clear duty to see to it that our citizens have a fair trial.  Secondly I ask for some amount of discretion on this matter.  It has been a major discussion point for the past month.  I ask my colleagues on the other side of the House to support this particular issue.  We have kept our heads in the sand on an issue which is of absolute relevance to the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You cannot make a speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>You will understand, I am sure as well as anybody else, how important it is that this issue should be addressed.  I ask the Deputy Leader of the House why this issue will not be discussed. It has been discussed in every house and in every place outside of here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You can hear the answer, but you cannot make a speech. We are all aware of what you are saying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I await the Deputy Leader's answer on the point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NualaFennell" hpid="Mrs. Fennell Mrs. Fennell">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Fennell</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to raise the matter of the Adoption (No. 2) Bill and to ask the Deputy Leader of the House to give us an indication of when we will have it for discussion again.  It will not change things radically.  It is quite a small Bill with minimal consequences, but I would like to see it coming back into the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Mr. Mullooly Mr. Mullooly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mullooly</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Order of Business, I would like to raise the very short <Col N="954" /> notice which Members on this side of the House were given of the Labour Party motion on the Order Paper today. Apparently, this motion was not handed in until Monday.  We have heard the points made from the other side of the House on many occasions.  It is helpful for Senators to have as much advance notice as possible of items which will be coming up.  If groups and Members wish to be helpful to Senators, when motions are submitted Senators should have advance notice of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>Through the Chair may I advise Senator Mullooly that the Whip of the Government party was notified at the end of last week that the education motion would be discussed.  It is our prerogative to have an allocation of time to decide on the actual wording of the relevant motion.  That was cleared and lodged at the appropriate time, in time in fact, for the Senator to have amended it, so I do not see anything wrong with the timing.  It was done in precise timing and in consultation with the Leader of the House.  Could I ask the Deputy Leader of the House, who has now signified a change in the agreed procedures for taking Private Members time, why we were not advised until now that our time was changed?  I accept that there is a reason for it, but I was not told.  We had agreed on a procedure to be followed, and just now I have been told there is a change.  If we were to make changes, I would like to have known last week because people have prepared speeches.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>I share Senator Fennell's concern about the Adoption (No. 2) Bill.  Certainly last week Senator Lanigan seemed to appreciate the concern of Senators.  He indicated that he would press the Government very strongly to have it brought before the Seanad speedily, so I hope the Deputy Leader of the House can give us some assurances on that point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When is it anticipated that we will take Item No. 24: That Seanad Éireann takes note of the Fourth Report of the Joint Committee on Women's Rights &mdash; Sexual <Col N="955" /> Violence.  I ask this in the knowledge that legislation, and the preparation of such legislation, is getting under way. The Law Reform Commission brought forth an important report dealing with this area.  There is a certain debate taking place in the wider public forum.  I feel it would be very useful if we in this House debated that report as a way of signalling some input into the preparation of the legislation.  It is a matter of concern because there is a rising incidence of this kind of crime, which is to be deplored.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to add my voice as strongly as possible to that of my colleague, Senator O'Toole, in seeking some real indication of when Item No. 15 will be taken.  The reason I do this is that this matter has been brought up repeatedly and we have been fobbed off with specific undertakings which were not lived up to.  As representatives we come continually under pressure from constituents who want to know why this matter is not being debated in this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You are supporting Senator O'Toole, but do not copy him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>He is inimitable.  May I raise one technical point?  It is a technical point about the Business of the House. I have noticed for some time that the monitor is quite indistinguishable.  We cannot read what is on it.  I wonder if this is the same kind of reception that is being received around the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a breakdown at the moment.  When everything that is relevant comes on, you will see the names.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Cathaoirleach is not suggesting that my voice is irrelevant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>May I add my voice to that of other Senators?  The Leader of the House was very angry last week, and quite rightly so, about what he felt was being fobbed off by Government Ministers and about delays in proceeding with <Col N="956" /> Government legislation.  Added to that list of items being fobbed off are the Companies (No. 2) Bill and the Video Recordings Bill.  I do not want to get up here every week and repeat what happened on the Committee Stage of the Video Recordings Bill, but we were forced by the Minister to rush that Bill through at the time which was inconvenient to some of us who had a lot of amendments down, because we were told that the matter was urgent, and we accepted that the matter was urgent.  I accepted without doubt the information supplied to me by the Government side. It is a fact that that Bill was rushed through because we were told, quite understandably, that it was urgent.  It is still urgent and nothing is being done about it.  I would like to know what is happening.  I will not ask you to protect me from Senator Cassidy&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Toole protected you&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it in order for Senator Cassidy to refer to my absence from the House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, when an inaccuracy is being stated I think it is only fitting that I should point out that it should be corrected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not a point of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am speaking on the Order of Business, and was speaking consistently on the Order of Business.  It was the interruptions which distracted me. On Item No. 15 &mdash; and I will be very brief &mdash; there is at this stage a very deep feeling in this country of concern about the nature of justice in the jurisdiction nearest to us which, as far as Irish people are concerned, can no longer be regarded as a parliamentary democracy in terms of the rights of the citizen.  It is extremely important, therefore, that Senator O'Toole's and Senator Norris' Bill should be discussed particularly in order to allow <Col N="957" /> the Members on the other side who have such deep views on this matter to express themselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, I would like to bring to your attention the fact that the clock has stopped.  On the Order of Business I would like to make it clear that, from my point of view, with regard to Item No. 15 I think the House, and some of the House certainly, would agree with me when I say that there are already quite adequate extradition arrangements provided for in law in this country.  Therefore, I want to state very clearly that I see no reason to regard Item No. 15 as a matter of urgency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnRobb" hpid="Mr. Robb Mr. Robb">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robb</NameTxt>
      <P>May I add a few words to what Senator Murphy said?  I think there is a slight danger at the moment that not only will Britain put the clock back but that Ireland might put the clock back too. I can see no reason at the present to debate Item No. 15.  There are many things that have to be clarified in the next few weeks without adding fuel to the fire.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Senators Senators">
      <NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator W. Ryan to reply and conclude on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamRyan" hpid="Mr. W. Ryan Mr. W. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the Labour Party motion the time was short. It has been the practice that we get motions on a Friday.  I pointed out to Senator Ferris last Friday that his motion had not been received.  He said it was probably the motion on education.  I understood it was the education motion that was on the Order Paper.  The motion we received is quite different and is much longer.  In fairness to Members of this House, motions should be in the hands of the Clerk by the previous Friday in order to give people an opportunity to prepare something on the item.  Senator Ferris also mentioned that he was not involved in regard to the change of time. I decided to do this because this motion lasts for one and a half hours only <Col N="958" /> whereas other motions last for three hours.  If Senator Ferris insists on getting 20 minutes, I am agreeable to that.  That is why I decided here today&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I only asked why it was changed.  You did not inform me that you had decided on anything.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamRyan" hpid="Mr. W. Ryan Mr. W. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I decided early today and I did not tell anyone.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>My number is 558.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamRyan" hpid="Mr. W. Ryan Mr. W. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not see what difference it would make.  That is what I have to say on this motion or any other motion in the future from any Party.  The motion should be received on the Friday before the date in question or, if at all possible, on the Thursday before that date.</P>
      <P>With regard to the Adoption (No. 2) Bill, I hope to have it for the House on this day fortnight.  I am insisting on that. I have asked the Minister to have the Committee Stage ready on that day.</P>
      <P>The Companies (No. 2) Bill was mentioned by Senator Ryan.  I expect to have that next week.</P>
      <P>With regard to Item No. 24 which Senator Bulbulia raised, it is our intention from now on if at all possible to have Government business only on Wednesdays and motions on Thursdays. When we have that sorted out in the course of a few weeks I expect we will then take Item No. 24 on today's Order Paper.</P>
      <P>In regard to Item No. 15 I am in complete agreement with what Senator Murphy and Senator Robb said about this Bill.  This week, of all weeks, is not the week to raise that matter in this House.  I am not sorry really, but we are not taking Item No. 15 today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to propose an amendment to the Order of Business. It is precisely this kind of panic politics of reacting to the times and saying when justice is&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Toole, <Col N="959" /> you have spoken.  Please move your amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I am proposing an amendment to the Order of Business and I am asking that the Senators on the Government side of the House be given a free vote on this issue.  I know that many of them feel&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Toole, we have to hear your amendment first.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I am proposing as an amendment to the Order of Business that Item No. 15 be taken first on the Order of Business today.  I am making the case that we have heard enough and know enough about&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Sit down, Senator O'Toole.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>If I sit down my motion <Col N="960" /> will be misunderstood.  I sit down reluctantly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it seconded?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That Item No. 15 be taken before Item No. 1.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Votáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is: &ldquo;That Item No. 15 be taken before Item No. 1.&rdquo;  On that question a division has been challenged.  Will those Senators calling for a division please rise in their places?</P>
      <P>
        <i>Senators Ferris, Harte, Norris, O'Shea, J. O'Toole and B. Ryan stood.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The division will now proceed.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 4; Níl, 40.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Eogan, George.<br />Norris, David.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">O'Toole, Joe.<br />Ryan, Brendan.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bohan, Edward Joseph.<br />Bradford, Paul.<br />Bulbulia, Katharine.<br />Byrne, Seán.<br />Cassidy, Donie.<br />Connor, John.<br />Cregan, Denis.<br />Cullimore, Seamus.<br />Daly, Jack.<br />Doherty, Michael.<br />Doyle, Joe.<br />Fallon, Seán.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Fennell, Nuala.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Hanafin, Des.<br />Haughey, Seán F.<br />Hillery, Brian.<br />Hogan, Philip.<br />Kelleher, Peter.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kennedy, Patrick.<br />Kiely, Rory.<br />Lydon, Donal.<br />McCormack, Padraic.<br />McEllistrim, Tom.<br />McGowan, Patrick.<br />McKenna, Tony.<br />McMahon, Larry.<br />Mooney, Paschal.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />Mulroy, Jimmy.<br />Murphy, John A.<br />O'Callaghan, Vivian.<br />O'Connell, John.<br />Nicolás Ó Conchubhair.<br />O'Toole, Martin J.<br />Reynolds, Gerry.<br />Robb, John D. A.<br />Ryan, William.<br />Wallace, Mary.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators J. O'Toole and Norris; Níl, Senators S. Haughey and Fallon.</P>
    <P>Question declared lost.</P>
    <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Housing Finance Agency (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1987: Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Housing Finance Agency (Amendment) Bill, 1987: Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="961" /> Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicMcCormack" hpid="Mr. McCormack Mr. McCormack">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCormack</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to speak briefly on the Housing Finance Agency (Amendment) Bill, 1987.  I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Connolly.  I wish to bring some points to the Minister's attention so that he may take heed of them and take action to rectify them in cases where it involves local authorities as we are representatives at that level also.  I would like to refer to the differential rents.  They have gone up by nearly 100 per cent in the local authority of which I am a member.  This is a very serious increase.  At this time it is hardly acceptable that an order could be made to change rents of lower income people because it is generally lower income groups who are living in local authority housing.  In some cases these rents have been increased by 100 per cent.  That is a very severe handicap on those people at this time.</P>
      <P>On the broader issue, I would like to ask the Minister what is the exact policy of the Government at this time towards the provision of local authority houses or towards the provision of finance for local authority houses.  In the Galway borough area for which I am a local representative no new houses were started in 1987.  Thatmeans that no new houses were started since this Government came into office. In the Galway County Council area only two new houses were completed in 1987. We consider it a very serious and backward step that finance is not being provided for the provision of necessary houses for the people who are waiting for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>To get that into perspective we would have to look back on the previous three or four years and see what exactly the situation is now in relation to what it was in the previous years.  For example, in 1983 in the Galway borough area £3,500,000 was provided for local authority houses.  In 1984, £4,220,000 was <Col N="962" /> provided for local authority houses; in 1985, £2,674,000 was provided, in 1986, £2,130,000 was provided and in 1987 only £210,000 was provided.  That was only provided to finish schemes already in progress, schemes that were started in 1986 and completed in 1987.  There is no indication so far of what the estimate for 1988 will be.  The same applies to County Galway.  The figures are quite similar for that so there is no use quoting them here.</P>
    <P>In the Galway borough area there are plans submitted for over a year now for a scheme for 20 town houses in a city centre development site which was acquired by the corporation and cleared in Whitehall.  It is in the centre of Galway, in the designated area in fact, and we have planned 16 one-bedroomed houses and 4 two-bedroomed houses for that site.  We are pressing for finance for those houses for the past six or eight months, because this is essential housing.  In fact, there is more demand for this type of house now than there is for the conventional type.  In most local authority schemes a number of houses of one bedroom and two bedroom dimensions were included for older people, but older people do not want to move out from the city centre to isolated areas &mdash; even though these are within the borough &mdash; two or three miles from the city centre, away from shops, Churches and services.</P>
    <P>Therefore, I ask the Minister to provide finance at least to let us go ahead with the scheme in Whitehall in Galway city where plans have been submitted for the erection of 20 houses.  This would cost about £500,000 or £600,000 and it is essential.  Land has been provided for housing in other parts of the city also.  A scheme was submitted to the Department for 70 houses in Ballybane about six or eight months ago and we have had nothing to indicate to us what we can do in that regard.  For the past eight to ten months the building of local authority houses had ceased entirely in the Galway borough area and this is having serious social and other repercussions on the people waiting for houses.  A backlog is building up of applicants waiting to be housed.  There are 150 qualified people <Col N="963" /> waiting for housing in the borough area and 60 of them are elderly, qualified people and there is no indication of what finance will be provided to allow us to start those houses.</P>
    <P>Also, since the abolition of all housing reconstruction grants by the present Government, extra strain and demand have been put on the local authority to provide houses because when a person urgently needs to repair a house and cannot get a grant to do it, the only alternative open to that person is to go on the local authority housing list, whether in a rural area or in an urban area.  This is also adding to the lists of people waiting for houses and is very false economy because eventually the local authority will have to provide such people with houses.</P>
    <P>Essential repair grants have been cut back drastically.  In the Galway County Council area £30,000 only has been allocated this year for essential repair grants. Thirty thousand pounds would not do essential repairs on two houses.  Again, that is false economy because the essential repairs grant was intended to cater mainly for old people who wished to prolong the life of a house for their life time so that they could continue to live there until they died.  That was the practice and the idea behind the essential repairs grant.  That is now cut back.  Because of this, houses have actually fallen down around these old people and I have first hand knowledge of this in Galway.  Then the local authority by de-mountable structure, by caravan or by emergency accommodation have to accommodate such persons.  I believe that, if we were allocated a reasonable amount of money, as in previous years, such as £200,000 for essential repairs grants, we could allow those people to do the necessary repairs themselves.  It is very false economy to allow the present position to continue.</P>
    <P>It is also false economy to allow the situation to develop to where we are running down our housing stock.  If we are not providing houses in either rural or urban areas, the housing waiting list will build up beyond all reasonable proportions <Col N="964" /> in the next three or four years. Then we will have an emergency such as happened in the seventies when we had to have an emergency housing programme. We solved that housing emergency by providing low cost housing and flats and we are paying for that ever since.  We provided the Rahoon flats in Galway which are a monument to that error. Also, under the Minister for Local Government at that time, low-cost housing schemes in different parts of the city were provided.  Houses were built in blocks with no chimneys, no fireplaces and it has cost the local authority, the Government and the State many thousands of pounds.  It was the worst disaster in catering for a particular housing problem at that time.  It cost more than the original cost of providing proper houses for those people would have been.</P>
    <P>Therefore, I would like to warn the Minister and the Department to end the present housing situation throughout Ireland.  I am dealing with my own local authorities, both urban and rural with which I am familiar.  Every other Senator could deal with his or her local authority and the same remarks, I am sure, would apply.  It is very false economy and very dangerous to allow a situation to develop where we are not building houses in Galway and allowing a waiting list to build up of people who are essentially in need of housing now having to wait to see if the position will change in two or three years time.  Because of the amounts of money allocated &mdash; about £14 million in four years &mdash; by the previous Government for the provision of local authority houses in the borough area alone naturally part of the housing problem was solved and it may not now be necessary to continue building 100 or 150 houses a year in my local authority.  It would be adequate to contain the situation by continuing to build 40 to 50 houses in the local authority.  That is my case.  It is false economy for the Department not to see that and not to provide the finances &mdash; to run down the housing stock altogether and, in so doing, allowing the housing waiting list to build up.  That raises all <Col N="965" /> sorts of problems.  Apart from the actual problem of housing those people and providing them with the houses necessary for them to live in, it leads to social, medical and other types of problems and it is entirely wrong that this should be allowed to happen.</P>
    <P>Finally, I would like to make a special case &mdash; and I am doing this on behalf of all of the Galway Borough Council &mdash; that the Minister should provide £500,000, or £600,000, or whatever is required, to allow us to continue with the scheme of 20 houses for old people in Whitehall, part of the scheme of housing Ballybane &mdash; not necessarily the 70 applied for, but at least 30 or 40 houses to cater for our need.  I make a special plea about Whitehall because Whitehall is an area in the heart of the city, in the centre of the area designated by the Government as an area for special concessions for redevelopment and expansion. Now the Department have a chance to play their part in that by providing the finances to allow us in Galway Borough Council to start the scheme of houses for old people in Whitehall.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Mr. Cregan Mr. Cregan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cregan</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I want to congratulate the Minister on allowing the increase from £500 million to £1,000 million. The Housing Finance Agency is an agency about which, when first established, there were questions regarding its working and the role it was trying to play. The general impression was that it was not catering for the people who were trying to use it and that people who could not finance themselves would not be able to use the system.  It worked out differently. I am glad it worked so well.  I will readily admit that there were areas where there was an impression that, among people we would like to see doing things for themselves, they were not quite happy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Government are now asking us to allow them to increase the agency's funding.  May I say in passing that by increasing funding to an agency like this, the impression might be given that the contributors are doing us a favour?  When you are 4 per cent over the odds and <Col N="966" /> when there is a recognition that £7 million was given last year to the society, £9 million this year and an anticipated £11 million in 1988 &mdash; somebody said that it would be decreasing in further years: I hope so and I think that would be right &mdash; the people who are giving in their money are getting a good deal, especially when there is the guarantee of the backing of the Government of the day.</P>
    <P>At the same time I do not deny that it is money that we were not getting before from corporations or insurance associations and I do not say we should not be using it.  I welcome that type of idea but, at the same time, we should make it clear also.  These associations now see that what is being pushed is the ideal thing, that there should be more encouragement. Certainly, they now see the inducement to provide money for areas like this.  I would not like to give the impression &mdash; and I am sorry to say that it is being given &mdash; that we are prepared to say: &ldquo;We will do less if you do more.&rdquo; We should not say to people who are in the less-well-off bracket that we will provide less for them or that it will cost more &mdash; like the increase in rents and in the rent review earlier this year.</P>
    <P>I would not like to give an impression to people who are in a stand-off situation &mdash; we are doing that &mdash; that by giving them more money we will be prepared to do less.  In other words, the Government are saying: &ldquo;We want the private sector to come up with more.&rdquo;  I am not saying that is wrong.  What I am saying is that it would be wrong if it is costing up to £9 million, £11 million and 4 per cent over the odds all the time.  We have to maintain a question mark over that.  It is only right to question it.</P>
    <P>The HFA have done a good job up to now.  Within the past 12 months or within the past two years people who took out a HFA loan were allowed over a period of time to transfer to the Small Dwelling Act loans, if they felt that would better their position.  I would appreciate it if the Minister would look at this.  Many people came off the housing list at the start of the HFA system and took out these loans <Col N="967" /> on the recommendation of local councillors and local officials.  They are not allowed to transfer to the SDA system. We should allow these people who have paid a certain amount to transfer.  I know people whose position, I am glad to say, has improved.  There are very few of whom we can say their conditions have improved over the past five or six years. I know one person on a HFA loan who is now paying back 18 per cent of his gross earnings, a lot of money, and such persons would like very much to transfer to the SDA system where they would have a fixed amount.  It would give them a fair break.  After all, they put a lot of money into it.  I wonder if the Minister would look at that.</P>
    <P>As regards the reconstruction area, if we are saying the agency is now allowed to give out money for reconstruction and if we are saying we are increasing their amount by 100 per cent, should not the agency be seen at local authority level because SDA loans and other loans are now transferred to the banks and building societies.  The Minister indicated that he was happy with the outcome and had the impression that it was working smoothly enough.</P>
    <P>The indications I have &mdash; and I know that the Minister listens at a local level &mdash; are that these arrangements are not working all that well.  I know many people who would be quite prepared to take the Small Dwellings Act loan or the HFA loan but, because of an indication from a local authority, they have to go to the bank or a building society and if they have not money on deposit they are not favoured very much.  If they have not got £3,000 or £4,000 in the local building society, or if they have it in the Trustee Bank rather than in one of the other banks, the banks are not prepared to consider them although they are quite comfortably circumstanced.</P>
    <P>The banks make a lot of money and they know when they are onto a thing and they are onto a good thing here. Generally, when people get a mortgage they are quite prepared to pay on it. Unhappily, I will readily admit that, <Col N="968" /> when they get a local authority dwelling, a higher percentage of people are inclined to think that because it is a local authority dwelling, they should not pay as much, or they should not be paying as happily. Generally, mortgage repayments here are quite good.  I do not agree generally with the idea of that the Government should not be getting involved more with banks or building societies.  If the money is there we should be using it and they should be getting a fair return for it.</P>
    <P>There are indications to me that the idea is not working so well and there is increased strain on the local authority lists.  Within the past few months &mdash; and I can say this for the Cork area &mdash; there has been an increase in the applicant list, whereas when we had the grants and when the authority were dealing with the matter themselves, we built up a relationship with people coming in and if they were comfortable at all we were prepared to sell them the HFA loan or the SDA loan, on better terms, I think than the banks or building societies.  We should not lose out now on that.  In the end &mdash; and this has been proved &mdash; the construction industry are not building as many houses.  Builders are saying that new houses are not going up as fast as they would like.  We know that, and the Minister knows that.  Naturally, every, incentive possible should be given to encourage a person to live in his own house if at all possible.  I am not happy with the new system that was implemented.  I hope I am wrong about it and that it can be changed.</P>
    <P>There was certainly an impression in our city that when you went to the local authority you got every assistance possible to enable us to sell the idea to you. We were getting our lists down.  Admittedly, the £5,000 grant scheme was an enormous success and I make no apologies for saying I was one of those who pushed very hard for it.  Even in Cork where there was a lot of accommodation &mdash; if not houses &mdash; available, within a very short period we will be back to square one.  Many people are saying: &ldquo;I cannot go to the banks because I do not have money there&rdquo; and &ldquo;I cannot go to <Col N="969" /> a building society because I do not have money there&rdquo;.  They get an impression, even though they know they can go back to the local authority, that they are better off on the housing list.  That is very sad indeed.  There are massive reductions in local authority building and I am not saying that is wrong.  I will admit that there were areas in which we were oversupplied as regards accommodation.</P>
    <P>The Minister has a duty not to spend money if he does not have to.  I like to spend money the best way I can and I look for ways to get the most from my money.  Are we to say to the agency: &ldquo;we must give you more money; you should be able to give out more because you should be making more&rdquo;?</P>
    <P>That would be very unfair to the less well off.  I do not want people to get the impression from this House, from the Minister, or from any Department that we are allowing a situation to develop where private funding is spent willy-nilly. It is private funding because the taxpayer does not have to pay for it.  I am not stupid enough to say that we should not be spending less but, at the same time, I do not want to see anyone in a situation he cannot get out of.  That is what I would be very much afraid of.  That would be sad.</P>
    <P>There have been massive reductions in the amount of money being allocated to local authorities.  Would I be right in saying that it has been reduced from £150 million to £50 million?  That is a saving of £100 million.  Could more be done with the £50 million?  Could we decide not to build in an area such as Cork, with a large population, where about 300 houses a year are built?  We will not be building that many this year.  I am not saying we will be short of accommodation.  We will be short of houses but we will not be short of accommodation because, we have plenty of flats built in the sixties.  It is an indictment of us as a society that we built them at all, but they are there so we must use them in the best way possible. Those buildings need to be reconstructed because they were not built properly.  The Irish are not used to accommodation like that.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="970" /> We should tell the local authority in Cork that they will get not £10 million or £8 million, but £5 million and it is up to them to do with that what they think is best for that area.  Unfortunately that will not be the case.  We will save a lot of money because we will not build more houses but we are not giving the local authorities the opportunity to do what they think is best.  Many local authorities are very good at accommodating the less well off.</P>
    <P>A lot of concern has been expressed about the homeless but, as a member of a local authority, I know that if we were allowed to allocate a certain amount per year in local grants we would shorten our housing lists.  There is no question about that.  People should be entitled to receive the agency loan.</P>
    <P>With the introduction of the £5,000 grant many people were able to buy their own houses.  In a short period of 14 months we got over 750 local authority houses back in Cork City because we gave a grant of £5,000 which enabled people to buy their own houses.  We saved £20,000 because we did not build new houses.  I will admit that the money paid out was probably paid out too fast.</P>
    <P>I can understand that when this Government came to office a lot of moneys were due and they had to cut back but they should not have eliminated the grants completely.  That has resulted in people rushing back to local authorities looking for houses.  The housing lists are increasing rapidly in all local authorities again.  The Government should give, say, 100 grants per year in the Cork area. They would have to pay that money but 100 local authority houses would be made available every year.  In the Dublin area perhaps 500 or 1,000 people could get the grant.  Many houses were made available in the Dublin region as a result of the £5,000 grant but problems were also created. Local authorities should be allowed to give the £5,000 grant to a certain number of people.  There are people living in local authority housing who can accommodate themselves and that has been proven without doubt.  A certain number of grants should be paid and this <Col N="971" /> would not cost the Government a large sum.  In the region of £120 million was paid in grants in a very short period. That is probably a little too high.  I am saddened to think that we have abolished nearly all grants.</P>
    <P>Loans are still being given for reconstruction purposes but the people are not fully informed of this.  The local authority will not inform people because it is the HFA agency that is involved.  The local authorities should have more responsibility for looking after their local affairs. Everybody in Government or in politics seems to agree with that but they never seem to do anything about it.  They are not prepared to say that local authorities should have that responsibility.  The national politician is the local hawk; he is the watchdog.  He is the man who says if something is going wrong he will report it nationally, and rightly so.  He is elected to represent people nationally and keep his eye on matters.</P>
    <P>I have listened to the Minister many times and he has shown an interest in this area.  I ask him to consider giving a certain amount of money per year in local grants but I am not saying that everybody who applies should get them.  If we could get 100 houses back every year we should do so but we should not try to get 300 houses a year.  If we got 300 back over a three year period it would mean not having to build as many at £25,000 each.  People should be given the agency loan.  We should concentrate more on that area.  I understand that if we open the floodgates here will be a massive flow of people looking for grants.  The construction industry said to us locally that they could not believe that all the grants were taken at once.  Much employment can be created in this area.  We know we are losing many people from the industry to Britain in particular.  A certain percentage of grants should be allowed and I am sure that could only help the agency.</P>
    <P>In regard to the Housing Finance Agency, there are certain regulations and rules.  I ask the Minister is it possible that the agency can be sold better?  We in Government circles unfortunately give <Col N="972" /> the impression that we have nothing to do with them.  Nobody likes getting letters from the Government, particularly if they are in brown envelopes and therefore how can we inform people about our national building agency, the Housing Finance Agency?  Generally people get the impression that they are stand-offish, that they are not associated with the person on £200 a week or on £10,000, £8,000 or £7,000 a year.  What can we do to dispel that impression?  Can we ask our local authorities, for instance, to send information to people, perhaps in the form of a leaflet such as that used by political parties?  The local authorities should inform every one of their tenants about the Housing Finance Agency.</P>
    <P>People should not get the impression that because their parents live in a local authority house they too should live in one.  We should tell people the options that are open to them, for instance, that the £2,000 first time buyer's grant is still in existence.  Many people have the impression and the Minister knows this as well as I do &mdash; that all grants are gone. I know that is not true.  When will the Government tell people that the £2,000 grant for the first time buyer is still in existence?  It would be unfair to the Government if people thought that grant was abolished.</P>
    <P>I do not think we are doing enough as a Government to inform our young people in particular that there are agencies and facilities available to them.  It is appalling for the Minister to say that happily the early indications are that the new arrangements are now working well. That is not so.  Young couples going into banks with no accounts are being told they will not get a loan.  Those people want to do something for themselves. They go to building societies and the position is the same and that is sad.  When they go to the authority they are asked where they are working and how much they are earning and are told they can be assisted.  I have pushed for a very long time for this type of system.</P>
    <P>I make no apologies for saying that many more of our people should not be in local authority housing.  With a little <Col N="973" /> bit of assistance they can provide houses for themselves.  That has been proved with the introduction of the £5,000 grant. We should concentrate more on that area.  The Government will allocate £50 million next year and this year to local authorities.  I ask the Minister to allocate to local authorities £500,000 a year to do with it what they think best and perhaps provide grants for people to buy their own houses rather than put them in local authority houses.  That would mean a saving of £25,000 per couple.  The taxpayer pays £90 a week on average for every local authority tenant.  If you told a person in a local authority house that is so he would not believe you but it is a fact of life.  Great savings can be made in that area.</P>
    <P>I know I digressed a little from the agency.  The Minister is saying that the scope of the agency must be broadened, particularly in the area of reconstruction. If that is done the National Housing Finance Agency should advertise and inform people what they are entitled to.  That would be doing something positive.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill seeks to achieve a comparatively modest purpose, to double the ceiling on the borrowing which the Housing Finance Agency can enter into in order to fund house purchase loans.  It has been clear from the reception of the Bill that that purpose is supported on all sides of the House.  Clearly it is desirable that there should be more funds available for use by those who are availing of an income-related loan scheme and who are therefore helped to buy houses.  At the moment this measure, and any measure in the area of housing, has to be examined in the context of the overall housing situation.  I find it difficult to assess objectively and accurately how this measure affects the overall housing situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have listened carefully to the contributions in this House and I have examined the record of the contributions made in the other House when this Bill was being debated and it is clear that those representatives who serve on local authorities placed great emphasis on the crisis in local authority funding, which we are <Col N="974" /> all aware of and on the fact that there are going to be virtually no new starts on corporation housing in 1988 and probably for the next couple of years.  This in itself will contribute to worsening the problem, particularly in some areas with housing lists.  It is also clear that social problems have existed for some time but have become strikingly worse, for example, the problem of young homeless people. That problem has become notably worse in the past 12 months and there is no reason, unfortunately, to believe that it is evening out.  On the contrary the voluntary agencies dealing with the young homeless are gravely concerned that the problem is accelerating at a very serious rate.</P>
    <P>Another problem we are failing to cope with and which is also increasing, because the net numbers are increasing, is the problem of the travelling community.  We still have a major social, housing and sheltered problem and we are failing to address the needs of travellers in our communities.  Some local authorities have made greater efforts than others and the Department of the Environment have taken some steps in that regard.  I accept that the recent budget acknowledged the severity of the problem of homelessness.  This is the first time I can recall that a specific allocation was made &mdash; an allocation of £1 million &mdash; to be diverted to the needs of the homeless.</P>
    <P>That is only recognising the manifestations and the visible evidence of a very serious problem.  It does not really meet what I believe is a crucial element of the present situation, that is, that we need to review our overall housing policy precisely because we have to provide for housing as for any other need within the constraints of the present crisis in our overall finances.  When it comes to housing, that poses particular difficulties because you have to have lead times and you have to have policies well established in order to provide overtime for housing needs.</P>
    <P>This Bill will improve in some measure the situation of the low income family who need support in order to be able to apply for and obtain a loan to enter into <Col N="975" /> a house mortgage.  That is meeting one defined need, but where does it come in the order of priorities and what policy considerations does it reflect?  At a recent international conference Ireland was shown up as being the only country represented at the conference that did not have legislation supporting the right of people to basic shelter, in other words, a legislative right to have housing needs not only considered and then put on a list but actually dealt with.  We pride ourselves on the fundamental rights provisions of our Constitution.  Where is the right to shelter in our Constitution and how is it reflected in our housing policy? This is the critical issue that arises on any Bill relating to housing, including this Bill increasing the loan capacity of the Housing Finance Agency.</P>
    <P>It would seem a matter of urgency that the Department of the Environment should publish a review of policy in the area of housing and establish, or at least propose for consideration, the priorities within the limited resources.  It seems that those priorities should start with those in greatest need.  At the moment the funds are being allocated to those who already have a base, who have grounds to argue that they should be supported or helped and not, for example, those without shelter, persons who for various social reasons have been rendered homeless, or who have not got serviced sites or other places where they can have the most basic right to water and sanitary facilities which go with minimal shelter requirements. We do not seem to have an order of priorities.</P>
    <P>My colleague, Senator Brendan Ryan, has sought on innumerable occasions in this House to bring forward his Private Members' Bill on housing the homeless but it has not been possible to give time for the priority consideration of that Bill. The failure in this House to get a debate on it reflects an overall failure.  I am not blaming this Government specifically.  It is not a new problem; it is a problem we have had in the past and it continues to be a problem.  We do not have a real order <Col N="976" /> of priorities which reflects the priority of housing needs.  We are addressing the issues on an <i>ad hoc</i> basis.</P>
    <P>Many of the contributions to the debate on this Bill have reflected frustration with the way in which local authorities are prevented from addressing the priorities within their own areas.  A number of the points that have been made, including those made by the last speaker, on that point warrant attention. If we have a genuine willingness to look at the overall resources which are there to meet housing needs and to help people to meet their own housing needs we can then have a value system which is fair.  If it is to be fair there must be a much greater recognition of the housing needs of those who have no shelter at the moment.  That must mean that there cannot be the kind of starving of funds to local authorities in the area of housing which is evident at the moment, because there is no way that people who have neither a home nor even a modest income can avail of the resources of the house purchase loans provided under the auspices of the Housing Finance Agency. Therefore, it is important when the Minister is replying to the debate on this Bill that he places the purposes of it in an overall context.</P>
    <P>I would welcome some indication that there will be a published review of our housing policy and of the policy of this Government on meeting the needs of those who are not able to provide for their own housing needs either with the help of a loan, where there is an income-related loan scheme such as this, or otherwise, and those who need some special kind of provision such as the travelling community who need particular provision either by way of serviced sites, group housing or other appropriate accommodation.  We must ensure, not that they are given some kind of favoured treatment but, for the first time perhaps as a society, that we can say we are beginning to ensure that they have the most minimal rights to shelter, water and sanitary facilities.</P>
    <P>Another issue in relation to our housing policy which has been referred to by <Col N="977" /> a number of contributors to this debate is the extent to which it is encouraging the segregation of the population, particularly in Dublin and other urban areas. Housing estates have become, in effect, social ghettos where, partly because of the very policy that we are adopting, those who can get out do so with the result that there is a very high rate of unemployment, up to 75 per cent, in those estates.  There are single parent families and people with multiple problems but there are no resources within that community to meet those problems. That is part of the housing issue.  It is greatly influenced by our policies and our priorities in relation to housing.  It cannot be dealt with purely under a housing hat but our policy on housing has a very major effect on it.</P>
    <P>All of these problems have been there in the past.  They have been there in various ways over the past decades.  It is my experience, and it is a more limited experience than that of those who serve on local authorities, that those problems are becoming dramatically worse.  The segregation problem is worse; the number of homeless people is increasing; and the number of travelling families in need of basic shelter is greater.  It is a matter of urgent priority that we stand back from the components of the problem and decide to take the decisions that are open to us, notwithstanding the constraints on the public purse.</P>
    <P>Most of those decisions have to do with diverting resources to those in greatest need, designing those resources to ensure that we are not aggravating the social problems on the ground and, above all, ensuring that any citizen of the State who is not able to provide for his shelter needs has, under our Constitution and our law, a right to those basic facilities which really are an extension of the basic human personality, the right to a basic home and shelter.</P>
    <P>While I welcome the limited purposes of this Bill for the reasons which were given by the Minister in introducing it to this House, it must be seen in that overall context and I hope the Minister, in his <Col N="978" /> reply, will deal more fully with that context.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardCConnelly" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Connolly) Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Connolly)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Connolly)</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I would like to thank Senators for their very positive contributions to this debate. It has been a very wide-ranging debate, going far beyond the context of the Bill, but I accept it in the spirit in which it was put forward by Members.  A Leas-Chathaoirligh, you might have to bear with me if I go a little outside the scope of the Bill, if that is in order, but I will be directed by you.</P>
      <P>Senator McCormack complained about the new differential rents scheme in Galway.  That is a matter for the local authority in Galway.  The previous Government amended the regulations to give the local authority and, especially the manager, power in that area.  That concerns all local authorities.  Discussions with the National Association of Tenants Organisations are in progress with a view to formulating a new rents scheme which, while maintaining the traditional social character of the local authority rents scheme, will ensure that those tenants who can afford them will pay realistic rents.  I want to point out that the revision taking place in many local authorities is being done by the managers and I have explained the reason for that.</P>
      <P>Senator Cregan suggested that there should be flexibility for changing from income-related loans to annuity loans.  This flexibility does exist.  A person can change from an income-related loan to an annuity loan at any time during the life of the loan.  The loan will, however, continue to attract a variable interest rate which at present is very favourable. Senator Cregan also suggested that the HFA should be sold better to potential borrowers.  I would remind the Senator that the agency no longer lends money to individual borrowers.  That is now done by local authorities.  The agency's function is to raise funds which it lends to the local authorities to finance house loan schemes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Bill is a technical measure <Col N="979" /> designed to provide a statutory basis for the broader role which the Housing Finance Agency is now undertaking, as the primary source of State funding for private house loans.  Despite the fact that it is a short Bill it is an important one.</P>
    <P>A number of Senators referred to the new arrangement whereby applicants must first approach a building society or a banks before applying to a local authority for a loan.  As the Senators are aware, these publicly-funded loan schemes were always intended to assist those in need of housing and who are unable to obtain a loan from any other financial institution. In practice this requirement was implemented in varying degrees by different authorities.  The new arrangement, under which the commercial lending agencies have undertaken to contribute £70 million to the market sector currently catered for by the local authorities renders it essential that this requirement be implemented in full.  The arrangement now in operation is the most efficient one.  For example, an arrangement under which local authorities will assess all applicants in the first instance would not work.  How could a local authority have access to the criteria used by banks and building societies for assessing applicants?</P>
    <P>It would inconvenience an applicant far more were he assessed by a local authority, told to apply to a bank or a building society &mdash; be refused by them &mdash; and then forced to return to the local authority.  It is preferable that he go first to a bank or building society so that, on applying to a local authority, he knows that his application will be accepted and processed.  I must emphasise that these arrangements with the commercial lending agencies will not affect a person's capacity to house himself or herself.  On the contrary, there will be more funds available in 1988 than would otherwise have been the case.  In addition, a borrower is afforded greater choice and flexibility in choosing the type of loan financing best suited to his or her particular needs.  I am happy to say that these arrangements are now working well.  I <Col N="980" /> want to commend the banks and building societies for the prompt, efficient way in which they are dealing with applications.</P>
    <P>It has been my experience of this new arrangement that many banks and building societies are issuing approval of loans within 48 hours.  While not wishing to condemn any local authority or throw any aspersion on them, in some cases many applications to local authorities have taken up to two months to be approved.  Not alone are the banks or building societies giving a commitment to enable people build a house, but some are giving a commitment up to a certain level.  This means that an applicant can go anywhere in the county provided the relevant house passes a surveyor's report and is otherwise in order.  That constitutes a big step.  Another matter I dealt with on resuming office &mdash; and for which I should get some thanks &mdash; is that the income of the second spouse is not now taken into consideration by local authorities. Let us say the income of the main earner is £9,800 and the wife's income is £8,000.  That £8,000 income is not now taken into account by local authorities. The Minister and I should be thanked for that.  That is a big help to applicants for house purchase finance.</P>
    <P>I admit that there were some teething problems in the operation of the new arrangements.  I accept that.  Many Members of this House brought it to my attention.  We did our best to sort them out.  There have been no complaints recently on the operation of the scheme. In local authorities in many instances there were as many as six people handling a loan application.  In the other lending institutions there are now only three, which is speeding up the process.  That is what I am endeavouring to bring about. I do not think it is right that anybody should have to wait up to eight weeks &mdash; after planning permission has been granted and all the necessary documentation supplied &mdash; to learn what may be wrong in the processing of their loan. I do not agree there should be such delay. I have asked all the local authorities to speed up the process.  I do not want any local authority to obstruct the operation <Col N="981" /> of the scheme &mdash; I am not saying they are &mdash; I want it to run smoothly.  If an applicant is refused a housing loan by a bank or building society they can go back to the local authority.  All the local authority require is the relevant correspondence from the institution that refused the application, when they will process the application.  That is a very fair method.</P>
    <P>Senator Fallon suggested that a loan guarantee should not be given to the banks and building societies.  The reason for the guarantee is that these agencies are now granting loans of a higher percentage of house value than they would normally.  The guarantee is a very limited one and covers 50 per cent only of the amount by which the loan exceeds 75 per cent of the value of the house.  It has been my experience that some banks and building societies do not seek such a guarantee at all.</P>
    <P>I am glad to hear Senator Doyle welcome the recent introduction of the variable interest rate for housing loans at a time of falling interest rates.  Obviously it is in the interests of borrowers to be able to avail of the cheaper rates as they arise.  Senator Doyle suggested that borrowers should be given a choice between fixed or variable rate loans.  It would not be practical to operate two schemes side by side.  In any event I consider the variable rate the correct arrangement. However, I should like to point out that people whose loans were approved before 28 October last when the new system was announced are being given the option of a fixed rate of 10.75 per cent, including mortgage protection, or a variable rate which is currently 9.25 per cent.</P>
    <P>Senator Hogan suggested that the £2,000 unsecured, improvement loan should be increased.  The unsecured loan was increased from £1,000 to £2,000 in May 1986.  I do not consider it would be prudent for local authorities to lend more than £2,000 without security.</P>
    <P>Senator McMahon questioned why it had been found necessary to increase the borrowing limit to the Housing Finance Agency in view of the fall-off in demand <Col N="982" /> for loans.  As I explained in my opening speech, the role of the Housing Finance Agency has now been broadened to include the provision of all funds which local authorities lend by way of income-related, convertible and SDA loans as well as improvement loans.  To enable the agency raise the funds necessary for all these loans the borrowing limit had to be increased.</P>
    <P>Senator Hogan suggested that we should look at other sources of funding for house loans.  He suggested that insurance and pension funds might be used in this respect.  The Housing Finance Agency relies on various agencies, such as insurance companies and pension funds, to invest in the various bonds the agency issues.</P>
    <P>Senator McGowan suggested that the directors of the Housing Finance Agency meet with local authority members as all of the loan schemes operations are now the responsibility of local authorities.  The Housing Finance Agency does not grant loans to individuals.  The role of the agency is now one of block lending of funds to local authorities.  In these circumstances there would be little point in a meeting as was suggested by Senator McGowan.  The Senator also spoke of a penalty being imposed by the Housing Finance Agency when an income tax return is not furnished on the due date. I presume he was talking about a return of income required to be at the end of the tax year, in other words by 5 April. I should say that there is no penalty imposed if an income tax return is not furnished on time.  Instead the agency puts the relevant borrower on an annuity repayment basis until such time as the relevant return of income is received. The agency must have some basis for calculating repayment in the absence of an income tax return.  This is the logical basis on which to proceed in the interim.</P>
    <P>Many members have a great interest in the usage of Housing Finance Agency loans for voluntary housing.  I have a great interest in it also.  Senator Hogan suggested that the Housing Finance Agency funds be used to help in the provision of voluntary housing.  We are <Col N="983" /> effecting some amendments in regard to the amount that has to be advanced in order to help voluntary housing organisations. I should say that the expenditure under the voluntary housing scheme is increased annually.  However, it has not achieved much by way of additional accommodation for the homeless.  The additional £1 million provided in the budget will bring to £4 million my Department's contribution to fully subsidised loans to the voluntary housing organisations in 1988.  In addition to increasing the funding, I should inform the House that I am also amending the terms of this scheme in recognition of the fact that the existing requirement to meet 20 per cent of the cost of providing accommodation is particularly harsh on voluntary organisations assisting the homeless.  We have decided to increase from 80 per cent to 95 per cent the level of assistance available in any case of accommodation for homeless persons.  That is to be welcomed. I know many Senators like myself, have very strong views on that matter.</P>
    <P>Senator Norris suggested that housing co-operatives should be encouraged more.  I should point out that housing co-operatives have been given support over the years by way of flexibility in relation to eligibility for loans and higher levels of loans.  This means that housing co-operatives could avail of sites provided by local authorities at a subsidised price. However, the level of activity of housing co-operatives in recent years has been disappointing.  I would hope that local authorities would see the encouragement of housing co-operatives as a means of meeting part of the housing needs in their areas.  Certainly I and my Department will continue to encourage local authorities to do so.</P>
    <P>Senator McMahon urged me to make money available to Dublin County Council for the purchase of re-possessed houses.  I should say that, where a local authority re-possesses a house &mdash; which cannot be sold at a reasonable price on the open market &mdash; they can take such a house into their housing stock.  The <Col N="984" /> outstanding debt on such a house can be met from the relevant local authority's internal housing capital receipts.  It is a matter for each local authority to arrange their programme accordingly.</P>
    <P>Senators Doyle and Hogan referred to the matter of local authority housing.  I should point out that each housing authority have been asked to submit a claim for capital allocation for their 1988 housing construction programme.  Until such claims have been received, allocations cannot be made to individual local authorities. Having regard to the current law numbers on housing authority waiting lists and the large numbers of vacant houses I am satisfied that the availability of local authority housing will not constitute a problem this year.</P>
    <P>Senator Fitzsimons referred to delays in the carrying out of essential repairs. The implementation of such works is entirely a matter for the local authority concerned, who can decide on the amount of money they will spend in any year within their overall allocation for loans and grants.</P>
    <P>Senator Robinson dealt in some detail with our overall housing problems.  Here I might point out that we have the highest home ownership ratio in Europe.  When I came to the Department in 1979, the then Minister and Government initiated a major housing programme.  I would like to point out that in that respect we changed the policy that had pertained until then.  What concerned me at that time was that most houses were being built in the greater urban areas.  I decided that rural Ireland should be looked after as well and that we should spread out our activities into towns and villages.  I am glad to say that that happened throughout the country.</P>
    <P>I have a good knowledge of the way things operate on the ground.  As you know, a Leas-Chathaoirligh, people in the midlands will not accept a house if it is not the end one with the large garden. They will not accept a centre one.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>The one with a lake view.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardCConnelly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>They will accept an end <Col N="985" /> house with a large garden or possibly one with the nice entrance.  They say to me: &ldquo;There is a house coming up in Daingean in County Offaly; we will not take one in another part of the country.&rdquo;  No; they are picking and choosing.  I should like to say to local authorities &mdash; and I have been saying this to county managers also &mdash; that, in regard to the allocation of houses, I should like to see them allocated more speedily.  Delays in allocation create problems, such as vandalism and so on.</P>
      <P>I should like to turn now to a thorny problem, that of the housing of itinerants. We have allocated money this year for caravan parks in various parts of the country.  We are giving up to 100 per cent grants.  But in many such cases we are not receiving much co-operation from members of local authorities.  There are also those do-gooders who say: &ldquo;Yes, look after them but do not locate them near me.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDoyle" hpid="Mr. Doyle Mr. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>And some of the Minister's own party too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardCConnelly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>In my county, in Tullamore, we have looked after the itinerants. I will bring the Senator down to see it.  Many members of local authorities have seen the excellent job we have done in Tullamore thanks to the urban council and others also.  I will do my utmost to get agreement on the part of all concerned so that we will be able to look after these people, placing them into what I might describe as reasonably good housing conditions. But we cannot do so without support.</P>
      <P>As Senators are aware, the Minister announced £3 million for the homeless in the budget.  We must take into account the fact that local authorities are dealing with a new type of applicant, one with whom they did not have to deal, say, 20 years ago; there are unmarried mothers, separated people and so on.  Local authorities are looking after their housing needs.  I want to thank them in that respect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the future of local authority housing in general it should be remembered that before I allocate a penny for local <Col N="986" /> authority housing this year, the subsidy to local authority housing will be over £200 million, or approximately £85 per local authority house.  That is an enormous amount.  If all goes well the Minister and I hope to be able to announce shortly a new tenants' house purchase scheme.  I know many Senators are anxious that something should be done in that area also.</P>
    <P>We have increased the allocation for remedial works on housing from £7 million to £10 million this year.  This means we will be able to carry out essential repairs on houses in a large number of estates throughout the country.  I admit we could do with more funds but Senators know where such must emanate from. Many Senators asked how I envisage local authority funding in the future. Senators will realise that, as a result of the very tight financial position in which we find ourselves in there is one way only in which we can provide money for housing, that is, by way of taxation or borrowing.  I am hoping we will be able to involve the financial institutions more. With interest rates coming down the prospects are looking good.  For example, the reduction on a £25,000 20-year mortgage is £55 per month on the loan repayment compared with that obtaining at the same time last year.  Remember that is cash into the pocket of the householder. That reduction has been brought about by a tight rein being maintained on national finances.</P>
    <P>We cannot depart from that strategy. We must live within the overall Estimate for our Department passed by Dáil Éireann.  There are many projects, a Leas-Chathaoirligh, for which we would like to provide funds but we are unable to do so &mdash; some very good projects.  But we will have to devise some new means of making funds available for local authority housing in the future.  There now is a limit to what tax revenue can do.  It will be a good thing if we can involve the financial institutions more.  Over the years there have been many people Governments have rehoused who, in my opinion, were well able to house themselves.  If we can make loans and interest rates attractive, <Col N="987" /> they should house themselves and not expect the taxpayer to do so.  I am not prepared to house them.  This should be entertained only where there is need.  The homeless spring to mind immediately. There are many good voluntary organisations undertaking tremendous work in this respect.  You know that to be the case, a Leas-Chathaoirligh, in your county.  I am very favourably disposed in that direction.</P>
    <P>There is another group of people I should like to help also.  I would also like to help those people who want isolated cottages in the country, maybe on a small piece of land where they have lived all their lives.  As a rural man I do not want to see rural Ireland deserted.</P>
    <P>Finally, the new arrangements we have made are working satisfactorily.  They will always be open to review.  If improvements can be brought about and I have the finances to do so, I shall be only too glad to carry them out.  I hope I have covered most of the points raised.  It was a very wide-ranging and interesting debate.  There were many enlightening contributions made, some of which I have taken notes on as time does not allow me to go into them in more detail.  Nevertheless, I am hopeful that all of the money made available by the financial institutions will be taken up this year.  I want to thank all Senators for their help and co-operation.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Housing Finance Agency (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1987: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Housing Finance Agency (Amendment) Bill, 1987: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 and 2 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDoyle" hpid="Mr. Doyle Mr. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted that the banks and the building societies have <Col N="988" /> taken an interest in supplying funds for house purchasers.  But, as Senator Fallon said last week in the House, banks are now looking for business.  We all know the detrimental effect this had on the farming community in the seventies when the banks had a lot of money available and people invested in farms and were not able to meet their commitments.  I am afraid that could also happen in the housing sector and that people who make applications to the banks would be well received and given loans which may be beyond the ability of some to repay.</P>
      <P>The fact that the Minister said that the banks can clear people within 48 hours worries me because, even though local authorities might have been slow, they were always very prudent and there is a value in that.  Therefore, I would like the Minister to comment on how banks are giving loans to people and on ability to pay in future, because problems could arise and interest rates might not stay as they are at present.  I hope they will decrease further.  Nevertheless we have to take into account international events which have a bearing on interest rates in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardCConnelly" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Connolly) Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Connolly)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Connolly)</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, Senator.  So far I am pleased with the contribution the banks and the building societies have made.  The banks now take into consideration the person's ability to pay.  The beauty of the banks and the building societies over the local authorities is that, if a person is earning over £10,000 gross per annum, there is no problem in getting a loan.  From dealing with my constituents with regard to the banks and the building societies I can say that they are very prudent as to people's ability to pay and they will always point out a problem to the borrower and also ensure that the person who takes out this commitment will be able to meet the repayments.  It is essential now &mdash; and most companies and financial institutions insist on this &mdash; that a mortgage protection policy be taken out to cover the sum borrowed because, if the borrower dies, the survivor, who may be the wife, <Col N="989" /> or the son, or the daughter, automatically owns the property because the mortgage protection policy covers that.</P>
      <P>I am grateful to the Senator for raising that point.  People today do not want to be left a long time wondering if they will or will not be approved for a loan.  All in all, I am satisfied now that this is operating satisfactorily.  If there are any other complaints I shall be glad to take them up with the financial institutions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephDoyle" hpid="Mr. Doyle Mr. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>There is one remark which I would like to make in relation to the £5,000 grant.  The Minister said he was anxious to improve the housing situation. I feel the time has come to abolish the £5,000 grant for people who are living in local authority houses.  I ask the Minister to consider at some stage providing that £5,000 grant for people who live in local authority flats to allow them to enter private housing.  Often people living in flats have not got the points necessary to get local authority housing in Dublin. The flats could then be left for homeless people and single people.  This would be an opportunity to turn round the housing stock to house smaller units in flats and allow larger families to enter into housing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardCConnelly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate the Senator's remarks.  The £5,000 grant served its purpose.  In some estates throughout the country it was creating some problems where people were leaving estates, the estates were becoming run down because of a reluctance on the part of tenants to go to live in the estates &mdash; for what reason I do not know.  Then there was an unprecedented delay in reallocating housing to those in need.  I agree that there would be a problem in the Dublin area in regard to the re-allocation of houses but, in some cases, it was taking up to 12 weeks to re-allocate a house.  That was leaving these houses open to vandalism and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When I came into the Department the total amount due in applications and the amount needed in March of last year to cover the grants, including house improvement grants, was approximately <Col N="990" /> £235 million.  That has to come from the taxpayer.  Applications in the house improvement grant area are still coming in at a very high rate.  The grant has served its purpose.  When these schemes are completed we can reconsider the position and see what is best to do then.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 4 and 5 agreed to.</P>
    <P>Title agreed to.</P>
    <P>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardCConnelly" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Connolly) Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Connolly)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Connolly)</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to thank you, a Chathaoirligh, and the Leas-Chathaoirleach and Members for their co-operation with me on this Bill.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Worker Participation (State" RHead="Enterprises) Bill, 1988: Second Stage">
    <Title>Worker Participation (State Enterprises) Bill, 1988: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="Minister for Labour (Mr. B. Ahern) Bertie Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Labour (Mr. B. Ahern)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill now before the House translates into action the Government commitment in the <i>Programme for National Recovery</i> to provide legislation to facilitate the introduction of worker participation at sub-board levels in State enterprises.  The Bill also extends provision for worker director elections to employees in two further State enterprises &mdash; Aer Rianta and the National Rehabilitation Board. In addition, the Bill makes a number of amendments to the Worker Participation (State Enterprises) Act, 1977.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill is broadly similar to that introduced in this House in December, 1986. That Bill lapsed from the Seanad Order Paper following the general election.  I am confident that on this occasion the <Col N="991" /> proposals before this House will reach the Statute Book.</P>
    <P>It is 11 years since the Worker Participation (State Enterprises) Act, 1977, passed into law.  At that time, there was considerable debate as to whether board level participation was the most appropriate starting point for worker involvement in our State enterprises.  Some argued that shop floor level participation was the essential first step in any worker participation initiative.</P>
    <P>In the event, the worker director legislation went ahead in seven major State enterprises.  Subsequently, in 1983, provision was made in the legislation which established An Post and Bord Telecom Éireann for worker directors on the new boards.</P>
    <P>The debate about the merits of different ways of promoting greater involvement of employees has continued.  The elected directors have been critical of the isolation forced upon them by the absence of well designed structures and appropriate representative arrangements at sub-board level.  In 1980 the then Minister for Labour published a discussion paper which emphasised the importance of participation below the level of the board.  The Commission of Enquiry on Safety, Health and Welfare which reported in 1983 proposed an integral role for employees in enforcing safety and health standards in the workplace. In 1986, the Advisory Committee on Worker Participation examined and reported on the scope for development of employee participation at sub-board level in different types of work organisation.</P>
    <P>When I assumed office as Minister for Labour, I found that there was a fair body of expert opinion as well as a published Bill which together identified a variety of options for progress in the area of worker participation.  The ground work had been done.  My task was to take up some of the proposals for action and bring them to fruition.</P>
    <P>The purpose of this Bill is to underpin <Col N="992" /> the development of worker involvement below the level of the board in the semi-State sector.  There are 39 State enterprises listed in the First Schedule of the Bill.</P>
    <P>All of these enterprises are covered by the sub-board provisions.  Some of the enterprises listed have made some progress with participation.  Many of the enterprises have yet to consider joint consultation; this Bill should help them to take the first steps in the participative process.</P>
    <P>We need to legislate in this area in order to stimulate change by means of a concerted effort on the part of management and employee at enterprise level.  There has been a tendency on the part of those enterprises &mdash; both in the public and the private sector &mdash; who have pioneered new forms of employee involvement to keep their experience very much to themselves.  I have spoken before of the need to shed more light on the new forms of work organisation and of co-operation which have been developed in this country.  I see this Bill as a useful catalyst in this context.</P>
    <P>The Bill gives to employees in each State enterprise the right to initiate arrangements for sub-board participation. The enterprise and the representatives of its employees are required to devise between them mutually acceptable arrangements for employee involvement following a request from a majority of employees.  Although the Bill provides for a direct initiative by employees within each enterprise, it does not interfere with the freedom of management to develop its own proposals and to approach employee representatives about the development of sub-board participation.</P>
    <P>It is up to the employee representatives and the company management to work out arrangements best suited to their organisation in each case.  The whole range of options &mdash; from direct to representational forms of participation and from the highly structured to the relatively informal &mdash; are accommodated within the legislative framework.</P>
    <P>I hope that enterprises will be innovative in their use of the legislation.  The <Col N="993" /> Bill does not seek to impose a uniform framework.  There is scope for a wide variety of different practices providing always that the arrangements made are acceptable both to the enterprise and to the workforce.  This flexibility in the legislation ensures considerable freedom at enterprise level.</P>
    <P>The agenda for participation will have to be decided between the enterprise and its employees.  I expect that at the outset some enterprises may opt for a narrow range of subject areas.  As confidence grows and the level of trust develops, further subject areas can be brought within the participative process.  In the ESB, for instance, where all the unions and management have reached agreement on the establishment of structures for worker participation, it was accepted by all concerned that they were engaged in a long term process and that some objectives would only be gained by years of genuine effort by both sides.</P>
    <P>Although flexibility is the keynote, some critical elements are essential to the evolution of participation and these are set out at section 6(2) of the Bill.</P>
    <P>The Bill requires the exchange of views as well as the exchange of clear and reliable information between the enterprise and its employees; the communication in good time to employees of information likely to have a significant effect on their interests; and the distribution to all employees of views and information arising from the participative process.  These are the basic requirements. There are, of course, many issues on which management and unions could make progress for mutual benefit, by sharing information and joint discussion, leading to better decisions for all concerned.</P>
    <P>Another feature of the Bill is the extension of worker director arrangements to two further State enterprises.  These are Aer Rianta and the National Rehabilitation Board.  The 1977 Act gave employees in seven commercial State enterprises the right to elect worker directors in numbers equal to one-third of total board membership.  Aer Rianta is another commercial enterprise and will <Col N="994" /> be accommodated within the framework established in the 1977 Act.</P>
    <P>The National Rehabilitation Board is the first non-commercial State enterprise to be brought within the general arrangements. The original formula of reserving one-third of all board places for worker directors was framed with commercial boards in mind.  I believe that greater flexibility is necessary to take account of the circumstances of the non-commercial State bodies.  Employees are only one element among the diversity of representative interests to be accommodated on these boards.</P>
    <P>In deciding the level of employee representation on boards of this kind it is important to maintain the balance of representational interests and to ensure at the same time that the board remains an effective body.  These considerations can be judged only on a case by case basis.  As a result, the Bill permits the Minister for Labour to vary the number of worker directors below the one-third arrangement by order &mdash; subject to a minimum of two worker directors.</P>
    <P>There are a number of other amendments to the 1977 Act which I would like to bring to your attention.  The 1977 Act was an experimental measure.  It did not provide scope for extending its provisions beyond the seven enterprises designated in the Act.  As a result further developments in board level participation were entirely dependent on voluntary initiatives or on special legislative developments &mdash; as in the case of the establishment of An Post and Telecom Éireann.</P>
    <P>This Bill provides for the extension of board level participation to further State enterprises without recourse to primary legislation.  It empowers the Minister for Labour after consultation with other interested Minister's and with the approval of both Houses of the Oireachtas to designate further enterprises for worker director elections.</P>
    <P>Section 9 of the Bill will allow the employees of company subsidiaries to take part, subject to very precise requirements, in elections to the main board. Their inclusion in the overall electorate <Col N="995" /> is a matter for the State enterprise concerned.</P>
    <P>The Bill provides that any proposal for their inclusion must be sent in writing to the Minister for Labour and the views of staff representatives must be communicated to him at the same time.</P>
    <P>It is only at this stage that the Minister for Labour, in consultation with other Ministers concerned, would consider bringing the employees of the subsidiary into the overall electorate for the main board.  In any event, a draft order to give effect to the proposal would require the approval of both Houses of the Oireachtas.  I am aware that this provision has given rise to concern particularly in relation to the position of overseas subsidiaries.  I appreciate the difficulties which might arise.  I am reviewing the options in this area and will return to the matter in more detail on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>The other amendments I want to mention are more straightforward.  I propose to extend the term of office of worker directors from three to four years.  This change follows on requests for a period of office longer than three years, both from worker directors and from the boards of some designated enterprises.</P>
    <P>There is also provision that worker directors who cease to be employees of the State enterprise should relinquish board membership.  Worker directors are meant to be just that &mdash; employees of the enterprise who have a seat on the board. It is reasonable to expect that they should give up board membership when they retire or resign from the enterprise.</P>
    <P>The provision ensures that employees are represented at board level by a fellow worker and is particularly apt at this stage because of the extension from three to four years of the term of office of worker directors.</P>
    <P>Worker participation can make a positive contribution to improving the relations between management and employees.  I see worker participation as <Col N="996" /> a model for a new maturity of purpose by Irish workers and management.  Central to this is the establishment and maintenance of a relationship of trust and co-operation in the workplace.  The present generation have the education to assess and evaluate economic and business information.  They have grown up in a &ldquo;right to know&rdquo; society.  Yet, the workplace has hardly changed in my lifetime.</P>
    <P>The focus on the development of sub-board structures in the <i>Programme for National Recovery</i> is a positive step which, I believe, calls for reciprocal initiatives from employers and trade unions.  The programme is about concerted efforts on the part of all interests based on a commitment to the provision of employment and to the better use of natural and human resources.  I hope this Bill will help to strengthen the spirit of co-operation which has been a feature of our State enterprise.</P>
    <P>I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NualaFennell" hpid="Mrs. Fennell Mrs. Fennell">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Fennell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am pleased to welcome this Bill into the House.  Its objective is to support the concept of industrial democracy in the widest sense and to enable workers to know that their views and their experiences will be taken into account in important stages of management planning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is, indeed, regrettable that there has been a delay in introducing this legislation. I know that the same view was expressed here in the Seanad in December 1986 when the Coalition Government introduced the previous Bill which was very much the same in its objectives as the present Bill.  Unfortunately as the Minister pointed out, because that Bill had not completed all stages in the Seanad before the election, it did not go on the new Dáil Order Paper and so we have to start from scratch again.  I must laud the confidence with which the Minister assured us that this Bill would not suffer the same fate as the last one. However, I do not believe there will be any serious disagreement from any side of this House on the progress of the Bill. All parties not only agree with the proposals <Col N="997" /> in legislation such as this, but at various times in Government have introduced legislation in the general area.</P>
    <P>In this context I would like to comment on the work of the Advisory Committee on Worker Participation whose report was presented to the previous Minister for Labour in October 1986.  It is a report which, although the committee had a restricted time in which to work and to bring forward their report, is extraordinarily comprehensive in its range.  It gives a very good brief and background to the whole movement for worker participation in this country and elsewhere and has even contributed an evolution in Ireland of the movement.  We see from this section of the report that, while the first discussion or examination of industrial democracy in Ireland happened in May 1967, it was not until June 1976 that the first Worker Participation (State Enterprises) Bill was introduced to the Dáil by a previous Coalition Government and this legislation became law in April 1977.  So we can see that this move towards the very desirable participation of workers on company boards is a slow process and we have to be suitably grateful that this legislation is now before the House.</P>
    <P>This Bill, I believe, represents a balance between State intervention in the interests of establishing basic rights and representations and the provision of voluntary mechanisms which leave it up to workers to decide whether or not to exercise those rights.  The Bill before the House will support employee influence in companies without regulating or setting down any absolute rules in detail on how decisions should be made and what decisions should be reached.  Of course, there are a number of different patterns or forms in which employee participation can be effected and, as the advisory committee reported, it would be difficult to pick a way through the many forms of human interaction which bear the name of employee participation.</P>
    <P>The application to Ireland and the experience of other countries lead to a number of general conclusions.  Ireland <Col N="998" /> has remained isolated from the widespread interest in other countries in the development of new forms of worker participation and management.  Hence the first need was to awaken realisation among people here to the possibilities and the need to move away from centralised systems of managerial domination towards the involvement of workers in the organisation of productive activities.  It was necessary to overcome the opposition among Irish employers and to secure support for the introduction of appropriate legislation.  It would be necessary for the trade union movement to accelerate the process of developing improvements in structure in their service to their members, and to familiarise themselves with the solution discovered in other countries.  To quote from the Seanad report of 10 December 1986 the Minister, Deputy Ruairí Quinn, introducing the Second Stage of the Worker Participation (State Enterprises) Bill, 1986 said:</P>
    <P>The worker director experiment, initially confined to the seven State companies covered by the 1977 Act and subsequently adopted in An Post, Bord Telecom and ACOT... has been judged largely successful.  Nevertheless both management and unions have been reluctant to consider the effects of the experiment and developments at lower levels in the enterprise. For their part, the elected worker directors recognise the need for more support in reporting back and in maintaining contact with other employees. Across the State sector generally the information issue has been tackled in a piecemeal fashion.  The outcome in all fronts has, by any standards, reflected limited success, limited awareness and hardly any integration.</P>
    <P>This Bill is a further recognition of greater awareness in industrial relations and represents a recognition of the improvement in the education of workers today.  Although the class of distinction, that the &ldquo;them and us&rdquo; syndrome of years past, is fading quite fast, there is still <Col N="999" /> too much evidence around to suit fair-minded people who believe that workers should have a voice and a role in decision-making and in corporate planning.  It is valid that the State not only should take a lead in this matter, but needs to be constantly aware of the further development of the concept of worker participation and the research and development and training requirements necessary to enable the worker directors to integrate fully and to meet expectations of them.</P>
    <P>At present, when this country is going through a painful and difficult era in regard to job losses and inability of the economy to provide sufficient jobs to meets the needs of the young expanding population, it is vitally important that we continue to explore all avenues which will lead to better industrial relations and exploit to the full the talents and skills available whether they are in the ranks of management or in the ranks of the workers.  There are many advantages for any organisation in tapping and using the resources of workers and putting them into effect in the heretofore rarefied atmosphere of the boardrooms.  It has got to be to the advantage of any corporation to have at the highest level the value of actual experience, actual insights and actual knowledge of the operation of a plant, firsthand experience of the technical and human resources operating at production level.</P>
    <P>Added to this must be the firsthand understanding and experience of workers of the industrial relations process within their company.  Good industrial relations machinery has got to be a fundamental part of the co-operative and harmonious working of a company.  It is easy to see that this can be had to the best advantage through the involvement of the workers on the factory floor.  Overall the natural intelligence and ability of the workers is an important dimension.</P>
    <P>The experience up to now is that the workers' representatives have met the challenge of this new role, and have made a very positive contribution.  But then it cannot be easy initially for them, <Col N="1000" /> moving from the work environment where for many years they would have been familiar with the rules, practice and expectations and have had the support and the companionship of their peer group, into a totally new and different environment of management.  Not only do they in effect have to cross into new work terrain which would have been strange and maybe even hostile to them in the past, but they are also required to master aspects of a strange agenda, which they may not have the ready skills or background to cope with, such as financial statements, or planning, or economic analysis.</P>
    <P>The experience has been that the role is seen by directors in a very serious way, and can mean that these directors will very often take more of an intense interest in matters coming up for discussion than, perhaps, would the outside directors.  Nobody could underestimate the enormous responsibility involved in this role, one that requires the members to set aside their union differences and to develop a commitment on the one hand to the company and maintain their commitment to their constituency of workers.  No one can doubt that it is a difficult if rewarding and important position because it may be fine to be a director when the company is making a profit and forging ahead in a worthwhile way and with a lot of good news.  It is a completely different story and it is not so easy when the same company is going through a difficult time and may need, for instance, to negotiate to close a plant down or to relocate, or seek necessary redundancies.</P>
    <P>The need to ensure that the best interests of all concerned are accommodated indicates the importance of the development of the sub-board structures. The sections in this Bill which deal with the machinery for establishing these sub-board structures are comprehensive and clear and when established should contribute to greater understanding of issues and the possibility of resolution of differences with representatives and management and workers sitting down together for consultations, mutual understanding, hopefully, and decision <Col N="1001" /> making.  This will mean that the worker directors will not be working in a vacuum but will have dialogue and broad agreements on issues for decisions.</P>
    <P>With regard to section 9 which provides for the optional appointment of worker directors to subsidiaries of companies, as the Minister admits some disappointment was expressed that this is being maintained on ministerial discretion.  I would like to ask why it was not possible to have agreement for the company and the union to opt in or out as best suited them. It has been suggested that some pretty robust lobbying went on behind the scenes in that event.</P>
    <P>Further, on section 10, I would like to remind the Minister that this section increases to four years the term of office of worker director members and replaces the provision of a three year term of office in the principal Act.  I would like to ask the Minister if he sees this provision being extended to the Telecommunications Act, 1983, which when set up provided for worker directors but catered for a term of office of three years only.  How does the Minister intend to deal with this matter?</P>
    <P>Finally, could I draw the Minister's attention to section 13 which amends, replaces and inserts certain interpretations in section 1 of the principal Act.  The definition of &ldquo;employee&rdquo; in the principal Act is amended to include part time staff working at least 18 hours a week.  I would like to suggest to the Minister that this unnecessary restriction causes me grave reservations, certainly about the 18 hour threshold.  I feel this threshold is unacceptable in general, but I would say that it is specifically unacceptable because it discriminates against women workers.  I question whether this section is included just because it has become a feature of legislation in a whole lot of other areas where I accept there would be financial or social welfare consequences or implications.  Is it really necessary here because these issues are not of consideration or implication?</P>
    <P>I suggest there is no rationale in this event because there are no such consequences. <Col N="1002" /> I propose that the determining qualification should be a contract of employment, regardless of the hours worked.  I suggest that, if you examine the statistics relating to the number of female workers in the work force who are temporary as against the male workers, you will accept that this provision of an 18 hour threshold treats women less favourably than men.  I will give an example.  The figure is 13,900 males regularly working part time as against 43,800 women.  I suggest that perhaps the Minister should examine this provision again more carefully and, at the same time, he might be moved to set a market for the need to increase the number of women at director level.  This could be done, in my opinion, by recommending that in the nomination and selection process of worker directors, or members of a board, regard should be had to the male-female balance.  I believe this could be done and it would be a legitimate criterion to use.</P>
    <P>Finally, I would like to say again that I welcome the Bill as a realistic move towards greater democracy in the work place.  I know it will change procedures and practices, but I trust that it will also contribute to changing outmoded and conservative attitudes which are still too prevalent in our society.  In the face of continually changing patterns and work relations in the modern industrial community, caution, tradition and fear can become blinkers which serve to inhibit progress and development.  I trust that workers in the various State enterprises will recognise what this Bill offers, and take advantage of all the opportunities it brings to allow them to become involved in the decision-making process at the enterprises in which they work.</P>
    <P>I trust, too, that management involved at all levels will have the necessary foresight and responsibility to see these initiatives in a positive light.  Their support is vital.  It goes without saying that, in the last analysis, the best guarantee of success and steady expansion of this concept is in the effective and meaningful contribution by those workers who now are members of the boards of their companies.</P>
    <Col N="1003" />
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not a contentious Bill.  I warmly welcome it.  I would like very briefly to make some observations on the general theme of worker participation.  For that we can look at European experience with different economic and social systems.  The experience elsewhere suggests that worker participation is, indeed, worthwhile, that it works and that it leads to an improvement in industrial relations. In that context I think one should make the point that the older autocratic ways of running a business have failed to draw out the energies and skills and potential of workers to anything like what is available if the conditions are right.</P>
      <P>Studies of better run businesses indicate that the way to release those energies and to provide greater satisfaction in the work place and to help in raising the level of productivity and efficiency is not by confrontation or recrimination but rather the emphasis is on putting the relationship on to a new basis which will involve not just management but all the workers in the enterprise in decision-making across the range of company activities. Such a change in outlook and attitude can only come about as a result of giving workers a real as opposed to a token say in making decisions.  Experience in other countries does, indeed, suggest that this type of real say will release energies and abilities which may be frustrated or not used otherwise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The original Worker Participation Act in 1977 was enacted in different economic times.  Those were the days of growth, compared with the more pressing and demanding times in which these State enterprises must operate today.  The aim of the original Act was to set up arrangements for board representation in a number of major State enterprises in line with developments in other European countries.  The initiative in introducing participation at this level was taken by the Government because it was considered that a legislative push was necessary to get the system into place.  Lower growth rates and intensive international competition for goods and services characterise the present time but, of <Col N="1004" /> course, it can be argued that the relevance of worker involvement, including board representation, is now more important than ever.</P>
    <P>The current financial stringency and the challenge of national recovery are making new and fresh demands on our State enterprises today, so that co-operation between management and workers in achieving enterprise objectives is particularly important at present.  Under the 1977 Act worker directors enjoyed the same status as other directors.  I think it is worth saying that again, in that the same rules of company law applied to them in respect of disclosure of interest, confidentiality and voting.</P>
    <P>This, in turn, raises the question as to whether worker participation can assist in job creation or contribute to it.  Are the benefits from board membership worth the costs in time and effort invested by both sides?  Can the advantages be quantified?  Unfortunately, I have to say that we do not have sufficient evidence to be sure that this is the way forward. Nonetheless, there are encourging signs that the board representation experiment has, indeed, worked.</P>
    <P>Preliminary research was conducted by Murphy and Walsh of the Irish Productivity Centre in 1980 and the results were published at that time.  This study reported on the attitudes of worker directors to a range of issues at the time of the first elections or shortly thereafter. Among the findings they reported were that the worker directors experienced little difficulty in fitting into their new roles; that support for them was forthcoming from other board members and from management and supervisors but rather less enthusiasm was found among trade union officials and shop stewards.</P>
    <P>The IPC study showed that trade union officials were concerned that the collective bargaining process should not be adversely affected.  Shop stewards felt that there was insufficient feedback from the worker directors.  The worker directors themselves, in the same study, showed concern about the need to develop sub-board structures to link them with their constituencies.  To the extent <Col N="1005" /> that the Bill before us will contribute, as it undoubtedly will, to improving communications between the board and lower levels of the organisation, then it is particularly welcome.</P>
    <P>The point I would make about the experience to date is that there is a need for a further study or an updating of the experience of worker directors and that such a study might be funded by the Department of Labour.  The findings should inform policy making that much better than is possible at present.</P>
    <P>I touched a moment ago on the institution of collective bargaining which is concerned with the direct negotiations between employers and trade union representatives on pay and conditions. Given the dominance of collective bargaining in this country it is not surprising that the IPC study in 1980 found a lack of enthusiasm by trade union officials and shop stewards for the worker director system.  Irish trade unions have, for many years, catered for worker interests through collective bargaining through this direct negotiation process with the emphasis on economic issues &mdash; pay and conditions &mdash; as opposed to other issues affecting the enterprise.</P>
    <P>Trade unions argue, with justification, that much has been achieved for workers through collective bargaining without having to rely on other forms of participation. For their part, trade union officials and shop stewards will continue to ensure that worker directors and sub-board structures will not conflict with traditional collective bargaining arrangements. It should also be pointed out that management, too, have long experience in negotiating with trade unions in the collective bargaining context.  The adversarial relationship which collective bargaining implies has been understood by both sides to exclude worker representation on the board.</P>
    <P>Over the years management have opposed worker representation at board level as they have viewed it as being incompatible with the collective bargaining process.  The traditional management argument has been that a conflict of interest is inevitable if workers <Col N="1006" /> are on the board which, in turn they argue, leads to ineffectiveness in decision-making at board level.  This obviously raises the question as to whether the fears of trade union officials as well as senior management have been justified by the experience of worker directors in State enterprises.  Trade union anxieties have been largely catered for in that trade union activists have typically been the successful candidates in the various worker director elections.  Moreover, most of those elected continue to hold some trade union office which, in turn, serves as an important link between worker directors and their trade unions.</P>
    <P>Like other sectors of the economy, the commercial semi-State enterprises have to work for economic viability.  This is never easy.  For several of these enterprises it is that much more difficult in the harsher economic climate of the late eighties.  Nonetheless, worker directors on boards have the potential to make a very special contribution.  From the evidence we have available, limited as it is, that is the case.  It must be rememberd that worker directors have probably more at stake in an enterprise than any other director.  They earn their livelihood from these enterprises.  They have a detailed knowledge of aspects of the working of these enterprises.  They have a very special interest in the success of the State enterprises where there are directors.  It is, therefore, up to the worker directors, together with other board members and managment, to move towards greater co-operation in the interest of overall enterprise success to their mutual advantage.</P>
    <P>With regard to the sub-board structures worker participation at board level is not, by itself, sufficient to ensure an extension of industrial democracy.  What is needed, of course &mdash; and the Bill addresses this &mdash; is an inter-related structure of participation at all levels of the enterprise.  A well developed structure below the board is clearly vital.  Experience elsewhere indicates that it is up to each company to work out its own programme for the extension of participation at various levels.  The Minister emphasised in his opening speech that the two <Col N="1007" /> sides should work out the arrangements best suited to their own organisation.</P>
    <P>The question is not so much to build upwards from the bottom or work down-wards from the top.  The task is rather to build on existing structures, so that a complete system evolves fitted to the particular needs of the company concerned. The provision, therefore, and the idea behind the Bill of flexibility, is praiseworthy and eminently sensible in this regard.</P>
    <P>One of the main objectives of the Bill before us is to facilitate the introduction of sub-board participation arrangements in a range of State enterprises, as I have said.  In this context I would like to compliment Fr. Tom Morrissey and the members of the Advisory Committee on Worker Participation, who produced their report in record time, and which has thrown considerable light on the subject of sub-board structures and on participation in general.</P>
    <P>In the past, unfortunately, there have been experiments with sub-board structures, such as work councils.  Too often, these councils dealt only in trivia.  A noted writer in the field said that their work was confined to discussing toilets and tea towels.  There is every prospect now that this legislative push will help the development of sub-board structures, that issues like company plans, manpower policy, budgets and so on will find their place in a serious way on to the agenda of the sub-board structures when they are put in place.</P>
    <P>It is clearly important before these arrangements are worked out that there should be full consultation between both sides.  In particular, I would urge that line management should have a substantial input at the design stage of these structures because they are the people who will be needed to actively involve themselves in the working and operation of these sub-board arrangements.  Trade unions for their part will want to see the sub-board structures to be founded on existing trade union structures.  It goes without saying, therefore, that those <Col N="1008" /> arrangements which complement collective bargaining rather than replacing it offer the best prospect for success in the Irish situation.  This should not, however, &mdash; I am now referring to the pre-occupation of the trade union representatives to ensure that it is built on trade union structures &mdash; exclude the right of management to communicate directly with their employees on various issues if they consider it necessary.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>People who care.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>This kind of dual communication may well be necessary to get the fullest understanding among the workforce and to underline the importance of full understanding of the company objectives by both.  In those enterprises where worker directors already exist, the same worker directors could play a very valuable role in advancing the establishment of sub-board structures precisely because they are on the board.</P>
      <P>Sub-board arrangements should enjoy a higher profile within the organisation and a greater degree of commitment from other board members because they will have the backing of worker directors. The problem with sub-board structures in the past is that there was not the commitment from the top to them.  Such a commitment from the top of the organisation should help to ensure that the sub-board arrangements are taken seriously by all concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 6 of the Bill outlines the essential features of the sub-board participative arrangements which will be drawn up jointly between the State company concerned and its employees.  These concern first, a regular exchange of views and information between management and employees concerning matters which are specified in the agreement; secondly, the giving in good time by management to employees of information about certain decisions which are liable to have a significant effect on employees' interests and finally, dissemination to all <Col N="1009" /> employees of information and views arising from the participative arrangements.</P>
    <P>I have been on successive Joint Committees on State-Sponsored Bodies.  We have examined these commercial semi-State bodies over the years.  One such body was Fóir Teoranta, on which we reported in 1981.  It became evident in the course of the evidence that we got from the top management and chairman of that company that those manufacturing companies that were in trouble &mdash; up to that point at any rate &mdash; who sought financial assistance made untold efforts not to disclose the plight of the company to anybody, not even their bankers.  The point I am making is that disclosure of information could make a very significant contribution to the rescue of companies.  The employees themselves are key stakeholders.  They have every reason to want the survival of companies, precisely because their livelihood depends on it.  Putting more emphasis on information disclosure and on informing employees in good time is to be highly commended and something that I hope will be implemented in practice when they are putting their participative arrangements in place.</P>
    <P>Detailed comment on other sections of the Bill can be left more appropriately to Committee Stage.  However, I wish to refer to section 13 which changes the definition of &ldquo;employee&rdquo; in the Principal Act to include part time staff.  Senator Fennell has referred to this.  There has to be some limit on hours and 18 hours is what is put forward here.  The need for part time workers arises for a number of reasons: there are cost considerations; new technology has made a significant impact on workforces and has led in turn to this evolution of part time workers.</P>
    <P>A number of studies have pointed to the evolution of a dual workforce in future.  It is envisaged that there will be a critical workforce or core group who will be responsible for carrying out the more specialised activities of the organisation. Side-by-side with this highly qualified, critical, workforce will be the peripheral workforce.  These peripheral workers will be working part time, or will <Col N="1010" /> be sub-contractors, or workers who are on fixed term contracts.  The number of part time workers in the Irish economy is growing, following the introduction of new technology and, indeed, following the shortage of full time employment. This section addresses this issue in a fair and legitimate way, in that it provides for board representation for part time workers, recognising the reality of this change in the composition of the workforce as between full time and part time people.  I welcome this particularly.</P>
    <P>I should like to turn briefly to the provision for worker directors.  Aer Rianta and the National Rehabilitation Board will now be permitted to proceed with their elections for worker directors.  I wish to comment on Aer Rianta, because I am familiar with the exceptional initiative which unions and management in that company have shown in identifying what participation is all about.  Their Industrial Democracy Council has addressed participative issues in the company for some time past.  A more recent development has been the formation of a joint working group of management and Industrial Democracy Council representatives to recommend future initiatives in the area of participation.  It has been stated company policy in Aer Rianta for several years past to encourage staff participation in the workplace and generally to promote an open style of management in conducting the affairs of the company. The purpose of the joint group is to examine the future possibilities for participation at below board level in Aer Rianta.  The Government initiative in the Bill will support the initiatives already taken in Aer Rianta, while the skill and experience gained by management and workers in the company to date will provide both with the ability to contribute to decision-making at various levels.</P>
    <P>I specifically want to put on the record the excellent practices in Aer Rianta by both management and trade unions in preparing for worker participation.  They have eagerly awaited the enactment of this legislation and their efforts in preparing in advance will serve them well <Col N="1011" /> when the board members are duly elected.</P>
    <P>One should not make too big a deal of the Bill and I do not think the Minister would do that either.  Initiatives at national level in the area of participation can only provide a framework for action on worker participation.  They are no substitute for the initiative and enthusiasm which management and workers in the State enterprises can themselves provide. These are the essential ingredients.  Joint initiatives at company level only succeed when management and employees become convinced of their ownership of the new development and the commitment to those structures and to participation then follows.</P>
    <P>Worker participation is, of course, no panacea.  We need to be realistic about what worker participation can achieve. Participation on its own is not a solution to job security or low productivity.  Progress in participative arrangements requires patience, time and discussion.  It is a matter of urgency, however, in the difficult economic environment in which enterprises operate today for management and workers to identify the common ground, as opposed to confrontation, between them and to take it from there.  Worker participation with the emphasis on co-operation should help to bring about a climate of trust which, if achieved, should make a significant contribution to the solution of the pressing problems facing the State enterprises concerned in the Bill.</P>
    <P>Genuine participative arrangements should enable management and workers to co-operate together to achieve greater productivity and prosperity for their enterprises.  I warmly welcome the Bill and congratulate the Minister on having it before us today.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I certainly do make a &ldquo;big deal&rdquo; about the Bill and I warmly welcome it.  I congratulate the Minister for bringing forward this legislation.  It is worthwhile putting on the record his own commitment to good industrial relations and fair and proper developments in the <Col N="1012" /> whole area of industrial relations.  He has shown that commitment, both in a physical way as well as in the legislative way.</P>
      <P>As I have stated, I welcome the Bill which is a good one.  It is positive legislation. I am happy with 90 per cent of it but I would say that it could go a bit further in various areas &mdash; I would always be saying that, anyway.  There is no such thing as perfect legislation&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It was you who said it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I am an honest person. I am aware of my own inadequacies in this area.  I am glad Senator Hillery made the point of worker involvement.  I will deal with the question of the flow of information later.  I have said time and again that nobody has a greater vested interest in the efficiency and in the proper running of a company than the workers involved in it.  For anyone to suggest at any time that workers would take a decision which would be bad for the company is incomprehensible to me.  I just cannot understand it.  I will deal with what I would consider to be a point of tension in a moment but certainly a worker has an investment in the company which he or she cannot walk away from &mdash; not in the way that the owner can, in the sense that the worker is selling his or her labour and depends for a living on getting paid for that labour at the end of every week, whereas the owner of the factory can perhaps liquidate, sell off and walk away with the profit.  It would be fair to say that in many ways &mdash; and looking at it from many different perspectives &mdash; the worker would have more of a vested interest in a properly run company or structure than the owner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are two things involved: the worker is interested in work and the owner is interested in making a profit.  If we are honest and reflect on and recognise those two points of view, then we come to what I consider the only point of conflict.  &ldquo;Conflict&rdquo; is, perhaps, the wrong word to use as we can look at it as &ldquo;tension&rdquo; in this case.  In other words, the worker is interested in continuing in <Col N="1013" /> employment and the owner is interested in continuing in profitability.  The good thing about those two objectives is that they can both be reached by going down the same road.</P>
    <P>One of the reasons this Bill can be so much welcomed in the national interest is that, if a factory owner, or the owner of a company, or the board of a company, realise that they can be more efficient by getting rid of a couple of hundred workers and if the worker directors on the board say: &ldquo;We are going to fight against that because we feel that efficiency must be balanced with the national need in terms of employment,&rdquo; the State and the nation are served in that way.  If, by putting those opposite arguments and through that tension of different points of view we find a middle line of progress the national interest is well served in that particular area.</P>
    <P>I regret that we have not yet seen in legislation or proposed legislation the extension of this concept into private industry, I recognise that it would not be proper to include it in this particular legislation but I am saying to the Minister that I urge that this be looked at and legislation be brought forward as quickly as possible.</P>
    <P>Senator Hillery referred to the problem that has come up time and time again in Fóir Teoranta, the idea of creating surprises for the workers.  There should be no surprises for the workers; they should know the state of their industry; they should know the state of their work area and they should know the problems. We can apply that to any place.  I have this great belief that if you put 15 people around a table and give them the same set of difficulties they will come very close to finding the same road to the solution whether they be directors, workers or whatever they are in the company.  We should have confidence in people and give them the information, seek their wisdom, seek their experience and put it all into the equation in order to find a solution.  That is the great positive thing about this legislation &mdash; that we are finding a way of tapping the experience and the objectives of the workers.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1014" /> I would also like to be associated with the remarks of the previous speakers who referred to the Report of the Advisory Committee on Worker Participation.  It is certainly a very useful document.  It is the groundwork on which this legislation is based.  It is the positive body of information on which we make our decisions about this area.  We should place on record our thanks to the people who participated in that.</P>
    <P>I would raise one point on that through you, a Chathaoirligh.  One of the recommendations of this report was for a special participation council and agency.  I would like to see that covered in the legislation and perhaps the Minister will respond at the end of this debate and say whether he would envisage that as new legislation or something which might be added to this or something which he will bring in separately or something to which he is opposed.  If he is opposed to it perhaps we will hear the reasons for that.  Apart from the reasons given here in the report itself in its favour, there is another reason.  When any new structure is set up, when any new area is being developed we need very much to share the experience of the participants.  The worker directors in Bord na Móna might have a completely different experience from the worker or other directors in Aer Lingus. It would be useful for them to meet to discuss and share ideas &mdash; I am not talking about discussing the affairs of the company; I am talking about the broad general terms and principles by which they work &mdash; and by sharing their various experiences and general difficulties in principle that they would then develop a consensus and maybe establish procedures which could be of use to people who could learn from the shared esperiences. It would be a very positive way forward.  I know that the Government are not over-enthusiastic about setting up any sort of councils of a national nature at the moment but that is another day's work.  Perhaps legislation could be introduced in that area at a later date.</P>
    <P>I hope I am misinterpreting and misreading Senator Hillery's speech when I get somehow from him the idea that the <Col N="1015" /> trade union movement and trade unions in general would be in any way supportive of inefficiency or slackness or low productivity. That is not what we stand for and certainly in my discussions with various unions about this legislation &mdash; I discussed it with the ICTU, with the Post and Telegraphs workers union and with worker directors themselves &mdash; and from my own experience I can assure the House that I totally disagree with such a suggestion.  I think we pull up slack and all of us have the same interest in doing that and therefore we stand for&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>When he reads the record the Senator will see that I implied no such claims in relation to trade union activity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the record will show that Senator Hillery gave the impression that in some way trade unions might be opposed to high productivity.  I think that will be quite clear in the nuances of what he said.  However, we will read the record and discuss it at a later date.  For the record, we are in favour of effective, tight participation and the highest levels of efficiency and productivity.</P>
      <P>It always worries me when I hear people talking about the problem of the trade union structure being too close to the structure of the company and that management should always retain the right to communicate directly with workers.  Those are words which we heard, I suppose, in the first place from Mr. Edwards and the coal board and from various other people over the last number of years.  It did not get anybody on any side anywhere.  Workers will choose like any other group the democratic structures which they want to be part of.  This particular Bill makes that very clear in its reference on a number of occasions to 15 per cent of the work force.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In fact, if anything, this Bill is weighted against people who would wish not to participate in trade unions.  I am saying, for the record, that they have allowed within this Bill workers to group outside trade unions and that where 15 per cent of <Col N="1016" /> them can get together they can nominate people for the elections.  I think there is enough of protection, if that is what Professor Hillery is referring to, or what the State want in this particular case.  I would, of course, differ entirely from that.  I would say that the best possible voice for the workers is their trade union, that this is the democratic structure that they choose and this is the structure by which they will indeed be represented.  I suppose any democratic structure is dependent on its efficiency in representing the common good while at the same time making sure that no offence is given and that in no way are the rights of the individuals or the minorities offended.  That is really the strength of the democratic structure and whether it be a national structure or trade union structure the same thing applies.</P>
    <P>It is imperative that the trade unions be involved in this.  I think the Minister would agree with me that the preparatory work done voluntarily in this area by the trade unions indicates their commitment. Certainly the example referred to of Aer Lingus is not the only one; this commitment has been shown all the way through.</P>
    <P>At this stage I would like to refer to the fantastic programme of education and training and experience being provided by the training section of the Irish Congress of Trade Unions for worker directors. Anybody participating in the boards of any of the State or semi-State industries would agree that this has been productive and positive and, certainly, in all our interests.</P>
    <P>I will be coming back to various areas like the part-time workers and the 18 hours which I have great difficulty with. I would say in passing with regard to the idea referred to by the previous speaker about the dual work force with the core of permanent workers and the outer area of part-time people, I would have a slightly different view on that.  What we need is to have a flexible work force so that people will work in different areas and when technology catches up with their own area, they can move on to another area.  It is wrong to suggest that <Col N="1017" /> instead of having full-time workers we would have part-time workers, because part-time means insecurity of tenure; it means insecurity with all the tension and the stress that go with that.  It is totally alien to the history of this country where we have fought for so long for security of tenure and security of employment <i>et cetera.</i>  I would disagree very much with Senator Hillery in that matter.</P>
    <P>The principal legislation as referred to by the Minister was the 1977 Worker Participation Act.  That was the Act which initially envisaged worker directors in semi-State companies.  That idea was developed over the years and extended.</P>
    <P>One of the difficulties which I will be referrring to and which the Minister has touched on in his speech has been the fact that in the intervening period, since 1977 and before this new proposed legislation of 1988, there was also the Posts and Telecommunications Act, 1983.  That Act dealt with the setting up of worker directors in those two companies, An Post and An Bord Telecom.  That has certainly raised a number of difficulties for us.</P>
    <P>One difficulty raised with me by the General Secretary of PTWU, David Begg, was the fact that under the Second Schedule of this Bill the Minister may add to or remove from the list of enterprises in Part III of the schedule.  It seems to include Telecom and An Post as ones that may be added to the present legislation.  I would like to have clarified whether or not that is proper in the context of the 1983 legislation, or whether some amending legislation needs to be introduced at that point.</P>
    <P>The 1983 Communication and Services Act which of course is nearly identical to the 1977 Act with minor changes in the area of election &mdash; I will refer to them again &mdash; needs to be addressed.  One of the difficulties with the legislation is that I believe it is incompatible with the 1983 Act.  Perhaps the Minister could explain this to us.  The Minister made reference to extending the period of office of the worker directors from three to four years. Does this apply to the people in An Post and in Telecom who are covered under <Col N="1018" /> the 1983 legislation?  Does it mean the Minister would be prepared to look reasonably at the question of amending that legislation as part of this legislation? I will be putting that forward.  I do not think there is any argument against having a uniform system through all the semi-State bodies in that it creates problems if one is going to be treated differently from all the others.  I think it is something that slipped through the net as we were going along and just needs tidying up.  I look forward to hearing the Minister's views on that.  No adequate reasons have been put forward for maintaing the difference.</P>
    <P>In that whole area one of the other difficulties that have arisen between the two pieces of legislation is that a number of anomalies will exist.  The first one is the different periods of office but there is also the area of running the elections. The returning officer has clear duties outlined in the new legislation, and rightly so.  They should also be extended to or included in the 1983 Act.  In other words, I think we should go for uniformity, even if only in the sense of the interpretation of the law because I can see some judge down the road in nine or ten years time comparing both pieces of legislation and trying to play one off against the other, or to interpret one by virtue of the experience of the other.  I want that problem to be addressed.</P>
    <P>I am referring to the date of nomination day, the amount of time people have to return completed ballot papers, that type of detail; it is really tidying up, housekeeping, but it should be done.  I agree that the enfranchising of subsidaries is important.  Again I would raise the question: will this also apply to An Post and An Bord Telecom because it would appear at the moment it does not? They are some of the areas with which have a difficulty and they are creating a difficulty for the worker directors in those companies.  I ask the Minister to consider that and to respond to it at the end of Second Stage and then we will consider whether or not amendments are necessary on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>Section 6 of the Bill deals with the <Col N="1019" /> provisions for and the terms of reference and the setting up of sub-board structures. There is one part of that which gives me some difficulty.  I am not saying I can propose an amendment to make it any tighter, but it is the use of the phrase &ldquo;in good time&rdquo;, in other words that information shall be given to workers in good time.  I would like to have on record exactly what that means.  I am not saying it is bad as it is written.  I cannot think of a better form of words.  The view and thinking behind it are right.  We believe workers should have the information and have it in &ldquo;good time&rdquo;, but what does that mean?  I raise it with the best will in the world.</P>
    <P>Going back to one of the points made by previous speakers, information is important but it is also important that information should find its own level among the workforce as they begin to assimilate it and begin to adjust and make judgments on it.  Sudden judgments and surprises are not helpful in this area.  I have some difficulty with that at the moment.  It seems a bit vague and weak, and perhaps we could tighten it up in some way or make it easier to define.</P>
    <P>Section 9 to me is the core of this legislation.  It provides for the setting up of the sub-board structures.  It deals with the participation of workers from subsidiaries of the main company in the election of worker directors.  This is essential. Plants and workplaces differ widely within a company geographically.  It is very important to have an input at various levels.  I take on board the point that it must be a very serious input and a serious level of decision making.  It is not just whether the canteen needs a coat of paint or the supply of toilet rolls is adequate etc.  Serious discussion is needed.  That can happen and will prove effective only when management accept, understand and are educated into an understanding that not all wisdom is invested purely in those who happen to be in management. Therefore, we have a clear duty in this area to provide education structures for people in management, not just for the <Col N="1020" /> workers, not just for the worker directors. Let us not for a minute consider that the only directors who need help and support in this field are the people who have just been elected as worker directors. Many who have been there for years could do with a lot of help and this might be the time to give it to them.</P>
    <P>The Minister dealt very subtly with the problems of enfranchising the subsidiaries. I read it once and I am not quite clear on what he said.  I suspect the Minister put it in a way that is not easy to interpret immediately, so I ask him to explain what precisely he means in terms of communicating with the Minister about any decision to give a franchise to the subsidiaries of a company.  He will have to explain to us how that works.  I suspect he believes correctly that there should be consultation on the issue.  It must mean, I presume, some form of amendment to the legislation.  Perhaps the Minister would indicate what that will mean.</P>
    <P>Basically the problem is that in many cases the subsidiaries could over-run the main companies in terms of the number of employees.  I am not saying that is a bad thing, but it could create problems. It could create a particular problem in a case where some of the subsidiaries are located outside the State.  I would like the Minister to address that point and explain to me whether that creates any difficulty in this legislation.  Are we talking about giving a vote to somebody perhaps who is working in Hong Kong in a subsidiary of an Irish semi-State company? I am not saying we have moved out to those far flung, distant shores yet, but one never knows.  Many of our semi-State companies have subsidiaries.</P>
    <P>Aer Lingus have a chain of hotels in the United States and we are now talking about electing a worker director to serve on the board of Aer Lingus who at the moment is working in a hotel in San Francisco. It seems to create some sort of logistical difficulties.  I would like to know how it will work logistically and how he envisages it working.  Are there any implications in the fact that we are talking about non-nationals as in this case?  I do <Col N="1021" /> not think it does, but I would like to have it spelled out.</P>
    <P>The system of the election of workers is the system of primaries in which people have to get a nomination before they get on the ballot paper.  It is one which I am very well aware of because we use it in our own union all the time.  Whereas some people consider it to be very cumbersome, I believe it is a very straight and honest way of setting up a ballot paper.  The system of election is important. It will have to be cleared and explained to workforces in work places how that is going to work.  That will take a fair amount of information and literature.</P>
    <P>Does section 9 create difficulties for the 1983 legislation?  Does it, in fact, allow the enfranchising of the workers in subsidiaries of An Post and Bord Telecom? I keep going back to these, not to harp on the issue but to point out that we must address this point, particularly when I am looking at what is happening with the similar services in Britain.  Whether it is already done or not they certainly have it organised in such a way that the parcel service is separate from the postal service and they are producing counterservices under different headings.  That would mean that they could well organise those as almost subsidiary companies.  I can see something similar happening here and it is important if these people should, in fact, be included.</P>
    <P>Mention has been made already of section 12 which deals with the disqualification of a worker director on resignation. I think the Minister was a bit flippant in dealing with this in his speech. He stated that it is reasonable to expect that worker directors should relinquish board membership when they leave the company.  I agree with that.  In general, the trade unions would agree with that as well.  It is also reasonable to expect that they would give up board membership when they retire or resign from the enterprise. I would certainly go along with that.  That is the whole spirit of the legislation. It was always meant to be people <Col N="1022" /> working who would represent people who were working.</P>
    <P>The difficulty here is that it could happen that a board could conspire to sack a worker and, in sacking a worker who happened to be a worker director, they would in effect be sacking a director. That sounds like a very devious operation but, at that level, devious things can happen very easily.  If the board are not happy with, let us say, one of the directors and they feel the only way to sort out the difficulty is to get rid of him or her for some period, they could, in fact, dismiss that person or arrange to have that person dismissed for whatever reason or on some pretext.  The difficulty about doing that is that there is no redress; there is no remedy for that worker director because, as the Minister will be aware, the Unfair Dismissals Act can only be initiated when the person has been dismissed.</P>
    <P>Therefore, a person who is dismissed from the company is immediately off the board and no matter what then takes place in terms of remedy, that person is off the board for a period of time.  It also raises the question of whether during the period when that person is seeking a remedy through the unfair dismissals legislation a new director would have to be elected.  A new director could be elected: the original director could win the case under the unfair dismissals legislation; and there would be no remedy because the second person would be duly and properly elected.  I have a real difficulty there.  I see a way around it.  I think that what we could do in that case is to provide that there should be a period when the person might be dismissed from the employment but, if an appeal is going on, he would continue as director for the period of the appeal, or for the period of taking it through the appropriate legislation. I raise that particular point because it is a situation that could be abused.  Therefore, if it could be abused &mdash; I am not saying that we should always legislate for the exceptional but this is a glaring case and I would be worried about it &mdash; we should legislate to prevent that. It is something that has been raised by many people.  The ICTU have raised it <Col N="1023" /> and the worker directors themselves have raised it in various forms.  I think we should address it.</P>
    <P>The wording in the Bill is that the vacant position will be deemed to have occurred on the day following the day on which the person ceases to be an employee of the body.  Let me say again that it is not that I am opposed to it, it is just that, in the case of a dismissal of a worker, in that narrow area of the dismissal of a worker who happened to be a worker director, it could get us into the difficulties I have talked about.  Certainly what I am proposing is that that person should continue to be a director pending the hearing of the case, if a case were to be taken under the Unfair Dismissals Act, and if a case was not taken we should have a time period during which a person would have to lodge the appeal.  That is in the legislation anyway but, perhaps, even a shorter period in this case to initiate the legislation could be allowed.</P>
    <P>Section 20 of the Bill causes some difficulty. It is the area which deals with the conflict of interests of worker directors. I read this and I re-read it and I have gone through it again.  There is something very patronising about this section which seems to say: &ldquo;You can be a director of a company.  We feel you have something to offer but we feel in particular areas there is going to be a conflict of interest&rdquo;. I really appeal to the Minister to respond to me and say what are the actual examples he can cite of conflict of interests.  I cannot think of any conflict of interests except the one to which I referred at the beginning where the board might feel they wanted to lay off workers in order to increase their profit and the worker directors would feel they would prefer to continue people in employment with a reduced profit.</P>
    <P>I am making the case purely from the point of view of the board.  I have said what the workers want and I have said what the other directors might want.  Is it not in the national interest that we should keep people in employment?  It is not also in the national interest that our industries should be profitable?  Therefore, is it either of these that we want?  We want a <Col N="1024" /> middle line there.  We will only get that middle line if all the arguments are brought into the discussion within the board structure.  I do not see that as a conflict of interest that would be envisaged here.  If the Minister can give me an example of where there would be a clear conflict of interest I will accept that, but I cannot think of anything.</P>
    <P>A director might be on the board of a semi-State and be a director of company C which is offering supply services, or selling goods, or marketing on behalf of company A.  That to me is a conflict of interests which could cause far more damage to the board than the worker who is seeking to protect some of the narrower interests of the workers in the work place.  We should tease that out a little further.</P>
    <P>I have asked people about it.  I have had talks with people as to whether it has been used because it is in the 1977 legislation.  I am talking about the section in the Principal Act which I am suggesting should be changed.  I used the rule of thumb on it.  Has this been abused at any stage?  Can I present examples of where worker directors were told in the past ten years &ldquo;that is a conflict of interest, you cannot vote on that.  Get out while we discuss it&rdquo;?  In fact, I can come up with one example only.  I am weakening my own case now and I hope the Minister does not take advantage of me.</P>
    <P>The only one I could find was where the chairperson decided that the worker/director should not have a vote because what they were discussing was the proposed increase in pay, or the wage claim of the workers.  I certainly would not agree that was a conflict of interest. I see nothing whatsoever wrong with the worker director being there and making the case to the board.  It is important for the board to have that information.  They can say at the end of the day: &ldquo;We have listened; we have heard what you have to say.  We do not agree with it and we are not going to give the rise.&rdquo;  This is something that can be dealt with in another forum rather than the board, but it is the right that should be there.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1025" /> This section could be used to discriminate against the contribution and vote or franchise of a worker director and it could be used now that we are expanding the area of sub-board activities. It becomes a difficulty now which we must address.  I find it impossible to understand what area of work of a company or board would not be of real interest to the worker directors and would, in fact, create a conflict of interest between the workers' interests and the company's interests.  It certainly is unacceptable that any of the matters being discussed about the company or the board should constitute a conflict of interests in the way some people have suggested worker directors cannot be trusted.  Of course they can be trusted.</P>
    <P>I note also that there are certain semi-State sectors such as the Central Bank, etc., which are not included in the legislation.  I know all the reasons for this and I will not comment except to say that at the highest level of this State, what is said at the table Ministers sit around once a week, is very often reported in the newspapers.  It is unfair to blame the workers for leaks.  We have seen time and time again information coming from companies which did not come from the worker directors.  As Senator Hillery said earlier, if it is information that is of value to the workers and is necessary for the workers, it is easily enough assessed.  If it will damage them if it becomes public, the worker directors will be the last people to leak information of that type. I am saying that for the record.  I am not making a case for the simple reason that I have not actually given it enough study. It would be quite helpful in the rarefied atmosphere of the Central Bank to get some of the workforce in there to consider what exactly they are talking about in lay person's terminology.  That could be useful.</P>
    <P>Section 13 of the Bill refers to section 1 of the Principal Act and the definition of an employee.  Every speaker so far has referred to that matter.  While Senator Hillery was absent I made it clear that I did not accept what he said about the <Col N="1026" /> great need in the future of the dual role workers.  I am quite aware of what he is talking about and I have seen the diagrams of the different types of companies and the different elements and satellites, etc. but I do not agree with it.  We need to look towards a more flexible workforce, to bear in mind changing technology and to say to a worker at age 20; &ldquo;The job you are doing today will not be necessary at age 30&rdquo;.  Let us start by knowing that so we will also plug into our system a system of re-education and retraining at age 29 so that at age 30, when this company has progressed into new areas, as it will with worker directors, you will be able to take over new areas of work.  I object to changing permanent employment to part-time or temporary employment.  It creates an unnecessary insecurity of tenure.</P>
    <P>There is a difference of principle involved.  I am not contradicting what was said by any previous speaker.  I am saying that we should be going in a different direction.  The work I am talking about here is the word &ldquo;permanent&rdquo;.  The question has come up about giving the vote in the election of worker directors to workers who are working in the company for 18 hours per week or longer.  I am certain Senator Fennell is right and the only reason 18 hours was chosen is that that is the figure which has been used in so much of the labour legislation which has, in fact, excluded workers from their rights.  At a time when more and more of the workforce is working in a part time and temporary capacity, we should be conscious of and sensitive to their needs and rights.</P>
    <P>When discussing labour legislation we should bear in mind and always take cognisance of the fact that there are now huge numbers of workers in part time employment whether we like it or not and I do not like it.  Because they are in part time employment is not an argument for excluding them and the Minister has not given the case for excluding them. Perhaps there is a case, but I do not see it.  If we were to change the number of hours to 17 I do not see that it would make any great difference.  I do not know <Col N="1027" /> why 18 hours was picked.  I do not intend to suggest a number because the hours of work change from place to place but I will put a condition on it.  I am not saying anybody who happens to be in the work-place on the day the vote is taken should have a vote.  I am proposing that any permanent employee, whether he is working ten, 40 or 60 hours a week &mdash; if he is permanent in the company he has something to offer &mdash; should be represented and should have a vote.</P>
    <P>Let us leave the hours aside and look at the matter from a different point of view.  If the worker is a permanent worker in the company, perhaps part time but in so far as he is attending work week after week, this person should have a vote and should be allowed to participate in the election of the worker directors.</P>
    <P>The point that strikes me &mdash; and I have discussed this matter with ICTU and the various unions, and it is also a point that has been made very forcibly to me by members of the women's committee of ICTU &mdash; is that with the huge number of women workers working part time there is a certain inequity between the sexes.  I am not saying it is there deliberately, but it is there by virtue of the way things are. It is something that is against women's participation in industry.  That is another reason the matter should be looked at in a different way.  We are talking about permanent employees but many part time employees happen to be women and, in this sense, let us take a step towards equality and bring them into the net.  We should bring them under the umbrella of labour legislation in this area and under the umbrella of worker participation and democratic structures which produce worker directors.  This group of workers who are now left without the protection of labour legislation, which is bad enough, should not also be left without representation by the worker directors.  I am not saying the worker directors would not represent their interests, having been elected, but they should also have a vote in that election.</P>
    <P>There are no financial implications that <Col N="1028" /> I can think of.  It will just mean a couple of extra ballot papers.  If the people are on the books and in permanent employment it does not create a difficulty.  If it does create a difficulty we should hear about it.  I am making the case to forget about the number of hours and to talk about permanent employees.</P>
    <P>There is a problem, in section 21 of the principal Act, with the appointment of elected worker directors by the Minister after the election.  The election takes place and then the Minister makes the appointment.  There is a lacuna there which is unnecessary and which should be filled by legislation.  There should not be any gap.  It has led to confusion and difficulties.  As far as I know &mdash; and again I stand to be corrected on this because I did not check it out in the last number of days &mdash; there is one instance of that at the moment in B &amp; I who are at a very critical time in terms of board meetings and meetings at which workers would like to be represented.  If the worker directors have not been appointed in the last period, that is scandalous.  They should be there.  It is a matter of tidying up the legislation so that when a seat is vacated for whatever reason &mdash; there are a number of ways in which it could happen under the legislation &mdash; we should seek to have that seat filled as soon as possible. I use the words &ldquo;as soon as possible&rdquo; wisely because I am not saying you can fill them the following day.  Seats can be vacated suddenly for many reasons like death or somebody changing employment very quickly.  I am not saying seats can be filled in all cases without leaving a gap.  In the case of a retirement, the person can be replaced without having a gap in the representation whereas in the case of somebody leaving suddenly without notice it means that we need to set the machinery in operation straight away.</P>
    <P>I would like the Minister's views on one point.  When filling a vacancy from the electoral list, I presume the highest person on the list who did not get elected will be the person who will fill the vacancy in that instance.  That of course creates a difficulty for many of the groups who would put forward one person.  In trying <Col N="1029" /> to operate the PR system they would lose representation.  I have mixed views on that.  I have thought about it and about the interests involved and the interests of democracy and I am not sure if there is a resolution to it, but I would like to hear the Minister's views.  I notice he did not deal with it in his opening statement and perhaps he might come back to it at another time.</P>
    <P>I have dealt with two areas: the filling of a casual vacancy and appointed people after the election.  I would like those two areas to be addressed by the Minister to see whether they should be tied into legislation and whether a certain number of days or weeks should elapse following an election, which I presume would allow for appeals against the election, before the person would be appointed.  There are other more detailed areas which I wish to address but the Second Stage of the Bill is not the appropriate place to do that.  I will listen to the Minister's response to the general issues and then consider what amendments to put forward for Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>I will finish as I began by putting it on record that the Minister for Labour has certainly shown himself to be committed in this area.  I have many difficulties with the way Governments operate and in particular with the policies of this Government which I have been loud in articulating and voicing whenever I got the opportunity.  In this legislation the Minister for Labour has shown his own personal commitment to improvements in the areas of industrial relations, to an improvement in the participation of workers in industry and, indeed, to taking a step which is positive and progressive and which will take us very far forward in a way that has been proven to be effective in many other countries.</P>
    <P>I am glad the Minister, in all his dealings with problems in industry, has recognised the role of trade unions.  He knows that in countries where the trade union movement have worked closely with the Government &mdash; I am talking here of the Government and the trade union movement having had serious negotiations over the past number of months &mdash; negotiations <Col N="1030" /> have been fruitful.  He will see that it is important to have the trade unions always involved, always referred to and always included in the discussions and in any negotiations in this area. People in the trade union movement who have expertise in this area are always willing, as the Minister will confirm, to give of their time, of their expertise and of their energy.  I thank the Minister for introducing this legislation.  I will certainly be supporting it strongly and I will be putting forward minor changes as we go along.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I call Senator John Robb.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnRobb" hpid="Mr. Robb Mr. Robb">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robb</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Senator Ferris may have some difficulty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I have.  I will try to finish as quickly as possible because the next motion is to be taken at 6.30 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnRobb" hpid="Mr. Robb Mr. Robb">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robb</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that in order, a Leas-Chathaoirleach?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I call Senator Ferris.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Robb for allowing me to contribute at this stage. Obviously Senator O'Toole and I have been briefed by the same source and that will be of some help in that my remarks will not be as extensive as his.  The Irish Congress of Trade Unions have obviously made a submission to Senator O'Toole as well as to me and he has covered some of the ground which I wanted to cover.  I would welcome the Minister's response to the specifics in various sections of the Bill.  It would be remiss of me if I did not welcome the fact that the Minister has brought in the legislation.  Even though it differs from that of his predecessor and my colleague, Deputy Ruairí Quinn, it covers much of the areas we had hoped it would cover.  It follows from the report which was made to the Minister by the excellent Advisory Committee on <Col N="1031" /> Worker Participation.  Perhaps the Minister, in the generous response which I know he will give, will tell us, as a progressive Minister which we all know he is, his real views on the actual conclusions and recommendations the review group and advisory committee submitted to his predecessor, particularly in the area of the extension to the private sector of worker participation and their rights. They also recommended the establishment of a council on employee participation with functions as outlined in their report.  The Minister's response is eagerly awaited by everybody in the trade union movement as to whether he agrees with the principle of involving workers in the whole workforce area, whether in the private or the public sector.  It is not an ideological but a very fundamental comment that will be eagerly awaited from the Minister.</P>
      <P>This Bill deals with a number of companies in the State sector and, as has been mentioned, they are outlined on page 17. Even though Senator O'Toole was aware of the reasons for excluding some financial institutions, perhaps the Minister would be forthcoming and tell us why he excluded financial institutions such as the Central Bank and Irish Life, areas where financial decisions are being made and where we contend, for a labour and a trade union point of view, worker participation would be of benefit to the nation and certainly to the company.  We were disappointed that those institutions were excluded.  The Minister also excluded RTE, VHI, Bord Gáis and Irish Steel, the kind of companies that are dynamic and successful and would benefit from this whole concept.  I know the legislation gives the Minister power to add to the list of companies and I hope he will use that power.  I will have some comments to make on his powers to remove some companies because that would be against the principle of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to make various comments dealing with some of the concerns of the Congress of Trade Union people I spoke to and worker directors.  On the question of the liberal interpretation of a good <Col N="1032" /> length of time, the workers would like to have adequate time in which they can consider proposals which emanate from management in advance of the board meeting.  These would involve areas of finance, staff changes, development of the company, planning, rationalisation and all areas in which workers may need to consult with their peers who have elected them.  The management might think two days sufficient but a worker director might need a month and therefore, the Minister will have to be more specific.  I do not think the word &ldquo;adequate&rdquo; is sufficient.  It is too weak and the Minister should see if there is some way he can strengthen the wording in that section.  The wording in section 6 is also a bit weak and perhaps we could have the Minister's views on how we could strengthen it.</P>
    <P>I am concerned about section 9 and the power to extend worker participation. That seems like an excellent thing to do but the Irish Congress of Trade Unions have made other suggestions in this regard.  Section 9 refers to Aer Lingus and the Minister has indicated that this is an area where a problem arises.  Whatever about Tokyo, we know that Aer Lingus, an Irish national flag-carrying company, have a tremendous involvement in the United States.  The trade union movement are worried that workers outside the jurisdiction, particularly in the United States, could have a vote in management decisions in their company.  We are concerned about this, as are Congress and the Minister.  Perhaps the Minister might define whether he will confine voting rights for workers in companies with outside subsidiaries to within the EC in that concept.  If he did that he would probably conform to EC law and he would have our support in doing so.  It is an area of concern for all of us.  I welcome the fact that the Minister mentioned it in his Second Stage speech and that he has agreed to look at it before we get down to the nitty-gritty of Committee Stage and Report Stage where we will discuss section 9 and how it will affect the workers in Aer Lingus.  There is a central representative council in Aer Lingus, a <Col N="1033" /> fairly powerful body, and we would like to have their consent and agreement to this legislation.</P>
    <P>We are also concerned about the definition of &ldquo;employees&rdquo; for voting purposes under section 13.  A number of hours has been mentioned which seems to be unacceptable.  I accept Senator O'Toole's point that, if the person is permanent in a company, irrespective of the number of hours he works, he should have voting rights to elect people to represent him as worker directors on a board.  Decisions would then be made which would involve all the employees of the company.  The vested interest of a worker director was mentioned.</P>
    <P>I know from experience in my own county, in Bord na Móna and in Comhlucht Siúicre Éireann Teoranta, that the company, in making decisions which involved the future of employees, whether on pay agreements, productivity agreements or otherwise, asked employees not to participate.  They were not privy to information that was released to other directors in advance of some of these decisions, based on the fact that the chairman of the day of the company interpreted this special interest clause as referring to worker directors.  I know the Minister has the spirit of this Act at heart and that he will not be afraid to define the &ldquo;vested interest&rdquo; clause.  Certainly all of us have vested interests, as members of local authorities, in planning and if outside financial interests are concerned then they have a vested interest also. Surely if we believe in the concept of the election of worker directors to sit on boards then all worker directors should have a say in the decisions of the board. I hope the Minister will confirm that when dealing with this section.</P>
    <P>I am also interested in another area which has not been mentioned by previous speakers and that is the situation that has arisen <i>vis-á-vis</i> the board of NET.  About two years ago discussions took place between the then board of NET and ICI and a joint venture project was set up of which NET has a 51 per cent interest and ICI 49 per cent.  The worker directors on the board of NET <Col N="1034" /> are precluded from decision making. There are no worker directors involved. The normal work which is applicable to worker directors has been interfered with by the new IFI board.  Facilities such as cabinets and telephones, have been removed from the worker directors.  The number of days that they can spend at board meetings which are relevant to the IFI enterprise but are only discussed at NET board meetings has been curtailed. The new directors of IFI have precluded board members from participating fully as they have done in the past and have reduced the number of days that they can take off to attend board meetings.  That is contrary to the whole spirit of what was confirmed in a letter from the Department of Industry and Commerce in January to the new board members of NET. I will put on the record that the Minister for Industry and Commerce informed the worker directors that he had signed the warrant appointing them as directors with effect from 21 December 1987 and sent them a copy of the warrant.</P>
    <P>The conditions which apply to directors of the company are contained in the relevant provisions of the articles of association of the company.  In particular the following terms apply.  &ldquo;As much time shall be devoted by each director to the performance of his duties as may be necessary for the proper and efficient discharge of those duties&rdquo;.  That would have been acceptable in the past with the board of NET but now the new board of IFI have put question marks on the number of days allowed for meetings and on whether the worker directors would have the day before the meeting to make preparations. Certainly they have excluded the day after the meeting which was used as a day for reporting &mdash; it is called a communications procedure &mdash; a procedure of reporting back to the shop stewards decisions that were made at the board meeting which were relevant to the terms of employment or otherwise.  The new board of IFI do not allow that day off anymore.  One of these worker directors who happens to be the chairman of the whole national worker directors group has been excluded from carrying out his <Col N="1035" /> duties as a chairman of the whole group and also, as a worker director in NET, from participating in this follow through. That is against the whole spirit of the Worker Participation Act, 1977.</P>
    <P>Perhaps the Minister might use his influence with the new board of IFI which, I think, specified that, as a new joint venture project, they did not want worker participation.  I thought that NET, with 51 per cent and the majority of the new company, would ensure that their worker directors should be adequately represented at all meetings relevant to the functions of IFI but apparently that is not the case.  I am putting this matter to the Minister in the House in the hope that it will bring to the attention of the Board the fact that worker directors are being denied some of the facilities they had in the past.  This could mitigate against the co-operation of the trade unions and other people in the future in what might be considered joint venture projects under the National Development Corporation or any other State agency that we would put in place to try to stimulate the public and the private sector to work together.  If this concept of worker participation is denied in that new development then that would be a backward step in industrial development.</P>
    <P>A letter was sent to all the staff in Irish fertilisers industries, signed by Mr. Jago, the managing director, in which he confirmed that they would have all the normal facilities that are available.  He said that is essential for the future viability of the business.  He also said the new company will have a broad range of products, strong market position, <i>et cetera.</i> He confirmed in that letter that the staff would have the same employment opportunities as existed elsewhere and that they would automatically have the same rights and so on as a new company.  The worker directors, although they had the same terms of employment, because of their involvement in the old NET enterprise were precluded from carrying on their duties.  They have asked the company for a specific response in various <Col N="1036" /> areas but that has not been forthcoming. The Minister should address that problem.</P>
    <P>I will deal briefly with the question of the Minister's right under this legislation to add to or take from the list of companies. The Second Schedule, Part II, subsection (2) (a) states:</P>
    <P>Subject to subsection (3) of this section, the Minister may by order amend&mdash; (a)</P>
    <P>the First Schedule (as amended by subsection (1) of this section) to the Principal Act by&mdash;</P>
    <P>(i) adding or deleting one or more bodies to or from, as the case may be, the list of bodies contained in Part I or Part II thereof,</P>
    <P>I believe it will be the Minister's philosophy to add companies to this list that has been circulated but I would have the gravest reservations about giving some successor of his in the future the power to delete any number of companies that he saw fit without recourse back to us. I would prefer if this section gave the Minister the power to add more companies and certainly we would all be in favour of that.  The Minister should not have the power by legislation to remove names of companies because then the whole concept of what we are doing is questioned.  Some Minister in the future &mdash; not the present Minister because he is progressive &mdash; might use this power against the spirit of the Act.  We will be looking for the Minister's advice on this matter and maybe assist him by putting down a suitable amendment to remove various words, but I would prefer if that kind of initiative were taken by the Minister.</P>
    <P>There is the question of the time factor between the outgoing directors and the incoming directors who have been formally elected but have not been formally appointed by the Minister.  We feel that there should be no time lapse, that the outgoing members should continue in position as worker directors until such time as the new directors take up occupation. Otherwise there could be a period <Col N="1037" /> in which no worker director would be represented at board level.  The Minister of the day might not have had time to make the order appointing the new member elected.  We want a continuation of service of worker directors in all of these companies.  If there is an election held to replace them we contend that the existing worker directors should continue in office until such time as the new worker director is appointed by the Minister.</P>
    <P>I want to thank the Minister for having introduced the Bill.  I hope he will be forthcoming in his amendment in order to tighten up some of the sections worrying people directly involved in the legislation and whose co-operation will be needed to render the provisions as effective as possible in the future.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Education Policy:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Education Policy: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I remind Senator O'Shea that, as proposed, he has 15 minutes and each subsequent speaker will have ten minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianOShea" hpid="Mr. O'Shea Mr. O'Shea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Shea</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann&mdash;</P>
      <P>(i)  aware that the Minister for Education and the Government have made one of the most profoundly erroneous and damaging policy decisions in the development of first level education in the history of our country in relation to the pupil-teacher ratio at primary level; and conscious that the Minister has seriously under-estimated the amount of hardship and disadvantage that her Circular Letter 20/87 will cause; and mindful of the impact on social justice and future economic, social and cultural development of such a severe attack on primary education, calls on the Minister to cause the Circular to be withdrawn, and further calls on the Government to make a full and detailed statement immediately in connection with the proposed review of the primary education system;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1038" /> (ii)  conscious of the particular attack on the vocational sector represented by the cuts inflicted on the sector by the Minister for Education and the Government; noting in particular, the increase in the pupil-teacher ratio from a band of 17-19 to 20 to 1 in the vocational sector and an increase from 19 to 1 to 20 to 1 in the community and comprehensive sector with a reduction of 10 per cent in the teaching members; further, noting the halting of the building programme and conscious of the disproportionate share of the remedial teaching and special provision for the disadvantaged, carried by the vocational sector; calls for the rejection and withdrawal of the proposals of the Minister and the Government for the sector.</P>
    <P>The motion deals, first, with primary education and second, with vocational education. At the outset I should like to read from the <i>Programme for National Recovery</i>, the first section from the introduction:</P>
    <P>The Government, the ICTU, the FUE, the CII, the CIF, the IFA, Macra na Feirme and the ICOS, conscious of the grave state of our economy and social life, have agreed on this programme to seek to regenerate our economy and improve the social equity of our society through their combined efforts.</P>
    <P>Paragraphs 15, 16 and 17 of the education section which appear later in the document read:</P>
    <P>15.  The Government recognise the importance of the educational system in the promotion of equity in society and will ensure, in implementing whatever adjustments are necessary in that sector because of financial considerations, that the burden of adjustment does not fall on the disadvantaged.</P>
    <P>16.  There is a range of measures in place to assist disadvantaged groups. There is also considerable Exchequer <Col N="1039" /> support for travellers and the mentally and physically handicapped.  Special attention will be given to identifying those with special needs and to provide measures designed to help these groups achieve their full potential.</P>
    <P>17.  The Government will continue to encourage and foster the participation of the disadvantaged at all levels of education.  A particular area of focus will be to encourage more second-level pupils to complete the senior cycle.  It is considered that this will be a key factor in encouraging more working class children to advance to third-level education.</P>
    <P>Those are very laudable and praiseworthy aspirations enunciated in the <i>Programme for National Recovery.</i>  Certainly the Labour Party would have no problem whatsoever in supporting them.  The whole question of access to education in a truly equitable and universal way is central to all that the Labour Party stand for.  Unfortunately, the reality between the aspirations which I have just read and what the Government propose constitutes the problem.</P>
    <P>The essence of this motion this evening is to combat the wrecking of the primary and vocational sectors.  Primary is the sector accessible to all children of the nation.  The vocational sector caters for children of all abilities, in particular for the disadvantaged.  These two sectors have been singled out for a particularly devastating attack.  Regarding the primary sector, the Government have responded to the nationwide protest from all those involved in primary education. I believe the nationwide protest of parents in particular brought this about. The Taoiseach has announced the establishment of the primary education review body, the structure of which reflects the various interests in primary education. The INTO, of which I am a member, are keen to take part in this review. However, there is an inherent problem.</P>
    <P>In a statement issued by the Government on 1 December last under the heading <i>Primary Quota Review Committee</i> it <Col N="1040" /> was stated that no change under the terms of circular 20/87 would take place before the end of the school year, in June 1988, and that notices arising from that circular were suspended.  The statement also announced that schools which, in the ordinary course of events, would be entitled to make appointments under the normal schedules, may continue to do so. Department of Education Circular 24/87 formally set out that information. However, it has now transpired that these appointments are being sanctioned by the Department of Education on a temporary basis only.  This is in contradiction of the previous undertakings given.  The Department of Education are now stating that such appointments will be on a temporary basis pending consideration by the Primary Quota Review Committee.  This is a somewhat unusual animal, and rather difficult to identify.</P>
    <P>It was suggested previously that this committee should consist of two INTO representatives, two management representatives and two representatives of the Department of Education.  No INTO or management representative has offered for membership of the committee. In fact, there is no such committee. There is a clear breach of the Minister's undertaking and of the precise terms of Circular 24/87.  The Government are renaging on their commitments.</P>
    <P>The impression was created by the Government, and was endorsed in writing, that no changes under the terms of Circular 20/87 would come into effect before June 1988.  I call on the Minister to put into effect the terms of Circular 24/87 in all its aspects.  If implemented Circular 20/87 would result in the suppression of 2,000 teaching posts.  Let us stress here that we are not talking about teachers losing jobs.  We are talking about pupils losing teachers.</P>
    <P>As a national teacher at present on leave of absence I have had 20 years experience in national schools.  I know, for instance, that we have the largest average class size in Europe.  In the situation that would evolve we would have larger class sizes and many more split classes.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1041" /> Something that needs to be taken on board as well is that, in quite a few of our urban schools where split classes are not a feature at present, such split classes would undoubtedly become a much more notable feature of our schools.  Against all this background it is disadvantaged pupils who will suffer most.  Under the terms of Circular 20/87 the system would further disadvantage the already disadvantaged at the very primary or foundation level.  I must refer again to the education aspirations contained in the <i>Programme for National Recovery</i> and to Circular 20/87.  They are absolutely and utterly incompatible.</P>
    <P>A further point which must be made here is that gifted children would not be brought to their full potential either in a Circular 20/87 scenario.  Teachers will experience a lot more strain and stress dealing with the middle stratum of the class, dealing with the disadvantaged pupils.  Indeed the extra work undertaken by teachers, which has always been one of the most striking features of our educational system, where brighter pupils are brought along by such extra work on the part of teachers in the classroom, will be greatly diminished.  As a nation, if we are not doing the very best for our gifted people, those same people will not make their fullest possible input into solving the huge problems we face today.</P>
    <P>I will move on now to the proposed cuts in the vocational sector.  If Circular 20/87 is to be implemented these cuts will further compound the problems of disadvantaged children who have been severly damaged already at foundation level.</P>
    <P>The argument of bringing the pupil/teacher ratio in vocational schools in line with secondary schools sounds plausible on the surface but it should be remembered that we are not comparing like with like.  The vocational sector provides second-level education for children of all abilities and has a much higher proportion of disadvantaged pupils than the secondary sector.  Vocational schools provide practical subjects such as woodwork, metalwork, building construction and home economics which, of their very <Col N="1042" /> nature, require more space, more individual contact between teacher and pupil and, consequently, a lower pupil/teacher ratio.  Previous cuts that have been introduced have caused already a move from the practical to the academic in schools of my acquaintance.  As a member of two VECs and of the board of management of a community college I have had some experience in this area.  I have seen this move away from practical subjects to academic ones as being to the detriment of disadvantaged pupils.</P>
    <P>Another feature of the cuts at vocational level would be that remedial teachers &mdash; who cater in the main for those with literacy difficulties &mdash; would be going back into mainstream teaching, again very much to the disadvantage of the disadvantaged.  The problem which arises for smaller vocational schools countrywide is that, if the cuts are effected, if the pupil/teacher ratio in vocational schools is brought up to 20:1, the range of subjects on offer at senior cycle will be much diminished. This will have an effect on the intake at junior cycle and, at the end of the day, may very well place the viability of such schools at risk.</P>
    <P>The community college of which I am a member of the management board started in the early seventies in spare rooms in the local national school and local scout hall.  That school at present caters for the disadvantaged right through to offering seven honours subjects at leaving certificate.  The impact of the cuts on this school would be devastating inasmuch as subjects such as German, French and Physics as honours leaving certificate subjects would be placed at risk.  Bearing in mind the promotion of the teaching of German by the Department and all that that offers in terms of employment potential for young people, such cuts are very regrettable.</P>
    <P>At the other end there is the risk of the provision for remedial teachers being diminished also.  There is also a problem <i>vis-á-vis</i> practical subjects.  The school has absorbed cuts heretofore.  For instance, the length of the classroom session has been shortened.  The school day <Col N="1043" /> has been shortened.  The problems arising from implementation of this circular can be dealt with in a number of ways.  But, if we are talking about shortening class periods, in terms of shortening the school day, then that is indeed a very regrettable road to be travelling.</P>
    <P>The Labour Party is concerned first and foremost with the whole area of access, particularly equitable access, to education. As was enunciated in the <i>Programme for National Recovery</i> we want to see more and more disadvantaged children progressing through second level education into third level.  Present Government proposals are particularly regrettable when one remembers that a Minister of this Government, Deputy John Wilson, when Minister for Education, reduced the pupil/teacher ratio in vocational schools to 16:5.  That same Fianna Fáil Party, now in Government, are in the business of bringing that pupil/teacher ratio up to 20:1.  We are totally opposed to what is proposed and reject the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the motion seconded?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion and will speak to it at this point if that is in order.</P>
      <P>My colleague, Senator O'Shea, in proposing the motion and as a teacher, has dealt with the effects of implementation of the proposals by the Minister's Department. I do not intend to cover the same ground.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This motion has been tabled as a result of what I might describe as the fiasco in another place before Christmas on a similar motion on behalf of our party. Had the spirit of that earlier motion been accepted by all the other political parties, with the exception of the Government party, it could have brought to an end this dilemma of whether the infamous Circular 20/87 had been withdrawn.  We had put down a responsible amendment to the Fine Gael motion to the effect that if that circular was withdrawn we would ask all other parties to join with the <Col N="1044" /> Government in seeking a solution to the problem in the primary sector in particular.</P>
    <P>Our efforts proved to be unsuccessful, all the motions cancelling one another out.  At later stages in the debate and outside of the House the Taoiseach and the Minister for Education decided to have a review carried out, postponing a decision thereon until September.</P>
    <P>All of the schools in my constituency &mdash; the same as that of the Minister of State present, are now in the unhappy position that they do not know whether they are coming or going.  The are afraid that in September &mdash; when all the schools will be closed &mdash; the provisions of circular 20/87 or its successor will come into operation. They fear that teacheres will be lost in Golden, Thomastown, Cashel, Cahir, Rosegreen and Tipperary town.  I have attended schools in all of these places.  I know that the Minister present has attended some.  This is the record put to us on those occasions.  Indeed the statistics to back up such record without any brief being held political or otherwise on the part of the people who advance them. Many of the teachers publicly identified themselves as being supporters of the Government party but contended that from an educational point of view the proposals were inoperable.  They described the proposals in various derogatory ways at public meetings.  I have never seen teachers and parents in this whole area of the primary sector &mdash; which touches all of our families &mdash; so incensed.  It must be remembered that all our children receive primary education. This motion affords the Minister an opportunity to say categorically now in this House &mdash; where there is not the same political hype as there is in the other House &mdash; whether Circular 20/87 or its successor is withdrawn.  Are we now discussing realistically with parents and teachers proposals that might overcome some of the Government's financial difficulties?</P>
    <P>In the time remaining to me I want to deal with the vocational sector.  I was a member of a VEC for many years until the Minister's party decided to remove <Col N="1045" /> me from that body.  Apart from that stroke, I made the contribution I could to the vocational sector.  I might add that I am a product of the vocational sector, which is possibly an indication of its importance.  Certainly I consider the vocational sector to be an important one. I know from briefings I have had with the remaining Labour Party members on the VEC in South Tipperary and from the document entitled <i>IVEA Information</i> published in December last by the Irish Vocational Education Association what these education cuts will mean in this sector.  In that document they say:</P>
    <P>Educational cuts have continued unabated in the vocational sector since 1983.  Budgets have been drastically reduced, class sizes have increased and jobs have been lost.  VEC second level schools, while representing only 25 per cent of second level provision, are being forced to carry almost 100 per cent of the cuts at second level.</P>
    <P>That is a spectacular statement emanating from a responsible association &mdash; that the VECs, although they only deal with 25 per cent of that sector are expected to carry almost 100 per cent of the total cuts by the Government at second-level education.</P>
    <P>I might refer again to south Tipperary. There is a vocational school in the Minister's town of Cashel.  We are hoping to replace it in Clonmel, where there is a new school; in Cahir, where there is a proposal for a school, with an existing one; in Cappawhite where there is a small school really under threat; in Tipperary town, in Killenaule and in Carrick-on-Suir. All of those schools were represented in Athlone on Saturday last.  I should imagine the town of the Minister for Education, Deputy O'Rourke was chosen deliberately to bring home to her, on her doorstep, the absolute impossibility &mdash; at vocational level &mdash; of being able to implement some of her departmental proposals.  To demonstrate how these proposed cuts will affect us in Tipperary, in particular, I would have to cite the experience of a representative school there.  In that school in 1981 or 1982 the <Col N="1046" /> staff allocation to service 330 students amounted to just over 23 teachers.  In 1987-88 with an enrolment of 390 students, the allocation would constitute a small increase but, with those additional students, which mean a reduction in teachers; that typical school would lose up to four teachers.  This would lead to larger classes, restriction on or no choice of subjects, possible loss of subjects, the abolition of some courses, a reduction in remedial and guidance services at vocational level, a shorter student day which, from an educational point of view, is totally unacceptable.  There would be enrolment restrictions and total closure of senior cycle and small schools.</P>
    <P>This is what is happening in the Minister's constituency.  There is no better way to understand the problem than to realise how it will affect each of us.  That view was confirmed at a recent meeting in Clonmel attended by parents, teachers and representatives of the Vocational Education Committee, chaired by Councillor Josephine Quinlan.  Those attending that meeting concluded that if the cutbacks were to continue as proposed it would involve a reduction of four teachers in the institute in Clonmel, to be effected by the termination of any post that might be temporary, part-time, by voluntary redundancy &mdash; this glorious solution now accepted universally as the panacea for all our problems &mdash; early retirement, or transfer to another school. This could constitute a way of threatening members of the staff that if they did not move to another school they would not be eligible for voluntary redundancy having acted contrary to or in breach of their contract.  That would lead to a total reduction in class numbers from about 25 down to 22 and a reduction in class hours per week, to approximately 960.</P>
    <P>I suggest that when these Government proposals have been tried out on the ground and vetted by the professional people who will have to operate them, particularly when parents realise the consequences for their children, they will be found to be unacceptable, and inoperable, without any justification whatsoever on social or educational grounds. <Col N="1047" /> One can argue the economics for putting forward these proposals.  But if Government priorities do not include primary and second-level education, particularly at vocational level &mdash; certainly at second-level which it is to be hoped most children will attain &mdash; what hope is there, in an economically harsh period for the survival of any of the social services we consider to be so vital?  One thinks immediately of health, social welfare and job creation.  Education is fundamental to every argument advanced from any side of the House.</P>
    <P>In seconding this double-edged motion it is our belief that there must be an alternative way of revaluing this problem. The Fianna Fáil Party suggested at election time that there was another way. We should now be told of that other better way.  Certainly balancing the books is no way to treat students or their parents who are concerned about them and certainly not our teachers who have given tremendously loyal service to the State since its foundation.  They were never consulted by any Government on how these proposed cuts would be implemented on the ground.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Mr. Mullooly Mr. Mullooly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mullooly</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>To delete all words after Seanad Éireann and substitute the following:-</P>
      <P>aware that the education services account for £1,031.946 million, approximately 18 per cent of net Exchequer expenditure on non-capital services and recognising that the sum provided for education in the current Budget will ensure the maintenance of the education service at its existing high level</P>
      <P>endorse the action taken by the Government with a view to making the education service more cost-effective and so enabling it to continue to make a vital contribution to the economic and social development of our country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1048" /> When I read the motion submitted by Labour Party Senators I was amazed and appalled at its extravagant and emotive language.  When Senator O'Shea was proposing the motion he used the phrase, the wrecking of the primary and vocational sectors, a further example of the intemperate, emotive and extravagant language being used in relation with this motion.  Certainly the manner in which the motion is worded is not conducive &mdash; or perhaps I should say was not intended to be conducive &mdash; to a reasoned, constructive debate on the issues involved. Furthermore, the motion attempts to give the impression that cutbacks in the educational sector started only in the lifetime of the present Government.</P>
    <P>I noticed, before Senator Ferris rose to speak, that he had a copy of an <i>IVEA Information</i> document in his hand and that he did not read for us the first sentence of that document which refers to education cuts.  I will now read that first sentence which reads:</P>
    <P>Education cuts have continued unabated in the vocational sector since 1983.  Budgets have been drastically reduced, class sizes have increased and jobs have been lost.</P>
    <P>I might point out that cuts in education spending did not begin with this Government. Indeed, it might be no harm to remind ourselves of some of the cutbacks that took place under the Coalition Government in which the Labour Party was a partner.  For example, there had been cutbacks in the free books scheme, in school transport, school building and maintenance, in the provision for teaching aids and equipment, in the provision for remedial education and for career guidance.  There were also cutbacks in vocational education scholarships to regional and vocational colleges.</P>
    <P>The reason I refer to these cutbacks which took place during the lifetime of the Coalition Government is to expose the dishonesty of the Senators who have proposed and seconded this motion.  I am not saying these cutbacks did not have an adverse effect on the quality of the education service, I believe they had and <Col N="1049" /> I accept that the cost-cutting measures proposed by this Government in the area of education have created problems for people involved in education at every level.  I have never tried to deny that.  I am as conscious, as is any other Member of this House, of these problems.</P>
    <P>When I spoke in the Seanad on 28 October last year during a debate on a similar motion I conceded that it would be extremely difficult to maintain the quality of the education service in the present very difficult economic circumstances. At paragraph 898 of the Official Report of Seanad Éireann on 28 October 1987 I said:</P>
    <P>I regret, as I am sure every other Member of this House does, that because of the economic situation the Government found it necessary to provide for a reduction in overall expenditure on the education service in the Estimates for 1988.  I regret also that the provision for primary education has to take its share of the overall reduction.</P>
    <P>The Government, however, have to have regard to the overall range of services which have to be provided and the limited resources which they have at their disposal for the provision of these services.</P>
    <P>The priority which the Government attach to education is underlined in the <i>Programme for National Recovery</i> which was agreed with the social partners last year.  In the section dealing with education there are four paragraphs which outline the Government's priorities in relation to education.  I do not intend to quote this section because the proposer of the motion has already quoted extensively from it but I want to emphasise its main points.</P>
    <P>First, the Government recognise the importance of the educational system in the promotion of equity in society.  The Government are committed to ensuring, that whatever cutbacks or cost cutting measures have to be taken, the burden of these will not fall on the disadvantaged. The Government are also <Col N="1050" /> committed, the section tells us, to assisting disadvantaged groups and to providing considerable Exchequer support for travellers and the mentally and physically handicapped and also to providing measures which will help these groups to achieve their full potential.  The Government are also committed to fostering and encouraging the participation of the disadvantaged at all levels in education. Then, of course, there are the various vocational preparation and training courses which are extensively subsidised and assisted.  So this section of the <i>Programme for National Recovery</i> indicates the very high priority the Government give to education.</P>
    <P>However, we have to consider the provision for education in the current year against the background of the serious economic problems which this Government have begun to address so successfully. Indeed, I might point out that many of these problems were created by the previous Government.  If I had time I would quote again from the introduction to the <i>Programme for National Recovery</i> where we are given an outline of the various difficulties which the Government have to confront.  Everybody now accepts that we could not continue to borrow at the rate at which we were borrowing in order to provide and maintain the various services irrespective of how desirable these services might be. We must recognise that a huge amount of money is still being provided for education. In the current year 6.5 per cent of our gross national product, that is 18 per cent of non-capital Government spending, is being spent on education so that the amount of money being provided for education is, in anybody's language, huge.</P>
    <P>Circular 20/87 has been referred to.  I am pleased that the implementation of this circular has now been deferred.  The Government, in consultation with the INTO, have established a review body to review all aspects of primary education. This is a 21 member body which will be chaired by an eminent former president of UCD, Dr. Tom Murphy.  I want to congratulate the Minister for Education <Col N="1051" /> and the Government on having established this review body.  I believe this is one of the most important developments that has ever happened as far as primary education is concerned.  I often heard it said that, sometimes out of evil comes good, and I believe this will be the case in this instance.  If Circular 20/87 had never been issued, this review body would never have been established.  I believe that, in due course, this review body will come to be seen as one of the best things that has ever happened as far as primary education is concerned.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Your time is up, Senator.  Would you conclude please?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Mr. Mullooly Mr. Mullooly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mullooly</NameTxt>
      <P>I will conclude by complimenting the teacher unions and the parents' associations on the very responsible, dignified and effective way in which they have conducted their campaigns against the education cuts.  It is important that the general public, as well as the Government, should be made aware of the feelings of those who are most closely involved in the education service.  Every teacher and every parent wants to see the greatest possible provision for education and over the years teachers have always campaigned for improvements in the service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Senator conclude on that note because we are very short of time.  I apologise for not reminding you when you had one minute to go but you have taken a minute's injury time.  I call Senator Peter Kelleher.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterKelleher" hpid="Mr. Kelleher Mr. Kelleher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelleher</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity to say a few words on this motion even though some of it is a repetition of a similar motion on education which we had in October last year introduced by Independent Senator Joe O'Toole.  This motion is more comprehensive, of course, because it deals with more than Circular 20/87.  It deals also with the very damaging cuts in the vocational sector, the halting of the building programme, etc.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1052" /> I spoke at length last October on the 20/87 circular and I intend to speak very little on it tonight and to confine my remarks to the section dealing with the vocational sector.  Circular 20/87 and the 1988 Estimates for Primary Education represent a vicious and unprecedented attack by this Minister for Education on the primary school system with a staggering £43 million being removed from primary education.  Many changes have taken place since last October and obviously this was not going to be tolerated. I welcome the setting up of the primary review committee.  I believe that, under the terms of reference this review could take up to two years which would mean that Circular 20/87 could be suspended indefinitely which, to me, is a retreat on the Government's initial position.</P>
    <P>The behaviour of this Government in the education area since the publication of the 1988 Estimates is a record of blunder, confusion and retreat.  We now see the bitter results of decisions taken last summer which have caused massive disruptions and discontent.  Last Saturday, in the Minister's own town of Athlone, over 12,000 people turned out in a major protest against the proposed cuts in the vocational system.  Teachers and parents, representing 38 vocational educational regions around the country, turned up. My home village of Ballyvourney and Ballingeary in the Macroom area were very well represented in Athlone last Saturday.  They warned the Minister that she could not take 700 teachers out of the VEC system, that it would be a retrograde step and that the development and expansion of the vocational sector was necessary for economic recovery and development.</P>
    <P>The TUI president stated that the public sector third level institutes are one of the outstanding educational successes of the past 20 years.  Government proposals will curtail their development and will reduce access for students and deprive the nation of the rich contribution which the staff and students can make.</P>
    <P>The Government must rethink their <Col N="1053" /> decision to take some hundreds of teachers out of the vocational, community and comprehensive schools from September 1988.  This is a socially regressive step, an attack on the section of post-primary education least able to bear it.  The vocational schools provide a range of practical subjects requiring equipment and, necessarily smaller classes.</P>
    <P>However, they also take children regardless of social standing or intellectual ability. They have contributed beyond measure to education and social progress in Ireland.</P>
    <P>I, like all other public representatives, have been receiving deputations from the INTO, from the vocational sector, from the TUI, teachers and concerned parents.  Recently I had one from a group in my own area where they were concerned that if the cutbacks were implemented one or two of the subjects in that school would be cut out completely. They were referring to subjects like metalwork or commerce.  Metalwork is very important for anybody who wants to enter into a trade in a rural area or even for somebody who might want to take up farming as a livelihood.</P>
    <P>To survive in any walk of life one needs to be self sufficient and that would certainly mean a knowledge of metalwork in the farming sector at the moment. Needless to mention, commerce is also a very important subject.  Accounts are important in any walk of life whether it is business, farming or otherwise.  It is therefore very important to retain both of these subjects in the vocational education system.  I agree with the comments by Senator O'Shea that because of the nature of the subjects being taught in the vocational system, which include metalwork, construction and woodwork, that more individual contact is very necessary. Obviously a lower pupil-teacher ratio is vitally important.</P>
    <P>The Government cannot ignore any longer the direct contradiction which these cuts represent to the stated aim of the <i>Programme for National Recovery.</i> In that document they stated:</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1054" /> The Government will ensure that the burden of adjustments does not fall on the disadvantaged.</P>
    <P>This has been pointed out again and again, but the Government and the Minister have turned a deaf ear.  There is a mechanism established in that programme, the Central Review Committee, which can be convened by the social partners to review the progress of the programme.  I call on the Government to convene that committee in order to re-examine the contradiction which the vocational cuts represent and to find a better balance between public service numbers and pay as they affect vocational education.</P>
    <P>Since the Government came to office we have seen the establishment of no less than four major bodies, committees or commissions.  The Curriculum Advisory Council, the Primary Curriculum Review Body, the Primary Quota Review Committee, the Review Body on Primary Education, and now there is talk of yet another review body on post-primary education.  Is this not making a joke of education policy and planning?  The decent concerned people who have been invited to chair or sit on these bodies are being asked to mop up after the unholy mess created by this Government and the Minister for Education since they came into office.  It is time above all to see if the present political leadership in education is capable of not only putting right the damage done already but of bringing forward the kind of dynamic policy which is needed so desperately for Ireland's hope for the young people.</P>
    <P>It took a defeat of this Government on the education motion to bring them to their senses.  We in Fine Gael have been pointing out to them that they have been wrong in their approach to the cutbacks in education.  My party's position on this motion before us is to vote against the Fianna Fáil amendment to the motion as we do not believe that the sum provided for education in the current budget will ensure the maintenance of the education service at its existing level.  We will be abstaining on the Labour Party motion <Col N="1055" /> which is divided into two paragraphs: on paragraph (i) because we feel that the primary review committee set up to examine Circular 20/87 should be given an opportunity to report back with a firm conclusion and on paragraph (ii) because we feel that the Minister is about to make another retreat on the vocational cuts. This we welcome and we want to allow her and the Government ample room to implement this retreat.</P>
    <P>It is my belief that education has taken a sudden and massive blow under this Government.  This is all the more despicable because of the guarantees given to the education boards two days before the general election.  Fine Gael's minor cuts were described as devastating and it was said it would be completely counterproductive to implement them.  Fine Gael's prudent and caring management of the education budget is now being seen for what it was.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMcCarthy" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Industry and Commerce (Dr. McCarthy) Minister of State at the Department of Industry and Commerce (Dr. McCarthy)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Industry and Commerce (Dr. McCarthy)</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to say at the outset that the Government welcome the opportunity which the motion before the House gives them to bring the House up-to-date on developments in the area of primary education.</P>
      <P>The announcement of the proposals in relation to pupil/teacher ratio changes in national schools generated considerable controversy when it was made last October. I am not going to deny that the proposal was a controversial one.  The Government were aware that the very significant reductions needed in public expenditure, if the national finances were to be restored to a healthy condition, were not going to be able to be made painlessly.  It was to be expected that any measures in any area of public spending which would have substantial effect would give rise to strong opposition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Nevertheless, the controversy generated has been of value in helping to clarify for people the issues in question. It has enabled people to realise that getting the public finances under control is an aim of the first importance and of <Col N="1056" /> immediate urgency but one which cannot be achieved without sacrifices.  The question then is, what sacrifices have to be made and how do we measure the sacrifices which have to be made against the benefits to be obtained.  The debate has helped people to be clearer on these matters and it will be towards that clarification that I will devote what I have to say.</P>
    <P>Because this same matter of the pupil/teacher ratio in national schools was already the subject of debate in this House at the beginning of November and again in Dáil Éireann later in that month, I cannot deal adequately with the question without, of necessity, going over again some of the ground then traversed.</P>
    <P>The principal areas which I intend to touch upon, although not in the same depth as in the earlier debates are, first, that relating the pupil/teacher ratio changes to the general issue of curtailing public spending and secondly, that describing what is involved in the pupil/teacher proposal itself.  In the course of this I will bring the House up-to-date on the present situation.</P>
    <P>I have already explained that our starting point is the need to curtail public spending.  By now, people do not any longer need to be persuaded that this is a first priority.  It is, however, significant to note that even with the limited curbs on public spending which this Government were able to introduce last year, total national debt still climbed by more than a further £900 million to over £26 billion in 1987.  This represents a slowing down but it does mean that the growth of debt has not yet been halted, let alone reversed.  It is with the aim of halting this growth that the further major reductions, amounting to nearly £500 million, have been made in the current year's Estimates.</P>
    <P>As pointed out before, this is not, as some have alleged, a matter of bookkeeping only, of putting balancing the books before people.  In the first place, the servicing of the debt is eating up the equivalent of close to the whole PAYE, tax yield, thus soaking up resources which could be used elsewhere, including the <Col N="1057" /> improvement of the level of educational provision.  In the second place, the effect of the debt burden is to be found in high levels of taxation and high levels of interest, both of which have had a significant effect in discouraging investment for employment purposes.</P>
    <P>Granted that the national debt situation must be brought under control, the question now is how it is to be done. I am well aware that one of the elements in a general strategy for doing this is to broaden the tax base.  I shall not go into that issue here; Members of this House will have ample time to discuss it in the budget debate and, later on, on the Finance Bill.  However, I think it should suffice to say that tax reform is a matter of concern to the Government and the Minister for Finance in his budget has set out the steps which are being taken in this regard in the current year.</P>
    <P>Tax reform is not a panacea, however, and the main work of reducing the national debt must fall to public expenditure reductions.  There are two points to be grasped in regard to the relation of public expenditure reductions to the question of pupil/teacher ratio reduction. The first of these is that two-thirds of non-capital supply services spending goes on the areas of social welfare, health and education.  Curtailment of public spending cannot happen without curtailment of spending in these areas overall and, within these, education cannot expect to escape at the expense of social welfare and health.</P>
    <P>The second point is that four-fifths of spending in education is on pay.  In primary education, teacher pay in 1988 will amount to 80 per cent of the total Primary Education Estimate.  We simply could not make significant savings in the education area without reducing the amount of money going on teacher pay.</P>
    <P>One way of doing this would have been to have curtailed teacher pay.  Effectively, this is what the main Opposition party was suggesting last November when it proposed that the pay provision in the <i>Programme for National Recovery</i> be revised downwards to provide the money <Col N="1058" /> which would be saved under the proposal on pupil/teacher ratios.  For reasons that I do not propose to go over again, the Government rejected this approach.  The alternative was to reduce the total number of teachers in the schools and that is what the Government measure is aimed at accomplishing.</P>
    <P>It is at this point that the misunderstandings begin to arise.  The proposal in Circular 20/87 is stated in the form of a revised schedule of average enrolments required for the appointment and retention of teaching posts in national schools.</P>
    <P>The first misunderstanding relates to the question of over-large classes.  The impression was given in some quarters that, as a result of these measures, classes of 50 or over would become quite common, if not the norm.  This was wildly inaccurate.  The average class size throughout the country is currently 30.5. The Department of Education has calculated that, as a result of the pupil/teacher ratio changes, this will increase to 33.</P>
    <P>The second thing is that the existence of exceptionally large classes must be related to a school's choices for organisational purposes.  Thus, for reasons which have to do with the age and distribution of pupils, there may be one grade in a school with a significantly larger number of pupils than other grades.  For example, there may be 45 pupils in 4th grade.  This is, obviously, a regular occurrence at present.  There are ways of dealing with this kind of situation. Some of the pupils may be put with a smaller 5th grade.  Or 4th and 5th grades may be reorganised to give two mixed classes of more even size.</P>
    <P>This is not at all an unusual practice. Almost two-thirds of our schools have four teachers or less.  In all these schools, teachers have to work with classes composed of two or more grades.  Even in larger schools, the number of grades does not always allow an even matching with the number of teachers.  In many apparently homogeneous single-grade classes, some of the pupils may be a year ahead, and others a year behind, in, say, reading <Col N="1059" /> ages.  The teacher's solution to this is grouping within the class.  Grouping together of, say, pupils whose reading age is ahead of a 4th grade is not so very different from putting these pupils with a 5th grade class in respect of that area of curriculum.</P>
    <P>Some schools would, of course, prefer to retain a larger than average number of pupils in a single class than regroup.</P>
    <P>This is a choice the school makes itself and it is within the competence of the principal teacher, subject to the authority of the board of management, to come to the best arrangement in the circumstances of each school.  Nevertheless, there are limits and the Department in a circular issued in 1978, for example, asked schools to limit class sizes to a maximum of 40.  Despite this many schools continued to operate organisational arrangements which left them with classes of over 40 pupils.</P>
    <P>Nevertheless, in order to meet the concern expressed by many well-meaning people, the Minister announced before Christmas that she was setting up a quota review committee, following a precedent set earlier in relation to post-primary teachers, to look at the effects of Circular 20/87 in detail.  The purpose of the committee would be to see how, within the limits of expenditure laid down in the 1988 Book of Estimates, the best possible arrangement could be made in the deployment of teachers, the size of classes and the organisation of primary schools generally.  In particular, the committee would concentrate on any difficulties which might arise in certain schools following the issue of Circular 20/87 where the implementation of the circular would create unacceptably large classes.</P>
    <P>The guidelines prescribed for the committee were as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(1)  problems would be examined on a school-by-school and class-by-class basis.</P>
    <P>(2)  the maximum size of any class would not exceed forty; where, because of exceptional circumstances, <Col N="1060" /> it was impossible to adhere to this limit, the permission of the review committee and the Minister would be required;</P>
    <P>(3)  the effects on schools of population changes would be taken into account;</P>
    <P>(4)  special consideration would be given to schools in disadvantaged areas;</P>
    <P>(5)  special consideration would be given to the remedial needs of schools;</P>
    <P>(6)  existing remedial posts would not be affected by the changes under Circular 20/87 nor would special posts in disadvantaged areas; and class sizes would be appropriate to the actual size of the classroom.</P>
    <P>Pending the committee's beginning work, officials of the Department have visited all schools where a post or posts would not be retained under the terms of Circular 20/87.  Most of the schools cooperated by making available school records to the departmental officials.</P>
    <P>I understand that it has been alleged that the circular will continue to effect further reductions in the times ahead. This is not so.  The circular was designed to have a &ldquo;once-off&rdquo; effect.  Further reductions in teacher numbers could, of course, come about as a result of a decline in pupil numbers.  This, however, would lead to a loss of teaching posts in any event without the intervention of Circular 20/87.</P>
    <P>A final misunderstanding relates to the timing of the implementation of Circular 20/87.  Many people thought that the teachers whose posts would be rendered surplus under the circular would be without jobs from 1 January 1988.  However, the Minister stated, when announcing the quota review, that no change under Circular 20/87 would take place before 30 June 1988.</P>
    <P>I have dwelt at length on the misunderstandings in the public perception of what Circular 20/87 means in order to show that the impact of the circular has been exaggerated and that the strictures contained in the motion are not well-founded. The Government believe that, <Col N="1061" /> in setting up a quota review committee with wide terms of reference and in offering representation on this committee to the various interests concerned, they have shown that it is intended to apply the circular in a reasonable way and taking into account any special difficulties which individual schools may have.</P>
    <P>If I might turn now to the call in the motion for a statement in connection with the proposed review of the primary education system, I would like to refer to the Minister's recent announcement in this regard.  In that announcement she indicated that the terms of reference would encompass a wide-ranging review resulting in a report which would be submitted to the Government.  The areas to be covered would include the structure of primary education, demographic trends and their implication, the quality of primary education and school organisation.</P>
    <P>Dr. Tom Murphy, former President of University College, Dublin, has agreed to act as chairperson and the Minister has invited representation from the Irish National Teachers' Organisation, the managerial bodies, the National Parents' Council, the Association of Secondary Teachers, the Teachers' Union of Ireland, the Colleges of Education and the Primary Curriculum Review Body. The Department will also be represented on the review body and the Minister proposes appointing two nominees of her own.  The Minister intends to launch the review formally very shortly, as soon as she has nominations from all the bodies to be represented.</P>
    <P>In announcing the review, the Minister stated her belief that it was timely and expressed confidence that the report of the review body would greatly assist the Government in the task of planning for the future of primary education in this country.</P>
    <P>In the context of our discussion today, I would like to refer to one area in the review, namely, that of demographic trends and their implications.  All available evidence points to a very substantial decline in enrolments in primary schools up to the end of the present century.  The needs of the system, including the staffing <Col N="1062" /> requirements of schools, can be considered in the light of the declining demand which the drop in pupil numbers will make on our resources.  I am confident that this will be in a situation where the various measures now being taken by the Government will have enabled the crisis in the public finances to be surmounted and where Government policies will have led to an improvement in the state of the economy generally.</P>
    <P>While the present position of the public finances has necessitated Government measures of an unwelcome kind such as we have been debating to-day, I believe that the situation in this respect will improve according as the steps we are taking have effect and according as the pressure on demand on the educational system eases with the decline in pupil numbers.  It is in this context I would expect the review body to carry out their deliberations.</P>
    <P>The vocational education system has been one of the cornerstones of the Irish education system since 1930.  Over the past 50 years it has made a major contribution to the development of Irish society and will continue to do so in the years ahead.</P>
    <P>The 1930 Vocational Education Act in establishing the vocational system stated that it would include &ldquo;general and practical training in preparation for employment to trades, manufactures, agriculture, commerce and the industrial pursuits and also general and practical training for the improvement of young persons in the early stages of such employment&rdquo;.  This clearly outlined the specific purpose for which vocational education was established.</P>
    <P>The successful training of young people in various skilled trades and occupations was of central importance to the development of the economy of the country in the years following independence.  That this objective has continued to be achieved in the intervening decades is substantiated by the number of technically skilled young people leaving school each year and in the current competitive success of our apprentices at international level each year.  The development of <Col N="1063" /> regional colleges and other third-level technological institutions reflect the success of vocational education.</P>
    <P>The introduction of free post primary education by the late Donogh O'Malley in the late sixties brought with it sweeping changes in the whole area of education provision.  Student numbers increased from 55,000 in 1965 to 200,000 plus in 1986 and the education budget itself increased from £19 million in 1965 to £1,269 million in 1988.  That radical initiative resulted in substantial changes in the post primary education system. Secondary schools extended their programmes to cater for pupils with different abilities and aspirations.</P>
    <P>The vocational system also broadened its horizons by the introduction of intermediate and leaving certificate programmes and a wide range of adult education programmes.  Gradually new types of post primary schools also emerged: comprehensive schools, community schools and more recently vocational schools established under section 21 of the 1930 Act i.e., community colleges. This has resulted in a more complex administrative system but one which is broadly similar in its curricular provision.</P>
    <P>The majority of all post primary schools now provide a curriculum comprising of both academic and practical subjects and cater for a wide range of ability levels.  Nor is size any longer the monopoly of any one sector of education. For example, there are virtually as many small secondary schools as vocational schools, 138 to 139.  In that overall context the Government is of the opinion that this developing equalisation of education provision should be reflected in the allocation of teaching posts at post primary level.</P>
    <P>The Government indicated their continuing commitment to the area of disadvantage in the <i>Programme for National Recovery</i> and have again made provision in this year's budget for the maintenance of literacy programmes, prison and traveller education which is under the aegis of the vocational education committees. The Department of Education have also <Col N="1064" /> acknowledged on an ongoing basis the involvement of vocational schools with disadvantaged students by consistently allocating over the last nine years the substantial majority of remedial and resource posts to the vocational sector and will maintain that provision again in 1988.</P>
    <P>Reference has been made to the question of the post primary building programme. This is now closely linked to the whole question of demographic trends. Every single project must be carefully analysed in the context of a declining pupil enrolment pattern.  All developments in building will be assessed on a rationalisation-community basis.  To do otherwise would be a gross waste of existing resources.  Within these parameters and the limited financial resources available, some initiatives will be taken during the 1988-89 academic year.</P>
    <P>At a time of great economic stringency this Government have clearly shown their commitment to education by maintaining provision for all our young people from primary to third level.  The Government's strategy of controlling the public finances has been proved in the financial year 1987 to have been an outstandingly successful one.  Public expenditure is down, interest rates are down, borrowing is down.  The Government cannot and will not jeopardise the progress that has been made to date in achieving economic stability and are confident that they have the full support of the public in realising that objective.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, representing the university graduates &mdash; a great majority of whom are probably teachers &mdash; I have no choice but to express my support for the motion.  There is really no time to add to the debate.  I would rather use a minute or two to make a specific plea for one severely disadvantaged class of pupils.  I would cite specifically an education institution in Cork which is at the receiving end of the cuts in their worst aspect, the Cork Spastic Clinic and School of the Divine Child.  I am told that they represent the kind of school which caters for severely <Col N="1065" /> handicapped children who need daily education, treatment and therapy.  They are being particularly affected by a change in the transport system of bringing these children to school from widely scattered points.  The new system apparently of offering a capitation grant per family or per child is simply not comparable at all in its effect to the public collection system which was hitherto operated.  I should be glad if I could be informed of the Department's policy on this matter. If we are talking about the disadvantaged these, surely, are the most pitiable of the disadvantaged and even in the most draconian climate some regard must be had for these very special cases.</P>
      <P>Having used very little time I would ask you, with great respect, a Chathaoirligh, to extend some of my theoretical time to my colleague, Senator O'Toole, who has a primary responsibility for this area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not take up too much time on this part of the debate.  I am grateful to get in on it.  I thank the Minister for coming along.  I am not sure if the Government reshuffled a place during the day or if he is merely standing in for the Minister for Education.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to deal with one point that the Minister raised.  It is important to get it cleared and out of the way.  He went to great lengths to describe for us the primary quota review committee, and presented it in the most reasonable terms, as parents, teachers and the Department examining schools on a one by one basis and deciding what would be done in the schools.  He took great pains to go through the Minister's statement of, I believe, 9 or 10 December last, which covered the guidelines for the primary quota review committee.  It seemed that the problems and effects would be examined, and that the committee would appear to solve the problems within the schools.  If the Minister were to propose to us that parents, teachers, management and the Department would sit down with the power to make decisions for each school, we would not be wasting any time <Col N="1066" /> about getting in there.  We are not idiots this side of the line.</P>
    <P>What was left out very conveniently in the document which the Minister was given to read was the next few lines which indicated that when the committee had examined each school they would then make a recommendation to the Minister, which the Minister could choose to carry out or not carry out.  It further added that the Minister would also take representations from other groups and interested parties, at which time Fianna Fáil TDs all over the country began to sprinkle documentation to their local primary schools along the lines of &ldquo;Please tell me the problems in your school so that I can make representations to the Minister in order to sort out the difficulties within your school&rdquo;.  In other words, what that seemingly innocuous document was doing was creating the greatest recipe for political graft that I have seen in my whole experience of primary education.</P>
    <P>The Minister was taking into her hands the giving and the taking by her gift of 1,300 teaching jobs.  It would be totally unacceptable in a situation in primary schools where appointments are made strictly on the basis of enrolment and where there is no room for political interference. In all fairness political public representatives do not want to be involved at that level, because it creates more problems than it resolves.  That is the problem with the primary quota review committee.</P>
    <P>I am glad of the opportunity to make it clear to people that if the Minister were setting up a committee where parents, teachers, management and the Department in equal numbers would sit down and examine each school and make recommendations that would be binding, that would be a horse of a different colour.  It was not that that was being presented to us here.  Last term there was a lot of what was referred to by other people as campaigning against the detrimental effects of the proposed Circular, 20/87.</P>
    <P>At the height of that crisis, campaign and organisation the Taoiseach, Deputy <Col N="1067" /> Haughey, made a statement at the Fianna Fáil presidential dinner &mdash; if I recall rightly on 10 December &mdash; and he referred to the particular difficulties in primary education of the time.  He spelt out the importance of primary education and the need that it should be properly resourced.  In very clear and unambiguous terms he invited various interested parties to participate in a review of the whole primary education system by what was later called the primary education review body.  He said that within that body, through the procedures of that body and through its recommendations we would find &mdash; and I quote &mdash;&ldquo;the solution to the current problems and difficulties&rdquo; as well as looking at the difficulties which would be created in the future.  It was on that basis and on that very clear invitation of the Taoiseach that this body was set up which was, as the Minister has said, responding and reporting back to the Government.</P>
    <P>I believe in the Government's good faith in this matter.  For that reason both the parents, as represented both by the National Parents Council and also by the Christian Brothers Schools Parents Council and the INTO, representative of the teachers, decided to suspend their public campaign until such time as a resolution of the difficulties could be found within the review body.  It is within that situation that we are at the moment.  I would also draw to the Minister's attention that during that period of time and also on 9 December the Minister issued Circular 24/87.  In fact, the document the Minister read from was part of it.  It said that from 1 January until the end of the school year appointments would be made in primary schools as per the normal schedules.  Just for the record, that is not happening.</P>
    <P>The Minister has taken the decision unilaterally that all appointments in primary schools from 1 January have been temporary, pending a review.  In other words, the Minister is in breach of her own rules and regulations because, as the House will be aware, a circular changes <Col N="1068" /> the rules.  The Minister has the power to do that.  The Minister said to management, to schools and to teachers on 10 December &ldquo;You will now make appointments as per normal schedules and Circular 20/87 is suspended&rdquo;.  That is not happening.</P>
    <P>I shall not take up any more time because it would be inappropriate for me to go into details, particularly because of the sensitive negotiations taking place.  I want to stress that the Government offered an invitation which teachers and parents are happy to accept, recognising the difficulties in a reasonable, honest and fair attempt to find a resolution.  It is in that way that we should go forward.  It is a pity that the Minister should be harking back to other issues here tonight.  I believe in taking a more positive approach.  If the formula for a resolution is presented we should seek to find a resolution within that formula.  It is with that progressive and positive statement that I will now sit down.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>The motion before us must be put in context.  It is before us because, realistically speaking, expenditure cuts were necessary across the board when the Government took office. We are in a very difficult situation in the circumstances of the late eighties.  The national imperative is the control of the public finances.  There will be differences in emphasis and approaches and so on as to how this can be achieved but it is a fact that, when the Government took office, the national debt had doubled to a figure of £25 billion.  That was extremely serious and had to be tackled.  The economy was practically at a standstill and confidence was at a very low ebb.  This meant that little new investment had been made when the Government took office last March.  Putting the public finances on a sound footing is vital to everything to which we, as a people, aspire.  That has meant tackling, at times in a painful way, expenditure in various Government Departments.  Education, therefore, could not escape.  The most detailed thought and attention was paid <Col N="1069" /> to the cuts in each Department to make them as equitable as possible in a difficult situation.</P>
      <P>I want to refer very briefly to international comparisons that are made in the educational field.  Our population of young people of school going age is very high in comparison with other countries. Consequently our capacity to pay for given levels of education is that much less, especially in times of economic stringency. Nonetheless, the percentage of GNP spent on education in Ireland is one of the highest in Europe.  For many years past the numbers of children of primary school age have been rising.  At the same time, the number of teachers has been rising even faster.  The result is that the pupil-teacher ratio and class sizes are right now better than in the past.</P>
      <P>I would like to make this point.  At present the average class size is 30.5, compared with 35 some 20 years ago.  We all would like to see the pupil-teacher ratio somewhat lower, but the Minister has scotched the speculation and rumours about classes of 50 or more being the order of the day under the proposals. That is obviously not so.</P>
      <P>We must also look ahead at educational policy.  The recent DKM report on population projections underlines a trend.  The numbers in primary schools are projected to fall by some 80,000 or 14 per cent by 1996.  Educational planning must take account of these trends.  The establishment by the Minister of an overall review body on primary education is, therefore, timely and relevant.  The Minister has also recently established a comprehensive review of the primary school curriculum.  Efforts are being made by the Minister to accommodate what we hope will be a temporary, very difficult financial situation and simultaneously some important measures have been taken to plan for the future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is 7.50 p.m. and I should call Senator Brian O'Shea but I understand he is giving three minutes to Senator Brendan Ryan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to talk about <Col N="1070" /> vocational education in particular because that is where I come from.  The union I belong to represents people in the vocational sector.  I was not here, but I read the Minister's script.  May I say that, if this Government had the willingness to deal with cutbacks so that those who could most afford to handle the cutbacks would be the ones penalised, there would be no need to penalise particularly vocational education at the second level which in this city and in my home city deals with the oppressed, the poor and the children of the poor and the oppressed. Vocational education at second level has a remarkable record.  The record is even more remarkable given that in this city and in Cork it tends to have to take the people who are rejected by private secondary schools which operate invidious selection procedures which are meant to be tests of ability, but which tend to work out as tests of social background.</P>
      <P>There is, of course, the solution to the problem of cutbacks in education.  I will invite the Minister to think about it.  It is to get rid of almost £20 million or £30 million a year which the State provides in subsidies to private fee paying secondary schools to finance the education of the children of the privileged.  The payment of salaries for teachers in schools who choose to charge fees to their pupils is a national disgrace.  There is no justification for State subsidies for the parents of families who choose, for no justifiable education or reasons other than pure snobbery, to send their children to private fee paying schools.  There is £30 million a year of our money being devoted to finance the education of the elite of this country, those who have notions of their own superiority, those who have notions that their children should not mix with our children, those who have notions that somehow these private schools &mdash; the vast majority of which, incidentally, are run by agents of my Church which is a disgrace to my Church and to our society &mdash; should be subsidised by the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If people want private education let them pay for it as they have to do in <Col N="1071" /> primary education since the foundation of the State.  Let the State take away the £30 million that is paid every year to private fee paying secondary schools.  Let that be transferred to the public sector and there would be no need for any cutbacks. I invite this Government who, incidentally, by and large are not the product of private schools, to take on that particularly powerful vested interest, which is the Catholic Church and its allies in the religious orders, and to take away the money they quite unjustly get, and to give it to other areas of education.  Then there would be no need for cutbacks.  Let the rich pay for their elitest education, if they wish.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianOShea" hpid="Mr. B. O'Shea Mr. B. O'Shea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. O'Shea</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to refer to the comments made by Senator Mullooly at the beginning.  He stated that the language in the motion was intemperate. I reject that allegation.  Any reasonable reading of it would not call the language intemperate.  He used another term which I found more objectionable, and he used it in the context of my colleague Senator Ferris and myself and that was that we were dishonest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Mr. Mullooly Mr. Mullooly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mullooly</NameTxt>
      <P>Politically.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianOShea" hpid="Mr. B. O'Shea Mr. B. O'Shea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. O'Shea</NameTxt>
      <P>Politically dishonest is a different kettle of fish from dishonest. I reject that we were either dishonest or politically dishonest in presenting this motion.  No other Government in this State have tried to introduce policies to take 2,000 teachers out of the primary sector and 900 teachers out of the vocational sector.  Cuts were made previously and nobody is denying that.  But how horrendous these cuts are.  I do not withdraw the words Senator Mullooly found objectionable &ldquo;wrecking the primary education system&rdquo; and &ldquo;wrecking vocational education&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I believe that is the pattern that is emerging.  I have strong feelings about it. I am a teacher; I am a parent; I am involved in management at vocational level.  What I say I say with conviction out of my experience, out of the various <Col N="1072" /> patterns I see emerging.  On one hand we have rampant emigration.  Our young people are leaving our shores.  Hopefully, those who are going are educated to a level where they will be getting employment which is a lot more appropriate to people in the 20th century than our emigrants got in the past.</P>
    <P>In the script read by the Minister there was nothing essentially new.  There was one point that still remains unclarified for me.  It is proposed to set up two committees. One is the primary education review body, the larger body, which is reporting to the Government.  That is a very important point.  It is a broadly based committee with a broadly based mandate. The INTO are keen to play their part there.  The other committee which I refer to is the Primary Quota Review committee.  There is no such committee. The INTO and management indicated that they were not going to take part in any such committee.</P>
    <P>In spite of commitments, in writing and verbally, before Christmas, when it was stated that appointments under normal schedules in national schools would go ahead as heretofore, that has not happened. All appointments are being made on a temporary basis, subject to their being considered by this non-existent committee.  I am accusing the Government here of backtracking.  This, to my mind, is a dishonest role and not in keeping with the impression created both verbally and in the written word before Christmas to defuse a situation which was existing in every parish in Ireland when parents, without exception, were saying: &ldquo;We will not have this.  Our children are not going to be the victims of Fianna Fáil financial rectitude.&rdquo;  I do not dispute that the national debt is a problem.  It is a problem that has to be grappled with. That is accepted.</P>
    <P>The problem that really exists relates to who suffers.  In spite of lofty and weighty aspirations in the <i>Programme for National Recovery</i> the sector at second level which caters for children, one third of whom have learning difficulties, is singled out for special attack.  The primary sector, the one that has universal and <Col N="1073" /> utter accessibility to all the children of the country, is also being singled out for special attack.  I agree that intemperate language should not be used, but strong language should be used.</P>
    <P>We in the Labour Party stand four square in every sense with the disadvantaged. Financial rectitude was the essence of most of what we heard from the Opposition side, but it is a question of priority.  It is a question of people. More important, it is a question of our disadvantaged people.  We have a lot of empty aspirations and pious platitudes in that document; the Government are coming out and doing the very opposite.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I learned nothing new <Col N="1074" /> from the Minister's speech tonight.  As a matter of fact, some clarification which I sought was not forthcoming &mdash; the whole area regarding the two committees.  Until the non-existent one considers something, we cannot have the new appointments in primary schools sanctioned on a full-time and permanent basis.  In conclusion, if this is the road we are travelling to disadvantage at primary level first of all, our least advantaged, our least able people, and if we are then going on into the vocational sector to compound that problem, no argument of financial rectitude or any other argument can justify that because that is counter to all social justice.</P>
    <P>Amendment put.</P>
    <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 23; Níl, 18.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bohan, Edward Joseph.<br />Byrne, Seán.<br />Cassidy, Donie.<br />Cullimore, Séamus.<br />Doherty, Michael.<br />Fallon, Seán.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Fitzsimons, Jack.<br />Haughey, Seán.<br />Hillery, Brian.<br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kiely, Dan.<br />Lydon, Donal.<br />McEllistrim, Tom.<br />McKenna, Tony.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />Mulroy, Jimmy.<br />O'Callaghan, Vivian.<br />O'Connell, John.<br />Ó Conchubhair, Nioclás.<br />O'Toole, Martin J.<br />Ryan, William.<br />Wallace, Mary.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bradford, Paul.<br />Bulbulia, Katharine.<br />Connor, John.<br />Cregan, Daly.<br />Daly, Jack.<br />Doyle, Joe.<br />Ferris, Michael.<br />Harte, John.<br />Hogan, Philip.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kelleher, Peter.<br />Kennedy, Patrick.<br />McCormack, Pádraic.<br />McDonald, Charlie.<br />Manning, Maurice.<br />Murphy, John A.<br />O'Shea, Brian.<br />O'Toole, Joe.<br />Ryan, Brendan.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators S. Haughey and Fallon; Níl, Senators Harte and O'Shea.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the motion, as amended, agreed to?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Senators Senators">
      <NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the motion, as amended, be agreed to.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Senators Senators">
      <NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
      <P>Vótail.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1075" />
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>On the question: &ldquo;That the motion, as amended, be agreed to&rdquo; a division has been challenged.  Will the Senators calling for a division please rise in their places?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1076" />
      <i>Five or more Senators stood.</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The division will now proceed.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 24; Níl, 6.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bohan, Edward Joseph.<br />Byrne, Seán.<br />Cassidy, Donie.<br />Cullimore, Séamus.<br />Doherty, Michael.<br />Fallon, Seán.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Fitzsimons, Jack.<br />Haughey, Seán F.<br />Hillery, Brian.<br />Kiely, Dan.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Lydon, Donal.<br />McEllistrim, Tom.<br />McGowan, Patrick.<br />McKenna, Tony.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />Mulroy, Jimmy.<br />O'Callaghan, Vivian.<br />O'Connell, John.<br />Ó Conchubhair, Nioclás.<br />O'Toole, Martin J.<br />Ryan, William.<br />Wallace, Mary.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Ferris, Michael.<br />Harte, John.<br />Murphy, John A.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">O'Shea, Brian.<br />O'Toole, Joe.<br />Ryan, Brendan.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Senators S. Haughey and Fallon; Níl, Senators Harte and O'Shea.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamRyan" hpid="Mr. W. Ryan Mr. W. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>At 10.30 tomorrow morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matter. - Limerick" RHead="Hospital Proposed Closure">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter. - Limerick Hospital Proposed Closure.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful for the opportunity to raise this matter on the Adjournment and to give my full support to the retention and development of Barringtons Hospital as an acute medical hospital with a vital and essential casualty and outpatient service.  In doing so, I deplore and condemn the announcement by the Minister for Health, Dr. O'Hanlon, that acute services at Barringtons Hospital will cease early in 1988.  I call for the immediate reversal of that decision.  It was in 1829 that Sir Joseph Barrington-Bart, a name inseparably interwoven with the history of Limerick decided with his sons, Matthew, Daniel, Croker and Samuel, to found a charitable institution at their own expense for the relief of the poor of Limerick city and county.  In 1830 under an Act of Parliament of George IV it was constituted as a hospital for the city and county of Limerick.</P>
      <P>Barringtons Hospital was opened for the reception of patients on 5 November 1831.  Ever since, Barringtons has been a life support machine for the people of Limerick, a place where doors never closed and where help was never failing. Barringtons Hospital is part of the tradition, the history and the heritage of Limerick and it symbolises all that is best in Limerick, treating rich and poor, old and young, alike without discrimination. Barringtons has played a vital and significant role in the provision of essential medical services to the people of the Limerick area for the past 160 years.  I firmly believe that it must continue to do so, to ensure that the people of Limerick and the catchment areas of Limerick in Clare and North Tipperary receive the level of medical care to which they are entitled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1077" /> In support of the case for the retention and development of Barringtons Hospital I would like to emphasise the following salient and pertinent points.  Barringtons has a basic bed complement of 84 beds, while an additional eight beds can and frequently are put up to cater for emergency admissions.  There is additional scope within the hospital for a minimum of another 20 beds if the appropriate funding was available.  I would also like to emphasise that an additional 50 beds could readily be provided by using the new nurses' home.  This is a modern, three-storey building which was built in 1949.  It is attached to the main hospital and is in first-class condition, having recently been upgraded and decorated. Limerick corporation have also designated land adjacent to the hospital for car parking purposes and this would also be available to Barringtons Hospital for the provision of car parking facilities and for other purposes.</P>
    <P>The hospital itself is in excellent structural condition being built entirely of cut stone and all the floors are of reinforced concrete.  A number of major improvements were carried out in recent years with the approval and funding of the Department of Health.  In 1981 and 1982 the mechanical and electrical services were upgraded to meet the chief fire officer's requirements.  The boiler house was re-roofed and the kitchen was renovated and refurbished and a new medical oxygen system was installed.  The total cost of these works and the ancillary improvements amounted to £212,000.  In 1983 and 1984, a new lift and a lift shaft were installed.  A ward was converted and refurbished as an intensive care unit at a cost of £130,000.  A suite of two totally enclosed, fully air-conditioned and pressurised theatres was completed in 1969.  These theatres are equipped with every modern facility and are considered among the best in the country.</P>
    <P>Since 1982 capital grants totalling £190,000 have been received for the purchase of replacement items of equipment. In addition to the above capital works, in 1986 the Department of Health <Col N="1078" /> approved and funded the purchase of two houses adjacent to the hospital at a cost of £60,000 to provide additional space for the development of the casualty and outpatients department.  On 27 February 1987 in response to representations by me, I received the following letter from Deputy John Boland, who was Minister for Health before the present Minister for Health, Deputy O'Hanlon.  Deputy Boland stated:</P>
    <P>Dear Pat,</P>
    <P>You were in touch with me recently regarding the proposals to develop the Out-Patient Department at Barringtons Hospital.  The position is that the planning brief for the development is currently being considered by officers of my Department in consultation with the authorities of the hospital and this process is likely to take some time to complete.  Of course you are aware that two adjoining properties have been purchased at a cost of £60,000 to make way for this development.</P>
    <P>On 8 April 1987, the 1987 budget allocation for Barringtons Hospital was notified and this allocation of £1.897 million amounted to a reduction of 13 per cent on the 1986 allocation.  Indeed, it was notified so late in the day that it amounted almost to a real cut of over 20 per cent in the remaining months.  On 29 October 1987 the chairman of the board of management of Barringtons Hospital, in company with the chairman of the other voluntary hospitals, was invited to the Minister's office in Dáil Éireann to receive notification of the 1988 financial allocation.  A sum of £1.6 million was allocated by the Minister for 1988, a reduction of £297,000 on the 1987 allocation.</P>
    <P>On 1 December 1987 responding to Deputy Bernard Allen at Question Time, Deputy O'Hanlon, Minister for Health, stated:</P>
    <P>I did not say anything contradictory. I said it was my belief that there should be no further acute hospital closures in 1988 other than those already in train.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1079" /> Yet on 10 December 1988 the Minister for Health informed the secretary manager of Barringtons Hospital that acute hospital services at Barringtons Hospital should cease early in 1988.</P>
    <P>Indeed, the Minister's shock announcement came less than four weeks after he had strongly denied that he was planning to close any more of the country's hospitals.  Responding to an exclusive report in the <i>Irish Medical Times</i> for Friday, 13 November 1988, the Minister told the <i>Irish Independent</i> of the same day that he did not envisage any more hospital closures other than those already in the process of being shut down or those which had already been notified that they would be closed.</P>
    <P>Three weeks earlier the Minister for Health also assured the chairmen and the chief executive officers of the eight health boards at a meeting here in Leinster House that he did not anticipate the need for any further closures in 1988 other than those already in train.  It is clear from these statements that Barringtons Hospital was not among the hospitals targeted for closure.  The purported closure of Barringtons Hospital, in the face of such strong denials by Deputy O'Hanlon that he was contemplating shutting down any more hospitals, places a question mark over the future of every hospital in this country, other than the super regional hospitals.  It also puts a serious question mark over how much reliance can be placed on ministerial assurances.</P>
    <P>Barringtons Hospital is the heart of Limerick and it is the lifeline for over 90,000 of our people in Limerick city and county and in the catchment areas of Clare and north Tipperary.  Barringtons, of course, has traditionally catered for the poorer sections of our community and this can be seen from the fact that over 80 per cent of all the beds in Barringtons are public beds.</P>
    <P>I would also like to emphasise that despite what Deputy O'Hanlon publicly stated on Radio Telefís Eireann &mdash; that no health professionals took part in the march on 9 January 1988 &mdash; the Limerick <Col N="1080" /> city and county branches of the Irish Medical Association issued a joint statement deploring the purported closure of Barringtons Hospital.  These doctors demonstrated their practical opposition to the closure when they marched under an IMO banner at the protest march in which over 25,000 took part.  In their statement the local branches said:</P>
    <P>We, the Limerick city and county branches of the IMO, including consultants, non-consultant hospital doctors and general practitioners, deplore the proposed and imminent closure of Barringtons Hospital.  We view it as a major loss of facilities to care for the 46,000 patients who visit it annually, in its role as an acute hospital, as a casualty department and as a venue for the investigation of patients on an out-patient basis.  In particular we feel that insufficient significance has been attributed to its very central location both in regard to its proximity to city patients requiring our urgent attention, and to its social and medical importance over many years to city patients.</P>
    <P>Maurice Lenihan, the distinguished historian, in his history of Limerick dated 20 February 1866 stated:</P>
    <P>In seasons of severe epidemic, as at the outbreak of the cholera morbus in 1832, Barringtons Hospital was of incalculable benefit to the citizens as it has also been in all cases of accidents, whenever immediate relief is demanded by the sufferer.  It would be a great pity that so deserving an institution should decay or fail from want of spirited support.</P>
    <P>In total, between out-patients, casualty, and in-patients, 50,000 people were treated in Barringtons in 1987 at a cost to the Department of Health of £1.897 million.  By any standard of comparison this is a very efficient and cost effective delivery of service and offers value for money.  The people of Limerick and the surrounding areas have shown, as Maurice Lenihan has said, spirited support and a determined and united approach <Col N="1081" /> for the retention and development of Barringtons Hospital.  I therefore call upon the Minister for Health to reverse this decision so that this great hospital can continue to serve our people with the same dedication and commitment as it has done down through the years.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I call upon the Minister for Health to enter immediately into discussions and serious negotiations with the board of management of Barringtons Hospital so that a way can be found to prevent the closure of one of the country's oldest and most respected health care institutions.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelSmith" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Energy (Mr. Smith) (For the Minister for Health) Michael Smith">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Energy (Mr. Smith) (For the Minister for Health)</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate very well the Senator's concern about the closure of Barringtons Hospital.  In order to put the matter in a proper context I should perhaps outline the background and the sequence of events which have taken place.  It is now well known that, shortly after I took up office as Minister for Health, I initiated a comprehensive review of the acute hospital system.  The group which carried out the review held discussions with the management of all acute hospitals and met with Barringtons and St. John's in June and again in August of 1987.  At these meetings it was pointed out to both hospitals that there was an apparent surplus of beds in the Mid-Western Health Board area as a whole.  The health board had permanently closed a number of beds in its hospitals but it was clear that further rationalisation was still required.</P>
      <P>The review group indicated to the management of both St. John's and Barringtons hospitals and to the management of the Mid-Western Health Board that the voluntary hospital sector in Limerick would need to be rationalised on to one site with about 100 beds.  Both hospitals later put forward detailed submissions as to why each of them should be the hospital to be retained.  It was very significant that neither submission suggested that both hospitals should be retained and it seemed that the logic of the situation was accepted by both hospitals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1082" /> I want to remind Senator Kennedy that he would seem to be ignoring these developments.  When the Minister first invited Barringtons and St. John's for discussion, which was long before October, it was clear to both sides that one or other of the two hospitals would eventually be closed.  The option, therefore, was given to both sides to submit, in a substantive way, their views as to the future developments of either hospital.</P>
    <P>In deciding which hospital should be retained I had careful regard to the outcome of the meetings with the Mid-Western Health Board and management of St. John's and Barringtons Hospitals.  In addition, I obtained an architectural report on the suitability of both hospitals as to their future participation in the public hospital health service in the area. All of the evidence from the outcome of these meetings and the architectural aspects pointed towards the retention of St. John's rather than Barringtons. Having carefully examined all of the evidence before me, I decided that St. John's Hospital should be the site on which the voluntary hospital services in Limerick should be located.</P>
    <P>There are a number of reasons for this. First, St. John's has a more spacious site. Secondly, the building of St. John's is in better condition due mainly to the fact that £500,000 was spent on improving the fabric of the building in 1986.  Thirdly, St. John's is more readily adaptable to the changing emphasis in the practice of acute medicine.  For example, it has a unit which is extremely suitable for day hospital services containing, as it does, an endoscopy room, two five-bed rooms and an area for the theatre.  There has been a considerable shift in emphasis recently from traditional in-patient care to treatment on a day basis.  Fourthly, the mechanical and electrical services are superior to those in Barringtons Hospital.</P>
    <P>I might add that I arrived at my decision purely on the basis of the physical facilities and the management cooperation of the two bodies concerned. Since I announced my decision I have been accused of inconsistency in view of the statement I made in the Dáil that <Col N="1083" /> there should not be any further hospital closures other than those which had already been announced or were in the process of being closed.  I would like to make it clear again that detailed discussions regarding the future role of the two voluntary hospitals in Limerick have been in progress since June 1987.  Therefore, as the process which led to my decision had been under way for a number of months, in full consultation with the managements of the hospitals concerned, there is no conflict whatsoever between my statement in the Dáil and my subsequent announcement about Barringtons Hospital.</P>
    <P>Since I announced my decision many people have expressed great concern about the effect the closure will have on hospital services in Limerick.  First of all, I want to point out that at the start of 1987 acute hospital services in the Mid-Western Health Board were being delivered from nine different locations, five of which were in Limerick city.  Clearly this was not a sound basis on which to build an efficient hospital system and while subsequent bed closure by the health board reduced the number of locations to seven it was clear that further rationalisation was required.  It is more economical to effect these closures in one hospital rather than having them spread over a number of centres.</P>
    <P>Some fears have also been expressed that the casualty service in Limerick will be adversely affected as a result of the closure of Barringtons Hospital.  The position is that in a city the size of Limerick we simply cannot afford to have two 24-hour casualty services available seven days a week.  Indeed, it is worth mentioning that a place like Tallaght, which has a population of roughly the same as Limerick, does not have a casualty service of its own and that in Dublin as a whole there are only two hospitals in the accident and emergency rota after 5 p.m. It is clear that a significant proportion of the casualty cases which attend at Barringtons Hospital are of a minor nature and should properly be dealt with by general <Col N="1084" /> practitioners.  Moreover the number attending at night time is relatively low, about 14 per night.</P>
    <P>The closure of Barringtons Hospital will require some improvements to be carried out in the accident and emergency departments at Limerick regional and St. John's hospitals and plans for this work are already well under way.  A casualty service will be available in St. John's Hospital and considering that it is only 400 yards from Barringtons Hospital the new location will not present any difficulties. This service will operate on a day time basis from 8 a.m. to 8 p.m., since, as I have already said, it is simply not viable to maintain two 24-hour casualty units within a few miles of each other. This change will not present any difficulties since the number attending at Barringtons Hospital outside these hours is quite small.  As already announced, it is the Government's intention that the in-patient facilities will transfer to St. John's and the regional hospitals, as appropriate, by 31 March 1988.</P>
    <P>In summary, the logic of the situation is that one of the two voluntary hospitals in Limerick has to close.  This was an extremely difficult decision for me to make but in the end I am satisfied that I made the right one.  I am also satisfied that, with the necessary improvements at Limerick regional and St. John's, the two hospitals will provide a very adequate general hospital service for the people of Limerick.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I wish to thank the Minister of State, who, like myself, is a member of the Mid-Western Health Board, for coming in to read the Minister's speech this evening.  I certainly believe a bad decision has been made and that there is no real basis, medical, economic or social, for the closure of Barringtons Hospital.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Kennedy can ask a question.  He has made a 20 minute contribution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to assure the House that the campaign to retain Barringtons Hospital will go forward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1085" />
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we adjourn, as this is Deputy Smith's first time here as Minister of State, I would like to welcome him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1086" /> The Seanad adjourned at 8.45 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 4 February 1988.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>