<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="1" Month="Oct" Year="1953" Vol="42" No="13" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 1 Deireadh Fómhair 1953" DateEnglish="Thursday, 1 October 1953" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="933">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="933" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Has there been some arrangement about the taking of the Seanad Electoral (Panel Members) Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, it has been agreed that the Bill will be taken at 5.30 in the hope that it will be finished by 6 o'clock and after that we will resume the consideration of the Health Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Health Bill," RHead="1952&mdash;Committee (Resumed)">
    <Title>Health Bill, 1952&mdash;Committee (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That Section 16 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Health (Dr. Ryan) James Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Health (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I was asked about certain figures with regard to the number of beds available for maternity cases.  I gave some figures in the Dáil when this matter was under discussion.  I have not checked up on it, but I think there might be a few additional beds since then.  At that time the number available for maternity cases in hospitals was 1,112.  On the basis of each bed accommodating 25 women in the year, which is about a fortnight roughly per person, these beds will accommodate 44 per cent. of the maternity cases in the country.  In addition to that there were 640 private maternity home beds and they would accommodate 24 per cent., making a total of 68 per cent., a figure which, as I said yesterday, compares very favourably with the number of beds available in Great Britain or the Scandinavian countries which are supposed to be very well hospitalised.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="934" /> In addition to that, we have authorised in the Department of Health the building of certain new hospitals and the addition of beds to county hospitals which will provide an additional 550 beds.  It will, of course, take a few years to get these completed. Some of them will be ready to come into use before the end of the year and some next year.  I think the last of these 550 beds will be probably those in the Coombe Hospital which, I expect, will be ready in about four years' time.  When these are provided there will be accommodation for 89 per cent. of the maternity cases in the country, so that only 11 per cent., therefore, will have to remain at home.  These beds, I think, will be more than sufficient to meet any demand there may be for hospital accommodation for maternity cases.</P>
    <P>Other interesting figures which I looked up last night are with regard to the number of cases which have been dealt with by the three maternity hospitals in Dublin.  On their own figures as supplied for the <i>Hospital Year Book,</i> in 1951 the Rotunda Hospital dealt with 4,000 cases in the hospital and with 2,000 cases on the district outside; that is, domiciliary treatment.  The National Maternity Hospital, Holles Street, dealt with 4,150 indoor and 400 outdoor.  With regard to the Coombe Hospital, I have not got the figures for the same year, but in 1952, 2,250 cases were accommodated in the hospital and 750 on the district.</P>
    <P>It will be observed from these figures that in the case of the Rotunda, which deals principally with the north city, one out of every three was dealt with on the district in their own homes.  In the case of Holles Street, one case out of 11 was dealt with on the district, and in regard to the Coombe, practically one in two&mdash;17 to 22.  A small number, about one in two, was dealt with off the district and the remainder in the hospital itself.  It is not easy to explain in the case of the Rotunda and the Coombe why such a big proportion should be dealt with in a domiciliary way and such a small proportion dealt with in Holles Street, because if you take it from <Col N="935" /> what you might call the social point of view of the fitness of the house for delivery at home, you would imagine that Holles Street would be better situated than the other two hospitals. Both the Coombe and the Rotunda Hospitals are situated in the middle of the slum area of the city.  Holles Street is a bit outside the slum area and is, therefore, in a district where the houses are better on the average than the houses in the vicinity of either the Rotunda or the Coombe. However, it is sometimes very hard to explain these things, but that is the position.</P>
    <P>There were a few other points raised last night.  Senator Cunningham told us that in France they give a lump sum of £30 to a woman in confinement.  Of course, there is no use comparing France with this country because if we had the same fertility rate here as they have in France we could afford to give £30.  Fortunately or unfortunately, perhaps, our fertility rate is different.  Therefore, we could not deal with the matter on those lines.</P>
    <P>There is one point to which, perhaps, we have not adverted in this discussion as to whether there will be more and more cases applying for hospital accommodation rather than have the maternity take place at home.  Undoubtedly, there is a tendency that way.  The reasons given by certain Senators were the domestic difficulties with regard to domestic help, and so on.  As some Senator very aptly put it, a woman with two or three children who would, perhaps, find it impossible to get domestic help could not have her baby at home but she might succeed in getting her baby placed with her mother or her mother-in-law.  That is a tendency and the Bill will not interfere with that.  The tendency may continue to grow.  The Bill has nothing to do with that.  So far as the Bill is concerned it would pay the woman and her husband as well if she had the baby at home as if she had it in hospital. We are not interfering with that tendency in any way.  Indeed, I should like, if possible, to alter that tendency and make it more attractive <Col N="936" /> to have domiciliary treatment as far as possible.</P>
    <P>I think that the best way to do that is to try and induce the doctor concerned to keep the woman at home rather than send her to hospital.  The best way to do that is to pay the doctors better if they look after the baby at home.  That might have some effect.  That will be the scheme as far as it goes.</P>
    <P>I am afraid that giving a grant, as was advocated, I think, by Senator Cunningham, to a woman in the case of maternity is not going to cover the case as we want to cover it from the health point of view.  It is all very well to give a grant to the woman who is a truly provident woman and her husband.  They will probably spend that money on her maternity and on clothes for the children and so on, but I think that Senators will agree that if you give a grant to certain young married people who are expecting a baby the money may be spent before the baby comes at all and then we may have to do something about the maternity.  I think it is better that we should provide that the woman will be looked after in the case of maternity.  As far as the grant is concerned, that is different.  There is a grant of £4 for women in the lower income group.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>When do you give that &mdash;after the arrival of the baby?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be given at that time, either the day before or the day after.  I do not know.  It will be given around that time.  It is designed to help the woman to buy clothes for the baby, but whether she will spend it in that manner I do not know, but she will get that £4 into her hands.  It was put to me by certain people who advised me in regard to that scheme that if she has her baby at home and if she gets the £4, in all probability it will be spent on entertaining her friends when they call to see her.  We cannot help that.  If it is spent in that way 75 per cent. of it will come into the revenue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Some Senator also said&mdash;as a matter of fact, I think it was Senator <Col N="937" /> O'Higgins&mdash;that this particular section could not be operated for three or four years.  I must say that I cannot see that.  Let us say that the appointed day is the 1st April&mdash;I do not know whether we will be ready for that; regulations will have to be framed&mdash; and that we have the regulations ready for Section 16 to bring the maternity scheme into operation and that we make the Order before the 1st April.  In such an event the local authorities will be in a position to operate the scheme if they so wish.  I do not see what is to prevent local authorities from operating the scheme from that particular date.</P>
    <P>They will have to get the doctors to agree to work the scheme.  That may be done centrally.  If the I.M.A., apart from their non-co-operative attitude, are prepared to talk to me about what terms should be offered to medical men in this particular scheme when the Bill becomes law, then we might be able to make a national agreement with doctors who will participate in this scheme.  There should be no great difficulty then in having the local authorities operate it.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Higgins also said he noted that there was not a choice of doctor. He took the very extreme example of a dispensary doctor in a remote district. Admittedly, a choice of doctor is difficult in that case but it is not impossible.  These districts do not cover the great majority of the population. The great majority of the population is situated either in towns or at any rate in places within ten or 12 miles of a town or village, and there will be a choice of doctor for the great majority, even for those women in the remote districts.  They may have a sister, a mother or a mother-in-law living in a town and they may be quite free to take up residence in the house of the sister, mother or mother-in-law for the period of their confinement. They will have a choice of doctor in that way.</P>
    <P>That also covers, I think, the answer to the query that was put by, I think, Senator O'Reilly when he mentioned a person living in a town which is situated between three different counties. <Col N="938" /> All that the section says is that the doctor must have an agreement with the local authority.  If Senators think over it, it is obvious, I think, that the local authority concerned must have an agreement with the doctor, but there is nothing to prevent them having an agreement with doctors outside their own county.  Let us take an extreme case.  Take the case of a woman living in the County Kerry and that her mother, let us say, lives in the County Kildare.  If she likes she may go back to her mother, have her baby at her home and she can make an agreement with her doctor there.  All that the doctor there has to do is to write to the secretary of the Kerry County Council and to say: &ldquo;I want to be put on your panel.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Supposing her mother also lives in the County Kerry as she may?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Then, of course, there is difficulty.  They all live in the County Kerry.  I am answering a question about a woman who goes outside her own county.  The point that Senator O'Reilly made was that we should change the words &ldquo;the local authority&rdquo; to &ldquo;a local authority.&rdquo;  I think we will have to keep to the words &ldquo;the local authority.&rdquo;  I was taking, for example, a case in the County Kerry.  In that case, Kerry will pay the bill and there is nothing to prevent it paying the bill.  If the doctor in the County Kildare, or in any other county, formally writes to the secretary of the Kerry County Council and says: &ldquo;I want to be put on your panel,&rdquo; that is the end of it. Having got an acknowledgment to his letter, he treats this lady who has come up from Kerry to live with her mother and when everything is over he sends in his bill and gets paid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not think any difficulty will arise about a doctor living outside a county.  Of course, there is no doubt but that many women will be inclined to come to Dublin for their confinements. If they do, they can go to a doctor in Dublin.  All he has to do is to write to the county concerned and say: &ldquo;I want to be put on your panel.&rdquo; When he does that, he is all right as <Col N="939" /> far as getting his remuneration is concerned.</P>
    <P>The question was also asked: &ldquo;Who is going to decide who will go to hospital?&rdquo; The first thing that happens is that the woman who is about to be confined selects a doctor off the panel. She goes to him and tells him that she is expecting a baby and asks him to look after her.  He says he will do that.  He is then in sole charge.  If he says to her that she can have her baby at home, well that is the end of it.  But if she says that she would prefer to go to hospital&mdash;I suppose we may not have doctors with the moral courage to resist&mdash;but if we have a doctor who will resist and say: &ldquo;You must stay at home,&rdquo; then she must stay at home if she wants to come under the scheme.  If, on the other hand, he says: &ldquo;Yes, I am going to send her to hospital,&rdquo; it is he who decides.</P>
    <P>No one but the doctor decides whether she goes to hospital or not. Suppose he decides that she is to go to hospital, he knows probably, and, if not, he gets in touch with the local authority, what hospitals are on the list for this county and he selects a hospital for his patient.  If a bed can be found in that hospital, then that is decided, as far as that is concerned. If, however, there is no bed available in that hospital, then the woman must go to some other hospital.  That is all.</P>
    <P>I think that what I have said covers the queries that have been raised on this particular section.  I think myself that there is a rather unwarranted anxiety about the possibility of working this section.  I do not think there is any difficulty whatever if the I.M.A. would be helpful, if they would co-operate and negotiate for a settlement with regard to what they should be paid.  If they do not, then I suppose all we can do is to put in advertisements for doctors who are prepared to work under this particular scheme.  But, once having got doctors to work the scheme and having them on the panel of the local authority, women will get to know who these doctors are.  Then, I think, the <Col N="940" /> scheme will work fairly smoothly.  I want Senators to keep in mind that it is the doctor, and nobody else but the doctor, who takes on a woman who is in sole charge, and of saying whether she will have her baby at home or whether she will go to hospital.  If he says that the woman must go to hospital that is the end of it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Suppose there is no bed, who is in control then?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>If there is no bed there will be a bed found, I hope.  We have been working in this country now for a long time.  Work has been going on here as long as the Senator and I can remember.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>And before our time, too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The country has gone on during all that time and if people wanted a bed badly they got it.  We are going to provide more beds.  The Senator should not be raising what are, if you like, unreal difficulties.  I cannot see how any Senator can argue that there will be more beds required as a result of this Bill than there are at the moment.  Apart from this Bill, it must be admitted, I think, that there is the tendency to-day for people to want to go to hospital.  A lot of women want to go to hospital now who did not want to go there before.  I think I could argue, as far as this Bill is concerned, that it is going to ease that position a bit because at least we can now say to a woman: &ldquo;If you stay at home we will pay the doctor; we will pay the nurse and we will pay your chemist's bill; we will pay all that for you if you stay at home.&rdquo;  That certainly should be some inducement to a woman to stay at home if she can manage it at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has made a great number of promises in regard to maternity hospitals.  He has, in fact, promised more beds.  We have been listening to these promises for at least 20 years, but apart from the National Maternity Hospital nothing has been done.  I, unfortunately, was not here in time to hear <Col N="941" /> the figures which the Minister gave in regard to maternity beds in this country.  Somebody else will deal with them.  I very much doubt their accuracy.  If the Minister was so anxious to provide maternity beds for patients why has he been so slow, or why have the Departments under the various Governments that we have had in this country, been so slow in providing the beds?  Plans for maternity hospitals were drawn up years ago.  The Coombe Maternity Hospital was promised a new hospital long before the last war.  So far nothing has been done.  They are still working on plans.  New plans had to be made because the old ones had to be scrapped.  New sites had to be found.  All that has been going on. Why has not the maternity hospital in Galway been built?  They started on that, but all they have is a small unit. They have not a proper maternity hospital there.  Why did they stop building the maternity hospital in Limerick some months ago?  That is held up. We have had all these promises.</P>
      <P>The Minister said that the beds in the local authority hospitals for maternity cases amount to 1,112.  I should like him to specify where they are.  I have been in charge of a maternity hospital in this town and time and again I am rung up from the country to say that they had no beds down there for their maternity patients.  So far as those parts of the country are concerned, are those beds in the county homes or are they in the county hospitals?  Where are they?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not wish to detain the House by recalling some of the things which have been happening with regard to maternity patients in the country, of patients being sent from the county home to the county hospital and from the county hospital back to the county home and then back to the doctor to take the patient&mdash;the patient having been in an ambulance for hours.  As regards nursing homes, the figure of 640 beds has been given.  Why should patients go to a nursing home if they can get treatment free in a hospital? The total of 1,152 beds has been given. The figure is absurd.  The Minister is very native and has a great facility for <Col N="942" /> turning an argument or a figure in his own favour.  He spoke of the Dublin maternity hospitals and the number of cases they deal with and why it is that one hospital will deal with a higher percentage of cases than another hospital. The Dublin maternity hospitals are in three districts.  The Rotunda deals with most of the north side.  You find by far the biggest number of the working class people living on the north side of the river and the Rotunda serves that district.  The Minister said that one in three of these patients stays at home.  A lot of these patients have always stayed at home.  Some of them will in future but the tendency has been there to go into hospital.  I know that perfectly well because I visit the Rotunda several times a year. I go there to conduct examinations and I see patients lying on trolleys in the corridors waiting for somebody to vacate a bed.  The Rotunda has been concerned for years in trying to select patients as between those who should go in and those who could stay at home.  If all the patients who wanted to go in did so there would be something like 5,000 and not 4,000.</P>
    <P>The position in regard to the Rotunda Hospital would be much worse were it not for the fact that we have the National Maternity Hospital on the other side of the city.  The National Maternity Hospital has about the same number of beds as the Rotunda and the district which it serves is entirely different from that served by the Rotunda.  There are not so many working class people there although there were years ago.  When I was much younger I worked in that hospital as an assistant.  I knew the district very well down by the docks, the tenements, and so on.  There were all kinds of houses and a very large number of people lived there.  You may remember between 1930 and 1938 or so a lot of these places were pulled down and the people were evacuated mostly out to Crumlin and the population of that district has dropped.</P>
    <P>If the Minister had inquired as to where the patients in the National Maternity Hospital come from he would find that a very high percentage of them come from the north side of <Col N="943" /> the city because they know they cannot get into the Rotunda.  If he is anxious to get the figures I am sure we could give them.  We have a very small district of people living around us.  We have only something over 400 deliveries in the district in the year but a very big number in the hospital because they come from all over the place, from the county and from the country.</P>
    <P>The Minister has tried to make the point that the Rotunda encourage the patients to stay at home and that the National Maternity Hospital take all they can in and do not encourage them to stay on the district.  If we had 50 more beds in the National Maternity Hospital we would still have a certain number on the district.  The Coombe Hospital is in exactly the same position. They are in a big area where there are poor patients.  They cannot take in any more than they do and they have a very high percentage of patients living around the district who cannot get into the hospital.  These are plain facts and anybody who wishes to inquire further into them can do so.</P>
    <P>According to the Minister, this Bill encourages patients to stay at home, because the patient's doctor will be paid, the patient's nurse and chemist's bill will be paid and the patient will be given £4 to spend.  However, in regard to the patient who comes into the maternity hospital, her doctor is paid, her nursing and chemist bills are paid.  It is all free and she is also given £4 to spend, whereas the patient who remains at home has to be looked after.  The nurse does not stay all day; someone has to cook for her and look after her children; she has to provide linen, light, heat and everything else that is necessary.  Which patient is worse off?  All that is provided free in hospital, but the patient in her own home has much more expenditure and the encouragement she is getting is £4 into her hand.</P>
    <P>The Minister referred to the point I made in regard to patients in France getting a grant of £30.  The French people were anxious to increase the <Col N="944" /> birth rate and they therefore gave this inducement.  Surely the Minister does not think that handing 30,000 frances into a patient's hand to spend as she likes is the method that was adopted.  Nobody would be crazy enough to suggest that.  The patient is given this money in the form of grants.  Her doctor's fee is guaranteed to a certain figure; the hospital and nursing fees are also guaranteed to a certain degree and she gets a certain allowance to spend.  The Minister condemns this method of giving money to spend, although he himself proposes to give them £4.  I think the patient should get some money to spend as she thinks fit, but if you gave a sum of £30 to a patient for confinement you would not hand it as cash into her hand.  It was never suggested that you should.  Under the insurance scheme you do not.</P>
    <P>Then the Minister went on to introduce something which I think is dreadful.  He suggested paying a doctor more if the patient could be encouraged to stay in her own home. That is a dreadful thing to do.  It would mean that the doctor would be anxious for the patient to stay at home because he would get more money.  That inducement might balance his better judgment in regard to sending that patient to hospital if he thought she should be sent.  That is a very wrong attitude.  Why should a doctor be paid more to encourage a patient to stay at home?  It is imposing a strain on the doctor which is unfair.</P>
    <P>The suggestion was also made by the Minister that if the members of the Medical Association are prepared to go down and talk to him he will settle all this business up and everything will be grand.  We have talked with the Minister several times and what it amounts to is this.  We approach the Minister with a few little points on which we do not agree.  Having consulted the Minister, if we agree with him he will then tell us what he is going to pay the doctors.  It is there in the Bill.  He has the power.  The Minister is the dictator.  He can tell us and that is what you call consultation <Col N="945" /> with the Minister.  If we agree with him he will tell us how kind he is going to be to us.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not wish to intervene in the discussion on this particular section except that reference has been made by Senator Cunningham to the Galway Maternity Hospital.  I would like, as one of the representatives coming from Galway, to make it quite clear to the members of the Seanad that as far as the Galway County Council and Galway health authority are concerned they have been in the past and are at the present one of the foremost health authorities in the country in making provision for both maternity services and sanatoria and every other medical provision that can possibly be made in the county. There was what the majority of us will refer to as undue delay in going ahead with the erection of the Galway Regional Hospital, and I have no hesitation in stating here or elsewhere that that delay was in the main due to no other section of the community than to the medical profession.  I attended meetings of the Galway Board of Health, as it was at the time; an architect was appointed, plans were drawn up&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>When?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Plans were submitted to the board of health and on every occasion that such plans were submitted there was one or other of the medical profession who attend the Galway Central Hospital, as it was then and is now, who queried or questioned or suggested that certain alterations should be made in regard to the particular section they themselves were in charge of.  As a result, there were innumerable alterations and each alteration&mdash;as every member of this House who is on a local authority knows&mdash;took up considerable time.  If there was delay in having the work put under way in Galway, it can be laid only on the people concerned. There is a new maternity hospital erected in Galway.  Not alone has it been in operation for quite a considerable time, even prior to the war, but the regional hospital which has cost <Col N="946" /> over £1,000,000 is completed and about to be opened one of these days; apart altogether from the fact that a regional sanatorium has been erected there inside the last few years at a cost of another £1,000,000.</P>
      <P>I do not think it is right for any Senator&mdash;and particularly a Senator occupying the position of Senator Cunningham&mdash;to get up in this House or elsewhere and accuse, as has been the case, a local authority that has lived up to its responsibility so well as Galway health authority or county council has in the past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>My accusation was not against the local authority.  I asked the question why the Galway maternity hospital has not been built.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been built.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Completely?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>That is news to me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>All the Senator's information it not as up-to-date as he expected it would be or should be.  I have a feeling, having listened to the discussion on the various sections of this Bill both to-day and yesterday, that much of what has been said would bear better fruit if it were put forward by the spokesmen of the medical profession in consultation with the Minister and that more good would have come from it than can be expected to come from many of the statements that must be taken as representative of the medical profession here in the last few days.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Cunningham queried the Minister's figure in relation to the number of women who were treated in maternity hospitals in Dublin, but there is one question in connection with this matter on which I would like to have a figure from him.  Apart altogether from the number of persons treated in hospitals and treated by the staffs of hospitals in their homes, the most important figure to have is that of the number of women who were turned away because of lack of hospital <Col N="947" /> accommodation, who should have had accommodation in the hospital, rather than be compelled to have their babies at home.  Can Senator Cunningham justifiably give one concrete case where a woman presented herself for admission to either of the maternity hospitals in the city or in any part of the country, and where the doctor in charge of the maternity hospital was quite satisfied that that was a case that should receive hospital treatment&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I never said that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the question I am putting&mdash;with that knowledge, from his experience and from his skill in his profession, being satisfied that this case should have hospital treatment and because he had not that accommodation at his command, that person was turned away and allowed to have her baby at home with consequences that, as Senator Cunningham has pointed out in many of his statements here, might result in the death of that person?  If that has been the case, has it not taken Senator Cunningham and those associated with him quite a long time to go to the Minister or to the Department or to the public in general and point out this state of affairs, that nothing has been done in this country for the last 20 years in providing maternity hospitals and hospitals of that kind?  This attack has been held back and this vital knowledge has been kept from the people.  I have no doubt that if a man in Senator Cunningham's position in his profession made known the position to the people, money would not be the obstacle in providing the accommodation. It has all been held back.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I look rather scantily at the various papers published in this country from time to time and I have not seen the medical profession or any individual of it making known these facts to the people, saying that something should be done to provide the hospitals&mdash; until this Bill is introduced.  Then we have a suggestion made at various times in this House and elsewhere that this Bill is not worth the paper it is <Col N="948" /> written on, until such time as the accommodation Senator Cunningham proposes is provided.  The worse case that any person could make is an exaggerated case, as he is not going to get such support he might get for a reasoned case.  That is what Senator Cunningham has set out to do in his approach to this Bill.</P>
    <P>Senator Cunningham took the Minister to task for suggesting that the provisions of the Bill will help to encourage those women who can stay at home to do so and that the provision made in it will also influence the doctor to encourage people to stay, as the doctor's bill, the chemist's bill and the nurse's bill will be paid.  We do not live in the clouds.  Most of us live amongst the working-class people of the country and know their conditions and what influences them to avail of facilities that are provided.  I know from the greater part of the people that I meet in my particular locality, those of them who do go to a maternity hospital go there because of the free service which they would not get at home.  Quite the majority of the women I know would prefer to stay at home if they were assured they would get the free service and would not afterwards be presented with a nurse's bill, a doctor's bill and various other bills that might arise out of the particular case.  Senator Cunningham, having less confidence in his colleagues than we ordinary people have, suggests that because the doctor is going to receive some slight increase in remuneration from attending such a case, he will encourage them to stay at home for no other reason, not to relieve congestion and not because the home conditions would be better for the woman concerned.  Senator Cunningham has definitely stated that the fact that the doctor is going to receive more for attending a woman in her own home is going to influence him because of that extra remuneration to advise her to stay at home.  I do not believe any man in this country would do it despite what Senator Cunningham suggests.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a very difficult matter, obviously, for a layman to <Col N="949" /> enter into a discussion on this question as the Senator who just sat down has demonstrated.  I am quite satisfied the House would agree with me that he has made no contribution whatever towards clarifying the difficulties which confront us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Who made no contribution?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Hawkins.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, we will wait for it now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>If I make a contribution it will not be my first intervention and I will at least try to be as reasonable and as intelligent about this as it is possible for me to be.  I think that, irrespective of the side of the House on which one sits, we must all agree that Senator Cunningham has made a tremendous contribution to this discussion, and, further, has made the type of contribution that ought to be welcomed in this house, because he has spoken about something which he knows and which is part of his being. He is talking about the work of his profession in the way we know a master who understands his work talks.  He is putting the benefit of his enlightened experience before the House.  I think it is a magnificent thing to have a man as busy as Senator Cunningham is known to be in his profession prepared to come into the Oireachtas and give us the value of his experience.  It would be better for the Oireachtas if there were more people like him and the Oireachtas would be a better place if there were more like him in it, but they will not be encouraged to come in here by the kind of approach that Senator Hawkins made to the suggestions that were put to the House.  I am rather surprised at Senator Hawkins.  On the whole, one can find little fault with him, but I do not know what has taken him to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Senator would now discuss Section 16?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, Sir.  It is very difficult to discuss it in the light of the speech made by Senator Hawkins. <Col N="950" /> The Minister will recall that I put a query to him and he has not yet answered it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>What is it?  I will answer it if I can.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I am going to try to get an answer to it before I leave the House.  We go back to the beginning. When is this part of the Bill going to come into operation?  The Minister has indicated that he hopes to be able to make a start on it on the 1st April, he said.  I have tried to elicit from the Minister what is to be the position of a local health authority if he commands that they will provide certain facilities and it is beyond their capacity to do so.  If patients suffer in consequence, if either serious injury or death results because this service cannot be provided for the people whom the Minister declares are to have it, does an action lie against the authority as a consequence?  I am not a lawyer but I would like to know the position.  Senator Cunningham indicated he has fears as to where the doctor would stand in this regard.  I must confess that the Minister was unconvincing so far as I was concerned. There was an air of unreality in the case which he made, when I thought of conditions and what they are like as I know them to be myself in the area which is to be the Cavan health area in the future&mdash;and the Minister earlier admitted that Cavan seemed to be a rather different problem or a peculiar problem inasmuch as there were demands for hospital treatment there beyond the capacity of the hospitals. That position is there and is going to be there after the 1st April. It is all very fine for Senator Hawkins to stand up and proclaim to the country the magnificent achievements of the Galway County Council and the Galway health authority.  Where did they get the money?  Did these millions come from the rates of Galway or from the sweepstakes?  If you got them the other way you got something that we have not got and of which many other counties are just as badly in need and unable to secure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If you have a maternity hospital near completion in Galway which <Col N="951" /> costs £1,000,000 and which was started during the régime of the inter-Party Government, where did the money come from?  If there was another type of hospital built earlier in Galway where did the money come from? Fourteen years ago Cavan health authority purchased a site to build a hospital and not one stone has been put upon a stone yet and when some time ago we asked the Minister to receive a deputation from Cavan County Council he did not absolutely turn us down&mdash;he rarely does that; he is always ready to listen and on the whole he is always ready to receive people and not ungraciously either&mdash; but he indicated to Cavan County Council that there did not seem to be any hope of anything being done until after the five-year period or the seven-year period and that they would be wasting their time.  Yesterday he admitted that there was a peculiar problem in Cavan.  I put it to the Minister&mdash;where are we going to find beds for maternity cases in our circumstances at present and what are to be the consequences in a county like mine?  I am quite certain that if other Senators told of local conditions in their counties they could tell the same story because we are not the least progressive in Cavan in regard to the reconstruction of our hospitals since the early days of this State.  I cannot see how we can meet the demands of the Minister in this and I am concerned and perturbed about it.</P>
    <P>I would like to have this further information from the Minister.  If he says we are going to start on the 1st April, when is he going to make his Order?  When is he going to indicate that he is going to start on the 1st April, because there will be financial commitments and as all members of local authorities know quite well it is not on the 1st April you levy your rates.  The estimates are prepared on the 1st January and it is at the February meeting that you strike the levy.  The Minister would have to have his mind made up by December as to when he is going to bring this part of the Act into operation.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="952" /> I feel that much of this is still in the air and we are not going to be able to bring it down to earth, because we have not the space to cater for the people who should be catered for.  I am not going to go into the case and the many points made by Senator Cunningham, but I see in my own part of the country the problem that is there.  You have one type of problem in my county.  On the other hand, I do not want to go too wide of the particular branch of the medical science under discussion, but at the last meeting of our county council we had an intimation that in the sanatorium in Cavan we are now going to have to treat patients from, I think, Westmeath and Longford, where they have no sanatorium to be treated at home.</P>
    <P>That is the problem all over the country, and when you have that position, much of the thing is in the air and however desirable it may be to do so when you try to bring it down to earth there is no place you can rest your cot.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The debate on this section provides a good example of the point I was trying to make yesterday. When this Bill passes into law it will effect nothing.  Nothing will happen until the Minister makes an Order putting the Bill into operation.  He may make an Order putting some part of the Bill into operation.  He may make an Order putting the Bill into operation in certain areas.  But even then nothing will happen until the Minister makes regulations.  The great difficulty in discussing this Bill is that it depends absolutely and entirely on the kind of regulations the Minister will make and the Minister has given no indication at any stage of what kind of regulation he will make.  Therefore, it is not possible for anybody, without knowing what the regulations will be, to discuss adequately what will happen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Cunningham, who is intimately experienced in the matters with which this section deals, can give a certain idea of what may happen but even he, despite his knowledge and <Col N="953" /> his experience, cannot adequately discuss this matter without knowing what the regulations will be.  The section is based entirely, as indeed is the whole Bill, upon the ground that the Minister will get the requisite powers&mdash;remember, the Bill is permissive&mdash;and that, having got those powers, he will then make regulations.  He is prepared to consult all kinds of people.  He is prepared to meet all kinds of people; he is prepared to be nice and gracious and sympathetic and pleasant, but he is not prepared to tell us anything and the main reason why he is not so prepared is because he himself does not know.  Nobody knows what the effects of the Bill will be and the Minister does not know what he will put into the regulations.</P>
    <P>I do not like intervening in a discussion between two medical men but this section, together with certain other sections, does offer an inducement to women to go into hospital rather than remain at home.  That appears to be quite clear.  The Minister says the reverse is true but, having said the reverse is true, he then says he could give a further inducement. What shocks me in the Minister's speech is the extraordinarily low standard he attributes to everybody, both doctors and expectant mothers. Surely it is not true to say that if doctors get a higher fee for attending patients in their own homes they will keep more and more women at home. That seems to me an astounding statement.</P>
    <P>Secondly, he pointed out that if expectant mothers got the grants they would spend the money foolishly on entertainment instead of keeping them for the purpose for which they were given.  I cannot visualise any section of our people setting themselves such a low standard or acting so foolishly as that.</P>
    <P>We may as well get on with the section because, until we see the regulations, we have really no idea what will happen.  It is quite clear that there is not a sufficient number of maternity beds.  It is quite clear that this section, together with other sections of the Bill, tends towards <Col N="954" /> more and more hospitalisation as distinct from treatment in the home. Under sub-section (4) a doctor practising maternity will have most of his practice taken from his unless he makes an agreement with the local authority and becomes to that extent the servant of the local authority.</P>
    <P>All through this Bill the fundamental aim is the nationalisation of medicine.  Doctors will work under regulations made by local authorities and those local authorities will in turn be responsible to the Minister.  The intention is to make doctors employees through the medium of agreements with local bodies.  I think that is a bad thing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to say a word about Cavan County Council.  I said yesterday that I knew there were sometimes 100 patients waiting in Cavan.  Nevertheless, there is a fairly good hospital there.  There is a fairly good hospital in Wexford.  Wexford has no county hospital such as Cavan has.  Surely Senators ought to have some consideration for the Minister for Health.  He cannot build all the hospitals simultaneously.  He has to spread the programme over 20 years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>That is agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Therefore, some will be done straightway and some will have to be left until later on.  A Minister for Health&mdash;it was not I who did it&mdash; picked out the areas where the hospital services were fairly good and decided they could afford to wait.  I was in Manorhamilton and I found the hospital there in an appalling position. A new hospital will be opened in Manorhamilton in the next few weeks. There are hospitals under construction in Longford, Carlow and Dundalk, but Senator Cunningham would give the impression we are doing nothing.  We are spending over £5,000,000 this year on hospitals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I was speaking about maternity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>If the British were spending £200,000,000 I am sure Senator Cunningham would tell us what they <Col N="955" /> were spending on hospitals, because he admires the British.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister must have a very weak case when he begins to wave the flag.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Did we not hear all about the British yesterday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>This is all so much nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Cunningham is a member of the Fine Gael Party.  He is always telling us what people are doing in other countries and accusing us of doing nothing here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>If it were not for the Fine Gael Party nothing would be done here.  Everything done here is based on what the Fine Gael Party did in the past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Cows in the distance have long horns.  Fine Gael never built a hospital.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>They built this State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>They took over the workhouses and when we came in in 1932 those institutions were in exactly the same condition as they were in when they were taken over ten years previously.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister not meet the case without losing his temper?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Cunningham says there has been no progress in hospital building for 20 years past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I was speaking about maternity hospitals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Cunningham said there was no progress.  I have a statement here showing what has been done in relation to maternity hospitals in every county.  Senator Cunningham was a member of the Joint Committee and the recommendation of that Committee was to add 100 beds to each of the three Dublin hospitals, 50 private <Col N="956" /> and 50 public.  Mark you, 50 private. That would give a total of 300 beds. He now says that if we add 550 beds we are adding too many because we are adding them all over the country and not just in Dublin.  Senator Cunningham has the Dublin hospital mentality.  He does not see why we should have 550 beds all over the country.  If we accepted the recommendation of the Joint Committee, of which he was a member, and added 50 private and 50 public beds to each of the three Dublin hospitals, that would be a grand thing.</P>
      <P>I said we would pay doctors at an increased figure for treating people in their own homes and that that would be an inducement to both doctors and patients to accept treatment in their own homes.  I am accused immediately of imputing low motives to doctors by Senator Cunningham and Senator Hayes.  I also said that if the maternity grant was given beforehand some of the women might spend it foolishly. I do not believe that every doctor would be influenced by what he would be paid.  Neither do I believe that every woman would spend the grant foolishly, but it might happen in some cases.  Will any Senator, even a Senator with his eye to propaganda in the way Senator Hayes has his, tell me that no woman would spend that money foolishly?  We know very well that some of them might.  Having spent the money, we would have to do something about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>What point is the Minister trying to make?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Hayes accused me of imputing low motives to women because they might spend the money foolishly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>That is if the grant is given before the birth actually takes place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Supposing we did&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Whoever would suppose that would be a stupid person.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>What can we do with the stupid person?  We must deliver the <Col N="957" /> baby even though the mother has been stupid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>But the stupid person would be the person who would give the grant before the baby arrived.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Because I said it would be stupid to do so, Senator Cunningham and Senator Hayes accused me of low motives.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Not at all.  You said they might spend it if you gave it to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course they might spend it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>It is on that you built your case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>If people get money to spend surely the Minister is not going to lay down the way they should spend it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No, but I say that she gets money because she is going to have a baby and the idea is that she would look after herself when she got it.  I say that if she gets this money she may call a party of her friends and say that she is going to have a baby and spend the money first and then we have to look after the baby.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not that the usual thing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Because I said that, I am accused of low motives by the propagandists in the Fine Gael Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>About the Irish Medical Association, Senator Cunningham says they will not meet me because, he says, if they do meet me and if they agree with me, I will say: &ldquo;Good men; it is all right now,&rdquo; and, if they do meet me and I say &ldquo;No,&rdquo; I am a dictator. Let us reverse the position.  If I meet them and agree with them, they will be the dictators.  That is what he wants, that they should be the dictators as to what should be done where they are very intimately concerned with regard to payment, and so on.  I think the doctors are a good body of men, just as good as the carpenters <Col N="958" /> or the plumbers or anybody else.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>They are just as good. We would not certainly call the carpenters together and say: &ldquo;I am not a dictator.  Whatever you say, we will give you.&rdquo;  They say: &ldquo;We want 14/- an hour,&rdquo; and I say: &ldquo;That is all right, you can have it.&rdquo;  That is what Senator Cunningham wants for the doctors.  I am not a dictator if I agree with whatever you say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Rubbish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>If I do not agree I am a dictator and, because I will not guarantee to agree beforehand, they will not meet me, they will not co-operate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I said nothing of the kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>But they said they will not co-operate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Minister is fair to himself in that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>They said publicly at their annual meeting that they would not co-operate in this Bill and Senator Cunningham says that, if I did agree, everything was well and good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say they would not meet you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>They said it.  I thought Senator Cunningham said they would not meet me.  That is a change.  I welcome that change.  Senator Baxter wants to know what will the local authority do if they are committed to do a thing and cannot do it.  Senator Baxter is always looking for difficulties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>It is important to look far ahead.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senator Baxter had been a Member of Parliament 75 years ago when a Bill was brought in to compel the local authorities to bury people he would have asked what would happen if there was a heavy frost.  He is always looking for difficulties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="959" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is merely evading answering my question by that sort of comment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no use in Senator Baxter putting questions like that.  If he were in my place, he would say that nothing can be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Minister ever heard of an action for negligence by a patient in hospital?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>He would say to the people: &ldquo;I cannot do anything because it may happen that in some particular case a person would go to the local authority and the local authority would say that they had no bed for the patient and the patient would take an injunction against them and get heavy damages.&rdquo;  It is a ridiculous question. He knows he is looking for ridiculous questions which do not deserve to be answered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister cannot answer, just as he cannot answer any other question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot answer.  If there were an epidemic and if 5,000 people in County Cavan got sick on the same night and came to the local authority, perhaps they would have an action against the local authority.  I do not know.  How can I answer that question? What can we do about it?  Are we going to wait, to say that we cannot go ahead and must drop this Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Are not you creating that legal situation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Then we must drop the Bill because we cannot do anything about it?  Senator Baxter is searching for difficult questions and because I cannot answer he says I am trying to evade.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I think you ought not to apply it.  That is my difficulty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We ought not to apply the Bill at all!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>In areas where its application is beyond the physical capacity of the hospitalisation facilities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>And where we have <Col N="960" /> hospitalisation as good as any other country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>We have not the space.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>County Cavan, of course, need not adopt this Bill for some time, if they like.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>If you say that, it is different.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>They can make arrangements with other hospitals at the moment.  In County Cavan, if a person comes whom they cannot accommodate in the county hospital, they can ring up some hospital in Dublin and send the patient there.  Why could not they continue to do that under the Bill? Why makes difficulties, as if it were impossible to do that?  When the Bill is passed they can continue the same thing as they do now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>They cannot.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not see why they should not.  My objection to some of the Senators who have spoken is that they are raising difficulties that nobody could possibly deal with because they are ridiculous difficulties.  They are raising difficulties giving instances of cases that may even happen at the moment and that have to be dealt with.  When the Bill is passed, cannot they deal with them in the same way?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no legal obligation on us to provide services for all these persons at the moment.  You are doubling the number of people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are adding certain people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>In my county there will be double the number.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like Senator Baxter to deal with this&mdash;suppose there is a person in the middle income group who is very ill and who will die to-night unless he can get into a hospital and suppose I do not pass the Bill, how does he propose that that man should be dealt with?  Does he think it is all right if the county manager could say: &ldquo;There is no legal <Col N="961" /> obligation on us.  You can go and die.&rdquo; If the Bill is passed there is a legal obligation.  Does Senator Baxter think he should die?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think anything of the kind, as the Minister knows.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the sort of question the Senator is putting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not.  Perhaps the Minister will give me a chance to put it to him again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Very well, I will.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry to intervene again, but there are just one or two points that I want to refer to.  One is of considerable importance and has not been previously ventilated. The Minister raised it and I think I should have permission to refer to it.  Before I do so I should like to refer very briefly to something that Senator Hawkins said, that was, why was it that the maternity hospitals did not make it known before now that they were so short of beds? It has appeared in the daily Press&mdash; not very frequently&mdash;we do not like to publicise these things; it does not help anybody.  If the Senator would read any report of any of the three Dublin maternity hospitals he will find it in every annual report going back goodness knows how many years.  He will find it mentioned in every annual report by the master of the hospital. These reports are published very punctually every year.  I am sure there is no reason why Senator Hawkins should read one but that condition of affairs is well known to the Department of Health for a number of years as the Minister will bear me out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister referred to the fact that I sat on the committee which recommended to the Department of Health that the Dublin maternity hospitals should be increased in size to the limit of 100 beds each.  The new Coombe Maternity Hospital, just about to be built, will contain 250 beds.  The present Rotunda and National Maternity Hospitals each contain about 150 beds.  In counting <Col N="962" /> the number of confinements in Dublin, the number of patients being refused admission, the number who will require admission in future with the growth of the city, we decided that we would require for these patients an additional 50 beds in the Rotunda and 50 in the National Maternity Hospital. Let the Coombe go on with its plan to build its hospital for 250.</P>
    <P>When the Department of Health was planning with the Coombe Hospital to build this new hospital they specified that a certain number of beds in the Coombe Hospital should be private beds.  The Minister, I am sure, will not contradict that.  They specified that a certain number should be private beds.  With that, I am in thorough agreement.  People know that for any surgical condition of a maternity case&mdash;I mentioned it yesterday&mdash;they are safer in a properly equipped hospital.  No nursing home, unless it is very big and deals with a big number of cases, can ever be as well equipped as a hospital.  Therefore, it has been the custom in various countries.  You will find it if you wish to go to Denmark for example&mdash;you can fly there without touching England. You will find it in Switzerland, where they have very up-to-date hospitals and in not very old hospitals on the Continent and in every hospital in America.  That is as it should be and as the Minister and his Department have recommended for the new Coombe Hospital, capable of dealing with any patient irrespective of her class or her ability to pay.  The wealthy man's wife is just as much entitled to the best service as the poor man's wife. The poor man's wife gets the best service at present, especially in maternity cases when she goes into hospital.  The well-to-do man's wife has to go to a nursing home and the hospital is better equipped to deal with an emergency than a nursing home.  If you have a nursing home, as recommended for the Coombe Hospital, attached to the hospital, you have all the services of the hospital like X-rays, laboratory, blood transfusions and all those things very readily available, and that is as it should be.  We have fallen very much behind in that way.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="963" /> There are only a few hospitals in the city like the Mater, Jervis Street, and Vincent's, which have nursing homes attached to the hospital.  We find that very helpful in dealing with the most difficult cases.  So it should be with maternity or with any hospital of any kind such as a mental hospital which can deal with all classes of patients.  Why should we stick to the old-fashioned idea that maternity hospitals as such are only for the poor? The Minister mentioned that, and it was our recommendation in the Coombe Hospital, to have a certain number of private beds&mdash;I have forgotten the exact number&mdash;but we recommend that for the benefit of patients paying rates and taxes there should be these private beds.  Other hospitals also should have some private beds and I stand by that.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 17.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 17 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Now Section 17 has to deal with infants.  This Section 17 includes all infants, as you will see if you read it carefully, and it is going to give rise to a certain amount of difficulty again.  For example, sometimes these infants, infants born in a maternity hospital or in the patient's home or in a private hospital under this Act, may if ill require special treatment or specialist treatment very often.  An infant specialist may have to be called.  You may find an infant specialist who has signed an agreement.  Some of these infants are rather difficult and peculiar cases.  As you can readily understand, some of them require surgical operation or very specialised medical treatment.  Now we find in every city and in every country that these operations are highly specialised ones and you will find very few men who are prepared to undertake to do them.</P>
      <P>There are certain operations which I have in mind which will turn up in one maternity hospital three or four or perhaps five times a year and you may have the same number in another.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="964" /> You will find there is probably only one surgeon, or at most two, that you can pick upon who has had experience and is capable of dealing with it.  If this surgeon has not signed an agreement, is independent, and likes to keep his independence and freedom, and has not signed this agreement to work under the Department of Health, can he be called to treat that infant?  If he has not signed an agreement, remember that you would not have a great choice of doctor here, and should he be called, will he be paid for treating that infant if there is nobody else who has signed an agreement available?  That is a point I want to raise which I would like the Minister to answer, please.</P>
    <P>As the Bill stands at present, the parent, in this case, of the infant has a choice of doctors.  If the infant is in one hospital and it is ill and its people select a doctor from another hospital and want him to come in there to treat or operate on or specially attend that infant, can they do so?  This is a very special point because if, say, an outside doctor can be called in to treat patients in a public hospital in the city it can give rise to a great deal of trouble and confusion.  As a rule all these patients in a hospital are treated by men on the staffs.  They have complete staffs in the maternity hospitals and they call in consultants where necessary.  If they are going to have people called in from one maternity hospital to another, this is going to be very upsetting to the staff. If the patient has the choice and demands that a doctor be taken from another hospital that is very difficult, and I want to know how the question of choice is to be applied in cases like that.</P>
    <P>Again if a patient is in a nursing home and if she has to pay the £2 and if her infant gets ill in that nursing home and the doctor wants an infant specialist to come in, and the patient now claims that she is being treated under this Bill and that, therefore, she is entitled to free treatment from the specialist called in, although she can well afford to pay for the treatment of the infant, can he refuse to go?  She is, remember, a patient who is entitled to <Col N="965" /> this treatment and she wants this doctor to come in to treat her under the Bill.  She is in a nursing home under a doctor.  Can a doctor who has not signed an agreement refuse to treat that patient because she is paying in the nursing home?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not sure if I have got the questions exactly, but the Senator will correct me if I have not got them correctly.  I think the first question is that if an infant is suffering from disease which requires very specialised treatment and if the mother is a paying patient being treated in hospital, can she employ a specialist not on the panel?  Is that the first question?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>No, the first question was if the infant requires very special treatment in the way of operation and the man capable of doing it is not on the panel.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, that is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>It was how he can be remunerated?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, that is a question that I think can be got over.  I am not going to say exactly at this stage how we are going to remunerate specialists of that type, but obviously they must be brought into the scheme somehow or other.  The local authority at the moment has power, so far as I understand, to employ specialists, to send their people to specialists if it is necessary, and I think that by an extension of that power the difficulty that is mentioned by the Senator may be got over.  At any rate, I think you may take it that the aim is to get the best possible treatment whatever it may be.  It would be, therefore, necessary to employ eminent specialists if necessary in any particular cases. Number two, I think, is where the patient chooses her own hospital, can she ask for a specialist not attached to that hospital?  I would say &ldquo;no&rdquo;, because the position there is that under Section 25 a patient can choose her own hospital, but she chooses that hospital, of course, naturally under agreement with the hospital concerned, <Col N="966" /> and if the hospital concerned says: &ldquo;You came to us to be looked after by our doctors,&rdquo; that is the end of it and she cannot go further than that. So really it is a matter for the hospital. That is what it amount to.  The local authority take no further responsibility for the person who chooses her own hospital.  They say: &ldquo;We pay a certain amount, but that is all the responsibility we have.&rdquo;  It is a matter, therefore, for the person concerned and the hospital to make whatever agreement they like themselves.  At the moment, if a person goes to any particular hospital, he or she has to abide by whatever rules apply there.  If that hospital says: &ldquo;You cannot take in any outside specialist here,&rdquo; that is the end of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask the Minister a question in regard to sub-section (2) of this section.  This is a question which has been put to me and which I should like to hear the Minister answer.  A parent can choose a doctor from those who have made an agreement&mdash;that is, from the doctors on the list.  That much is quite clear.  Suppose that the doctor who has been chosen by the parent is uneasy in regard to this abnormal case and wants a consultation immediately, can he do so?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Even though that consultant might not be, for the time being, on the list?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to make it clear that I do not like to say &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; unconditionally there.  What happens at the moment is that the local authority have specialists on their panel.  In other words, they have an agreement with certain specialists.  I am not sure of the position in regard to gynaecology but, as regards ophthalmology and some other specialised branches of medicine, certain specialists agree to come and look after any case that may be referred to them.  That will continue. In fact, it may be extended to other specialists besides, for instance, ophthalmologists.  Radiology, orthopaedics and some other branches of <Col N="967" /> medicine have been dealt with so far. These specialists have been appointed by various counties.  In a few places, they have appointed a whole-time gynaecologist.  It has been the practice of councils to appoint specialists who are there for consultation with the ordinary practioner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Frankly, I am looking at this more or less from the point of view of my own experience.  I am trying to deal with this as a problem and, therefore, let us forget about this scheme for a moment.  The child is very ill and the doctor who has been called in by the parent is not happy and wants a consultation.  If the parent can pay and the doctor says that he is going to call in a certain specialist, the parent agrees to pay.  I want to translate that into the terms of free service under this Bill.  I want to know, in the case of a child who is very ill, if the doctor can&mdash;as I think he should be able to do&mdash;call in the best advice available, and, assuming that the parents cannot pay for it afterwards, there should be some way by which the doctor can receive reasonable payment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the intention, certainly.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 18.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 18 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>This section is very short and it reads as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;A health authority shall, in accordance with regulations, make available, without charge, at clinics, health centres or similar institutions, medical, surgical and nursing services for children under the age of six years.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Does that include all children?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, all children.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Irrespective of whether their parents come under the Act and irrespective of whether the infant was born under the Act?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="968" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I should put it this way.  The service will be available for all children as far as advice goes.  Whatever small treatment that might take place in the clinic would be free, but any subsequent treatment outside the clinic would come under Sections 14 and 15.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I realise that this is a small point, but how is surgical treatment to be given in the clinic?  I suppose it means minor surgical treatment.</P>
      <P>A very important point arises here in connection with children's hospitals. Remember that children's hospitals, wherever they are&mdash;we have a couple of them in Dublin&mdash;run what we call &ldquo;out-patients' departments&rdquo; or &ldquo;clinics,&rdquo; where the parents bring the children to be examined by the doctors and where treatment is prescribed for them.  That takes place in what used to be known as the dispensaries of these hospitals: we now call them out-patient departments or clinics.  A clinic is a place where you examine patients, investigate as far as you can, and then decide what is to be done.  These are run every day in all the children's hospitals.  Will the Minister explain to us the position under this Bill of these hospitals and these out-patients' departments that are run by these hospitals, because it is not quite clear?  I think they are not mentioned in the Bill and they are the departments that are doing most of the work in this city.  I should like to hear how they will be affected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator referring to maternity hospitals only?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I am referring specifically to children's hospitals such as Temple Street, Harcourt Street and the new hospital at Crumlin.  We have infant clinics in the maternity hospitals, too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to infant clinics in the maternity hospitals, some consultation has taken place between Dublin Corporation and the maternity hospitals.  A temporary arrangement has been made that the maternity hospitals would do the work for Dublin <Col N="969" /> Corporation.  If that arrangement works smoothly, it means that the problem for Dublin Corporation under this Bill is solved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>That is working.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us take, next, the children's hospitals.  There are two children's hospitals in this city and soon there will be a third.  They are voluntary hospitals.  They will be treated much the same, as far as any arrangement is made, as the ordinary general hospitals.  I have already pointed out, in reply to a question by Senator Baxter, that if, for instance, County Cavan had not room in the county hospital for a case or that if the medical men there thought it a case that could not very well be treated in the county hospital, then, in all probability, it would be sent to a Dublin hospital where there would be room or where some specialist treatment could be given.  The county would make an arrangement with the children's hospital or the general hospital, as the case might be, and send the patient along.  That will continue under this Bill except that a wider range of patients will be sent than have been sent in the past.  Otherwise, things will run much the same.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Dublin has only one what you might call local authority hospital and that is St. Kevin's.  It is not nearly large enough for its requirements.  Therefore, Dublin has to send most of its cases to the hospitals in the city. Dublin has a different type of arrangement with the voluntary hospitals&mdash;an arrangement which I am not sure can continue.  At any rate, it is there at the moment.  Instead of paying the capitation rate which is paid by county councils for their patients in voluntary hospitals, Dublin Corporation give a lump sum to the voluntary hospitals and expect the voluntary hospitals, in return, to take any patients that may be sent by the doctors.  In that way, Dublin Corporation get over their obligation to those in the lower income group who, at the moment, are public assistance patients. When this Bill comes into operation, Dublin Corporation, like the county <Col N="970" /> councils, will have to look after those in the middle income group in regard to hospitalisation.  I suppose they will make a somewhat similar agreement with the hospitals.  I suppose, too, that the hospitals will expect to get more from the corporation&mdash;but that is a matter for them&mdash;and that they will then send their patients along.</P>
    <P>I think the Senator mentioned out-patient departments.  A good deal of consideration has been given to the out-patient departments and it was proposed at one stage&mdash;I must say I thought it was a very good proposition, but naturally I do not know as much about these subjects as Senator Cunningham and men like him who are working in Dublin hospitals&mdash;that the patients should be screened before reaching them; in other words, that patients should reach them only as sent by the dispensary doctor and that people should not come direct to these hospitals.  In that way, the Dublin general hospitals in their out-patient departments would get the more difficult, the more specialised cases which could be dealt with more efficiently by the hospitals than by the dispensary doctor and which would, secondly, be more useful material for teaching than would be available in the ordinary cases which come along there. I do not know what progress has been made in that regard, but so far as I am concerned if the Dublin hospitals were still of the opinion that that should be done, they would certainly have my support.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I was interested to know what assistance the hospitals would get from the Department in connection with the work they are doing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I said yesterday that we were paying deficits to hospitals.  The deficit, in the first instance, is based on a number of beds occupied per week.  In the end, the deficit is paid under some other heading, but that is how we start.  Again, in that respect, it has been put to me on more than one occasion that we should also make some allowance for the number of patients treated outdoor.  We are considering that and I suppose that, in <Col N="971" /> all fairness, we should do something of the kind, because there may be a voluntary hospital with 100 beds and treating on the average 50 patients per day in the out-patient department and another hospital with 200 beds but treating only ten patients per day in the out-patient department.  In one case, the hospital is dealt with on the basis of 100 beds and, in the other, of 200 beds, and that is obviously unfair, because the hospital with 100 beds and treating a large number in the out-patient department have to supply dressings, medicines, heating, as well as time&mdash;of course, time is not charged for at the moment&mdash;and it is obviously unfair that that should not be allowed for.  It is a matter which is being considered at the moment.  If it should come that a payment would be made per bed per week to the voluntary hospitals, some consideration at that stage should also be given to the out-patient departments.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 19.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 19 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not very clear as to what &ldquo;treatment service&rdquo; in sub-section (3) means.  The sub-section reads:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Where a health authority are not satisfied that an adequate health examination and treatment service is available for pupils attending a school in their functional area which provides elementary education and is not a national school....&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The normal position in most private schools is that the school authorities know that the parents are in a position to provide and pay for medical services and if a child becomes ill, the doctor is sent for.  The child is sent home and the parents are able to, and in fact do, provide a doctor.  On the face of the sub-section, if I understand it correctly&mdash;I may not so understand it&mdash;it seems as though practically every private school will come under the section because they have not got in the school itself a treatment service. Each individual parent provides the <Col N="972" /> treatment service and therefore it would look as though the health authority was expected to provide for a health examination and treatment service&mdash;whatever that means; I take it that it means some kind of medical treatment&mdash;in every private school.  I do not think that is intended, but I do not know exactly what is intended, and I should be glad if the Minister would clarify the situation and say what exactly is intended in relation to the private school for small children whose parents are able to pay.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanRuane" hpid="Mr. S.T. Ruane Mr. S.T. Ruane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S.T. Ruane</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a phrase occurring with monotonous regularity in the Bill: &ldquo;A health authority shall, in accordance with regulations, make available, without charge ...&rdquo;  The peculiar aspect of this is that the local authority will have quite an amount to do with the operation of the Bill. Local authorities will have to collect the wherewithal, or part of the wherewithal, to make the Bill operate, if it ever operates, but members of local bodies have got no indication whatever as to the weight of this obligation on local finances.  We had some talk here yesterday on this question of something for nothing, and many of us have experience of the abuses which a something for nothing service may lead to.  Personally, I know of such a situation in relation to the administration of the scholarship scheme.  A local authority provided an <i>ex gratia</i> grant for the children of poor parents who had won scholarships and whose parents could not afford to provide the necessary equipment for the secondary school.  Several people for whom the concession was never intended applied for that grant and so manipulated &ldquo;pull&rdquo; on the local authority that they got it and a stage was reached at which the Government had to cut out the concession completely, with the result that poor parties suffered.  I visualise something similar happening under this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>So far as regulations are concerned, a local authority may refuse to carry out the regulations of the Minister. That may lead to a dissolution of the local body which will, in turn, lead to chaos.  Local authorities at present are very much concerned about the size of <Col N="973" /> local bills and the Party line-up, so far as expenditure is concerned, in different local bodies is not what it used to be.  For that reason, I should like to say that we are really legislating on lines of which the people who will have to pay know nothing of what the financial commitments may be.  They have not been taken into the confidence of the Government.  Round figures have been given&mdash;it may cost so much in the £&mdash;but the people generally have not got the remotest idea of what the administration of the Bill, when it becomes law, will cost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Sub-section (3) opens with a phrase: &ldquo;Where a health authority are not satisfied...&rdquo;  How is that to be determined?  Is it the county medical officer who will determine it?  What sort of investigation is to be carried out before it is determined that a service is not adequate, that the examination and treatment service available for children attending a school is not adequate? This function of the health authority is one which the health authority will be very chary and hesitant in undertaking. The school may be a convent school under the jurisdiction of a health authority, a school where there is a kindergarten to which children whose parents are able to provide a health service for the children themselves are sent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think that any health authority will be very hesitant before deciding that their officers should walk into a school without saying even as much as &ldquo;by your leave.&rdquo;  If anything like this is to be done, I would suggest to the Minister that he might amend the sub-section by inserting a clause to provide that this treatment would be made available after consultation with the educational authorities of that school.  Quite frankly, if I were a member of a health authority in my county and we had to consider the case of the school to which I have referred, where the children attending are receiving education which would be on the level of that received by children in the national school, the first thing I would suggest before any officer of ours put his foot inside the door <Col N="974" /> would be that he should go and consult with the authorities of that school. I suggest that a provision of that sort might be inserted in that sub-section because failing that, difficulties will have to be faced and they will not be pleasant difficulties.  I think there is still sufficient respect for educational institutions throughout the country to make members of local authorities rather hesitant about entering these institutions without any discussion beforehand&mdash;going in, as it were, armed with the big stick of the health authority and the Minister.  I think we should be very careful as to the way in which we use our legislation in this regard.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Department will have very much trouble in these private schools. I am quite in agreement that it is desirable that school children should be inspected but when you come to the private school where you have children whose parents are capable of looking after them, and generally do look after them well, I think that this question of forcing inspection on them in any way is very undesirable.  I am thoroughly in agreement with Senator Baxter on that point.  I think this whole paragraph is undesirable and that it should be deleted entirely. These people as a rule look after the children very well but even so I do not see any objection whatsoever in suggesting to the school, as has been done elsewhere, that they might have a medical man attached who would go in periodically and inspect the children.  That might be done but I do not think that they should be compelled or that there should be any dictation to the school from the Department of Health.  I think that would be very undesirable.  The Medical Association wrote to the Minister on this point and they asked him certain questions about it.  They asked, for example, as to how the authorities would know that the obligation imposed on the school was being fulfilled.  The sub-section says:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;Where a health authority are not satisfied that an adequate health examination and treatment service <Col N="975" /> is available for the pupils attending a school in a functional area, etc.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>We wrote and asked them how they proposed to be satisfied and what procedure they would take in order to be satisfied.  The reply we got was that it will be for the authorities of a school other than a national school and not for the teachers or parents&mdash;in other words, the authorities must satisfy the health authority in relation to the adequacy of any health examination and treatment or service provided in the school.  It is very definite that they must satisfy the Department that there is adequate examination and treatment.</P>
    <P>In reply to the second point they stated:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;It is expected that the authorities of the school and the health authorities will be able to come to a conclusion on these matters without questionnaires or inspectorial visits to the school.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That, to me, does not make sense.  I cannot understand how the Department of Health is going to be satisfied that the health examination in these schools is adequate and satisfactory without even inquiring about it.  Not only do they not intend to inquire about it but they do not even inspect. How then are they going to be satisfied? The thing is rather contradictory and I should like the Minister to clear it up.  I would appeal to him instead of dictating to these schools and threatening them with the mailed fist that he should encourage the schools.  I think in that way he will get plenty of co-operation and that he will find that there will be no difficulty in dealing with these private schools.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>First of all, if we want to be logical we should be satisfied that the health of children attending these private schools is being looked after as well as the health of children attending national schools.  It would be anomalous if we were to provide by law that regulations should be made to have children attending national schools examined and leave these <Col N="976" /> other children without any attention whatever.  Various suggestions were made to me when drafting this Bill. First of all, I took in even secondary schools and vocational schools as well as national schools, but when I came to consider the matter later, after various objections had been made, I thought the logical thing was to get some sort of uniformity for children whatever type of schools they might be attending.  I thought it better then to leave out secondary and vocational schools, but to have an examination carried out some time in all primary schools.  That is why these private schools are included.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>That is in regard to the examination.  It was about the treatment service I asked.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall deal with that matter in a moment.  Then there is the question of who determines.  As the letter to the Irish Medical Association says, we did not want to lay down hard and fast rules about serving notice because in most cases the county medical officer of health will hear probably whether or not the children are being looked after from the point of view of health.  If he is satisfied that they are being looked after, well and good.  If he is not satisfied he will probably ring up the headmaster or approach him in an informal way and state that he would like to have an assurance that things would be put right.  I am sure that after this second step, things will be put right but if things are not put right, he may have to serve a notice to have the examination carried out. I am just stating that to illustrate the way in which an effort will be made to have things put right informally before resorting to more formal steps. That is why we did not lay down that notice should be served by such a date and all that sort of procedure.</P>
      <P>The point is that if the local authority on the advice of the county medical officer of health says that they intend to carry out an examination then the manager must be informed under Section 32 sub-section (5) which says:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="977" />&ldquo;Without prejudice to the foregoing sub-sections of this section, a health authority shall consult the school manager of a school before determining the day or days on which and the time at which a health examination of children in the schools will be held and shall, so far as may be practicable, comply with the wishes of the school manager.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I do not think, therefore, that the school manager could have any great complaint, because, as I say, he will probably be approached, first of all, informally and asked to put things right.  If he does not, then an examination must be carried out and he will be consulted with regard to the date on which the examination will be held. It says here, as Senator Douglas has pointed out, not only examination but treatment.  The treatment covered here is only a very small matter.  It is only treatment which might be necessary on the spot.  We were advised that if we did not put in &ldquo;treatment&rdquo; a doctor going to a national school to carry out an examination if he found, let us say, that a child had just cut his finger and treated the child he might be in for trouble because he treated the child without permission.  &ldquo;Treatment&rdquo; is put in to cover that sort of minor treatment on the spot.  Any further treatment is dealt with in further sections.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Must not the school prove that they have somebody who will give this treatment?  That is in the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I know that.  In most schools, as Senators know, they have a matron or a nurse who looks after minor injuries.  Of course a doctor can be called in if necessary.  No health authority surely will insist that a doctor must be called in every day or must be there at all times.  It will be sufficient if there is a doctor who can be called upon if any further treatment is necessary.  Suppose a doctor, as a result of an examination in a national school or a private school, finds that there is some defect which would mean bad teeth, bad ears or <Col N="978" /> bad eyes or a malformation which would require orthopaedic treatment in the case of a national school pupil the treatment for any defect will be free.  It does not matter what family the national school pupil belongs to, the treatment for defects will be free, but nothing else will be free.  If, on the other hand, a doctor when examining pupils in a national school suspected, let us say, that a pupil had congenital heart disease&mdash;I think that would not be regarded as a defect&mdash; he would say to the pupil in that case: &ldquo;You had better get that treated.&rdquo; Whether that treatment would be free or not would depend on what group the child belonged to.</P>
      <P>Senators should understand that defects discovered in a national school examination will be treated free no matter what group the child belongs to.  As to other ailments, where the doctor concerned would say: &ldquo;You had better see the doctor,&rdquo; whether the treatment will be free will depend on what group the child belongs to.  In the case of children attending a private school, if there is anything wrong with pupils the medical examiner will say: &ldquo;You had better see the doctor,&rdquo; and these pupils would fall into their own particular group, whatever it might be, as regards payment.  That is how the question of payment will be determined.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>That seems to be reasonable except for the provision of treatment service.  I think most small private schools would be well advised to provide for examination.  I agree with the Minister that that is as desirable in a private school as in a public school.  But to provide treatment service in the case of a small sized school or kindergarten school would create some difficulties.  If it only means getting a bandage, that is a treatment service in the ordinary meaning of the words, but if there are serious defects which will have to be treated they should be treated by the doctor at the expense of the parents, not of the school.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is something in what the Senator says.  My anxiety was to put them exactly on a par with the national school pupils.  Perhaps it is <Col N="979" /> unfair to insist on it here.  I think however it would be interpreted as having a small first-aid set on the premises. In case we might have any medical officer of health who is a crank, I will consider taking it out on Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I think you would get co-operation for the rest of it if you took that out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I point out that sub-section (1) of Section 32 says: &ldquo;A health authority intending to arrange for a health examination of children at a school, under this Act, may give to the school manager of the school notice in writing of such intention...&rdquo;? The words there are &ldquo;may give&rdquo;; there is no obligation.  I think that whatever way you may deal with a national school these schools are in a slightly different category and that you ought to take account of that.  If the Minister is reconsidering the drafting of it he should consider the possibility of inserting in it some such words as I have suggested so that this would be done after consultation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Sub-section (5) of Section 32 says that they shall consult the manager and so on and try to meet his convenience if they possibly can. I should like to explain that we start off by saying &ldquo;they may&rdquo; because, as Senators know, the medical officer of health is going round the county, say County Cavan, and he knows all the parish priests and managers and if he meets one he may say: &ldquo;I will be round next week&rdquo;.  If the manager says: &ldquo;Come around next week&rdquo; there will be no trouble.  We do not say &ldquo;shall&rdquo;, because in that case he would have to send a formal notice, but if the manager insists on it he shall do that or if the manager does not agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be more proper to discuss that when we come to Section 32.  It seems to me, however, that the beginning of sub-section (5) is somewhat ambiguous. The question would arise as to whether sub-section (1) or sub-section (5) of Section 32 would be the prevailing <Col N="980" /> section and thereby a collision would occur.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We had better deal with that when we come to Section 32.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>That is why I think that when dealing with schools other than national schools you would require some different words.  I think you would get more co-operation by the insertion of the words &ldquo;after consultation&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister stated that he would give that consideration before the Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>That is with regard to treatment, but this is a different point.  The Minister says that he supposes what would happen is that the county medical officer of health would ring up or meet the manager but there might be some who would not have knowledge, as the Minister has, of the different methods of approach of county M.O.H.'s It would be unfortunate if you had a county M.O.H. who did not approach this in the right way and I feel strongly that there should be an obligation that this should be done after consultation.  I ask the Minister to look into that because people do not want the big stick held over them.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 20.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 6:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 6, line 39, to delete &ldquo;dental and ophthalmic&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;dental, ophthalmic and aural&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is consequential.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 20, as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>As a matter of drafting, Section 20 says that the charge for an appliance which has been broken or destroyed through neglect shall be as approved of or as directed by the Minister.  Is that particular <Col N="981" /> or general?  Surely it is not intended that the Minister shall make an Order for every specific case, but it seems to be worded like that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be a general Order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that clear from the wording?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it to the amendment the Senator refers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The section&mdash;the last words in Section 20.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Let me give an instance. At the moment the people in the lower income group are entitled to free spectacles.  If a lady is paying for spectacles for a child she will be able to train the child, even though it may be small, to mind them.  The child may break a couple of sets, but he will be trained eventually.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree entirely with what the Minister wants to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The parent may not bother about training the child and the intention is that we will charge 2/6 or 5/- for spectacles in the future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>That is one up for us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The intention is to have the parents train the child.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The intention of the section then is that the Minister will make a general recommendation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 21.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 7:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 9, line 4, to delete &ldquo;dental and ophthalmic&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;dental, ophthalmic and aural&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is consequential.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any idea as to the cost of this particular part of the Bill now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="982" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  I would not like to hazard a guess.  I think the dental section of this Bill is going to be comparatively costly.  Compared with the other things in the Bill, I believe it is one of the biggest items.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section, as amended, put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 22.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 22 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamFearon" hpid="Professor Fearon Professor Fearon">
      <NameTxt>Professor Fearon</NameTxt>
      <P>Suppose the Minister is dissatisfied with the responsible local authorities.  Some of the things in this Bill may be so large that they will not understand what they have let themselves in for.  I take it the Minister asks them to strike a rate to enable them to provide the services he requires.  Suppose they decline to strike that rate and make difficulties. Are the finances going to be made difficult?  What happens if the local authority does not come up to scratch?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I just want the Minister to reiterate what he said earlier with regard to these regulations.  These regulations are going to be sent to the local health authorities before they are implemented.  By the local health authorities I do not mean the executive officers.  I mean the members of the local authority, whoever these may be. I am not going to dwell upon this point at length as I have said enough about it already.  I merely want to add now that I am quite satisfied the Minister appreciates that in all the local authorities there are people who are interested in the improvement of the health services.  The way for him to achieve his end is to secure the co-operation of these people by passing on to them information and knowledge as to what he wants to do.  I suggest that he ought take steps to see that regulations that are being made by him under this Bill and which relate to the responsibilities of the health authority are put into the hands of every member of every local authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>In my view, Section 22 is one of the most important sections <Col N="983" /> in the Bill quite apart from the fact that it brings up the general question of this whole scheme depending practically entirely on ministerial regulations about which the Dáil knew nothing when they passed this Bill and about which the Seanad knows nothing at the moment.  I think it is quite clear from the characters of the section that the fate of this Bill in so far as it is going to be implemented or not depends entirely on Section 22.  Section 22 seems to me to provide that no matter what has gone earlier, no matter what benefits are referred to in Sections 14 to 21, they are not going to be provided unless the Minister makes regulations under this section and if they are to be provided they are only going to be provided to the extent that the Minister will direct in the regulations which he will make under Section 22.</P>
      <P>I want to put it plainly to the Minister.  What is the meaning of this particular section?  Has it any meaning? Does the Minister and do those supporting him intend that the services provided in Sections 14 to 21 are to be given?  If it is intended that those benefits are to be given, why is it necessary now in Section 22 to provide that the Minister may make regulations applicable to every health authority, every health authority of a particular class or a particular health authority not only as to the manner but also as to the extent to which they may make available the services already provided in this Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That seems to me to have been included as a possible way out&mdash;an escape&mdash;for the Minister or anyone succeeding him from implementing the services already provided in Sections 14 to 21.  I do not necessarily say at this stage that it is a bad thing for the Minister to have left himself a line of retreat, but I want to know is that the intention of this section? If it is not the intention of the section, why is the section included? Surely the section must mean that we are now limiting the extent of the services provided in the various sections from Section 14 to Section 21.  Not only are we limiting them, but we are providing, if we enact Section 22, for <Col N="984" /> the possibility that those services, first of all, may not be provided at all unless the Minister directs that they shall be provided.  Secondly, if they are to be provided, the people need not expect that they are going to be provided in the full measure about which so much boosting and boasting has been done, but that they will only be provided in the manner and to the extent that the Minister decides by the regulations he may make under this section.  None of us knows at the moment what these regulations will be.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to draw the attention of the Seanad to the wording of this section. It says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The Minister may make regulations applicable to every health authority, every health authority of a particular class or a particular health authority as to the manner in which and the extent to which they are to make available the services specified in Sections 14 to 21 of this Act....&rdquo;</P>
      <P>In other words, the Minister can dictate to any health authority.  He can tell them the manner in which and the extent to which they are to make available the services specified.  He can tell them exactly how they are to run their hospitals and the extent to which they are to run them.  He can, if he wishes, according to this Bill, nullify all the advantages already in the Bill.  He can wipe the whole thing out if he wishes.  The powers are there for him to do so.  A Minister for Health can do that under this Bill. The Bill gives him complete dictatorial powers in his control of the local authorities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have mentioned before that I do not think that that is a desirable thing in our national life and I do not think it is desirable at all where health is concerned.  It is very dangerous and objectionable.  The Minister has more or less accused me several times of attacking him.  I know the Minister's intention in that clause.  At the same time, any Minister, given the powers set out there, can do exactly as he likes.  He can cancel this whole business <Col N="985" /> if he wishes.  Perhaps I was unwise to mention anything about it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>There are two points which occur to me which, perhaps, I might plead as making the section necessary in this form.  I mentioned already that the Dublin Corporation had made an arrangement with the Dublin maternity hospitals with regard to infant treatment, examination and so on.  If I were to publish regulations dealing with infant treatment, I probably would have to make different regulations for the other counties from those for the City of Dublin.  I should say that it will be necessary to make regulations applying to particular authorities or to one particular authority.  We must have the power, I think, to make one regulation for one authority and another regulation for another authority.  The instance I have given shows that that will be necessary.</P>
      <P>As regards limited extent, I was asked about dental treatment.  I said that dental treatment was going to be a very big item.  Apart from being a very big item as regards cost, it is going to require a good deal of organisation.  Most counties at the moment have one or two dental surgeons employed.  They will want many more.  I do not know whether the counties will be inclined to employ more dental surgeons or, alternatively, contract with existing dental surgeons to do some work for them.  Personally, I would prefer the latter.  After all, if dental surgeons set up in practice in certain towns, they look forward to a fair remuneration from it to enable them to live, and so it would be unfair to take it from them.  I think it would be better for the local authorities to contract with these people to carry out certain duties for them on a sessional basis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have said sufficient, I think, about all the various possibilities as to how dental treatment can be carried out. It is possible that some counties will say that they are going to employ dental surgeons whole-time.  If so, you will have certain regulations applying to them.  Other counties will say that they are going to employ dental surgeons on a sessional basis.  We will <Col N="986" /> need to have other regulations applying to them.  Suppose we come to the conclusion that it is not possible to deal with the whole dental business at the moment, and maybe will not be possible for two or three years, we should at least try to keep teeth as good as they are.  In other words, we might prescribe conservative treatment and not do anything about dentures at the moment.  To the limited extent, therefore, of giving conservative treatment, we might make regulations and say: &ldquo;No dentures until we are ready that...&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There are various possibilities.  I think that if Senators would look at this from the point of view of the person who is very anxious to put the Bill into operation as soon as possible, with full regard, of course, to ordinary efficiency, they would come to the conclusion that there will have to be a great deal of latitude in the regulations, first of all, possibly by applying them to certain local authorities and not to others; and, secondly, in giving limited service in some cases where the full service cannot be given. On the whole, I think the section is necessary.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like the Minister to be honest with the House. Is it not a fact that this section puts into the Minister's hands the power to nullify every benefit given under the Bill, and that Section 22 empowers the Minister to cancel everything that has gone before it?  Is it not a fact that Section 22 leaves it entirely to the Minister, or to anyone who may succeed him, to decide whether this Bill is going to be implemented or not, and that, without any limitation as to time and without giving any remedy in law to a person who may be in receipt of benefits under the Bill, the Minister, or anyone who succeeds him, may cancel those benefits without giving notice to the recipients or to anybody else?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As far as I can see, every word that I have spoken with regard to the importance and effect of this section is true.  It is a matter of some surprise to me that Senators, sitting on the same side of the House as the Minister, <Col N="987" /> who were inclined to applaud every time the words &ldquo;Health Bill&rdquo; were mentioned, have never referred to this section.  As far as I can see, everything that has gone before is all &ldquo;cod&rdquo;, having regard to this section. Undoubtedly, it gives the Minister a stranglehold on the Bill.  It gives him authority to cut off benefits, to discriminate against a particular health authority as well as the right to pick and choose as between the various sections and categories set out in sub-section (2) of Section 15.</P>
    <P>The Bill does not, as a matter of right, give either a mother and child scheme or any other health scheme to any section of the people.  There is no right under the Bill to give these unless the Minister should decide to make regulations defining the manner in which, and the extent to which, a health authority may provide these services.  I am not quite clear as to whether a health authority can provide these services should the Minister decide not to make any regulations, but I am quite clear, because it is set out in black and white in Section 22, that whether or not a health authority is giving these benefits, the Minister may put a stop to them.</P>
    <P>There is no mother and child scheme unless the Minister decides that a particular class are going to get it under regulations made under Section 22. There is no school examination or treatment if the Minister decides, for any reason that may cross his mind, to limit or to cut out the operation of Section 19.  There is no mother and child scheme under Section 16 if the Minister decides to limit the effect of it.  I want to get it honestly from the Minister whether or not he intends to use the powers in Section 22.  Is it not a fact that, under Section 22, he has the power to cancel the operation of every benefit in the sections from 14 to 21?</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>I move to report progress.</P>
      <P>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Seanad Electoral (Panel Members)" RHead="Bill, 1952&mdash;Recommittal">
    <Title>Seanad Electoral (Panel Members) Bill, 1952&mdash;Recommittal.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="988" /> Government amendment No. 1:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Before Section 13, to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>13. Part V of the Principal Act is hereby amended by the insertion after Chapter IV of the following chapter:&mdash;</P>
    <P Just="Center">CHAPTER V</P>
    <P Just="Center">Death or Disqualification of Candidate.</P>
    <P>79A.  (1)  Where, before the latest time for receiving nominations at a Seanad by-election, a nominating body satisfies the Seanad returning officer that a person nominated by the body has died or become disqualified for membership of Seanad Éireann, the Seanad returning officer shall forthwith cancel such nomination and thereupon it shall be deemed never to have been made.</P>
    <P>(2)  Where, before the latest time for receiving nominations at a Seanad by-election, the Seanad returning officer is satisfied that a person nominated by members of the Oireachtas has died or become disqualified for membership of Seanad Éireann, the Seanad returning officer shall forthwith cancel such nomination and thereupon it shall be deemed never to have been made.</P>
    <P>(3)  In the counting of the votes cast at a Seanad by-election, all the preferences recorded for a candidate of whose death (whether before or after the ruling upon nomination) the Seanad returning officer is satisfied before the close of the poll shall be disregarded and regard shall be had in lieu thereof to the next available preferences.</P>
    <P>(4)  Subject to the foregoing provisions of this section, the fact that a candidate has (whether before or after the close of the poll) died or become disqualified for membership of Seanad Éireann shall not invalidate or prejudice the nomination of the candidate or any preferences recorded for him and, if he is elected, his election shall not be invalidated <Col N="989" /> by reason of his having so died or become disqualified, but he shall be deemed to have vacated his membership of Seanad Éireann immediately after his said election thereto.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 13.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 2:&mdash;</P>
    <P>In page 7, line 27, to delete &ldquo;33, 34 and 35&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;33 and 35 and sub-section (1) of Section 34.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>In this case I would like some explanation from the Minister, because it does not seem to me that this is clear.  If you turn up the original Act, Section 34, you will find that it contains two sub-sections, sub-section (1) and sub-section (2).  The effect of this amendment is to repeal sub-section (1) and leave sub-section (2).  When you read sub-section (2), which is still left, it says: &ldquo;In sub-section (1) of this section...&rdquo;  If sub-section (1) is gone that expression means nothing.  I am not at all clear as to why that was put in, and failing an explanation I feel that you should now make a further amendment deleting those words in sub-section (2).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Minister for Local Government (Mr. Smith) Patrick Smith">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government (Mr. Smith)</NameTxt>
      <P>My officials have discussed this matter with me and have given me to understand that the parliamentary draftsman regards this as all right.  I am prepared to accept the assurance and unless a member of the Seanad were to press me for further consideration of the matter I would be quite satisfied myself to say that this would be all right as it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not clear what it means.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>This definition is referred to in Section 7 of this Bill and it is considered therefore that sub-section (2) should not be repealed even though it has no significance for its original purpose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I can quite understand why the provisions of sub-section (2) should stand.  I cannot understand why you retain the words &ldquo;in sub-section <Col N="990" /> (1) of this section the expression &lsquo;appropriate number&rsquo; means.&rdquo;  It is purely technical and I am not, of course, going to press the Minister. I am quite sure the parliamentary draftsman has far more experience of this than I have although I am not prepared to accept his infallibility.  In any case it is our job here to draw attention to matters of this kind. Although I do not intend to press the Minister, it looks to me to be a mistake.  However, this Bill will come before the other House and there will be plenty of opportunities to refer to this amendment.</P>
      <P>Perhaps I might be allowed to call the attention of the members of the House who are not on the committee to the fact that this Bill was amended unanimously.  There were no differences of any kind on Party lines.  We received very great assistance from the Minister when he found there was agreement in preparing the amendments required and we also had particularly useful and impartial assistance from the officials of the Department. Although not perhaps strictly in order, I think the House will agree that it is desirable that that should be said by someone on the committee because there were many technical difficulties in regard to which we received invaluable assistance.  Even though it may not contain by any means all the amendments we should like to see, the public should know that this Bill is non-Party and has the general support of the members of the committee.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendments reported and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining stages now.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash; put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Business suspended at</i> 5.35 <i>p.m. and resumed at</i> 6.45 <i>p.m.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Health Bill," RHead="1952&mdash;Committee (Resumed)">
    <Title>Health Bill, 1952&mdash;Committee (Resumed).</Title>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="991" /> SECTION 22.</P>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That Section 22 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>Just before this debate was adjourned, Senator O'Higgins suggested that the section would empower the Minister to refrain altogether, if he wished, from bringing into operation the benefits accruing under this Bill.  He wanted to know, or purported to want to know, why we on this side of the House were not objecting to the Minister being given these powers.  For Senator O'Higgins' benefit, if he really wants to know, the answer can be given in a few words.  The reason we are not worrying is that we have the utmost confidence in the desire of the Minister and of the Fianna Fáil Government in general to bring this legislation into operation.  Every move made in recent years to improve health legislation has been opposed tooth and nail by the Party to which Senator O'Higgins belongs.  Were a Fine Gael Minister for Health in charge of this legislation, we would have the utmost fear of the consequences that would flow from this Bill; but knowing that not only is the Minister himself thoroughly enthusiastic but he is backed by a Government that is enthusiastically in favour of health legislation of this nature, we have the utmost confidence that the provisions of the Bill will be brought into force by regulation at the earliest possible moment consistent with efficiency.  If Senator O'Higgins thinks otherwise, he is due to be disappointed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of Senator Yeats' speech, may I ask the Minister a question relating to the Section?  Could he tell me has such a section been embodied in any other Bill?  Is this creating a precedent?  In the actual wording in previous Bills, has it not been mandatory and not left to the discretion of the Minister to make regulations affecting the matter?  If this is creating a precedent, why should we create a precedent?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not give the <Col N="992" /> Senator any specific instance of the same type of clause in any other Bill, but I am sure it would be found if I had time to search for it.  It is not a revolutionary thing; it is on the line of other Bills of the kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I am inclined to think this Section is an essential part of the Bill, as the Bill is permissive.  It gives to the Minister or his successor specific powers by means of regulations and if you did not provide that that was elastic it would be quite inconsistent with the scheme.  This is not really a Health Bill: it is a Bill to enable the Government of the day to provide a health scheme.  I think that is a mistake; I am opposed to it for that reason, but as this is the type of Bill that is going through I do not see how you could avoid having Section 22. The cost is uncertain.  The capacity of the country at the moment to carry out certain services is uncertain.  The Minister says so.  It is, therefore, inevitable that it will not be possible to carry it all into operation and it may be found that you try certain services and find you cannot carry them out and you have to make an Order for part of the country or the whole of the country terminating them for the time being.  If you have this kind of Bill you cannot avoid some kind of power such as you have in Section 22.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I put some questions to the Minister which he has not answered.  I do not know whether he accepts the remarks of Senator Yeats as an adequate answer.  I do not think they are.  Senator Yeats said my proposition was that Section 22 would empower the Minister to refrain from bringing this Bill into effect and Senator Yeats' answer to that was that he had the utmost confidence in the Minister and in the Fianna Fáil Government. That gives me the opportunity of reminding Senator Yeats that he is only one individual and that there is a great number of individuals in this country who have not got the utmost confidence in the Minister or in the Fianna Fáil Government.  However, that is only by the way.  Senator Yeats' argument was that he was quite <Col N="993" /> confident that the Minister and the Government fully intended implementing this Bill as soon as possible and he had the utmost confidence in them.</P>
      <P>I took the trouble to listen to, and subsequently to read, the Minister's speech on the Second Reading of this Bill in the Dáil.  Possibly Senator Yeats has overlooked it.  In concluding that speech, the Minister uses this phrase, reported in the Dáil Debates for the 22nd February last, column 1914:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Neither do I intend to push local authorities unduly to implement the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I want to relate my remarks on this Section to the Minister's expressed intention of not pressing local authorities to implement the Bill.  I wonder if Senator Yeats has given any consideration to that aspect of the matter. Does that in any way shake his confidence that the Minister and the Fianna Fáil Government intend to implement this Bill and implement it quickly?  The Minister has fixed the Dáil with notice that as far as he is concerned he is not going to press local authorities to implement the Bill, that he is going to get the Bill through the Oireachtas and then going to wash his hands of it.  That is the Minister's approach to this Bill as expressed in the phrase I have quoted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>Your gloss on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator doubts my words, he can read the Dáil Debates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator ought to read the whole sentence.  Half a sentence is hardly fair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I have read an entire sentence.  There is a full stop in front of the word &ldquo;Neither&rdquo; and a full stop at the end of the word &ldquo;Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought there was a semi-colon.  I have it here; it is all right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no full stop after the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>That approach of <Col N="994" /> the Minister was commented on during the course of the Second Reading debate in the Dáil, and it was put to the Minister that his approach to the Bill was to get it through the Oireachtas and then wash his hands of it. He did not deny that, although he concluded the debate.  I am suggesting to the Minister, to Senator Yeats, and to the House that this is a section which is put in as an escape route for the Minister, that it is an escape route which he intends using, and that he has no intention of implementing this Bill.  I am not complaining about that.  I think he might be very wise not to implement the Bill as it stands at the moment.  I think he would be very wise to reconsider the whole matter, but my argument is that this is an escape route and an escape route which the Minister intends using.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The fact of the matter is that Section 22 of the Bill provides that the Minister may make regulations as to the manner and as to the extent to which the benefits given in Sections 14 to 21 will be implemented by health authorities.  Those benefits, those services have been discussed here for the last couple of days.  They are the services, in particular, noted in Sections 14, 15 and 16 of the Bill.  Section 16 is that dealing with the mother and child scheme and Section 15 is that dealing with institutional and specialist services.  None of those services may be available, and it is simply bluff and hypocrisy for any member of this House to try to proclaim this Bill as an instrument that is giving the people as a matter of right the services referred to in Sections 14 to 21.  No one is getting those services as a matter of right and we should recognise that.  They are getting the services subject to the Minister deciding that they ought to have them.  Any particular class set out in sub-section (2) of Section 15 is not guaranteed either free or cheap institutional treatment or free specialist treatment.  They are not guaranteed that.  They cannot as a matter of law demand it and the reason they cannot demand it as a matter of right is because of Section 22 which we are discussing at the moment. <Col N="995" /> What I want the Minister to do&mdash;and he is not doing it&mdash;is to acknowledge the fact publicly that Section 22 gives him the right to cancel or nullify all the benefits mentioned under Sections 14 to 21.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Higgins has suggested that Section 22 is an escape route, especially designed by the Minister, and Senator Frank Hugh O'Donnell asks a question as to whether there was a similar section ever incorporated in any other Bill that passed through this House.  I would like to bring the minds of Senators back to just one or two Bills that were passed through here that both Senator O'Donnell and now Senator and then Deputy O'Higgins supported.</P>
      <P>There was a Housing Bill introduced in 1948 by the late Deputy Murphy, the then Minister.  There was a Gaeltacht Housing Bill introduced by Deputy Blowick, then Minister for Lands.  I think that Senator O'Higgins will agree with me that in both of these Bills, that later became Acts that passed through this or the other House, there was a section of this kind enshrined so that, despite the fact that these Bills made provision for the payment of grants to various classes or categories of persons for the erection or reconstruction of houses, it always depended afterwards on regulations to be made by the Minister.  Would Senator O'Higgins suggest that putting such a clause into the Housing Bills of these dates was done designedly by the Minister as an escape route so that the grants which the House made provision for should not be paid?</P>
      <P>Senator O'Higgins went further still. He suggested that this section is being put in with the intention of depriving a large section of our people of the benefits enshrined in this Bill.  It is the first time, I think, it has been suggested from the other side of the House that there are any benefits to be derived from the passing of the Bill when it becomes law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>He later made reference to the <Col N="996" /> statement by the Minister, in concluding the debate in the Dáil, that he did not propose to press local authorities in this matter.  I have not got that statement directly before me, but I can quite appreciate that what was in the Minister's mind at the time was that, in connection with the majority of local authorities, there would be no need to press them because those people, elected as representatives on local authorities, county councils and borough councils, in general, are very anxious to give the best service possible to our people, and it is only where for political purposes some organised attempt might be made by those people who are opposing the passing of this Bill through this and the other House, to avail of whatever small representation they have on the various county councils to hold up the operation of the Bill, that there could be any question of the necessity arising for any pressure either from the Minister or any other source to give full implementation to the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>First of all, with regard to Senator O'Donnell's question&mdash;this section, I believe, is to replace Section 28 of the 1947 Act, Section 20 sub-section (3) of the Public Assistance Act of 1939 and Section 90 of the Public Assistance Act of 1939, all of which are in very much the same tradition as this particular section.  I do not think anybody was accused at the time of putting that section into these various Acts with the deliberate intention of holding up the Bill that was brought in in that particular instance. I think anybody would regard Senator O'Higgins' allegation as the most fantastic thing that was ever heard, and I am quite sure he has no belief whatever that there is any intention to hold up this Bill.  Why should the Fianna Fáil Party waste weeks and weeks of their time in the Dáil fighting the opposition of Fine Gael&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>To placate a few Independents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not mind about the Independents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>You asked me a question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="997" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Why should we issue a White Paper in 1947 stating this scheme before we even heard of these Independents, and why should we come along to implement our White Paper?  This talk about pacifying Independents is all the greatest nonsense, and after all the opposition of Fine Gael to this Bill we are now accused of intending not to put it into operation at all.  If the Senator thinks that, why not let the Bill go through and be done with it?  There will be no trouble, if what the Senator thinks is true.  That would be better instead of wasting all this time and worrying about what will happen.  The Senator says we do not intend to put it into operation.  Why the opposition then? Possibly the Senator is trying to stir up a little bit of trouble telling Fianna Fáil supporters that the Government is not serious.  As far as our supporters are concerned, they will not take very much notice of anything Senator O'Higgins says and he is, therefore, only wasting his time.</P>
      <P>I have the greatest respect for the official reporting staff, but I think that there should have been a semi-colon in the particular passage quoted instead of a full stop:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Some time must elapse before all the necessary facilities are available and all the necessary arrangements made, but there will be no deliberate holding back on my part.  Neither do I intend to push local authorities unduly to implement the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I tried to make a balanced statement. I was being accused at the time of steam-rolling local authorities.  We have to have regard to such accusations. I had no intention of steam-rolling local authorities.  I suppose this Bill provided the first occasion on which a Minister bringing in a Bill met all the local authorities and discussed the matter with them before proceeding with the Bill.  I am not saying that they agreed to every provision but, as as a result of that meeting, there were certain amendments introduced, amendments which went some part of the way to meet the views put forward by the local authorities.  The charge of £2 in certain cases was put in to meet some of their proposals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="998" /> I wanted to assure the Dáil that the Bill would not be put into operation immediately.  Certain regulations would have to be made.  Staff would have to be provided in many cases before the Bill could be implemented. At the same time I wanted to assure the Dáil that there would be no steam-rolling of local authorities.  If a local authority wanted a little more time we were prepared to agree that that would be reasonable.  I think it was on the Fifth Stage of the Bill I was asked if that leniency towards local authorities would last for long; I said that it could not last for all time.  I pointed out that if all the counties, except one, adopted some particular provision, the competent authority would have to insist that the county which had not adopted the particular scheme would fall into line, having been given time to come in of its own free will and having failed to do so.  When one talks reasonably to the Dáil or Seanad, it is hard to be taken up by a Senator and have what one says turned back on one as if one was playing a huge joke on the people, on the county councils, on the Dáil and on all concerned.  It has been said by Senator O'Higgins that when this Bill is passed I will turn to Section 22 and say: &ldquo;We will not operate it at all.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 23.</P>
    <P>Government amendment No. 8:&mdash;</P>
    <P>In sub-section (1), page 9, line 20, to insert &ldquo;in an institution&rdquo; after &ldquo;maintain&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as Section 23 is concerned, it has already been discussed sufficiently on Section 16.  There is not much more that could be said on it.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 23, as amended, put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 24 put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 25.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 9:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In sub-section (1), page 10, lines 5 and 6, to delete &ldquo;, on application <Col N="999" /> being made to them,&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;, in accordance with such regulations as may be made by the Minister,&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to this section, we have already discussed some of the sub-sections, but there are some matters in sub-sections (1) and (2) to which I wish to draw attention.  We have heard a good deal of talk and boasting, and experienced a great deal of flag-waving, as it were, in connection with this question of choice with regard to doctor and institution. Here we find that the patient has a choice at two guineas per week.  If the patient does not go to the institution to which he is expected to go, he may go to the institution of his choice, but he is penalised in doing so to the tune of two guineas per week.  I cannot understand that.  I do not know why the patient should be penalised.  A patient should be entitled to go to the hospital of his choice without any penalty.  In cases of serious illness patients very often have great faith in a particular institution, a particular doctor or even a particular nurse.  It is very much better from the point of view of the patient's chance of recovery that he has confidence in the institution and the individuals looking after him, and from that point of view I think it is unfair to the patient to penalise him.  Why all this talk about free choice when it is not a free choice?  Why should a patient, if he goes to the institution to which he is directed, be paid for at the rate of £5 12s. per week while, if he goes to the institution of his choice, he is only paid for at the rate of £3 10s. per week.  It seems a rather extraordinary thing but, indeed, it is really only part and parcel of the whole theme running through this Bill&mdash;control and direction.  I will not say any more than that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know how the Senator can accuse us of anything wrong in this particular matter.  This is the absolute essence of choice.  When the Senator calls the provision made here &ldquo;control&rdquo; one has some idea of <Col N="1000" /> the mentality of the Senator.  What could be more free than to tell a patient he can go to any hospital he likes?  If the patient does not want a choice of hospital the local authority will pay so much; if he wants a choice, the local authority will possibly or probably take two guineas per week off for institutional treatment.  Would it not be very unfair if there were two people and one goes to the institution to which the local authority sends him and the other says he would prefer to choose his own hospital if the latter was treated better because he made his own choice?  I do not think anyone could defend that.  If a person chooses his own hospital, he cannot expect to be treated better than the person who does not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Why penalise him to the extent of two guineas per week?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We do not penalise him.</P>
      <P>Section 25, as amended, put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 26 to 32 inclusive put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 33.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 33 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this intended only to refer to false statements with regard to means?  Is it intended to cover the means test or is it intended to cover the possibility of a person saying that they had some illness when they had not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it could be interpreted as making any false statement. I do not know what false statement a person would be likely to make except in regard to means.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>What I mean to convey is, is it only intended to cover means?  I was referring to statements made regarding illness to a doctor or someone else.  In that case it would seem to be undesirable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1001" /> Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 34 to 37, inclusive, put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 38.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume we may discuss amendments Nos. 10 to 15 together.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 10:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), in paragraph (a) (ii), page 14, line 30; in paragraph (b), line 33; and in paragraph (c), line 38, to delete the words &ldquo;vehicles or stalls.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Practically all the suggested amendments arise from a matter I discussed on Second Reading.  On that occasion the discussion was cut short to enable me to tabulate these amendments for discussion on Committee.  The amendments are clear enough, although an evening paper yesterday has given a wrong construction to the meaning of these amendments.  That has been rectified in to-day's morning and evening papers.  The meaning of these amendments is simply not to require licensing or registration of vehicles and stalls.  That, ultimately, would mean food vehicles and food stalls, because that is the definition that applies in the Food and Hygiene Regulations at present in force.  My desire is that that additional power should not be put into the Bill in this House or in the other House.</P>
      <P>On the last occasion I explained that Section 38 of this Bill is a paraphrase of Section 55 of the Principal Act.  It is a paraphrase and enlargement. The main enlargement is the inclusion of vehicles and stalls for licensing or registration.  So far, the word &ldquo;licensing&rdquo; has not come in under the regulations which apply to certain food premises at present. Therefore, up to the present, the word &ldquo;licensing&rdquo; does not apply.  Registration does apply to certain food businesses.  I need not go into details of such food businesses.  Registration does apply to them and anyone who is not so registered is not legally entitled to carry on the business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1002" /> I will omit the word &ldquo;licensing&rdquo; and refer simply to registration.  If we introduce registration of every food vehicle and every food stall, we present those who have to carry out the regulations with an impossible situation. One of the most important streets in this city has been referred to already, prematurely, in the Press, in connection with this matter.  It has forestalled the discussion.  Does the Minister seriously contemplate officials of a local authority endeavouring to register every stallholder in Moore Street, no matter what type of food material is being sold from the stall? Does he seriously think of imposing on any local authority or their officials the task of registering every food vehicle?  As defined in the existing regulations, &ldquo;food vehicle&rdquo; means a vehicle, vessel or aircraft which is not a food stall and in which food intended for sale for human consumption or food material is or is intended to be conveyed otherwise than in an impermeable container.  So that, he would expect the local authority to register an aircraft coming into Collinstown, to register every car which brings vegetables into the city.  I do not want to dilate on this matter because I could make it ridiculous. Every railway carriage would have to be registered.  I would impress on the Minister and his advisers that it would be impossible to carry out the proposed legislation.</P>
    <P>I do not want to be termed an obstructionist by delaying the House. I have made my statement as clearly as I can.  In my opinion, the inclusion of vehicles and stalls as types requiring registration or licensing is ridiculous. These words were not in Section 55 of the Principal Act, which referred to &ldquo;premises&rdquo;.  Possibly, I am anticipating the Minister's reply that he wants to include these two types in case of necessity but that, of course, the regulations will not be altered to include them unless it is found necessary at some future date to do so. The inclusion of them now is some indication that there is some concrete reason for it.  Personally, I cannot see any reason for their inclusion.</P>
    <P>I want to impress on Senators that the requirements of the Food Hygiene <Col N="1003" /> Regulations under the 1947 Act apply to both food vehicles and food stalls. The requirements with which food vehicles and food stalls have to comply are laid down in black and white.  The legislation applies to them.  Why introduce a clause which requires registration or licensing of them which will entail the filling up of pages and pages, practically rooms full of documents which are absolutely unnecessary?  I shall not say any more until I hear what the Minister has to say in connection with this ridiculous innovation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I am rather surprised my friend Senator Hawkins did not jump up and give a little lesson on the bad propaganda of any form of exaggeration.  Whether there should be registration or whether there should be licensing, if this Bill is passed, it will be left to the Minister.  If you have provisions designed for the health of the community, for control by means of registration or licensing of shops and if there is exemption of a shop which is out on the street as a stall, the whole purpose is defeated. It would be grossly unfair.  If you have provisions of this kind, both these powers must be given to the Minister. There is probably something in what Senator O'Donovan says, that it might be found necessary to register stalls, and possibly, too, vehicles, and if there was any abuse the Minister administering this would certainly have to have the powers, it seems to me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>This power has been taken, but it is not necessarily to be inferred that the power will be used to the full in case of all stalls and travelling shops.  I agree with Senator Douglas that it would be entirely inconsistent if we should register shops everywhere and leave stalls out.  Take meat, for example.  I think that meat is one of the things we should deal with as soon as we can.  We are dealing with it.  Well, if we make certain regulations with regard to exposure of meat in butchers' shops and so on it would be very unfair if we would allow stall to set up outside the butcher's <Col N="1004" /> shop and be free from any regulation whatever.  So from the pure viewpoint of consistency we have to bring in stalls as well as everything else.  We would apply the meat regulations to the stalls when we applied them to the shops.  A great many of these stalls are dealing with fruit and other things where perhaps regulation is not so necessary, because in fruit anyway you have some sort of covering on the fruit that is removed by the buyer before he consumes what is inside and there is certain protection in that, at any rate, against contamination or disease; but meat, I think, is a thing that will strike everybody as being an article that must be controlled if we are going to bring in food regulations at all, so I think that we would have to have this clause in the Bill.</P>
      <P>We would naturally have to take into account the capacity of the local authority to administer any particular regulation before it is made.  And if it was thought that the local authorities could not possibly cope with a particular situation, well, we would have to consider and see how that would be got over.  But I think that Senator O'Donovan need not be afraid that we are immediately going to deal with all stalls selling food in the open.  It will be a process which will be extended gradually to the foods that need protection most, such as meat and foods of that kind, where exposure is obviously a very dangerous thing from the point of view of health.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to hear the Minister giving the explanation, so far as it goes, because the Veterinary Medical Association, which has external association only with the Irish Medical Association, advised the Minister at the time not to allow fish, poultry, rabbits or any meat to be sold on these exposed stalls.  That advice was not taken.  I agree thoroughly that stalls with meat or meat products should not be exposed on a public thoroughfare.  The suggestion was put forward at the time that a communal shelter or house or market should be provided co-operatively by themselves or by the local authority, where such foods would be sold under conditions <Col N="1005" /> where food hygiene regulations could be applied.  Still, the local authorities are doing the best they can to have those meat products, when sold in stalls, sold under as hygienic conditions as possible.</P>
      <P>I will again emphasise that there is a series of regulations at present in force to control those stalls.  The registration of them even in this restricted way will not help a whole lot. It is just filling in forms, and the Minister and his officials do not seem to appreciate the amount of work that is entailed in registration of the premises that have to be registered up to the present.  By a curious coincidence yesterday, the 30th September, was the final day for the registration of the registrable food businesses at present.  Those that were fit for final registration had to be notified yesterday. Those that were unfit had to be notified that their registration was refused; and those that were helping to provide or to comply with the requirements had to be notified of an extension up to six months to enable them to apply.  Now that entails a tremendous amount of work on officials, clerical and professional, of the local authority.  They are only doing what applies to every food business, and doing it because they have to be registered, and I again suggest to the Minister that in the majority of towns or cities there will be so few of these meat stalls and fish or rabbits and poultry stalls, that it is not necessary to have all this verbiage in an enactment. The one place probably where it does apply would be the City of Dublin, because there would be so many of them, but I still think that putting this clause in requiring registration or licensing is just not necessary, that the local authority can deal with them effectively without registering them, because registering does not mean anything else only filling in their names.  I still think that this addition to the legislation is not necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment being withdrawn?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, any amendments I have tabulated in this House I have tabulated with the purpose of <Col N="1006" /> trying to convince the Minister of their reasonableness and that he should adopt them.  If the Minister refuses to adopt them I will withdraw them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment is being withdrawn?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is just the one that we are discussing, the one dealing with&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 10 is withdrawn and amendments Nos. 11 to 15 are not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 11 and 12 are different.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It was understood that amendments Nos. 10 to 15 were to go together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg your pardon, I did not understand it in that light.  I spoke only on the amendments relative to the vehicles and stalls.  There are two amendments, Nos. 11 and 12, dealing with the deletion of the words &ldquo;authorised in that behalf&rdquo;, so if you will allow me to discuss them I will be glad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 10 is withdrawn?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Amendment by leave withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 11:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (2), page 14, paragraph (a), line 48, to delete the words &ldquo;authorised in that behalf by the health authority.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In connection with this amendment, a clause is inserted in the Bill with regard to the keeping of the register. Section 38 (2) (a) says that any register kept pursuant to the regulations by a health authority shall be deemed to be in proper custody when in the custody of an officer of the health authority authorised in that behalf by the health authority.  Now I cannot see that that is actually necessary, and I cannot see subsequently any officer authorised in that behalf producing any evidence in <Col N="1007" /> court, as it may present difficulties to the local authority.  I would suggest to the Minister that there is no necessity for requiring the local authority to authorise a specific officer to keep this register when it is in the keeping of the local authority, which has subsequently to produce evidence for the court by an officer who is authorised in that behalf.  If that officer happens to be ill there would be just nobody who could produce the evidence in court, and if necessary you would have to authorise, I will not say a series of officers, but a number of officers, so that the local authority would be safeguarded.  I cannot see just why it is necessary to put in that clause &ldquo;authorised in that behalf.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I suggest the deletion of the words &ldquo;authorised in that behalf by the health authority&rdquo;, as in amendment No. 11, and the deletion of the words &ldquo;authorised in that behalf&rdquo; as in amendment No. 12.  Will the Minister accept that?</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Minister will not accept these particular amendments. I think it is a matter of some importance that the registers kept under this section should not be allowed to float around the offices of any health authority or local authority and be considered as being in the proper authority no matter what official of a local authority might hold them.  I think that the section, as worded, requires a health authority actually to authorise a particular officer or particular class of officer before the register is considered as being in the proper authority.  That is a provision that should be retained. I hope the Minister will resist these two amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a class of officer that is mentioned.  It is an officer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>It could be done by two or three.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Senator O'Higgins is right.  In fact, I am advised that the county manager, being the executive officer, could authorise more than one person to keep the register.  A <Col N="1008" /> county manager might authorise a certain person to keep the register and if that person became ill and could not appear in court he could authorise another person.  It is very important that he could authorise another person. Otherwise, I am advised, a junior clerk could get hold of the register and make an entry in it&mdash;for instance some entry that would be of great importance to the person concerned and that might be of great import if brought before a court where the local authority was making a prosecution.  I think Senator O'Donovan, if he agrees that it is possible to authorise more than one person, would not push the amendment. It is quite possible to authorise more than one person.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not read like that.  However, if I cannot convince the Minister, I am satisfied to withdraw these two amendments.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 12, 13, 14 and 15 not moved.</P>
      <P>Section 38 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 39 and 40 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 41.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 41 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Am I right in interpreting this section in this way? Under sub-section (17) the Minister may request the advice of the National Health Council on any regulation, including the regulation which deals with conditions of employment, but with the restriction in sub-paragraph (a), which reads as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Sub-section (98) of the Principal Act is hereby amended:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(a) by the deletion in sub-section (1) of the words &lsquo;to give to the Minister when so required by him advice on matters affecting or incidental to the health of the people&rsquo; and the substitution therefor of the words &lsquo;to advise the Minister on such general matters affecting or incidental to the health of the people as may be referred to them by the Minister and on such other general matters <Col N="1009" /> (other than conditions of employment of officers and servants and the amount or payment of grants or allowances) relating to the operation of the health services as they think fit&rsquo;&rdquo;;</P>
    <P>Am I right in interpreting the section as meaning that the Minister will submit to the National Health Council any regulations that he makes and that they can submit to him any suggestions they like, but that they cannot submit to him a regulation involving conditions of employment? Is that so?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Not exactly.  The best way to interpret the section would be that they cannot, of their own initiative, raise matters of conditions of employment. For instance, some regulation might be issued which would deal with the employment of a specialist in a certain capacity.  When it is a regulation they can discuss it and make any suggestion they like.  What I wanted to avoid here was that, at the end of the meeting, I would receive a resolution from them saying, for instance: &ldquo;You are not paying as much as you should pay.&rdquo;  I wanted to exclude matters that do not arise in the regulations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the Minister's intention, and it is the obligation obtained in sub-section (17), that whatever regulation the Minister makes&mdash; whether or not it concerns conditions of service&mdash;will be submitted to the council and that, on these regulations, the council can make any suggestions they please, including conditions of service, but that they cannot initiate discussion on conditions of service.  Am I correct in assuming that the only restriction is that they cannot initiate a discussion on conditions of employment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any particularly strong reason why that exclusion should exist?  Has the Minister anything in mind?  I do not want to pry into it if it is something more or less of departmental importance.  It seems to me, however, that the council <Col N="1010" /> might very properly hold views which they feel should be put before the Minister but, as the section stands, they cannot do that&mdash;not as a council, in any event&mdash;unless the Minister first refers it to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Consultative Council, having the name of being interested in health matters&mdash;naturally&mdash;and the name of being in touch with the Minister and giving him advice, and so forth, might be asked by any particular section of the community&mdash;for instance, nurses, midwives, doctors, mental hospital assistants&mdash;to receive a deputation because they want to discuss their conditions of employment.  I think that that would be undesirable.  The council might not feel that they were in a position to refuse, and it would be undesirable that they should be asked to do that sort of thing.  After all, all these sections have their own ways of approaching the Minister, and have various organisations&mdash;the Irish Medical Association, the nurses' organisation, and so forth&mdash;which deal with matters of that kind.</P>
      <P>I may say that when this was being discussed at the Consultative Council, the representatives of the Irish Medical Association were very much in favour of it.  So long as matters in the regulations could be discussed, whether dealing with conditions of employment or not, they were quite satisfied that the council should not be asked to go further in discussing conditions of employment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very pleased that the Minister has decided to have the council.  I think it is a very important step with regard to health generally in this country.  A health council means one thing and it is of great importance how that council is constituted.  I should like to impress on the Minister that it is very important to have on that council people who will be of help to him in the matter.  You can have a council composed of people who will not be of help and you can have a council composed of people who will be of help.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Sub-section (16) deals with the <Col N="1011" /> presentation of an annual report.  It states:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The National Health Council may present each year to the Minister an annual report and the Minister shall publish the report with such comments (if any) as he thinks fit.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I should like the Minister to add to that paragraph a provision indicating how soon he will publish the report. If a report is not published within a reasonable time, it is generally useless. I do not know whether the Minister intends to publish this report with the report of the Department of Health, but the Department of Health Report is very big and involved and is often published very late.  It takes a good deal of compilation, I know, but that report on some occasion has been three years old when published.  Therefore, I should like an undertaking from the Minister that he will publish the report as a separate document.  It concerns the health of the whole country and it should be published within a reasonable time because such a report is a safeguard for everyone. Those interested can read it and see what is happening, so that it acts as a safeguard for the people.</P>
    <P>Finally, sub-section (17) sets out that the Minister shall request the advice of the National Health Council on any regulations he proposes to make... &ldquo;except where he is satisfied that the making of the regulations is a matter of urgency and, in such case, he shall request the advice of the council on the regulations as soon as may be after they are made.&rdquo;  In other words, the Minister is here given power to make regulations without consulting the National Health Council. I do not think that is advisable. If you have a health council, you should consult it.  Perhaps the Minister knows more about it than I and he may have in mind certain cases where he may have to make a regulation very rapidly.  If he will put up such cases, I shall be quite willing to agree with him, but, in principle, it is wrong to set out that the Minister shall take advice from the Health Council in one case and then say that he can make <Col N="1012" /> regulations and then consult the council. There may be cases where it may be necessary, but I cannot see why, even in a case of emergency, a quorum of the National Health Council could not be summoned rapidly.  Many of the members will be living in the city and it would be possible to get a quorum summoned quickly.  The Minister should consult or inform them as to the regulation being made, but under this he can make a regulation without doing so.  We know the Minister has power to ignore the council. Let us hope that in future he will not do so.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that provision with regard to urgency must remain. It may be a rather minor matter, so far as advice is concerned, and still be very urgent.  The most urgent situation I can think of is a situation in which an outbreak of smallpox is notified here.  We would immediately make chicken pox a notifiable disease and that would have to be done in a matter of hours.  There is not the smallest chance that any consultative council would have the slightest comment to make on such a decision.  If a Minister has a clause like that before him, under which he is bound to submit the regulations to the Health Council, I do not think he is going to put forward the plea that it was urgent and that he could not submit them to the council. The plea of urgency would, I think, be very seldom used, but I think it is necessary.  The Senator need not worry very much about it.  As I said to the present Consultative Council with regard to some of these provisions, if the Minister is not keeping faith, as it were, they have their annual report and no Minister would like to be accused in that report of not keeping faith.  That report must be published.  He may make his comments but it still must be published, so that that annual report is a big safeguard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to publication of the annual report, the intention is to have it published as soon as possible.  We issued an annual report of the Department a few days ago for 1951-52 and presumably the annual report of the <Col N="1013" /> Consultative Council would be for 1952-53, and, coming in at the same time, it would be incorporated.  We would not have to wait for the 1952-53 annual report of the Department.  If the report came in from the Consultative Council and if, after examining the position, we saw it was not likely that we would have the annual report of the Department for the next nine or ten months, we would not hold it up, but I do not like to be tied to time. If I am to be tied to time, I would say perhaps 12 months but that looks ridiculously long and if we say six months, we might find that we would exceed the six months, so that it is better left out.  I think the annual report itself is the best safeguard.  As I said in speaking to the present Consultative Council, if there is not good faith between the Minister and the Consultative Council, things will not work well anyway.  It is better to depend on that good faith rather than to have everything put down in black and white.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister meet Senator Cunningham by incorporating some such phrase as &ldquo;as soon as possible&rdquo; or &ldquo;with all convenient speed&rdquo;?  The Modern Homes case brings to mind the phrase &ldquo;with all convenient speed&rdquo;.  I think some gesture of that sort will show that it is not intended to shelve it.  Senator Cunningham mentioned a point which the Minister might think worth considering, that the report should not be incorporated in the general Department report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Does Senator Cunningham think it should not be incorported?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>It should be separate, if possible, from the general report, because the general report might hold it up.  I want to stress the point that a great deal of the value of a report lies in the fact that it is published quickly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with that.  I will consider the suggestion put forward by Senator O'Higgins before Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1014" /> Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 42 to 47, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 48.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 48 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Sub-section (3) prescribes how the consultative health committees shall be made up. Sub-section (1) sets out that the council of a county (other than Dublin or Waterford) shall by resolution appoint a consultative health committee.  In other words, it is the county council appoints the health committee, the local health committee we are dealing with.  Sub-section (3) then sets out that the committee shall consist of ten members including (a) not less than four members of the county council, (b) the county medical officer for the county, (c) the county surgeon of the county, or somebody representing him, and (d) two other registered medical practitioners.  These people are all specified&mdash;four county councillors, one county medical officer, one county surgeon and two medical practitioners. The committee shall consist, in the first place, of not less than four members of the county council, and we must remember the opening sub-section under which the health committee will be appointed by the county council.  It means, I think, that very often the county council will appoint six members, because there are two vacancies.  If the sub-section prescribed four members, the county council could appoint only four members, but the sub-sections says &ldquo;not less than four members,&rdquo; so they can appoint six members.  I think that is what will happen in actual fact, in most instances.  The county council will appoint six members and then you will have six members of the council with four others on that committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In a community of any kind, I think, you will find that there are people outside both the county council and the medical profession whom it might be very desirable to have on a committee of this kind.  If you agree to delete <Col N="1015" /> these words &ldquo;not less than&rdquo;, the committee would then consist of four members of the county council and these other public officials&mdash;the county medical officer, the county surgeon and two other doctors.  That committee could then co-opt or elect two other members. That would provide an opportunity of bringing in people who are outside the county council and the medical profession and who might be of great help.  I think that would be the better way to do it and it would not prevent their bringing in two other members of the county council, if the original committee of eight decided to do so.  As the committee would be constituted under the present proposal, it would mean that there would be six council members and you might miss out somebody in the county who would be of great help to the committee&mdash;some people who have special knowledge in regard to health matters or somebody who had retired and who had plenty of time to devote to that type of work.  I would suggest therefore that in sub-section (3) (a) the words &ldquo;not less than&rdquo; should be deleted.  Of course it is important to remember that this committee has only an advisory function.  That, I think, is quite clear but I should like the Minister to let us know exactly the power of a committee of that kind.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to appeal to the Minister not to change the provision as set out in the section because I believe that under the proposal contained in the section you will get the best people available on this committee&mdash;that is, members who are elected by the people.  I feel that the elected representatives should have at least six members on this committee because if they do not do their duty, they will have to answer to the people while the other members of the committee will have to answer to nobody. I would appeal to the Minister not to change the representation provided for members of the council on this committee. The elected representatives should be given as much power as is still left to them under the existing law and goodness knows that is little <Col N="1016" /> enough at the present time in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I should be glad if the Minister would give us some reasons for what I regard as an extraordinary provision contained in sub-section (5). To take an extreme case, if this body meets six times in the first month of its existence, it cannot meet any more for the rest of the year unless the manager or the county council calls it together.  It is quite conceivable that the committee might meet monthly for the first six months.  If that should happen, it could not meet again for the rest of the year unless a meeting were called by the county manager or the county council.  I do not imagine that the Minister would want monthly meetings, but it does not seem reasonable that if in the early stages of its existence the committee should hold monthly meetings, then after six months it cannot meet again during that year unless it is specifically summoned by the manager or by resolution of the county council.  I cannot see why monthly meetings would not be quite reasonable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMcCrea" hpid="Mr. McCrea Mr. McCrea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCrea</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to add my voice to the views expressed by Senator Tunney.  After all, the county council will be responsible for putting this Bill into operation.  The county council will have to find the wherewithal to finance the measure and the county council, the elected representatives of the people, will have to stand up to whatever criticism may be levelled at the Bill after it comes into operation.  I think they should be allowed to have sufficient people at their own funeral, and the Minister should not accept the suggestion made by Senator Cunningham.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>There were three points raised on this section.  First we had the suggestion by Senator Cunningham that we should confine the membership of this committee to four members of the county council with four medical representatives, and that they should be allowed to co-opt two others.  That suggestion was opposed by two other Senators.  I see no great reason for adopting Senator Cunningham's suggestion. The county council are quite <Col N="1017" /> free, should they wish to do so, to put on the committee any two people representing other interests, and I hope they will do so, but it is very hard to provide for all these interests, such as nursing, mental hospital attendants, pharmacists and so on.  There might be other organisations such as the Red Cross, who should be represented, and I think the best procedure would be to let the county council appoint two other people, if they do not want to appoint two of their own members to complete the committee.  County councils do sometimes appoint outside people on these committees.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>On the vocational education committees, for example.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Sometimes you get a very good type of outside members.  In all the circumstances, I think it is better to allow the proposal in the Bill to stand as it is.  Senator Cunningham also wanted to know what the function of the committee would be.  It will be purely advisory, of course, but, I think it will be a very useful committee in many ways.  For instance, there is no such thing in a county hospital as a visiting committee although there is in the mental hospital and in the county home, I think.  This committee could do the work of a visiting committee in the county hospitals if they thought it necessary.  They could visit the county hospital occasionally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to meetings, it will be observed that four members of the committee can ask for a meeting.  The reason it was thought necessary to have this provision about six meetings is that I was somewhat afraid that you might have a clique of four people on the committee who would like to meet, say, once a fortnight, while the other six members might not think that the business was of sufficient importance to meet so frequently.  It was merely to prevent any attempt by these four members to insist on holding frequent unnecessary meetings that that provision was inserted.  On the other hand, if it happened that they met every month and did good work and found after a time that the six meetings were exhausted, there is no doubt whatever that in a case like that the county <Col N="1018" /> manager, or if he does not agree, the county council, would authorise them to continue to hold these monthly meetings.  Where the committee is doing good work, Senators need not have the slightest fear that they will be curtailed in the number of meetings which they are allowed to hold.  It is merely to put a curb on mischievous members that this provision appears in the section.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I quite appreciate that, but I think the provision is a bit clumsy and that it might be advisable, if a majority feel that a meeting should be called, that they should be empowered to call a meeting.  The members of the committee may have called a meeting on four occasions in the year on their own, and may have been called together twice by the county council, but once they have met on six occasions, in no circumstances for the rest of the year can they be called together without a special order from the manager or a resolution of the county council.  I have every sympathy with the Minister's desire to prevent unnecessary meetings, called merely because some members of the committee may have a bee in their bonnet, but I think there could be a safeguard against that if it were provided that a meeting could be called by a majority of the committee.  Remember, six meetings are provided for but none of these may have been called by the committee themselves.  I imagine that the first regular ones will be called by the manager, and if they meet six times in the first six months &mdash;I think monthly meetings would be reasonable&mdash;in the latter part of the year they would be deprived of meetings. I would be satisfied if you provided that they could not call additional meetings more than three times in the year.  I think this is too drastic, but I am not opposing the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Senator Douglas is much too generous.  This is the most fantastic provision I have ever seen in an Act of Parliament.  The reason given by the Minister is, I think, possibly even more fantastic&mdash; that he, with all the weight of his ministerial responsibility, is introducing <Col N="1019" /> this section in case you may have selected on to one of these committees three or four cranks who will insist on meeting more than half a dozen times in the year.  I would imagine that the attitude of anyone to a person who wants to meet more than half a dozen times in the year would be to compliment him on such energy and citizenship.</P>
      <P>Senator Cunningham and Senator McCrea have, I think, expressed what the point of view of a county council or city council would be to one of these consultative committees, that they would insist that the majority of the committee would be composed of members of the local authority and that six seats would be filled by local authority members.  I really cannot see that the explanation given by the Minister for the inclusion of this sub-section can stand up.  Would it not be better to leave it out and let things take their course?  If the Health Bill is interfered with in any drastic way by a few mischief-makers, it is always possible for the Minister to come back with an amending section.  I think this would be a fantastic precedent to create in a Bill of this sort.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 49.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 49 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like the Minister to say what is intended to be covered by this section.  The section provides that, where a health authority is making an agreement for the provision of services with any person, it shall comply with any requirement specified by the Minister. Am I right in assuming that that is intended to refer to the context of the agreement; in other words, does the section mean that the Minister is retaining control over the agreement which is to be entered into between the health authority and the person giving the services, even on such matters as remuneration?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The local authority will <Col N="1020" /> be quite free to make an agreement with any hospital they wish, but they must keep within the regulations laid down.  As I explained already, it is advisable&mdash;I think everybody will agree to that&mdash;that the same amount per week should be paid by each local authority to voluntary hospitals for patients.  At the moment the amount is £5 12s. 6d. per week.  That is the type of regulation they would have to comply with when making an agreement with a voluntary hospital.  Then there will be other things.  For instance, we had a discussion last night about making an allowance for the staffs in the voluntary hospitals. Some local authorities may not agree with that.  They may say that they have always got their patients treated free and why should they be made to pay now.  Obviously, if the Minister should make an agreement with the medical profession that staffs in voluntary hospitals should be paid, it would be up to him to see that the local authorities, in general, would carry out that agreement.  There are various regulations like that that may be made from time to time which they would have to fall in with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that you will want some kind of uniformity. I am thinking of a case where an agreement is entered into with two members of the medical profession, one in a rural area in Connemara and another in a densely populated area. The services to be provided would not be anything equivalent as between two such areas.  Will there be something like a <i>per capita</i> sum laid down for treatment or a lump sum?  If there is to be a lump sum, it would seem that in one case the man would be paid more than he is worth and in the other case the man would probably not be getting enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator must have the question of maternity in mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I was thinking of Section 16.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that is the only section the Senator could have in mind. I think in the case of maternity it <Col N="1021" /> would be a sum for each case.  I do not think we should make a distinction whether it is a rural or a city area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>In the case of maternity, that would be a satisfactory way of dealing with it.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">NEW SECTION.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 16:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before Section 50 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>The manager of a county or a county borough shall not, save on the direction of the Minister or on the advice of the Consultative Health Committee appointed under this Act,</P>
      <P>(a)  direct any medical practitioner to give medical treatment or treatment in a particular manner to any person entitled to treatment under this Act or to withhold any such treatment from such person,</P>
      <P>(b)  require any medical practitioner to make a medical report on a patient other than with the consent of the patient,</P>
      <P>(c)  require the production of the medical record of any person.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In moving this new section to the Bill, I will point out that the Labour Party have made it clear that we support the measure because of those improvements in the health services which it contains and not because it, by any means, provides the services needed by the people.  Our desire is that the Bill shall not only become law but that it will also become operative. The doctors have, through their association, of which I am neither the advocate nor representative, expressed and repeated their fears that this measure will interfere with the confidential relationship between patient and doctor.  The Minister has assured this House that neither himself nor the officials of his Department will disturb that relationship, and I accept his word in that respect.  The Minister for Health cannot, however, as the law governing local administration now <Col N="1022" /> stands, guarantee in the same way that such interference by county managers or some county managers may not take place.</P>
    <P>Closing the debate in the Seanad on the Second Reading of this Bill, the Minister correctly stated that this was not a measure on which the authority of county managers should be debated, and I have no intention now of going into the manner in which some of these officials have exercised their powers.  It is pertinent for me to remark, nevertheless, that legislation has placed tremendous powers in the hands of county managers who could, unless the necessary safeguards are provided, demand the records of patients from doctor-employees of local authorities or in other ways interfere with the practice of their profession on the grounds that such doctors are members of local authority staffs and subject to the direction of the county manager.</P>
    <P>This new section is designed to prevent legally possible abuses on a very intimate matter concerning a patient or what a doctor may do for him.  As I have stated already, fears have been expressed of a danger to the doctor-patient relationship.  This relationship is essentially an ethical question, and has deep roots in the Christian way of life.  Misgivings that it is imperilled can readily militate against a more ready implementation of this Bill when it becomes law.  The Labour Party are anxious that the services proposed should be provided promptly and, if this section is accepted by the Minister, then he will have made full legal provision to prevent an ethical abuse, removing one contentious matter from the difficult path he will have of making this in fact a fully operative service.</P>
    <P>As to the section itself, it might be argued that it will enable any doctor to refuse to treat a patient, to give a medical certificate to a patient and to conceal records which may indicate carelessness or negligence.  The section does none of these things.  Doctors employed by local authorities, whether as dispensary doctors, hospital medical officers, specialists or county medical officers are all employed in a statutory manner, with statutory <Col N="1023" /> duties to perform competently and efficiently.  The Minister has machinery for ensuring that neglect in carrying out these duties is investigated and, if necessary, punished.  This section does not alter that position and neither does it alter the position where a patient can have his grievances voiced, if he so wishes, at a county council meeting, or redress for neglect pursued, in the courts of justice.  The saving clauses, furthermore, in the section ensure the preservation of a machinery which may deal with a doctor's failure to cater for a patient's needs, should such arise.</P>
    <P>The section, as stated earlier, is designed to prohibit an autocratic manager from abusing his powers to infringe on an old-established and recognised principle.  It would be a serious matter if a manager could compel any doctor to disclose records or make reports on the medical condition of a patient without the knowledge and consent of the person concerned. There may be records of such attempts on the files of the Minister's Department; he will know that.  If there are none such, it would be possible for the Minister to get the information from those doctors engaged in or retired from the service.</P>
    <P>The inclusion in this section of the prohibition of the county manager directing a doctor to withhold a service is very important.  We are approaching that point, if we have not reached it, where there is over-specialisation in medical science.  There is a risk with intensive specialisation on the eye, the ear, the heart, the lungs, the stomach, the kidneys, the bones and so on, that the patient, a human being, is overlooked. Members of local councils are aware of the increase in their staffs since the county managers were appointed, and where so often it is impossible to find out who exactly is handling a particular matter.  We are anxious, knowing the background, to make sure that this same approach is not going to mutilate the human being, that, for example, a county surgeon will not be prevented from&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="Mr. O'Donovan Mr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Senator <Col N="1024" /> asked the permission of the Chair to read this speech, or whose speech is he reading?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>With all due respect to the Senator, I interrupt nobody.  In any event, I have explained the points.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that Ministers frequently read speeches in this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>And Senator O'Donovan never complained.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is understood that members in the House may not read their speeches without permission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMcCrea" hpid="Mr. McCrea Mr. McCrea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCrea</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nothing criminal in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>I press the Minister to accept this amendment.  Why should any county manager have authority over a doctor?  A doctor is a professional man, and the doctor and the patient have their own way of life. There is a recognised principle in this country.  The majority of county managers are very decent men.  Why should any county manager, if he so desires, prevent a doctor from doing a certain thing and compel him to do another thing?  If, for instance, there was anything wrong with Senator O'Donovan&mdash;I hope that will never be the case&mdash;why should the county manager have the right to know that? In the hope of making this Bill operative and successful, I appeal to the Minister in all earnestness not to give such power to any manager.  As I said, the majority of them are decent men, but there is always the danger of there being a scoundrel.</P>
      <P>A minute ago the Minister referred to the reason why he was preventing meetings was because there was the danger that there might be four people who would not act correctly.  Now, you are giving power to one person.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Where are we giving him the power?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>Are not the dispensary doctors and the doctors we appoint servants of the county manager and can he not demand the records?  Is not that in the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1025" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is not anything like that in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>The idea of this amendment is to prevent that happening. However, I will finish by appealing to the Minister to take notice of this new section and, if possible, accept it. If he does not accept it, I would ask him to bring in something between this and the Report Stage, that will protect the harmony that has existed in this country between doctor and patient&mdash;that harmony with which no layman has the right to interfere.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMcCrea" hpid="Mr. McCrea Mr. McCrea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCrea</NameTxt>
      <P>In seconding this amendment, I want to support all the points that have been made by Senator Tunney.  I want to make it perfectly clear that we are supporting this Bill, not, of course, because it gives us everything we desire but because we appreciate that it is an improvement in the social services and the health services.  For that reason we have given careful consideration to this section.  We put it down with a view to making the Bill more acceptable to the people who are at present entitled to free medical treatment and the multitude of people who will come in under this new Health Bill.  If this amendment were adopted, there would be nothing in this section which would enable a doctor legally to refuse certificates or whatever records are required for purely administrative purposes.</P>
      <P>On the other hand, where certificates are required for allowances under, say, the Infectious Diseases (Maintenance Regulations) Act, T.B. priority cases under the Housing Acts, or where medical evidence is required for claimants for home assistance, then we hold that no powers should be given to a county manager to refuse the medical certificate in the cases I have mentioned where information is required for administrative purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister is a doctor.  I know he is conversant with all aspects of rural life.  He knows how difficult it is to get people to enter a hospital or a sanatorium, particularly the younger people.  It is even difficult to get them to attend a clinic, a dispensary or a doctor's residence.  Let me illustrate <Col N="1026" /> the point in this way.  Let us say that Mary Murphy is paying a visit to Dr. Ryan.  It may be a personal visit. Her next door neighbour sees her going to the doctor and says: &ldquo;There must be something wrong with Mary Murphy.  I saw her going to the doctor.&rdquo;  Her next door neighbour confirms that by saying that she thought Mary Murphy was not looking too well.  By the time it has got to the end of the townland, Mary Murphy will probably be suffering from heart disease or cancer and will be looked upon as a menace to society.  That is the position, as I see it.</P>
    <P>If the manager is given authority to demand the records of every patient who comes into hospital, and if these records are kept on the files in the county health office so that every Tom, Dick and Harry there can peruse them, you may have a whispering campaign in the county and that is certainly not going to help in the success of this Bill.  I would be a great satisfaction for a patient to know that the confidence between his doctor and himself was being maintained.  That is one of the reasons why we are asking the Minister to accept this amendment and have such a guarantee inserted in the Bill.  I cannot see any substantial reason, and I believe Senators will agree with me, why the private and personal affairs of every man, woman and child in this State should not be kept inviolate.  No one should be permitted to interfere as far as that is concerned.</P>
    <P>There is no suggestion, as Senator Tunney has pointed out, that a doctor coming under this section should be safeguarded in, say, a case of the neglect of a patient.  There is ample provision in the Bill for dealing with matters of that kind.  I regret that the committees which are to be set up under the Bill are not being given statutory powers to deal with such matters, similar to those possessed by the committees administering the British health services.  Our only purpose in putting down the amendment is to improve the Bill and to make it more acceptable to those who will come under it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>My objection to the <Col N="1027" /> amendment is that I cannot see any necessity for it.  It is all right to say that a county manager must not order a doctor to give a patient any particular treatment.  He never did that and never will.  One might as well put in an amendment saying that the county manager must not prevent a doctor from saying his prayers.  He has never done anything like that and never will.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMcCrea" hpid="Mr. McCrea Mr. McCrea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCrea</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister can assure us that the county manager will not be in a position to demand the records that we have spoken of, then we are satisfied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The two Senators are members of local authorities and they know that, over the years, patients have been coming into the county hospitals, the county homes and the mental hospitals.  I suppose a fair number of people would know about a person going into a mental hospital. Information of that kind is not abused. Everyone gets to know about it, and it cannot be helped if uncharitable people go around saying that such a person has gone into a mental hospital.</P>
      <P>I would direct the Senator's attention to sub-section (3) of Section 5 of the Health Act of 1947, which provides:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Where regulations under this Act require records to be kept in relation to the health of individuals, such provision shall be made therein as the Minister thinks necessary or proper for ensuring that the parts of such records containing the names of such individuals shall be treated in a confidential manner, and shall not be published save with the consent of such individuals.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not think that any doctor will report on any patient without the patient's consent.  It would be a very serious thing for a doctor to do.  A patient, for example, goes to a dispensary. The fact that he does so means that he is accepting free treatment. The doctor will give the patient treatment at the dispensary, but he may have to send him on to the county hospital.  If so, he naturally has to tell the county surgeon what he thinks <Col N="1028" /> is wrong.  Otherwise, the county surgeon would not know whether he should admit the patient or not.  If the doctor said that this was a very urgent and serious case of ulcer of the stomach which was likely to prove serious, the county surgeon would say that he would have to admit the man. On the other hand, if it was a case of hernia and was not a case of strangulated hernia, the county surgeon might say that the patient could wait for some time, and that he would admit him when there was room in the hospital.  The point is that the doctor must tell the surgeon.  As far as I know, that information does not go beyond the county surgeon.  Records are kept in every hospital, but I think that these things are done fairly well. In all these things there is nothing as good as custom and practice.</P>
    <P>Let us take, for example, what has been going on in this country for many years.  Doctors have been examining people for national health benefits and signing certificates that patients were suffering from so-and-so.  These certificates are sent up to headquarters here&mdash;24,000 of them arrive every week. The clerks working in Cathal Brugha Street must, at that rate, get to know the ailments of a couple of hundred thousand people every year.  The information just goes through as a sort of routine, and the clerks are not very interested in it.  They get the certificates and the cheques go out.  You could not run that organisation otherwise. As I have said, practice and custom work out in that way.  If you had any regulation about secrecy in that case, a conscientious doctor might say that he could not sign the certificate for a patient.  The patient would then say that he could not get his national health insurance benefit.  The doctor's reply would be: &ldquo;That is not my affair; I cannot sign the certificate under the new regulations&rdquo;.  I suggest to the Senator that it would be much better leave things work out as they are.</P>
    <P>As far as this particular matter is concerned, we are adding on certain people.  Over a number of years, a third of the population has been getting free services.:  Now, we are <Col N="1029" /> adding on a certain number who will be entitled to hospital and specialist services.  I do not know why any Senator should be disturbed, or why he should think, that there is going to be an undue violation of secrecy as far as those people who are being added on are concerned.  I do not see why they should not flow in with the others, and why we should not allow things to work out as they have been working in the past.</P>
    <P>I feel that if we were to accept an amendment like this it would be a sort of admission on our part that things had not been done right in the past and that we should put them right now.  I must say that I have never got any complaints from any county council or anyone else in this particular issue.  I think there would be a certain amount of danger if we were to accept the first part of the amendment. I sometimes have to deal with complaints.  I may get a complaint from a person saying that he sent for a dispensary doctor, that he did not come until the next day and that when he came the child was dead or some other kind of complaint.  The charges made are very serious sometimes, but the doctor was not to blame, because he never got the message or something else may have happened.  I think we should leave things as they are.</P>
    <P>As I have said, a third of the population, those in the public assistance classes, have been getting free services and treatment for many years now.  The information that a certain number of doctors, nurses and hospitals have about some of those people has never been misused.  Under this Bill, we are going to include a certain number of other people as well for hospital treatment.  I do not see why we should think that there is going to be a great violation of secrecy in the future.</P>
    <P>As far as doctors are concerned, there is no doctor, I think, as far as I know, who would take dictation from anyone as to how he would treat a patient.  I do not think he could be ordered as to how he would treat a patient.  I want to assure the Seanad and the public that if any doctor tells me, as long as I am Minister for <Col N="1030" /> Health, that anybody has attempted to interfere with him as to how he should treat his patients, I will be on the doctor's side on that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMcCrea" hpid="Mr. McCrea Mr. McCrea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCrea</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to make the position perfectly clear as far as we are concerned.  We are no perturbed in any way as far as the doctor, the patient or the people in Cathal Brugha Street are concerned.  We are worried about giving extraordinary powers to the county manager.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think there is anything in this Bill like that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMcCrea" hpid="Mr. McCrea Mr. McCrea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCrea</NameTxt>
      <P>He might have power to demand certain records from a doctor if certain expenses are to be incurred in connection with a patient. If the Minister could assure us that that will not happen we are perfectly happy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  If a middle income group person, say, a farmer with £40 valuation, wants a simple operation for appendicitis the doctor says to him: &ldquo;You need an operation; I will send you to a hospital.&rdquo;  The farmer says: &ldquo;Very good, I will go into hospital.&rdquo; Nobody interferes except his own doctor.  The county surgeon accepts him, he undergoes the operation and is sent home.  Now the county manager comes along and says: &ldquo;This man perhaps could pay a couple of hundred pounds.&rdquo;  It is not from the doctor he seeks that information. He goes to somebody else.  I presume he will go to the home assistance officer because they know the people very well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMcCrea" hpid="Mr. McCrea Mr. McCrea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCrea</NameTxt>
      <P>Too well for my liking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Maybe too well, but they will be able to give information to the county manager whether they should charge or not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has cited the case of a doctor sending a man from the country up to a surgeon.  That has been the practice and, thank goodness, it has never been abused in this country.  However, if a small farmer goes to the doctor and the county manager is asked about the bill, the latter, a lay person, comes into the <Col N="1031" /> picture and knows what is wrong with the man.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No, not necessarily.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>If you give that assurance we will accept it.  What we are afraid of is that the manager will be given too much power.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No, he will not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Health will not have much power to deal with him because I understand that the manager is the servant of the Minister for Local Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No, he is not the servant of the Minister for Local Government. He comes under the Minister for Local Government and under my Department for other legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>We hold the fear that the manager and his clerks will know what is wrong with the farmer.  We would like the situation to continue as it has been going on in the past which reflects great credit on the doctors.  I still would ask the Minister very earnestly between now and the Report Stage, if he is not prepared to accept this new section, to devise some means whereby some clerk in a county council office will not know what is wrong with certain patients.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>If the county surgeon insists on his right that cannot happen. He will accept a patient, operate on him and send him home.  As far as the county manager is concerned all he will ever be told is that such and such a person was here from 6th June to 7th July.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I can take it that the Seanad can consider the Minister's remarks as a definite assurance that so far as regulations can be made by him under Section 22 dealing with the manner of provision of institutional and specialist treatment are concerned, they are not going to infringe the principles which are suggested in this amendment.  I think the Minister is right in saying that under the Bill as it stands there is nothing there <Col N="1032" /> specifically giving authority to the county manager or anyone else to inquire into records or to dictate to the doctor as to the manner of treatment. But it does seem to me that by a sidedoor method this power could come into the Bill by reason of the fact that this Bill is dependent entirely on ministerial regulations.  I accept from the present Minister his assurances that any regulations made by him will not be such as to give these powers to the county manager or to the local authority as a whole.  We are not legislating just for the term of office of the present Minister.  It may be that this will crop up in seven, ten or 15 years' time when another Minister with a different outlook is in office. I gather Senator Tunney's appeal to the Minister is to see if something could be devised to ensure that the undertaking given by the Minister now in regard to these regulations will have the force of law in some way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>As long as the professional people&mdash;and Senator O'Higgins and Senator Cunningham will, I am quite sure, agree with me that they are jealous about their rights and privileges&mdash;the county surgeon and the county physician insist on their rights nothing can go wrong.  Unless you have a weak county surgeon combined with a scoundrel of a county manager nothing can go wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree entirely with the Minister's presentation of the facts of the case, but surely the amendment actually gives power to the Minister and gives power to the consultative health committee which, according to the Minister, nobody has now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the amendment makes the position of the doctor very much worse.  It suggests that the Minister now will have power to compel a doctor to reveal all kinds of secrets and records about his patient which the Minister has not got at the moment.  This question of what we call professional secrecy is not a matter that benefits the doctor in any way.  It is for the protection of the patient.  It prevents anybody else <Col N="1033" /> knowing what was wrong with the patient.  It does not affect the doctor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Except legally, I think it does.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Legally, perhaps. I agree with what the Minister has said and I am satisfied that the doctors have these rights to withhold information from the county manager or from anybody else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>I will accept that if the Minister will give me an assurance that the patient has the same rights in this regard.  He has no organisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The patient has the rights.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 51.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 51 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Under Section 51, sub-section (2): &ldquo;The Minister may by Order vary the division of the functional area of a health authority into dispensary districts and may by such Order provide for such transfers of officers as he considers necessary or expedient.&rdquo;  In other words, he may change the dispensary district and, so far as I read from this, change the dispensary doctor from one part of the country to another.  It may mean that he will only change from one part of a county to another, but I think it possibly gives him power to change from one part of the country to another.  However, that does not matter very materially.  What does matter is that a doctor may be told at any time that his residence and his whole area in which he worked is going to be changed and he is going to be moved from, say, North Donegal to South Donegal or, for all I know, he may be moved from Donegal to Cork.  I think that is a hardship on the doctor.  It may affect his family and it may affect his own life.  He and his wife have made their friends.  He <Col N="1034" /> may like the school his children are attending; they may be getting on well there.</P>
      <P>Some Senators may say there are other Government officials, like civil servants, who are also changing in that way.  However, they are not sent from one remote district to another but go from one big town to another where things like education make no difference.  If the doctor is sent from one remote town to another, it causes great hardship.  There is another difference between a civil servant and a doctor.  A doctor living in a certain area of the country has made friends and people get to like him.  He knows a great deal about them and has built up a certain amount of private practice and goodwill.  As soon as he is changed he loses that completely&mdash; someone else takes his place&mdash;and he is at great financial loss for some time for that reason.</P>
      <P>We have had some examples of forcible removal and forcible appointments and do not want to have trouble of that kind again.  It is really not necessary that a doctor should be moved around in this way and I would appeal to the Minister to alter the wording by adding, say, &ldquo;with the doctor's consent.&rdquo;  The Minister might suggest to the doctor that he should be moved and the doctor may agree. That is done very often in other appointments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Furthermore, the doctor has no one to whom he can appeal.  The Minister will bear me out that there is no appeal provided.  The Minister's word is law. He can direct a dispensary doctor to change from one part of the country to another.  It is very unfair and will cause great hardship on doctors if it is passed.  It will be made use of in certain cases and can give rise to trouble.  A doctor may be moved against his will from one place to another.  He has no appeal and must do as he is told.  He is tied hand and foot, as if he resigns from the dispensary service he loses his pension rights, seniority and so on.  Therefore, he cannot resign, he is absolutely tied and the Minister and the Department would know that and would know that <Col N="1035" /> they can move him around.  It is very unfair and frightfully unjust to have a person in the position where he must go.  He might be given the option to go but I do not think he should be compelled.  I would appeal to the Minister to reconsider the section.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree fully with Senator Cunningham, if the section can be interpreted as Senator Cunningham says, namely, that the Minister can transfer a dispensary doctor from one part of the country to another.  When I read it, that was not the meaning I took.  I understood it would give the Minister power to alter dispensary areas, possibly to make two where there is one now&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and that the doctor would be retained in the same geographical area.  I would not see the same objection if that is so, as would exist if it has the interpretation Senator Cunningham says.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Some years ago when Dr. Ward had a National Health Bill before this House, I remember making some little contribution on the question of dispensary doctors and their operating districts.  I hold the same view very strongly to-day.  When our present districts were allocated, we had not the means of transport and communication we have now.  Districts which then would be very large and difficult to operate would not be so difficult to-day.  The suggestion I put forward then was that in a large part of our country we could amalgamate a number of dispensary districts and the person relieved of duty as a dispensary doctor could be better employed looking after the school medical inspection or in some other specialised medical occupation.  I am sure he would be just as content and would be doing much more useful work, than operating in a district in which there is very little to do.  It is extraordinary how the whole picture can change overnight. When you meet dispensary doctors down the country who are making a case to the county council or <Col N="1036" /> the health authority, their case is that there is no private practice, that a dispensary doctor has to live on his remuneration as a dispensary doctor. Now we have the suggestion read into this by Senator Cunningham that the purpose of this amendment is to give the Minister power to transfer a dispensary doctor from one area to another, and that the doctor is going to lose the very valuable asset he had of private practice and social life.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>It would vary in different areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>This case is not made at all when there is an application before the local authority, to be presented to the Minister, for increased remuneration.  It is quite the opposite case then, but that is beside the point.</P>
      <P>I would urge the Minister to retain the powers given in this section for that particular purpose, as our dispensary districts are outworn and do not conform to modern times.  There should be some co-ordination or cooperation between the Department of Health and the Department of Posts and Telegraphs to provide a telephone service to a greater extent for calling a doctor or a nurse in the remote parts of the country.  That would improve the medical service very much and, at the same time, would not deprive any dispensary doctor of his livelihood.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFitzsimons" hpid="Mr. Fitzsimons Mr. Fitzsimons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzsimons</NameTxt>
      <P>I approve of this section, subject to adding something on the Report Stage.  It says that the Minister can by Order vary the division of the functional area.  I suggest the Minister should add: &ldquo;After consultation with the county council.&rdquo;  Most local authorities have been looking for years for this power.  Dispensary doctors in most counties want some readjustment of their areas so the time is appropriate for us to show some signs of democracy.  The Minister could add: &ldquo;After consultation with the county council&rdquo; or &ldquo;After consultation with the doctor&rdquo;.  That would be an improvement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanHartney" hpid="Mr. Hartney Mr. Hartney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hartney</NameTxt>
      <P>As one who referred to that matter on the Second Reading, I cannot see that there is anything intended to bring undue hardship on any <Col N="1037" /> officer&mdash;I am convinced there is a necessity for an alteration of the present districts.  If that necessitated the shifting of a doctor, it could not mean very much.  He would still be within striking distance of his previous district. He is working for a certain health authority and he could be shifted only from one functional area of that authority&mdash;usually a county&mdash;to another functional area of the same authority.  In most cases it could only be to another part of the county and it would be very rarely that would happen.  I would not see anything happening as Senator Cunningham suggests, where a doctor could be taken out of a remote place in Kerry and, to make his purgatory still harder, shifted to Mayo or Donegal.  He could be shifted only within the area of the health authority by which he is employed.</P>
      <P>In fairness to doctors, it would often be better for doctors, when they come into a health district, to be employed just by the health authority, with no fixture in any area.  It would often be better for the doctor if he could be removed.  We know that in the past the same thing could be done and he could be changed around.  He may just come into the service in the county and then be shifted from Clonakilty to Mallow and in a month's time be sent to Castletownbere.  There is nothing by way of hardship to doctors there and if necessity demands it it is only right that there should be this provision. In fairness to local authorities I have seen in the past where they have given the benefit of the doubt to doctors who wanted to go into places they thought would be suitable.  I do not think it is intended to create any hardship and I believe that it is quite fair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to say that what I had in mind in this section was the revision of dispensary districts.  In some of the newly built-up areas in Dublin where there is a shifting population, I am sure Senators will agree, there is necessity for the new dispensary districts which have been set up. It might have happened&mdash;although I do not thing it has in any particular case&mdash;that a man might be operating <Col N="1038" /> in a particular area and partly outside it and that he would be given some of these new areas to cover and would say: &ldquo;That is not my area.&rdquo;  It is to cover that kind of case that there is this provision in the section.  I know a town in my home county that is being divided into two areas.  There is no trouble there about a man accepting half, but he could legally say: &ldquo;I am not going to accept half.&rdquo;  It was to get over cases of that kind that this provision was put there.  I admit that Senator Cunningham has a point and the provision could be used harshly and I would like to look into it again and see what could be done.</P>
      <P>Section 11, for instance, deals with a very similar case where an institution is closed and a man may be allocated to another institution by the local authority If the man feels aggrieved&mdash; the very same case was put to me in the Dáil&mdash;because he might be in a town where there was a good secondary day school for his children and might be moved to a place where the school facilities were not good, what are we going to do about it?  The Dáil agreed that he could appeal to the Minister.  Here, of course, it is the Minister who is doing it, and unless we change it and let the local authority do it and then let him have an appeal to the Minister as an arbitrator or put in some such condition as, say, &ldquo;a reasonable or short distance,&rdquo; or something like that, I do not know what else can be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I would suggest, &ldquo;without undue hardship.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Or &ldquo;in consultation with the local authority.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 52 to 57 inclusive agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 58.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 58 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>This is an excellent section.  Is it possible to prohibit the importation of filling material unless the importer has a warranty from the seller, such as happens at <Col N="1039" /> present about pulp?  Would not that simplify the whole thing?  There is a very elaborate provision about the importation, and is it possible to prohibit the importation unless there is a warranty from the seller?  Would the Minister consider that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Importers are registered, and having been registered and licensed, I think they are quite entitled to import then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, I see.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 59.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 59 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we have something to say about this section. This is a very important section, and it really has nothing to do with the new Health Bill.  It is one of these general sections about health and again about control.  This is a section meant to bring about and arrange about the control of certain substances including what we call radio-active substances, and also, it seeks to control irradiating apparatus.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now radio-active substances are substances which give out constantly various types of rays which are used for several purposes in science, in various laboratories, and they are also used in the universities by research workers and also extensively in the treatment of disease.  Most of these substances are quite new and I suppose that is the reason for this new legislation to control their use.  These substances are dangerous; if they are handled by people who do not understand them they may cause injury to the person who may come too close to them if they are not properly managed or handled.  So that there is something to be said for controlling their use and storage and distribution. There is a certain amount of these things in this country and, as I said, they are used in laboratories and in hospitals.  They are not produced here really, or only to a very slight degree, but they are imported from abroad <Col N="1040" /> under the control system which is laid down by the country from which they are imported and the transportation is quite safe because they are properly guarded and up to the present they are handled only by people who understand them.  There has been legislation in these countries abroad about these substances and I have no objection whatsoever to the Minister introducing in this Bill a clause to control them.  They are substances which should properly be controlled but I think they should be controlled by a properly constituted body and not by the Department of Health because I do not think the Department is qualified to do it.  I think you require a body something like the Medical Research Council.  I have been told and I hope it is true that the Minister intends to hand over control of these things to the Medical Research Council and with that I am quite in agreement. I also wish to emphasise that I agree that these substances should for the present at any rate be controlled until we have more experience and know more about them.  On the other hand I suppose nobody will attempt to use them except people who know about them.  They are used at present by certain doctors in Dublin and by scientists, but nobody else has access to them and it is right that they should be controlled.</P>
    <P>Now we come to irradiating apparatus. That is a much more serious matter from our point of view because irradiating appartus includes such appliances as X-rays, and short-wave therapy which is used in the treatment of certain inflammatory diseases, of rheumatism and very extensively in surgery, and which is used, I suppose, in every hospital in Dublin at the present time and in many doctors' consulting rooms.  We have things like infra-red lamps used by nurses in the treatment of aches and pains and rheumatism and by masseurs and masseuses and people of that kind for special treatment.  We also have Finsen light and ultra violet light used in the treatment of skin diseases and many other diseases.  We have the ordinary sun lamp used as a tonic and often recommended because of its beneficial rays as treatment for children <Col N="1041" /> especially in winter time and which you will find in many people's homes. Patients are sometimes recommended to use these rays and parents are often advised to give these rays to their children, especially during the winter, since they are particularly beneficial in this climate.  Naturally people find it cheaper and more convenient to buy these lamps instead of bringing the children to some institution every day. These lamps are not very expensive. The people are shown how to use them and there is no danger.  Indeed, they are less dangerous than an open electric fire.</P>
    <P>Powers are being sought under this Bill to control all these things which have been used so extensively here for years past.  Now if a doctor wants to have an X-ray machine in his consulting room he must procure a licence.  If a nurse requires any of these special lamps or lights that I have mentioned she must have a licence.  Why?  The Minister will tell us, of course, that there will be no difficulty about getting a licence; all one need do is apply.  But this provision gives the Minister a certain control.  We have never had any reports of damage or injury from the use of these machines.  Yet, the Minister is now seeking to get control of them.  He will, in future, know who possesses them.  I think the provision gives the Minister certain undesirable powers.  He will be in a position to refuse a licence.  Some people may think I am exaggerating but let me repeat again, and this is important, that I know a hospital in this city where there was a treatment machine which became worn out.  The Department of Health has refused to give a grant to the hospital to buy a new machine.</P>
    <P>Now in all hospitals one gets cases of cancer.  In some cases the disease is not diagnosed until after the operation has been performed and microscopic examination has taken place. Patients may have to be treated by machine following operation and, if there is no machine in the particular hospital, the patient will have to be transferred to another hospital.  Very often the relatives ask that the patient should not be told from what he or she <Col N="1042" /> is suffering when it is a case of cancer. If the treatment machine is not available in the particular hospital in which the patient happens to be the patient will have to be transferred to a cancer hospital.  He may be sent to St. Luke's, in Rathgar.  He will immediately know the disease from which he is suffering. Furthermore, the doctors who operated will lose control and touch with the patient.  The principle is entirely wrong.  The people responsible for the operation are also responsible for the subsequent treatment in consultation of the colleague who carries out that treatment.  At the moment the patient remains with his own doctor.  That is desirable.  It is customary.  That may not be customary in the future if this Bill passes into law.</P>
    <P>A new hospital is being planned in Dublin at the moment and the people who are planning it were told not to make any arrangements about X-ray treatment for patients.  Here we have a direction from the Department of Health as to what may or may not be done.</P>
    <P>I commend the Minister for introducing this measure for the control of radio-active isotopes because they are dangerous substances but I see no reason why the other apparatus I have mentioned should be controlled.  The control does not exist in other countries. These machines have been in use for more than 30 years in hospitals, in doctors' consulting rooms, in private houses.  Why does the Minister seek control now?  I hope the Minister will tell me I am wrong in suggesting that it is merely to get more power and control but that is the fear I have because of certain things that have happened.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any use in telling the Senator that he is wrong, since he will only get up and say the same thing over again.  How often has he told the poor simple Senators the way in which I am interfering with the voluntary hospitals?  Yet, that is just not true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not take it personally.  I am referring to the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is just not true.  I will <Col N="1043" /> not say any more about it.  I do not care how often Senator Cunningham repeats it.  It is not true.  It is Irish Medical Association propaganda and it should stop.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not Irish Medical Association propaganda.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister will not interefere. He is paying the voluntary hospitals' expenses.  He will do anything the voluntary hospitals ask him. This is just Irish Medical Association propaganda and there is no foundation whatsoever for it.</P>
      <P>The Department of Health has been considering for a long time some legislation in relation to radio-active substances. I must say when I read the literature on these substances I found it absolutely frightening.  If someone gets hold of radio-active substances for the purposes of experimentation, or anything else, it is impossible to get rid of them.  They cannot be burned, since the ashes left are themselves radio-active.  They cannot be put into water, because the water becomes radio-active.  It is a frightening substance and someone must control it. For health purposes, it is the Minister for Health who should control it.</P>
      <P>As Professor Cunningham has pointed out, doctors use certain irradiating apparatus; so do hospitals and nurses.  I have no intention of interfering with these.  I can well imagine that had I not included this provision the Irish Medical Association would have come to me asking me to control the use of these irradiating apparatuses because unauthorised people were using them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>We have never done that, not once in the last 30 years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I suppose that was because the association did not think of it, but you did more foolish things than that in the past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>We instruct both nurses and masseuses in the use of the apparatus.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1044" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not referring to those.  I am speaking of unauthorised people who are neither nurses nor doctors nor anything else.  It will be a good thing if we can stop such people using these things.  There is no reason why nurses should not use infra-red or sunlight treatment, but there are unauthorised people using apparatus and it is important that they should be stopped.</P>
      <P>It seems to me that when I include a provision in the Bill the Irish Medical Association thinks up all the arguments against it.  I must say they have thought up very good arguments in this particular instance.  Had I not included the provision I am sure they would have thought up excellent arguments as to why I should put it in. That is the position in which I find myself all the time.  They oppose anything I try to do and, if I do not do something, they ask why I have not done it.  To a great extent I suppose that is what is responsible for the delay we had in passing this Bill in the Dáil, and for some of the time we have spent in discussing the Bill here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not being unreasonably delayed here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I admit that.  I have already arranged to consult the Medical Research Council in connection with all these matters.  I do not know anything about them.  I would not know one end of an X-Ray from the other.  I would not know which side to stand on.  But, I want to get advice and I intend to get advice from the Medical Research Council on all this business.  As far as I am concerned I am quite prepared to exempt certain things only for the fact that unauthorised persons are using them. For that reason it may be well to say that doctors can use this and nobody else or that dentists can use this or that hospitals can use it, as the case may be.  To that extent, I think the regulation might be useful.  If Senator Cunningham would look at it in that way, he might see some good in this section.  If the Medical Research Council, which is composed, I think, entirely of doctors, say to me: &ldquo;Leave <Col N="1045" /> certain things out of your regulations altogether,&rdquo; I will do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister would not consider putting in sub-section (2) &ldquo;the Minister may after consultation with the Medical Research Council&rdquo; so as to put the Medical Research Council into the Bill, considering that the Department, as he says, and it is of course quite credible, has no specialist knowledge of this particular thing, which is peculiarly specialised? If the Minister is in fact going to make regulations, not only after consultation but on the advice of the Medical Research Council, would not it be advisable to put that into the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I see one objection to that, that there may be no Medical Research Council there, perhaps, in three or four years time and then the Minister could do nothing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is again accusing me of attacking him personally, which I do not do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am taking it as the Minister, not personally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I refer to a Minister for Health in this county.  I mentioned this question of a certain hospital which was refused permission or were told that, if they bought this apparatus which they wanted to renew one that had worn out, they would not be allowed money for it on the deficit. That is what I was told about it.  I do not know whether that occurred during the present Minister's occupancy of the position or not.  I do not know who was the Minister at the time. That happened.  I would like the Minister to deny here that that did happen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not deny it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Then why accuse me of putting forward this as a matter of propaganda?  It is not propaganda.  It is a matter of fact. The old apparatus is still lying in the hospital in the room where it was used and no patient has been treated there for a couple of years because they had not go a new one.  Is it not a fact that a certain hospital could not get permission <Col N="1046" /> for a treatment machine from the Department of Health?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to see that too.  I am not accepting that as true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister accuses me of being grossly inaccurate and of putting forward propaganda. I am not.  I am merely pointing out that that is what has been happening; that is the tendency and the more power that is given to the Minister or the Department under him, the worse it is.  In that way they control everything; they can direct things.  That is the theme of this whole Bill: control, dictatorship, direction.  That runs right through the Bill the whole way. The Minister, whoever he may be, will be master of the whole medical profession and of all the people who are ill.  They will do what they are told and so will the doctors.  That is dictatorship of a kind you have not in any other country as far as medicine is concerned.  I would like to ask the Minister, finally, is there any precedent for this control of an irradiating apparatus?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>In other words, is there any other country that he can tell me where all these things that are being specified are under the control of the Department of Health?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, in our neighbouring country, England, Scotland and Wales.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>In England, no.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Radio-active isotopes alone were handed over and the Minister refused to have anything to do with them and he gave them to the Medical Research Council in England, but X-rays and other things are not controlled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>They control irradiating apparatus, just as is proposed in this section.  The Senator mentioned certain specific instances where we turned down, let us say, an X-ray apparatus. I would like to see the facts of that <Col N="1047" /> case.  I think that if I put the facts before this Seanad or a jury of this Seanad they would say that the Minister had a point, and may be some of them would say that the Minister was quite right.</P>
      <P>I got a proposition the other day.  A certain hospital&mdash;I forget which&mdash;has eight operating theatres.  There is very full apparatus for giving anæsthetics which costs about £120.  They had seven of these.  They wanted the eighth.  It was put to me by the Department, why should they want the eight.  Are there ever eight operations going on at the same time?  I said: &ldquo;Maybe so, but you had better not bring me down again on the voluntary hospitals&rdquo;.  I thought it was ridiculous to give the eighth, that at least they could use the ordinary apparatus for giving an anæsthetic and not put the country to the expense of another £120, but I had to sanction it because, otherwise, Senator Cunningham would be quoting here to-night that I turned down an apparatus for giving an anæsthetic costing £120.  That is the sort of thing that is being put up every day of the week.  There was a very costly apparatus asked for by a hospital. I do not remember the name of it but I do remember that it would be used only very occasionally, perhaps three or four times in the year, by any hospital, but it would be very important for those three or four times.  A neighbouring hospital had it.  We asked them could they not send three or four patients a year over to this hospital and they said: &ldquo;No, they would not&rdquo;.  We had to pay out of the hospitals' fund for that.  These are the sort of things that are put to us and these are the sort of things we have to agree to.  If we did not, Senator Cunningham would say that the control is going on.  They are most ridiculous things.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A new hospital is going to be built. The proposition was put to me that not only did the operating surgeon want a shower bath, but that every surgeon wanted his own shower bath. That is the sort of thing that is being put up.  Of course, we did not allow it.  Senator Cunningham does not <Col N="1048" /> quote that because he knows that the Seanad would laugh at him if he accused me of controlling the voluntary hospitals in that respect.</P>
    <P>There are the sort of propositions that are being put up.  That is the sort of money that would have to be spent if you had not some Minister or somebody else to control the ridiculous propositions put up by the staffs of the voluntary hospitals.  They are never refused anything reasonable.  In fact, they get a lot of things that are unreasonable. Why?  If you like, because I have not the moral courage to be accused by Senator Cunningham or the like of him of being unkind to the voluntary hospitals.  He has cowed me, I admit, by this talk.  Senator Cunningham and men like him, with this talk, have cowed me into agreeing to things that I should not agree to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a marvellous line for the Minister.  The Minister is excelling himself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should not agree if I were only fair to this country, but they are getting away with things of that kind.  Even so, you come along and quote some hospital that is going up where we said: &ldquo;Do not put in costly apparatus.&rdquo;  I do not remember any such thing.  I would like to see the circumstances and to know what they are in this particular case.  In some other place there was some other apparatus worn out which was not renewed. I do not remember that either, but I do remember, as I quoted, some of the ridiculous things I did agree to in order to try to prevent this propaganda going on that the Department of Health and the Minister for Health were up against the voluntary hospitals. If I had known that Senator Cunningham would come here, and if I had known that he would quote these cases, I suppose they would have got their X-ray and all these other things.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps they will get them before the Report Stage.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 60.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 60 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1049" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly Mr. P. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>The section gives power to the Minister to control materials for the destruction of rats and mice.  I wonder why rats and mice were specifically mentioned?  The Minister should delete &ldquo;rats and mice&rdquo; and substitute the word &ldquo;vermin.&rdquo;  Alternatively, he should add the word &ldquo;rabbits.&rdquo;  I read in the newspapers recently that a doctor or a scientist in France brought out some substance for use in the destruction of rabbits.  Possibly that may mean the destruction of the rabbit population in France.  Since rabbits in particular, perhaps, can or might become a very serious matter, and are becoming a very serious matter in this country, and since they are classified by most people as vermin, I think the Minister should at the Report Stage eliminate, &ldquo;rats and mice,&rdquo; and substitute, &ldquo;vermin,&rdquo; as an alternative.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister should stick to his rats and mice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I read about the particular virus referred to, and I do not know if it is dangerous to human beings.  That being so, I do not think it could be dealt with under the Health Bill.  However, I will have it examined before the Report Stage.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 61 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 62.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 62 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>On Section 62, I want to ask the Minister for some explanation on this section.  So far as I can read it, it provides facilities, for example, to teach, but the university is not getting control over those appointments.  I would like to know from the Minister if that is so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not get the point. Would you repeat it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>This section provides facilities to teach medicine but no medical school has control over the appointments of those who will teach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1050" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not exactly right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like an explanation of that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Take a college.  First of all the college will, in the legal wording, say: &ldquo;We are interested in such and such a hospital for clinical teaching.&rdquo; If the Minister thinks that that is right, he makes an Order that the hospital comes under this section.  The local authority then must provide facilities for clinical teaching.  At that stage, of course, you only go so far as saying that the surgeons, the physicans, or the gynaecologists in the hospital actually will do the clinical teaching.  That is as much as some colleges at least require at the moment &mdash;that the teaching be done by the staff there.  But they may go further. If a vacancy occurs, for instance, for a surgeon, the college may then say: &ldquo;We are interested in this appointment.&rdquo; If the Minister agrees that they have a case for being interested in the appointment he brings a certain regulation into force, and if he does the Local Appointments Commission in choosing their board will take three &mdash;or at least I should say half, let us say three&mdash;from the governing body of the college concerned, and appoint three themselves, and the Minister appoints the chairman.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There was a long-standing tussle between local authority hospitals and colleges in certain cases.  The local authority hospitals were making their appointments, as they were bound to by law, under the Local Appointments Commissioners, and the colleges argued that they were practically compelled to appoint those men professors when they were appointed, like pathology, bacteriology, surgery, medicine and so on&mdash;that they had no option.  They felt that it was very unfair to them, that is to the teaching college.  Well, I could not see how it could be got over, because we could not very well have the thing reversed&mdash;that the university would first make the appointment and the local authority would have to take whatever person it was, because he might not be the most suitable person for them, and after all the local authorities' first consideration <Col N="1051" /> must be the health of the people, not whether there is a good professor of surgery or medicine.  The health of the people is their first consideration, so they have to insist that they would have the appointment made with that point of view in mind.  Both sides met, and it was they suggested&mdash;it was not I suggested&mdash;I can tell you that&mdash; that they would agree to have the board composed of half and half with a neutral chairman, and eventually they agreed that the best person to appoint the neutral chairman was the Minister for Health.</P>
    <P>That is how the section arrives here; and the operation of the section&mdash;I would just repeat it before I sit down &mdash;is that, first of all, if a college medical school claims to have an interest in a hospital for clinical teaching the Minister may make an Order, and then the local authority must provide facilities for clinical teaching with the staff that is there.  If a vacancy occurs in that hospital, then the college may claim to have an interest in the appointment, and if it is agreed that they have an interest then the machinery laid down here would be brought into operation for the appointment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister.  I really wanted to draw attention to that, and must stress that it is a matter of great importance, especially at the present day.  I meant merely to warn&mdash;when I use the word &ldquo;warn&rdquo; I do not mean threaten, but to warn in a friendly sense&mdash;that if any establishment or hospital is being given facilities for teaching, or teaching is being established in a hospital, clinical teaching for students attending there, some medical school in Dublin&mdash;as you know we have three medical schools&mdash;should have a big say in the appointment of the people who are going to give the teaching, or that a medical school should at least approve of the appointment of those who are going to give that teaching. That, nowadays, has become essential, and, therefore, it would be a great mistake if facilities were given at any hospital where people in that hospital who <Col N="1052" /> would give this teaching were not approved of by some medical school in the city.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 63.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 17:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before sub-section (3) to insert the following new sub-sections:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(3)  Where a health authority provide a course of instruction under this section, they may, at their discretion, permit registered medical practitioners who are not medical officers to attend at such course.</P>
      <P>(4)  The Minister shall notify the Medical Registration Council of courses of instruction approved under this section.</P>
      <P>The amendment, I think, is fairly clear.  I think it is perhaps somewhat, if you like, on the lines of Senator Cunningham's warning on the teaching and that the teaching authority should have some say on those appointments. It has been put in that where a local authority provides a course for its own officers in any particular subject they shall at least notify the Medical Registration Council, which, of course, is the supreme authority so far as medical teaching is concerned in this country.</P>
      <P>In that way they keep at least in touch with that authority.  Now at the Consultative Council meeting we held recently I was pressed very strongly to bring this amendment in by the medical members, and provided this amendment was brought in they also thought that a second amendment should be brought in, that is, that where these courses are provided by a local authority for local authority officers there was no reason why other practitioners in the area, if they liked to avail of the courses, should not join if they wanted to; so these two amendments, therefore, are included in this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Why the Medical Registration Council instead of one of the teaching bodies?  It is not a teaching body.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1053" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>They are all appointed there by the teaching bodies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the only one that does combine them all.  That is fair enough.  Quite right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed &ldquo;That Section 63, as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCunningham" hpid="Professor Cunningham Professor Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Professor Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>There are certain things here that are somewhat worrying and give rise to a good deal of doubt.  I think that originally in this section there was some intention to establish a post-graduate medical school.  That has been dropped because I think the Minister very wisely has come to realise the inadvisability of that.  The State does not take on the teaching of a learned profession.  That lies within the province of a university or a special school appointed for that reason.  The State should have no say in it, and anybody who would attempt to interfere with that, take over control of it or upset it in any way from the State point of view or a Department of State would, I think, be crazy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The thing would get nowhere, and it would not be recognised by anybody. The teaching there would not be recognised by any other country.  That is a very serious matter.  Why does the Minister want to do all this about post-graduate teaching?  Remember that the hospitals that are best equipped to do this are the clinical hospitals.  You have the men there who are most experienced in that line of work, and they are the hospitals that should do it.  Do not think for a moment that I have any interest in this.  I have taken part in post-graduate courses in Dublin: our various medical schools run them fairly regularly.  We have one that is run by a combination of hospitals in Dublin. We have one in St. Vincent's Hospital for people studying for the M.D. degree, which goes on the whole year. Doctors come from all over the world for their training in the clinical hospitals.  Why does the Minister interfere and start something like this?  Do <Col N="1054" /> not think that I have any special or what has been called here &ldquo;vested&rdquo; interest.  I have taken part in a number of courses in Dublin.  We do not get any salary for it: we do not get paid. It means very hard work.  These men expect the most up-to-date things to be taught to them.  We do the work voluntarily.  The only charge is a nominal fee to cover expenses.</P>
    <P>I hope the House appreciates that I have no financial interest of any kind in the matter.  I am only interested in seeing that the doctors who come up from the country to do these courses will get the very best teaching.  Where will you find it?  It was intended to start a post-graduate medical school in St. Kevin's Hospital, Dublin.  You may have the most brilliant staff there: I do not say that you have not.  However, you have men in other hospitals who are well known as specialists in their own line and who are teaching and have been teaching for years and who have experience in how to teach. Many of them are on the staffs of universities and other medical schools in the city.  Which would you prefer should give this post-graduate teaching? Remember that we in this House are deciding it now.  The Minister may say that he has no intention of establishing a post-graduate medical school.  Let me, however, read sub-section (2) of Section 63 which states:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;A health authority, with the approval of the Minister, may do all things necessary to provide from time to time courses of instruction for medical officers (including medical officers of other authorities).&rdquo;</P>
    <P>In other words, he can do anything he likes.  He can start a post-graduate medical school to-morrow if he wishes. I think that that was in the original Bill or in a Bill a year or two before that.  I want the House to give this every consideration because it is very important.  Which do you think is the place where these men would get the better courses?  Is it in St. Kevin's Hospital or in some of the clinical or other of the hospitals?  It is for the members of this House to decide that. <Col N="1055" /> I think it is very dangerous for any Department of State to interfere with education in the learned professions. This provision may have been inserted in the Bill without giving it due consideration. Remember that State medical teaching does not exist elsewhere and it will not be accepted.  You may give post-graduate courses, but I do not think you will get the best value if you do it in that way.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not very much to say.  We thought it was necessary to have these courses in certain cases for local authority officers in particular. It might happen that the best person to give the course would be a man attached to a local authority hospital. Senators must bear in mind that the staffs in these local authority hospitals are now growing in experience.  They were recruited on very good competitive lines.  The best man was selected and got the job in each case. No influence of any kind was used on their behalf.  We have got an extremely good staff in these county hospitals. They now have experience, and they may prove to be the best men to give courses in certain subjects that would be necessary for local authority officers.  I do not see why I should make any apology for providing for that.  The power is not there at the moment.  I was informed that, legally, a local authority could not provide its hospital for clinical teaching of any kind, either post-graduate or undergraduate. This clause is necessary to enable local authorities to have their hospitals used for that purpose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It was never my intention to have a post-graduate school, as Senator Cunningham says.  I had no intention of having any diploma or any degree of any kind conferred as a result of a course of this kind.  The only thing that was ever thought of&mdash;as far as I am concerned&mdash;was courses in various things.  I do not see why anybody should object.  Knowledge is a great thing, wherever it comes from, if it is good.  If we can get a certain amount of knowledge from the local authority <Col N="1056" /> hospitals which might not be got as well from any other source, I think we should take power to see that that knowledge is got.  That is the object of the section.</P>
    <P>Section, as amended, agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 64 to 67, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 68.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Minister anything to say about the wording of sub-section (2) of this section, which reads:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Any offence which is to be prosecuted consequent on an inspection carried out in pursuance of this section by an authorised officer may be prosecuted by the health authority.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>It strikes me that you prosecute a person in respect of an offence.  You do not prosecute the offence.  Would the Minister look into that point?  It is just a matter of wording.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, I see.  I will look into that.</P>
      <P>Section agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 69 to 72, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Schedule and Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported with amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the next stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest Wednesday week next, the 14th instant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will we get the remaining stages on the 14th?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>We will see that later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is not doing very badly, for all his air of injured innocence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Thanks very much.</P>
      <P>Report stage ordered for 14th October.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 9.50 p.m. until Wednesday, the 14th October, 1953.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>