<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="21" Month="Jan" Year="1982" Vol="97" No="3" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 21 Eanáir 1982" DateEnglish="Thursday, 21 January 1982" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="269">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="269" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GemmaHussey" hpid="Mrs. G. Hussey Mrs. G. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. G. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take business in the following order: Nos. 1 and 2, with No. 1 concluding this morning, the Minister to come in at 12 o'clock. It is proposed to adjourn from 1 p.m. to 2 p.m., to begin No. 2 at 2 p.m. and to conclude at 5 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CatherineMcGuinness" hpid="Mrs. McGuinness Mrs. McGuinness">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGuinness</NameTxt>
      <P>May I make an inquiry about Nos. 7 and 8 and, in particular, No. 7?  The understanding given to us at the end of the session before Christmas was that at the first opportunity in Private Members' business these motions dealing with education would be taken.  In fact, my understanding up until late last week was that they were scheduled for today. Perhaps the Leader of the House would explain the reason for this blanket of silence.  I have made inquiries but I find I am simply being told that it will not be taken, not even that it will be taken next. I would like to know what exactly has happened.  Is it the same old excuse about legal proceedings?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>As my name is on the two motions I would like to support Senator McGuinness in her inquiry.  I would also like to add that we were told about these legal proceedings before Christmas and that this motion would be taken in the first week when we came back.  I presume the answer will now be that it is because <Col N="270" /> of legal proceedings again, but I ask the Leader of the House the reason we are not taking either of these two motions or taking them together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>My memory of this controversy about whether we should take these two motions is that in the opinion of this side of the House there was legal action pending.  It was on assurances from the other side of the House that there was no such legal action pending that the assurance was given by the Leader that we would take these after Christmas. Indeed many of us were anxious that they would be taken.  But since the assurance was given by the Opposition that no such legal proceedings were being instituted, it has been confirmed by the secretary of the INTO that such an action is pending.  I certainly would not recommend that this House should discuss something which is likely to end up in court.  I think it would be most prejudicial to anybody's case in this matter.  I agree with the Leader that this matter should not now be taken in view of what has been said by the INTO.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to clarify one point.  Assurances were never given by the Opposition that litigation would not be taken.  Our point last term was that at that stage proceedings had not been instituted and, consequently that there was no reason for not having the motions taken.  Certainly we did not give, nor would we be in a position to give, any assurance that litigation was not going to be taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Members may speak only once on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GemmaHussey" hpid="Mrs. G. Hussey Mrs. G. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. G. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>Senators will be aware that I gave an undertaking before Christmas that the motions would be taken at the first possible opportunity after the Christmas recess.  Indeed, I an sure that Senators will accept that that was a firm intention made in absolutely good faith. It is the view of this side of the House that the situation has changed considerably since then.  In fact I have here a sheaf <Col N="271" /> of newspaper cuttings since Christmas and almost everyone of them carries a threat of imminent legal action.  This culminated in &mdash; as the Leader of the Labour group in the Seanad has just said &mdash; a very definite statement on the radio on Monday, 18 January 1982 by the General Secretary of the organisation concerned that it was their intention to go ahead with legal action at the earliest possible opportunity.  We regret very much that this should have changed the situation. We had decided and had hoped to have a very good debate in this House on those motions, but it is considered extremely inadvisable in the circumstances that this House should involve itself in a full-scale debate on an issue which is apparently coming before the courts quite early.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CatherineMcGuinness" hpid="Mrs. McGuinness Mrs. McGuinness">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGuinness</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of the privilege of this House, not on the Order of Business, is it to be understood that if any Tom, Dick or Harry says in the papers that he is going to issue legal proceedings but has not, in fact, served a writ, that this House is to be muzzled in discussing it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The matter does not arise at this time.  The Leader of the House has concluded and the question is that the Order of Business be agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CatherineMcGuinness" hpid="Mrs. McGuinness Mrs. McGuinness">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGuinness</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a challenge to the privileges of this House.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Appropriation Act, 1981:" RHead="Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>Appropriation Act, 1981: Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann notes the supply services and purposes to which sums have been appropriated in the Appropriation Act, 1981.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Senator G. Hussey.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBruton" hpid="Mr. R. Bruton Mr. R. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>To give a little bit of the economic background to the Appropriation Bill, it is well to bear in mind the <Col N="272" /> out-turn of spending and taxation for 1981.  The main thing that concerns people at present is the fact that our current deficit is 8¼ per cent of gross national product.  That is up 50 per cent on the previous year in money terms.  The seriousness of that situation would have been far worse were it not for the July budget.  In fact, it would have come out at about 10 per cent of GNP.  Our basic problem in the economy at present stems from our very high reliance on foreign credit for economic activity.  Last year about 14 per cent of all our spending was funded by foreign borrowing, that is, both public and private.  Three-quarters of that was in the public sector and that is why the problem of the current deficit being run by the Government is so acute. We are effectively drawing on foreign resources to finance our current deficit.</P>
      <P>The other point to bear in mind about our foreign borrowing performance is that it is a relatively recent phenomenon. In the past four years our reliance on foreign credit for our ordinary spending averaged 10 per cent of GNP.  Back in the late fifties when Senator Whitaker was at the helm of the economy, at least on the public service side, even 3 per cent reliance on foreign borrowing was regarded as of crisis proportions.  We really have slipped in terms of our financial performance since then.  I do not believe that foreign borrowing should be avoided if we were confident that the resources were being used properly, but the size of the current deficit obviously points to the fact that we are using foreign resources in such a way that we will not be able to service the growing debt in the coming years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I believe our problems now do not lie so much on our ability to continue borrowing abroad.  In terms of the importance of public borrowing in Ireland, at least the importance of public debt as it stands now, compared to other countries, we are reasonably well placed.  About one-third of our annual income is accounted for by foreign debt.  That I do not believe is excessively high.  But the worrying feature is that so much of that has been incurred in the past four or five years.  Heretofore we did not rely at all <Col N="273" /> on foreign borrowing.  Therefore, we are rushing, headlong, along a dangerous road and in the coming budget we must take action to stop it.</P>
    <P>I do not intend to try to attribute blame for introducing the practice of using borrowing to finance day-to-day spending. As Senator E. Ryan pointed out yesterday, it started in earnest under the Coalition in 1973 to 1975.  Let me point out that, at that time, all of the economists were urging the Government to do precisely that.  It was said that, in the wake of an oil crisis, the Arabs had vast resources with which they could do nothing else but lend.  Therefore the Government at that time were advised that it would be folly not to borrow.  For that reason it is a bit hollow to hear the economic commentators now berating all politicians, of all shades, for their borrowing practices because it was the enthusiasm with which politicians took up the original economic advice that has us in our present position.  Given that encouragement, the Government in 1973 to 1977, realised, mid-way through their term, that it was a practice that had to be stopped.  Their success, within two years, in reducing the then borrowing for current purposes from 7 per cent to 3½ per cent &mdash; halving it in effect &mdash; was a remarkable achievement.  The incoming Government, in deciding on a policy of borrowing to launch the economy &mdash; as they then said &mdash; on a path of sustained growth and rising employment, were profoundly misguided.  They did so at a time when the economy was recovering anyhow and the capacity to meet the extra boost in demand that they put in by borrowing was not there.  Effectively the extra demand that they boosted was diverted into buying goods abroad.  It did not do the economy the lasting good they had hoped.  It has also undermined our room for manoeuvre now at a period when we are in economic recession.  In principle it would be very desirable for a Government to be leaning very hard on new projects, investing new money in the economy now when unemployment is rising. But ability to do that has been undermined by three or four years of misguided use of foreign exchange.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="274" /> The other worrying feature about our present dependence on foreign borrowing to offset our balance of payments deficit is that it seems now to be much more fundamental than it was in the mid-seventies. In 1975 we succeeded in eliminating entirely our foreign borrowing on the balance of payments although in 1973 the Arabs had put it into serious deficit with their oil price increases.  It has been proven in the last two years that we have no longer the capacity to reverse our dependence on foreign borrowing in the way we were then able to do.  The reason for that fundamental change in our position is that the deficit is now founded on unrealistic expectations built up over the last three years.  I believe that the Government have a very hard task ahead of them in turning around people's expectations as regards the living standards that can be supported for the amount of work done.  That is the economic background to our present spending situation.</P>
    <P>At the public level &mdash; where we are dealing with public spending and public taxation &mdash; there is a deep cause for our present situation.  That is the failure of the man in the street, the Oireachtas and indeed Ministers, to link spending with taxation.  As regards the man in the street it will be discovered that there are very strong lobbies that build up in support of all sorts of spending proposals.  But there is not at all the same strong lobby in favour of keeping down taxation.  The people who are interested in reducing taxation tend to be much more scattered and weaker in their ability to muster public support whereas the people who are backing spending can always point to the true needs of extra spending in specific areas.  That tendency in the mind of the man in the street is being reinforced by the way in which we consider our spending in this House.  The spending estimates are completely divorced from the taxation proposals.  The tax seems to be entirely the responsibility of the Minister for Finance.  It is imposed in one fell swoop at the budget when everyone is prepared to say what a deplorable thing it is to be increasing taxes.  On the other side, the spending proposals are farmed out among individual Ministers whose interest <Col N="275" /> it is to maximise their spending to try to maximise the way they cater for their particular responsibility.  I do not believe that that approach to spending and taxation &mdash; which we pursue in this House &mdash; does anything by way of improving the man in the street's ability to see why taxation is necessary and what value he is getting for that taxation.</P>
    <P>Another matter that has encouraged our reliance on borrowing in recent years was pointed out by Dr. Kieran Kennedy, Director of the Economic and Social Research Institute recently.  That is, that there have been hidden victims of our borrowing policies.  He took an instance of someone who lent £99 in 1962 to support a national loan.  He estimated that in real terms the value of that £99 that person lent in 1962 is, in 1981, £10.  That performance, whereby people who &mdash; out of a commitment to the national economy &mdash; sank their savings into investment in the future of the economy means in effect that those people have been robbed of nine-tenths of the money they invested. That is a disappointing situation in many regards and has encouraged our use of borrowing in a way that has not been giving proper value for money.</P>
    <P>The &ldquo;Late Late Show&rdquo; last Saturday threw down a clear political challenge to us to tackle the present financial problems, to tackle the problem of getting value for State money and for pulling the economy back from the very high level of unemployment now involved.  The fact that we squander public money is undermining our ability to provide jobs.  I believe we can tackle this problem along four distinct paths.  One is to establish clearer controls and standards for the various sectors of public spending. Another is to explicitly link public spending and public taxation.  A third is to look at the distribution effects of various schemes which have been introduced which, to my mind, have been largely hidden from public view.  The final one &mdash; which would draw the others together to some extent &mdash; is to introduce an explicit plan for the public sector, not an ambitious one setting targets for the whole economy but a plan for public <Col N="276" /> spending itself.  We might not always be able to meet what we plan to do, but at least we would have clear guidance on where we go.</P>
    <P>I should like to deal briefly with each one of those paths.  On the question of practical standards and controls, it is very important that public representatives be given a means whereby they can judge the performance of various schemes in operation and debate them each year in both Houses.  That to my mind does not exist at present in the system of presenting Estimates.  In this House we do not even get to look at the Estimates.  The Appropriation Bill provides our only opportunity to compare the performances of different areas of public spending.</P>
    <P>As regards semi-State bodies, one way to have more effective practical controls would be to set cash limits for the contribution from the general taxpayer.  In the long term, the level of contribution by the general taxpayer would be set on the basis of social objectives.  In the case of CIE, there are definite social reasons for running services that are not economic, but there should be a fixed contribution from the general taxpayer for that sort of service and it should not be allowed to grow unchecked and unaccounted for.</P>
    <P>Secondly, we should have the courage of our convictions.  We have set up the semi-State bodies as independent bodies to administer certain areas of spending. We should, therefore, give them flexibility of operation and free them from political intervention in their operations.  In particular, we should give them freedom in the area of pricing.  In the past, there have been several efforts to prevent public semi-State agencies from implementing price increases that they believed should be brought in in order to protect the public money invested in their companies. Politicians on occasions have tried to stand in their way.  That is not why we set them up as independent bodies, with independent boards.</P>
    <P>The other area in which we should give them freedom is in their investment decisions, their decisions on policy.  In return for freedom of operation and flexibility we should demand from them the <Col N="277" /> same sort of responsibility for their actions as would be demanded of an executive and a board in a private company. In relation to capital spending proposals in particular, they should present their reason for choosing a particular investment over other possible alternatives and show that it is a worthwhile investment.  They should publish detailed costings for its implementation and, should there be an overrun on that spending, it should be clearly available and visible in the Estimates.  The executives of those companies should have clear responsibility for that overrun in much the same way as in a private company.  In semi-State bodies, executives must stake their reputations on the proposals they put up and take the consequences if they deviate from them without proper explanation.</P>
    <P>In relation to the annual operation of semi-State bodies, I would like to see the Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies devise simple criteria of performance that would be available to public representatives each year, to see how they are performing in line with economic standards.  We have already had a debate on Fóir Teoranta.  I suggested in that case that possible criteria would be to look at the proportion of their lending which they write off each year and at the proportion of the commercial return on the public money recouped from the companies which they assisted.  That would, at least give public representatives an idea of whether Fóir Teoranta were improving or deteriorating in their performance. Our Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies should set about devising measures which every year would give politicians a way of looking at how these agencies are doing and not make them wait until the joint committee have got around again to having a look at that particular semi-State body.</P>
    <P>A second way in which we could have more effective control and let the taxpayer see what is happening to his or her money would be to charge the interest on borrowing.  If the Minister for Finance borrows in order to finance an agency, the loan interest on the money borrowed should be explicitly in their accounts.  At <Col N="278" /> present several agencies and Departments are receiving loans from the Minister for Finance without explicitly showing how much interest they ought to be paying and how much of that interest falls on the taxpayer.  It would give a clearer view to public representatives and the public of what these agencies are costing the taxpayer and whether we are getting a valuable return.  In the case of the IDA, they give out capital grants every year and it is never clear to the public what that means in cost to the taxpayer.  There is a build-up in debt for each year they give out capital grants.  It would be valuable for the public to know about this build-up.</P>
    <P>A third effective control in getting better value for State money would be that, where grants are given there should be in all cases a now and an after element in them, the after element being conditional on the receiver of that grant having lived up to the performance asked of him. Again, in the case of IDA grants people who apply for grants do so on the basis that they are going to provide a certain number of jobs.  An element of that grant should be held back to ensure that the company in question meet the standards previously outlined by them.  Similarly in the case of borrowing for agricultural purposes, when farmers borrow for building, part of the grant should be paid in the beginning and part later on when they have achieved the increases in stock numbers which they intended.</P>
    <P>On the question of how we might link spending with taxation, one way of doing this is by each new programme giving, in simple terms, the tax cost involved.  It could be set out in such terms that we could see exactly what was involved. Another item which we should consider is that when we enter into an agreement with the public sector on pay, should that be exceeded by special claims in the course of the year there should be special tax measures brought in at once to recoup that amount for the Exchequer.  That would strengthen the Government's resolve to resist unreasonable fresh claims.  The taxpayer would also see the real cost to him or her of higher public service claims.  That would be a very <Col N="279" /> worthwhile link between spending and taxation.</P>
    <P>Another suggested change to try to give the public a better view of what is happening to their tax money would be each year to publish the tax yield that would have been provided if tax bands and thresholds had been index-linked.  Too often the Minister for Finance gets away with saying, &ldquo;I am taking people out of the tax net by certain proposals,&rdquo; when in fact in the course of the previous year the process of inflation has been bringing far more people into the tax net.  The taxpayer is entitled to see that in a clear way.  I do not propose index-linking in the way it has been done in some of the Scandinavian economies because, in the long term, that fuelled inflation.  The taxpayer is entitled to see what is happening to his or her tax and what is the real effect of tax changes.</P>
    <P>Another area I feel strongly about in our failure to link spending with taxation is that public service pensions which are index-linked and cover a growing number of people in the public sector are in no way being funded annually by the taxpayer.  In effect there is an enormous liability outstanding in the future on our tax resources and we are not making allowance for that in the way the private sector would fund a pension fund.  That is something that should be seriously looked at in our approach to public spending because the problem in that area is going to get more and more serious as the large numbers of people who are recruited into the public sector in recent years move on towards retirement.</P>
    <P>The final point I would like to make about linking spending with tax is that I am strongly in favour of introducing charges over a much wider range of services. It is not just in order to bring in extra finance although that is probably a welcome side of it.  It also ensures that there is a public interest in the performance of the various schemes involved.  In my local authority area the services that the public come to me most often complaining about are the ones that they pay <Col N="280" /> a certain contribution to, namely, water in our area.  It concentrates the minds of people administering those schemes if the public have that sort of first-hand interest in how efficient the service is.  On that question of the linking of taxing with spending, I very much approve of the two recent major schemes brought in by the Government, namely, the Youth Employment Agency and the Housing Agency.  Both of those have been self-financing in a way that should be done in the public sector.  There is an explicit tax providing the resources for the Youth Employment Agency, and the Housing Agency is going to be a self-financing one also.  They are very worthwhile improvements in our approach to public spending.</P>
    <P>I will be very brief on the question of the distributional aspects of State spending. We have not looked at all at what is happening to social fairness in our spending in recent years.  In previous contributions in this House I dwelt at some length on the effects of our spending on education, housing and on various sections of the community.  The conclusion that I have drawn is that there is a clear bias in favour of the better off in those schemes.  Similarly, in the area of taxation, there are several places where the tax system is achieving results that are not desirable on distributional grounds. In particular, the position of large families has deteriorated in recent years.  That is something that, as public representatives, we should have information about so that we can make clear decisions about them.</P>
    <P>Finally, I would like to turn to the question of economic planning over the longer term.  In the past it was an error to try to introduce economic planning that involved very broad targets for the sectors that were not in direct Government control.  No actual policies were proposed that would allow the Government to achieve those targets but they were published. What we need now is for the Government to concentrate on their own public spending.  There are three goals in mind on public spending.  One is to achieve efficiency, a second is to achieve a fair distribution and a third is to stabilise <Col N="281" /> the economy in times of recession.  These have not been adequately tackled and addressed individually, in particular in relation to allocation.  There has been a complete failure, particularly on the part of the Department of the Environment, to plan in any systematic way.  The county councils go through a very elaborate planning process whereby they draw five-year plans for their whole county and for individual towns within it.  Those plans set out the sort of objectives they want to fulfil, for example, introducing a water or sewerage scheme in a particular area up to a certain capacity and allowing housing over the coming five years to live up to the capacity of their sewerage schemes.  What happens then is that the Department of the Environment do not appear to put any financial planning into backing up those plans by the local authorities.</P>
    <P>In my area of Meath, which is so influenced by the growth of the Dublin population, towns that we had hoped would be planned on a rational basis have not been sanctioned for the essential services that are needed in those towns.  For example in east Meath, a very large section consisting of Laytown, Ashbourne and so on, we had plans for an extra water supply for that whole area.  At present we are forced to try to put a stop to development and cut off water several times every year, several times over this Christmas, because we have not got the financial backing for our plans to expand the water supply in that area.  That is the sort of practical approach to planning in the public sector that is needed to back up what is being done in the local authorities.</P>
    <P>I will not delay the House any longer as I know that time is limited on this debate.  I thank the House for its attention.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>The present motion gives us an opportunity for an interim assessment of, among other things, Government policy on a wide range of issues. I would like to touch in a small way on one or two and to make a more substantial point on the economy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With respect to the Government's performance <Col N="282" /> in general, it strikes me that it is an extraordinary mixture of reforming zeal and ineptitude.  That makes a pleasant change from ineptitude <i>per se.</i> The ineptitude of course is demonstrated quite clearly in the topic which gave rise to some controversy on the Order of Business, the raising of the school entry age.  Incidentally, since Senator O'Rourke spoke at length about this yesterday in the House and was apparently allowed to do so, it seems to me that the point of the Leader of the House that it would be somehow injudicious to allow debate on a substantive motion is hardly valid.  What I want to say, however, is that when the motion comes up I will certainly give it my wholehearted support. The decision to raise the school entry age was educationally highly dubious; it was bureaucratic and arrogant to do so.  It was something of a nonsense from the financial point of view as well since perforce the Minister had to concede that he would compensate by providing some money for pre-entry nursery schools.  Given the storm of opposition it has raised and, in practical politics, given the considerable clout of the INTO, the Minister would be extremely wise to beat a hasty and graceful retreat on this issue. On the other hand, I must say that I welcomed warmly the rapid decision to set up a curricular and examinations board.  We debated this at length in the House.  That is an instance of the Government's genuine reforming zeal.  To complete a brief point on education I wish that the Government would devote some attention to finding a better way to distribute resources available for third level education.  I accept in the present circumstances that it is not possible to increase grants and that there is a cutback in real terms.  There is dissatisfaction that the way in which money is being distributed is not achieving the ends of social justice.</P>
    <P>I am not one of those who believe that students should live in the lap of luxury. Their cost to the taxpayer is extremely high <i>per capita.</i> They are a privileged class and so I never subscribe to demands that they should have elaborate sports complexes and so on.  It is important that <Col N="283" /> they should have adequate if frugal housing and subsistence while they are attending college and in many cases they have not.  The main worry about financing our education is that the whole system of grants for higher education was meant to further the objective of equality of opportunity. It is not doing that as well as it should.  Many students are now coming to college who could not have afforded to come in the days of total fee paying but equally certainly there is no evidence that people from the less privileged sectors of society are making any impact at all on the wall surrounding third level education.  This is a matter which does not necessarily involve finance.  It is more about how this distribution could be more effectively organised.</P>
    <P>Under the general headings of the Departments of the Taoiseach and Foreign Affairs I should like to say that although 1981 has been a difficult year for Anglo-Irish relations nevertheless we should be thankful for the level of relations being as good as it is.  Above all there are signs of grounds for modest optimism in Northern Ireland as a result of what seems to be the genuinely imaginative thinking and policies that are now coming out of the Northern Ireland Office.</P>
    <P>In general terms of foreign affairs, it is a great pity that the year which saw Ireland becoming a member of the United Nations Security Council and thereby having her status greatly enhanced in the international community, should see a continuation of the erosion of our independent foreign policy because of pressures emanating from the European Community.  We had an argument in the Dáil and in this House about the relative responsibility of the present Minister for Foreign Affairs and the previous Minister on the question of the discussions on European Political Cooperation and the extent to which our neutrality policy is being eroded.  There was a lot of shadow boxing between this administration and the last on that matter because the truth is that neither Fianna Fáil nor Fine Gael are serious in their commitment to our military neutrality.  I <Col N="284" /> do not believe either of them when they assert that they are committed to this principle.  I do not mean that they are consciously telling lies but I mean that they are guilty of a form of self-deception. The fact is that while we should be grateful that our country is not a base for nuclear weaponry and that we are not a member of any military pact, our so-called neutrality is illusory.  It is a phoney neutrality.  All it means is that for the moment we are not a member of a military pact but that membership is inevitable and implicit in our continued participation in the European Political Cooperation talks and in the harmonisation of foreign policy which is an increasing tendency in the Community.  I wish our Government were more honest in this regard.  At least if they admitted openly to the people, &ldquo;You may have cherished neutrality in the past but it is incompatible with our membership of the European Community&rdquo;, that would be more honest than the present deception.</P>
    <P>I want to draw attention to something that involves foreign affairs and Irish-American relations and therefore North-South relations eventually.  This is a matter for which no Department are directly responsible but which involves semi-State bodies as well as RTE.  I refer to what seemed at first sight a very imaginative decision whereby a package television programme was to be distributed to American TV cable companies.  RTE would put together a two hour weekly package that would be aimed at American audiences and would include a cross-section of events in Ireland and various features of Irish life.  The idea was that it would attract an ethnic audience and following the ethnic audience would be business.  Trade follows the ethnic audience.  The IDA and so on would exploit the new potential that there was as a result of an awakened American interest in Ireland.  This seemed an excellent idea but just before Christmas there was a modification made to the programme which was deplorable and which should be investigated.  It was decided that the news and current affairs element in the package should be dropped, apparently at the instigation of the semi-State <Col N="285" /> companies who were sponsors of the idea in the first place.  The thinking was that we would not get American companies to invest in Ireland if as part of what they saw was news about kidnappings, ransoms, bombings and so on.  A decision has been taken to exclude the news and current affairs aspect from the package. This is a deplorable decision for a number of reasons.  First of all, from a purely pragmatic point of view it seems that the hypothetical American investment will not be interested in Ireland unless it has the full truth about the country and if it is lured under false pretences to a sunny land of shamrocks and then discovers that there is a lot of harsh reality about life in Ireland that is a fraud.  More important, it is vitally essential and our kith and kin in the United States should continue to be properly informed about what is happening in Ireland and not be allowed to see us through the green tinted spectacles which they have worn for over 100 years and which has such disastrous practical results in their attitude to bodies such as the Provisional IRA.  It is very important that a realistic image of Ireland should continue to be projected, that we should be seen, warts and all.  This matter should be investigated.</P>
    <P>With regard to the economy, I would like to do something which is now almost going out of fashion.  I would like to quote Wolfe Tone, this time none of the hackneyed quotations but an opinion which applies quite appropriately to the state of the economy at the moment.  Wolfe Tone once said: &ldquo;We are able enough to take care of ourselves if we were once afloat or, if not, we deserve to sink.&rdquo;  I think that that opinion would be shared by the great majority of Irish nationalists from Tone's time onwards.  Perhaps Irish nationalists like Tone were too naive and optimistic in assuming, as they did, that Ireland free would be Ireland prosperous. They would certainly be startled at the state we are now in.  If we are not exactly sinking, in Tone's phrase, there is an urgent need for us to swim more vigorously.</P>
    <P>Some of our problems are agreed to be those of bad national housekeeping and improvident borrowing, and of course no <Col N="286" /> voice is more eloquent and authoritative in this Chamber and outside it in that respect than that of Senator Whitaker, who, Cassandra-like, has been uttering dire predictions here for the last four years.  You will remember that it was the fate of that unfortunate daughter of Prim and Hecuba that not only were her predictions true but that she was never believed.  With great respect to Senator Whitaker and other conservative economists, while we accept their warnings and while there is bad or irresponsible national housekeeping, the problems go much deeper than that.  It is very doubtful, to come back to Tone's metaphor, whether we were ever properly afloat to begin with since independence.  In other words, the considerable natural resources of this country have never been properly exploited in the public interest. There has been mismanagement, waste and neglect of our resources and that is a fact of our economic life for the last 20 years at least.  Ever since the economy began to take off it has been mismanaged. There has been private rape of the economy.  Even a more sombre reflection than the state of our public finances is the thought that there has been this chronic mismanagement, waste and private exploitation.  This also implies the hope that we still have the potential &mdash; even the gloomiest economists will concede that this country has the potential but it has to be under a radically different economic philosophy &mdash; to put the country afloat once more and to keep it afloat.</P>
    <P>Meanwhile, the immediate pressing problems must be solved.  Caithfear an gad is gaire don scórnach a ghearradh. There is now a public awareness for the first time &mdash; I think Senator O'Leary suggested this yesterday &mdash; of the gravity of the financial situation.  People are ready, perhaps for the first time, to accept the gravity of the situation and the severity of the measures needed to correct it. There are signs that the electorate will not fool themselves any more by listening to the politics of promise.  One hopes that the politics of promise is a thing of the past.  That kind of dishonesty and hypocrisy did not begin today or yesterday, nor is it the exclusive property of any one <Col N="287" /> party.  The Fianna Fáil election manifesto of 1977, of course, reached new heights in this regard with its colourful bags of Smarties dangled cynically before a young electorate, but that differs only in degree from the facile promises made by Fine Gael in the last election.</P>
    <P>Both main parties stand indicted in the ludicrous proposal to build an international airport at Knock.  If County Mayo needed money and investment, and indeed it does, it could have been invested in many more realistic ways.  At least this Government, prodded by the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, plucked up the courage to reverse their fatuous decision in this case. Equally ludicrous, increasingly so as the months go on, and another example of a bag of Smarties, is the £9.60 something-for-nothing proposal.  By the time, if ever, it is paid, its real value will be down to about £7.60.  Given the wasteful administrative publicity costs involved in the scheme, God only knows the eventual cost to the taxpayer.  The real beneficiaries of the scheme, apart from Peter being robbed to pay Paula, will be relatively few.  Again, like the Knock airport proposal, if money had to be given or needed to be given to housewives who needed the money, surely it could have been done in a more efficient way.</P>
    <P>If the politics of promise is to be ended it will require a mature electorate and honest leadership.  People will accept that severe measures have to be enacted if they see an equitable distribution of the burden and that the broadest and fattest backs are made to carry the heaviest burden. However, if governments are sincere in trying to correct our economic problems, people will expect governments to exercise maximum control of these economic problems.  I mean that people will be asking, I hope, why the Government do not establish the maximum control over our economic and financial resources in the public interest. Various groups of ordinary workers who are hard pressed to pay their household bills and meet mortgage commitments, are beginning to be tired of being told that they are holding the country up to <Col N="288" /> ransom if they seek pay increases partly to meet rising inflation if they have to run very hard to stay in the same place. They are becoming tired of being lectured on their greed and materialism and on holding the country up to ransom. They resent these constant accusations because they know that the real avarice, the big-time avarice and the big-time materialism, the real holding the country to ransom, come from those who control the sources of our credit, who determine the rates of our interest.  Was it not James Fintan Lalor who said, in an insight unusual for Irish nationalists of his time, that he did not care who made the country's laws provided he had control over the land?  In today's circumstances he would undoubtedly see that the crunch control is the control exercised by faceless and ruthless financial institutions.  If we are to survive, let alone prosper, in this country there has to be a radical economic overhaul.  In that overhaul Government control, which is public control, must be established over the means of exchange as over the means of production.</P>
    <P>I am not talking anarchy or far-out radical economics.  All we have to do is to take a leaf out of the book of our Community colleagues in France.  No-one can accuse M. Mitterrand and his government of being visionaries or anarchists or Bolshies, yet they are courageously embarking on a programme of public control of private banks to provide the wherewithal to reflate the economy and to increase public spending in housing and transport.</P>
    <P>In the present financial crisis with all the reams of print that have gone into the discussion about our financial problems, there has been very little challenging of some absolutely basic points.  For example, everyone seems to accept that the high rates of interest and the private determination of credit are unchallengable facts of nature, acts of God.  It is about time we realised that a substantial part of our problems, from the agricultural crisis to inflation, unemployment and poverty, is due to the way in which financial interests operate, to the fact that profit is the sole criterion and that the <Col N="289" /> loyalty of these institutions is not to this country, or the community at large, but to a small group of shareholders and to the international big brothers of these institutions.  The attitude of these financial institutions in the present crisis is clearly reflected in the brazen memorandum recently circulated to Members of the Oireachtas from the Irish Banks Federation. This memorandum, in effect, threatens dire international retribution if a modest levy is imposed on the vast profits of the banks.</P>
    <P>It is about time that we began to think in terms not simply of levies but of public control.  If money talks, then the strongest voice must be that of the community in general, not a plutocratic network of bank directors whose interests extend not only to many areas of the private sector but who are encroaching as well on semi-State bodies.</P>
    <P>In this connection it is also high time that we knew precisely what are the financial interests of each Member of the Oireachtas.  Only by a frank disclosure of their involvement in financial matters can public representatives assure the electorate that there is no conflict between the private and the public interests.</P>
    <P>If this really is a reforming and a courageous Government, if they are prepared to take harsh measures to deal with the public finances and if they still hope for public support for that resurgence and turnabout in our whole economy and psychology, then the Government must demonstrate, even if it means a dramatic confrontation with the gnomes of God-knows-where, that they mean to be economic masters in their own house.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to remind the House that the Minister is to get in at 12 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. J. Harte Mr. J. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought it was to be 12 o'clock tomorrow.  I will be as brief as I possibly can in the hope that I will leave some time for anybody else who wishes to make a contribution.  When we are talking about the Estimates, we naturally have to look back and ask ourselves what were the circumstances following the January budget.  When the new Government <Col N="290" /> took office they found that the housekeeping exercise had not been done.  The position was that there was a total imbalance. The whole question of the housekeeping had gone wrong and whoever did the figures was responsible.  There was no real care taken to assess what would be needed in the public interest. In order to redeem that situation it was necessary to bring in the July budget which was the subject of a very great deal of controversy and criticism.</P>
      <P>It was hard to understand why a Government with a 20-seat majority could not have brought in a very strong budget with no deficiencies in the Estimates for the year.  It is hard to understand why they did not do that.  They need not have gone to the country for another eight or twelve months.  They knew that if they were returned to office they would have to walk a very similar line to that which the present Government walked when they took over the administration. Despite that, when the tough measures were taken the Opposition argued that they would not have had to take that course of action.  It is generally accepted now that they would have had to do so unless they continued borrowing abroad for non-productive purposes as they had been doing.</P>
      <P>It is necessary for me to make that point because we are talking about the Estimates for the year.  When the new administration took over they discovered that there was no money available from the 1981 Estimates to pay for essential services.  The budget seemed to be a deliberate disguise to make the people believe that most of the needs could be met, but it fell very far short indeed.  In the long run it was discovered that there would be no money for some areas, for example, social welfare and the defence forces.  Money for the Garda would have run out in September.  Whether this was deliberate or due to fault is irrelevant now.  We cannot have such a situation under the present Estimates.  It was irresponsible to leave essential services so desperately in need of assistance that the new administration had to introduce this emergency budget.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The under provision in the Social Welfare <Col N="291" /> Vote is criminal.  I speak as a working class person knowing the effects on people who depend on unemployment benefit etc.  Even in regard to agriculture there was a shortfall.  Posts and Telegraphs would have had a shortfall of about £19 million, Transport and Energy a shortfall of £87 million and Environment £35 million.  All of these very essential services had not been catered for.</P>
    <P>By not estimating correctly we were dealing with a £740 million deficit.  That is the origin of the other budget.  The essential services had to be provided and it was necessary to take tough measures. As Senator Murphy said, people are beginning to realise that these steps are necessary and they are now settling down to the fact that the new Estimates will have to take care of such matters.</P>
    <P>Faulty estimating in the case of agriculture is very serious.  Very often working class people are accused of not understanding the farm situation.  I do not claim to understand it but I try to do so.  Farmers had been going through a very bad time from 1978 onwards, with the real effects hitting them in 1979.  Apart from the weather problems, they had the very small rise in farm prices of 5.8 per cent, when their actual input needs were about 13 per cent.  When their output prices rose by only 3 per cent and their actual input prices increased by 15 per cent, they were in difficulties.</P>
    <P>The Fianna Fáil Party, who claim to be very concerned about agriculture, did an injustice to agriculture in the sense that they had not looked ahead to this situation and they left the farmers with a shortfall. This was criminal at a time when farming families had experienced a decline of about 50 per cent in their incomes during 1979-80.  At a time when loan interest rates were beginning to bite, they were allowed to suffer this burden. It was a question then of whether the other administration, if they got back into power, could save the situation.</P>
    <P>In this developing crisis people have tried to lay the blame at the door of the present administration, but we deny that. When we come to the 2 per cent levy, the disease levies and so on, that was done by <Col N="292" /> Fianna Fáil.  It certainly did not do anything to help the people in agriculture who were in that critical situation.  I am not saying that the present Estimates will solve the problem, but I think that the Minister for Agriculture is doing his best to arrest the decline.  The 5 per cent subsidy for the developing farmers and the similar assistance he is introducing for the farmers who are not in that category will be very helpful.  Also helpful have been the discussions he has been having with the lending institutions in relation to having the loan repayments eased.  In addition, there has been a £70 million increase in expenditure in about a five-month period.  These are all signs of the concern felt by the Government about agriculture.  Fianna Fáil also expressed concern when they were in office, but I do not think they measured up to it.</P>
    <P>When it is necessary to tighten the belt somewhere, at least the Government on this occasion have had the good sense to look upon agriculture as a very vital part of the economy and to ensure that, even though it may be necessary to cut back in other ways, there is development and progress in this area.  The level of sheep headage payments was increased.  VAT refund levels have increased.  Work is being done to bring about an increase in the numbers of livestock.  Those engaged in agriculture have to be encouraged to improve husbandry and to start cutting back on expenditure.</P>
    <P>We could not pay too much attention to youth unemployment.  More than half of our population are in the youth category and these are the people we will have to deal with.  The setting up of the Youth Employment Agency has been very encouraging.  I believe a lot remains to be done in the coming year.  We cannot just leave it at that.  Our youth constitute the largest group in our society.  They are the people who have the right to work and the right to fight for work.  If we do not provide for the youth of the country they are not bound to accept the standards society lays down, especially if society cannot produce the goods for them or show them some hope for the future. Why should any youth not being assisted in a proper way to advance himself feel <Col N="293" /> he owes anything to society?  I suggest he owes society something, but in these circumstances we cannot expect him to live up to the standards of society.  It is imperative that the right of youth to work be given top priority.  For years the Labour Party have been very concerned about a youth employment agency.  Now, after going into Coalition, we see it in existence. I do not think the Youth Employment Agency is the answer to the whole problem, but it is a major contribution. I believe it will do a good job for us. However, I would like it borne in mind what the mentality of the youth is liable to be if we do not keep trying to resolve this problem and making more progress than we are making at the moment.  The youth cannot be blamed for their despair and indifference.  They are experiencing great frustration.  This is brought about by long spells of inactivity.  It is our problem and we have to look seriously at it again.</P>
    <P>On the question of local government reform, there have been dozens of occasions when we made estimates in regard to this.  One of the factors in relation to local government reform is the question of whether anybody has seriously looked at the possibility of more autonomy for local government.  Local government operations are much closer to the people than those of central government. Instead of talking about building new offices in Castlebar, Killarney and so on, why can we not get down to the question of examining what could be handed over to local government to administer in their own areas?  Is it necessary for everyone to contact or to come to Dublin to get something done in relation to questions of social welfare, health and so on?</P>
    <P>I believe there is plenty of room in the area of local government for further reform and autonomy.  Local government is subject to much more critical comment than central government because it is closer to the people.  The financing of local government current and capital proposals is of paramount importance.  I know that the finance is not available and it is something we have to think very seriously about.  There is urgency in regard to the question of local government <Col N="294" /> autonomy.  I urge that in the lifetime of this Government they should see what other functions can be given to local government to meet the people's requirements. If we could examine questions such as that rather than talking about erecting new buildings, we would be doing something more useful.</P>
    <P>There is great scope there to have local government funded in a different way, or to consider the whole question of how it is structured.  We have an obligation in this respect.</P>
    <P>I have to laugh when I hear people in the private sector talking about the creation of full employment.  They cannot create full employment.  They never could and they never will.  Throughout Europe there are close on 14 million people unemployed.  This is very serious because there is a great deal of poverty running parallel with affluence.  We keep going the old way, employing the same methods and the old ideas.  If somebody comes up with an idea that might be a bit revolutionary, he is branded a communist &mdash; reds under the bed.  This is galling. Since I was a boy living in the inner city of Dublin, I have been listening to Governments talking about creating full employment.  I did not see it in my home or in any other home around me, and I do not expect to see it in my lifetime.  I do not believe private enterprise can create full employment.</P>
    <P>We work on a system of &ldquo;propping up&rdquo;.  We talk about private enterprise providing jobs, but do they?  Most of the money spent by the Government for the creation of jobs in industry clearly indicates that there is no such thing as the private sector supplying jobs.  The Government are supplying the jobs by the backup rescue organisations &mdash; the IDA, Fóir Teoranta and so on.  If there was a full examination of that situation we might have a very interesting debate and see exactly what value the country gets for money spent by the Government in this area and how much private industrialists are providing to create jobs.  I am sure the figure for jobs created by the private sector from their own resources would be very low indeed against the amount spent by the State.  It is a misnomer <Col N="295" /> to talk about the private sector creating jobs.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>This morning on the Order of Business it was announced that we will reconvene at 2 o'clock.  I have a message from the Minister for Defence, who cannot be here until 2.30 p.m.  By agreement, could we reconvene at 2.30 p.m.?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. J. Harte Mr. J. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister want to reply to this debate at 12 o'clock?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Minister for Defence will not be available until 2.30 p.m, would Senators agree to reconvene at 2.30 p.m. instead of 2 p.m.?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mícheál Cranitch Mícheál Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. J. Harte Mr. J. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>Rescue operations are necessary when businesses get into difficulties. We should tell the people the private sector are not providing all these jobs.  It is the taxpayers who are providing the jobs.  If they got a fairer return &mdash; if they had more control over those industries &mdash; it might be more understandable. In my view these rescue agencies are not the answer.</P>
      <P>Detailed economic planning has been missing for a long time.  On the question of maintaining employment, it is not enough to introduce Bills from time to time seeking a few extra million pounds to save 1,000 jobs or 100 jobs or to bail somebody out.  That does not work.  It never has and it never will.  Chronic underdevelopment is very evident on the industrial scene.  This is an indictment of private enterprise.  It has proved a failure particularly in the area of industrial development.  I am not suggesting that I have all the answers, but I seriously suggest that when large companies fail, instead of getting involved in rescue operations, the State should consider either part or full ownership, particularly in the industrial area where they have a very small investment at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="296" /> Instead of handing out grants, dole and so on, the State should get directly involved and make sure they will have a say in further developments.  State involvement should not be confined only to rescue operations.  Is there any clear evidence that these rescue operations in the final analysis turn out to be self-sustaining? Is there any clear evidence that the people who have been rescued do not come back?</P>
    <P>For example, I was talking to people in Galway where an industry was going out of existence.  Those people were being retrained in a fourth skill.  This makes people think about rescue operations and whether we are tackling the subject the right way.  Our efforts in this area are very feeble.  It is time we got a bit revolutionary and faced up to the real problems, that is, getting into socialist, detailed economic planning.  No matter how distasteful it might be, we will have to face up to radical shakeups.  If these trends continue, we could be talking about 180,000 jobless &mdash; 14 million in the EEC, and we are not going to get much help from them.  The question of money expected from the EEC is another area that is going to affect employment.  Men with ideas get money and the men with money but no ideas do not seem to be investing at home.  This is a pity.</P>
    <P>Agriculture and youth employment are in a very serious situation, but I am delighted to see agriculture is taking a turn for the better.  On the question of youth employment, no matter what Government are in power unless they come up with very good proposals many of our youth will be asking: what do I owe the State?  That can only lead to an increase in crime.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before I call Senator Cranitch, is the Minister willing to forego a few minutes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BarryDesmond" hpid="Mr. B. Desmond Mr. B. Desmond">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Desmond</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mícheál Cranitch Mícheál Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to thank everybody concerned for making five or ten minutes available to me.  It is a pity that the debate has to be curtailed at all because this is the one chance we get in <Col N="297" /> Seanad Éireann of dealing with various aspects of the economy.  I thank everybody concerned for making these few minutes available to me.</P>
      <P>First, I wish to commend the Minister on his excellent introductory speech.  It is short, concise and it says a lot in a few words, <i>multum in parvo.</i> I was particularly impressed by his statement regarding the colossal expenditure of £4,370 million where he says that the question we must ask ourselves is whether we can afford this level of spending and whether all our public programmes are cost effective. When I read that I immediately thought of the answer Johnny gave to his mother when he had done his first public examination. Johnny was not a very good scholar.  He did not study what he should have studied.  His mother asked him if the questions were very hard, if he was able to read them.  His answer was that he could read the questions quite well, that he knew what they meant but that the only difficulty was that he did not have the answers.  That is the sort of problem facing our State at the moment. The economic plight is very serious.  I am not going into the various details.  They have been gone through in the past 24 hours.  Inflation was mentioned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Unemployment got an honourable mention but perhaps some other desperate problems were not emphasised.  I am referring now to the malaise that seems to hang over our people at the moment. They are pursuing a life of selfishness, pleasure seeking, meanness, trying to dodge out of this, that and the other, have all the pleasure and goodies possible, but pay no entertainment tax.  What we want in the State is a crusade, not like the infamous crusade that was attempted a short time ago but which was stillborn before it got off the ground at all, but a real crusade to bring people back to the full understanding that we are a small country with limited resources, that we must cut our cloth according to our measure. One of the first things that was inculcated in me and in all my neighbours by our parents when we were growing up was that if you cannot afford something, you do without it.  If the Minister of State <Col N="298" /> at the Department of Education had been here, I intended putting this point to him. I will mention it now as the present Minister may be able to get it across to somebody, that is, that our educational programmes, formal and informal, should be tailored to try to get people back to a realisation of the facts, to inculcate in them a sense of independence and to give them a vision of the greatness we can achieve by being independent and hardworking. I remember the textbooks we had when we were going to national school.  We had books on nation building, industries, thrift, progress and saving.  All these virtues were extolled.  Unfortunately I do not think you have that in the present-day textbooks.</P>
    <P>The greatest educator we have apart from the formal system is RTE.  That is the great moulder of opinion.  It could be used and harnessed to try to give the people a picture of their land, of what their forefathers have done.  Instead of presenting the people with a picture of what they should be doing, they are presented with a false picture.  I have had many complaints from constituents and from people all over the country regarding the type of programme we get from RTE, more than I have got about any other Department.  People are being given a false impression.  I have to say that there seems to be an attempt made by various people to undermine our christian values.  Complaints are constantly coming in.  I do not have that much time to see television programmes or to listen to radio programmes, but I have got innumerable complaints and I wonder what can be done about this situation. When the second channel was being brought in, it was strongly suggested that we take the material from the BBC.  I worked very hard to see that that would not happen.  However, looking back, I wonder if I did the right thing because there are programmes on the home channels in which the Holy Name is used. Some programmes are almost blasphemous. A picture of pagan living is presented to us as an ideal.  It is something which should be examined, because the radio and television are very powerful <Col N="299" /> and could be used to very good effect in bringing us back to reality.</P>
    <P>Something that is giving the whole Irish-speaking population in various parts of the country cause for grave anxiety is the present position so far as the Irish language is concerned.  Foilsíodh an ráiteas seo le déanaí ó Ghael-Linn.  Is é <i>Todhchaí na Gaeilge sa chóras Oideachais i bPoblacht na hÉireann</i> agus sa chéad alt deirtear:</P>
    <P>Ó bhunú an Stáit i leith ní raibh seasamh na Gaeilge sa chóras oideachais riamh chomh lag agus atá sé le roinnt blianta anuas &mdash; agus é sin ag tráth nuair atá sé léirithe arís agus arís eile go bhfuil bá chroíúil ag an bpobal leis an nGaeilge.  Tráfaidh an bhá sin go tapa mura mbíonn inniúlacht réasúnta sa Ghaeilge ag an aos scoile feasta, rud nach bhfuil á fháil ag cuid mhór díobh faoi láthair.</P>
    <P>That is a very serious statement and one with which I entirely agree.  Should there be anybody in the House at the moment who does not understand what it means I will repeat it in English.  It is:</P>
    <P>Since the Foundation of the State the position of Irish in the educational system has never been weaker than it has been in the last few years.  The position is still deteriorating in spite of the fact that it has been demonstrated again and again that there is a great fund of public goodwill for the language. This goodwill will soon disappear if the present school going generation does not achieve reasonable competence in Irish, a situation which is not so in the case of a great number of students today.</P>
    <P>That is the factual position I entirely agree with.  I have seen this decline taking place in the past four to eight years.  It is time to take stock of it.</P>
    <P>I will not go into all the reasons why we should save our language, promote it and see that it takes its rightful place in the life of the nation.  That would take a long time.  You probably all know the arguments in any case.  I will confine myself to saying that we have the oldest <Col N="300" /> vernacular in northern Europe, apart from Latin and Greek.  It is something we can be very proud of.  It is a beautiful language, a language in which we can really express ourselves.  It is worth the reviving and speaking of it if for nothing else than for the wealth of knowledge and the wisdom and philosophy we have in our seanfhocail.  It is worth doing it for that alone.  I hope that cognisance will be taken of this by the appropriate Department. I hope the Minister will convey these views.  We are very perturbed about the situation.  There is much that could be done to improve matters.  There are several recommendations made in this pamphlet from Gael Linn and there are many recommendations also in the <i>White Paper on Educational Development</i> publised at the end of 1981.  They are all there and they should be implemented.  I will not pursue the matter further with regard to the state of the language.  The recommendations are well worth a trial.</P>
    <P>Another pertinent point concerns Gaeilge and Radio Telefís Éireann. Announcers should take the greatest care to see that their pronounciation is faultless. I am not finding fault with anyone trying to learn a language and whose pronunciation is not perfect, but when it comes from a supposedly authoritative person, whether newsreader or otherwise, pronunciation should be perfect. As far as Italian, French or German are concerned pronunciations are invariably correct but when it comes to our own language announcers are careless and slovenly.  We had a glaring example a few mornings ago.  I will not mention what programme it was because I do not wish to indentify any particular person on it.</P>
    <P>After all those grumblings, I congratulate the Garda and the Army for the wonderful work they always do, and particularly during the recent blizzard.  They are a credit to the country.  I had intended to speak at length on their service; when all is said and done maybe God was very wise in sending the blizzard because it might bring people back to the reality of life and the fact that &ldquo;nuair atá an gad cóngarach don scórnach&rdquo; everybody must get up and fend for himself.</P>
    <Col N="301" />
    <Speaker pid="BarryDesmond" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. B. Desmond) Barry Desmond">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. B. Desmond)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senators for their contributions to the debate on this motion.  I shall endeavour to deal with as many points as possible, bearing in mind that time is fairly short.</P>
      <P>Senator Honan raised the question of the Youth Employment Agency.  In 1982 £41 million will be provided for employment and training of young persons.  The scheme will be entirely self-financing, which is to be welcomed.  This is a substantial increase over the level of expenditure last year which was only £19 million and it is envisaged that about 37,000 young persons will be involved in employment and training schemes this year compared with 21,000 in 1981.  This will require a great deal of organisation in the coming 11 months by the new board of the employment agency.  I stress that the youth employment levy will only come into effect at the beginning of the tax year &mdash; 6 April 1982.  Accordingly, in 1983 and in subsequent years the yield from the levy will be much greater than the £41 million I have mentioned for 1982.</P>
      <P>Senator Honan expressed concern at the level of existing commitment to the services for the disabled and in relation to the longer term planning in this area. I am sure the Senator &mdash; who has a particular interest in this area &mdash; will recall the report of the working party on services for the mentally handicapped which was published in 1980.  That report sets out the basis for future development of the services for mentally handicapped people.  The report received a general welcome.  It is appropriate to point out at this stage that the Minister for Health hopes to publish shortly a Green Paper on the services for the disabled.  At present that paper is at the final editing stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The paper will review in a comprehensive fashion the whole range of relevant services, including income maintenance, residential care, employment and education for the disabled.  I believe that Members will generally welcome the decision here, as a further commitment in a concrete form to the services now, rather than just planning for the future. I instance as an example of this Government's <Col N="302" /> concern that, despite the overall very difficult financial situation, we are prepared to introduce a welcome extension to the disabled persons' maintenance allowance scheme which should assist in the general area.</P>
    <P>Senator Honan and Senator Hussey raised aspects of land transactions, namely Senator Honan's comment about the legal costs involved in the purchase of a house.  I share her views on this matter.  I have conveyed my views to the Minister for the Environment and I understand that the Minister and the Department are actively looking into the matter.  I know that sounds like a trite public service phrase but I am assured that they are looking into this matter with a view to taking some action on the legal costs involved in the purchase of dwellings. I regard the situation as intolerable and unnecessary.</P>
    <P>Senator Hussey correctly expressed concern about excessive profits accruing to individuals involved in land speculation deals.  The Government share this concern.  Last September we issued a statement declaring our intention to introduce legislation which would have the effect of precluding the making of unjustified profits as a result of land rezoning decisions in areas of urban expansion or where services are provided by the public authorities.  With the imminence of the budget I am sure Members can appreciate that that is about all I can say on that issue at this stage.</P>
    <P>The seriousness of an inflation rate of 20.4 per cent for the calendar year or the four quarters of this year is hard to over-state.  But it is fair to point out that the figure for the full calendar year of 1981 is not 23 per cent or 24 per cent; that was the quarter for the 12 months to mid-November last and it included the figure of 23 per cent or 24 per cent and some large reassessment items.  Therefore, the best method of gauging the average rise in the consumer price index is obtained by taking the outcome for the four quarters of 1981: that gives an average of 20.4 per cent.  That is intolerably and unnecessarily high in many respects but it is not as high as Senator Kiely and Senator Fallon alleged.  With a view to <Col N="303" /> endeavouring to hold back prices during the period to March 1983 the Government, as part of their anti-inflation programme, will, during this period, subsidise key foodstuffs such as bread, milk butter and margarine.  This will help to mitigate the rise in the inflation rate.</P>
    <P>We should also bear in mind that our position was exacerbated by the appreciation of both sterling and the dollar in the first half of 1981.  This contributed to the general rise of import prices in the last three years and was responsible for the rise from 13½ per cent in 1979, to 18 per cent in 1980 and 19½ per cent in 1981. It has had a fairly significant impact on our present rate of inflation.</P>
    <P>A comment was also made about the £9.60 tax credit to home-working wives. There were criticisms expressed and the only comment I would make is that the number of applications to date has been 42,000.  It is a reasonable response to a completely new scheme and it is not possible at this stage to give a breakdown of the applications but it would be interesting to do so later on.  You will appreciate that it is a very small percentage of the total number of persons entitled to apply.</P>
    <P>I was very pleased to note that Senators welcomed the initiative taken by the Minister for Finance in proposing a review of financial procedures.  A discussion paper entitled &ldquo;A Better Way to Plan the Nation's Finances&rdquo; has been circulated. I suggest that the subject matter of that paper is of great importance and demands careful consideration.  To this end the Minister for Finance has initiated a wide-ranging consultation procedure and, indeed, was engaged yesterday in a seminar with the heads of Government Departments, with semi-State bodies and with industries on this issue.</P>
    <P>When this consultation is completed &mdash; and I will draw the Minister's attention to the high degree of interest expressed by Senators in this debate &mdash; the issue will be debated in Dáil Eireann.  At that stage it will be possible to take decisions on further procedures.  It is hoped that part of the discussion paper will be implemented this year in relation to 1983 expenditure.  This will make the debate <Col N="304" /> in 1983 more relevant by having consideration of public finance business when it counts, before the event rather than having a formal review as we have been doing here over the past two days when, on a post-dated basis, it was extremely difficult to exert any real influence over public expenditure.</P>
    <P>An area of reform on which I place particular emphasis is a review by the Dáil of existing expenditure schemes to ascertain if each of them still gives value for money and answers the needs of a modern republic.  I hope the Seanad will be able to join in that review.  Central to the proposal is the possible establishment of a Dáil public expenditure review committee. In the context of considering how a committee might be supported, consideration is also being given to the possible expansion of the role of the Comptroller and Auditor General or, alternatively, the establishment of a new office of public expenditure commissioner.  This goes some way along the road advocated by a number of Senators, in particular Senator Quinn, who called for a cost-benefit analysis of all major projects to be considered by the Oireachtas in advance. That is essential.  I am not sure if, in the long run, that work can stop some of the more ill-advised projects, but nevertheless it will be a major addition to the work of the Houses of the Oireachtas and will be generally welcomed.</P>
    <P>Senators have rightly acknowledged the need to restrain public expenditure but it is ironic that, throughout the whole debate, despite that acknowledgment, time and again there were repeated proposals from Senators for more expenditure on particular projects, whether on Tralee hospital, or in Ballyforan, or on Wexford hospital, to take different sides of the House.  There is an unending stream of demand for public expenditure without taking the necessary steps to fund that expenditure either from taxation or from growth.  Inevitably all of us suffer from this contradiction, this dichotomy. It underlines the relevance of the proposals we intend to make in relation to a cost-benefit analysis of public expenditure.</P>
    <P>The question of government borrowing <Col N="305" /> loomed large in this debate.  I should like to give a few examples.  In 1981, interest payments on the Exchequer's debt came to £947 million.  The Exchequer statement at the end of the year showed that income tax receipts for 1981 were £1,243 million.  This means that 76p in every £ of income tax revenue in 1981 was used to pay interest on our national debt.  To put it in even starker terms, which are quite staggering, almost 87p in every £ of income tax paid by the PAYE sector alone was absorbed by interest payments.  Of that 87p, 23p went straight out of the country to foreigners, which was even more staggering.</P>
    <P>The problem is getting worse.  The extra amount paid in income tax by PAYE workers in 1981 over what they paid in 1980, which was roughly an extra £215 million, was not sufficient to pay the increase in the bill for interest on our borrowings in 1981 as compared with 1980.  It is no secret that the interest payments on our foreign debt will rise substantially again in 1982.  I think I have said enough to highlight the fact that this is an extremely serious problem, perhaps the most serious of the many problems facing the Government.  The only way in which we as a community can repay our borrowings is by investing in productive assets which will generate a return sufficient to cover the costs of repayment of the principal and the interest on the loans.</P>
    <P>Unfortunately, much of the borrowing in recent years has been to finance day-to-day spending.  What was invested was often invested in projects of quite dubious value.  I say that as an advocate of public expenditure, as one who wants to see the public sector expand.  Therefore it is essential that the practice of borrowing to finance current budget deficits should be eliminated as quickly as possible, and that we should cast a very cold eye on some areas of public investment on which the return would appear to be zero.  I want to stress that the Government's freedom to manage the economy is being very seriously threatened by the ever-increasing burden of interest and principal repayments on our loans.  Every increase in revenue is being <Col N="306" /> gobbled up, rather than being made available to finance socially desirable expenditure.</P>
    <P>The balance of payments position, which is serious enough without adding to our problems, is being exacerbated by the ever-increasing payments on our foreign debt.  As recently as 1979, foreign interest payments amounted to over £100 million.  This year the figure will be a multiple of that.  Therefore, the overall picture is quite clear; we simply cannot continue to live beyond our means.  Last year's budget was the first step towards rectifying a dire situation and we intend to continue along that road.  It would be quite irresponsible to turn our backs on that major problem.  As a social democrat I maintain that is not monetarism; it is not Thatcherism by any manner of means.  It is simply a recognition of the harsh reality which confronts 3,500,000 people in the context of running our own affairs.</P>
    <P>Senator E. Ryan made a rather tongue-in-cheek defence here.  I have the greatest personal regard for Senator Ryan who is much underestimated in many respects in terms of his business acumen.  He said no Government had ever succeeded in keeping current expenditure to planned levels.  That might be so.  I would not necessarily dispute that, but I do not think any Government in the history of the State underestimated expenditure requirements to the extent Fianna Fáil did in 1981.  Last year the total amount of Supplementary Estimates needed for current supply services amounted to £588 million, or over 18 per cent of the original provision.  An underestimation of 18 per cent is colossal.</P>
    <P>Senator Ryan also stated that borrowing for current purposes was initiated in a very big way by a Coalition Government. He went on to say that all through the Coalition period of office in 1973 to 1977 such borrowing continued to grow and that, by the end of the period, it was a very firmly established practice.  On a television programme last Saturday night it was again inferred that the Coalition Government were the first to start the practice of having a current budget deficit. But it was deliberately planned in <Col N="307" /> 1972-73.  That was before the Coalition Government came into office.  It is true that when the oil crisis struck in 1973-74 the Government then deliberately borrowed for current purposes in order to sustain economic activity.  It is relevant to note that that action was in accordance with the advice of international organisations to Governments at that time.  I remember being in Government then and it was generally accepted by the OECD and from EEC general advice on the economic front that there was a case to be made &mdash; in 1973, 1974 and 1975 &mdash; for some level of budget deficiting.  But when we saw the budget deficits were not greatly helping economic activity at the time we took action to narrow the gap between current revenue and expenditure. We saw also that it was gravely affecting the balance of payment deficit and we took action, evidenced by the fact that, as a percentage of GNP, the current budget deficit was reduced from almost 7 per cent in 1975 to less than 5 per cent in 1976 and below 4 per cent in 1977.</P>
    <P>Unfortunately, we decided to go to the country immediately after doing so and not wait until 1978 when the benefits accrued back.  Through miserable political strategy at the time the Government found themselves out of office.  But they had done the right thing.  Coalition Governments tend to have the habit of doing the right thing and getting little thanks for so doing.  Therefore the trend in 1975, 1976 and 1977 was sharply downwards. That was needlessly reversed to my absolute dismay at the time.  I can barely attempt to forgive my constituency colleague, Deputy Martin O'Donoghue, for advocating that kind of reversal of policy which was outrageous and totally unnecessary. It was needlessly reversed by the new Fianna Fáil Government.  Thus the seeds of our present difficulties were sown.</P>
    <P>We had a budget deficit of approximately 3½ per cent of GNP in 1977.  That was relaxed into one of double that amount in 1979 and would have reached 9¼ per cent of GNP in 1981 had we not had the July budget.  Even with the odium we incurred in July last the budget deficit <Col N="308" /> of 8 per cent of GNP last year was the highest recorded in the history of the State.  Therefore even taking into account our corrective measures we still had the highest level ever recorded in the history of the State.</P>
    <P>I want to deal with some particular points raised.  Senator Mullooly suggested that there is to be a postponement of the briquette factory at Ballyforan and the ESB generating station at Arigna.  We had better look at these projects quite specifically.  He contended that the Government had abandoned the development of the west &mdash; of course, the last refuge of a politician, when hard up, is to start encouraging regional rivalries, county by county rivalries.  I am not suggesting that Senator Mullooly has descended to that level, but it is wrong to suggest that the Government have decided to postpone Bord na Móna's proposed new briquette factory at Ballyforan. As far as the briquette factory is concerned the Government have never given any indication that they are not prepared to provide money for the project. The delay arises from difficulties which Bord na Móna themselves are experiencing in securing finance from the European Investment Bank for the project. It is as simple as that.  The board now expect that these problems will be resolved satisfactorily very shortly and that the construction of the factory will start on schedule.  I should put that on record.</P>
    <P>As regards the Arigna generating station &mdash; and one must take into account the views of State bodies conveyed to Government &mdash; the ESB consider that the commissioning of this station should be deferred owing to the fact &mdash; and Senators should swallow hard when they hear the reality &mdash; that the ESB currently have 40 per cent excess generating capacity and this is going to increase.  These are the realities, not the west versus Cork or Moneypoint or Tarbert versus Dublin or anything else like that.  We should bear in mind, and place also on record, that the previous Government gave full approval to the ESB and they are currently investing £650 million in a new coal-fired power station in Moneypoint, <Col N="309" /> County Clare.  That station is due to come into operation in 1985.  This project is testimony to the Government's commitment to the west.  That will be a major coal-fired power station costing £650 million. I do not think Senators can ignore these facts.</P>
    <P>There has also been a suggestion, not necessarily from Senators but from some Deputies and public representatives in the west, that I in particular and other Deputies who allegedly live in Donnybrook &mdash; even though we do not &mdash; are all out to do down the west.  This is merely political posturing which demeans politics. We should take into account the scale of transfers of State resources to the west.  In 1979, the latest year for which I have detailed information, national expenditure of social welfare, health and education came to £1,538 million.  That represented £456 per head of population for the whole country.  But in the west of Ireland it represented £523 per head of population.  Admittedly there are certain aspects of employment involved, but it is not true to say, by any stretch of the imagination, no matter what Department Vote one takes, whether it is social welfare, or health, for example, that the west is being done down or allocated a disproportionate share of State resources.</P>
    <P>Total expenditure on agriculture and industry was £367 million in 1979, which represented £109 per head of population, but in the west it represented £136 per head of population.  Taking just a few Votes, social welfare, health, agriculture and industry together that gives us £565 per head nationally and £659 per head in the west.  Therefore, to suggest that the west has been treated less favourably by successive Governments is to indulge in what I might call selective whining journalism which appears twice a week in <i>The Irish Times</i>, in particular by one columnist, and merely ignores the realities in that area.</P>
    <P>Allegations are also being made that the west is being abandoned on the employment front.  It is a regrettable fact that throughout the country, including the west, unemployment has increased <Col N="310" /> substantially.  However, in the period July to December 1981 it is of interest to note that in the west, the north-west and in the Donegal planning regions, the increase in registered unemployed was 5.83 per cent while the increase in the State as a whole was 10.2 per cent. Admittedly there has been a particular situation, say in the Galway region, with recent redundancies and so on but it is quite untrue to say that unemployment has hit the west more heavily than the rest of the country.  In fact Dublin, Cork and Waterford in particular, to take three cities, have had a major impact on the employment situation.  In fact, Dublin, Cork and Waterford have had a very considerable unemployment problem. Generally the west of Ireland has benefited as much as any other area, and in fact has benefited to a greater degree than many, in respect of State expenditure and some of the highly selective politicising that has been conducted regarding Government action in the west of Ireland has not been true.</P>
    <P>The matter of aircraft facility for the Garda Síochána was raised during the debate.  This brings us back to the question of public expenditure.  The previous Minister for Justice announced there would be a major helicopter and light aircraft facility for the Garda Síochána but a cost-benefit analysis was not carried out.  He did not even seek a detailed report from the Commissioner regarding the cost.  If the Garda are to have their own aerial capability with the necessary back-up facilities, it is obvious that the Department of Justice, the Department of Finance and the Garda Commissioner must have a detailed analysis of the cost effectiveness of alternative methods of dealing with the needs of the Garda in this regard.  Because of the magnitude of the project it was obvious we should not take a decision until a full evaluation had been made of various options and the decision has been deferred pending a full and detailed report to the Government. Simply because someone suggests that every Garda division should have helicopter and light aircraft facilities it is outrageous to suggest that automatically <Col N="311" /> the Government should agree to that without carrying out an examination.</P>
    <P>As I pointed out, we spent £333 million in 1981 in respect of security measures. We tend to forget that in the past ten years we have spent £500 million because of the continuing Border security situation. Of the £333 million spent last year a sum of £90 million was directly attributable to a massive period of overtime in respect of Border duties by our Defence Forces.  We could have built 3,000 houses for that amount.  We could have wiped out the unemployment problem in Cork and Waterford.  At the current rate of IDA expenditure it costs approximately £7,000 to provide a new job.  Waterford has 3,000 people unemployed, the number in Cork is 7,000 and the amount of money we had to spend on security in the Border areas would have cleared the unemployment problem in those places.  The £500 million spent on security measures along the Border would have produced 100,000 jobs or would have paid for 25,000 houses.  The Provisional IRA have carried out a campaign of genocide among our people; all of us have deplored this and Senator Murphy, in particular, has been eloquent and more than courageous on this issue. Apart entirely from the genocide campaign of the Provisional IRA, their activities have meant loss of jobs and almost a loss of sovereignty, because we have had to borrow to meet current public expenditure.  We have suffered a loss of exports and a dramatic reduction in investment because our Border security situation appears in every investment analysis of every bank here and abroad. We tend to be blasé, to forget about it and to become coarsened in accepting the situation; but an investment analyst in America, Japan, France and elsewhere will be very aware of it and will not forget it when it comes to making a decision about investment.  The Provisional IRA have not just wreaked havoc on the Irish people; they have wreaked havoc also on our economy.  The lowering standards of living that we suffered in 1980 and 1981 and which we will suffer in 1982, despite efforts to maintain them, can be attributed <Col N="312" /> directly to the genocide campaign carried out by the Provisional IRA.</P>
    <P>Senator Carroll raised the question of economic and social planning.  We will definitely publish a national economic and social plan by mid-year.  It will include not just the ordered management of public finances but also the employment dimension.  That plan is in the course of preparation.  Rather than having, as we have had in recent years, <i>ad hoc</i> publications from the Department of Finance it is far better that there be an ordered general development.  There will be the budget in January, the national economic and social plan will be available in mid-year, the Estimates will appear in November at the latest, there will be a public debate on the Estimates and then we will have the budget.  The economic and social plan will feature strongly.</P>
    <P>I should like to quote from a statement made yesterday by Senator Whitaker when he spoke to the United States Chamber of Commerce in Ireland.  He said:</P>
    <P>Unless, however we recognise in our attitudes to incomes, productivity, value for money and the public finances, the need to do more to earn our present standard of living, and the impossibility of continuing to live beyond our means, external deficits and the borrowing they involve will overwhelm us and destroy our capacity to manage our economic affairs.</P>
    <P>Against the background I have outlined today, anybody who would advocate a continuation of Government borrowing on its present scale must be seen to be disgracefully irresponsible.</P>
    <P>Our parliamentary colleague is not given to strong language but I share his view that it would be irresponsible to advocate such a course of action in our situation.</P>
    <P>I will conclude by not being as gloomy as I was in the earlier part of my speech. When reporting on our economy last year the EEC Commission said that the longer-term prospects for our economy were significantly brighter than the short-term outlook.  I share that sentiment.  Our economy has many potential strengths and, if they are exploited properly, they <Col N="313" /> can make that possibility a reality.  There is no doubt that there has been some recovery.  It has been slow but it is there and there are clear signs evident in many of the indices for the first three-quarters of 1981.  It is a tribute to the 50,000 Irish workers who are now exporting to the international markets on a profitable basis.  There is a very solid industrial base for exports and recovery has been confirmed by external trade indices and in terms of industrial exports which have performed very well, despite the persistance of recession in our main markets. Some of the more recent business surveys available from the Central Statistics Office indicate that there is a mild recovery. It will be well into the middle of 1982 before this is reasonably evident.  It certainly will be the end of 1982 before it will have any impact on employment because, such is the over-capacity in industry that there is at least six months time lag before the effect is felt on the manpower vacancy situation.</P>
    <P>I am not pessimistic.  The International Monetary Fund very nearly intruded into our economy within a fortnight of our taking office.  I can say that because I was aware of the situation.  If getting a reasonable balance in the nation's finances does not involve a situation whereby foreign banks and domestic banks would take a decision to refuse to lend money to the Irish Government &mdash; as was immiment in a certain situation &mdash; if that can be avoided, as it has now been avoided, and our creditworthiness restored in terms of more external reserves, which now are at least the equivalent of two-and-a-half months of export earnings, as commented on by Senator Whitaker in the past 24 hours, we can face the prospect of a full economic recovery.</P>
    <P>It is not enough to put the nation's finances right.  It is not enough to restore rational criteria in public expenditure and in taxation.  One also has the problem of industrial production, industrial recovery, industrial investment.  The Government must set a time limit to enable an upturn to occur.  By the middle of 1982, we will have succeeded in doing that, with the National Development Corporation under way.  The corporation will <Col N="314" /> not be a panacea for all the problems but will assist in that development.  With the Youth Employment Agency also in full operation and with sanity prevailing on the taxation front, I am quite convinced that we can provide employment for the thousands of young school leavers in 1982 and in the years ahead.</P>
    <P>I thank the Senators for their contributions to this debate and will advise my colleague, the Minister for Finance, and the Government of the views of Members of this House on the Appropriation Act, 1981.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GemmaHussey" hpid="Mrs. G. Hussey Mrs. G. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. G. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to adjourn until 2.30 p.m.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 12.55 p.m. and resumed at 2.30 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Army Medical Corps:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Army Medical Corps: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann considers that the status and efficiency of the Army Medical Corps should be improved as a matter or urgency in the interests of the Defence Forces as a whole.</P>
      <P>At the outset I should like to welcome the Minister.  I think it is his first appearance here as Minister for Defence, although I think he put in an appearance for another Minister on one occassion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What I have to say is in no way political. I am not here to, as it were, bash the Minister.  In fact, I think he will recall an event which happened five or six years ago in County Clare where I had the pleasure of coming to his rescue in a very practical way and I think both of us got a fair degree of enjoyment from that event.  I am not here to criticise the Minister, Deputy Tully, and I am not here to criticise past Ministers.  I know, in so far as Deputy Tully is concerned, that he has inherited the problem which I will outline. I will be asking him to remedy the situation.  I am here to highlight a problem that exists in so far as the Army Medical Corps is concerned.  What I say I would be saying to any Minister for <Col N="315" /> Defence, irrespective of which political party he belonged to.  I want to set the record straight from the word go.</P>
    <P>This problem of the Army Medical Corps is one that I have been watching and listening to over the years.  I have read about it in newspapers.  Army men have mentioned it to me.  I have made my own inquiries and have read about it in the <i>Irish Medical Times.</i> I read the Supplementary Estimate for the Minister's Department with great interest.  I take a particular interest in matters of defence for the obvious reason that I come from an Army town.  We have a very proud tradition and a very fine barracks, one of the best in the country.  Many of my friends are there and therefore I take a particular interest in matters of defence. I studied the parliamentary debate dealing with the Supplementary Estimate but I found no reference to the Army Medical Corps.  Other areas like housing and promotions were mentioned.  Even Deputy Hugh Byrne, who I understand is a medical doctor, made no reference to the Army Medical Corps.  In fact the only reference I saw in the whole debate was the word &ldquo;medicines&rdquo; with a figure of a very small amount.  I was a bit disappointed that Deputy Byrne referred to an aspect of another corps and made the point that people convicted of vandalism and some of the layabouts of the city should be recruited into this new corps. At a recent corporals' mess dinner at Custume Barracks I publicly congratulated the Minister for saying that that type of person is no longer wanted in the Irish Army.  The Army nowadays is too good a job for layabouts.  The Minister was quite right, and I congratulate him for saying so so quickly in that debate. Down the years district justices for some reason or other used to say to people who got into trouble with the law: &ldquo;Why don't you join the Army?&rdquo; That day is gone, thank God.  The Army is now a good job, a good career, and the best type of young men should be recruited to it.</P>
    <P>In so far as the Army Medical Corps itself is concerned, it is known that the figure for establishment as recommended by Public Service and the Department is <Col N="316" /> 72; in other words, there should be 72 medical people in the Army Medical Corps.  That is the requirement and the figure generally accepted and recommended. Possibly a bit less might suffice. But, in fact, the total strength this week of the Army Medical Corps is 31.  In the debate the Minister referred to the fact that the Army has almost 15,000 personnel.</P>
    <P>It has 31 medical staff and, of the 31 medical people, two are overseas; each battalion of roughly 600 men that goes overseas brings with it two doctors.  This is very good.  That is a good doctor-patient ratio and obviously we hope it will not be interfered with in any way. Two more are presently on study leave &mdash; that is another problem that I will touch on later.  There is a total of 16 in administration doing routine, perhaps important, paperwork, but it is administration. There are four specialists working in the three hospitals of St. Bricin's, the Curragh and Cork.  That leaves a total of seven who might be called non-consultant, non-administrative, ordinary, decent practising medical men doing routine doctoring work.  So the ratio is seven to 15,000.  I am wondering how that could, by any stretch of the imagination, be considered to be sufficient, bearing in mind that 72 is the establishment figure. The four specialists, as I said, engaged in hospital work are working at general medical work also.</P>
    <P>The motion refers to the efficiency and the status of the Army Medical Corps, but let me quickly say that I am in no way commenting on the efficiency of the doctors who are presently there or who have been there over the past few years.  They are excellent people; they are known to be excellent doctors.  But they must be working under some very serious strain. There are no doctors available for the Air Corps.  There is no doctor available for the Naval Service.  The medical care for the Defence Forces is totally inadequate countrywide.  As a result of it being that way, it must be seen to be operating with minimal efficiency.</P>
    <P>The question of pay for Army doctors is a burning question.  The pay is unrealistic having regard to the present rate of <Col N="317" /> inflation.  There is no index-linking; it is not related to the national wage rounds. I feel that at all times the professional pay should be at least 33? per cent more than the regimental pay.  Regimental pay and professional pay should be linked.  It is wrong that the pension of an Army medical man should be based on regimental pay only.  Why should this be? It does not make sense.</P>
    <P>The status of the doctor in the Irish Army does not compare favourably with the status of doctors in the medical corps of other armies.  If we take our nearest neighbouring army, a comparison might be no harm.  When one joins the medical corps one does so as a captain.  The promotion from captain to commandant, depending on vacancies, can take up to nine years.  In our nearest neighbouring army promotion from captain to major will take place after five years.  I understand that the Irish Medical Association has requested on a number of occasions that this change should take place.  So the normal age of an infantry officer, that is captain to commandant, would be about 32 years.  The normal age of an Army medical commandant after promotion would be 38/39, despite the fact that an Army medical man would have about seven years' training to be a doctor, whereas the other person would have most likely a leaving certificate standard qualification.  That is not fair.</P>
    <P>In the Irish Army promotion from commandant to lieutenant-colonel depends on a number of factors &mdash; deaths, retirements and resignations.  It may take up to 30 years, or it might never happen.  On the other hand, in our nearest neighbouring army, promotion from major to lieutenant-colonel takes place after 13 years.  That is pretty well guaranteed. As regards promotion from lieutenant-colonel to colonel for an Army medical man, for the majority of them this will never happen.  Promotion from lieutenant-colonel to colonel takes place after 23 years in our nearest neighbouring army.  The Irish Army Medical Corps has no worthwhile career structure for the majority of its members.</P>
    <P>Another aspect which is clearly worrying for young doctors joining, and it <Col N="318" /> should not be, is the scope for post-graduate training.  Apart from ordinary medical officer courses, there is no encouragement to allow them to do post-graduate training.  The opposite is the case.  If a person obtains a place on some of these training schemes and wants leave of absence with or without pay in most cases he will not get it.  The general attitude would be not to allow this to happen. That is not right.  Obviously if a young Army medical officer goes off and improves himself with or without pay it will be to the benefit of the Army subsequently. They can obviously make a contract with him that he stay with the Army for a period of 20 or 25 years.  The Army would be the clear beneficiaries in that situation.</P>
    <P>For the Army Medical Corps there has been no adequate provision for widows and orphans since 1978.  For example, if an ordinary officer was killed in overseas activity, his widow would be looked after, and rightly so.  But if an Army medical officer was killed overseas on duty his widow would not have the same benefit at all.  This is totally unfair.  I cannot understand why it should be.  I am told it is a fact.</P>
    <P>There is always the problem of retirements, deaths and resignations.  From 1977 to 1981 six young medical officers of the Army resigned out of sheer frustration at the conditions in which they were asked to work.</P>
    <P>Since July we know there has been an embargo on jobs in the public service.  It applies to the Army although there is an obvious scarcity of people here.  The Army regularly advertise for medical officers and the response has been totally hopeless.  The <i>Irish Medical Times</i> of 24 July 1981 makes the point that a Dr. Flanagan, who is a lady doctor&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair would prefer if names were not mentioned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that there are three lady doctors.  They are not asked to go overseas although they would like to do so.  That is wrong.  If they want to go overseas to work as their male counterparts are doing, the opportunity should <Col N="319" /> be there for them.  Perhaps the Minister would comment on why this is so.  The <i>Irish Medical Times</i>, dealing with the aspect of recruiting people to the Army Medical Corps, stated that the Army was looking for 15 doctors at the time but the response appeared to be so bad that the Department of Defence readvertised for doctors in January of 1981.  This seems to be the trend.  The response seems to be very bad for the reasons I have given.</P>
      <P>There is no Army doctor in Donegal. There is no Army doctor in Mullingar where there are about 200 people.  There is no Army doctor in Longford.  The same applies in many other areas.</P>
      <P>If advertisements were inserted or perhaps if they were done on a different basis &mdash; for example, if one could specify in some way that these advertisements were for specific areas of the country &mdash; perhaps one would have a better response.  I know and appreciate that if one recruits a doctor or an Army man generally, he could be in Cork for a year, spend another year in the Curragh or be transferred anywhere.  Having regard to the problems in getting people to join the Army, it might be a good idea perhaps if some changes took place.  Of the 450 graduates from the various medical schools of Ireland, approximately 150 or thereabouts obtain employment immediately, some emigrate and some pursue further studies, but almost none will join the Irish Army.  That should not be the case.  I understand that England has a medical cadet scheme whereby second-year medical students are commissioned to the rank of lieutenant and from there on they are taken and kept in the Army as medical people.  Perhaps some such scheme could operate here.  The Minister might look at this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It would be interesting to find out the amount of money paid annually to civilian doctors doing work for the Army as is the case all over Ireland.  It would be very interesting to find out the number of not just the doctors but also the consultants and other specialists who give this service.  Perhaps the funds given to these people, if put towards better wages or salaries for the Army medical people, <Col N="320" /> would attract more people to this service for the Army.  Something will have to be done in this regard.</P>
    <P>I cannot help feeling that we are lucky to have such a very healthy Army of 15,000.  At the same time, if a medical examination is carried out on any one in, say, July, it could happen that a kidney complaint, heart condition or whatever would arise later in a reasonably short time.  While we have a specimen of a healthy people in our Army, it is very important to have a good back-up medical team right across the country.  I suggest that the figure I have given is totally inadequate.  If the present trend continues the present crisis with the Army Medical Corps will become much worse.  In my opinion, it is a crisis situation now which arises out of lack of recruiting and other reasons which I have given in my address.  Unless radical improvements take place we will have a total collapse within two or three years.  We would not like that and it would not be good for any of us, for the morale of our soldiers and for the nation in general.</P>
    <P>I have attempted to highlight in the presence of the Minister the problems that exist with the Army Medical Corps. I hope that as a result of this debate &mdash; which is intended to highlight, not to criticise, the inadequacies &mdash; much improvement will come about and that the Minister will investigate the matter and, more important, will endeavour to rectify this terrible sad situation.</P>
    <P>I conclude by saying, looking at the Minister, what a fine Athlone man he is, and I have been his friend for many years.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish formally to second the motion and will speak later on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCarroll" hpid="Mr. Carroll Mr. Carroll">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carroll</NameTxt>
      <P>I have some personal feeling for this question because my father was a member of the Army Medical Corps for a number of years and from discussions and so on I know something about it.  First of all, in joining in the welcome that Senator Fallon extended to the Minister, I would also like to extend to the Minister my personal congratulations on the wonderful job of work done by him and the Army during the recent very adverse period we went through. <Col N="321" /> There is no doubt that the Army Air Corps and the ordinary soldiers who were out on the streets, the drivers and all the others who were involved in helping during that period, did a fantastic job of work and deserve the highest credit from all of us.  Of itself that experience establishes, as Senator Fallon said, that within the Army we have a high standard of not alone personal efficiency in respect of individuals but a high standard of health. These lads were able to respond to fantastic demands on their time and on their personal resources and they responded very well and showed all of us that so much is to be gained by having a public commitment, a code of conduct and a standard to aim at and to maintain.  Such a code would benefit this community as a whole if it could find an equal level through all sectors in our society.  We can draw from that example the conclusion that the Army are reasonably well-fed, well-clothed and well-looked after within the resources available to us, and therefore we have a lot to be thankful for.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>At the same time I go along with the broad basis on which Senator Fallon made his submission, which is that we should always be looking to improve whatever services are required either within the Army or on the social scene generally so that we can be always aiming at the highest possible standards and for a general contribution towards the improvement in these standards within the nation.  I imagine that when evaluating the question of the medical services for the Army we must have regard, not alone immediately to the financial resources available to the Army itself, but to the other medical and health services available within the State as a whole. I hope that the authorities concerned will ensure that whatever particular consultation or diagnostic or treatment services are required to handle special problems will be available from the ordinary public health services.  I am quite sure that there is a very efficient arrangement whereby the hospital services and general health services can provide the type of special service or attention that may be needed from time to time to meet difficulties such <Col N="322" /> as a kidney problem, heart problem and so on.</P>
    <P>It would seem illogical to anticipate a situation where every county or regional area &mdash; I do not know how the Army is broken up &mdash; should carry its own total medical service and equipment.  Apart from the economics of it I imagine that we could have much redundant service if we approached it in that way because the demand would not be there for that high level of applied service on a regional or area basis.</P>
    <P>I agree with Senator Fallon that, if there is not an adequate link-up with the public health services, the hospital services and so on and the Army authorities, then this is a failure; but that failure cannot be laid at anybody's door.  It is something that we have inherited over the last 20, 30 or 40 years.  It is not the responsibility of any one Government other than to ensure that if they are recruiting medical personnel or any other professional expertise into the Army the terms of recruitment should be such as to attract the best people possible.  It would be wrong &mdash; if it is so &mdash; that any Army medical people would be discriminated against either in the reward they would expect to get for their expertise and professionalism or in the opportunity available to them to advance in their career.  I am upset to have heard &mdash; I do not know how factual it is &mdash; that some impediment seems to be in the way of Army medical people developing their careers.  This may be due to the fact that so many vacancies are unfilled that those within the service are over-committed and their workload excessively heavy and, therefore, they cannot be released to take post-graduate courses or refresher courses.</P>
    <P>If this is a problem I would join Senator Fallon in requesting that the matter receive urgent examination. Not having the facts, I am not being assertive on this but I agree with the broad principle that the Army Medical Corps should be appropriate to the needs of soldiers in a modern army in which there may be different types of tensions and stresses from those experienced years ago.  The Army <Col N="323" /> are now more involved in the social scene and their role may expand.  They may need a different type of medical service and the Minister might tell us whether studies are being done to determine the manner in which the medical service may best operate.</P>
    <P>While I agree with the broad principle that the Army should have the best possible service, it is implicit in the wording of the motion that there is something seriously amiss in respect of the Army medical services.  If there were something seriously amiss I should imagine that the Irish Medical Union and other medical authorities as well as the representative organs within the Defence Forces would have brought this matter to the attention of successive Governments.  It will be interesting to hear from the Minister the position in that regard.  I would not wish to be identified with a motion of censure if that censure cannot be established as bona fide.</P>
    <P>The general services available to the community should be available to the Defence Forces so that they can get the best treatment and service.  If this can best be done by bringing in outside consultants or admitting soldiers to public hospitals for operations, this should be done.  Medical personnel would, of course, be needed to deal with day-to-day minor ailments with which all of us are afflicted and there are areas of residence where families of soldiers need a local service.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already seconded this motion and I join Senator Fallon in welcoming the Minister for Defence.  I come from Athlone and share a common concern with Senator Fallon on this subject.  I should like to correct a misapprehension by Senator Carroll.  It was not intended that this should be a motion of censure and Senator Fallon explained that it was a motion expressing concern and designed to highlight a particular area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Fallon mentioned several aspects of this matter which he wished to highlight and perhaps the most salient point concerns the numerical disproportion. The statistic upon which we must <Col N="324" /> concentrate is that there are 31 medical doctors to serve 15,000 people.  If two of these are overseas, two are on study leave, 16 are working in administration and four are specialists, the number of doctors who attend to the everyday ailments of the soldiers is very scant.  The proportion of medical officers to personnel cannot be seen as equitable.</P>
    <P>Pay and status are also very important. Naturally we are all interested in pay in order to live but men and women within the Army Medical Corps must also be very concerned about status and promotion and the lack of career opportunities. The latter point would be an obstacle to any person considering entering the Army Medical Corps because the idealistic young person who has been well trained obviously seeks a position where there is a possibility of advancement and for specialist development and post-graduate work in order to further his or her education and better to serve the interests of those whom he or she is employed to help.  Further training in any job can only be to the benefit not only of the person receiving that training but also to the benefit of those being served.</P>
    <P>The Army have expanded and evolved in every way and the image and status of the Defence Forces have improved enormously. Successive Governments have been well served by Ministers for Defence and this has never been seen as a Cinderella posting.  The task of the Minister for Defence has been seen as highly important and relevant to our everyday life.  I come from an Army town and Custume Barracks has a large number of Army personnel both men and women. The idea of recruiting women to the Army was initiated by Deputy Robert Molloy when Minister for Defence and taken up by his successor, Deputy Barrett, and by the present Minister.  The Army have developed their scope and their rôle and they appear to be modern and forward-thinking.  We can be proud of their rôle not only at home but treasna na dúnta in far-off lands.</P>
    <P>It would be a pity if there were a lacuna in any aspect of Army life and it is this concern which has prompted the putting down of this motion.  Napoleon said that <Col N="325" /> an Army marches on its stomach and the culinary aspects of Army life are very well looked after.  It would be a pity if such an important matter as the health of Army personnel were to be adversely affected through any lack of numbers in the Army Medical Corps.  I would imagine that this situation has arisen over the years and that while the Army has evolved in other areas this aspect has not. I do not speak with authority on this point but it seems that the rôle of the medical corps was allowed to be obscured and the system under which personnel were recruited, served and retired remained static.</P>
    <P>I am very glad that the Minister has taken the trouble to come here to listen to our viewpoints.  I reiterate that this is not a motion of censure but is designed to express concern for the Army in general and particularly for an improvement in the status and efficiency of the Army Medical Corps.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is mian liomsa, ar dtús, fáilte a chur roimh an Aire Cosanta agus fáilte a chur roimh an rún seo atá ar an gclár agus buíochas agus comhghairdeas a ghabháil leis na Forsaí Cosanta as ucht a bhfuil déanta acu ó bunaíodh an Stáit seo chun síocháin a chaomhnú agus a chosaint sa tír seo agus in áiteanna eile ar fud an domhain.</P>
      <P>I am pleased to support this motion that the position of the Army Medical Corps should be reviewed in the interests of the Defence Forces as a whole.  The time is opportune, as the Leader of the Opposition in the House said yesterday, for a comprehensive and constructive review, embracing all aspects of the working conditions of our Defence Forces.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The primary function of the Army Medical Corps in peacetime is to provide for the preservation of the health and physical fitness of the Defence Forces. While it is true to say that the actual strength of the corps falls short of the establishment, it is also true to say this is not of recent development.  The corps, nevertheless, have been able to carry out their responsibilities assisted by civilian doctors, dentists and specialists.  The <Col N="326" /> Army Medical Corps have at the moment a current strength of 29 non-specialist medical officers compared to an establishment of 46, a strength of four specialist medical officers against an establishment of 25, a strength of eight dental officers as against an establishment of 14, a strength of four pharmaceutical officers as against an establishment of five, a strength of four line officers as against an establishment of eight, a strength of 149 non-commissioned officers as against an establishment of 171, a strength of 172 privates as against an establishment of 326 and a strength of 86 Army nursing staff as against an establishment of 93. These figures pinpoint the necessity for a comprehensive review.  They do not indicate, however, a very serious crisis situation.  They indicate the need for a constructive and comprehensive review.</P>
    <P>I would like to take the opportunity here, as this is the first occasion the Minister has come to this House as Minister for Defence, to pay tribute to the Permanent Defence Forces and the FCA for the great work they have done since the foundation of the State in advancing and promoting peace in this country.  The effective strength of the Permanent Defence Forces at the moment is 15,000 as against a total peacetime establishment of 18,000 including all ranks.  The effective strength of the FCA is 21,700 as against a total establishment of 22,200 all ranks.  I would like also to pay tribute to the Slua Muirí for the work they are doing in assisting the Naval Service in sea defence, port control and vessel investigations.</P>
    <P>It is appropriate to pay a well-deserved tribute to all our personnel who have been engaged in maintaining and fostering international peace overseas since this country became a member of the United Nations in 1955.  The importance of the peace-keeping missions that have gone from this country overseas can be seen from the fact that 6,400 members of all ranks served in the UN force in the Congo between 1960 and 1964, 9,400 of all ranks served in the UN force in Cyprus since its inception in 1964 and over 4,000 have served in the Lebanon.  At present 650 Irish personnel are with UNIFIL, the <Col N="327" /> United Nations Interim Force in the Lebanon.  This mission, in particular, has faced one of the most difficult tasks that this country&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Reynolds) Acting Chairman (Mr. Reynolds)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Reynolds)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Senator is getting away from the Army Medical Corps of the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I was paying a well-deserved tribute to these forces in view of the presence of the Minister in the House for the first time.  I would like, seeing that I have singled out certain units of our Defence Forces, to pay tribute to the Naval Service and to the Air Corps. I would like to compliment the Army and the Air Corps for the great work that they did leading up to and during the historic visit of Pope John Paul II to this country.  In conclusion, I would like to support this motion, to welcome the Minister to this House, and to congratulate him, the Army and all the units under him for the work they are doing for this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>Since Senator Kennedy has gone through the motions of defending the Defence Forces and has given us the statistics dealing with Defence Force activities, I hope I will be permitted to make a few comments.  I have a little knowledge of the Army Medical Corps in the sense that I had an uncle in the Army who died in an Army hospital and I have a first-cousin who is a nurse in the Army Medical Corps.  Indeed, one of the things that has concerned me in the last few years is that the nurses in the Army Medical Corps did not get officer status, non-commissioned officer status and private status within the Department of Defence.  The nurses who operate the majority of the medical services in the Army have no status.  It is about time they were given the right to wear a flash on their uniforms.  They are given a uniform but they do not have even the status of a private in the Army.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am a member of the Organisation of National Ex-servicemen as an ex-corporal in the FCA.  I have a reasonable knowledge of what goes on in the Army and of <Col N="328" /> what status means.  One of the things that has always annoyed me is that if I go to university and get myself a degree as a doctor I can walk into the Army as a commandant.  If I am a nurse I get a job in the Army as a nurse but I get no status under the Department of Defence.  A nurse in the Army Medical Corps goes in as a nurse and goes out as a nurse.  There is no promotional prospect.  A doctor goes in with possibly the same amount of training.  He starts off as a commandant and comes out as a lieutenant-colonel. This is an area of concern.  I do not feel the doctor should have any more promotional prospects in the Army than a nurse.  I would like to see within the terms of the motion that nurses in the Army be given a status within the Army.  Senator Kennedy mentioned the number of people who served at home and abroad under the Department of Defence and I accept all his figures.</P>
    <P>It is very noticeable, if one goes abroad to visit the Irish forces working with UNIFIL, UNWRA and other international organisations, that there is not one medical person from the Irish Army working in those areas.  We have every grade within the Army working in the Lebanon from general to private, but, as far as I know, there is not one medical officer or nurse working there.  Senator Kiely and Senator Fallon proposed that there be an upgrading of the Army Medical Corps.</P>
    <P>In Kilkenny we have about 350 Army personnel, but there is no nurse or doctor. There is no place in that town where a member of the Army can go for medical attention except to a private doctor.  In Dublin we have an Army hospital but there is no hospital in Limerick, Cork, Kilkenny or Athlone.  Why should Army personnel in Kilkenny have to go to a private doctor for medical attention? Why is there not a doctor or a nurse?  No private industry with an establishment of 350 would be allowed to operate without a doctor or nurse on their staff.</P>
    <P>Our Army have done a fantastic job and, from the establishment of the State, have been faithful to the Government of the day.  However, in my view, they do not get the support they deserve.  This <Col N="329" /> motion, as drafted, allows us to discuss this aspect of our Defence Forces.  Successive Ministers &mdash; when I say &ldquo;successive Ministers&rdquo; I am going back to the establishment of the Army &mdash; accepted the support of the Army but have never given them the status they deserve. Thank God the day has gone when district justices used to say &ldquo;Join the Army or go to England&rdquo;.  A career in the Army is one of the most admirable professions. If one visits South Lebanon one will see that even the youngest member of our Army is a professional.  Therefore, these men should be given more support than they are getting at present.  What is the status of a member of the FCA serving full-time in the Army?  There are many of these people.  They cannot go to an Army doctor; they have to go to a private doctor for medical treatment.  This situation should be changed.</P>
    <P>The Minister is doing a very necessary job.  He has shown his concern for Army personnel.  Within the terms of this motion there is no doubt that every Army establishment should have its own doctor, nurse and medical centre.  I am not concerned about their promotion prospects of if they are paid enough, because a person joining knows in advance what work is ahead of them, their promotion prospects and their income.  The Minister should improve standards so that our Army personnel should get as good if not better treatment than anybody else.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceOConnell" hpid="Mr. O'Connell Mr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>Before I address myself to one possible role for the Army Medical Corps, I should like to thank the movers of this motion for giving us an opportunity to discuss this matter.  This is an example of how we can address ourselves to matters of national importance on a non-partisan basis in an intelligent and constructive way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The debate has addressed itself in the main to the immediate practical role of the Army Medical Corps.  One might define that by saying that it provides medical services for the Defence Forces.  I would like to put forward a suggestion for the Minister's consideration.  It is a suggestion which would require very careful thought because there are as <Col N="330" /> many disadvantages to the proposal as there are likely advantages to it.  I have in mind the question of how the Army Medical Corps might provide one particular area of service to the country at large.  Down through the years one has heard of, maybe participated in private debates or discussions on the whole question of conscription or national service or the inclusion under the general umbrella of the Defence Forces of some kind of volunteer service.  There are many advantages to such a proposal, but on the other hand there are some very substantial disadvantages. If that question ever were to come up for serious consideration it is something we should devote very careful consideration to before embarking on such a project.  I am talking here in terms of the general idea of using service in the Defence Forces for what essentially are non-military purposes.</P>
    <P>Those of us who have experience of living in Great Britain and who are of a certain age will possibly know something about the experience of that country with regard to national service.  It was an experience which was of great benefit to some people but it was also an incredible waste of time for many others.  It was something which did not give unmitigated benefits either to those who participated in it or to the country itself.  Therefore any proposals that might come forward in that regard should be thought about very carefully.  There is also, particularly in this country, the possibility of the political dangers that might arise, if one had large numbers of young people together in a disciplined situation, possibly a captive audience, from particular doctrinaire, political or ideological ideas.</P>
    <P>However, I should like to put forward to the Minister for his consideration, possibly on a long-term basis, the possibility of using the Army Medical Corps as a means of medical service to the community at large on a volunteer basis.  Reference has been made here to the difficulty of recruiting suitable people as fully-qualified medical doctors.  This is not a problem that is limited to this country.  It arises on a worldwide level and is very much related to the kind of financial remuneration available to the medical profession <Col N="331" /> outside the public service.  What I would suggest is that in a situation where some qualified medical staff are faced with emigration some means might be considered for providing them with outlets through some kind of short service commission.</P>
    <P>My professional experience as a guidance councillor has brought me into contact with a great many young people who would like to be involved in some kind of paramedical service either of a temporary nature or something with more long-term career prospects.  They find themselves caught in a situation in which the medical profession and careers of that kind tend to be divided between what can be classified as high-qualification situations &mdash; medical doctors and, within that category, all the complexes of high grades &mdash; and also other outlets, say, the nursing profession, which may not be attractive to many people.  This applies to males rather than females, males who may not be interested specifically in nursing or who may be subject to the remnants of sexist prejudice which are still attached to the nursing profession, males who would like to be involved in some kind of paramedical service but find very few outlets in this area.</P>
    <P>Basically what I am suggesting to the Minister is that he should give consideration to the possibility of some kind of volunteer service through the medium of the Army Medical Corps by which a certain number of people would have an opportunity for a certain degree of medical training, medical education and at a level substantially below that which is required under our system for qualification for a medical doctor.  Such people would be available to the community, not just on an emergency basis but possibly through the hospitals, in particular in areas where hospitals are understaffed.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I would stress the point that in any project which involves the idea of using the Defence Forces for civilian purposes we should tread very carefully.  By and large our history is one in which the Defence Forces have carried out, in relation to the civil power, a role which excels honour, excels the kind of duty that one would expect in a democracy <Col N="332" /> of our kind.  We should be careful in any kind of project of this nature not to upset that balance and not to put people in a situation where they become involved possibly in a political role in the community as has happened in other countries &mdash; for instance, in Portugal and in France.  This is an an area where the Army could make a contribution and it would be something which would be of direct benefit to many individual young people who want to serve the community.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTully" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. Tully) James Tully">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. Tully)</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I should like to thank those Senators who contributed to the debate, which has been very interesting.  I have learned something from the debate, though some of what I have heard is not correct.  However, in any debate here, one gains some extra information from the wide experience of the various Senators.  I thank Senator Fallon for his kind remarks.  I always found him an able debater and a very fair-minded person. I thank Senator Carroll for his reference to the actions of the Army in general.  I am grateful to all the people who have sent their thanks as a result of what happened in the past two weeks.  We are all very proud of the Army.  I want to thank those people on my own behalf and on behalf of the Army.  When there is an emergency the Army are needed and everybody appreciates them but when there is no emergency people tend to take them for granted.  I hope that as a result of last week's episode people will appreciate that we have a dedicated Army of men and women who are prepared to help their fellow citizens when they are needed.  The Army carried out so many mercy missions that it seemed they had taken over from the medical service.  The Army hospital in the Curragh had to deal even with maternity cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am also grateful to Senators who referred to soldiers serving abroad.  They have been attempting to keep the peace in the Middle East and I feel they are not appreciated.  We are not prepared to try to find out what they are doing, not alone in Cyprus and in Lebanon, but also in Syria, Egypt and Israel.  People seem to think these people are going abroad for <Col N="333" /> excitement when in fact they are doing a fantastic peacekeeping job.  Many of them told me that they went there as boys and became men overnight.  Nothing will bring somebody to his senses more quickly than being under fire, not once but several times over a period of a few months.  One old man, a native of Lebanon, told me that the Irish troops were respected by the local people because they respected the local people.  This is a record of which we are very proud.</P>
    <P>There are two medical officers and a dentist in Lebanon.  In his spare time, one of the medical officers looks after hospitals and many local people who in a war-torn country would not be able to get any medical assistance without him. This is something which is provided free and we are very glad of it.</P>
    <P>This is my first opportunity to address the Seanad as Minister for Defence and I look forward to having a constructive and harmonious relationship with all Members.  While I regret that the tenor of the motion might suggest that our Medical Corps is a less than efficient body, I am sure the movers did not mean that.  I accept what they said and am very glad to be able to correct any false impression which may exist and to speak of the excellent record of the Corps and its very high standards of application as evidenced by the fine health and physical record of our Defence Forces.</P>
    <P>The primary functions of the Corps in peacetime are to provide for the preservation of the health and physical fitness of the Defence Forces and to help to fulfil the Corps' operational role in wartime. In wartime a number of main headings would be: advice on the health of troops and prevention of disease; evacuation and treatment of sick and wounded; advice on positioning of medical units; supply and replenishment of medical supplies and equipment; provision of nursing and dental services; compilation of records and statistics regarding sick and wounded for military and medical use. These are very onerous and widespread responsibilities and we appreciate that the peacetime organisation of the Corps can provide no more than a nucleus around which the Corps could expand <Col N="334" /> and develop to cope with wartime functions.</P>
    <P>In order that the Medical Corps would be in a position to fulfil their role in wartime, it is necessary to maintain a peacetime military medical establishment that will provide (a) the personnel to command units of the Medical Corps, (b) the personnel and facilities for the training of non-commissioned officers and privates of the Medical Corps, (c) facilities for military training, including training in providing medical support to combat troops, (d) opportunity in medicine that would attract young doctors to the Corps and (e) facilities for the development of medical expertise and for professional advancement.  The under strength of the establishment is not a recent development as has been said here.  The last time it was anywhere near the full establishment was around the early forties during the time of the Emergency when there was a very large Army of which I was happy to be a member.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has stressed the importance of the Army Medical Corps.  Will he reply to the question asked about the status of a nurse within the Medical Corps?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTully" hpid="Mr. Tully Mr. Tully">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tully</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, During the Emergency we had, as we had before and since, people who were of all sorts of different political opinions serving the country faithfully.  Nobody could have been more opposed to the Government in power at that time than I was.  It did not stop me and thousands like me from joining the Army and doing what we considered to be the right thing.  I see an usher across the floor who was in the same company with me so there are a few of us still around.  While the Corps are actually short of their establishment, and this has been so for some time, they have been able to carry out their responsibilities, assisted where necessary by the employment on a full-time, part-time or free basis of civilian doctors, specialists and dentists.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It would be unreasonable to suggest that where there are small units established there should be all the medical <Col N="335" /> facilities which might be required.  The arrangements that exist mean that the people who are there have the right to avail of the same type of medical facilities from a local doctor, whether he is private or otherwise.  Those who are members of the FCA have exactly the same right as soldiers in places where there are Army medical officers available, so they are at no loss.</P>
    <P>I have been Minister for only six months or so and there are a lot of things to be looked at.  The decisions which my predecessors reached may be entirely different from the ones I will reach.  That does not mean I am right and they are wrong but this is one of the places where we may have to make a change.  While it is true that quite a number of areas are very well served by private medical doctors, it does not make sense that we should have private doctors when we could get Army doctors.</P>
    <P>There has been the question of competing for the services of those doctors. For some reason young doctors have not been keen to join the Army, possibly under a mistaken impression that it was not as well paid as outside service.  It is true, if we believe what we read, that there are quite a number of doctors who make very large amounts of money.  It is also true that there are young doctors who are just able to make a living.  In case it is not known by doctors who might consider joining the Army Medical Corps, I should like to emphasise that they can get credits for their service outside if they come into the corps.</P>
    <P>They all start at the level of captain and, after nine years, normally they become commandants.  There is a proposal that this should be reduced, and it probably will be reduced, perhaps not as much as the association want it reduced. With their captains' pay they get a service pay, a substantial amount of money.  If the House wishes I can give the details of the amounts which can be paid which show that they are entitled to very large amounts in addition to their ordinary pay.</P>
    <P>For instance, captains who come in on a minimum of £9,132, get £1,303 added <Col N="336" /> as professional pay, and a military service allowance of £544, making a total of £10,979.  For each year in rank they receive an increment and eventually, after six years, the ordinary line pay of captains is £10,040; the professional pay is an addition of £1,778, plus a military allowance service of £544 making a total of £12,362.  Apparently that is not generally understood.  If it is, I can see no reason why young doctors should not avail of the opportunity to serve in the Army.  I should like to see them joining the corps.</P>
    <P>Some of them have said that the pay and conditions are not attractive enough. Despite that, in the past few months we have taken in four, three of them ladies, and we are very glad to have them in the Army.  The number who resigned over the past few years is very small, since 1970 about three or four only.  The remainder of them have stayed.  A number have died and a number have left because they reached pensionable age.  I am not taking them into consideration.  I am talking about those who were dissatisfied and left, which is a different matter.</P>
    <P>It is true that the nurses are not officers, NCOs, or privates.  There is quite a big number of them.  We would have something like the Chinese Army if they were all officers.  It would be rather an embarrassment.  They can go up the line, and they are entitled to promotion.  The pressure to have them commissioned as officers is not very great.  As nurses they are in a different category.  Many of them would not want to be under Army discipline which they would be if they were officers.</P>
    <P>From my experience, the ladies in the nursing services have all the rights which an officer has.  They are treated, and rightly so, very much better than officers. They can tell the highest ranking officer to do something, and I do not think anybody else could try to do that and get away with it.  There are not many complaints. If there are, I should be glad to have them looked into to see if we can help.  At present there is a proposal that a number of them should be commissioned as officers, but it is not being pressed as hard as I thought it might be.</P>
    <Col N="337" />
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not concerned about whether Army nurses should be designated as officers, but they should have a rank rather than be treated as uniformed civilians as they are at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTully" hpid="Mr. Tully Mr. Tully">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tully</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a slight problem. They are recruited in the grade of sister. That is the equivalent of a staff nurse. They may be promoted to theatre sister, or staff sister, or assistant matron, or matron.  Their pay and conditions of service at all levels are generally the same as those of their counterparts in the health boards.  They might not be too anxious to get away from that.  I will have a look at it to see if it needs attention.  I do not think it is as urgent as has been suggested. As I said, we would like young doctors to come forward and join the corps but we must consider the question of supply and demand.</P>
      <P>The peacetime function of the corps is the preservation of the health and physical fitness of the Defence Forces.  This function is carried out by ensuring that the highest standards are laid down for admission to the Defence Forces.  I was very glad to hear Senator Fallon saying he agrees with me that we do not want people who are not of good character in the Army.  Literally we do not want them and we will not have them.  This has been the standard for quite some time and it will continue to be the standard.</P>
      <P>As I said, the preservation of the health and physical fitness of the Defence Forces is carried out by ensuring that the highest standards are laid down for admission to the Defence Forces, for advancement within the forces and for retention in service and, through a system of regular examination and grading, that these standards are adhered to.  In addition, the Medical Corps administers and staffs three military hospitals &mdash; St. Bricins in Dublin and the Curragh and Cork Hospitals. That these measures have been very successfully operated by the corps is self-evident.  Indeed, I would say that our standards widely displayed both at home and on overseas service are the envy of many.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The corps also provides an outpatient's <Col N="338" /> clinic on Saturday mornings for all pensioners under the Military Service Pensions Acts, 1924 and 1934, and disablement pensioners whose disability is due to services in the period 1916 to 1924. During 1981 over 350 pensioners were seen at this clinic.  Additionally, an Army medical officer acts as a member of the Army Pensions Board established under the Army Pensions Act, 1924.</P>
    <P>Another function of the corps is to provide a medical officer to act as President of the Civil Aviation Medical Board which medically examines applicants for the issue and renewal of civil aviation licences on behalf of the Department of Transport.  At present, up to 1,000 examinations are carried out annually by this board.</P>
    <P>It is my intention that the Medical Corps will continue to develop so that it will be fully capable of fulfilling its own very important role of ensuring that our Army is composed of personnel whose health and physical fitness are maintained in peak condition so that they will be able to undertake the many and varied demands made on them in these troubled times both at home and overseas.  This, to my mind, is the most important role of the Medical Corps at present and I think events have proved that it has been very successful in this respect.</P>
    <P>At present arrangements are in hands for the amendment of the Defence Forces Pensions Schemes to make certain improvements in the conditions for the grant of retired pay and gratuity to, among others, medical, dental and chemist officers of the Army Medical Corps.</P>
    <P>It is worthy of mention that members of the Medical Corps &mdash; including medical and dental officers &mdash; have the opportunity of service abroad with contingents of the Permanent Defence Forces serving with United Nations Peacekeeping Forces.  Two medical officers and one dental officer are currently serving with the Irish contingent in the Lebanon.  The experience gained during such service is a great asset to these officers on their return home.</P>
    <P>Medical officers are, when circumstances permit, released to attend courses of study leading to specialist qualifications. <Col N="339" /> At present two officers are attending such courses &mdash; one for three years and the second for four years.  Every effort is made to encourage the most highly qualified doctors to join the corps and special incremental credit is now given for higher qualifications and post registration experience.</P>
    <P>When we were in office before, an ambitious programme was embarked upon which has since produced highly efficient, well-equipped Defence Forces. Many improvements in organisation, pay rates, allowances, accommodation, equipment, clothing and conditions of service generally have taken place.  The Medical Corps, in common with all other elements of the Defence Forces, has benefited from these improvements.  As I stated recently in the other House in the course of a debate on the Supplementary Estimate for my Department, it is my aim as Minister for Defence to provide, in men and equipment, a modern well-trained Army capable of meeting the many demands made on them in these troubled times.  I can assure Senators that, in the achievement of this aim, the importance of the role being performed by the Medical Corps will not be overlooked.</P>
    <P>I should like to thank the Medical Corps for the way in which they have carried out their duties over the years.  Of course the people in the Medical Corps can get a substantial pension; when they retire they get a plus-pension as well as pay.  Incidentally, the actual number of the establishment is 70, not 72 and the current strength is 32.  I would be much happier were it much nearer its full strength, but that is the way it is.</P>
    <P>There is no statutory bar on overseas service by female medical officers.  The question of permitting women to serve overseas will be considered in the very near future.  Overall I think the Army and the Medical Corps do a very good job.  I quite appreciate that it was never the intention to cast any slur on the Medical Corps by putting down this motion. I thank those Senators who took part in the debate and those who introduced it, <Col N="340" /> because it is refreshing to hear people's views on these things.  If there is something I have said in my reply in respect of which Senator Fallon is not quite clear and if he will so indicate, I will reply to him by letter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Fallon has 15 minutes to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for the courtesy of a very fine reply.  He departed from his script on many occasions. he spoke very much from the heart.  Clearly he is a man who has a great interest in the Army and Army affairs generally.  Indeed, I did not comment on the great work done by the Army during our recent harsh weather.  I congratulate them and should like the Minister to express my appreciation to them.  On many occasions at functions held in Athlone I have had the pleasure of congratulating the Army on the great work they do on our behalf in so many areas overseas. That goes without saying and is deserving of our fullest praise.  I agree with the Minister when he says that many young men learn a lot when they go abroad.  As he said, they go out as young men and return fully mature, as it were, in every sense of the word.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>To revert to the motion, my main concern would be that there are not sufficient men joining the Army Medical Corps. The Minister has mentioned this fact on many occasions.  Senator O'Rourke stressed this concern also.  Young men are not joining the Medical Corps.  I understood there had been an embargo on recruitment since July last.  The Minister mentioned there had been a number of recruits recently to the Medical Corps. Accepting my error in the establishment figure of 72, which should be 70, the Minister said there were 32 whereas I had given a figure of 31.  I wondered if my figure is not more correct, because I understand there was one retirement on Friday last.  I make the point, and have been at pains to stress that while there are 31 or 32, there are 16 engaged in administration, two overseas, two at study level, four specialists and seven non-consultant, non-administrative personnel <Col N="341" /> endeavouring to cover the whole country.</P>
    <P>Senator Lanigan made a good point that in a factory employing, say, 350 there would be a medical attendant.  That is the number of personnel in the barracks in Kilkenny.  I agree with the Minister when he says that every little outpost should not have a medical attendant.  But thinking of Donegal, with four barracks, they should have at least one between them. Perhaps a barracks with 350 personnel should have one.  I do not agree with Senator Lanigan that the salary does not matter.  Salary is vital.  A young medical person today in private life will make £25,000 per annum whereas an Army medical man with the same qualifications will not make anything like that.  As the Minister outlined, the maximum he can earn is £11,000 or £12,000 per annum.</P>
    <P>Retirements will continue to represent a problem and over the next three years there will be eight or nine.  My information is that in 1982 there will be three, in 1983, two and in 1984, three retirements. Given the level of recruitment into the corps, the fact that 450 people qualify from medical schools every year, and we must strive to get between one and three, we will encounter severe difficulties in the future.  I understood that six young doctors resigned from the Irish Army between the years 1977 and 1981.  The Minister said the figure was four, but why should even four have to resign?  It is a reflection on our system that this should be allowed to happen.  Unless the whole scheme is rendered much more attractive in terms of salary, pensions, post-graduate training, widows' and orphans' allowances and so on, we will not attract young medical men into the Army in the numbers we would like.</P>
    <P>Let me stress again that the establishment figure is 70.  The Irish Medical Association give a figure of 100.  They have been critical generally of the role played by the Department of Defence <i>vis-á-vis</i> the Army Medical Corps.  I read in <i>The Irish Medical Times</i> that the Army would be content with a figure of 50, but we are not attracting anything like that figure.  My whole worry is that people are not joining the Army Medical Corps and <Col N="342" /> they will not do so unless we can offer better conditions overall.  Having seven or eight general practitioners &mdash; if one can call them such &mdash; endeavouring to cover the whole country must be seen as representing very nearly an unworkable system.  I am sorry to repeat it, but unless we offer much more attractive conditions in terms of salary and so on we will not attract in young men, we will not attract any of the 450 who qualify each year.  This would be a terrible pity and a reflection on us all.</P>
    <P>The purpose of putting down this motion was to highlight a problem.  I think the debate has been worthwhile.  I should like to think the Minister learned something from it and will go back to his Department and examine the whole system in order to ascertain how it can be improved.  If this debate has done nothing else but highlight the problem, I suppose something will have been achieved.  But, hopefully, the Department of Defence will see fit to remedy the situation obtaining. Then, perhaps, in two or three years' time my pessimism will be converted to utter optimism, something which would please me enormously and would constitute a good day's work on behalf of the Department and the Army generally.</P>
    <P>I thank the Minister and his officers for having attended and sincerely hope this debate has been a worthwhile exercise.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the motion withdrawn?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask the Minister one specific question with regard to the Army Medical Corps.  On the question of entry into the Army Medical Corps, as into the commissioned ranks, there is a stipulation that one must have a number of natural teeth opposing natural teeth. I wonder why that regulation is still relevant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTully" hpid="Mr. Tully Mr. Tully">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tully</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not aware that such a regulation existed.  I have all my natural teeth but I am sure I would not qualify. As I told the House, a number of regulations have been handed down in the <Col N="343" /> past 40 years that might do with some updating.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a fact that a person cannot get into the Army today unless he has a number of natural teeth opposing <Col N="344" /> natural teeth and that appears ludicrous to me.</P>
      <P>Motion, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 4.15 p.m. <i>sine die.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>