<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="27" Month="Apr" Year="2006" Vol="183" No="10" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 27 Aibreán 2006" DateEnglish="Thursday, 27 April 2006" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" LastSrc="2" cnum="761">
  <Col N="761"/><HtmlBk SectId="1" />
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar<?oasys _jy ?>10.30 a.m.</P>
    <Line />
    <P Italics="Y" Just="Center">Paidir.<br />
  Prayer.</P>
    <Line />
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I have received notice from Senator Tuffy that on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government to provide information (details supplied) on social and affordable housing.</P>
      <P FLI="0">I regard the matter raised as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and it will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Order of Business is No. 1, Registration of Deeds and Title Bill 2004 [<i>Seanad Bill amended by the D&aacute;il</i>] &mdash; Report and Final Stages, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business and to conclude not later than 1 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>As we all know, we are in the run-up to a general election in the next 12 months or so. In that context, it is vital that the electoral register is accurate and up to date and that those who should be on it are on it. There is considerable public concern that, as the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government said, there are at least 300,000 additional persons on the register this year than there are people entitled to vote. Some people have suggested the inaccuracy is close to 500,000.</P>
      <P>It is unacceptable that so close to a general election this kind of electoral register inaccuracy exists. We must deal with the issue and make a number of changes. We should introduce a system whereby people are registered when they get their PPS number and local authorities must take more concrete action in the compilation of the registers. Also, we have new residential communities in areas such as west Dublin where 4,000 to 5,000 houses were built in the past five years, but no polling stations are provided for the <Col N="762"/>people there, despite the best efforts of local authorities to demand polling stations from the county sheriffs and returning officers.</P>
      <P>On 29 March I wrote a letter to the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government proposing a simple legislative change in this area, but I still await a reply. The issue is urgent. Will the Leader arrange a debate where we can hear what the Minister wants to do about this urgent matter?</P>
      <P>Given the position taken by the junior partner in Government last weekend that electronic voting should be abandoned, is that the collective view of the Government? Is this not the time to deal with the issue and state clearly that there will not be e-voting at the next general election?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Mr. O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>When the Abattoirs Bill was going through the House approximately 15 years ago, some Members pointed out the difficulties it would create for local butchers and industry and we have discussed the subsequent problems many times. On several occasions over the years I have heard the Leader talk about the difficulties created for the development of home industry which is destroyed by an overly strict interpretation of European regulations.</P>
      <P>We are now about to do the same again. European regulation 854/2004 will create havoc for small supermarkets and butchers. Whereas throughout our lives we have seen local butcher shops provide steak and meat to local hotels, we now have a situation where the regulation will require the butchers to register as wholesalers as opposed to retailers. This will result in a whole new set of regulations, thereby doubling up on the regulations with which retailers must currently comply. The regulation will also require veterinary and health officers to examine each business to ensure the butchers are within the regulations. This will create havoc around the country.</P>
      <P>The interpretation the Government is taking has not been taken in other countries, particularly not in the UK. I do not want to go into the details but will give a simple example of the outcome. Around the Border areas butchers will be in competition with their colleagues. On this side of the Border, butchers who sell more than 500 kg of meat over a certain period to a local hotel or business will have to register as wholesalers putting them in competition with people from the other side of the Border who can sell up to 2,000 kg.</P>
      <P>This regulation means we are going to over-regulate once again, put small industries out of business unnecessarily and create hardship and difficulty. This is a matter for the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Health and Children and I want her to come to the House to discuss it. The T&aacute;naiste has shown herself to be practical on issues such as this and I do not believe she would want the regulation to go ahead. I understand she has been pushed into it by the Food Safety Authority of Ireland, but we should review it and ensure that <Col N="763"/>Irish butchers and meat outlets are not under a more difficult regime or regulations than their colleagues in the UK. We should adopt the same approach throughout the island in accordance with the Good Friday Agreement. We should ask the T&aacute;naiste to address the issue.</P>
      <P>Yesterday, Senators referred to the importance of St. Michael&rsquo;s CBS, Inchicore, which is located in a highly-underprivileged area. I did not intervene in the debate because I wished to check something. I believe the Christian Brothers are closing the operation because the school is situated on two acres of prime development land. We are walking away from a highly-underprivileged, disadvantaged community for the sake of a small investment. We should discuss this. The Minister for Education and Science must abide by decisions of the management and school authorities, who seem determined to close the school, but she should support the appointment of an additional staff member. This is one of the most underprivileged areas, a fact I have been aware of for many years. The school has done Trojan work despite difficulties and opposition. It deserves our support.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMinihan"><NameTxt>Mr. Minihan</NameTxt>
	<P>I join with Senator Brian Hayes in highlighting the issue of the electoral register. Democracy and our system of voting begins with an accurate register. Those of us who stand for elections are conscious of results and have seen how seats have been won by a margin of a couple of votes. Considered alongside the inaccurate figures on our register, the principle of democracy and elections is called into question. Regardless of whether the method of voting is electronic or manual, the starting point is the register. I encourage the Leader to invite the Minister to the House to debate this issue. We can then see what action is being taken to ensure an accurate, honest register is presented to the people so that the general election can be held in a fair manner. It is too easy to have misrepresentation and we should not facilitate it by failing to ensure a proper register.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinucane"><NameTxt>Mr. Finucane</NameTxt>
	<P>I listened with great interest to the debate on the electoral register in the other House. The latest register contains many inaccuracies, including the names of people who are deceased. Currently, voting papers are franked before voting and may subsequently be declared invalid because they were not properly franked. Returning officers should take an interest in this. Research should be done to determine the polling booths in which these errors are made. Having been the subject of a close vote, I know that candidates become conscious of all these issues. I was in favour of electronic voting because of the serious deficiencies in the existing system but that debate is over.</P>
      <P>I refer to an issue on which the media have focused, which is very important for the telecom<Col N="764"/>munications industry, namely, the bid for Eircom by Babcock &amp; Brown. Eircom will have had four owners in seven years if this bid is successful. Its turnover last year was &euro;1.6 billion and it made profits of &euro;160 million. The assets and capital infrastructure of this country have been sweated to facilitate venture capitalists making big money. In that context I urge the Government not to accede to Babcock &amp; Brown&rsquo;s request for a commitment that it will not be pressurised into unbundling the local loop.</P>
      <P>Telecommunications is in a mess at present. ComReg is at loggerheads with a telecommunications company, various companies have initiated litigation and we have a dismal record in provision of broadband. In that context, the concessions sought by Babcock &amp; Brown may be unpalatable for the industry and I urge the Government to examine this. The Minister should come to this House to discuss telecommunications.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn"><NameTxt>Mr. Glynn</NameTxt>
	<P>The debate on the electoral register takes place regularly. The current system is a failure. I have come across many people who did not wish to be on the electoral register. If this is not an offence, it should be because registering to vote and voting should be mandatory. How people cast their vote is up to them.</P>
      <P>In order to correct the system, we should have all-party agreement to defer the general election for a year. We might have as much chance of getting agreement on that as we have had to date on correcting the electoral register.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Glynn might find that difficult.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>We will not defer it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMinihan"><NameTxt>Mr. Minihan</NameTxt>
	<P>The polls must be good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinucane"><NameTxt>Mr. Finucane</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader&rsquo;s star sign is looking good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>An horrific case of someone charged, found guilty of rape and sentenced was reported yesterday. The body that employed the person had been unable to verify references of potential employees with the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na. Two years ago I referred to the opportunity to provide this information to those involved in child care and general businesses. This requires investment but it is a business opportunity to provide a service for which businesses would pay.</P>
      <P>This service is provided by 300 people working in the police force in Scotland. In Ireland we have allocated 30 people to this function. An investment in technology is also required and any employer should be able to access information on a potential employee&rsquo;s records before taking somebody on. This business opportunity for the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na would benefit the community as a whole.</P><Col N="765"/>
      <P>I urge the Leader to arrange a debate on nuclear energy. Today a British Government body will announce plans to bury the nuclear waste of the past 60 years in Britain, some 470,000 cu. m. of nuclear waste. It is currently stored in 500 temporary underground sites. The former president of an Irish university stated that we should not close our minds to the option of nuclear energy. The Leader has stated that we do not wish this to occur but we should consider the implications. I seek a debate on nuclear energy to hear both sides of the story.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Mr. Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Nothing concentrates the minds of voters and candidates like the electoral register. It is appropriate that we have a debate now rather than when the election is under way and people are busy canvassing. The census, held on 23 April, is the best possible record of every voter in Ireland.</P>
      <P>In the past, when finance officers collected the rates, they were also the best people for collecting names as well. However, that day is gone. I am not sure about the confidentiality issue. Commitments were given that the census would be confidential but surely the names, addresses and location could be used.</P>
      <P>The Minister should also outline the regulations for the register of electors with regard to prisoners. Mountjoy Prison has a high prison population which could affect the outcome of the election in Dublin if all the prisoners voted in the Dublin Central constituency. That is also true of Roscommon, which is the location of Castlerea Prison. It is important the Minister outlines what rules will apply to prisoners, who have a constitutional right to cast their vote by post, and whether they should cast their vote in the location where they are resident or in their home constituency where they were resident before being imprisoned. We should have a debate on this as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I support Senator Brian Hayes&rsquo;s comments with regard to the electoral register, fraud and so forth. The Minister said recently that there are approximately 300,000 inaccuracies in the register. That has the potential to affect a significant number of seats. It is a basic requirement of presiding officers to ensure that ballots are franked. Sadly, in too many parts of the country unstamped ballots were given to genuine voters. Perhaps polling clerks were not paying enough attention in some instances. However, it is such an essential element of their function that where there were breaches of that regulation on the part of presiding officers, steps should be taken to ensure they are not reappointed. Perhaps in the past some of them were doddering or did it deliberately but it is a basic requirement and they should not be reappointed.</P>
      <P>The Official Languages Act contains the daft proposal, to which Senator O&rsquo;Toole and I have referred previously, that all documents be trans<Col N="766"/>lated into Irish, regardless of whether it is necessary. It is mandatory under the Act, of course, and we must respect that. All of us are interested in the promotion of the Irish language but we know these documents are not requested and are being dumped. The point was made previously that these could be provided on disk or whatever when requested rather than go through the unnecessary and wasteful expenditure of having everything printed, merely to be dumped. It is a national scandal. If the Government wishes, it is something Senator O&rsquo;Toole and I can rectify in our Official Languages (Amendment) Bill which is on the Order Paper. We will await word in that regard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We will not debate it now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I will not debate it. You understand that I would never do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not know whether I do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">You do, a Chathaoirligh, you are a wise old owl. Everybody knows that individual councils are spending anything from &euro;70,000 to &euro;100,000 annually and this is a significant extra imposition on their budgets. One councillor said to me last week that given that this is mandatory, it should be opened up to the local Conradh na Gaeilge groups. It would be a way of funding good, well meaning local groups that are actively promoting the language.</P>
      <P>There are 24 Bills before the Houses of the Oireachtas at present. How many are Seanad Bills on the D&aacute;il Order Paper and what progress will be made on them before the summer recess?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonScanlon"><NameTxt>Mr. Scanlon</NameTxt>
	<P>I support Senator O&rsquo;Toole&rsquo;s request for a reasoned debate on the regulations being introduced that will affect small butchers throughout the country. A number of years ago small abattoirs were regulated out of business and that is now seen as a serious mistake. They had to compete against heavily subsidised meat exporting plants which were supposed to be exporting meat but which are now selling meat on the home market. They just could not compete; one cannot compete against a business that is being heavily subsidised. We must be careful and I welcome the call for a reasonable debate. We must be seen to support small local butchers. If we continue as we are, we will simply regulate them out of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoannaTuffy"><NameTxt>Ms Tuffy</NameTxt>
	<P>I support calls for a debate on improving the electoral register. One issue which must be discussed in that debate is the position of people who have permission to remain in the State but who are not Irish citizens. They had a vote in the last local elections but they will not have a vote in general elections unless they secure citizenship. Some of them are in this country many years. They work and pay taxes here and <Col N="767"/>their children go to school here. They will possibly be in this country for the rest of their lives.</P>
      <P>It is important that we address either the issue of them acquiring citizenship on time or allowing them to vote in general elections. It takes a long time to acquire citizenship. Many people have been in this country far longer than the period of time that is required to apply for citizenship and those who do not have citizenship are left in a limbo. They should have a right to vote and this will be an important part of any debate we might have about improving the electoral register.</P>
      <P>I support the idea of the Minister for Communications, Marine and Natural Resources, Deputy Noel Dempsey, on the GPO being used as a museum to commemorate 1916. Senator White spoke about the importance of history. It is important for everybody, which is why we held celebrations on the 90th anniversary of the 1916 Rising. However, it should be recorded that James Connolly founded the Labour Party and was a member of that party when he was executed in 1916. There was no mention of that in the material produced&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That was discussed yesterday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoannaTuffy"><NameTxt>Ms Tuffy</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;for the 90th anniversary, including on the Taoiseach&rsquo;s website.</P>
      <P>Before the summer recess we should hold a debate on local government, particularly the rights and powers of councillors. Another issue is the pension rights of councillors. I and other Senators attended the LAMA conference last week which debated councillors&rsquo; entitlement to pensions. I support them on that issue. There should be a debate on this issue and on the role of councillors and local government. Most Members of this House are elected by councillors and we must maintain that connection. We are no longer allowed to be councillors as well, so we must keep up the special relationship the Seanad has with councillors and ensure we raise their issues in this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMauriceHayes"><NameTxt>Dr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>With regard to the point raised by Senator Coghlan about the production of reports in the Irish language, could we extend the debate to include the production of many of the reports in the English language? It would ease my recycling bill if those reports were made available electronically and could be supplied on demand. I also support Senator O&rsquo;Toole with regard to the harmonisation of regulatory powers across the Border. That is an important function for the North-South bodies and should be carried out by them.</P>
      <P>Does the Leader intend to schedule a debate on Europe on the occasion of Europe day next week? In that context, I intend to provide a report on the recent activities of the forum to the Taoiseach towards the end of next week. We <Col N="768"/>have made arrangements for it to be available to Members of the Oireachtas on the Monday of the following week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="UlickBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. U. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I support the call for a debate on voting procedures and the electoral register. I recall that during or immediately after the last general election, at a polling station in south Galway, 40 valid voting papers were declared invalid. I inquired into this because a large number of votes for me, which I considered to be valid, were declared invalid. It would not have made any difference to the outcome.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">11 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P>We encourage people to vote and complain when a high percentage do not do so.  However, there can be inefficiency either through a deliberate or mistaken attempt by a presiding officer to invalidate a vote. There is something seriously wrong when one reports that to a returning officer who may dismiss it out of hand and reappoint the same presiding officer for the following election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="UlickBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. U. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>It is not just a situation concerning the electoral register. The whole appointments procedure for presiding officers and clerks should be scrutinised more carefully than has been the case heretofore.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Absolutely.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="UlickBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. U. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>We cannot legitimately complain about people&rsquo;s lack of determination to vote when, in such instances, one sees a high percentage of votes invalidated through that mechanism. The Minister should attend the House for a debate to review the entire voting procedure, not to mind the question of electronic voting. I shudder to think what would have happened if some of those traditional presiding officers had been in charge of electronic voting without proper training. That area needs to be reviewed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">We will debate the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="UlickBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. U. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I hope we will have such a debate soon.</P>
      <P>I ask the Leader to request the Minister for Education and Science to review her determination to publish school evaluations on her Department&rsquo;s website against the wishes of the teachers&rsquo; unions. In order to maintain goodwill with the teachers, the Minister must carry out further consultations on this matter. Following their recent conferences, some of the teachers&rsquo; unions clearly indicated they wanted further consultations. There is little disagreement between the Minister and the unions over her proposals, provided there is more consultation to resolve the outstanding points. It all boils down to the continuing endeavours by certain sections of the media to publish league tables. If we take that route, people within the education system will <Col N="769"/>become demoralised. If we can afford to do that in the current situation, things will have reached a very low ebb.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGerardHanafin"><NameTxt>Mr. Hanafin</NameTxt>
	<P>I join in the calls for a debate on the nuclear industry. Yesterday marked the 20th anniversary of the Chernobyl incident, which answered the question concerning the probability of the impossible occurring. We were told such an event was impossible, yet it happened. Whether we like it or not, we live in a nuclear zone. We should bear in mind the fact that Dublin is a lot nearer to some of the nuclear facilities in England than Portsmouth,<?oasys _jy ?>Southampton or London.</P>
      <P>I am raising this point in light of the recent RTE programme entitled &ldquo;Fallout&rdquo;. Whether one considers the programme to be good or bad, and however it was presented, the reality is still there. As I understand it, caesium is carried by clouds. During the recent G8 summit in St. Petersburg, clouds were sprayed before reaching the city to ensure that rain did not fall on the area. I am not suggesting that contaminated clouds should rain on the Isle of Man but God forbid that something unforeseen should happen at Sellafield. The facility&rsquo;s name was changed from Windscale some years ago for public relations reasons. Should anything untoward happen at Sellafield, however, it would be a good idea for our Air Corps to be able to spray the clouds before they reach our shores, thereby protecting the population.</P>
      <P>I share in the call for a debate on the electoral register. We have focused this morning on getting people onto the register who are not listed but there are others already on the register whose names should be removed. As a Member of the Oireachtas, I had reason recently to send out a large number of letters in the Dublin area. Many of these were returned to me, so I forwarded them to the franchise section of Dublin City Council. As a result, many of those people were taken off the register on the basis that An Post could confirm they were not living there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator White had got to them first.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGerardHanafin"><NameTxt>Mr. Hanafin</NameTxt>
	<P>Is it not time for us to ask some public bodies to think outside the box? They could contact the direct-mail companies which are getting letters back stating there is nobody of that name at an address. Such a list could be used to remove people&rsquo;s names from the electoral register.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Last night, I tabled a matter on the Adjournment about the flight which was recently diverted from Paris to Prestwick.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That matter was discussed last night, so I do not think we can repeat it now.</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="770"/>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P>Arising from that worthwhile Adjournment matter and the Minister&rsquo;s frank reply, will the Leader contact the Office of the Taoiseach to ask if he was aware of the flight being diverted? Last night, the Minister told the House that the flight was diverted to Prestwick Airport when, in fact, there were other airports nearby. This incident concerned a bomb scare on the plane.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Ryanair one?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Yes, it was a Ryanair flight. There was a subsequent incident involving an Aer Arann flight. If British citizens had been aboard the flight would they have been treated in the same way? Those passengers were left for two hours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator raised all those points last night. We cannot have a repetition of that debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">They were left for two hours on the aeroplane after landing and were not allowed to disembark.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator got an answer last night. What is the purpose of raising matters on the Adjournment if Senators can raise them here again the following morning?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P>This matter arises from the Adjournment debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Should we forget about matters on the Adjournment altogether?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P>No. My point follows on from the explanation that was given last night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not think we should discuss what was said last night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P>We should do so at a higher level.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is the Senator seeking another debate?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P>I have made my point and will finish with it now.</P>
      <P Just="Left">I ask the Leader to arrange an urgent debate on yesterday&rsquo;s decision by the Minister for Transport, Deputy Cullen, on provisional driving licences. I am not sure if the decision has yet been finalised. Apparently, there are over 400,000 such licences, which cover almost one fifth of all licensed drivers. The Minister is planning to forbid people who fail the driving test to drive again prior to resitting the test.</P>
      <P>A case was illustrated on the radio earlier today concerning a lady who arrived at Rathgar for a driving test and crashed into the wall of the driving test centre. She then failed her test and drove home. None of us could condone such <Col N="771"/>behaviour. An urgent debate is required in this regard.</P>
      <P Just="Left">It is unfair, however, to think that people who fail the driving test could be banned from driving for a year or more while awaiting another test. Some 4,000 applications were made recently for contract driving tester positions, yet none has been appointed to date. It is a major problem on which we should have a full debate. There is no point in solving one problem while creating an even bigger problem through the Minister&rsquo;s proposals.</P>
      <P>The issue of lapsed drivers has also arisen in this context. According to a radio report this morning, a 78 year old lady who had been driving for 50 years&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator can raise all those points in the debate he is seeking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P>We need to examine that sector and perhaps an exception could be made for such people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>It is understandable that a body such as the Institute of Industrial Engineers would like to reopen a debate on nuclear energy. However, I am sure all of us remember being warned that the lights would go out in or around 1985 and, therefore, this matter will be treated with a great deal of scepticism. A debate on the subject would be useful in order to set out certain realities. There is not a constituency in the country that would be willing to house a nuclear waste dump or a nuclear power station and people who are re-engaging in this debate should realise this fact.</P>
      <P>We have not always been good at looking after our heritage. I hope, however, that the authorities concerned will think seriously about the preservation of the house or houses on Moore Street to which those engaged in the GPO in 1916 fell back and from which they issued to surrender. This is particularly relevant at this time of year.</P>
      <P>I wish to reassure Senator Tuffy that our founder &Eacute;amon de Valera&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I think that is&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>I want to say only one sentence&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinucane"><NameTxt>Mr. Finucane</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator is being controversial.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>I am saying nothing controversial.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinucane"><NameTxt>Mr. Finucane</NameTxt>
	<P>It is very unfair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="UlickBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. U. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should remember what happened to Senator White.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We have discussed this&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="772"/>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>We did not have a debate. There was a demand in the House for a debate on 1916 but we never held it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinucane"><NameTxt>Mr. Finucane</NameTxt>
	<P>We have had enough of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>Mr. de Valera said that James Connolly was the person to whom he felt closest among the leaders of 1916 and Connolly was very close to Countess Markievicz, who went on to become a founding member of our party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator is quoting again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>I was very glad to see the deputy leader of the Labour Party dressed up as Countess Markievicz recently.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">
        
        Too many history lessons have been given on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="UlickBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. U. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should remember what happened to Senator White.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMinihan"><NameTxt>Mr. Minihan</NameTxt>
	<P>The Mullingar accord is gone again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu"><NameTxt>Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</NameTxt>
	<P>We should have ongoing debates on nuclear energy because I have noticed recently that the big powers are orchestrating this issue. On several occasions, including Prime Minister Blair&rsquo;s visit to Australia, this was choreographed. We need to be particularly vigilant. We have been reminded, through the generosity of the Irish people who continue to respond to the tragedy in Chernobyl, of what can happen when nuclear energy goes wrong.</P>
      <P Just="Left">
        
        An heroic woman, Adi Roche, received the Pearse Award last night for her work in Chernobyl. Someone like her is a constant reminder to us of the terrible dangers that exist in nuclear energy. Small nations should not allow themselves to be undermined by the orchestrated approach of world leaders.</P>
      <P>It would be helpful to invite the Minister for Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs to the House to discuss the Official Languages Act on an ongoing basis. It is a multifaceted Act which places specific requirements on over 700 agencies. One of these requirements is that they draw up a programme which will be submitted here for discussion in the Houses.</P>
      <P>I have seen news reports about some agencies which have completed that work. In that context, any relevant issue, including translation must be considered. Prior to the enactment of that legislation several legal judgments were handed down, including by the Supreme Court, on the rights of citizens to have access to documents when they are brought before the courts.</P>
      <P>I understood that this Act was intended to harmonise several Acts which already existed. Ongoing and updated reports on this by the Minister and others would be helpful.</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="773"/>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Brian Hayes spoke about the errors in the electoral register. There was a debate on that matter yesterday in the other House. We will seek to bring the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, Deputy Roche, into the House. There are serious inaccuracies in the register, not just regarding people who are no longer here, or have moved, remaining on the register. More important is that large numbers are not on the register.</P>
      <P Just="Left">I spent one week over the Easter break in Kinnegad, and one in Rochfortbridge, and found over 300 people who are not on the register. They are new to their areas and had never been put on the register, or did not know how to go about being put on the register. I submitted their names to the fine woman in charge of this in Westmeath County Council. She will call a meeting of all the parties to discuss ideas on how to deal with this problem.</P>
      <P>We may talk about democracy but if one is not on the register one cannot vote. Then the people blame us when we call on their houses. I will be there on a second occasion, when the new register comes out, and maybe a third time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMinihan"><NameTxt>Mr. Minihan</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader should make three visits.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator also mentioned the lack of polling stations and e-voting. He wants a debate on the electoral register, as do we all.</P>
      <P>Senator O&rsquo;Toole mentioned the Abattoirs Bill, which we recall, and the new EU directive which will work against small butchers and leave them open to too much competition with butchers over the Border. Generally speaking it imposes more onerous regulations on small butchers who find it difficult enough to manage.</P>
      <P>The Senator also raised the question of St. Michael&rsquo;s national school in Inchicore and the fine land around it which will be sold for development. This does not harmonise with the purpose of the school, namely, helping disadvantaged young people. The Minister for Education and Science is emphatic about seeking to retain a school there.</P>
      <P>Senator Minihan said we want a debate on the electoral register. Senator Finucane spoke about the non-franking of ballot papers because it is upsetting to be gathered around the table for a count and hear votes deemed invalid simply because they have missed the franking machine. The Senator knows more than anyone how upsetting that is, having lost out by such a small margin in the last election. I do not understand why this happens. Every paper given to a voter should be franked.</P>
      <P>Senator Finucane also referred to Eircom, Babcock &amp; Brown and the unbundling of the local loop. That was covered by an EU directive approximately eight years ago which has not yet <Col N="774"/>been implemented. I do not understand why. Eircom will not do it for proprietorial purposes.</P>
      <P>Senator Glynn said it should be mandatory for a person to be registered and to vote. I note the edict from Mullingar to defer the general election. There is an edict from Athlone which says &ldquo;No&rdquo; to that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>The lines are drawn, and not in the sand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn"><NameTxt>Mr. Glynn</NameTxt>
	<P>I made the comment with more hope than conviction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Quinn said how difficult it is for employers to get information on an employee and we heard about the sad case he mentioned. The Senator thought the Garda should use technology to get the facts on a particular person. He also said that the nuclear waste from Sellafield is being buried in 500 sites and is familiar with Dr. Ed Walsh&rsquo;s report, which I too saw.</P>
      <P>I said yesterday that there is an orchestrated attempt to make nuclear energy nice and present it in a favourable light. This will come into a debate but on behalf of the Government I can say we do not intend to promote nuclear energy as a policy. I am not rebuking the Senator. He is right to say we should discuss it but we do not intend to make it a policy.</P>
      <P Just="Left">Senator Leyden is worried about the prisoners in Roscommon getting their votes, which is correct, as that is now the law. He spoke about the census collectors. There is some legal difficulty on that point. It is correct that everybody should be enumerated wherever they should be, which is useful.</P>
      <P>Senator Coghlan also mentioned the franking of the ballot papers. He and Senator O&rsquo;Toole are very involved in the Official Languages Act and the translation of all the documents into Irish which are then dumped.</P>
      <P>The Senator asked me about Bills. I do not have the precise information other than to say that 147 Bills have been published since the Government came to office almost four years ago, and 58 of those were Seanad Bills. I realise that is not the information the Senator requested but I will endeavour to get the required information. I did not have time to do so this morning.</P>
      <P>Senator Scanlon supported Senator O&rsquo;Toole&rsquo;s point about the over-regulation of small butchers. We can always rely on the Senator&rsquo;s voice to be the voice of sanity for small businesses in rural Ireland.</P>
      <P>On the matter raised by Senator Tuffy, the Senator&rsquo;s colleague raised the matter of James Connolly yesterday and the Labour Party being the oldest party in Ireland, which it is, but his gripe was that the Taoiseach&rsquo;s website did not mention James Connolly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoannaTuffy"><NameTxt>Ms Tuffy</NameTxt>
	<P>It is my gripe as well.</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="775"/>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I said we might have a joint Labour Party-Fianna F&aacute;il website quite soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>Which upset the Leader&rsquo;s colleagues on the other side of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMinihan"><NameTxt>Mr. Minihan</NameTxt>
	<P>It upset Fine Gael terribly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoannaTuffy"><NameTxt>Ms Tuffy</NameTxt>
	<P>In the tradition of Connolly we want to provide an alternative to the right-wing Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We will not have a debate on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Tuffy also raised the burning issue of pensions for councillors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>A Senator</NameTxt>
	<P>Very much so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator also raised the question of citizenship and the vote. Deputy Bruton spoke on that also. One cannot vote until one becomes a citizen but I agree with the Senator. I constantly meet people who say they would like the vote but they cannot get it. It is a question of whether we should give status to the asylum seekers first and then the vote will follow. We will wait and see how the other matter progresses.</P>
      <P>Senator Maurice Hayes would have regard to all reports. We are getting far too many but we look forward to his report on Europe. We are planning debates here on Europe day. Will the Senator&rsquo;s report be out by then?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMauriceHayes"><NameTxt>Dr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>It will be out on the Monday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>We have to get <i>dramatis personae</i> first but we will see how we do on that.</P>
      <P>Senator Ulick Burke raised the issue of the electoral register and 40 papers being invalid. His point was that the returning officer should demonstrate a concern about such a matter and check up on it. He wondered about the appointment procedures for presiding officers. We all know how that happens, it is chaotic.</P>
      <P>The Minister has consulted on the question of whole school evaluation but she is willing to have further consultations, which is the point raised by Senator Burke. I have spoken to very sensible teachers about this matter and there is a fear of pinpointing particular teachers without having to name them but the Minister has gone very far with the consultations and I am sure she will have more.</P>
      <P>Senator Hanafin called for a debate on nuclear energy. He made an interesting point about the electoral register and letters being returned but it would not be satisfactory to remove people from the register just because letters were returned with &ldquo;Not known at this address&rdquo; written on them. That would not be the correct procedure. People are very squiffy about being removed <Col N="776"/>from the register if they are still around. I do not believe one could&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Allegedly, 300,000 of them were not around.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Browne spoke about a diverted flight but the Cathaoirleach has ruled that he got an answer to that question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Italics="Y">(Interruptions).</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>He also called for a debate on driving licences.</P>
      <P>Senator Mansergh raised the question of nuclear energy. Of course we will debate it but we do not want it. He also referred to the Moore Street houses and our heritage. He referred to the Labour Party but we dealt with that yesterday.</P>
      <P>Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; spoke about the ongoing debate on nuclear energy and he praised Adi Roche. We all admire her humanity and I am glad she got the Pearse award. He also called for a debate on the Official Languages Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Registration of Deeds and Title Bill 2004:" RHead="Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Registration of Deeds and Title Bill 2004 <?oasys _cf1- ?>[<?oasys _cf2- ?>Seanad Bill amended by the D&aacute;il<?oasys _cf1- ?>]<?oasys _cf3- ?>: Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>This is a Seanad Bill which has been amended by the D&aacute;il. In accordance with Standing Order 103, it is deemed to have passed its First, Second and Third Stages in the Seanad and is placed on the Order Paper for Report Stage. On the question &ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;, the Minister may explain the purpose of the amendments made by the D&aacute;il. This is looked upon as the report of the D&aacute;il amendments to the Seanad. For Senators&rsquo; convenience, I have arranged for the printing and circulation of the amendments. The Minister will deal separately with the subject matter of each related group of amendments. I have also circulated the proposed groupings of the subject matter of amendments. A Senator may contribute once on each grouping. I remind Senators that the only matters that may be discussed are the amendments made by the D&aacute;il and the amendments in the grouping. Group 1 deals with ground rents, the subject matter of amendments Nos. 1 to 5, inclusive, 51 and 52. I call the Minister to explain the amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><TitleTxt>Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>This group of amendments is related to the insertion of two new sections relating to ground rents in the Bill. They are <Col N="777"/>amendments Nos. 51 and 52. The purpose of these new sections is to deal with problems that have arisen under current ground rents legislation.</P>
      <P Just="Left">By way of background, I should tell the House that section 8 of the Landlord and Tenant (Ground Rents)(No. 2) Act of 1978 contains the general right to acquire the fee simple. Section 9 provides that this general right to acquire the fee simple applies to a person holding the land under a lease provided that the conditions set out in that section, section 9, and one of seven alternative conditions in section 10 is met. The seven alternative conditions in section 10 cover a broad range of situations. Section 16 of the 1978 (No. 2) Act, on the other hand, contains various specific restrictions where the right to acquire the fee simple does not apply.</P>
      <P Just="Left">Amendment No. 51 will add a new category to the restricted list in section 16. It will prohibit the acquisition of the fee simple, that is, the purchase of the ground rent, in a case of the sub-lease of land granted by a lessee who is not eligible to acquire the fee simple. In other words, if someone holds land under a long lease and is not entitled to acquire the fee simple, he or she cannot, simply by creating a dummy company and giving it a lease of the land on conditions that do comply with the Act, effectively give to the dummy company the right to do something he or she cannot do. This will ensure that an eligible sub-lease cannot in future be carved out of a non-eligible lease in a manner that was neither intended nor foreseen by the 1978 (No. 2) Act.</P>
      <P>One exception is being allowed and that arises in the case where the only reason a lessee is not eligible to acquire the fee simple is that a covenant entered into by that lessee to erect permanent buildings on the land has not been substantially complied with on the date on which the sub-lease is granted but the covenant is substantially complied with by the sub-lessee after that date. This exception to the general prohibition has been recommended by the Law Reform Commission.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 52 amends section 28 of the same Act. It also stems from a recommendation of the Law Reform Commission. The commission has identified an anomaly within existing law where, on acquisition of the fee simple, not only covenants within the lease under which the land was held, say, for certain specified covenants, but also collateral covenants are extinguished. The new text of subsection (1) contained in this amendment makes it clear that only covenants in the lease under which the person held the land, save for the specified covenants, will be extinguished on the acquisition of the fee simple. It also provides that new covenants may be entered into with the agreement of the person acquiring the fee simple. Both of these amendments take effect from 27 February last, that is, the date on which I circulated the text of the amendments and issued a press release indicating my intention to deal with the problem that has arisen. This back<Col N="778"/>dating was vital because if I had signalled that I intended to halt people&rsquo;s right to create sub-leases, get around the groundsman&rsquo;s legislation and not specify a date from which this new closing off of the loophole would operate, people would have rushed to their solicitors in the last few weeks to create all these leases.</P>
      <P>Any time lag in giving effect to them would have afforded an opportunity to those who could profit from these weaknesses in the current legislation to take advantage of them prior to the enactment of this legislation. As these new sections to the landlord and tenant code relate to it, it has been necessary to amend the Long Title to exclude those sections in the collective citation and commencement provisions of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>We agree with these amendments because they are sensible and plug the loopholes in the legislation. We agree that backdating is necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Group 2 consists of amendments Nos. 6 to 13, inclusive; Nos. 16 to 19, inclusive; Nos. 21 to 24, inclusive; Nos. 26 to 29, inclusive; Nos. 32 to 34, inclusive; Nos. 43, 45, 46, 47 and 48; and Nos. 54 to 57, inclusive. I call on the Minister to explain the amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>These amendments are drafting and technical amendments which should not bother the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Group 3 deals with membership of the property registration authority, the subject matter of amendments Nos. 14 and 15. I call on the Minister to explain the amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>These two amendments relate to section 11 of the Bill, which deals with membership of the authority. During discussions in the D&aacute;il, I accepted a proposal to delete the subsection which provided that a member of the authority could only serve two terms of office. The argument that this could lead to the loss of expertise in the authority was well made and I had no difficulty in accepting this proposal.</P>
      <P Just="Left">I proposed an amendment to subsection (13) &mdash;<Insert> now</Insert> subsection (12) &mdash; which sets out the grounds under which a person ceases to be a member of the authority. The amendment introduces two new grounds, namely, conviction of an offence involving fraud or dishonesty and disqualification from being a director of a company.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>We agree with these amendments. The Minister took on board a number of sensible suggestions made in the other House, for which I applaud him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyKett"><NameTxt>Mr. Kett</NameTxt>
	<P>I agree with the sentiments expressed by Senator Cummins. The Minister&rsquo;s actions in this regard are very sensible because an element of flexibility is required in respect of membership of the authority. The authority could contain <Col N="779"/>some very capable members, which one would like to retain, as well as some dead wood. Flexibility is needed in this regard. However, I wonder whether it will be possible to find someone who is prepared to put in six or more years of service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>We will see.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Group 4 deals with the Comptroller and Auditor General (Amendment) Act 1993, the subject matter of amendment No. 20. I call on the Minister to explain the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>This amendment inserts a new section into the Bill which relates to the Comptroller and Auditor General (Amendment) Act 1993. The purpose of the amendment is to ensure that the 1993 Act applies to the property registration authority as if it were a Department. The need arises because the authority will have its own Vote, as the Land Registry and registry of deeds currently have. The chief executive will be the Accounting Officer under section 23 of the Bill. A similar provision was inserted into the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act to come into effect when the Garda Commissioner becomes the Accounting Officer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Group 5 deals with terms of leases, the subject matter of amendments Nos. 25, 31, 38, 39 and 49. I call on the Minister to explain the amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>The Registration of Title Act 1964 provides for the registration of ownership of both freehold land and leasehold interests. Leasehold interest is defined as an interest in land under a lease for a term of which more than 21 years are unexpired at the date of registration. It would be desirable to move towards a situation where leases of less than 21 years could also be registered. It is for this reason that I propose to introduce the possibility of changing the 21-year period in the definition of deed in section 31 and the definition of leasehold interest in section 49. In both cases, I am proposing that the registration of deeds and title rules committee be allowed to prescribe a different period.</P>
      <P Just="Left">I am also proposing an amendment to section 62 &mdash; amendment No. 49 &mdash; in order to add a new subsection which will guide the rules committee in its deliberation on this issue because we must lay down some guidelines to help the committee decide these kinds of issues to ensure we are acting constitutionally. It provides that in determining whether the period should be altered and by how much, the rules committee shall have regard to the authority&rsquo;s function to promote and extend registration of ownership of land and the resources available to the authority for performing this function. These changes trigger consequential changes in sections 69 and 72 of the <Col N="780"/>1964 Act and are covered by amendments Nos. 38 and 39.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Minister have a period in mind in respect of asking the rules committee to prescribe another period?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I am informed that England and Wales have moved towards a period of seven years. However, this may be a long-term objective. This issue concerns resources and practicality. There is, as the new set of amendments provide, an imperative on the committee to examine the resources available to the authority and to look to the broader interest of encouraging registration. It would make no sense to clutter up title with shorter leases of two or three years. Such an arrangement would make life very complicated. We might reach a point in the future where all this can be handled electronically. The committee will progress by degrees towards the kind of figures achieved in the UK.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Group 6 deals with the transfer of land, the subject matter of amendment No. 30. I call on the Minister to explain the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>On Committee Stage in the other House, I accepted the principle of an amendment designed to ensure that the provisions of section 38 of the Bill concerning the validity of certain registered deeds did not affect proceedings which were pending at the commencement of the section. Amendment No. 30 gives effect to the intention behind the original amendment, which I accepted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Group 7 deals with qualified title, the subject matter of amendments Nos. 35 and 36. I call on the Minister to explain the amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>One of the primary functions of the new authority will be to promote and extend the registration of ownership of land. My Department has engaged in extensive consultations with the Land Registry, the Law Society and the Irish Mortgage Council on practical means of achieving this objective. One of the suggestions that arose from these discussions related to the categories of title which may be applied for under the Registration of Title Act 1964. Under the 1964 Act, the categories of title which may be registered are as follows: in respect of freehold land, an absolute title, a qualified title or possessory title; and in respect of leasehold interest, an absolute title, a good leasehold title, a qualified title or a possessory title.</P>
      <P>In cases where the application for an absolute or good leasehold title is submitted but the title can be established only for a limited period or with certain reservations, the 1964 Act allows the registrar to grant a qualified title. However, the <Col N="781"/>Act did not concurrently permit applications for qualified title. In respect of the status of qualified title, section 39 of the 1964 Act, which relates to freehold, and section 47 of the 1964 Act, which relates to leasehold, provide that a registration of an owner with a qualified title shall have the same effect as registration with an absolute title, except that registration with a qualified title does not affect or prejudice the enforcement of any right appearing by the register to be accepted.</P>
      <P>Arising from discussions with the relevant bodies, I have introduced amendments to the 1964 Act to permit applications for qualified title with a view to removing the stigma currently associated with qualified status. In effect, an applicant would be free to apply for registration of a title, subject to certain reservations which will be recorded on the relevant folio in the Land Registry. The entry on the register will accept from registration any right arising before a specified date, under a specified instrument or otherwise particularly described in the register. Someone with an imperfect title will be able to apply to register it knowing of the imperfection, which will be recorded. I should not use the term &ldquo;imperfection&rdquo;, rather &ldquo;area of uncertainty&rdquo; or whatever.</P>
      <P>This change will apply to both sections 33 and 40 of the 1964 Act, which deal with freehold land and leasehold interests, respectively. While these changes are relatively modest in scope, in the interests of clarity I have decided to replace section 33 by amendment No. 35 and section 40 by amendment No. 36 so that practitioners will be able to see the exact meaning of the two sections without needing to take out notebooks to make their own insertions and amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I agree to these amendments. From a practitioner&rsquo;s point of view, it is important that these issues are clarified. The matter of qualified status has been discussed for a long time. While the amendments are modest, they will be important for all practitioners in this area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Group 8 deals with the Registration of Title Act 1964, the subject matter of amendments Nos. 37, 40, 41, 42 and 44. I call the Minister to explain the amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>This group comprises a number of amendments to the 1964 Act that are designed to improve registration procedures and, therefore, assist the new authority in promoting and extending the registration of title. Amendment No. 37 introduces a new subsection to section 51 of the 1964 Act to make it easier to register long-term leases in registered freehold properties. In the case of a registered freehold property, any lease of the property or parts of it is deemed under current law to confer an unregistered leasehold interest. Before such an interest <Col N="782"/>can be registered, it is necessary for the lessee to apply for what is called first registration.</P>
      <P>Having examined the issue, the current law should be amended to provide that a leasehold folio can be opened without the need for an application for first registration of such cases. This can be done by means of the amendment to section 51, which provides that the word &ldquo;transfer&rdquo; shall include a lease, which will go far in simplifying the registration of units, in particular in multiunit apartment blocks which have become more popular in recent years.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 40 involves the substitution of a new text for section 90 of the 1964 Act, which deals with the powers of a person entitled to be registered as first owner of a land or charge. Where such a person wishes to transfer the land or charge before he or she is registered as owner, he or she may do so subject to any rights affecting his or her interest. However, a person who is entitled to be registered as owner, having obtained ownership by way of a lease, is not entitled to deal with the property in the same manner as a person who is entitled under a transfer.</P>
      <P>This is not appropriate in modern conditions and, therefore, I am amending the section to allow for this measure. In reviewing the section, it also became clear to me that the wording in the 1964 Act was open to a number of interpretations. In order to remedy the situation, we substituted a revised text of the section for the benefit of interested parties, particularly practitioners.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 41 substitutes a new wording for section 104 of the 1964 Act. The Land Registry identified section 104, which relates to stamp duty, as a section that causes difficulties for it in its day-to-day operations. My Department has discussed the operation of section 104 with the Land Registry and the Revenue Commissioners and an agreement has been reached on the revised wording of the section, which is the subject of this amendment. In future, the Land Registry will not proceed with a registration where it has reasonable grounds for suspecting that the correct amount of stamp duty has not been paid.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 42 substitutes a new wording for section 108 of the 1964 Act. Currently, that section allows the registrar to make an entry in the register granting priority to an intending purchaser or lender where a solicitor certifies that the applicant has entered into a contract to purchase all or part of a registered portfolio or has contracted to lend money on the security of a charge on the property. The effect is to inhibit all dealings on the folio for a period of 14 days. While it is possible to apply for further inhibitions on the expiration of the 14-day period, the Land Registry considers the time limit in this section is too inflexible. Therefore, we are increasing the 14-day inhibition period to 21 days.</P>
      <P>I am also aware that business and conveyancing practices are changing and I am anxious to intro<Col N="783"/>duce some flexibility into the arrangements. Accordingly, I have made provision that the time period may be changed by means of general rules without reverting to the Oireachtas. This will allow the rules committee, with the consent of the Minister, to extend the period to 21 days to accord with existing conveyancing practice. Amendment No. 44 updates the penalties for offences under section 119 of the 1964 Act by bringing them into line with the penalties set out in section 40 of this Bill in respect of the registry of deeds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>There are a number of amendments in this group. As the Minister outlined, they are mainly technical and complex but simplify the situation and adapt the legislation to modern practice. We agree with the amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Group 9 deals with abolishing land certificates and certificates of charge, the subject matter of amendment No. 50. I ask the Minister to explain the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>This is an important amendment to the Bill. It responds to concerns expressed in earlier debates about the delays and costs currently associated with the registration of land. Under current legislation, if a registered owner of land wishes to deal with it in any way, a land certificate issued in respect of the land must be presented to the Land Registry before further transactions can be registered. Similarly, the legislation requires that the Land Registry issue a certificate of charge on the mortgage of registered land and that this certificate be produced in respect of any further dealings.</P>
      <P>From meetings we held with the parties involved, including the Land Registry, the Law Society and the Irish Mortgage Council, a consensus has emerged of a radical kind, namely, that the land certificate and certificate of charge system is completely incompatible with the introduction of e-conveyancing, which is a product the Government is trying to advance. The Department and I became convinced that such a system cannot continue if we wish to progress to a fully electronic conveyancing system with all of the benefits e-conveyancing would bring to practitioners and consumers.</P>
      <P>The main reason current legislation requires the submission of any existing land certificate is that it could have been lodged with a financial institution as security for a loan by way of an equitable deposit, which is generally referred to as an equitable mortgage. While such informal mortgages have become less common, the fact that any outstanding land certificates must be presented before any new transaction in respect of the property can be registered gives rise to a significant administrative burden for the Land Registry. Moreover, the predictable loss and misplacement of certificates, which may have issued <Col N="784"/>many years ago and often decades previously, cause long delays and add to the costs of conveyancing.</P>
      <P Just="Left">The new section provides for the phasing out of land certificates over a three-year period. Specifically, it provides that land certificates and certificates of charge issued before the commencement of subsection (1) and not already cancelled will cease to have any force or effect three years after the commencement of subsection (2). If someone has loaned in a private transaction or as a lending institution on foot of a deposit or arrangement whereby he or she held onto the land certificate, he or she will effectively have three years to do something with his or her interest in the land. Otherwise, it will cease to have any significance by the end of that time. In addition, we have provided that section 105 of the 1964 Act, which requires the production of a land certificate or certificate of charge on the lodgment of a dealing in the Land Registry, shall cease to operate three years after the commencement of subsection (2).</P>
      <P>I am making provision for the conversion of any outstanding equitable mortgages into legal charges during that three-year period. Subsection (3) contains details of this conversion process and also requires the new authority to publish the new provisions and provide information on their implications for holders of land certificates or certificates of charge. This will not be done by stealth &mdash; it will be publicly advertised so no one can say later that he or she never heard about it and had been relying on keeping someone else&rsquo;s land certificate under the pillow as security for a loan or whatever.</P>
      <P>Despite the provision that adequate notice be given of these changes, it is possible that some people may not become aware of them or their implications and could suffer financial losses as a result. This might arise by reason of a person suffering from a disability. For example, if someone received one of these certificates but developed Alzheimer&rsquo;s disease or something similar, he or she might be prejudiced and could not grasp the significance of a newspaper advertisement.</P>
      <P>In practice, this is unlikely to arise, except possibly in the case of a private transaction between individuals, as presumably the banks will not develop Alzheimer&rsquo;s disease. For this reason, I have made provision in subsections (4) to (8) for a compensation mechanism. In the event of it being used, the holder of a land certificate or certificate of charge could apply to the court for compensation for the claimed financial loss. Under the stringent conditions set out in subsection (5), the court could declare that the holder was entitled to compensation and determine the amount. That provision was included in an abundance of caution, in case someone&rsquo;s property rights, particularly those of a vulnerable person, could be extinguished without their knowledge and to their prejudice.</P><Col N="785"/>
      <P>I readily acknowledge that these changes are far-reaching and radical. However, as we move towards e-conveyancing, the idea of producing 30 year old pieces of paper which may have been in deed boxes, under beds, in solicitors&rsquo; offices, in bank safes or whatever before one can do anything in respect of land is simply not compatible with an electronic system. Hence, although this change is radical, it is justified and necessary if we are to move to the e-conveyancing of land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>The safeguards for vulnerable people are absolutely necessary and the move towards e-conveyancing is undoubtedly important and ground-breaking. It moves our system closer to those operated by our European neighbours, where the process of buying a house is much simpler and faster. We wish to reach such a position here, particularly in this age of increased technology and instant monetary transfers. Hence, the aim is to simplify matters and to make them quicker and easier. However, as the Minister noted, it is important to include these safeguards as we proceed towards e-conveyancing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyKett"><NameTxt>Mr. Kett</NameTxt>
	<P>I fully agree and if one takes the e-conveyancing route, one must dispense with the paper trail completely. While I am unsure whether there is any set of circumstances in which paper would return to the network, I believe it should not. If it does so, the entire electronic element of the process would be rendered meaningless.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The House will now proceed to group 10, which relates to the amendment of the Ombudsman Acts, the subject matter of amendment No. 53.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>Briefly, this amendment is designed to ensure that the authority is subject both to the Ombudsman Act 1980 and the Ombudsman for Children Act 2002 in the same way as the Land Registry and registry of deeds, which are already included in the Schedules to both Acts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><TitleTxt>Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to take this opportunity to thank the Cathaoirleach and the Members of both Houses for the constructive approach shown with regard to this Bill. Last year when it was introduced to this House, I stated that the reforms contained in the Bill would help to make the conveyancing of land easier and faster and would reduce registration delays and associated costs. The additional reforms introduced by means of amendments during its passage through both Houses will also contribute sig<Col N="786"/>nificantly to the process of modernisation of our property registration system. This modernisation will in turn contribute to an improved domestic business environment and will improve our international ranking as a location in which to do business.</P>
      <P>The new property registration authority will have the function of controlling and managing both of our existing registries, the Land Registry and the registry of deeds, as well as promoting the extending of registration of ownership of land. The extending of registration of ownership of land is a key objective as we move towards electronic conveyancing of land.</P>
      <P>I have already extended compulsory registration to three further counties, namely, counties Longford, Roscommon and Westmeath, with effect from 1 April. However, further rapid progress is essential and I will ask the new authority to give particular attention to the further extension of compulsory registration in its first strategic plan.</P>
      <P>When I introduced the Bill, I also referred to the urgent need to update and streamline our land and conveyancing laws. I mentioned the joint modernisation project which my Department has undertaken with the Law Reform Commission. In that context, the text of a land and conveyancing Bill is close to being finalised for publication and I intend to have it presented to this House in the current session. The new Bill will simplify and streamline land and conveyancing law, with a view to making it more easily comprehensible for legal practitioners and the public alike, updating it in order to accommodate changing social, economic and demographic needs, including new forms of property ownership, and making the conveyancing of land easier and faster.</P>
      <P>I look forward to introducing the new Bill in this House because it will sweep away many centuries of accretion of law, going back in some cases to the 13th century. Hence, this will be a quite radical and reforming Bill. More than 150 pre-1922 statutes will be swept away and replaced with provisions which are more suitable to the 21st century. Some of the statutes are almost as old as the arrival of the Normans, which shows something.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyKett"><NameTxt>Mr. Kett</NameTxt>
	<P>That tells us something.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>In any event, until I introduce the Second Stage debate of the new Bill in this House, I wish to thank all the Members of this House who assiduously contributed to the passage of the present Bill through both Houses. I also wish, unprompted, to pay tribute to the officials in my Department who have worked on both projects and who are engaged in bringing about real, genuine and radical change in a manner in which the media probably are hardly interested. However, it is for Ireland&rsquo;s betterment.</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="787"/>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I compliment the Minister on introducing this long overdue legislation. I also compliment the officials involved on the great amount of work that has gone into this extremely technical and complex Bill. While I was about to express the hope that it would be the first in a series of Bills to bring our law to the point at which it should be with regard to this area, I was glad to hear the Minister state that a new Bill will be introduced in the not too distant future which will deal with land law and conveyancing law. This is most welcome as all parties, as well as the practitioners, have been crying out for such legislation. The promised legislation will bring us up to date in respect of the entire area of land law, which is badly needed. I again compliment the Minister on bringing forward this legislation and I thank his officials.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyKett"><NameTxt>Mr. Kett</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister and his officials for this welcome and reforming legislation. It is clear that we need effective and efficient legislation to deal with modern Ireland. Undoubtedly, it is also true that this kind of legislation has the capacity to contribute in a meaningful manner to economic activity.</P>
      <P Just="Left">Recently, I heard the Minister refer, possibly on &ldquo;Questions and Answers&rdquo;, to the amount of archaic and ancient legislation that has been sitting on the Statute Book since Norman times or at some other point. The Minister has played his part in reforming the entire system and will continue to so do. It is ridiculous to think that we still suffer the laws and legislation of people who enacted them while wearing plus fours or carrying swords. However, that is another day&rsquo;s debate.</P>
      <P>In addition to reforming the legislation, it is also essential that it be simplified, in order that those who must deal with it in whatever capacity can understand it better. Again, I thank the Minister and his officials.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyKett"><NameTxt>Mr. Kett</NameTxt>
	<P>At 12 noon on Wednesday, 3 May 2006.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment" RHead="Matter">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter.</Title>
    <Sect LHead="Local Authority" RHead="Housing">
      <sTitle>Local Authority Housing.</sTitle>
      <Speaker pid="JoannaTuffy"><NameTxt>Ms Tuffy</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister has the details of my question. I ask it because I want to establish the up-to-date position regarding the implementation of Part V of the Planning and Development Act 2000 and how many affordable houses are being delivered on the ground, particularly how many planning permissions have been granted for affordable housing. I did not agree with the amendment to Part V as set out in the Planning <Col N="788"/>and Development (Amendment) Act 2002 and I am concerned about how this is affecting the provision of affordable housing.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">12 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P>It is important to monitor what is happening in regard to the provision of affordable housing. As the Minister of State will be aware, the price of housing continues to increase. In my estate, the price of houses has increased by approximately &euro;100,000 in the past year, which is not sustainable. As this means that first-time buyers are being left behind, it is important that as much affordable housing as possible is coming on stream.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NoelAhern"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. N. Ahern</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Senator for raising the matter which affords me an opportunity to clarify certain misconceptions regarding output from Part V of the Planning and Development Act. I am happy that Part V is now fully operational in all planning authorities. The provision of homes for first-time buyers and young families under Part V is gathering momentum. Figures for last year indicate that just under 1,400 social and affordable housing units were delivered to local authorities. This is more than double the output for 2004, when the figure was 600, which was the best up to that point.</P>
        <P>In addition to the number of negotiated units, 38 land transfers to local authorities were completed up to the end of last year, involving some 20 hectares. A further 213 partially or fully serviced sites were transferred to local authorities and voluntary housing bodies. More than &euro;24.5 million has been received <i>in lieu</i> of land and houses, and a further &euro;5.5 million was received under the withering levy, which was part of the change in the legislation. This output reflects the use of the various flexible options now available to satisfy Part V obligations. Further evidence of this increased activity is that at the end of 2005, 2,500 units were under construction, and a further 3,500 were proposed under agreements reached with developers. It is envisaged that more than 8,000 social and affordable units will be delivered under Part V over the next three years.</P>
        <P>There is a tendency to suggest that all housing output in the State is subject to Part V, which is not true. For instance, it is estimated that just over 10,000 units of the total housing output of 81,000 last year were subject to Part V. It is important to note that Part V is restricted to land zoned for residential use, or a mixture of residential and other uses. Therefore, not all housing developments are subject to Part V. While all the land around Dublin and the major urban cities may be zoned land, land around many smaller towns and villages throughout the country where housing developments take place has historically not been zoned, and Part V does not apply in these cases.</P>
        <P>To further illustrate this, from last year&rsquo;s total output of 81,000 units it is estimated that approxi<Col N="789"/>mately 20,000 were one-off units, 8,000 were built under social and affordable schemes and a further 40,000 or more were exempted as they were smaller developments of under four units, or less, or built on unzoned land, or with planning permissions granted prior to the introduction of Part V. The remainder of just over 10,000 units of the total housing output would have been subject to Part V.</P>
        <P>The provision of Part V units is dependent on the level and commencement of private sector residential development and the nature of Part V agreements entered into. Output is now beginning to gather momentum as much of the residential building coming through in recent years was on foot of planning permissions which predated the Planning and Development Act and did not have a Part V requirement. Increasingly, this will no longer be the case. If the Senator or anyone else reads the newspapers and looks at showhouses this week-end, they will find that many of the houses for sale are the product of planning permissions granted before the Act came into place. The normal timespan is five years, but in some instances some of the big developments would have obtained ten year planning permissions.</P>
        <P>There was a certain degree of stockpiling of permissions prior to the introduction of Part V. Many of the houses that are currently for sale do not have a Part V content because the planning permission was granted prior to the Part V legislation being introduced. However, this will no longer be the case. I am confident that the full benefits of Part V will be seen in the not too distant future, perhaps next year or the year after. Some people who find the arithmetic to be simplistic believe that 81,000 units divided by 20% should result in so many Part V units. It will never mean that applying this kind of simple arithmetic will add up to the Part V contribution. Anyone who thinks it is the case is wrong.</P>
        <P>Part V is not intended as the sole mechanism for the provision of social and affordable housing units. The local authority direct build programme, together with the voluntary and co-operative programme and the various affordable housing schemes, continue to be the major contributors to social and affordable housing output. It is worth mentioning that approximately 13,000 households were assisted through the full range of social and affordable housing measures in 2005. I believe this should be nearer to 14,000 households this year. I issued figures last week which indicated that the output of local authority housing last year was the highest in approximately 20 years. While output in 1960s and 1970s was higher, the output last year was the highest for approximately 20 years, which is significant. The budget this year for social, local authority, voluntary and regeneration schemes is &euro;1,400 million, which is a lot of money.</P>
        <P>I wish to refer to the amendments made to Part V of the Planning and Development Act 2000 and <Col N="790"/>contained in the Planning and Development (Amendment) Act 2002. Apart from enabling approved voluntary housing bodies, as well as local authorities, to provide housing more efficiently and effectively, the amendments were designed to ensure that the Part V objectives set in regard to the provision of social and affordable housing were easier to meet. The changes introduced to assist in meeting Part V obligations came about as a result of an accepted need for the introduction of some flexibility for all stakeholders.</P>
        <P>I mean all stakeholders &mdash; local authorities, developers and the voluntary housing providers; it is not, as some might paint it, that we are simply allowing developers off the hook. Flexibility was needed by everybody. Where a developer makes a financial contribution to satisfy his or her legal obligation under Part V, it is a matter for the local authority to accept or reject the offer, having regard to its housing strategy and whether it constitutes the best use of the resources available to it. The developers may propose, but the local authority decides, and when making its decision is bound to consider what is laid down and is needed under its housing strategy. That point must be clear. It is not the developers who decide. Developers may offer cash or land elsewhere but the local authority makes the decision.</P>
        <P>Where money or land is provided in lieu of housing, that can only apply for the purposes of social and affordable housing. The money is ring-fenced and is not applied towards any other general use. It could be used as a subsidy to help to supply super-affordable housing, so to speak.</P>
        <P>I have no doubt Part V will play a major part in the delivery of social and affordable housing in the future. The delivery of units &mdash; new homes &mdash; is my preferred option when reaching agreement with developers. I have made it clear to local authorities that this is what we want. I have asked them to vigorously pursue that and will continue to follow up with them. Primarily, we want units on site, but flexibility is needed on occasion. The example is regularly mentioned with regard to Shrewsbury or Ailesbury Road, where we could have got two social units at a cost of &euro;1.4 million each. That is ideology gone mad. In such a case it is much better to acquire other sites. Last week, affordable housing was for sale in Senator Tuffy&rsquo;s constituency, which was a result of the Harcourt Square land swap. I think the two-bedroom houses were for sale for &euro;142,000 and the three-bedroom houses for &euro;172,000.</P>
        <P>I accept that as Senator Tuffy says, house prices have again increased. I blame the financial institutions which introduced 100% mortgages for much of the increases. All last summer and autumn I was crying in the wilderness on this matter because too much credit was being extended in the market, and credit is by definition inflationary. I am glad the Central Bank, the Financial Regulator and others have now agreed on this, now that they have evidence. They would not <Col N="791"/>move on the matter last year because they were seeking evidence, rather than my hunch or feeling. The offer of 100% mortgages by financial institutions was the cause of the latest spurt in house prices and those institutions were not doing anybody any service by their offer.</P>
        <P>In my Department and in Government we are trying to look after people in certain income brackets who are under pressure. By means of all the various affordable schemes we built some 2,900 units last year, some of which were on sale in Senator Tuffy&rsquo;s constituency. We must do more in this area and with Part V playing a bigger part, we plan to increase the number of affordable units to approximately 5,000 on average over the next couple of years. We might achieve 4,000 this year, 5,000 next year and 6,000 the following year but we feel we will average about 5,000 over these three years. We can only look after people under stress and pressure in that segment of the market.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoannaTuffy"><NameTxt>Ms Tuffy</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister of State says his preferred option is that developers would provide affordable housing rather than buy themselves out of that provision. Does his Department have any idea of how many instances in which developers qualify for the buy-out clause, and how many are providing affordable housing? It is important to know to what extent the amendment to Part V as set out in the Planning and Development (Amendment) Act 2002 is being used by developers in order not to provide affordable housing.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NoelAhern"><NameTxt>Mr. N. Ahern</NameTxt>
	<P>I provided the figures of &euro;24.5 million plus &euro;5.5 million in levies. As I noted, some 1,400 affordable units were provided last year. Legally, the developer must provide houses <Col N="792"/>on site or else provide houses off-site elsewhere, or sites elsewhere, or half-completed houses elsewhere, or land or cash, but if there had been no flexibility in that last year, the figure of 1,400 units would probably have increased by 20% or 25%. Accordingly, the notion that we have only 1,400 units because all the developers are buying their way out of the obligation is untrue. As I say, the number of units might have gone up by 20% or 25% &mdash; one cannot estimate an exact figure, but we looked at the possible number. The various alternative provisions for developers will die out over the next couple of years, although the cash provision option will continue.</P>
        <P>Everybody wanted that flexibility. It makes sense when one instances Ailesbury Road, for example. We now have data from the different local authorities. One can see that some of them are accepting cash, sites or lands more than others, and one wonders why, so we are asking them why they are a little trigger-happy, using the flexibility measures more than other local authorities. As we have some data now, we can ask more questions, and are doing so.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The idea of flexibility is good. It was introduced for a purpose, not to let developers off the hook. That is not what I am about. Flexibility is sensible and wise at times and the money is ring-fenced. It is under the control of the Department, but we are responsive to any good ideas from local authorities. The money can be used for new social housing or for greater subsidies. For example, in theory, some of those houses I referred to as having been for sale last week could be sold at even lower prices, if local authorities made a proposal to the Department along those lines.</P>
        <adjournment>The Seanad adjourned at 12.20 p.m. until<?oasys _jy ?>12 noon on Wednesday, 3 May 2006.</adjournment><Col N="791"/>
      </Speaker>
    </Sect>
  </MainHeading>
  <?oasys _te ?>
</Debate>
