<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="1" Month="Nov" Year="2006" Vol="184" No="24" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 1 Samhain 2006" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 1 November 2006" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1973">
    <Col N="1973"/><HtmlBk SectId="1" />
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title></Title>
        <P>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar<?oasys _jy ?>2.30 p.m.</P>
        <Line />
        <P Just="Center"><i>Paidir.</i><br /><i>Prayer.</i></P><Line />
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad"> 
    <Title>Business of Seanad. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I have notice from Senator O&rsquo;Rourke that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Finance to give the precise up to date details of the decentralisation plans for the following three locations: Athlone, Mullingar and Longford; indicate, in the case of each location, if he will give details of the Department concerned; the planning and construction details; the numbers who have applied for transfer; the anticipated date of opening; and all other relevant matters in connection with each of these three decentralisation locations.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Feeney of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform to make a statement on the unsatisfactory situation where alleged rape victims in County Sligo have to be brought by Garda car to the Rotunda Hospital, Dublin, for medical examination; and if alternative arrangements can be put in place.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Bannon of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Education and Science to clarify the position regarding the inequity of charging fees of over &euro;6,000 for a student (details supplied) repeating a college year, with the allied loss of third level grant provision, in circumstances where she is relying for funding on a widowed parent, whose sole income is disability benefit, and to outline how, under natural justice, such a punitive measure can be enforced.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Kitt of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government to <Col N="1974"/>confirm the up to date position of a water supply for Ballygar, County Galway.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected Senators O&rsquo;Rourke, Feeney and Bannon and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.  Senator Kitt may give notice on another day of the matter he wishes to raise.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business"> 
    <Title>Order of Business. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements on the provisions of the Official Languages Act 2003 relating to placenames, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business and to conclude no later than 5 p.m., with the contributions of spokespersons not to exceed 12 minutes and those of other Senators not to exceed eight minutes, and the Minister to be called upon to reply no later than ten minutes before the conclusion of the statements; and No. 26, motion 23, to be taken from 5 p.m. until 7 p.m.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">On foot of the events that occurred in Dublin last night, which occur annually, I congratulate the members of the Dublin fire brigade and the other emergency service workers in the city and the rest of the country.  They have a considerable job to do every Hallowe&rsquo;en night.  Given the events of last night, it is now appropriate for the Government to review the effectiveness of the fireworks legislation put in place in the past 12 months.  In spite of the legislation, the Dublin Fire Brigade had to respond to 700 calls last night and there were many assaults and instances of anti-social behaviour.  Under the legislation as it stands, a company can apply to the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform seeking a licence for a special fireworks event.  We should possibly relax this provision to allow communities to host events jointly if they so choose, given that the local Garda Superintendent decides they are in the public interest.  We must clamp down on the anti-social behaviour that occurs at Hallowe&rsquo;en but in a way that brings the communities with us.  I thank the members of the emergency services for doing a splendid job last night.</P>
        <P Just="Left">There has been much comment in the past 24 hours on the Personal Injuries Assessment Board and its effectiveness.  When I saw the report on the board in the newspaper, I believed some of the claims being made about its effectiveness were quite fraudulent.  It is doing a very good job in terms of reducing the cost of premia.</P>
        <P>The other aspect of the insurance industry that we need to address concerns public liability insurance for local authorities.  In my local authority area, the county manager factored into the budget a sum of approximately &euro;1.7 million to meet small claims pertaining to footpaths.  The bill for footpath improvements in the local authority area is just &euro;800,000.  We are therefore spending twice as much money on settling claims <Col N="1975"/>through the courts as on footpath improvements.  We must tackle this.</P>
        <P>Some local authorities have done considerable work to highlight fraudulent claims and ensure people know the sums local authorities have to hand out on a daily basis.  I ask the Government to consider this.  Perhaps the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government will address in the House the issues of public liability insurance and the horrendous sums of money being handed out by local authorities to settle claims throughout the country.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Mr. O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>We had a long debate last week on the question of our commitment to the Kyoto Protocol.  I do not believe any Member on this side of the House is more committed to the environment than any Member on the other side but I firmly believe that Ministers and Members of Government parties are being set up with false information on the issue.  Last Wednesday night, the Minister stated everything was rosy in the garden, that Ireland is the only country in Europe not being chased by the European Union in respect of the protocol and that we are very much on course towards meeting our commitments.  Many people, including Senators Kitt and Brady, gave us back the information they had been given.  I do not blame them for that, but we need to recognise that it is not good enough any more.</P>
        <P>I am not asking anyone to concede anything to me here on the floor of the House.  I am just asking people to raise this matter in their parliamentary parties.  What is going on is disgraceful.  Two days after last week&rsquo;s debate, the European Community expressed the view that Ireland languishes near the bottom of the league.  It said that under current conditions, Ireland will miss its target by almost 16%.  It pointed out that Ireland&rsquo;s emissions will increase by 30% if something is not done.  Perhaps everybody is happy with that.  I want to know whether our colleagues are being misinformed in this regard.  If they are, it is disgraceful.</P>
        <P>I thank Senator Brian Hayes for highlighting the role of the Personal Injuries Assessment Board.  When I raised the issue in the House with the Leader on a previous occasion, she kindly agreed to arrange a discussion on it.  The reports in the news media yesterday were worse than fraudulent &mdash; they were misinformed, inaccurate and wrong in every way.</P>
        <P>I should declare an interest in this regard because I am the vice-chair of the PIAB.  I have double-checked every single fact.  I would welcome a debate on this matter as early as possible next week.  I wish to remove any doubt by making it clear that there is no backlog, despite what one might have heard in the news media yesterday about the size of the backlog and the length of time it will take to get through it.  The board is completely ahead of schedule.</P><Col N="1976"/>
        <P>It was reported that the PIAB has dealt with 4,000 cases so far this year, which is true.  It has been in operation for just a year and a half.  It will be in a position to clear 10,000 cases next year.  It has reduced the length of time it takes to settle a case from three years to seven months.  It has saved the country &euro;70 million in costs, to date.  It will save a further &euro;45 million every year from now on.  The PIAB settled 4,000 cases last year, but the courts settled fewer than 2,000 cases.  That was not mentioned in the news reports.  Next year, the board will settle 10,000 cases, or 200 cases a week.</P>
        <P>It was suggested by the news media that the board will have to increase its rate of case settlement from 50 per week to 200 per week.  The reporter in question was informed last Friday that the board is already settling approximately 170 cases per week.  We are there.  Everything is completely on target.  We are ahead of schedule.  We are ahead of our objectives.  The board will deliver exactly what the four main parties in this country have sought to support all the way through.  I ask people to have full confidence in the PIAB.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenOMeara"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Meara</NameTxt>
	<P>Like Senator Brian Hayes, I pay tribute to the work done last night by Garda and fire brigade personnel throughout the country.  They managed the events of Hallowe&rsquo;en in a very effective manner.  I would like to pick up on the point made by Senator Hayes about fireworks.  It is time to review the legislation on fireworks.  I am involved with a community arts festival in Nenagh, which organised a community event with fireworks last night.  The event, which was very popular and well-managed, was run voluntarily with support from the arts fund of the local authority.  It is a useful example of how problems can be avoided in a family-oriented and safe manner.</P>
        <P>I also pay tribute to the work of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na last weekend, which ensured that we are not referring today to road deaths in the way we have had to do on more than one occasion.  Thankfully, the number of road deaths this weekend was not as high as we feared it might be.  I do not doubt that the low level of fatalities can be attributed to the work of the Garda.  One would also hope that the message is finally getting through in that regard.</P>
        <P>I ask the Leader of the House for a debate on an aspect of our health care system.  I am aware that the House will consider the Child Care (Amendment) Bill 2006 tomorrow and that the Minister intends to introduce amendments in respect of various issues.  It is clear from recent reports that some existing mental health legislation will come into force today.</P>
        <P>We need to consider the mental health of young people and the provision of psychiatric services for young people, including children.  The Minister of State, Deputy Tim O&rsquo;Malley, has said that another two and a half years will pass before the level of service that is needed for young <Col N="1977"/>people will be fully in place.  He considers that to be a satisfactory position, but I do not agree with him.  Given the implications of that delay for young people, their families and their communities in particular, we need to ensure that psychiatric and mental health issues and the mental health needs of young people and children are placed at the top of the Government&rsquo;s agenda as a matter of urgency.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Mr. Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I request the Leader to arrange an early debate on pensions, particularly pertaining to the Bank of Ireland, where a second class scheme is proposed for new employees, while the chief executive of that bank receives &euro;2.5 million per annum in addition to a significant pension scheme and perks.  His pension is boosted regularly yet this second class scheme has been arranged.  I join the Irish Bank Officials Association in condemning the move which has been brought before the labour court where we await the discussion.  The second biggest bank in Ireland is proposing that new staff be afforded lesser conditions than those of existing staff and this move is against the best interests of employees.  Customers of the Bank of Ireland should make known their positions on this matter to senior officials there.  I feel this would be worthwhile because the issue of pensions could be an area for early debate in this House.  I condemn the activities of the chief executive and board of governors of Bank of Ireland in this regard.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I echo other speakers in complimenting the Garda and Fire Services on the manner in which they handled situations throughout the country last night.  However, many individuals, including taxi drivers and garda&iacute;, have indicated to me the lack of resources available to emergency services personnel, especially garda&iacute;.  These people work with limited resources and this has been highlighted time and again, yet the Government does not take action to provide the necessary resources.</P>
        <P>I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Social and Family Affairs, Deputy Brennan, to this House to debate the inadequate investment in community care facilities for the elderly, sick and disabled.  The essential repair and disabled person&rsquo;s grants have not kept pace with inflation over the years.  In local authority guidelines the disabled person&rsquo;s grant is still around &euro;20,000 per annum and that relating to essential repairs for the elderly is around half that figure.  It is impossible for those in receipt of the essential repair grant to acquire contractors to carry out work because the contractors are not interested.  The elderly are being neglected in this sense because the Government has not supplied sufficient funds for grants to support them.</P>
        <P>We must relax the eligibility criteria for the carers allowance to enable full-time carers qualify, an issue I have often highlighted.  Everything <Col N="1978"/>looks rosy in the Government&rsquo;s guidelines but the facilities are not available when the elderly and sick try to access them.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>Like Senators Brian Hayes and O&rsquo;Toole, I was dismayed to see individuals in the media proving a soft touch for vested legal interests.  The proof of the pudding is in the eating.  The Personal Injuries Assessment Board, PIAB, has been a catalyst in the reduction of insurance costs and deserves our support.</P>
        <P>The city was alight with fireworks last night as I approached via the Naas Road and there is a great deal of merit in Senator Brian Hayes&rsquo;s suggestion that community fireworks displays around the country could reduce the incentive for private and illegal enterprise.</P>
        <P>Does the Leader plan to invite our MEPs, or leaders of the groups, to the House before the end of this Seanad&rsquo;s term.  I was disappointed to see a group of MEPs denounce the Basque peace process in terms incompatible with the Irish peace process.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should not misrepresent them.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>I have the words used here.  The Basque peace process in itself merits debate in order that there is better information in this country.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>I agree with that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>Anyone who believes that when the Taoiseach wants to go electioneering, he ought to go to the European Parliament in Strasbourg&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>More misrepresentation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;has lost touch with reality.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I am glad that Senator Brian Hayes raised the question of the Personal Injuries Assessment Board and the ludicrous fact that it is paying out more in claims than is being spent by local authorities on fixing footpaths.  The local authorities should be spending more on their footpaths.  Three weeks ago I had a serious fall in Wicklow Street.  I did not sue anyone because I do not believe in that but I welcome the opportunity to bring this to the attention of the House.</P>
        <P>One of the problems is that the street surfaces in Dublin are either not properly maintained, being precipitous, dangerous and broken, or the wrong materials are used.  I was on Wicklow Street where there is cobble lock which has designs in white ceramic tiling.  It is very pretty but it is a death trap, the tiles are like ice.  The Spire has an attractive metal surround but people fall on it every day of the week.  The way the entire road surface in O&rsquo;Connell Street is designed is thoroughly dangerous.  There is no grip at all and elderly people are at serious risk.</P><Col N="1979"/>
        <P Just="Left">Will the Seanad provide an opportunity to consider No. 26, motion 3, in my name, on Tibet, especially in light of the appalling events there in recent days?  A group of 40 Tibetan refugees attempting to escape across the Himalayas were set upon, attacked and shot in the back as they moved away.  A 17 year old nun was killed.  As usual, the Chinese lied about it, saying that the border guards were protecting themselves.  Border guards should not be there; Tibet is not part of China.  We are collaborating in this because we have allowed, without any debate in the Oireachtas, a shift in our position that accepts the incorporation of Tibet into China.</P>
        <P>I also support Senator O&rsquo;Toole in his remarks on climate change.  We have been misled in this House and we have met complete and utter complacency.  The Minister indicated that he knows damn well that we are going way beyond our Kyoto targets and those targets will not even rectify the situation.  What is the answer?  We are happily told that we will buy our way out of it.  Buying carbon credits is the worst possible solution.  We know how serious this is now as a result of Sir Nicholas Stern&rsquo;s report.  The British Government has at last woken up to the problem, appointing Al Gore to talk sense to the United States, because it is among the worst polluters.  There should also be a debate on this, as outlined in No. 26, motion 21 on the Order Paper.</P>
        <P>Will the Cathaoirleach intervene in another matter?  Yet again today, and I am furious about this, as other Members should be, the House and the Cathaoirleach have been insulted by an Oireachtas committee.  The Oireachtas Joint Committee on Transport, of which I am a member and every meeting of which I have attempted to attend, has again, despite my protests and attempts to ensure it would not be quorate and despite my walking out last week, coincided the time of the committee meeting with the Order of Business in this House, showing complete contempt for it, as it does every week.  We are apparently prepared to put up with that.  Will the Cathaoirleach use his powers to ensure Seanad &Eacute;ireann is treated with some respect?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not know if it is a matter entirely for the Chair but I appreciate the Senator&rsquo;s concern.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde"><NameTxt>Ms Ormonde</NameTxt>
	<P>I endorse Senator O&rsquo;Toole&rsquo;s comments on the workings of the Personal Injuries Assessment Board.  Anyone who, like me, listened carefully to media reports at lunchtime yesterday will have concluded that the PIAB is in chaos and has a major backlog of work and that most of its claims will ultimately come before the courts.  Given the negative media attention the PIAB is receiving, it is good to have Senator O&rsquo;Toole in the House because he has inside knowledge and is able to provide Senators with correct information on the workings of the board. <Col N="1980"/> Coverage of the issue extended to three or four pages of a daily newspaper yesterday and reading it, one would be convinced that the PIAB has been a flop.  Having drawn this conclusion, I am pleased to learn from Senator O&rsquo;Toole that the PIAB is a success.  It would be appropriate for the House to debate the issue.</P>
        <P>The National Forum on Europe meets every week to discuss the future of Europe.  With Romania and Bulgaria due to join the European Union in the new year, this is an appropriate time for the House to debate the future of Europe.  We should invite some of our MEPs to the House to take part in a full discussion on how Europe is shaping up.  There is no better forum than the Seanad to bring this information into the public arena.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnPaulPhelan"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Phelan</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Leader for securing on my behalf a response from the Department of Health and Children about the primary school medical examination.  Unfortunately, as is frequently the case with departmental replies, it was wholly inadequate because it did not say anything. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I agree. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnPaulPhelan"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Phelan</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Health and Children or one of her Ministers of State to the House to debate the primary school medical examination.  We must ensure the examination, an important preventative health measure, is used nationwide because its implementation appears haphazard.  </P>
        <P>I support Senator O&rsquo;Toole&rsquo;s request for a debate on the recent report on global warming.  We have received contradictory information on this issue from the Government, European Union and other sources.</P>
        <P>I agree with Senator Brian Hayes on the issue of fireworks.  I, too, travelled to Dublin via the Naas Road yesterday evening and saw the night sky lit up.  If community groups want to come together to organise controlled firework displays, they should be encouraged to do so.</P>
        <P>I am pleased to read in today&rsquo;s newspapers that the Minister for Education and Science is considering changing the structure of Irish on the leaving certificate curriculum.  I am glad the debate generated by Fine Gael&rsquo;s policy position on this issue appears to be having an impact on Government thinking on the Irish language.  We cannot continue to treat the language as we have done in recent years.  I am glad the Minister is responding to the Fine Gael position.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P>I support calls for a debate on fireworks.  I was not on the Naas Road last night but in Carlow where hundreds, if not thousands, of fireworks lit up the skies.  I followed garda&iacute; on the beat into an estate and observed how ludicrous is the current position when the garda&iacute; in question were unable to apprehend those letting <Col N="1981"/>off fireworks directly in front of them.  Those involved included small children for whom no one appeared to take responsibility.</P>
        <P>The laws on fireworks should be standardised North and South.  The farcical nature of the current position is demonstrated by the fact that every firework set off last night was illegal.  Is it workable in a small island to have fireworks freely for sale in the North and prohibited in the South?  If fireworks were sold here legally, it would be possible to control their quality and thereby reduce the number of injuries.  It would also be feasible to trace fireworks when injuries occur.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">3 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P Just="Left">I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on an important issue in the health service. Recent figures for the number of outpatients awaiting appointments with consultants are far higher than expected.  There is also a huge deficit of information.  Last June, the Joint Committee on Health and Children requested information on the National Treatment Purchase Fund to see how it compared with procedures carried out in the public sector.  We are still waiting for that information.  The Department has refused to give it to us.  We are working in a vacuum.  Although compliments have been paid on how well the health service is working, we really do not know how it is working.  There should be a debate on the National Treatment Purchase Fund and the outpatients issue.</P>
        <P>Will the Leader also arrange a debate on MRSA?  At the weekend I was told about a pregnant lady who went to hospital to have a scan.  She happened to have a wound on her ear and contracted MRSA when getting the scan.  She faced the horrible choice of going on antibiotics, which would affect her baby, or not doing so and running the risk of her baby being born with MRSA.  It is outrageous that people cannot go into hospital for simple procedures without running the risk of contracting MRSA due to the negligence of the hospital authorities.</P>
        <P>Today the drift net fishermen are protesting outside the House about the buy-out plan.  A few years ago there was a similar case with the sugar beet growers.  The Government appears to have turned its back again on the growers.  As the budget is due to be introduced shortly, perhaps the Leader would arrange a debate on compensation for the sugar beet growers.  This compensation has been delayed due to court action as a result of dithering by the Government.  I also understand the growers will be liable to tax on their compensation payments, even though they did not want to leave the industry.  The Government ensured the wipe-out of the industry but the beet growers, through no fault of theirs, will now be liable to tax on their compensation whenever they get it, and that could take years.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn"><NameTxt>Mr. Glynn</NameTxt>
	<P>This time last year I raised the use of fireworks.  This year, certainly in Mullingar, there was a significant reduction in their use.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1982"/>
      <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P>We have them in Carlow now.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn"><NameTxt>Mr. Glynn</NameTxt>
	<P>The situation is far from perfect but we are going in the right direction.  A debate on this subject would be beneficial.  This time last year I spoke about a young local man who suffered serious injury as a result of using fireworks.  Will the Leader also arrange for a rolling debate on health?  Members of the Opposition have sought debates on health under various headings and I would appreciate such a debate as soon as possible.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimHiggins"><NameTxt>Mr. Higgins</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I agree with Senator Ormonde that this Chamber is a suitable venue to debate what is happening in Europe.  Members of the European Parliament who are not Members of the Oireachtas are <i>ex officio</i> members of the Joint Committee on European affairs and can attend those meetings.  The problem is the rostering of the meetings.  It is generally agreed that there was a useful exchange before the European elections, when outgoing Members of the European Parliament were invited to address the Seanad and take questions from Members, from the point of view of elucidating on what is happening at European level.  We would certainly welcome such opportunities.</P>
        <P>With regard to the point made by Senator Mansergh regarding the motion on the Basque peace process, which was taken in the European Parliament last Thursday, I make no apology for supporting our Spanish colleagues on that motion.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimHiggins"><NameTxt>Mr. Higgins</NameTxt>
	<P>There is a big difference between what is happening in Spain and what is happening in this country.  This country has a foreign occupier but Spain does not; it is an internal problem and should be resolved at Spanish level.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>Is that Fine Gael policy?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimHiggins"><NameTxt>Mr. Higgins</NameTxt>
	<P>Members raised the attempt to block the Taoiseach addressing the European Parliament.  I dissociate myself from that.  I had no hand, act or part in it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Who had?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimHiggins"><NameTxt>Mr. Higgins</NameTxt>
	<P>Irish Members of the European Parliament pride ourselves on collectively wearing the green jersey as much as possible in Europe and seek to leave our political divisions at home.  If somebody of that stature wants a right of audience, we should&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>This is not appropriate to the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimHiggins"><NameTxt>Mr. Higgins</NameTxt>
	<P>It has been raised.  Finally, I agree with Senator Norris that this country has a habit of signing up, willy-nilly, to accords, protocols <Col N="1983"/>and agreements.  Ireland, along with 34 other rich nations, signed up to the Kyoto Protocol but we walked away from our commitments regarding the 5% reduction on the 1990 emission levels. This must be addressed and I agree wholeheartedly with the excellent report produced by a former economist with the World Bank, Professor Nicholas Stern, which stated that there are great economic as well as environmental advantages in meeting our requirements on greenhouse gas emissions and on the non-usage of fossil fuels.</P>
    </Speaker><!--Fix-->
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I add my voice to those calling for a debate on global warming.  It seems to be such a huge task that we have felt that there is nothing we can do about it, but Sir Nicholas Stern and Al Gore have shown that this is in the hands of each citizen and that we can do something about it.  However, there are opportunities and not just threats from global warming.  I live on the coast and I have recently seen dolphins in the Irish Sea.  I believe whales and other species have also been seen.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>What about sharks?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>They are in here.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>In Leinster House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I mention this because we had an interesting discussion at the Joint Committee on European Affairs involving the Marine Institute.  Its representative explained to us that the opportunities that we have in Irish waters have not been used sufficiently well.  If he had a magic wand, he said he would like to see us avail of those opportunities.  Global warming can present us with an opportunity if we do something about it ourselves.  We have not met the requirements of the Kyoto Agreement and we must do so, but we should not look at everything as bad news because there are opportunities for us to do something and to gain advantage from that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Brian Hayes congratulated the fire brigade and the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na for policing and taking care of the fireworks displays last night and I wish to say the same for what happened where I come from.  There was a much quieter display but I take his point about community groups obtaining a licence for such displays. There is no greater thrill for a young person than to witness a bonfire and fireworks display and this could be done with parents&rsquo; knowledge if a community display were allowed.  I noticed that when children came to the door last night looking for trick or treat, their parents were outside ensuring they behaved themselves, which is a real improvement.  However, they would not sing as they had lost their voices.</P>
        <P>Senator Brian Hayes also spoke about the Personal Injuries Assessment Bureau, PIAB, and <Col N="1984"/>about the fact that the county manager in his area spent &euro;1.7 million of the council&rsquo;s budget on compensation payments for claims pertaining to footpaths, yet only half of that amount was spent on repairing footpaths.  That is certainly an anomaly.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator O&rsquo;Toole spoke about the debate on the Kyoto Protocol.  He stated that we are languishing at the bottom of the league and that he would welcome a factual debate on the matter.  I read the reports on the PIAB in the newspaper and it was three pages long.  I listened to the debate with Sean O&rsquo;Rourke at 1 p.m. and I thought the chief executive was magnificent.  She left the other lady standing and she gave us all the facts.  Perhaps they have been too modest about themselves and are waiting until the publication of the first annual report before they start blowing their trumpet, but they should not do so.  Insurance premiums have decreased and it is because of the PIAB.  The legal lobby is hurting and that is why this person was engaged to write the pieces in question, but she did not put up a good show.  I would welcome a debate on the Personal Injuries Assessment Board and I hope we can have it next week.</P>
        <P>Everybody spoke about bringing the MEPs before the House and we would be pleased to do so, but the EU ambassador to Washington, John Bruton, will talk to us about his job.  The Cathaoirleach agreed to the EU ambassador to Washington coming to the House to tell us about his job.  He responded very promptly to the invitation which was made by the Clerk.  He will be in the House this day next week and I hope there will be a good muster of Members.  I will be very interested to hear him speak about his job and, for the record, I proposed he be invited.</P>
        <P>Senator O&rsquo;Meara paid tribute to the work of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  She was thankful there were no road deaths but one can never say that.  However, the statistics for last weekend were very good.  She asked about psychiatric services for young people.  We are endeavouring to have that debated in the House.</P>
        <P>Senator Leyden referred to the Bank of Ireland which is offering a form of yellow pack pension for newcomers.  He asked for this to be included in a general debate on pensions.</P>
        <P>Senator Bannon referred to the lack of resources for the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Deputy Commissioner Rock was asked on &ldquo;Morning Ireland&rdquo; whether sufficient money was available for what they need to do and he said that there was more than enough.  We should not discount his word because he is dealing with the money.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">On a point of order, to what area was he referring?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Order, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>He did not mention Longford.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1985"/>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader to reply without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Bannon stated there was a lack of funding for the disabled person&rsquo;s grant and I agree with him.  It is more the slowness with which the matter is approached rather than the money.</P>
        <P>Senator Mansergh said the PIAB has been a catalyst for lower insurance costs and I agree with him.  He is very puzzled by the Basque peace process and the vote in Europe.  Senator Norris referred to the streets in Dublin and he asked for debates on Tibet and on climate change.  He referred to the utter complacency which he alleges exists about climate change.  He referred to the report by Sir Nicholas Stern and how Al Gore has been commissioned to awaken the United States to the dangers of global warming.</P>
        <P>Senator Ormonde asked for a discussion on PIAB and she referred to the debate on RTE Radio 1 yesterday.  She also asked for a debate on the future of Europe in light of the accession of Bulgaria and Romania.  It is a subject worthy of debate.</P>
        <P>Senator Phelan asked for a debate on the primary school medical examination.  He supported Senator O&rsquo;Toole&rsquo;s request for a debate on the recent report on global warming. He referred to the change in the structure of the curriculum for Irish in the leaving certificate.</P>
        <P>I think Senator Browne is the only fireworks in Carlow.  I thought he was the real fireworks in Carlow.  I do not know why all the fireworks went to Carlow because they have definitely gone somewhere.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P>I can testify to that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator also asked for a rolling debate on health and this was echoed by Senator Glynn who also wants a debate on fireworks.  When parents knew it was illegal to have fireworks, they kept a watch on their young people.</P>
        <P>Senator Higgins agreed with Senator Ormonde that this Chamber is a suitable venue to debate what is happening in Europe.  We are clearing Mr. Bruton for this term and hope to have the MEPs next term.  I agree that this is a very suitable Chamber for an in-depth debate on various matters.  Senator Higgins also raised the issue of the Basque peace process.  He also raised the issue of the Taoiseach speaking at the European Parliament and how Irish MEPs endeavour to wear the green jersey.  However, I refer to a very disturbing report by a particular MEP.  I will not name names and I will not talk about her.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>What is the Senator going to do?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not think the Taoiseach is looking for votes in the European Parliament.  He <Col N="1986"/>is a very distinguished person who brought the constitution together in one piece.  It is annoying that one would endeavour to undermine him in such a sneaky way and we on this side of the House will not allow it.  He will acquit himself wonderfully.  She can sulk in the corner if she wishes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That is not relevant.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I apologise, a Chathaoirligh, I could not resist it.  The awful thing about it all is that nobody seems to know it.  Senator Jim Higgins and Deputy Kenny do not know about it.  That is very odd.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That is not on the Order of Business today, irrespective of what was said in the European Parliament.  If we have a debate on the European Parliament, that matter can be raised then but not on the Order of Business today.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I think it is interesting.  Senator Quinn raised the issue of global warming and said there are advantages.  He said the sharks were in our seas and that one could see dolphins and other sea mammals much closer to land because of the warmer seas.</P>
        <P>I seek the indulgence of the Chair to explain again that Mr. Bruton will be in the House next Wednesday.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I understand the Minister is delayed and will not be here until 3.30 p.m.  Consequently, I propose that the sitting be adjourned until then.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P><i>Sitting suspended at 3.20 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</i></P>
 <HtmlBk SectId="3" />
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Official Languages Act 2003:" RHead="Statements"> 
    <Title>Official Languages Act 2003: Statements. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="EamonOCuiv"><TitleTxt>Minister for Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs</TitleTxt><NameTxt>&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v</NameTxt>
	<P>Glacaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an Teach seo as ucht deis a thabhairt dom c&uacute;pla focal a r&aacute; maidir le c&uacute;rsa&iacute; logainmneacha.  T&aacute; c&oacute;ras comhuaineach aistri&uacute;ch&aacute;in ar f&aacute;il sa Teach, agus, mar sin, t&aacute; s&eacute; i gceist agam mo ch&eacute;ad r&aacute;iteas a dh&eacute;anamh i nGaeilge, ach freagr&oacute;idh m&eacute; ceisteanna sa teanga ina dt&oacute;gfar iad ag an deireadh.</P>
        <P>T&aacute; s&eacute; thar a bheith t&aacute;bhachtach go bhfuil an d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht seo ar bun inniu.  Ba  mhaith liom c&uacute;lra a thabhairt maidir le c&eacute;n f&aacute;th gur tugadh isteach Cuid 5 d&rsquo;Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la.  Faoin Acht sin, is f&eacute;idir leis an Aire an leagan Gaeilge de logainm a dhearbh&uacute; le hord&uacute;.  Chomh luath agus a bheidh a leith&eacute;id d&rsquo;ord&uacute; reacht&uacute;il d&eacute;anta i leith aon logainm in aon limist&eacute;ar taobh amuigh den Ghaeltacht, is &eacute; &eacute;ifeacht na reachta&iacute;ochta nua n&aacute; go mbeidh comhst&aacute;das agus comhfheidhm dl&iacute;thi&uacute;il ag leaganacha Gaeilge agus B&eacute;arla an logainm.</P><Col N="1987"/>
        <P Just="Left">Maidir leis na limist&eacute;ir Ghaeltachta, rinne me an tOrd&uacute; Logainmneacha (Ceantair Ghaeltachta) 2004 ar 21 Nollaig 2004, agus th&aacute;inig an t-ord&uacute; i bhfeidhm ar 28 Marta 2005.  Tiocfaidh me ar ais chuige sin n&iacute;os d&eacute;ana&iacute;.  I dtosach, &aacute;fach, n&iacute; miste a mheabhr&uacute; do Sheanad&oacute;ir&iacute; gur ag leaganacha B&eacute;arla na logainmneacha amh&aacute;in, laistigh agus lasmuigh den Ghaeltacht, a bh&iacute; an seasamh oifigi&uacute;il roimh theacht i bhfeidhm Cuid 5 den Acht ar 30 Deireadh F&oacute;mhair 2003.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Is ar Acht Logainmneacha (Foirmeacha Gaeilge) 1973 a bh&iacute; muid ag brath go dt&iacute; sin.  Bh&iacute; an tAcht sin lochtach agus easnamhach.  C&eacute; gur cheadaigh s&eacute; leaganacha &uacute;dar&aacute;sacha Gaeilge de logainmneacha na t&iacute;re le haghaidh cr&iacute;che dl&iacute;, le bheith ioml&aacute;n beacht, chiallaigh se chomh maith de r&eacute;ir dl&iacute; go raibh an logainm f&eacute;in f&oacute;s i mB&eacute;arla amh&aacute;in.  Bh&iacute; doil&eacute;ireacht ann faoi sheasamh an leagan Gaeilge ach i gc&aacute;sanna &aacute;irithe at&aacute; luaite sa dl&iacute; f&eacute;in.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Bh&iacute; se thar a bheith m&iacute;sh&aacute;s&uacute;il go raibh bun-logainmneacha na t&iacute;re &mdash; agus tosa&iacute;ocht acu &oacute; thaobh dl&iacute; de &mdash; i mB&eacute;arla amh&aacute;in agus gan ach leagan Gaeilge a bheith ceadaithe le haghaidh cr&iacute;che oifigi&uacute;la, agus ansin amh&aacute;in sa ch&aacute;s go raibh ord&uacute; cu&iacute; d&eacute;anta ag an Aire.  Is d&aacute; bharr sin a chinn me ar na for&aacute;lacha a bhaineann le logainmneacha a bheith san &aacute;ireamh sa mBille a leagadh os comhair Thithe an Oireachtais agus ar ghlac an tOireachtas leo mar Acht in 2003 &mdash; Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la 2003.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Is &eacute;ard a bh&iacute; i gceist leis na for&aacute;lacha a tugadh isteach mar chuid d&rsquo;Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la n&aacute; comhst&aacute;das a thabhairt do leaganacha Gaeilge logainmneacha na t&iacute;re tar &eacute;is dom mar Aire an t-ord&uacute; cu&iacute; a dh&eacute;anamh, ach amh&aacute;in sa Ghaeltacht, &aacute;it a mbeadh t&uacute;s &aacute;ite ag an leagan Gaeilge.  Cinnte, bh&iacute; s&eacute; riachtanach an t-athr&uacute; seo a dh&eacute;anamh gan dochar d&rsquo;aon &uacute;s&aacute;id laeth&uacute;il, do chomhfhreagras, ceadanna plean&aacute;la, d&rsquo;ionch&uacute;iseamh no d&rsquo;aon n&iacute; eile de rogha an phobail &aacute;iti&uacute;il f&eacute;in.  Ba mhaith liom a r&aacute; go sonrach agus go soil&eacute;ir uair amh&aacute;in eile go dtugann an tAcht cosaint shoil&eacute;ir d&rsquo;&uacute;s&aacute;id an leagan B&eacute;arla de logainmneacha Gaeltachta ach i dtr&iacute; ch&aacute;s.  Is iad na c&aacute;sanna n&aacute;: in Achtanna Oireachtais agus in ionstraim&iacute; reacht&uacute;la; i l&eacute;arsc&aacute;ileanna m&oacute;rsc&aacute;la, arna bhfoilsi&uacute; ag an Ordnance Survey n&oacute; lena cead, a bheidh forordaithe, an cine&aacute;l l&eacute;arsc&aacute;ile a &uacute;s&aacute;idtear i gcl&aacute;r tal&uacute;n seachas l&eacute;arsc&aacute;ileanna turas&oacute;ireachta; agus ar chomhartha b&oacute;thair n&oacute; sr&aacute;ide arna chur suas ag &uacute;dar&aacute;s &aacute;iti&uacute;il n&oacute; thar a cheann.</P>
        <P Just="Left">N&iacute;l aon tionchar, i nd&aacute;ir&iacute;re, ar an ngn&aacute;thshaol ach ag an gceann deireanach sin, a bhaineann leis na comhartha&iacute; b&oacute;thair.  Mar sin, is ar chomhartha&iacute; b&oacute;thair amh&aacute;in a bheidh &eacute;ifeacht no srian &oacute; thaobh &uacute;s&aacute;ide &oacute; l&aacute; go l&aacute; ag Cuid 5 den Acht.  Fi&uacute; ansin, n&iacute;l aon &eacute;ifeacht ag an Acht ar aon chomhartha seachas ar chomhartha&iacute; b&oacute;thair agus sr&aacute;ide arna gcur suas ag &uacute;dar&aacute;is &aacute;iti&uacute;la amh&aacute;in.</P>
        <P>Is &eacute; an c&uacute;lra at&aacute; leis seo n&aacute; go raibh go leor ag&oacute;id&iacute;ochta sa Ghaeltacht sna 60&iacute; in aghaidh comhartha&iacute; b&oacute;thair d&aacute;theangacha mar gur <Col N="1988"/>bhraith pobal na Gaeltachta gurbh &eacute; an t-ainm Gaeilge an t-ainm ceart ar &aacute;iteanna sa Ghaeltacht.  Chuir siad in aghaidh leaganacha B&eacute;arla de logainmneacha a bheith &aacute; mbr&uacute; anuas orthu ag lucht maorlathais, mar a b&rsquo;fhacthas d&oacute;ibh &eacute;.  Mar thoradh air sin, i 1970 rinne Roibeard &Oacute;<?oasys _jy ?>Maoildhia, mar Aire Comhshaoil, ord&uacute; gurbh i nGaeilge amh&aacute;in a bheadh gach comhartha b&oacute;thair ar a mbeadh logainmneacha sa Ghaeltacht.</P>
        <P Just="Left">D&aacute; bhr&iacute; sin, &oacute; 1970 ar aghaidh, is i nGaeilge amh&aacute;in, de r&eacute;ir dl&iacute;, at&aacute; logainmneacha ar chomhartha&iacute; b&oacute;thair i gceantair Ghaeltachta, lena n-&aacute;ir&iacute;tear an comhartha &ldquo;An Daingean&rdquo; mar a bh&iacute; le feice&aacute;il i roinnt mhaith nuacht&aacute;n.  Mar sin f&eacute;in, &aacute;fach &mdash; agus is deacair a thuiscint c&eacute;n f&aacute;th &mdash; lean na l&eacute;arsc&aacute;ileanna a bheith i mB&eacute;arla amh&aacute;in, agus is rud &eacute; sin a bh&iacute; ina &aacute;bhar m&oacute;r mearbhaill.</P>
        <P>Bh&iacute; se soil&eacute;ir, &oacute; thaobh an turas&oacute;ra de, nach ndearna s&eacute; ciall dh&aacute; chine&aacute;l comhartha b&oacute;thair a bheith ann d&rsquo;&aacute;iteanna sa Ghaeltacht, cuid acu d&aacute;theangach agus an chuid eile i nGaeilge amh&aacute;in.  Lu&iacute;onn se le r&eacute;as&uacute;n, mar sin, go bhf&eacute;adfa&iacute; a bheith ag s&uacute;il, m&aacute; thuigeann an turas&oacute;ir an comhartha i nGaeilge amh&aacute;in laistigh den Ghaeltacht, go dtuigfeadh s&eacute; an comhartha c&eacute;anna lasmuigh den Ghaeltacht.  Ar an l&aacute;imh eile, mura dtuigeann s&eacute; comhartha i nGaeilge amh&aacute;in lasmuigh den Ghaeltacht, beidh deacracht den chine&aacute;l c&eacute;anna aige leis laistigh den Ghaeltacht.  Gan amhras, is &eacute; f&iacute;rinne an sc&eacute;il n&aacute; nach g&aacute; go dtuigfeadh an turas&oacute;ir ciall an logainm ar chomhartha&iacute; b&oacute;thair chun a dtreo a aithint agus sl&iacute; a dh&eacute;anamh.  Is &eacute; an rud is t&aacute;bhachta&iacute; don turas&oacute;ir n&aacute; go mbeadh comhartha&iacute;ocht b&oacute;thair mhaith ann agus go mbeadh s&iacute; mar a ch&eacute;ile chuile h&aacute;it, agus go mbeadh s&eacute; &eacute;asca d&oacute;ibh iad si&uacute;d a lean&uacute;int bunaithe ar an l&eacute;arsc&aacute;il.</P>
        <P>Maidir le c&eacute;n f&aacute;th n&aacute;r roghnaigh an tOireachtas comhartha&iacute; b&oacute;thair d&aacute;theangacha i ngach &aacute;it, braitheadh go spreagfadh a leith&eacute;id de chur chuige tuilleadh ag&oacute;id&iacute;ochta agus m&iacute;sh&aacute;stachta sa Ghaeltacht agus go bhfeicf&iacute; &eacute; mar ch&uacute;l&uacute; on gcinneadh, bunaithe ar &eacute;ileamh an phobail, a rinne Roibeard &Oacute; Maoildhia i 1970.  Glacaim leis go bhfuil dh&aacute; theanga sa t&iacute;r seo, ach maidir le l&iacute;on na gcainteoir&iacute; agus an m&eacute;id a &uacute;s&aacute;idtear sa saol poibl&iacute; &iacute;, is &iacute; an Ghaeilge is laige den d&aacute; theanga.  T&aacute; g&aacute;, d&aacute; bhr&iacute; sin, le beartais faoi leith chun &iacute; a chosaint, go h&aacute;irithe sa Ghaeltacht, mar a bhfuil s&iacute; f&oacute;s coinnithe mar theanga labhartha an phobail.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Socra&iacute;odh, mar sin, gurbh &eacute; an cur chuige ba chomhsheasmha&iacute; agus ba loighci&uacute;la n&aacute; go dtaispe&aacute;nfadh gach comhartha b&oacute;thair an t-ainm oifigi&uacute;il amh&aacute;in d&rsquo;&aacute;iteanna sa Ghaeltacht.  Rinneadh socruithe, &aacute;fach, go dtaisp&eacute;anfadh l&eacute;arsc&aacute;ileanna turas&oacute;ireachta a chuir an Ordnance Survey amach an d&aacute; leagan den ainm, is &eacute; sin, an leagan Gaeilge agus an leagan B&eacute;arla, chun go bhf&eacute;adfadh turas&oacute;ir&iacute; an &aacute;it a bheadh &aacute; lorg acu a aithint &oacute; mhapa&iacute; b&oacute;thair.  N&iacute; amhlaidh a bh&iacute; an sc&eacute;al i gc&oacute;na&iacute; san am at&aacute; caite.  T&aacute; tugtha le fios freisin ag Collins agus ag an AA go nd&eacute;anfaid&iacute;s amhlaidh, agus i gc&aacute;s an AA t&aacute; ainmneacha <Col N="1989"/>d&aacute;theangacha ar &aacute;iteanna sa Ghaeltacht acu ar chuid d&aacute; l&eacute;arsc&aacute;ileanna cheana f&eacute;in.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Cuireann an chonsp&oacute;id faoin ainm &ldquo;An Daingean&rdquo; an-bhr&oacute;n orm.  Maidir leis an logainm f&eacute;in, t&aacute; ceisteanna agus arg&oacute;int&iacute; a bhaineann leis an &aacute;bhar sin a phl&eacute;ifidh muid ar ball.  Is &eacute; an rud is measa faoi chuid mhaith den d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht n&aacute; an m&iacute;-eolas a bhain l&eacute;i on t&uacute;s.  Fi&uacute; sa <i>Kerryman</i> an tseachtain seo chaite, d&uacute;irt an eagarfhocal &eacute; seo.</P>
        <P LI="1">Only Minister &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v can explain why he and his department failed so miserably in applying any foresight or element of democracy or consultation to the Placenames (Ceantair Gaeltachta) Order 2004 which is at the root of all the controversy in West Kerry.</P>
        <P FLI="0" Just="Left">Is fi&uacute; go m&oacute;r dom, sa chomhth&eacute;acs sin, cur s&iacute;os a dh&eacute;anamh ar na c&eacute;imeanna a ghlac me chun an t-eolas is forleithne a chur i l&aacute;thair an phobail agus na bp&aacute;irtithe leasmhara uile.  Ba &eacute; seo an ch&eacute;ad uair ariamh a raibh dul i gcomhairle phoibl&iacute; ag Aire faoi logainmneacha.  I m&iacute; I&uacute;il 2003, d&rsquo;eisigh mo Roinn preaseisi&uacute;int ar cheist na logainmneacha, agus t&aacute; 15 f&oacute;gra eile eisithe &oacute; shin a bhaineann le logainmneacha.  T&aacute; m&eacute; &aacute; cur sin ar f&aacute;il do Bhaill an T&iacute; seo.</P>
        <P>I m&iacute; Mheithimh 2004, cuireadh dr&eacute;achtch&oacute;ip den ord&uacute; chuig na gr&uacute;pa&iacute; pobail go l&eacute;ir i ngach ceantar Gaeltachta &mdash; timpeall 80 ar fad, agus 15 cinn acu i nGaeltacht Chiarra&iacute; &mdash; chuig na comhairl&iacute; contae cu&iacute; agus chuig &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta.  Bh&iacute; s&iacute; ar f&aacute;il ar l&aacute;ithre&aacute;n gr&eacute;as&aacute;in na Roinne Gn&oacute;tha&iacute; Pobail, Tuaithe agus Gaeltachta freisin.  Tar &eacute;is sin, ritheadh pr&oacute;iseas comhairli&uacute;ch&aacute;in dh&aacute;-mh&iacute; faoina raibh deis ag na pobail &aacute;iti&uacute;la sna ceantair Ghaeltachta &eacute;ags&uacute;la na logainmneacha a bh&iacute; molta ag an gCoimisi&uacute;n a phl&eacute;.</P>
        <P>I bpreaseisi&uacute;int i m&iacute; I&uacute;il 2004, tugadh cuireadh do phobail agus do dhaoine &aacute;iti&uacute;la a dtuairim&iacute; faoi na leaganacha Gaeilge a bh&iacute; molta san dr&eacute;achtord&uacute; a chur faoi bhr&aacute;id bhrainse na logainmneacha sa Roinn faoin 31 L&uacute;nasa 2004.  Tugadh poibl&iacute;ocht don phr&oacute;iseas sin sna me&aacute;in &eacute;ags&uacute;la Gaeilge agus Gaeltachta, go h&aacute;irithe ar Raidi&oacute; na Gaeltachta, TG4, <i>Foinse</i> agus <i>L&aacute;</i>, agus mar thoradh air sin bh&iacute; d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht bhr&iacute;omhar faoi leaganacha &aacute;irithe de na logainmneacha ar na me&aacute;in sin.</P>
        <P>Ar 23 I&uacute;il 2004, v&oacute;t&aacute;il bord &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta d&rsquo;aonghuth i bhf&aacute;bhar an dr&eacute;achtordaithe, agus l&eacute;irigh s&eacute; a dtaca&iacute;ocht ioml&aacute;n, d&rsquo;aonghuth, ina leith.  T&aacute; 20 comhalta ar bhord &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta.  Toghann toghlach na Gaeltachta 17 acu go d&iacute;reach, agus ceapann an tAire Gn&oacute;tha&iacute; Pobail, Tuaithe agus Gaeltachta an tri&uacute;r eile, an cathaoirleach san &aacute;ireamh.  Is daoine Gaeltachta iad an tri&uacute;r a cheapann an tAire freisin.</P>
        <P>I m&iacute; Mhe&aacute;n F&oacute;mhair 2004, rinne oifigigh de chuid na Roinne Gn&oacute;tha&iacute; Pobail, Tuaithe agus Gaeltachta cur i l&aacute;thair eile do bhord &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta chun deis a thabhairt d&oacute; pl&eacute; ioml&aacute;n a dh&eacute;anamh ar mhionsonra&iacute; an ordaithe agus ar na himpleachta&iacute; a bhainfeadh leis.  I m&iacute; Aibre&aacute;in <Col N="1990"/>2005, bhronn me c&oacute;ipeanna ceangailte den Ord&uacute; Logainmneacha (Ceantair Ghaeltachta) 2004 ar ionadaithe na gcomharchumann Gaeltachta agus na gcomhairl&iacute; chontae cu&iacute;.</P>
        <P Just="Left">N&iacute;l ansin ach liosta garbh, gan tr&aacute;cht ar chl&aacute;racha a rinne oifigeach mo Roinne ar Raidi&oacute; na Gaeltachta ag pl&eacute; na ceiste go mion, altanna a ritheadh i bh<i>Foinse</i> agus i <i>L&aacute;</i>, m&iacute;reanna nuachta a ritheadh ar TG4, agus araile.  Cuireadh an t-eolas faoin ord&uacute; seo chuig gach seomra nuachta sa t&iacute;r, Gaeilge agus B&eacute;arla, gan tr&aacute;cht ar ghlaoanna guth&aacute;in agus n&oacute;ta&iacute; eolais a scaipeadh orthu.  N&iacute; f&eacute;idir le mo Roinn n&aacute; m&eacute; f&eacute;in tada a dh&eacute;anamh faoi muna bhfuil suim ag na me&aacute;in Bh&eacute;arla i gc&uacute;rsa&iacute; Gaeilge seachas nuair at&aacute; drochsc&eacute;al ann.</P>
        <P>Ba mhaith liom glacadh leis an deis seo chun na f&iacute;ric&iacute; a bhaineann le c&aacute;s An Daingin a chur ar thaifead an T&iacute; seo.  C&eacute; mh&eacute;ad ama at&aacute; f&aacute;gtha agam?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryHenry"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister may have as much time as he wants.  I am very interested in it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EamonOCuiv"><NameTxt>&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Ba mhaith liom glacadh leis an deis seo chun na f&iacute;ric&iacute; a bhaineann le c&aacute;s An Daingin a chur ar thaifead an T&iacute; seo.  T&aacute; breis is 2,300 logainm cl&uacute;daithe faoin Ord&uacute; Logainmneacha (Ceantair Gaeltachta) 2004, agus, go bhfios dom, n&iacute;l fadhb n&aacute; deacracht l&eacute;irithe ach i gc&aacute;s amh&aacute;in, agus mar is eol don t&iacute;r ar fad faoin tr&aacute;th seo, is d&oacute;cha, is &eacute; sin An Daingean i nGaeltacht Chiarra&iacute;.</P>
        <P Just="Left">T&aacute; se t&aacute;bhachtach go gcuimhneofa&iacute; gur foils&iacute;odh dr&eacute;acht den ord&uacute; roinnt m&iacute;onna roimhr&eacute; ar mhaithe le dul i gcomhairle le pobal na Gaeltachta.  Teasta&iacute;onn uaim go mbeadh s&eacute; seo r&iacute;-shoil&eacute;ir.  Mar sin, bh&iacute; an deis ag p&aacute;irt&iacute; ar bith aon tuairim&iacute; a bh&iacute; aige maidir leis an dr&eacute;achtord&uacute; a nochtadh sula ndearna me an t-ord&uacute;.  Mar thoradh ar an bpr&oacute;iseas seo, fuarthas 33 aighneacht san ioml&aacute;n ar an dr&eacute;achtord&uacute;, a bhain le suas le 250 logainm.  Cuireadh na haighneachta&iacute; faoi bhr&aacute;id Choimisi&uacute;n na Logainmneacha, agus rinneadh roinnt leasuithe ar an ord&uacute; bunaithe orthu sin.  Rinneadh an t-ord&uacute; ar chomhairle a fuair me on gcoimisi&uacute;n.</P>
        <P>N&iacute;or th&aacute;inig aon aighneacht chugam faoin Daingean n&oacute; Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is.  T&aacute; an-phl&eacute; d&eacute;anta maidir le c&eacute; acu is cirte.  T&aacute; an leagan oifigi&uacute;il, &ldquo;An Daingean&rdquo;, ag dul siar i bhfad.  Bh&iacute; P&aacute;draig &Oacute; Siochfhradha, &ldquo;An Seabhac&rdquo;, m&aacute;s buan mo chuimhne, iar-Bhall den Teach seo, mar chathaoirleach ar Choimisi&uacute;n na Logainmneacha nuair a moladh &ldquo;An Daingean&rdquo; mar an leagan &uacute;dar&aacute;sach.  N&iacute; d&oacute;igh liom go bhf&eacute;adfadh &eacute;inne a r&aacute; nach raibh aon eolas ag an Seabhac ar Ghaeilge Chorca Dhuibhne.  Lena chois sin, n&iacute; m&oacute;r dom a lua go bhfuil &ldquo;An Daingean&rdquo; leagtha amach mar ainm an bhaile ar chomhartha&iacute; b&oacute;thair laistigh den Ghaeltacht &oacute;n mbliain 1970 anall, agus go bhfios dom n&iacute; bhfuarthas oiread is gear&aacute;n n&oacute; aighneacht amh&aacute;in ag clamhs&aacute;n gur &ldquo;Dain<Col N="1991"/>gean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is&rdquo; ar cheart a bheith ann in &aacute;it &ldquo;An Daingean&rdquo;.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Ba mhaith liom d&iacute;ri&uacute; anois go sonrach ar an bpobalbhreith a reacht&aacute;ladh sa Daingean le gairid agus a tharraing go leor poibl&iacute;ochta, n&iacute; amh&aacute;in go h&aacute;iti&uacute;il ach go n&aacute;isi&uacute;nta agus go hidirn&aacute;isi&uacute;nta.  Mar at&aacute; r&aacute;ite agam go minic roimhe seo, de r&eacute;ir na comhairle dl&iacute; at&aacute; faighte agam &oacute;n Ard-Aighne, n&iacute;l aon &eacute;ifeacht dl&iacute;thi&uacute;il, faoi na hAchtanna Rialtais &Aacute;iti&uacute;il 1946 agus 2001, ag an bpobalbhreith seo, mar nach f&eacute;idir leis an bpobalbhreith an t-ord&uacute; faoi Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la 2003 a chur ar ceal.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Agus &eacute; sin r&aacute;ite, d&uacute;irt me go soil&eacute;ir le toscaireacht &oacute; Chomhairle Chontae Chiarra&iacute;, nuair a chas me l&eacute;i i m&iacute; an Mheithimh i mbliana, n&aacute;r bhain se liomsa an cinneadh a dh&eacute;anamh, n&aacute; aon tuairim a thabhairt ina leith, m&aacute; bh&iacute; an chomhairle contae ag iarraidh pobalbhreith a reacht&aacute;il mar reifreann comhchomhairleach.  Mheabhraigh m&eacute; don toscaireacht an uair sin, &aacute;fach, nach mbaineann an pr&oacute;iseas at&aacute; leagtha amach sna hAchtanna Rialtais &Aacute;iti&uacute;il leis an bpr&oacute;iseas comhchomhairleach a bhaineann le Cuid 5 den Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la 2003.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Agus &eacute; sin r&aacute;ite, d&uacute;irt me le baill na comhairle, d&aacute; dtiocfaid&iacute;s chugam tar &eacute;is na pobalbhreithe, mar ionadaithe tofa an phobail, le hiarratas a bheadh ind&eacute;anta faoin dl&iacute;, go mbeinn bre&aacute; s&aacute;sta staid&eacute;ar a dh&eacute;anamh air.  Ag an gcruinni&uacute; a bh&iacute; agam leis an toscaireacht &oacute; Chomhairle Chontae Chiarra&iacute; i m&iacute; an Mheithimh, rinneamar pl&eacute; ar thr&iacute; rogha &eacute;ags&uacute;il maidir le hainm oifigi&uacute;il bhaile an Daingin.  B&rsquo;iad na tr&iacute; rogha sin: an t-ord&uacute; a athr&uacute; le &ldquo;Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is&rdquo; a chur in &aacute;it &ldquo;An Daingean&rdquo;; an tOrd&uacute; Logainmneacha a ch&uacute;lghairm i gc&aacute;s &ldquo;Dingle&rdquo; agus &ldquo;An Daingean&rdquo; amh&aacute;in; agus &ldquo;An Daingean&rdquo; a athr&uacute; go &ldquo;Dingle Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is&rdquo;.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Maidir leis an gc&eacute;ad rogha d&iacute;obh seo, is &eacute; sin an t-ord&uacute; a athr&uacute; le go mbeadh &ldquo;Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is&rdquo; ann in &aacute;it &ldquo;An Daingean&rdquo;, an ceann is fusa.  N&iacute;l aon deacracht agamsa agus t&aacute; s&eacute; seo curtha in i&uacute;l agam do Chomhairle Chontae Chiarra&iacute;.  D&uacute;irt m&eacute; l&eacute;i siar i nDeireadh F&oacute;mhair 2004 go nd&eacute;anfainn &eacute; sin l&aacute;ithreach.  N&iacute;or th&aacute;ngthas chugam &oacute; shin, &aacute;fach.  T&aacute; s&eacute; m&iacute;nithe agam do Chomhairle Chontae Chiarra&iacute; go bhfuiltear m&iacute;chinnte maidir leis na himpleachta&iacute; dl&iacute; a bhaineann leis seo.  Is &eacute; sin, n&iacute; bheadh aon amhras ach go dtiocfadh s&eacute; ar ais go dt&iacute; Dingle.  N&iacute;l m&eacute; cinnte cad a tharl&oacute;dh don leagan Gaeilge.  T&aacute; breis comhairle &aacute; lorg agam anois &oacute; Oifig an Ard-Aighne ina leith.  D&rsquo;fheadfa&iacute; go gcaillfeadh an leagan Gaeilge a st&aacute;das dl&iacute;thi&uacute;il ar fad.  N&iacute; bheadh s&eacute; f&eacute;ar&aacute;ilte a r&aacute; le comhairle contae rud a dh&eacute;anamh muna mbeimis cinnte c&eacute;n toradh a bheadh air.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Maidir leis an tr&iacute;&uacute; rogha, is &eacute; sin &ldquo;An Daingean&rdquo; a athr&uacute; go &ldquo;Dingle Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is&rdquo;, t&aacute; s&eacute; m&iacute;nithe agam don chomhairle contae &mdash; agus n&iacute; m&oacute;r dom &eacute; a r&aacute; go soil&eacute;ir ar&iacute;s &mdash; nach f&eacute;idir liom, faoin dl&iacute;, logainm d&aacute;theangach a chead&uacute; do cheantar Gaeltachta.  T&aacute; s&eacute; curtha in i&uacute;l agam don <Col N="1992"/>chomhairle contae nach f&eacute;idir liom n&aacute; leis an Rialtas glacadh le hiarratas uaithi ar &eacute;ileamh a leith&eacute;id d&rsquo;athr&uacute; a dh&eacute;anamh.</P>
        <P>Arda&iacute;onn s&eacute; seo an cheist c&eacute;n f&aacute;th nach n-athra&iacute;m an dl&iacute;.  Mar at&aacute; r&aacute;ite agam cheana f&eacute;in, ar nd&oacute;igh, t&aacute; 2,300 ainm i gceist leis an Ord&uacute; Logainmneacha a rinne m&eacute;.  &Oacute; tharla go bhfuil an chuid is m&oacute; de na pobail Ghaeltachta s&aacute;sta leis an m&eacute;id at&aacute; curtha i gcr&iacute;ch maidir le st&aacute;das dl&iacute;thi&uacute;il a gcuid logainmneacha, bheadh s&eacute; i gcoinne an daonlathais dl&iacute; at&aacute; aontaithe ag an mh&oacute;rchuid de mhuintir na Gaeltachta a athr&uacute;.  Sin an &aacute;it a bhfuil an fhadhb.  &Oacute;n bpl&eacute; agus &oacute;n rud a chloiseamar &mdash; agus n&iacute; f&eacute;idir le h&eacute;inne a r&aacute; nach bhfuil a fhios ag an saol F&oacute;dhla maidir leis an ord&uacute; a rinneadh &mdash; n&iacute; l&eacute;ir go bhfuil aon &eacute;ileamh n&oacute; m&iacute;sh&aacute;stacht go ginear&aacute;lta sna Gaeltachta&iacute;, agus go m&oacute;rmh&oacute;r sna Gaeltachta&iacute; l&aacute;idre ina labhra&iacute;tear an Ghaeilge mar theanga pobail.  Mar sin, mar lucht d&eacute;anta reachta&iacute;ochta, caithfimid breathn&uacute; ar an gceist sin.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Mar fhocal scoir, &oacute;s rud &eacute; gur iarr an phobalbhreith ar na toghth&oacute;ir&iacute; v&oacute;t&aacute;il ar aon rogha amh&aacute;in, rogha at&aacute; dodh&eacute;anta faoin dl&iacute; i mo thuairim, scr&iacute;obh m&eacute; chuig bainisteoir Chomhairle Chontae Chiarra&iacute; sula raibh an phobalbhreith cr&iacute;ochnaithe, agus lorg m&eacute; cruinni&uacute; le comhairleoir&iacute; Chontae Chiarra&iacute; chun an dl&iacute; a bhaineann leis an gceist seo a mh&iacute;ni&uacute; go soil&eacute;ir, mar aon leis na roghanna r&eacute;ad&uacute;la at&aacute; ann d&oacute;ibh a phl&eacute;.  S&iacute;lim go bhfaighidh muid an bealach is fearr ar aghaidh m&aacute; shu&iacute;mid s&iacute;os agus m&aacute; bhreathna&iacute;mid go f&iacute;orch&uacute;iseach ar na f&iacute;or-roghanna at&aacute; ann taobh istigh den dl&iacute;.  M&aacute; t&aacute; siad ag iarraidh an dl&iacute; a athr&uacute;, ba cheart d&uacute;inn &eacute; sin a phl&eacute;, agus m&iacute;neoidh m&eacute; na pr&oacute;isis a gcaithf&iacute; dul tr&iacute;othu agus an comhairli&uacute;ch&aacute;n a chaithf&iacute; glacadh le pobal i bhfad n&iacute;os leithne d&aacute; mbeadh a leith&eacute;id sin i gceist.</P>
        <P>Beidh m&eacute; ag casadh le comhairleoir&iacute; Chontae Chiarra&iacute; ar 17 Samhain 2006, agus t&aacute; s&uacute;il agam go mbeidh pl&eacute; r&eacute;ad&uacute;il tairbheach dearfach againn i dtaobh na ceiste seo.  T&aacute; socr&uacute; &aacute; dh&eacute;anamh freisin agam freastal ar chruinni&uacute; poibl&iacute; i mbaile an Daingin f&eacute;in le deis a thabhairt don phobal an cheist a phl&eacute; liom go d&iacute;reach.  Nuair a bheas an pl&eacute; sin ar fad d&eacute;anta, tabharfaidh m&eacute; deis don chomhairle contae teacht ar ais chugam agus molta&iacute; a dh&eacute;anamh.  Tar &eacute;is dom na molta&iacute; sin a fh&aacute;il, d&eacute;anfaidh m&eacute; scr&uacute;d&uacute; orthu, agus f&eacute;achfaidh m&eacute; c&eacute;n bealach is f&eacute;idir linn dul ar aghaidh &oacute;n &aacute;it ina bhfuil muid.</P>
        <P>Is &eacute; an &aacute;it ina bhfuilimid n&aacute; gur achta&iacute;odh dl&iacute; sa Teach seo a thug, den ch&eacute;ad uair, st&aacute;das do logainmneacha Gaeltachta agus Gaeilge ar fud na t&iacute;re.  Is fi&uacute; a aithint sa t&iacute;r seo gurb &iacute; an Ghaeilge an ch&eacute;ad teanga oifigi&uacute;il.  Ar 1 Ean&aacute;ir, beidh s&iacute; ina teanga oifigi&uacute;il oibre san Aontas Eorpach.  N&iacute; raibh muid ach ag tabhairt st&aacute;das dl&iacute;thi&uacute;il cothrom do na logainmneacha Gaeilge ar fud na t&iacute;re.  I m&oacute;rchuid na gc&aacute;sanna, b&rsquo;shin iad na bunlogainmneacha, mar tagann an chuid is m&oacute; de na logainmneacha B&eacute;arla &oacute;n nGaeilge sa ch&eacute;ad &aacute;it.</P>
        <P>Maidir leis an nGaeltacht, t&aacute; c&aacute;s faoi leith ann.  Mhol m&eacute; &eacute;, agus ghlac Tithe an Oireachtais leis <Col N="1993"/>sin.  Nuair a bh&iacute; an d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht ar bun sa Teach seo, iarradh orm go leor ruda&iacute; eile a dh&eacute;anamh maidir le comhartha&iacute;ocht agus ruda&iacute; eile sa Ghaeltacht.  Glacadh leis seo.  Rinne m&eacute; dianmhachnamh ar an gceist seo maidir leis na comhartha&iacute; d&aacute;theangacha taobh istigh agus taobh amuigh den Ghaeltacht agus na comhartha&iacute; b&oacute;thair.  Sh&iacute;l m&eacute; ag an am gur ghlac m&eacute; le comhr&eacute;iteach a bh&iacute; me&aacute;ite, is &eacute; sin, go mbeadh na l&eacute;arsc&aacute;ileanna d&aacute;theangach agus na comhartha&iacute; mar a ch&eacute;ile taobh istigh agus taobh amuigh den nGaeltacht.</P>
        <P>Go ginear&aacute;lta &mdash; agus feictear dom go bhfuil glactha leis seo ar fud na Gaeltachta &mdash; t&aacute; fadhb sa Daingean agus s&iacute;lim gurb &eacute; an t-aon r&eacute;iteach air seo anois n&aacute; go bpl&eacute;ifear &eacute; seo leis an gcomhairle contae.  Ina dhiaidh sin, &eacute;istfidh m&eacute; go beacht agus go c&uacute;ramach le molta&iacute; na comhairle contae.  Nuair a bheas siad sin faighte agam, feicfidh m&eacute; c&eacute;ard is f&eacute;idir a dh&eacute;anamh leis an fhadhb seo a r&eacute;iteach.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Mr. O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>F&aacute;ilt&iacute;m roimh an Aire, at&aacute; istigh sa Teach ar&iacute;s inniu, agus go m&oacute;r leis an alt deireanach nuair a d&uacute;irt s&eacute; go raibh s&eacute; s&aacute;sta an rud seo a phl&eacute; agus go n-&eacute;istfeadh s&eacute; leis na molta&iacute; a bheadh ag teacht &oacute; Chiarra&iacute; ar an cheist chasta seo, c&eacute; nach bhfuil s&iacute; chomh casta sin.</P>
        <P>Is maith an rud &eacute; seo a chur ar an taifead inniu.  Aonta&iacute;m go m&oacute;r lena l&aacute;n de na ruda&iacute; at&aacute; r&aacute;ite ag an Aire. Mar shampla, aonta&iacute;m go m&oacute;r leis an m&eacute;id a d&uacute;irt s&eacute; dh&aacute; bhliain &oacute; shin sa D&aacute;il i rith Ch&eacute;im an Choiste d&rsquo;Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la.  D&uacute;irt s&eacute; go raibh locht ag baint leis an dl&iacute; mar a bh&iacute; agus go raibh doil&eacute;ireacht mar gheall ar st&aacute;das oifigi&uacute;il ainmneacha &aacute;ite Gaoluinne sna Gaeltachta&iacute;.  D&rsquo;aontaigh gach aon duine leis sin.</P>
        <P Just="Left">An uair sin, chuireamar leas&uacute; s&iacute;os &oacute; Fhine Gael le go mbeadh d&aacute;theangachas ann sa tsl&iacute; is go mbeadh st&aacute;das oifigi&uacute;il ag an ainm Gaoluinne.  N&iacute;os m&oacute; n&aacute; sin, chuir Sinn F&eacute;in leas&uacute; eile s&iacute;os le go mbeadh ainm d&aacute;theangach ann ach le t&uacute;s &aacute;ite ag an nGaoluinn.  Sin an m&eacute;id a d&uacute;irt an tAire anseo inniu.  D&uacute;irt s&eacute; gur ch&oacute;ir go mbeadh comhst&aacute;das leis an ainm.  N&iacute;l a fhios agam go beacht cad is br&iacute; le &ldquo;comhst&aacute;das&rdquo; nuair nach bhfuil ach an t-aon ainm amh&aacute;in in aon teanga amh&aacute;in i gceist, ach tuigim an m&eacute;id a bh&iacute; ar aigne aige.  Bh&iacute;os go m&oacute;r i bhfabhar t&uacute;s &aacute;ite a thabhairt don ainm Gaoluinne, agus d&uacute;irt m&eacute; &eacute; sin leis an Aire go minic an uair sin.</P>
        <P>Where did it go wrong?  Ag f&eacute;achaint ar an gconsp&oacute;id sa Daingean, mar a d&uacute;irt m&eacute; go minic leis an Aire, t&aacute; tr&iacute; ainm againn ar an &aacute;it sin.  T&aacute; An Daingean, Dingle agus Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is ann.  &Uacute;s&aacute;idim &ldquo;An Daingean&rdquo; i gc&oacute;na&iacute; cos&uacute;il le duine in north Wicklow a d&eacute;arfadh &ldquo;Newtown&rdquo; i gcomhair &ldquo;Newtownmountkennedy&rdquo;.  D&eacute;arfadh duine eile &ldquo;Carrick&rdquo;, and he might be talking about Carrick-on-Shannon if he lived near it, or Carrick-on-Suir if he lived near there.  D&aacute; gcuirf&iacute; ceist ar dhuine i mBaile &Aacute;tha Cliath cad as a dt&aacute;inig s&eacute;, &aacute;fach, d&eacute;arfadh s&eacute; &ldquo;Carrick-on-Shannon&rdquo; n&oacute; &ldquo;Carrick whatever&rdquo;.  Is &eacute; an tsl&iacute; ch&eacute;anna d&uacute;inn. <Col N="1994"/> Agus m&eacute; ag caint le duine &oacute; m&rsquo;&aacute;it d&uacute;chais f&eacute;in anseo sa chathair, is &ldquo;An Daingean&rdquo; a d&eacute;arfaimis lena ch&eacute;ile.  D&aacute; mba rud &eacute; go rabhas ag caint le aon duine eile, is &ldquo;Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is&rdquo; a d&eacute;arfainn n&oacute; &ldquo;Dingle&rdquo;.  T&aacute; &aacute;it ar leith ag na teangacha.</P>
        <P>Ag f&eacute;achaint ar an m&eacute;id at&aacute; r&aacute;ite ag an Aire, t&aacute;im an-soil&eacute;ir ar an m&eacute;id seo.  N&iacute;lim ag r&aacute; an mh&eacute;id seo chun consp&oacute;id a bheith agam leis an Aire.  T&aacute;im cinnte sa mh&eacute;id seo.  Maidir lena bhfuil r&aacute;ite ag an Ard-Aighne, deireann s&eacute; mar gheall ar an bpobalbhreith nach bhfuil aon &eacute;ifeacht dl&iacute;thi&uacute;il aici faoi na hAchtanna Rialtais &Aacute;iti&uacute;il 1946 agus 2001 mar nach f&eacute;idir leis an bpobalbhreith an t-ord&uacute; faoi Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la 2003 a chur ar ceal.  That is a classic miscall.  It is absolute truth, except that n&iacute;l aon duine ar domhain ag iarraidh &eacute; sin a bhr&uacute; siar scornach an Aire.  That is not what is going on here.  N&iacute; raibh pobalbhreith ag muintir Dhaingin U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is chun ord&uacute; a chur ar ceal.  N&iacute; h&eacute; sin an ch&uacute;is gur th&oacute;gadar an phobalbhreith n&oacute; gur chuir an chomhairle contae &iacute; ar si&uacute;l in aon chor.  Ba &eacute; an rud a dheineadar n&aacute; &eacute; seo.  Bh&iacute; pobalbhreith acu chun ainm nua a roghn&uacute;.  N&iacute; raibh siad ag d&eacute;anamh aon cheangail idir an phobalbhreith agus Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la.  Let us be clear that they are two separate issues.  Unfortunately, they have been connected.  &Aacute;it &eacute;igin eile, deireann an tAire nach cuid den phr&oacute;iseas comhchomhairleach a bhaineann le Cuid 5 d&rsquo;Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la &eacute;.  This is right.  I do not know of any kind of pr&oacute;iseas comhchomhairleach at&aacute; i gCuid 5 d&rsquo;Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la seachas dul i gcomhair le Coimisi&uacute;n na Logainmneacha.  This is not part of that and nobody is saying it is.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">4 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P>For the Minister to keep emphasising that the plebiscite has no place in the Official Languages Act and that it is not part of a consultation process under the Act is correct but irrelevant.  N&iacute; bhaineann s&eacute; ar chor ar bith leis an m&eacute;id a bh&iacute; ar si&uacute;l acu.  Dheineamar pl&eacute; air sin.  N&iacute; rabhamar in ann c&uacute;l&uacute; siar n&oacute; an t-ord&uacute; a chur ar ceal tr&iacute; aon cheann de na pr&oacute;isis sin, agus is &eacute; sin an f&aacute;th gur chuamar go dt&iacute; na hAchtanna Rialtais &Aacute;iti&uacute;il.</P>
        <P>Fuaireamar an m&eacute;id seo amach.  N&iacute; chuireann Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la na hAchtanna Rialtais &Aacute;iti&uacute;il ar ceal.  The Act does nothing to reverse the Acht Rialtais &Aacute;iti&uacute;il.  Mar at&aacute; fhios go maith ag an Aire, fi&uacute; san t-aon reference in aon chor at&aacute; ann, n&iacute; f&eacute;idir le Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la aon chinneadh at&aacute; d&eacute;anta faoin Local Government Act 2001 a chur ar ceal.  Gan amhras, n&iacute;l t&uacute;s curtha leis an Local Government Act 2001, so n&iacute;l aon relevance ag baint leis sin ach oiread.  N&iacute; chuireann Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la an tAcht Rialtais &Aacute;iti&uacute;il ar ceal, agus mar sin, b&rsquo;fh&iacute;or don Ard-Aighne nuair a d&uacute;irt s&eacute; nach f&eacute;idir leis an bpobalbhreith an t-ord&uacute; a chur ar ceal ach oiread.  They are not connected and stand on their own two feet.</P>
        <P>Ar an dtaobh eile den sc&eacute;al, n&iacute; bhraitheann an tAcht Rialtais &Aacute;iti&uacute;il ar an Aire Ghn&oacute;tha&iacute; Pobail, Tuaithe agus Gaeltachta.  N&iacute;l aon st&aacute;das oifigi&uacute;il <Col N="1995"/>ag an Aire sin in aon cheann de na hAchtanna Rialtais &Aacute;iti&uacute;il.  It is true for the Minister to say that he does not have to take direction from the plebiscite in Dingle to reverse the decision under the Official Languages Act.  The two processes are separate.  There is no process provided in the Act for the people to speak in the way they did.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Is &eacute; an rud a chuir isteach go m&oacute;r orm n&aacute; go raibh Acht na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la ag baint &oacute; mhuintir na nGaeltachta&iacute; a gceart sibhialta chun cinneadh a bheith acu ar ainm a n-&aacute;it d&uacute;chais f&eacute;in.  That was my point in getting involved.  D&uacute;irt m&eacute; gur cheart an ceart sin a thabhairt ar ais d&oacute;ibh, and they can decide on whatever name they wish.  N&iacute; bhraitheann na hAchtanna ar a ch&eacute;ile.  They are separate institutions.  N&iacute; dh&eacute;anann an pr&oacute;iseas san Acht Rialtais &Aacute;iti&uacute;il aon idirdheal&uacute; idir Gaeltacht agus Galltacht.  That is an absolute fact, a legal fact.  The Local Government Act 1946 makes no distinction between &ldquo;Gaeltacht&rdquo; and &ldquo;Galltacht&rdquo;.  The Minister knows what is listed, including civil parishes, localities, etc., ach n&iacute; dh&eacute;antar aon idirdheal&uacute; idir Gaeltacht agus Galltacht.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I am not raising these points for argumentation.  T&aacute; s&eacute; seo r&aacute;ite agam tar &eacute;is dianscr&uacute;daithe a dh&eacute;anamh ar an Acht agus dul i gcomhairle le habhc&oacute;ide agus people of great distinction, in their own eyes at least, about the implications of the Act.  Nothing I would put on the record today is incorrect and therefore a solution exists if we want it.  N&iacute; dh&eacute;anann an pr&oacute;iseas san Acht Rialtais &Aacute;iti&uacute;il aon idirdheal&uacute; idir Gaeltacht agus Galltacht.  Is f&eacute;idir leis an Rialtas cinneadh a dh&eacute;anamh.</P>
        <P>Under the 1946 Act, the returning officer in the plebiscite makes the decision thereon and then the county council makes the application to the Government, rather than just to the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government or the Minister for Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs.  In this sense, t&aacute; an ceart ag an Aire nuair a deireann s&eacute; nach bhfuil an fhreagracht air chun &eacute;isteacht leis an plebiscite.  &Oacute; thaobh bhunphrionsabail an daonlathais de, chun aon rud a dh&eacute;anamh ba ch&oacute;ir d&oacute;ibh dul i gcomhairle leis an bpobal, and in fairness to him, t&aacute; s&eacute; sin r&aacute;ite aige go minic &oacute; t&oacute;gadh an plebiscite.</P>
        <P>It is very simple.  The 1946 Act sets out an absolutely legal process.  It was incorrect for the Minister to say, at some stage, that the county council was not acting within the appropriate legislation.  It was acting within the 1946 Act, as amended by way of the Act of 1953, the guidelines of 1956 and an amendment in the 1990s.</P>
        <P>Under the process, a certain percentage must vote in favour of the proposal, which they did, after which the council makes an application for a change of name to the Government.  This process is legal and sound in all sorts of ways.  It is not correct to use the argument about the tie between the plebiscite and the Official Languages Act.  The Minister is correct in that they are two <Col N="1996"/>separate issues and follow two separate patterns.  There was no way to go through with it under the Official Languages Act.  The Minister must therefore convince the Government go bhfuil the people of Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is, An Daingean n&oacute; Dingle, mar a ghlaonn s&eacute; air, ar aon aigne, nach m&oacute;r, gur ch&oacute;ir an t-ainm a athr&uacute;.  De r&eacute;ir dealraimh agus an mh&eacute;id at&aacute; r&aacute;ite acu, is &eacute; an rud a theasta&iacute;onn uathu n&aacute; &ldquo;Dingle Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is&rdquo;.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EamonOCuiv"><NameTxt>&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v</NameTxt>
	<P>Mar ainm amh&aacute;in.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Mr. O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>Mar ainm amh&aacute;in.  Sin an rud a bh&iacute; ann.  Sin an rud at&aacute; r&aacute;ite.  Gan amhras, t&aacute; a l&aacute;n de seo ag brath ar an Rialtas.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EamonOCuiv"><NameTxt>&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v</NameTxt>
	<P>No.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Mr. O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>Caithfidh m&eacute; an m&eacute;id seo a r&aacute;.  &Oacute; thosaigh an chonsp&oacute;id seo, t&aacute; s&eacute; seo r&aacute;ite agam.  Mar nach bhfuilim i mo ch&oacute;na&iacute; san &aacute;it sin, n&iacute;or ch&oacute;ir go mbeinn &aacute; r&aacute; cad &eacute; ba cheart a bheith ann mar ainm.  F&aacute;gaim &eacute; sin faoi mhuintir Dhaingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is, An Daingin, n&oacute; Dingle.  Is &eacute; an rud at&aacute; &aacute; r&aacute; agamsa n&aacute; gur ch&oacute;ir don chinneadh a bheith d&eacute;anta acu si&uacute;d.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EamonOCuiv"><NameTxt>&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v</NameTxt>
	<P>Mar eolas dom f&eacute;in, bheadh s&eacute; ina chuidi&uacute; d&aacute; mbeadh s&eacute; seo pl&eacute;ite.  Is &eacute; an bhr&iacute; a bhaineann an Seanad&oacute;ir as an v&oacute;t&aacute;il n&aacute; go bhfuileadar ag iarraidh go mbeadh ainm nua amh&aacute;in ar an mbaile, &ldquo;Dingle Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is&rdquo;, agus gurbh &eacute; sin amh&aacute;in a bheadh oifigi&uacute;il.  B&rsquo;shin an bhr&iacute; a bhain an Seanad&oacute;ir as an bpobalbhreith.  Muna bhfuilimid soil&eacute;ir c&eacute; air a v&oacute;t&aacute;il siad, beidh fadhb ann.  B&rsquo;fh&eacute;idir go bhf&eacute;adfadh an Seanad&oacute;ir a mh&iacute;ni&uacute; cad &eacute; an cinneadh an fuaireamar.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Mr. O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">B&rsquo;fhearr liom go rachfa&iacute; i gcomhair le coiste mhuintir Dhaingin U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is chun &eacute; sin a phl&eacute; leo.  T&aacute; s&eacute; an-t&aacute;bhachtach.  Is &eacute; ceann de na ruda&iacute; a thit amach n&aacute; &eacute; seo &mdash; an ainm Gaoluinne n&oacute; B&eacute;arla &eacute; Dingle?  T&aacute; s&eacute; chomh Gaelach le &ldquo;hata&rdquo; n&oacute; &ldquo;corp&rdquo; n&oacute; 24 other words that I could give the Minister in Irish that are absolutely English in origin.</P>
        <P>I have never doubted the Minister&rsquo;s commitment although we differ very much on this issue.  I will defend him in other ways.  People were galvanised over this matter and difficulties arose.  D&uacute;irt an tAire go raibh br&oacute;n air mar gheall ar an gconsp&oacute;id.  M&aacute; t&aacute; br&oacute;n ar an Aire, t&aacute; br&oacute;n ormsa chomh maith.  Nuair a cuireadh an deighilt idir muintir an bhaile mh&oacute;ir agus muintir na tuaithe m&oacute;rthimpeall orthu, I was sad about that.  I was even sadder go raibh an feachtas seo curtha i gcomhth&eacute;acs go raibh s&eacute; i gcoinne na teangan agus na Gaeltachta&iacute;.  The biggest mistake &oacute; thaobh strait&eacute;ise de i ndeireadh na d&aacute;la nuair a bh&iacute; an plebiscite ag dul tr&iacute;d n&aacute; gur &eacute;irigh s&eacute; party political ina dhiaidh sin.  These were major strategic mistakes.</P><Col N="1997"/>
        <P Just="Left">The Minister should talk and listen to the people and recognise that they employed the process under the 1946 Act, on foot of which the application is made to the Government and not to himself.  The Minister&rsquo;s strong point is that he could make a decision on the order and reissue it.  I agree that it would be difficult to take two names, or the name Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is, from the big list.  He could just withdraw the whole list and issue the new one an hour later.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EamonOCuiv"><NameTxt>&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v</NameTxt>
	<P>I can do that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Mr. O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>That would make perfect legal sense.  Ultimately, we must determine our objective and arrive at a solution that will give equal status to the Irish name and make it official for the first time.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EamonOCuiv"><NameTxt>&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v</NameTxt>
	<P>N&iacute; f&eacute;idir linn aisghairm a dh&eacute;anamh.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu"><NameTxt>Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</NameTxt>
	<P>I dtosach, is mian liom f&aacute;ilte a chuir roimh an Aire agus, go m&oacute;rmh&oacute;r, an r&aacute;iteas a chuir s&eacute; os &aacute;r gcomhair inniu.  T&aacute; s&eacute; t&aacute;bhachtach, i nd&aacute;ir&iacute;re, na f&iacute;ric&iacute; a bheith &aacute; phl&eacute; againn agus, b&rsquo;fh&eacute;idir, an mh&iacute;thuiscint at&aacute; ann i l&aacute;thair na huaire a chuir ar ceal.  N&iacute; d&oacute;igh liom go gcabhra&iacute;onn an mh&iacute;thuiscint sin le aon ch&aacute;s.  Is cinnte nach gcabhra&iacute;onn s&eacute; le muintir Chiarra&iacute; n&oacute; muintir na Gaeltachta.  Is cinnte nach gcabhra&iacute;onn s&eacute; le chur chun cinn na Gaeilge freisin.  T&aacute; an-&aacute;thas orm go bhfuil r&aacute;iteas cuimsitheach curtha os &aacute;r gcomhair.  Ba ch&oacute;ir dom a r&aacute; gur beag Seanad&oacute;ir a chuireann an Ghaeilge chun tosaigh n&iacute;os m&oacute; n&aacute; an Seanad&oacute;ir O&rsquo;Toole.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Mr. O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>Go raibh maith agat.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu"><NameTxt>Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</NameTxt>
	<P>Labhra&iacute;onn s&eacute; as Gaeilge sa Teach seo go minic.  Is trua &eacute; nach mb&iacute;onn n&iacute;os m&oacute; den Ghaeilge le cloiste&aacute;il anseo.  Tuigim nach bhfuil aon drochthoil i gceist sa d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht seo.  Is maith an rud &eacute; go gcuireann an bheirt againn &aacute;r dtuaraim&iacute; ar aghaidh go minic ar an Ord Gn&oacute;.  I sl&iacute;, crutha&iacute;onn s&eacute; sin go bhfuil an Ghaeilge beo &mdash; gur beo-theanga at&aacute; i gceist.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Bheadh &aacute;r l&aacute; tagtha, i nd&aacute;ir&iacute;re, d&aacute; mbeadh d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht mar seo le cloiste&aacute;il ar thuarasc&aacute;lacha an Oireachtais ar RTE.  Chruth&oacute;dh s&eacute; sin &mdash; m&aacute; labhrann duine i nGaeilge, n&oacute; m&aacute; &uacute;s&aacute;ideann duine an Ghaeilge &mdash; go mbeadh an st&aacute;das ch&eacute;anna ag an Ghaeilge is at&aacute; ag an Bh&eacute;arla.  T&aacute; m&eacute; l&aacute;n-cinnte go raibh s&eacute; sin mar aidhm nuair a th&aacute;inig an reachta&iacute;ocht nua i dtaobh na Gaeilge isteach.  Bh&iacute; s&eacute; i gceist d&aacute;ir&iacute;reacht a chruth&uacute; maidir leis an Ghaeilge.  Bh&iacute; go leor taca&iacute;ocht b&eacute;al maidir leis an Ghaeilge le cloiste&aacute;il le blianta fada anuas.  Thaispe&aacute;in an tAire, an Teachta &Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v, &oacute;n tosach go raibh s&eacute; in ann a bheith raidiceach n&oacute; bun&uacute;sach.  Ag an am gc&eacute;anna, bh&iacute; s&eacute; ag iarraidh a thaispe&aacute;int nach f&eacute;idir linn an Ghaeilge a chur ar aghaidh i measc an phobail i gcoitinne gan reachta&iacute;ocht bun&uacute;sach a bheith ann.  Nuair a <Col N="1998"/>bh&iacute; an gn&iacute;omh sin &aacute; phl&eacute; i dTithe an Oireachtais, bh&iacute; s&eacute; soil&eacute;ir go raibh an-taca&iacute;ocht ann d&oacute;.  Is beag easaontas a raibh ann, rud a thug an-d&oacute;chas dom.  Nuair a fh&eacute;achaim siar ar na consp&oacute;id&iacute; a bh&iacute; ann maidir leis an Ghaeilge uair amh&aacute;in, go m&oacute;rmh&oacute;r sna 1960s, cuireann s&eacute; an-d&iacute;om&aacute; orm.  N&iacute; ch&oacute;ir, i nd&aacute;ir&iacute;re, go mbeadh easaontas ann maidir le aidhm n&aacute;isi&uacute;nta, ach tharla s&eacute; sin sna 1960s.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Nuair a th&oacute;g an tAire an reachta&iacute;ocht nua isteach, bh&iacute; s&eacute; soil&eacute;ir go raibh s&eacute; ag iarraidh an phobal ar fad a mhealladh leis.  Dhein s&eacute; &eacute; sin i dtosach tr&iacute; bheith ag caint le an-chuid daoine agus ag lorg aighneachta&iacute; maidir leis an Ghaeilge.  Labhair s&eacute; leis na heagrais Ghaeilge ar fad.  Th&aacute;inig s&eacute; isteach sa Teach seo chun labhairt faoin reachta&iacute;ocht.  Bh&iacute; s&eacute; ag iarraidh sinn uilig a aont&uacute; agus an phobal ar fad a mhealladh leis.  Fi&uacute; amh&aacute;in sna f&iacute;ric&iacute; a chuir s&eacute; os &aacute;r gcomhair inniu, t&aacute; s&eacute; l&aacute;n-cinnte nach raibh aon caimil&eacute;ireacht n&oacute; uisce faoi thalamh i gceist.  D&uacute;irt an Seanad&oacute;ir O&rsquo;Toole go glacann s&eacute; agus glacann gach duine mac&aacute;nta sa t&iacute;r seo go bhfuil cro&iacute; an Aire san &aacute;it ceart.  Go m&oacute;rmh&oacute;r, tuigimid go bhfuil s&eacute; ag iarraidh na cearta cu&iacute; a thabhairt do mhuintir na Gaeltachta.  Is fi&uacute; f&eacute;achaint siar ar na 1960s, nuair a bh&iacute; cearta sibhialta na Gaeltachta &aacute; phl&eacute;.  Bh&iacute; n&aacute;ire orm mar Ghael go raibh orthu troid ar son na cearta sin.  M&aacute; fh&eacute;achaimid ar na sean-scann&aacute;in, ar n&oacute;s &ldquo;Reeling in the Years&rdquo;, is minic a fheicimid p&iacute;osa&iacute; &aacute;irithe &oacute;n nGaeltacht ag d&eacute;anamh cur s&iacute;os ar an gcoimhlint a bh&iacute; ann ag an am.  Sa ch&aacute;s seo, bh&iacute; an tAire ag iarraidh a chinnti&uacute; nach mbeadh ar muintir na Gaeltachta dul amach a thuilleadh chun troid ar son a gcearta.  Is &eacute; sin a bhi s&eacute; ag iarraidh a dh&eacute;anamh.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Nuair a bh&iacute; m&eacute; th&iacute;os i nD&uacute;n Chaoin coic&iacute;s &oacute; shin &mdash; iarradh orm seminar a bh&iacute; &aacute; reacht&aacute;il ag Ionad an Bhlascaoid Mh&oacute;ir a oscailt go hoifigi&uacute;il &mdash; bh&iacute; seans agam labhairt le muintir na Gaeltachta.  Caithfidh m&eacute; a r&aacute; go raibh an-d&iacute;om&aacute; orthu go raibh an consp&oacute;id seo ag dul ar aghaidh.  Bh&iacute; n&aacute;ire orthu go raibh s&eacute; ag tarl&uacute;.  Luann siad i gc&oacute;na&iacute; gurb &iacute; &ldquo;An Daingean&rdquo; &mdash; seachas &ldquo;Dingle&rdquo; &mdash; an t-ainm at&aacute; acu don bhaile le blianta fada anuas, fi&uacute; amh&aacute;in sa litr&iacute;ocht.  Cheap siad mar mhuintir na Gaeltachta go mbeadh &aacute;thas ar dhaoine i ngach chuid den Ghaeltacht &mdash; D&uacute;n Chaoin, An Daingean, Conamara n&oacute; aon &aacute;it eile &mdash; go raibh seasamh agus st&aacute;das ceart &aacute; bhaint amach acu agus go raibh cosaint dleathach acu maidir leis sin.</P>
        <P Just="Left">D&uacute;irt an tAire inniu go bhfuil 2,300 logainmneacha i gceist sa d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht seo.  Bh&iacute; m&eacute; chun an phointe c&eacute;anna a dh&eacute;anamh.  De r&eacute;ir mar a thuigim &eacute;, is &iacute; An Daingean an t-aon &aacute;it amh&aacute;in, as an 2,300 &aacute;iteanna at&aacute; i gceist, a th&aacute;inig chun tosaigh maidir leis an gceist seo.  B&rsquo;fh&eacute;idir nach bhfuil aistri&uacute;ch&aacute;n ceart &aacute; dh&eacute;anamh agam ar an sean-r&aacute;iteas go nd&eacute;anann eisceachta&iacute; dl&iacute; olc.  T&aacute;imid ag pl&eacute; le pobal na Gaeltachta, An Daingean ina measc.  M&aacute;s rud &eacute; go bhfuil s&eacute; i gceist eisceacht a dh&eacute;anamh sa ch&aacute;s &uacute;d, ach gan bacadh leis an 2,300 &aacute;iteanna eile, beidh deacrachta&iacute; ag an Aire maidir le sin.  N&iacute; raibh an tAire ag smaoine<Col N="1999"/>amh ar An Daingean nuair a thosaigh an d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht agus an reachta&iacute;ocht seo &mdash; bh&iacute; s&eacute; ag smaoineamh ar chearta an phobail i gcoitinne.  Fuair m&eacute; glaoch guth&aacute;in &oacute; <i>The New York Times</i> s&eacute; n&oacute; seacht m&iacute; &oacute; shin.  Beidh an-&aacute;thas ar an Seanad&oacute;ir Coghlan a chloiste&aacute;il go bhfuil poibl&iacute;ocht mh&oacute;r &aacute; fh&aacute;il ag An Daingean amuigh i Nua Eabhrac.  N&iacute;l aon amhras faoi ach go bhfuil ag eir&iacute; leis an bhfeachtas ar aon n&oacute;s, mar go bhfuil an-chuid phoibl&iacute;ocht ag dul leis seo.  T&aacute; s&eacute; soil&eacute;ir os na f&iacute;ric&iacute; at&aacute; &aacute; chuir os &aacute;r gcomhair nach bhfuil aon chosc &aacute; chur ar &eacute;inne an t-ainm &ldquo;Dingle&rdquo; a &uacute;s&aacute;id.  Is bun-phointe &eacute; sin.  M&aacute; t&aacute;imid ag smaoineamh ar conas a &uacute;s&aacute;idtear na hainmnithe &eacute;ags&uacute;la, t&aacute;imid ag caint faoi Achtanna agus ionstraim&iacute; an Oireachtais, l&eacute;arsc&aacute;ileanna &aacute;irithe agus na comhartha&iacute; b&oacute;ithre ata &aacute; chur suas ag na h&uacute;dar&aacute;is &aacute;iti&uacute;la.  N&iacute;l an sc&eacute;al sin amuigh go poibl&iacute;.  T&aacute; s&eacute; t&aacute;bhachtach go mbeadh an sc&eacute;al sin amuigh.</P>
        <P>T&aacute; saghas d&iacute;om&aacute; orm go raibh ar an Seanad&oacute;ir O&rsquo;Toole imeacht, ach ba mhaith liom an pointe a rinne s&eacute; maidir leis an bpobalbhreith a fhreagairt.  Is cuma cad a bh&iacute; ag teast&aacute;il, mar n&iacute; raibh aon amhras faoin toradh a bheadh ann &mdash; go mbeadh ar an Aire n&oacute; ar an Rialtas an dl&iacute; n&oacute; an t-ord&uacute; a athr&uacute;.  T&aacute; s&uacute;il agam gur thuig m&eacute; an rud a bh&iacute; &aacute; r&aacute; ag an Seanad&oacute;ir O&rsquo;Toole.  An bhfuil s&eacute; ag r&aacute; anois go mbeadh muintir An Daingean s&aacute;sta le &ldquo;Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is&rdquo; n&oacute;, mar thugamar f&eacute;in air na blianta &oacute; shin, &ldquo;Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;ise&rdquo;?  An mbeadh na daoine san &aacute;it s&aacute;sta le sin amh&aacute;in ar na comhartha&iacute; b&oacute;ithre?  De r&eacute;ir mar a thuig m&eacute; an tAire, d&rsquo;fh&eacute;adfadh s&eacute; f&eacute;achaint ar sin.  An bhfuil s&eacute; sin ind&eacute;anta?  Thuig m&eacute; &oacute;n Aire go mbeadh s&eacute; sin n&iacute;os simpl&iacute;.  N&iacute; f&eacute;idir an d&aacute; ainm a bheith ann, mar n&iacute;l s&eacute; sin istigh sa reachta&iacute;ocht.  Is &eacute; sin an phointe a bh&iacute; &aacute; phl&eacute; ag an Seanad&oacute;ir O&rsquo;Toole.</P>
        <P>Bh&iacute; an tAire thar a bheith oscailte anseo.  N&iacute; amh&aacute;in gur ghlac s&eacute; le comhairle f&iacute;or-leathan nuair a bh&iacute; an reachta&iacute;ocht &aacute; chur i bhfeidhm agus nuair a bh&iacute; an t-ord&uacute; &aacute; chur le ch&eacute;ile, ach chomh maith leis sin thug s&eacute; seans do gach dream teacht chuige, faoi mar a d&uacute;irt s&eacute;.  N&iacute;or th&aacute;inig &eacute;inne ar aghaidh maidir leis An Daingean ag an am.  Cuireann s&eacute; ionadh orm, c&eacute; gur bhfuair an Aire breis agus 30 aighneachta&iacute; ar fad, n&aacute;r th&aacute;inig &eacute;inne chuige maidir leis An Daingean.  Cad ina thaobh gur thosaigh an consp&oacute;id &uacute;d n&iacute;os d&eacute;ana&iacute;?  N&iacute;l a fhios agamsa, ach t&aacute; an tAire tar &eacute;is r&aacute; go mbeadh s&eacute; l&aacute;n-s&aacute;sta labhairt le hionadaithe na comhairle, agus t&aacute; an ceart aige labhairt leo si&uacute;d at&aacute; tofa.  T&aacute; s&eacute; s&aacute;sta labhairt le comhairleoir&iacute; &oacute; Chiarra&iacute; chun an rud seo ar fad a phl&eacute; agus a mheas, agus t&aacute; m&eacute; l&aacute;n-chinnte go mbeidh s&eacute; s&aacute;sta a bheith r&eacute;as&uacute;nta sa ch&aacute;s seo, faoi mar a bh&iacute;onn s&eacute; i gc&oacute;na&iacute;.  T&aacute; s&eacute; tar &eacute;is cruth&uacute; ar&iacute;s nach bhfuil s&eacute; ag iarraidh aon rud a bhr&uacute; ar &eacute;inne eile.  N&iacute; bheadh s&eacute; ceart anois, &aacute;fach, na cearta at&aacute; bainte amach ag muintir na Gaeltachta a bhaint d&iacute;obh ar&iacute;s n&oacute; aon mh&iacute;thuiscint a choth&uacute; maidir le st&aacute;das 2,300 logainm bailte, sr&aacute;idbhailte, bhailte fearainn agus mar sin de.</P><Col N="2000"/>
        <P Just="Left">Ba bhre&aacute; liom, faoi mar a d&uacute;irt m&eacute; go minic anseo, go mbeadh dea-thoil ar&iacute;s le feiscint maidir leis an gceist seo.  I nd&aacute;ir&iacute;re, n&iacute; h&eacute; seo cro&iacute;l&aacute;r na ceiste maidir leis an Ghaeilge.  Is &eacute; an reachta&iacute;ocht agus an tAcht f&eacute;in an rud is t&aacute;bhachta&iacute;.  T&aacute; suas le 600 no 700 eagras poibl&iacute; a mbeidh orthu seirbh&iacute;s dh&aacute;theangach a chur ar f&aacute;il.  Sin an dea-sc&eacute;al, an sc&eacute;al m&oacute;r i mo thuairim.  T&aacute; an rud seo timpeallach ar fad, agus t&aacute; an tAire tar &eacute;is an doras a fh&aacute;g&aacute;il ar oscailt.  Beidh s&eacute; ar f&aacute;il chun an st&aacute;das a bhaineann leis f&eacute;in agus an fhreagracht at&aacute; air mar Aire a mh&iacute;ni&uacute; do mhuintir Chiarra&iacute; tr&iacute;d na comhairleoir&iacute;.  B&rsquo;fh&eacute;idir gur ch&oacute;ir d&uacute;inn go l&eacute;ir fanacht leis sin agus f&eacute;achaint cad a thiocfaidh as.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Is m&oacute;r an trua go bhfuil consp&oacute;id ar ainm Dingle.  I do not possess the beautiful Irish of the Minister for Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs, Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v, nor that of Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; and Senator O&rsquo;Toole.</P>
        <P>There is no doubt regarding the Minister&rsquo;s love of the Irish language and his interest in all the Gaeltacht regions of our country.  He went into great detail on the history of this matter, the wishes of the people of the Gaeltacht, the road signs and the actions of the former Minister, Bobby Molloy, in ordering Irish names for places in the Gaeltacht, including An Daingean.  I always thought Daingean was a town in Offaly and I do not think the people of Dingle wish to rob Offaly of a placename.</P>
        <P>Like Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute;, I knew the town as Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is when I was growing up.  I bow to Senator O&rsquo;Toole&rsquo;s superior knowledge as it is his native place and I reiterate and endorse everything he has said on this subject.</P>
        <P>The people of Dingle were happy as things were.  As the Minister pointed out, more than 2,300 placenames were involved and it is great that only one is giving difficulty.  I do not see history as being of major importance in this issue.  We have a difficulty.  I believe we should put it right and I have no doubt this can be done.</P>
        <P>The Minister suggested the plebiscite has no legal effect and that one cannot cancel an order.  He met Kerry County Council in June and is prepared to meet it again on 17 November, for which I salute him.  As Senator O&rsquo;Toole pointed out, a committee is in place and, while I am not sure a public meeting is necessary, we should do whatever it takes to solve this issue.  The Minister mentioned advice he received from the Attorney General but, again, I suggest there must be ways around such obstacles and I am sure the Attorney General would be helpful in this regard.  If we cannot allow a bilingual name, we should change the law or, as Senator O&rsquo;Toole suggested, change the order.  Only one placename presents a difficulty so I would have thought it could be easily surmounted.</P>
        <P>I gratefully accept that the Minister will examine recommendations received from Kerry County Council and the people of Dingle.  We <Col N="2001"/>should not construct a straitjacket by proceeding with preconceived notions.  The Minister said he is prepared to see what can be done on this issue and I think that is constructive.  I believe that a proper solution can be found through the Minister&rsquo;s advisers and other individuals who are prepared to be helpful.  As Senator O&rsquo;Toole said, the people did not vote to cancel an order, they voted to choose a new name.</P>
        <P>I also endorse a great deal of Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute;&rsquo;s sentiments.  He rightly states that the Minister was anxious to give the people of the Gaeltacht their rights and there is no doubt about the result which, as democrats, we all accept.  It is not acceptable in legislation but, I believe, we can put the legislation right.  Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; said he believed the Minister would be happy to be reasonable.</P>
        <P>Some 93% of the people of Dingle have expressed their desire to reinstate what they believe to be the town&rsquo;s historical bilingual name, Dingle Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is.  We have already gone into detail on the plebiscite, which was held under the rules of the Local Government Act 1946.  Dingle is as entitled to the protections and benefits of that Act as any other town in the country.  No judgment has been made to the contrary and we are confident that any court in the country would uphold Dingle&rsquo;s right to the plebiscite.  I am happy the Minister will meet Kerry County Council.  The rules of the Act state Kerry County Council is obliged to present the results of the Dingle plebiscite to the Government, at which point the Minister may or may not choose to act on the result.  I do not wish to prejudice the outcome of the consultations to take place on 17 November.</P>
        <P>I support Dingle&rsquo;s call on the Government to recognise the result of the plebiscite because the citizens have voted to reinstate what they see as the town&rsquo;s historical names.  All Irish towns have an official Irish name and an official English name and I join those citizens in asking the Minister to acknowledge, as I am sure he does, their democratic wishes.  I ask the Minister to make the necessary adjustments to the placenames order or perhaps, as Senator O&rsquo;Toole proposed, withdraw the order and replace it with another, following the consultations.</P>
        <P>I do not wish to labour this issue and I do not wish to be divisive.  I salute the Minister in his love and support of the language and Gaeltacht.  If he goes to Dingle and Kerry County Council with an open mind, bearing in mind what has happened, I have no doubt this minor difficulty can be overcome and a happy outcome found.  I hope the talks on 17 November go well.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelKitt"><NameTxt>Mr. Kitt</NameTxt>
	<P>T&aacute; an tAire s&aacute;sta bualadh le comhairleoir&iacute; i gCiarra&iacute; ar an 17 m&iacute; Shamhna agus cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimhe sin.  T&aacute; s&uacute;il agam go mbeidh s&eacute; in ann c&uacute;rsa&iacute; logainmneacha a r&eacute;iteach mar t&aacute; consp&oacute;id ann faoi l&aacute;thair.  Bh&iacute; an tAire ar an raidi&oacute; c&uacute;pla l&aacute; &oacute; shin agus cuireadh ceist air faoin <Col N="2002"/>logainm cheart &mdash; Dingle n&oacute; Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is.  D&uacute;irt s&eacute; ar an chl&aacute;r sin go scr&iacute;obhfadh s&eacute; le bainisteoir Comhairle Chondae Chiarra&iacute; agus t&aacute; sin d&eacute;anta aige agus t&aacute; an cruinni&uacute; socraithe.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator Coghlan made the point about Daingean in County Offaly as if it is the only Daingean in Ireland.  There is a CD available entitled &ldquo;Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is Ab&uacute;&rdquo;.  N&iacute;l an CD ag moladh an Aire, t&aacute; s&eacute; ag caint faoi turas&oacute;ir&iacute; a bh&iacute; ag iarraidh dul go dt&iacute; Ciarra&iacute; ach shroich siad U&iacute;bh Fhaill&iacute;.  If it was as simple as that, there might be a resolution but there are many places called Daingean, such as the place near Tuam in County Galway and Daingean Heights in Galway city.  It is a popular placename, it is not as simple as Senator Coghlan makes out.</P>
        <P>Is cuimhin liom an t-ord&uacute; a rinne Bobby Molloy nuair a bh&iacute; s&eacute; mar Aire sa Roinn Rialtas &Aacute;iti&uacute;il, go mbeadh Gaeilge amh&aacute;in ar gach comhartha b&oacute;thair le logainm Gaeltachta air.  Bh&iacute; an-fhadhb ag an am, le gluaiseacht cearta sibhialta i gConamara ag iarraidh go mbeadh an logainm amh&aacute;in ar na bailte agus scrios siad comhartha&iacute; ansin.  T&aacute; muintir na Gaeltachta s&aacute;sta leis an tsl&iacute; go bhfuil an tAire ag iarraidh an fhadhb seo a shocr&uacute;.  Is bre&aacute; liom a chloiste&aacute;il &oacute;n Aire go bhfuil s&eacute; ag dul go Condae Chiarra&iacute; agus ag &eacute;isteacht leis na comhairleoir&iacute; ansin.</P>
        <P>There is a difficulty that we have so many towns and townlands with the same name &mdash; how many Gorteens and Caltras are there in each county?  I have noticed this travelling around the country and I would not be happy with a coimisi&uacute;n that states that Irish for Gort in Galway is An Gort, because we always refer to it as Gort Inse Ghuaire, in honour of King Guaire.  My own village of Castleblakeney is named An Gallach but locally it is known as Gallach U&iacute; Cheallaigh on account of the Kelly family, one of the most hospitable peoples ever in Galway.  They ruled Hy-Many, an area known for hospitality.  The coimisi&uacute;n must look at other issues.  We are discussing the idea of Dingle, Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is or An Daingean but there are other towns throughout Ireland where placenames have been changed or shortened and that is wrong.  The old names say more about the history of a town and changing them is a backward step.</P>
        <P>T&aacute; s&uacute;il agam go mbeidh an tAire ag an chruinni&uacute; ar an 17 m&iacute; Shamhna leis an fhadhb seo a phl&eacute; agus go mbeidh r&eacute;iteach ar an sc&eacute;al chomh luath agus is f&eacute;idir.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire.  Is cuimhin liom seanfhocal &oacute;n scoil: &eacute;ist le fuaim na habhann agus gheobhaidh t&uacute; iasc, listen to the sound of the river and you will catch a fish.  It is a saying that I have used in my lifetime, listening to the public whether they are customers or citizens.</P>
        <P Just="Left">This debate is attracting a lot of crit<Insert>i</Insert>cism for the attention we have devoted to it.  The fact that we are wasting time today in this House on it vindicates the stand I took against the Official Lang<Col N="2003"/>uages Act 2003, when it was nodded through the House.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I supported the thinking behind the Bill for the same reason that I supported the establishment of TG4, which celebrated its tenth anniversary last night.  We all want the Irish language perceived not only as acceptable but interesting, fun and useful.  If a language is to be more than a museum piece, people must be able to carry out the main activities of their lives through that medium.  Given the standing of the Irish language in the Constitution, it is logical that people should be able to conduct their business with the State in the national language.</P>
        <P>I refused, however, to support the Bill because I thought it was putting energy, effort and expense into the wrong place.  I feared, and rightly as it turned out, that the implementation of the Bill would have enormous implications for the cost structure of all public bodies.  It has added a new layer of expense to the provision of every public service, to say nothing of the delays that have occurred while translation takes place, something we have raised on a few occasions.</P>
        <P>The Act failed to acknowledge a key fact of Irish life: the majority of our citizens are not competent enough to conduct their business as Gaeilge.  If everyone could speak Irish, we would not need the Act, but reality is different.  That reality has been repeatedly denied by successive Governments of all hues.  Our young people learn Irish from the first day they start school so why can so few people speak it?  Why do so few adults wish to speak Irish in their daily lives?  They may wish to use it but they do not feel competent enough to do so.  How did we fail our children and what must we do to engender in them a love of the language?  All of my children went to the Gaeltacht and came home enthusiastic about the language.  It was a joy to see them coming out of reunions speaking as Gaeilge again but as time went on they failed to hold on to it.  That is the issue the Act failed to address.</P>
        <P Just="Left">If we must invest money, enthusiasm and effort, it makes sense to devote that investment to improving the teaching of Irish in schools.  There is a massive State apparatus devoted to the teaching of Irish and in spite of that the majority of young people do not learn the language effectively.  Many young people leave school not just with a lack of enthusiasm but with a negative attitude towards the language.  It must be possible to overcome this because other countries have succeeded in doing so.  Some time ago I visited Israel where immigrants who cannot speak Hebrew when they arrive have consistently learned the language.  We can learn from this example.</P>
        <P>The current system of teaching Irish has utterly failed to engage the majority of the population, particularly students.  Why have we failed so miserably?  The reason is not that Irish is a particularly difficult language to learn or that we did not devote sufficient time or resources to its <Col N="2004"/>teaching.  There must be another reason for the monumental failure to achieve the objectives we set ourselves.</P>
        <P>I was pleased to read today that the Minister for Education and Science proposes to tackle the issue by taking a different approach.  Her message appeals to me.  Most of the communication in which we engage in daily life is spoken rather than written, whereas the teaching of Irish has been focused on grammar and written skills as opposed to speaking.  The Minister appeared to send out a message today that she will change this approach.</P>
        <P>If we genuinely have the interests of the Irish language at heart, we should not waste time making political footballs out of place names.  Instead, we should ask questions such as those I have posed and pursue the answers regardless of where they lead us.  For example, how can we achieve our objectives and obtain the best value for money?  I was virtually a lone voice in the House when the Official Languages Act was being passed.  I was interested to note, therefore, that in his first annual report, the Coimisin&eacute;ir Teanga, whose office was established by the Act, stated:</P>
        <P LI="1">It is estimated that almost 1,500 hours of tuition in the Irish language is provided to school pupils over a period of 13 years, from their first day at primary school to the end of secondary level.  This clearly raises the question: is the State getting value for money from this investment, if it is true that so many are going through the educational system without achieving a reasonable command of the language &mdash; even in the case of students who succeed in getting a high grade in Irish in their final examinations?</P>
        <P FLI="0">There is much meat in this sentence.  The passage continues:</P>
        <P LI="1">I believe that there is an urgent need for a comprehensive and impartial review of every aspect of the learning and teaching of Irish in the educational system, so as to ensure that the continuous and substantial State investment in Irish will ensure that students, having spent thirteen years learning the language, acquire a reasonable fluency or command of the language by the time they complete their schooling.  This is essential if we are serious about promoting Irish in every aspect of national life, including public administration.</P>
        <P FLI="0">These are not my words, but those of the Coimisin&eacute;ir Teanga.  Has the Minister, to whom the Coimisin&eacute;ir reports, read these words?  I note he is nodding his head.  If that is the case, has he paid attention to them?  He should use his time to do something useful to promote the Irish language rather than wasting time and money on a wild goose chase trying to bend the people of An Daingean or Dingle to his will.</P>
        <P>There is considerable good will towards the language and the Minister&rsquo;s heart is in the right <Col N="2005"/>place.  Although I do not have the solution, I believe that, with commitment, we will achieve the aims we have been striving to achieve for 80 years.  While I wish the Minister well, I believe he has chosen the wrong path in concentrating his energies on the issue of place names.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EamonOCuiv"><TitleTxt>Minister for Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs</TitleTxt><NameTxt>&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senators for their contributions to this thoughtful debate.  I will address my comments to Senator Quinn.  Last week, Ministers from Scotland, Wales, Ireland, the Isle of Man, Guernsey and Jersey had a most interesting discussion at the British-Irish Council.  It was amazing to learn how similar are the circumstances prevailing in the various jurisdictions.  Scotland, for instance, either has a language Act or is in the process of enacting one, while Wales already has legislation on languages which it intends to strengthen.  Both countries regard these laws as vital bulwarks for minority languages. </P>
        <P>The Welsh language is in a robust position.  Speaking to my Welsh colleague, it was interesting to learn that Ireland is not in a unique position because Wales is experiencing precisely the same problem as we are.  Welsh is taught in every school in Wales but the education system does not produce a large number of Welsh speakers.  We teased out how we deal collectively with this problem and our discussions were most instructive.</P>
        <P>On a broader matter, the Official Languages Act sought, in a minimalist fashion, to provide that Irish speakers will be entitled to certain basic services.  It did not make any impositions on English speakers but laid down and made available to Irish speakers a small number of rights.</P>
        <P>One of the problems about all debates on the language is that the truth is the first casualty.  I saw estimates of the cost of translating official documents running into millions of euro but when I asked Departments how much the translation of documents under the relevant section of the Act had cost them in 2005, I learned that the sum total of these costs between 15 Departments and the Office of Public Works was &euro;374,000.  The cost of producing the same documents in English in terms of time and effort was far in excess of that figure.</P>
        <P>The current cost of translation can be reduced to approximately &euro;100,000 per annum because many documents, for example, annual reports and accounts, are produced in the same format every year.  Machine translation facilities are available which will automatically translate any sentence that appeared in a previous document.  It will even change figures if one inputs the changes.  As Senators will be aware, the few documents requiring translation &mdash; strategy statements and so forth &mdash; tend to take a similar format every year.</P>
        <P>The Official Languages Act has not cost a large amount of money.  It has, however, freed up the <Col N="2006"/>incessant demands on my Department arising from the need to raid my Department&rsquo;s small budget for the Irish language every time someone needed to produce a document, however minor, in Irish.</P>
        <P>Senator Quinn referred to the controversy arising from the naming of An Daingean or Dingle or Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is.  Let us return to the facts.  Prior to the enactment of the Official Languages Act, no Irish place name, with the exception of places such as D&uacute;n Laoghaire and Cobh, had official status and the legal entitlement to use the Irish language form was not clear in certain circumstances.  The issue of whether I had a right to use the name &ldquo;Corr na M&oacute;na&rdquo; on a planning application had to be cleared up and we set about rectifying the matter.  What did we do?  We decided that, with the exception of the Gaeltacht, the Irish language version of a place name would have the same status as the English version.  This would be a matter of choice for citizens.  For the first time, there was no ambiguity and if a person in Donnybrook wanted to use the name &ldquo;Domhnach Broc&rdquo;, there would be no question that he or she could use the Irish version in all cases and it would have equivalence with Donnybrook.  Making this choice available afforded a right without removing any other rights.</P>
        <P>In the case of the Gaeltacht we provided specific, legal protection and provision for the use of the English language on equal terms with Irish.  Incidentally, the same position did not apply in reverse.  We provided that the Irish version of a place name would be the official version but in every circumstance the use of the English language version would be specifically protected in law, without equivocation, except in three circumstances.  The first of these was that the Irish version shall be used in the event that the Oireachtas passes an Act or makes a statutory order which refers to a town in the Gaeltacht.  This provision does not affect citizens on a day-to-day basis.</P>
        <P>The second exception was a provision that the Minister could make an order regarding Ordnance Survey maps.  The only order made thus far relates to large-scale maps.  That these maps were not bilingual effectively forced us to do all our business through English because they showed towns in the Gaeltacht such as An Ceathr&uacute; Rua and Ros Muc as Carraroe and Rosmuck, respectively.  Given the choice, we decided that large-scale maps, as opposed to tourism maps, would show the Irish version of place names in the Gaeltacht.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The third exception related to the vexed issue of signposts.  There may be days when I wished former Minister, Bobby Molloy, did not do what he did.  However, Bobby did what Bobby did and, in my view, left an impractical mess.  In Eyre Square in Galway, the signpost showed Carraroe and Ceathr&uacute; Rua.  By the time one got to Barna, Carraroe had disappeared but the map still showed only Carraroe.  It was not too difficult with Carraroe but when one was dealing with a <Col N="2007"/>place such as An Fhairche or Clonbur, one really had a pain in one&rsquo;s head.  I decided this had to be dealt with once and for all because I spent much of my life stopping at crossroads in Connemara to help people who were lost.  The maps were saying one thing and the signposts were saying another.</P>
        <P>I examined the options.  The first was probably the most attractive, and I considered it seriously.  It was that all signposts would show Carraroe and Ceathr&uacute; Rua and An Fhairche agus Clonbur, in other words, be bilingual both inside and outside the Gaeltacht.  However, I said to myself: &ldquo;Go there at your peril&rdquo;.  While the people of the 1960s would not do it, the children nowadays would be out with the paint.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The second issue was that it is irrational to accept the concept that tourists &mdash; signposts are for tourists, not for people who can find their way around &mdash; in Eyre Square can understand only Spiddal but when they get to Barna can suddenly understand An Spid&eacute;al.  My logic was that if the tourist could understand it in Barna, they could understand it in Eyre Square.  The problem for the tourist was the map.  The map showed only  &ldquo;Spiddal&rdquo; and the sign showed only &ldquo;An Spid&eacute;al&rdquo; and so forth.  I decided the way around it was to make all the maps bilingual and have the signposts consistently, inside and outside the Gaeltacht, showing the same thing.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I did something equally radical in the opposite direction.  There was a nonsensical situation in the Gaeltacht, and it is amazing nobody ever talked about it, whereby if one found a signpost in the Gaeltacht for somewhere outside such as Westport, the signpost showed only Cathair na Mart, which is Westport in Irish.  When one&rsquo;s map showed only Westport, how was one to find Cathair na Mart?  If one looks at this from the tourism point of view, there were only two realistic choices, that is, have the map bilingual and the signs in Irish only or have both the map and the signs bilingual.  However, the sign should show the same thing inside or outside the Gaeltacht.  It is irrational, from a tourism point of view, to have it any other way.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I decided that the signpost inside as well as outside the Gaeltacht for a placename outside the Gaeltacht should show, for example, Westport and Cathair na Mart.  People will criticise me for that but since there are two official forms of the name, it is rational that the signposts do not show Westport and Cathair na Mart outside and then only Cathair na Mart inside the Gaeltacht.  I made the decision, therefore, that they would show both forms of the name; that is, a signpost in Doire na Maol would show Galway and Gaillimh.</P>
        <P>Whatever one can say about the decisions I made, when one looks at it from a tourism point of view there is a certain consistency.  There is an irony in this.  I have been talking to my friends in Galway and have said to them, &ldquo;By the way, do you notice anything strange in Galway these <Col N="2008"/>days?&rdquo;  They say they have not.  When I ask if anyone has complained to them, they say they have not.  I approached the radio station presenter, who hosts the equivalent of the Joe Duffy &ldquo;Liveline&rdquo; radio show, and asked if he had noticed anything in Galway.  He said &ldquo;No&rdquo;.  I told him that somebody has carefully taken down Spiddal from every signpost around the city and all that is left is An Spid&eacute;al.</P>
        <P>We have had a fantastic tourism season and the people of south Connemara have said it was the best ever.  People in Spiddal said it was very good once the season got going.  Apparently, the signpost issue was never raised by anybody in the tourist office.  The simple reason is that the map shows Spiddal and An Spid&eacute;al.  Foreign tourists are used to the bilingual situation.  They know to keep following the signpost for An Spid&eacute;al until they find it.  The interesting thing is that this happened and nobody paid any attention to it.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The issue of democracy was raised.  We are all democrats but we make laws which all citizens must accept, even if they do not like them.  We make laws every day that apply across the country.  That is what we are elected to do.  If one small group in a small village does not like the smoking ban, we tell them it is the law of the land.  My problem is that 2,300 names appear to have great acceptance and one does not.  I am told I am the big bad wolf because I am imposing something on the 2,300 with which they are not exactly comfortable.  I am willing to listen to the people of Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is but it is a little disingenuous to say that there is a great flouting of democracy to expect that if one lives in the Gaeltacht and enjoys the great privilege of all that goes with it, one should do what the Gaeltacht people do.  Nobody can pass a law which states that one can smoke in a pub in Caherciveen but one cannot smoke in a pub in Dublin.  We tend to make our laws to cover specific areas or specific individuals.</P>
        <P>The difficulty with this has been that to row back on the process would be to stir up an even bigger hornets nest of discontent.  Even in Kerry there is great discontent.  This issue went to the board of &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta, which is a body elected by the people of the Gaeltacht, before I signed the order.  We consulted with the board.  D&rsquo;aonghuth or unanimously it supported what I was doing.  I will discuss it with the members of the board at the end of the week when I meet them again.  The hurtful and damaging aspect of this is that newspaper editorials claim we never consulted.  We did consult.  I do not mean simply putting an advertisement in the newspaper.  We wrote to all the community councils and told them what we intended to do.  We instituted debates on all the radio stations, magazines and so forth.  We went out of our way to try to make people aware of what we were doing.</P>
        <P>I foresaw huge perils in this with the forms of the names.  There is one form I do not like for Dooros which is D&uacute;ros.  I would spell it Dubhros.  I thought there would be murder locally but they <Col N="2009"/>did not complain so I did not change it.  It would not be my choice of spelling because the name comes from dubh ros.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator Kitt mentioned Gort Inse Guaire <i>versus</i> Gort.  What apparently happened is that a person named McLysaght, at the beginning of the last century, had an idea that an Irish name had to be long.  He used names such as Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is, Gort Inse Guaire, N&aacute;s na R&iacute;ogh and so forth.  In some cases, such as An Daingean agus Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is, there is authentic ancient validity for both versions.  However, in other cases, there is little, such as N&aacute;s na R&iacute;ogh.  That was only a reference to Naas in a poem.  In that case it was similar to saying Galway of the tribes in a poem.  That is all right in a poem but please do not put it on our signposts.  We will stick with the simple Galway in English and Gaillimh in Irish.</P>
        <P>Of course, as these names were taught in schools and were revivalist names, they caught on.  However, the commission examined these.  The commission is composed of a broad range of experts, ordinary people and people from the Gaeltacht and when it examines these names, one of the big guiding factors is what term the last native Irish speakers used if there are no Irish speakers in the area.  The commission will testify to the fact that around Gort it was known as An Gort, not Gort Inse Guaire.</P>
        <P>I recall a case when the then Minister, Deputy de Valera, overruled the commission on my advice.  An Cnoc is the correct and historical name for Knock in County Mayo.  In the 1930s a priest created the name Cnoc Mhuire or Mary&rsquo;s Hill.  It caught on in the Gaeltacht and if one says, &ldquo;Beidh oilithreacht go Cnoc Mhuire&rdquo; or &ldquo;There will be a pilgrimage to Knock&rdquo;, everybody knows it is Knock in County Mayo and not An Cnoc in Inverin.  That is part of the ordinary discourse in the Gaeltacht so the official name was changed to Cnoc Mhuire.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I must defend the commission and its integrity in terms of the detailed work it does and the historical references on which it bases its work.  In the case of An Daingean, I have no particular hang-up between Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is or An Daingean.  However, it is wrong to say that a civil servant dreamed up this in the 1920s and it is a slight on the seabhac, P&aacute;draig &Oacute; Siochfhradha, to say it.  An Daingean is historically well attested and so is Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is so which won the day?  I can tell the Senator what won the day for An Daingean.  If one goes back to the west Kerry Gaeltacht and talks Irish to the native speakers, they invariably use An Daingean.  I was slightly amused to hear one of those proposing Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is &mdash; a colleague of the Senator &mdash; speaking about a sewerage scheme for the town of Dingle on Radio na Gaeltachta.  He referred to a town called An Daingean five times in the interview and he was not talking about County Offaly.  In reality, that is what they all use all of the time.  If they want to discard that and use Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is I have no hang up about it, but to say that <Col N="2010"/>it is controversial to reaffirm what has been there since 1960 is to misrepresent the facts in the case.</P>
        <P>My memory of the legal advice is contrary to what Senator O&rsquo;Toole stated.  I am always open to looking at things again, but I am bound by the Attorney General&rsquo;s advice.  If the members of Kerry County Council suggest to me that they want a new name for the town of Dingle, that is, Dingle/Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is and that they want it done under the 1946 Act, I will look for further legal advice on the issue to see if it is legally possible.  If it is, it must be taken into account in the further discussion.  If it is not legally possible, I hope the House recognises that it is not acceptable for a Minister to act outside the law.  In other words, I am bound by the Attorney General&rsquo;s advice whether he is right or wrong.  That is a basic tenet by which I am ruled as a Minister.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The option to rescind the order is handy, but I am trying to find out if there is a snag to it as I do not wish to mislead anybody.  I want to check this before people get into a hullabaloo about this and ask for things that they do not really want.  I always thought that the people of Dingle wanted Dingle to be an official English language name and that Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is would be the official Irish language name, but not one composite name.  A composite name would be very awkward, but if I am wrong, I am wrong.  If I rescind the order, my understanding is that we revert to Dingle, but I must check what effect that has on any Irish language version.  The 1973 Act has now been overtaken by the 2003 Act and we might end up without any Irish language version of the place.  Before I do that, the people of Dingle/An Daingean/ Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is should be entitled to know the legal effect of any further actions we take on this issue.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Ba mhaith liom bu&iacute;ochas a ghlacadh leis an Leas-Chathaoirleach as ucht an c&uacute;pla n&oacute;im&eacute;ad breise a thabhairt dom.  Sh&iacute;l m&eacute; go raibh s&eacute; t&aacute;bhachtach go mbeadh deis agam freagra comh-cuimsitheach agus is f&eacute;idir a thabhairt.  Go raibh maith agat.</P>
 <HtmlBk SectId="4" />
    </Speaker><!--Fix-->
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Housing Policy:" RHead="Motion"> 
    <Title>Housing Policy: Motion. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelBrennan"><NameTxt>Mr. Brennan</NameTxt>
	<P>I move: </P>
        <P LI="1">&ldquo;That Seanad &Eacute;ireann:</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />recognises that Ireland&rsquo;s record levels of economic and population growth creates the challenge of meeting record housing accommodation demand across the country;</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />notes the Government&rsquo;s ongoing commitment to a modern planning system, which is strategic in approach and reflects the requirement for sustainable development and which delivers a performance of the highest quality;</P><Col N="2011"/>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />supports the measures taken to date by Government to ensure such a system is in place;</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />commends the Government on the publication of finalised sustainable rural housing guidelines for planning authorities in April 2005;</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />notes the Government&rsquo;s recognition of the strong and continuing tradition of Irish people living in rural areas;</P>
        <P FLI="0"><?oasys _is1p8- ?><?oasys _ix ?>asks the Minister for Environment, Heritage and Local Government to:</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />consider establishing an independent national planning monitoring committee on a statutory basis to, <i>inter alia</i>, advise the Minister on matters relating to planning policy, advise and assist local public representatives in the preparation of local planning policy and development plans, and regulate the implementation of Government policy and guidelines in relation to rural housing;</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />look at the need for a national water and sewerage services authority, similar to that which exists for national roads and group water schemes, to ensure the provision of an adequate and efficient network of water and sewerage infrastructure, with regional offices responsible for the planning, delivery and maintenance of water and sewerage infrastructure, and to implement water services investment programmes;</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />examine the appropriateness of the present definition of the word &ldquo;local&rdquo; in the rural housing guidelines for planning authorities, to end any inconsistency surrounding its use;</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />consider widening the interpretation of &ldquo;housing need&rdquo; in planning guidelines, to ensure equity and consistency;</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />address the situation where farming is seen as the only profession that qualifies a person for planning permission in rural areas;</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />investigate the desirability of an independent appeal boards within An Bord Plean&aacute;la to cover the three EU constituencies outside Dublin;</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />consider publication on the internet of information about the success rate of planning applications submitted by engineers and architects; and</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />contemplate how planning restrictions which may hinder a person seeking planning permission for a house <Col N="2012"/>specially designed to accommodate a person with a disability, might be removed.&rdquo;</P>
        <P FLI="0">I am pleased to move this Progressive Democrats motion and I welcome the Minister to the House.  The motion proposed by my party reflects our contention that planning and development are key issues for communities across this country. Ireland&rsquo;s people want and deserve a planning system that meets their needs for local economic development, for a good supply of affordable housing and for enhanced quality of life.  The correct planning law and the enforcement of subsequent decisions is critical to public confidence in local government.  This starts with political direction and political will and the Progressive Democrats is dedicated to providing this leadership.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Progressive Democrats is not in favour of unrestricted housing development and does not believe that people have the right to build wherever and in whatever style they like.  We do not underestimate the important steps taken by the Government in the past ten years.  We support fairness, choice and sustainability.  We have worked with our partners in the Government to ensure Irish people have access to a planning system with these qualities, to a modern planning system that is strategic in approach, which reflects the requirements for sustainable development and which delivers a performance of the highest quality.  I commend this Government and the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government on the measures taken to date to ensure such a system is in place.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The House should congratulate the Government for its ongoing recognition of the strong and continuing tradition of Irish people living in rural areas.  We do so in the full knowledge of increased challenges.  Ireland&rsquo;s record levels of economic and population growth create great challenges, such as meeting record housing accommodation demand across the country.  Challenges of balanced and sustainable development must continue to be met head on and this underpins my party&rsquo;s approach and the policy of the Government.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Planning for a Rural Future is the title of the Progressive Democrats&rsquo; policy document on rural housing, which was launched by the T&aacute;naiste and by our policy group on rural planning at the ploughing championships in Tullow in late September.  I congratulate our policy team for its diligent work on this topic, which consisted of the chairman, Deputy Grealish, Councillor Ciaran Cannon, Mr. Jim Cuddy and Councillor Thomas Welby.  Our policy is based on the fundamental principle that local people who live and work in an area, or have strong family ties with an area, are entitled to build homes in that area unless there are compelling safety or environmental reasons they should not do so.  In our document, we acknowledge the congruence of our objective <Col N="2013"/>with that of successive Governments and which is also at the core of the Minister&rsquo;s guidelines for rural housing.  However, my party believes that the guidelines, while well intentioned, are too vague and open to different interpretations by planners.  They are lacking in the necessary detail to cement the rights of rural people to remain living within their own communities.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The motion asks the House to call on the Minister to examine some key issues, namely, consideration of an independent national planning monitoring committee; the idea of a national water and sewerage services authority; the appropriateness of the present definition of the word &ldquo;local&rdquo; in the rural housing guidelines; the interpretation of the term &ldquo;housing need&rdquo; and why farming is seen as the only profession that allows a person to qualify for planning permission; the desirability of an independent appeal boards within An Bord Plean&aacute;la; publication of information about the success rate of planning applications, and details of pre-planning meetings to be included in planning files; and simplifying the planning permission process for a house specially designed to accommodate a person with a disability.  My party colleague, Senator Minihan, will expand on the third and subsequent points, while I will deal with the first two substantive issues.</P>
        <P>We ask the Minister to consider establishing an independent national planning monitoring committee on a statutory basis.  It is hoped that this committee could advise the Minister on matters relating to planning policy, and advise and assist local public representatives in the preparation of local planning policy and development plans.  It would have an overall regulatory role in the implementation of Government policy and guidelines on rural housing.  While the Department already plays a monitoring role regarding local authorities, this new body could act as a liaison between the Department and the elected representatives on councils.  The committee could help elected members implement directives from the Department, as well as identify and resolve local obstacles in the way of implementation.  The Minister and Members of the House will be aware that when it comes to the drafting of local development plans, councillors are entitled to consult and seek advice from local private planning experts, separate from local authority planners.  However, councillors must pay for this service.  The establishment of this new committee would meet that requirement.  The Progressive Democrats Party is of the view that if the Minister establishes this body on a statutory basis, local authorities will enthusiastically engage with it in the implementation of Government policy and guidelines on rural housing.  This must be facilitated, encouraged and welcomed.</P>
        <P Just="Left">In the second substantive point in our motion, the Progressive Democrats Party asks the Minister to examine the need for a national water and sewerage services authority.  We envisage something akin to that which exists for national roads, <Col N="2014"/>the National Roads Authority, and for group water schemes.  This authority would ensure the provision of an adequate and efficient network of water and sewerage infrastructure.  We propose that this body would have regional offices and would be responsible for the planning, delivery and maintenance of water and sewerage infrastructure in its region.</P>
        <P>It is important that this national water and sewerage services authority would be responsible for the implementation of water services investment programmes.  Every Member of this House will be aware of the problems that exist with implementing these investment programmes.  Last December, the water services investment programme 2005-2007 set out a comprehensive schedule of new schemes to start over the next two years.  The programme is made up of 899 projects with an overall capital value of &euro;5.1 billion.  Why is it that local authorities are no nearer to putting many of those schemes out to tender?  The latest programme for 2005-2007 contains many of the same projects as the 2004-2006 programme.  This is not satisfactory.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Progressive Democrats Party has three primary concerns.  First, rural Ireland may be left behind in the delivery of small schemes in towns and villages.  Councils have been told to group schemes but there is still toing and froing between the local authority and the Department.  Where rural areas come under the catchment of larger urban centres, they may get left behind.  The large population centres get their projects under way while the water and sewerage schemes in the hinterland are stalled or delayed.  This certainly has been the case in County Limerick, in Mungret, Patrickswell and Adare, where schemes are delayed.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Second, we are concerned that much needed new developments are being held up because the necessary water and sewerage services are not in place.  Local development plans and water services plans do not complement each other at present.  Where possible, the plan for water services should be agreed and in place before development is planned.</P>
        <P>Our third concern is that where services are absent and yet are included in the water services investment programme, developers install temporary systems and then pass the cost of this onto already hard-pressed home buyers and taxpayers. It is clear to us that this is unsatisfactory.  We await the Minister&rsquo;s view on the matter.</P>
        <P>My party&rsquo;s motion calls for further reform of the planning process, not for its own sake, but to enhance our planning system further.  I suspect that this goal is broadly supported across this House and by the Minister.  This is not just a rural issue.  As Senator Minihan will make clear in his contribution, the process in place for rural development has real and serious implications for the way our commuter towns, will develop.  An optimal rural planning system is necessary to <Col N="2015"/>complement proper urban development because they go hand in hand.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Progressive Democrats Party has examined how the system works and at how it can work better.  I move this motion in the confident hope that the Minister will consider it carefully and continue to work with us to improve the planning regime.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnMinihan"><NameTxt>Mr. Minihan</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the motion.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No 1:</P>
        <P LI="1">To delete all words after &ldquo;Seanad &Eacute;ireann&rdquo; and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />mindful of the neglect of rural Ireland that has taken place under the current Administration and noting;</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />that the Government has presided over a huge fall in the level of farm incomes &mdash; the average farm income has declined dramatically over the last ten years;</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />that the IFA claimed in 2005 that there are more than 15,000 farm families with incomes of less than &euro;200 per week and that last year, the average farm income was &euro;15,000, while the average industrial wage stood at &euro;30,000;</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />concerned at the flight from the land, illustrated by the fact that since 1997 the number of young farmers claiming installation aid has fallen by around two thirds, while it is estimated that seven farmers leave the business each day;</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />noting the Western Development Commission report published in May 2006, which highlighted a 30% underspend in the Border, midlands and west region under the national development plan, while the wealth gap between east and west has also grown since 2002;</P>
        <P FLI="0"><?oasys _is1p8- ?><?oasys _ix ?>Calls on the Government to reverse its <i>laissez-faire</i> approach to rural development and take concerted action to address the planning chaos and severe infrastructure deficit by:</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />reforming our planning laws to ensure that those who wish to live in rural areas are empowered to do so;</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />ensuring that planning permissions, when decided upon, take account of the need to attract returned emigrants and encourage people working in a locality to live there;</P><Col N="2016"/>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />recognising the urgent need to promote stable and sustainable development patterns; and</P>
        <P LI="1"><Miles com="mdash142" />at a time of great plenty, targeting investment in rural areas to ensure proper infrastructure exists to attract investment, create jobs and allow rural Ireland to thrive.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I welcome the Minister to the House to discuss this important and topical motion.  Listening to Senator Brennan, one would not think the Progressive Democrats Party has been part of the Government for the past ten years.  He appeals to and begs the Minister to do this, that and the other.  He is probably not aware that his party is part of this Government.</P>
        <P>The American broadcaster, John Madden, famously said, &ldquo;Self praise is for losers. Be a winner. Stand for something.&rdquo;  While he could not have known about the weakness of the current Government, he was certainly on the right track.  This motion is the desperate death rattle of a dying Government, substituting self-congratulation for lack of positive action over the past nine and a half years.  Empty words and empty promises and complete lack of follow-through are the hallmarks of a Government which certainly cannot stand over its record on planning or very little else either.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The basis for this motion is the Progressive Democrats policy document on rural housing, Planning for a Rural Future, which was launched last September.  This document follows each point of the motion, word for word.  It is therefore difficult to know whether this motion is an attempt at highlighting the contents of a document which is just another verbal whitewash in an ever increasing paper mountain or an attempt to give it credibility.  The Progressive Democrats Party has views on planning but its views have never been implemented by Government.</P>
        <P Just="Left">This is the latest promise feast from the junior partner in a Government that has driven farmers off the land and presided over a huge fall in the level of farm incomes.  The average farm income has declined dramatically in the past ten years, with the IFA claiming in 2005 that more than 15,000 farm families had incomes of less than &euro;200 per week and that last year, the average farm income was &euro;15,000, while the average industrial wage stood at &euro;30,000.</P>
        <P Just="Left">As we all know, this has led to a flight from the land, illustrated by the fact that since 1997, the number of young farmers claiming installation aid has fallen by around two thirds, while it is estimated that seven farmers leave the business each day.  Farmers have been caught in a trap of compulsory building necessitated by the nitrates directive.  They have been forced into expensive building projects at unrealistic prices caused by a 30% increase in the price of steel in the past two years.  The disastrous handling of the nitrates directive by the Minister for the Environment, <Col N="2017"/>Heritage and Local Government was a final nail in the coffin for many farmers.  I acknowledge he backtracked somewhat on what he said in this House last November.  He made a few U-turns on the nitrates directive and we all recognise that.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Hard-pressed farmers are once again under threat of being driven out of business by this Government by excessive demands on their resources.  Not only has the price of steel risen at an alarming rate in the past two years, since the beginning of this year, the price of concrete has also increased dramatically under the Minister&rsquo;s regime.</P>
        <P>According to the Teagasc-NUI report, Rural Ireland 2025, Foresight Perspectives, if the current trends continue, they will result in serious failures to achieve declared policy goals for rural Ireland.  On current trends, the following outcomes are likely by 2025 according to the report.  There will not be an acceptable regional balance in Ireland&rsquo;s economy, population, commercial agriculture and modern enterprises which will be even more concentrated in the east and south than at present.  Rural areas, especially in the north west and north midlands will lag behind in respect of communications and other infrastructure, especially as EU funds will not be available for future development.  There will be a dramatic reduction in farmer numbers, lower agricultural prices and widespread decline in commercial farming.  Lower volumes of farm output will threaten the viability of agrifood processing enterprises.  Forested land area will almost double, however the value of forestry and wood output will not increase to the same extent.  The rural landscape with Ireland&rsquo;s rich natural cultural environment will be under continued threat.</P>
        <P>New types of employment will not benefit the many rural communities outside of the commuting catchment zones but what could be achieved under a strong effective Government is a completely different picture.  If the national spatial strategy was implemented in conjunction with successive regionally focused national plans, the result would be a more balanced distribution of population and economic activity throughout the country.  Rapid communications and supporting infrastructure would provide greater accessibility throughout all parts of the country.  The rural economy could sustain more competitive enterprises through the development of additional entrepreneurial and management skills as well as further innovation in products, business organisation and marketing.</P>
        <P FLI="0" Just="Left">There is a need for greater commitment to rural and regional development throughout government and a constructive and effective institutional framework to ensure policies respond to the defined needs of the rural economy and rural communities.  A change is needed in the prevailing mode of policy making, public administration and policy delivery.  Tourism could be a vibrant sector of the rural economy, providing knowledge-based environmental goods and services, <Col N="2018"/>focused on Ireland&rsquo;s unique landscape and culture.  Forestry and the ocean economy could be sizeable suppliers to the energy sector and provide valued public goods.  During the debate on energy last week we said we should look at wave energy, an area on which the Government has done no research whatsoever.</P>
        <P>The bottom line for all of this is that these are aspirational concepts that could be realised through the actions of strong Government action.  The rhetoric of stated policy needs to be followed through with clear operational programmes, especially in relation to the White Paper on rural Development and the national spatial strategy.</P>
        <P>I support the motion&rsquo;s call for the establishment of a national planning monitoring committee, to act as an appeals mechanism to give people who have fallen victim to the Government&rsquo;s mismanagement of the planning process a voice to air their concerns and a structure that will iron out planning inequities once and for all.</P>
        <P>In all planning areas, who exactly have been the winners under the Fianna F&aacute;il-Progressive Democrats Government?  Certainly the developers and the concrete industry have been winners, as was highlighted in last week&rsquo;s motion on energy but not first-time buyers, those who wish to live and work in the rural areas associated with their families for generations or returning emigrants desperate to put down roots in their native areas. Government inaction is destroying family life in rural Ireland.  Parents are being forced to see their adult children and grandchildren driven into over-priced housing in towns while being denied permission to build on available farmland in their native areas, which would benefit the community by the establishment of a network of extended families.  This issue has arisen time and time again but the Government has refused to deal with it.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Taoiseach promised radical changes to the planning process but nothing has happened.  He has lost credibility in this as well as in every other area of trust, which the people have placed in him.  The promises he made in Sligo three years ago have not resulted in action.  As the election approaches, the Government is chasing its tail and trying to make something out of issues with which it did not deal during the past nine-and-a-half years.  The bottom line, however, is that no matter what the spin, the Government has neglected the people of rural Ireland.</P>
        <P Just="Left">It has been left to the county development plans of local authorities to address the issue of rural settlement.  Their aim is to strengthen the fabric of existing settlements and development clusters in the country, creating and maintaining vibrant and thriving urban and rural communities.  Let us take, for example, County Longford which is a highly rural area, with agriculture having been the primary land use and industry which has sustained its people for generations.  However, new economic and social forces have begun to change people&rsquo;s relationship with the <Col N="2019"/>land.  Agriculture has gone into decline and there is pressure for land in rural areas to be used for non-agricultural purposes.   Accordingly, the council has developed objectives with a view to reversing rural decline. Central to that reversal is the need to have firmly in place a planning process that supports the right of those who wish to live in rural areas and empowers them to do so.  This has not been the reality under the current Government.  One would think the Government was in opposition, given the behaviour of the Progressive Democrats and Fianna F&aacute;il on this issue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnMinihan"><NameTxt>Mr. Minihan</NameTxt>
	<P>Given that the Senator said nothing about rural planning, I am glad we did.  I thought we were having a debate on agriculture.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnPaulPhelan"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Phelan</NameTxt>
	<P>If Senator Minihan knew anything about rural Ireland he would know that agriculture and rural planning are very much interconnected.  Clearly he does not.  </P>
        <P>I second the amendment in the name of my colleague, Senator Bannon and all the Fine Gael Senators. Senator Bannon is correct. It is ironic that we are discussing housing. We have had a number of debates on housing in recent months.  Given the Progressive Democrats motion, one would not think that party had been in Government for nine-and-a-half years with its Fianna F&aacute;il partners.  It has singularly failed in all the objectives Senator Brennan outlined in his opening remarks.  He spoke of the need for a good supply of affordable housing.</P>
        <P>Last week we had a debate on housing.  It is clear that houses are still being constructed with hollow blocks in this city and there is certainly not a good supply of housing.  We all know about the problems of affordability, as outlined by Senator Bannon.  Senator Brennan mentioned the quality of life issues.  The Government has condemned people to living miles from their places of work and to commuting morning and evening.  If they have children they see them only for a couple of hours per day.  I would like those people to hear the Progressive Democrats&rsquo; motion and Senator Brennan refer to quality of life issues.</P>
        <P>If one has to work in Dublin and every day drive from the furthest point of the Minister&rsquo;s constituency in, say, Rathvilly, County Carlow, one has little by way of quality of life.  Some people spend two or three hours in a car every morning and evening getting to and from work.  The Government&rsquo;s motion proposes little to help those who find themselves in that position.</P>
        <P>I agree with Senator Brennan who said there is a need to put the contents of pre-planning meetings on the planning file.  That is the correct approach.  The standard of engagement that takes place with planners and those who make applications at pre-planning meetings varies widely across the country.  Something needs to be done in this area.  Often people get no indication one way or another from pre-planning meetings and, <Col N="2020"/>as Senator Brennan pointed out, these are not taken into account when the planning file is judged at a later date.</P>
        <P>One particular bugbear I have is the issue of vernacular planning in rural areas.  We have a particular problem in my neck of the woods in Carlow and Kilkenny where planners say they want small windows in houses.  The small windows in rural houses came from the time when the British authorities were in control and there was a tax on windows.  It is not acceptable in this day and age to implement the social policy of the British authorities as implemented here a couple of hundred years ago merely because it is covered by the term &ldquo;vernacular planning&rdquo;.  That is unsustainable into the future particularly in the case of a house facing south where a greater use of glass at the front would attract and maintain heat, given the problems of energy costs and sources.  There is a need for a commonsense approach to planning in local authorities areas.</P>
        <P>I have eight planning files of people in Carlow and Kilkenny who have been refused planning permissions on their own lands.  In some cases, this was done for quite good planning reasons but in many others the reasons were flimsy and a lack of commonsense was applied by planners.  When files were refused, people had to make a couple of minor adjustments before reapplying because the further information option was not used in the planning system.</P>
        <P Just="Left">We must ensure a continuous flow of people into rural areas.  In the past couple of years, it has been said that if one is from a rural area one should be able to build in it.  I believe in that concept but we should not erect a cast-iron barrier against people moving into rural communities from outside because such people will be essential to the future development of such areas.</P>
        <P>I share with Senator Brennan and others their sense of frustration with the operation of An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  I urge the Minister to ensure that there will be a shake-up in that organisation&rsquo;s operations.  In my short time in politics, I have seen many contradictory decisions emanating from An Bord Plean&aacute;la, so there needs to be more consistency in that regard.</P>
        <P>I agree with Senator Bannon that the rural housing guidelines and the Taoiseach&rsquo;s pronouncements in Sligo three years ago have not been implemented in full in rural areas.  I urge the Government to ensure that those guidelines are acted upon by local authorities and are included in local authority development plans.</P>
        <P>Renewable energy is another area of interest to me.  In recent years in County Kilkenny, a number of planning applications have been granted for wind turbines but they are not permitted by the Electricity Supply Board to connect to the national grid.  I readily accept that there are areas of the country which are suitable for wind energy, while others are not.  Where permission has been granted and where no local objections are raised, however, it is unacceptable for the <Col N="2021"/>ESB to continue to bar such turbines from connecting to the national grid.  The Minister and his Cabinet colleagues should do something to prevent that blockage from occurring in future.</P>
        <P>The Progressive Democrats&rsquo; motion refers to establishing a national water and sewerage services authority but I never realised that it was part of the Progressive Democrats&rsquo; political ethos to support the development of another quango.  Senator Brennan referred to the role of the National Roads Authority.  If the proposed new authority is envisaged as something along the lines of the NRA, I would oppose it tooth and nail.  Earlier on I spoke about An Bord Plean&aacute;la but the National Roads Authority is very much a law unto itself.  I would not like to see a similar authority being given powers over future water and sewerage developments.  That function belongs directly to local authorities.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Minister and the Government should ensure that adequate funding is provided for the upgrading, maintenance and installation of new sewerage schemes.  There are three or four such schemes in Kilkenny.  One scheme has been on the cards for 30 years in Kilmacow.  It is progressing a little at the moment but it has been progressing for the past ten years and there is still no sign of any building blocks being laid.  I could name umpteen other villages in Carlow and Kilkenny that suffer from similar problems.  Rather than setting up another quango, therefore, we should invest in local authorities so that they can provide the necessary services.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelKitt"><NameTxt>Mr. Kitt</NameTxt>
	<P>With your permission, a Chathaoirligh, I wish to share my time with Senator MacSharry.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senators will have four minutes each.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelKitt"><NameTxt>Mr. Kitt</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House for this interesting debate.  I take Senator John Paul Phelan&rsquo;s point that there is a connection between agriculture and housing matters.  Like Senator Bannon and other colleagues, I recently met with the Irish Farmers&rsquo; Association.  I found it interesting that the IFA&rsquo;s representatives did not have the doom and gloom approach to which Senator Bannon referred.  They raised three issues with me, namely, capital gains tax, land leasing and compensation for road development.  Those are interesting matters, given our pre-budget discussions.  This debate is relevant, particularly as we are always talking about having discussions on planning matters.  The proposals made by Senators Brennan and Bannon are well worth examining.  </P>
        <P>I am interested in the definition of the word &ldquo;local&rdquo;, which is something that exercised our minds on Galway County Council for many years.  Many councillors think we should not use the word local at all because one can argue the case along other lines.  One may talk about someone <Col N="2022"/>being local to an area but many of my colleagues on the county council have argued about people being in a particular parish or school catchment area.  It is disappointing that the rainbow of councillors on Galway County Council, of which Senator Bannon&rsquo;s party is the largest component, has now decided that &ldquo;local&rdquo; will mean eight kilometres or five miles from one&rsquo;s home, which is very restrictive.  It was much more flexible before the last review of the Galway county development plan.  The Minister, Deputy Roche, and his predecessors have been trying to give people an opportunity to live in their native areas, an idea which the Fine Gael amendment supports.</P>
        <P>Senator John Paul Phelan referred to pre-planning meetings.  Some councils use the excuse that they cannot talk to an applicant because an application is before the planners.  While this does not seem to be the case in many counties, it is unfortunately so in Galway where no discussions can take place while a valid application is before the county council.  That rule is wrong and should be changed.  We are all in favour of having more planners.  In addition, I hope the Minister will address the question of An Bord Plean&aacute;la in his reply to the debate.  It does not matter to me whether we have one board or two but we need an explanation as to what exactly is going on.  It is difficult to comprehend some decisions that are being made and this inconsistency is causing great frustration for many people.</P>
        <P>I note that the costings for the 2005-07 County Galway water and sewerage investment programme add up to almost &euro;500 million or half a billion euro.  It is a huge programme and I compliment the Minister on his achievements since taking over his current portfolio.  There is a huge volume of work to do next year.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I wish to ask the Minister about the issue of bundling applications.  I was in favour of the design-build-operate model with one contractor being responsible for a number of schemes but I am beginning to have second thoughts about it.  I have seen some very large schemes being bundled with small ones, which means that the latter schemes are held up.  In County Clare, colleagues of mine have said that their town was bundled with two towns that needed a foreshore licence.  I realise that this matter is not the Minister&rsquo;s responsibility but that of the Department of Communications, Marine and Natural Resources.  I believe that the application process for foreshore licences can take up to two or three years and, if that is so, I hope we can unbundle such applications.  We should examine the possibility of having separate applications for foreshore licences to avoid such problems arising in future.</P>
        <P>I welcome this debate which has given us an opportunity to discuss planning matters.  We could go into many other issues concerning rural housing but I hope this water and sewerage programme will be implemented.  It is important for the development of towns and villages where people wish to live but have not been able to do <Col N="2023"/>so due to a lack of investment.  We now have such an investment programme.  If the Minister achieves the co-operation of the local authorities, we will also have sustainable rural housing development.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarcMacSharry"><NameTxt>Mr. MacSharry</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">It is welcome that we are debating this important issue.  Whoever comes up with the optimum planning system will probably win the Nobel prizes for literature and peace.  Notwithstanding that, we need to monitor the issues continually and remain open to improvements.  Most of the Opposition&rsquo;s amendment to the motion warrants no comment other than to remind the House that nobody has done more for rural Ireland than this Government.  As somebody who comes from rural Ireland, I think it a case of a lot done, more to do.  I might wish a lot more had been done but&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>This Government has been in power for nine and a half years.  Who wants 15 years of Fianna F&aacute;il and the Progressive Democrats?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarcMacSharry"><NameTxt>Mr. MacSharry</NameTxt>
	<P>I note that the Western Development Commission&rsquo;s report revealed an underspend of 30%.  However, that money has not been spent anywhere else and we have until the end of 2009 to spend it.  I am confident the Government will meet its target in that regard.  The number of houses being built today is double the figure when this Government entered office in 1997.  With regard to planning issues in general, I support the broad thrust of the motion and urge the Minister to consider its contents with an open mind.  I have long had concerns about the right to object because I have a fundamental problem with the fact that somebody living in California can object to a planning application brought by a person who wishes to build a house in County Sligo.  That provision is simply wrong and needs to be changed.</P>
        <P>Earlier this year, we had the opportunity to welcome the Planning and Development (Strategic Infrastructure) Bill 2006.  That Bill will be of great benefit in terms of avoiding emotive scenarios such as the Sligo inner relief road, which took 22 years to complete largely because of local indifference.  However, we ought to revisit the issue of how a project in a particular area comes to be regarded as strategic because decisions in this respect vary between regions.  Lough Key Forest Park in County Roscommon, for example, brought significant local benefits in terms of employment and tourism, even if it was not strategically important to other regions.  I would support the establishment of local bodies, such as local authorities or regional units of An Bord Plean&aacute;la, which would have a better understanding of the area and would be more informed about cases.</P><Col N="2024"/>
        <P>We often hear it said by planners that their job is not to design houses.  However, applications have been often refused over issues which could have been resolved if the agent for the applicant had been advised in advance.  In that regard, a more proactive approach would be useful.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I propose to share my time with Senator Norris, by agreement.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>This motion is disingenuous, in so far as it attempts to focus attention on the specific issue of rural housing while ignoring the much more important and urgent problem of housing on a national basis.  It is an act of political opportunism on behalf of Government Members to cherry-pick the parts of an issue which suit them while closing their eyes to the areas where the record of this Government is anything but good.</P>
        <P Just="Left">During the past decade, we have achieved a great deal in this country.  I am often asked, when abroad, to explain why Ireland has become so successful.  We can be proud of many of our achievements.  We have consistently achieved growth rates well ahead of our partners in the European Union.  Unemployment has been reduced from crisis levels to the point at which everyone is prepared to forget about the problems which remain in that regard.  Young people in this country do not remember the high unemployment levels of the past and are in danger of becoming overconfident.  We have continued to attract foreign direct investment, which has been the real lifeblood of our boom.</P>
        <P>However, we have failed in a number of ways over the past decade.  We have not only failed to keep a grip on inflation but have even tended to encourage it recklessly.  We have also failed to provide an adequate infrastructure for the knowledge society we claim to be interested in developing, most notably through our abysmal failure to make broadband available to everyone in the country at a reasonable cost.</P>
        <P>One failure, housing, stands above all others.  We have failed to provide houses where they are needed and have instead created a nightmare of urban sprawl which has spawned a raft of problems, to say nothing of causing us to be held up to the world as a classic example of how not to plan cities.  Several weeks ago, I raised this matter on the Order of Business after realising we were second from the bottom of a list of countries which were criticised for urban sprawl.</P>
        <P Just="Left">We have failed to balance supply and demand to bring about an orderly property market.  For the past decade and more, we just let prices rip.  This has greatly benefited builders, developers and property investors but has created nothing but misery for the hundreds of thousands of young people who have been forced to pay outlandish prices for houses in places where they do not want to live.  They have been forced into a <Col N="2025"/>life of long-distance commuting on overcrowded roads and left with little time for their children.  I cannot believe that people are forced to make daily commutes to Dublin over distances of 150 km and more simply because we did not plan properly.  This situation was not inevitable but was allowed to arise by a Government which shut its eyes to the consequences of short-sighted planning and land use policies.  The people will pay for the consequences of those policies for many years to come.  With interest rates continuing to rise, we can safely predict that the worst of the pain is still to come.</P>
        <P>Our failure in housing is a major blot on the Celtic tiger and it is the height of foolishness to try to divert our attention by focusing on the less consequential issue of rural housing.  I do, however, concur with Senator MacSharry in his criticism of the right of somebody living in San Francisco to object to a development in rural Ireland.</P>
        <P Just="Left">We should focus our efforts on undoing, to the extent that it may still be possible, the grave damage inflicted in the past decade to housing in this country.  It is not yet too late to take the opportunity to make amends.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I am grateful to my colleague, Senator Quinn, for sharing his time with me.  The motion is a very long and self-praising piece of work.  I am reminded of the old clich&eacute;, self-praise is no praise.  That is advice which the Government should take on board.  I have a record of supporting the Government when I think it is right and criticising it when I think it is wrong.  I agree with Senator Quinn that much of this motion is disingenuous and I am glad that an amendment has been proposed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>It is worse.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>In that case, I am put in a quandary.  Once gain the Government is trying to pick a popular issue &mdash; rural housing.  Allowing one-off housing is seen to be supporting the farmers.  The Government is doing what it has a tendency to do in this area, which is curry favour with a specific element.  As we are discussing housing, the Minister might remember a debate we had in this House last week in which Senator O&rsquo;Toole and I managed to unearth a memorandum that showed the Government had stood over the construction of 250,000 hollow-brick houses which were defective in terms of heat conservation.  They were an environmental threat.  The Government did so to satisfy the demands of a certain section of the cement lobby.</P>
        <P>I object to the Government always going for the easy vote.  It curries favour with, for example, farmers and people in rural areas who want naturally &mdash; it is a very human wish &mdash; to be allowed to build wherever they like and to be able, in circumstances where farming is not as economically viable as it used to be, to make a living by selling <Col N="2026"/>off plots.  They often doctor it up as if it were for a son or daughter and once they get permission, it is flogged off, as the Minister knows perfectly well.</P>
        <P>There are votes in this kind of thing, just as there are votes in trashing groups such as An Taisce.  I am glad the Minister is present because I want to say this directly to him.  He has played a personal role in the trashing of An Taisce and undermining it.  The Government set out to do this with a chorus of approval from people with strong local authority links by undermining its statutory status, removing its grants, and turning it from a very useful organisation into one that is plagued by difficulties because of the way it has been undermined.  We now have a virtually amateur organisation and eventually the Government will remove its status.  This is damaging.</P>
        <P Just="Left">We all know the impact of one-off housing on the tourist business.  People from throughout the world continually ask me how we can destroy our own country and kill the goose that lays the golden egg in this atrocious and unsophisticated way.  This is always met by the accusations of so-called Dublin 4 voices.  It is not just Dublin 4 voices.  I hear it now from people who have lived in the countryside all their lives.  They are just as appalled as I am at what is happening in rural Ireland.  There is a significant problem.  How are we allowing houses with no sewerage, no effective planning and no services?  Do people have the right to put a house wherever they like and then expect the taxpayer to supply all these services?  If the Government is only looking for their vote, it will promise them anything.  I would like to think that a responsible Government would take into account the national interest.</P>
        <P>The same applies to affordable housing.  A great noise was made about affordable housing and how we would look after people.  We have not done it.  Once again we have given in to a group that is too close to Fianna F&aacute;il, the major party in Government &mdash; the building industry.  Those in that industry are allowed to weasel out of putting affordable housing in their nice expensive developments.  They buy it off.  The Minister is an artist in this regard.  I heard him this morning talking about how, despite us being bottom of the class in terms of Kyoto, we will buy our way out with carbon credits.  It is a disaster.  We should not be doing this.  We should not allow the builders to weasel out in this way and trade off useless bits of land so that people will be deprived of housing.</P>
        <P>The Minister&rsquo;s party was once the party of the plain people of Ireland.  The Government is not doing any favours to the plain people of Ireland in its housing policy.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><TitleTxt>Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>I am so grateful to Senator Quinn for sharing time with Senator Norris.  It is always very worthwhile.  Apropos of the plain people of Ireland, those who have their dinner in the middle of the day and tend to vote <Col N="2027"/>for Fianna F&aacute;il because they are plain, simple and wise people, we housed 90,000 of them last year.  Whatever other failures we may have, while we might quibble about where they have gone, we have built five times more houses than other nations in Europe.  Our rate is four times greater <i>per capita</i> than the United Kingdom, a country that is undergoing what is called an emergency housing programme.  Whatever else we have failed to do, we have not failed in the housing area.</P>
        <P>Senators may make the fair point that we have issues with urban sprawl.  It is a pity that Senators were not cognisant of what I did last week when I used powers never previously used by a Minister in the history of the State, precisely to prevent this type of profiteering and this outrageous scandalous and entirely counterproductive planning.  To suggest that Fianna F&aacute;il is somehow beholden is somewhat disingenuous and, in the circumstances of last week, is very difficult for me.</P>
        <P>However, I thank the Members for giving me the opportunity to speak in this debate.  In particular, I thank the Progressive Democrats.  It is important to propose ideas that we can debate.  My friends in the Progressive Democrats are almost being provocative in the sense that they know that more than any other Minister, I have a particular personal aversion to quangos.</P>
        <P>The Government recognises the strong tradition of Irish people living in rural areas.  Even if Senator Norris does not recognise it, in reality 40% of the people live in rural areas.  We should not force those people into what I call the European Environment Agency&rsquo;s short-sighted, blinkered and imperfect view of planning.  I remember walking across a hillside in County Wicklow with Jacques Delors a number of years ago.  He commented on how wonderful and idyllic it was that children could grow up in a rural background with a father who could make part of his living from farming and could also, as he did, commute to the city to work.  He said that as far as he could see, that was as close as it was possible to be to an idyll.</P>
        <P>We need to learn one thing, which is that we do not always get it wrong.  Senator Quinn was correct and generous in saying that when travelling abroad, people ask how this small country in 20 years could move from the position that existed in 1987, when Senator Bannon&rsquo;s party last relinquished power after a full term in office and when we were the basket case of Europe.  We had 71,000 people working in the building and construction industry.  Today, because of the Government&rsquo;s policies, we have 250,000.  We had people fleeing the country and now we have people coming here, which is wonderful.  They enrich us.  They are part of us and are making the country a better place.  How could anybody suggest that this country is in some sense a failure when the reality is otherwise?</P><Col N="2028"/>
        <P>We must realise that there is no prescriptive, one-form-fits-all approach to planning.  We have a different system of settlement which must be recognised in any planning debate.  I congratulate the Progressive Democrats Members, who are trying to get to the essence of the debate on what we are trying to and need to create.  I read the EEA report and have had heated conversations with Professor McGlade.  I do not agree that the EEA has it right and argue that it has it wrong.  To suggest that we should shove everybody into towns would be a disservice.  It would be desperately damaging to the fabric of Irish life.  I do not agree that we get it wrong.  We do not always get it right.  A little humility in Irish politics goes a long way.  We certainly make many mistakes.  In the planning area, I challenge anybody to say we always get it wrong.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">6 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P>There is a strong tradition of living in rural Ireland, which I celebrate.  I come from a town and am quintessentially an urban person.  However, having a countryside populated with people is incredibly enriching.  Otherwise we would have something approaching a desert.  I do not agree that the kinds of settlement patterns in this country are in some way inimical to planning.  I will certainly not take a lecture on planning and housing from people who come from countries that have created urban disasters.  I believe there is a fundamental problem in planning.  Far too much of our thinking about planning is informed by some sort of urban idyll, when I believe an alternative exists.  I support a strong progressive local government system that has at its core the right to plan and develop.  I support well-managed local decisions taken within a policy framework as set by local authorities.  I take issue with Senator Bannon in that regard.  The Senator was correct when he said planning must be informed by the national spatial strategy.  He said also the strategy must be informed at local level by the regional planning guidelines and incorporated into local planning.  I do not want to be particularly partisan but the Senator&rsquo;s colleagues in Laois took disgraceful action in the past six months when they attempted to overturn the national spatial strategy and the regional planning guidelines.  They forced me, as a strong defender of local government, into the invidious position where, for the first time ever, I had to issue an order overturning a planning decision by local councils.  I was more than surprised when the Senator&rsquo;s party put Charlie Flanagan out to defend that on the national airways because it was an indefensible decision.  I ask the Senator&rsquo;s party to review that position.  I was pleased to hear Senator Bannon say he sees the logic of the national spatial strategy and the regional planning guidelines.</P>
        <P>I say to Senators who took the view taken by Senator Norris, in his own inimitable and charming way, on rural planning guidelines that the sustainable rural planning guidelines were put in place to ensure we have sustainable development <Col N="2029"/>in rural areas.  A total of 40% of our people live in rural Ireland and we should not force them to live in urban areas.  We should try to encourage them to live in their own areas but in a way which is sustainable.  That is the essence of the rural planning guidelines.</P>
        <P>The guidelines include a presumption in favour of quality one-off housing in rural communities provided proposals meet normal standards.  The guidelines require the overall presumption to be applied to the actual local needs of a community.  The guidelines are very subtle in that they recognise there is a variety of rural areas that requires a difference in the approach.  The planning authorities are required to review and vary their development plans, where necessary, to ensure their policies on rural settlement are consistent with the policies set out in the guidelines.  The guidelines are not a desiderata, and I accept Senator Brennan&rsquo;s point that some local authority planners have not copped that.  The guidelines are law, not something they can apply if they wish.</P>
        <P>I appreciate that many Senators have genuine concerns about the inconsistencies in the manner in which planning has sometimes manifested itself.  I agree with Senator Brennan that we need consistent implementation of the guidelines.  That is my wish too and we have been addressing that issue.  I emphasise that my Department is very conscious of that and I have made that point forcefully in private meetings I have had with county managers.  I have made it clear to county managers that I expect them to apply the letter but, more importantly, the spirit of the guidelines.  The spirit is not, as Senator Norris suggested, a charter for people to sell off sites.  The opposite is the case.</P>
        <P>We have tried to bring coherence to the issue of rural planning in the guidelines.  We have held seminars to ensure local authority planning staff are aware of the guidelines.  In particular the seminars dealt with the preparation of the planning policies, providing better supports and advice, and giving an efficient, comprehensive and good mannered response.  I emphasised all of that in my contacts with county managers.</P>
        <P>The guidelines set a strong framework but they are not intended to straightjacket planning authorities, for example, by limiting their room to manoeuvre on who can and cannot be regarded as local.  I fully appreciate the point Senator Brennan and the Progressive Democrats made that &ldquo;local&rdquo; should not simply mean farming or farming stock.  I agree with them on that but the guidelines do not do that.  The guidelines provide that reasonable proposals on suitable sites for persons who are part of and contribute to the local community should be accommodated.  I cannot understand how any Senator could take exception to that.  In particular, I cannot understand how a gifted and talented man like Senator Norris could take exception to it.  What I said was that suitable sites for persons who make a contri<Col N="2030"/>bution to the rural community should be accommodated.  The guidelines state that examples of such persons would include farmers, their sons and daughters but they do not state that it must be exclusively those categories.  They provide for planning authorities to grant permission in cases where exceptional health circumstances arise.  I make no apology for doing that and I explained to this House the reason I made these specific arrangements for one-off housing where, for example, there is a handicap in a family.</P>
        <P>I was walking through a small village in Meath with a council colleague, Nick Kilroy, and had one of those experiences that one has only because one is a politician on the ground.  A young woman approached us and spoke about a planning problem she was experiencing.  She was not from the country.  She had two children with a very severe condition.  They could not live in a housing estate.  Mr. Kilroy told me that was a failure of the planning system because that woman could not be accommodated for a one-off house in a rural area.  That is why I changed the law.  I changed the law because I believe the law should have some humanity infused into it.  I made a special arrangement for families facing a special challenge to be given consideration and get planning permission.  I put into the law also a requirement that emigrants who return to this country should be given consideration.  Generations of people had to leave this country because of poverty.  It was their emigrants&rsquo; remittances that allowed us to build the Celtic tiger.  If they want to come back in their failing years and build houses in the countryside where they were reared, we would be a lesser nation if we did not accommodate them.  I make no apologies for those comments and make them simply by way of explaining the guidelines.  The guidelines are intended, on the one hand, to create a rationality but, on the other hand, to infuse a degree of humanity into the planning system.</P>
        <P>Promoting sustainable rural housing in a way that works for communities should be at the core of planning, particularly in non-urban areas.  In the guidelines we have tried to create a new template against which planning can and will be facilitated.  The key objective is to maintain a vibrant rural population while respecting and consolidating the traditional forms and the patterns of housing development in areas, for instance, where there are clusters of housing.  In the stronger rural areas the guidelines corporate development policies build on the strengths of those areas by striking a balance.  That is why I struck down the planning abnormalities in Laois last week.</P>
        <P Just="Left">With regard to the proposals in the motion, it was courageous, rather than opportunistic, of my Progressive Democrats colleagues to bring those forward.  I do not accept they were opportunistic.  We should debate issues in the open in a more mature way.</P><Col N="2031"/>
        <P>On getting local authorities to do the job correctly and applying the rules consistently, it is proposed that we should have a national monitoring committee.  As everybody knows, I have an aversion to quangos but there are practical reasons this approach might not be the correct one.  The central thesis is that a central advisory committee would be best placed to deliver better decisions.  It would be difficult for a national body to be able to intervene in the more than 33,000 planning applications for one-off houses.  That is the level of one-off housing applications.  Senator Norris was wrong when he suggested this was a minority problem.  A total of 33,000 applications were made for one-off houses in the past year.  I understand what the Senators are suggesting and I respect their views but it would be difficult to effectively replicate the planning process by having a committee that would oversee all of that, and it would be difficult to get the focus right.</P>
        <P>I would be concerned also that a body like the one proposed would merely replicate the functions already performed by the Minister of the day.  I may be faulty as Minister of the day but I am not unconscious of the concerns about rural housing.  There is a danger that functions which properly should be under the charge of the politician who is answerable democratically would be replicated.  That is my personal objection to and difficulty with quangos, as they are commonly referred to.  We must be careful before going that route.  The creation of new bodies is often put forward as a proposition in this and the other House but any such proposition requires a good deal of assessment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister might wish to be conscious of the fact that, according to Standing Orders, he has 15 minutes available to him.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Cathaoirleach for his latitude.  I strongly feel we should have a long debate on this matter and this is why I am so grateful to the Progressive Democrats for tabling the motion.</P>
        <P>I have some concerns over independent appeals concerning sub-boards of An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  I will explain why and my reason is not indicative of a knee-jerk reaction.  Great coherence is afforded through having a single national body such as An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  Under the strategic infrastructure legislation, I effectively created a second board within the board, namely, the strategic infrastructure board, but problems with staffing and resources will arise if we keep dividing the board.  One of the great planning challenges we now face is the shortage of well-qualified planners.  It will surprise the House to learn that, in the past few months, I have been talking about making further appointments to An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  However, some of the largest bodies with a role in submitting names in this <Col N="2032"/>regard have not done so.  We need to be careful in this area.</P>
        <P>When the motion was tabled, I took a lot of time to do some analysis.  I noted there were 5,500 appeals to the board last year but that only 551 related to one-off rural houses.  To establish a series of sub-boards to deal specifically with this issue would not necessarily represent the best use of resources.  However, I compliment the Progressive Democrats on allowing for debate on the issue.  As usual, I will send a copy of the debate to the chairman of An Bord Plean&aacute;la so he will be conscious of the concerns that exist.</P>
        <P>On the creation of a national authority for water and sewerage services, we are making incredible progress in this area.  I do not say this in any vainglorious way because I happen to be in a very lucky position in which other Ministers responsible for the environment were not.  I have resources beyond those available to the others.  We have made great strides, particularly in respect of rural water, and this has been recognised by the chairman of the National Federation of Group Water Schemes.  Structural issues arise in the water and sewerage programme and bureaucracy and red tape have caused frustration.</P>
        <P>The Members who proposed this motion should note I am not convinced that establishing a national water and sewerage authority along the lines of the NRA is the way forward.  I have taken steps to de-bureaucratise the whole programme.  One will notice that, in the past year, I have adopted a much more liberal approach to sanctioning the smaller schemes, particularly those under the &euro;5 million threshold.  I mentioned the streamlined measures previously.  The major focus will be on giving the local authorities greater responsibility in terms of procurement and more capacity to move forward, and on providing for a reduction in the number of stage approvals.  This will solve the problem.</P>
        <P>Our planning system is working well given the strains thereon.  It was designed when there were very few development cases but recently there has been great pressure on every planning authority in the country.  While I am sometimes critical of these authorities, I believe they have done well in general.</P>
        <P>The sustainable rural housing guidelines are a central plank in my personal approach to the planning system.  Members of the House will be aware that I have issued a series of guidelines to try to change the planning system.  There have been changes in the guidelines, including the retail guidelines, and in a variety of other areas.  The way forward is to ensure the guidelines are applied.  Intellectually and temperamentally, I am against the creation of additional quangos.  I am very conscious of the need to have balanced, fair and more appropriate planning in rural Ireland.</P>
        <P>I thank the Senators for their contributions.  I apologise if I went a little off script because I believe one should do so from time to time.  I will make a copy of this debate available to the chair<Col N="2033"/>man of An Bord Plean&aacute;la because it is very important.  It gives the Senators, who are very closely wed to the councillors throughout the country, an opportunity to outline their views on how the planning system is working.  There is nothing wrong with their being closely wed to the councillors.  If we all listen to each other rather than preach at each other, we will have a better planning system.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryHenry"><NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
	<P>It is nice to be in agreement with the Minister in respect of several parts of the Progressive Democrats&rsquo; motion, which parts I have also rejected.  I was particularly interested in his comments on the national authority for water and sewerage services.  When I became a Member of this House almost 14 years ago, the number of private water schemes polluted by e.coli amounted to 25%.  I believe this has decreased to 22% after staggering sums of money were spent on the problem.</P>
        <P>Nobody seems to take responsibility for any of these issues.  A very large proportion of the pollution in some private water schemes is due to septic tanks.  Between these and the pollution arising from the spreading of animal faeces all over the country, it is a miracle we do not have the most extraordinary outbreaks of infection.  It was brought to my attention today that there is a notice in an area in the west stating there has been no water for a number of months and that it is being delivered by tanker.  This is ridiculous in this day and age.  Not only has there been a problem with e.coli in private water supplies but there has also been cryptosporidium, a very serious parasite.  No attention seems to be paid to how it affects public health.</P>
        <P>I will not outline the position on private wells because there seems to be no attempt to determine the quality of the water therein or its effect on public health.  During my professional life, particularly when I was training, I was always taught about problems with water supplies.  One of the most important points we had to take on board was that there was a need to have proper water supplies, particularly in rural areas.  I remember endemic typhoid in parts of this country.  It is dreadful to think, so many years later, that so many private water supplies are still polluted.</P>
        <P>Given that we are referring to one-off rural housing, the most important matter I would like to address concerns septic tanks.  The regulations in this regard seem to be totally out of date.  While there seem to be regulations for the construction industry concerning virtually every material it uses, be it associated with fire safety, electricity or gas, there is a very weak code of practice concerning the materials used for septic tanks.  At present, they fall under the Sale of Goods and Supply of Services Act or consumer laws dating from 1991.  Much legislation has been passed since then and it surely should have been <Col N="2034"/>applied to septic tanks, which are incredibly important parts of buildings.</P>
        <P Just="Left">There are no specifications on the required performance of septic tanks, including in respect of discharge therefrom, on the required quality of the soil after the effluent has passed through it, on the durability of the tanks, on the filter period, or on essential maintenance, including the frequency of desludging.  I believed we had introduced a measure some years ago that septic tanks had to be desludged every two years.  I gather this has fallen into abeyance.  I also believe those who desludged tanks had to have expertise but I have been told this is no longer the case.  These are two very serious matters because the ponding of sewage effluent and pollution of the ground infects surface water and drinking water.  It has been put to me that this is happening because the pump-outs are too costly.  What could be more costly than allowing people&rsquo;s health to be affected?  We cannot continue to proceed in such a ridiculous manner.  We have to make a huge effort to change the situation.  We need proper certification of the products which are used in the building of septic tanks.  We should also provide for proper certification of those who do the desludging.  They should have to have licences or something like that so that people cannot decide to do something about the place every few years.  We need to put in place such safety features because it is ridiculous that we are facing circumstances of this nature, having invested significant structural funds in these areas.</P>
        <P>I gather that the only way to check how effectively a septic tank is working is to examine the flow in and out of the tank.  I am not aware of anyone in the country who does that, but perhaps the Minister has better information than me.  I do not think it is right that the health of consumers who have paid for the installation of septic tanks should be endangered as a result of our failure to ensure those tanks are adequate.  Many people have paid for tanks which are far too small for the amount of waste that can be expected to go through them.  The Minister is aware that we have a much broader idea of what passes through municipal sewerage schemes than we have of what passes through tanks which serve single houses.  We do not know how many people live in each house, what their cooking methods are, whether they use jacuzzis, how much detergent they use and what they are doing about the waste water arrangements in the house.  We should take more responsibility for such matters.  I am sorry to appear so cross about this matter but I thought we had solved many of these problems years ago.  When I think about the amount of money that has been spent, I feel a significant proportion of it must have been wasted.</P>
        <P>I do not think the health implications of private wells have been addressed anywhere.  We are aware of the various issues pertaining to private water schemes.  I do not think enough interest has been taken in the human effects of the nitrates <Col N="2035"/>directive.  We know that high nitrate levels in waters are important for pregnant women, babies, children and the adult population.  We are not in a position to say that changes in nitrate levels do not have serious consequences for public health.  It is all very well to talk about building houses in nice rural settings &mdash; such houses can be very charming &mdash; but we have to consider the public health implications of what we are doing.  I do not think they have been addressed sufficiently.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnMinihan"><NameTxt>Mr. Minihan</NameTxt>
	<P>I join previous speakers in welcoming the Minister, Deputy Roche, to the House.  I thank him for his contribution to this debate.  I echo the words of my colleague, Senator Brennan, in support of the Government&rsquo;s recent action on rural planning.  I remind some of the previous speakers that the Progressive Democrats Party is not in favour of unrestricted housing development.  It does not believe people have the right to build wherever and in whatever style they like.  Senator Brennan dealt in detail with the first two calls for action in the motion proposed by my party this evening.  I am delighted, notwithstanding the Minister&rsquo;s response to the motion, to expand on the other points and calls for action referred to in the motion.  The suggestions we have made are intended to improve planning and to provide for a rural future.  The Progressive Democrats Party proposes that the definition of the word &ldquo;local&rdquo; in the rural planning guidelines should be amended.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnMinihan"><NameTxt>Mr. Minihan</NameTxt>
	<P>We believe people born and reared in a rural area, including those with no access to family lands, people who have lived in a rural area for seven years or more and have forged strong links with the local community in that time, and emigrants who return to the rural area in which they grew up, as the Minister referred to, should be seen as &ldquo;local&rdquo; people.  A rural dweller who has no family land on which to build should be allowed to build on any site within 8 km of his or her family home, subject to the usual environmental and traffic safety provisions.  Nobody other than local people, as defined in the manner we have suggested, should be allowed to build in areas of the country which are under development pressure, subject to compliance with the various environmental and safety regulations.  Housing need in such areas that is generated by nearby urban areas should be met in designated settlement centres.  All people should be free to build in rural areas which are not under development pressure and are facing population stagnation, as long as they comply with the usual environmental and road safety standards.  People should be encouraged to move to areas experiencing population decline.  The <Col N="2036"/>planning system should not pose any impediment to them doing so.</P>
        <P>The Progressive Democrats Party is in favour of an appropriate broadening of the interpretation of &ldquo;housing need&rdquo;.  A family that seeks to move ten or 15 miles, perhaps because of a new job, should not be disqualified from developing a new rural home because they have an existing house.  At present, such a family could fail the housing need test.  We do not believe farming should be seen as the only profession that qualifies a person for planning permission in rural areas.  Approximately 14% of the workforce was engaged in agriculture in 1991, but that figure now stands at 5%.  If farming is seen as the only profession that enables one to get planning permission, we may well be providing for a slow death sentence for rural Ireland.  People of other professions and none should be made equally welcome.</P>
        <P>My party also proposes the establishment of a new appeals process in respect of all applications for rural housing.  Responsibility for hearing appeals on rural housing should be taken from An Bord Plean&aacute;la and given to regional boards of appeal based in the constituencies used for election to the European Parliament which are outside Dublin.  The new appeals boards should include representatives of the planning and architecture industries, people with environmental or scientific backgrounds, representatives of rural organisations and development groups and people from the legal profession.  Rural organisations and development groups include the Leader programme, Macra na Feirme, the Western Development Commission, the county community forums and the IFA, for example.</P>
        <P>If we are to provide for openness and transparency in the planning process, details of all planning decisions should be posted on the Internet, along with the reason for those decisions.  The names and contact details of the engineers and architects who submitted the original proposals should be published on-line.  League tables of successful and unsuccessful planning applications by architectural and engineering firms should be posted on the website of every county council to ensure people have appropriate information at their disposal to make informed choices when selecting the firms with which they wish to work.  The Progressive Democrats believe such a system is necessary.</P>
        <P>I echo the Minister&rsquo;s comments about applications for permission to build houses to accommodate the special needs of people with disabilities.  Other than the necessary environmental and road safety regulations, no impediments should be put in the way of the sanctioning of planning permission to such people.  Planning policy must take account of the needs of the disabled in a sensitive and caring fashion.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator Brennan outlined the evidence and logic that underpins the Progressive Democrats&rsquo; call for the establishment of an independent <Col N="2037"/>national planning monitoring committee on a statutory basis, as well as the establishment of a national water and sewerage services authority.  I look forward to hearing the views of other Senators on these two proposals.  The points I have made reflect the opinion of the Progressive Democrats that rural dwellers should have the same rights as urban dwellers when deciding where to live.  That view is articulated in the party&rsquo;s rural planning policy, which was launched last month.  The policy is based on the fundamental principle that local people who live and work in an area, or have strong family ties with an area, are entitled to build homes in that area unless there are compelling safety or environmental reasons they should not.  The adversarial planning permission culture that has been adopted by some county councils must be changed.  Incentives should be put in place to attract families into areas of declining population.  Farming should not be the only profession that qualifies people for planning permission in rural areas.  We must intervene to halt the death sentence that has been given to rural Ireland.  That fate has not been prevented by current planning regulations.  There has been a great deal of discussion on the unsustainable nature of one-off rural housing, yet the huge growth in the commuter belt around Dublin is truly unsustainable.  Here massive estates are built without the physical and social infrastructure needed to support new communities.  These areas, as they balloon, will lead to problems for future generations.</P>
        <P>The Government has done more than any previous Administration to meet the rocketing housing demand faced by Ireland.  The opening line of the motion is an acknowledgement that Ireland&rsquo;s record levels of economic and population growth are creating the challenge of meeting record housing accommodation demand throughout the country.  I ask the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, Deputy Roche, to look favourably on our suggestions and proposals to see how they can enhance our efforts to meet this challenge.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CyprianBrady"><NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I wish to share my time with Senator Ormonde.  I welcome the Minister to the House and I very much welcome the Progressive Democrats motion on rural planning.  My experience of this issue is not great due to my background in Dublin city.  However, this is an issue that has exercised the Joint Committee on Environment and Local Government for some time and I have discussed it with colleagues from both Houses.  During the summer the committee contacted every county and city manager in the country regarding the implementation of the guidelines and the majority replied in a positive manner.  Some questions remain as to whether the spirit of the guidelines is being upheld in some counties, but the majority of local authorities are doing their utmost to implement the guidelines in <Col N="2038"/>the spirit they are intended and to the letter of the law.</P>
        <P Just="Left">There are outstanding issues in both rural and urban contexts.  In Dublin there are pre-planning meetings and discussions with planners on suggested developments.  These are issues that affect every part of the country.  There has been a huge explosion in the building industry and, as the Minister pointed out, we have progressed from employing between 30,000 and 40,000 people to employing 250,000.  Record numbers of houses have been built each year in recent years and we have maintained a quality of environment that other countries throughout the world observe with envy.  This has been achieved through the prudent implementation of existing laws and the introduction of other elements, including the guidelines.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The debate seemed to be leaning towards agricultural issues earlier and we should return to the motion and the planning issue.  One of the first words in the Minister&rsquo;s speech was tradition.  He referred to the tradition of Irish people living in rural areas.  This may be even relevant in an urban context because, in Dublin, there are what are considered to be urban villages.  Issues such as the design, size and height of properties apply there as does density of population.  Tradition plays an important part in rural areas.  When one hears the Minister address this issue, one understands that any guidelines introduced are in the best interests of local communities.</P>
        <P>Getting information on how, why and when planning decisions are made is a major issue in Dublin.  Pre-planning meetings with planners save everyone involved trouble, not only those applying for planning permission, but also those with objections.</P>
        <P>I have listened to Senator Henry on the issue of water treatment and in the past ten years, we have progressed from 20% to 90% water quality.  This has been achieved through prudent investment, and many towns and cities, including Dublin, Galway and Cork, have first-class water treatment services.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The guidelines are not perfect as regards effects on rural areas and there always will be individual issues.  However, they are effective and once implemented in the right spirit, as the Minister said, they will enhance the countryside.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde"><NameTxt>Ms Ormonde</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senator Brady for sharing time with me and I thank the Progressive Democrats for tabling this motion.  I welcome the Minister and look forward to re-reading his script as I agree with many of the points he raised.</P>
        <P>There is not a family in the country that does not know about this subject.  I think every family in Ireland has, at some stage, submitted a planning application.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>They have submitted applications and been rejected.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="2039"/>
      <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde"><NameTxt>Ms Ormonde</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I seek only to represent the plain people of Ireland to best improve the quality of life for all.</P>
        <P>I represent an area that has experienced urban sprawl with between 300 and 400 housing schemes, no community life, few residents&rsquo; associations and no soul.  I welcome the Minister&rsquo;s rural guidelines because I want to see a movement away from large urban areas.  I seek a village concept that will engender quality of life and community spirit, where residents discuss issues and look after one another.  I am not referring to Southfork style developments; I am referring to simple sites with nice houses that fit into the environment and that allow people to return to live in the place they were raised.</P>
        <P>On one of my first campaigns for election to the Seanad I travelled to various parts of Ireland and never saw anything like the dereliction.  There was no soul and no life.  As I travel now I can see the development of a new type of life and I welcome the Minister&rsquo;s approach to it.  People are of greater significance than beautiful schemes.  A lovely environment is important, but not without people.  I do not wish to look out on a soulless place on a dark winter night.  I want life around me.</P>
        <P>Why is An Bord Plean&aacute;la getting such bad press?  A unified system is being sought rather than one based on regionalisation, but I think regionalisation is a good idea.  It could lead to a streamlined system and help deal with the existing backlog.  There are inconsistencies evident in the decisions of An Bord Plean&aacute;la which sometimes make sense and on other occasions are bewildering.  I am not confident in dealing with An Bord Plean&aacute;la and there is a perception that all is not right.</P>
        <P>Regarding consistency in local authorities, planners have their own agenda that can be difficult to break down. Very often the director of planning cannot tell his planners that the policy is to be implemented in a certain way.  They can get away with doing what they want because that is what they learned when they were studying.  I have experienced that and it is worrying.</P>
        <P>Senator Henry spoke about her worries about septic tanks.  I installed a septic tank in a house a year ago and I was put through the ringer by the local authority in terms of adhering to the specifications and post-installation monitoring.  I welcomed that and I can reassure the Senator that local authorities are equipped to deal with one-off housing.  We might lack services under the rural guidelines but once they are in place we will have a good concept of rural planning, with people living in the country away from urban sprawl.</P>
    </Speaker><!--Fix-->
      <Speaker pid="Ms O'Rourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  His willingness to come to this Chamber is remarkable and we appreciate it.  I also thank the Progressive Democrats for this motion which <Col N="2040"/>gives us a chance to look at the whole planning issue.</P>
        <P Just="Left">County Westmeath has the dubious honour of having the highest refusal rate for planning applications in the past year.  That fact was paraded as if it is wonderful.  Imagine being delighted to refuse so many people.  It did not happen under the current manager but I thought it made Westmeath an awful county in which to live.</P>
        <P>Whatever the county managers tell the Minister when they meet him, planning applications are still being refused.  Those refusals are based on the sustainable rural housing guidelines as laid down by the Minister.  Everyone who is refused is told that.  Planners sometimes do not even see any point in holding a pre-planning meeting, although that is part of their work, as they are under-resourced because the Minister does not supply the necessary funds.  These are the stories trotted out to us to embarrass us and ensure we will not take on people&rsquo;s cases.</P>
        <P>The sustainable rural housing guidelines should be a framework but it appears that is not the case.  Every sentence has been parsed and every refusal is couched in the awareness that the Minister who is refusing the planning application is in the background.  The Minister might not believe that but it is the truth.</P>
        <P>The Minister stated that the guidelines provide for those persons whose work is intrinsically linked to rural areas, such as teachers in rural schools.  I had a teacher refused a planning application yesterday because she was not linked to farming.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>Send her to me and I will address the matter for her.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>She does not want to hear from Senator Bannon, she knows enough about him.  She was told that she does not fit the Minister&rsquo;s guidelines but the Minister states that she does.  I will go back to the planner tomorrow with the Minister&rsquo;s speech.  She teaches in three schools within the community where she wishes to build her house.  Teaching should be a strong point in the sustainable rural housing guidelines.</P>
        <P>I wish these guidelines had never been published because they are being used as a stick to beat those to whom they do not wish to give planning permission.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>I draw the planner&rsquo;s attention to page 24 of the guidelines.  I will give the Senator a copy of them.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should have checked the guidelines before making representations.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Our county manager sent a letter to the committee saying that everything in County Westmeath as regards planning is fine but the opposite is the case.  I do not want to see rampant development, awful looking houses with ver<Col N="2041"/>andahs everywhere, but people submit a minimal plan and the planner says it is too large and bedrooms and bathrooms must be removed.  The planner would not take a bathroom from his own house.</P>
        <P>I notice now that the guidelines state that circumstances could also encompass persons whose work is intrinsically linked to rural areas, such as teachers in rural schools.  Is that not amazing?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>Did the Senator not check that before making the representation?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The woman must now make another representation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I will accompany her.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>This person does not want Senator Bannon to speak for her, she asked me to do that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I would have made sure to read the guidelines.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The definition of the word &ldquo;local&rdquo; is also strange.  There is an Army barracks in Athlone; a barracks cannot be five miles outside the town in a rural area.  An applicant whom I know is serving his country in the Defence Forces, with his father and mother living in rural Westmeath.  He wishes to build on a site his father gave him but he has been told he is not involved in farming.  He cannot be involved in farming, he is in the Army and the barracks is in Athlone, where we are all going tomorrow to wave goodbye to our fine forces going to the Lebanon.  The Minister&rsquo;s name is being taken in vain when people talk about the sustainable rural guidelines.</P>
        <P>I do not like the idea that we are all herded into settlements.  We had that with the Danes and the Vikings and I am not keen on what they left behind.  Also, there are no sites.  Those who live in a settlement and have a site increase the price and no one can buy it.</P>
        <P Just="Left">There is much work to be done but I do not know how to go about it.  We had great hopes that our new manager would change things.  He has shown a more open attitude to planning but he is the manager and the planners are the planners.  I have a vision of planners getting up in the morning, asking how many times they would say &ldquo;No&rdquo; that day.  Some are better at it than others.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  Some of the companies using treatment systems for houses tell us that they are fully operational and can treat effluent to the same level as community treatment units.  Some local authorities, however, will not grant planning permission for a house with a treatment unit.  That is unfair.  Will the Minister elaborate on what treatment units can be used?  Do departmental guidelines require that treatment units have a certain output?  </P><Col N="2042"/>
        <P>The cases highlighted by Senator O&rsquo;Rourke are common throughout the country and planners implement the guidelines in the manner she described.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>They are shouting that it is the Minister&rsquo;s fault.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>That is correct.  What is meant by the phrase &ldquo;attachment to a rural area&rdquo;?  Does it mean attachment to a parish, village or county?  May a person apply for planning permission in any part of his or her county or must he or she be from the village or parish in question?  Some parishes have half parishes which cover large geographical areas.  Can a person from a half parish apply for planning permission anywhere in the parish?  Clarification is required on these matters. </P>
        <P>As Senator O&rsquo;Rourke noted, planning officials have refused planning permission because the applicant&rsquo;s attachment to the area is not deemed sufficiently strong.  The Minister referred to those who farm or teach in a rural area but did not specify whether such a person may apply for planning permission only within his or her parish, village, local authority area or county.  He must be specific.</P>
        <P>The local contributions required towards small sewerage schemes are excessive.  Some areas, for example Achill Island, have few industries, shops, pubs or other commercial premises.  This means the commercial rate base is not sufficient to enable a county manager to raise the local contribution required for a small sewerage scheme.  The Department must reconsider its insistence that local communities must raise 40% of the costs of a sewerage scheme.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Ms White</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister and compliment him on grasping his portfolio by the scruff of the neck, as it were.  He is determined to have in place a more transparent and accountable planning system by the time he leaves office.  I encourage him to continue on the path he has chosen.</P>
        <P>As a member of the Irish Rural Dwellers Association, I intend to highlight a number of specific issues.  The motion calls on the Minister to consider establishing a national planning monitoring committee.  When such a body was proposed by the Irish Rural Dwellers Association and the Royal Institute of Architects of Ireland in December 2004, the Minister rejected the idea.  Will he reconsider his decision?</P>
        <P>The motion refers to the need for a national water and sewerage services authority.  The recent Progressive Democrats policy document, Planning for a Rural Future, makes no mention of this proposal.  The idea merits further discussion as issues pertaining to the provision of clean water remain to be resolved.  As the Irish Rural Dwellers Association has noted, &euro;7 billion of taxpayers&rsquo; money is being spent upgrading urban water systems, while rural dwellers, who make up <Col N="2043"/>one third of the population, are left to meet the full cost of the installation and upkeep of single house treatment systems.  Surely one third of taxpayers deserve one third of funding for this type of essential works.</P>
        <P>I support the call for an examination of the use of the word &ldquo;local&rdquo; in rural planning guidelines.  We must carefully consider what we are saying when we try to restrict the sale of property to people native to an area because any such restrictions could be considered to be in breach of human rights legislation on the basis that they discriminate against minority groups.</P>
        <P>The motion raises the issue of housing need and how it is interpreted in housing guidelines.  Individual planners should not have the right to determine housing need.  This is a specific and complex issue and equity, transparency and consistency are required in interpreting it.  While I sympathise with individuals who are unable to secure planning permission in rural areas because they are not considered to be farmers, this approach reflects the position of An Taisce and has never been Government policy.</P>
        <P>An Bord Plean&aacute;la&rsquo;s appeals system needs to be reformed.  I welcome the concept of an independent appeals board within the organisation to cover the three European Union constituencies outside Dublin as potentially the first step towards a fair and open appeals process.</P>
        <P>The Minister is sincere in his efforts and has demonstrated energy, drive and determination.  He is aware of the position on the ground from <Col N="2044"/>his experience as an elected representative and I wish him continued success.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Mr. Brennan</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank all those Senators who contributed to the debate and the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, Deputy Roche, for his address.  It was, as always, detailed.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">7 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>The core challenge facing the Government parties is to ensure local policies are delivered well and consistently.  I am pleased to note the Minister&rsquo;s commitment to do all in his power to deliver the water services programme on time and within budget.  As with planning issues, this will require the support of members of local authorities.  Senator Bannon should note that his party controls half the local councils.  I hope the Progressive Democrats policy document, as summarised in the motion, is in tune with the views of some of the Senator&rsquo;s party colleagues who have in recent months raised the issues alluded to in the motion at local council meetings.  I ask Senators to support the motion.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of information, the Government parties are in disagreement. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>As there is no facility to raise a point of information during Private Members&rsquo; business, I ask the Senator to resume his seat.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister rejected several parts of the motion tabled by the Progressive Democrats.  </P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment put.</P><Col N="2043"/>
      
      <Vote>
        <Result>The Seanad divided: T&aacute;, 12; N&iacute;l, 27.</Result>
        <YHeading>T&aacute;</YHeading><Col N="2043"/>
        <YesVote pid="">Bannon, James.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="">Browne, Fergal.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="">Burke, Paddy.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="">Coghlan, Paul.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="">Feighan, Frank.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="">Finucane, Michael.</YesVote><Col N="2044"/>
        <YesVote pid="">Henry, Mary.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="">McHugh, Joe.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="">Norris, David.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="">Phelan, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="">Ross, Shane.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="">Tuffy, Joanna.</YesVote>
<Miles com="level"/><Col N="2043"/>
        <NHeading><Col N="2043"/>N&iacute;l</NHeading><Col N="2043"/>
        <NoVote pid="">Brady, Cyprian.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Brennan, Michael.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Callanan, Peter.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Cox, Margaret.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Daly, Brendan.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Dardis, John.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Dooley, Timmy.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Feeney, Geraldine.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Glynn, Camillus.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Hanafin, John.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Kenneally, Brendan.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Kett, Tony.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Kitt, Michael P.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Leyden, Terry.</NoVote><Col N="2044"/>
        <NoVote pid="">Lydon, Donal J.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">MacSharry, Marc.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Mansergh, Martin.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Minihan, John.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Moylan, Pat.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">&Oacute; Murch&uacute;, Labhr&aacute;s.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">O&rsquo;Brien, Francis.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">O&rsquo;Rourke, Mary.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Ormonde, Ann.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Phelan, Kieran.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Scanlon, Eamon.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">White, Mary M.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Wilson, Diarmuid.</NoVote>
        <Tellers><Col N="2043"/>Tellers: T&aacute;, Senators Bannon and J. Phelan; N&iacute;l, Senators Minihan and Moylan.</Tellers><Col N="2045"/>
        <?oasys _cl11.7- ?><Decision><?oasys _is0p10- ?>Amendment declared lost.</Decision>
      </Vote>
        <P>Motion put and declared carried.</P>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>It is proposed to sit again at 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</P>
 <HtmlBk SectId="6" />
    </Speaker><!--Fix-->
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment" RHead="Matters"> 
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. </Title>
  </MainHeading><Line />
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Decentralisation" RHead="Programme"> 
    <Title>Decentralisation Programme. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Parlon, for coming to the House to speak about decentralisation.  I congratulate him on the progress he is making and the songs of doom that one hears are not true.  Considerable progress is being made.  Difficulties occur sometimes but these are not the makings of the Office of Public Works.  I am looking for precise details about decentralisation plans for Athlone and Longford and I know that the Minister of State will give them to me.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TomParlonPD"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. Parlon</NameTxt>
	<P>Arising from the Government&rsquo;s decentralisation programme, the Office of Public Works has the task of sourcing suitable property solutions throughout the country to meet the requirements of decentralising Departments and agencies.  The OPW has made good progress in this respect.  To date it has completed, or significantly advanced, property acquisition negotiations in 35 of more than 50 locations targeted under the programme.  Sites for the balance of the decentralisation locations are also being actively pursued.</P>
        <P>The decentralisation programme envisages that the headquarters of the Department of Education and Science would be relocated to Mullingar in County Westmeath.  The total number of posts to be decentralised to Mullingar is 299, and 234 applications have been received.  These numbers will provide a significant and welcome economic boost to the town.</P>
        <P>A number of property options were considered but these were ruled out for one reason or another.  The most recent preferred option of the Office of Public Works was to locate the new headquarters building adjacent to the proposed new town centre development in the Blackhall area of the town.  However, this development was recently rejected by An Bord Plean&aacute;la and, consequently, the option is no longer available.  The Office of Public Works subsequently identified an alternative site which has been accepted as suitable by the Department.  Negotiations on the terms and conditions have commenced with <Col N="2046"/>the owners.  Subject to satisfactory terms being agreed and a satisfactory outcome to technical assessments and so on, the Office of Public Works hopes to finalise the negotiations soon.</P>
        <P>In its latest report, the decentralisation implementation group has set out indicative timeframes for the completion of the construction of decentralised offices in selected locations, which include Mullingar.  The indicative timeframe for construction completion in Mullingar is early 2009.  Expressions of interest for this project, which is part of a public private partnership bundle that also includes buildings for the Department of Agriculture and Food in Portlaoise and the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment in Carlow, have been received from developers and contractors and are being evaluated by the OPW in conjunction with the National Development Finance Agency.  It is expected that this evaluation process will be completed soon when tenders are invited to procure the buildings on a basis of design, build, finance and maintain.</P>
        <P>The Office of Public Works is arranging for the provision of office accommodation for the Department of Education and Science at Lissywollen in Athlone, County Westmeath.  It is proposed to accommodate approximately 100 local staff housed on the same site in temporary accommodation as well as 108 staff decentralised from Dublin.  A total of 155 applications to decentralise have been received.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>That is very good.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TomParlonPD"><NameTxt>Mr. Parlon</NameTxt>
	<P>It is a very popular place.  A preferred tenderer has been selected and is in discussions with Westmeath County Council on matters relating to the planning permission which has been granted for the development.  In tandem with this, the design team of the preferred tenderer is preparing contract documentation consisting of working drawings, a bill of quantities and so on.  It is envisaged that these matters will shortly be finalised and that a contract for construction will be placed soon afterwards.  The Office of Public Works anticipates completion of the new building for the Department in the second quarter of 2008.</P>
        <P>It is also intended to decentralise the Higher Education Authority to Athlone.  The number of posts involved is 53 and 26 applications have been received.  The decentralisation implementation group has not yet identified a specific timeframe for this move.</P>
        <P>Senator Bannon will be very interested to hear about the plans for Longford.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>It is my motion.  Senator Bannon did not do anything.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="2047"/>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not take my eye off the ball and the Minister of State knows that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TomParlonPD"><NameTxt>Mr. Parlon</NameTxt>
	<P>The Irish Prison Service was among the organisations recommended for the first phase of moves by the decentralisation implementation group in its November 2004 report.  The total number of posts involved is 158 and 209 applications have been received.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>It is all very positive news.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TomParlonPD"><NameTxt>Mr. Parlon</NameTxt>
	<P>It gets better.  Construction of the new headquarters in Longford is well advanced and the Office of Public Works expects completion by May 2007.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Excellent.  That should suit Deputy Sexton very well.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TomParlonPD"><NameTxt>Mr. Parlon</NameTxt>
	<P>The staff will be ready to move in by&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>There will be no decentralisation to Mullingar until 2009.  The Government has let down Mullingar.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TomParlonPD"><NameTxt>Mr. Parlon</NameTxt>
	<P>It is important to remember that the timescales given are indicative, reflecting the fact that in procuring new buildings, unforeseen circumstances can arise that could impact on progress at different stages of the various projects, including planning, legal, technical, and contract negotiation issues.  However, the Office of Public Works will strive to ensure that all projects are delivered within the indicative timeframes set<?oasys _jy ?>out by the decentralisation implementation group.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Sexual" RHead="Offences"> 
    <Title>Sexual Offences. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="GeraldineFeeney"><NameTxt>Ms Feeney</NameTxt>
	<P>There have been three reported rapes and six sex attacks in Sligo since last July.  Two weeks ago, a young woman claimed she was raped in the toilets of a nightclub in the early hours of the morning.  She was out with a group of friends and having gone into the toilet, a man followed her in and subsequently into the cubicle where it is alleged he raped her.  She presented at Sligo Garda station in a highly distressed state and accompanied by a friend.  Two garda&iacute; had to drive the young woman to Dublin for an examination as no doctor was available in Sligo on the night to see the alleged victim.</P>
        <P>Sligo garda&iacute; have informed me they use the services of a female general practitioner who is very generous with her time.  However, on occasions, she can be on holiday or may not be working on a particular weekend.  There are times when she is not available.  Sligo garda&iacute; then have no option but to travel to Dublin to the Rotunda Hospital.  Sligo General Hospital has informed the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na it has no role to play and <Col N="2048"/>that it would be preferable if the victims were not brought to its accident and emergency department.  The Health Service Executive, HSE, has said it is a matter for the doctors of the town to deal with, yet Letterkenny General Hospital has a care unit which looks after alleged rape victims when they present, as has Mayo General Hospital in Castlebar.  This is an <i>ad hoc</i> arrangement as there are no real guidelines in place and it depends on the goodwill of the medical personnel who are available to the hospital, but things work well.</P>
        <P>The <i>Sligo Weekender</i> has reported recently that the Sligo Rape Crisis Centre has put in a strong plea for rape victims to be forensically examined by nurses where no doctors are available.  I spoke to An Bord Altranais, the regulatory body for nursing.  Under the Act, nurses are not covered to examine a patient forensically but the board is examining the possibility of expanding the role and practices of nursing. It is not aware of any forensic nursing course but it stated it would support the expansion of the nursing role and it would consider any proposal put forward.</P>
        <P>It is time Sligo had a dedicated sexual assault treatment unit of its own, perhaps attached to Sligo General Hospital.  This unit could cover Sligo, Leitrim, west Cavan, north Roscommon, south Donegal and east Mayo.  In the meantime there should at least be a more modern, updated medical room in Sligo Garda station where young women could be seen and treated without being forced to undergo that terrible 150-mile journey to Dublin under such circumstances, especially when they are very upset, very distressed and have undergone that type of attack.  Nobody should be subjected to this type of treatment in this day and age.  I thank Sligo garda&iacute; for delivering such a caring and sensitive service to young women who present having allegedly been raped.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrankFahey"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. Fahey</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senator Feeney for raising this matter on the Adjournment.  I assure the Senator that I share her concerns in this matter.  The trauma of having to undergo a medical examination following an allegation of rape should not be compounded by having to travel an excessive distance for that examination.</P>
        <P>Along with my colleague, the Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children, Deputy Se&aacute;n Power, I recently launched the national review of sexual assault treatment services.  The Department of Health and Children, the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform and their relevant agencies, in particular the Health Service Executive and the national steering committee on violence against women, have a particular interest in and responsi<Col N="2049"/>bility for improving facilities to meet the victims of this grossly abusive and harrowing crime.</P>
        <P>The review identified a need for sexual assault treatment units, known as SATUs.  By locating the site for carrying out tests in a unit separate from accident and emergency facilities or other usual first ports of call for treatment, the client is assured of privacy in an environment that is forensically suitable for the conducting of such examinations.  The client is attended to by staff who are specialists and are sensitive to the many issues that may arise in the aftermath of such a trauma.  The forensic clinical examination has unique features, with the medical practitioner required to perform a dual role in addressing the immediate needs and concerns of the victim and in acting as an agent of law enforcement in the collection of forensic evidence.</P>
        <P>There are five SATUs in Ireland in five HSE regions, namely, the eastern, south eastern, southern, north western and midland regions.  Many of the forensic clinical examiners are GPs in the local area.  The review found that there has been an over-reliance on the limited number of doctors volunteering to be on call, increasing the risk that they would withdraw from providing their services to a SATU.</P>
        <P>One viable solution to the problem of a steady supply of forensic clinical examiners, which has been identified in the review, would be the introduction of education and training for nurses to specialise in the area of forensic clinical examination.  They would provide services to victims who present to SATUs and would provide expert witness testimony where a case subsequently went to court.  Forensic nursing has already been introduced in a number of other jurisdictions. I am pleased to say that the Health Service Executive is already examining this recommendation with a view to establishing a pilot course for eligible nurses who would later be appointed as clinical nurse specialists in forensic clinical examination.</P>
        <P>The findings of the review show that the responses experienced by victims of rape or sexual assault in Ireland depend on where they live.  There is a particular difficulty in the west, with a combination of a lack of such facilities and the large distances to be covered, which led to the undesirable situation where the person referred to by the Senator had to be taken from Sligo to Dublin.  The review recommended that two new sexual assault treatment units be established, one in the HSE western region and another in the HSE midlands region, so that the travel time for victims of sexual crime in these regions would be significantly reduced.  I understand from the HSE that work has begun on establishing the recommended unit in Galway.</P>
        <P>A key recommendation of the review is that the provision of services in existing and proposed new SATUs should be standardised.  While all <Col N="2050"/>SATUs provide a consistently high standard of service to victims, some differences in approach were identified.  Significant progress has been made in this area.</P>
        <P>A multidisciplinary group from the school of nursing and midwifery in Letterkenny has devised a set of national guidelines on referral and forensic clinical examination in Ireland.  These guidelines clearly set out the procedures to be adhered to in each SATU.  The guidelines cover all aspects of the care, support and examination of treatment of victims from the moment the alleged crime is reported to the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  The practices at the Forensic State Laboratory are also set out.  I am pleased to note that the new guidelines have now been printed and distributed to the relevant practitioners.</P>
        <P>It is acknowledged that there is a need to develop a more comprehensive rape and sexual assault treatment service which is more easily accessible, provides appropriate privacy and is compassionate and empathetic to the victim while maintaining expertise and standards in service delivery.  The implementation of the recommendations in the review requires the commitment from my Department and the Department of Health and Children and their relevant agencies.</P>
        <P>I assure Senators that both Departments and their agencies are committed to implementation of the recommendations. From a health perspective the HSE, which was represented on the review committee, is responsible for the implementation of these recommendations.  The Department of Health and Children has been in regular contact with the HSE during and since the completion of the report and is keen to see an early and full implementation of the report&rsquo;s recommendations so that an equitable and holistic service can be provided to those who have been injured and traumatised by the perpetrators of a truly appalling crime.</P>
        <P>I reiterate that I share the Senator&rsquo;s unhappiness with the situation which she has outlined, and I assure her that the necessary steps are being taken by the HSE to establish a SATU in Galway which it is hoped will service the Sligo area in a more effective way than has been the case until now.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="GeraldineFeeney"><NameTxt>Ms Feeney</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister of State and welcome the review.  Given that Galway is a two-hour drive on a bad road from Sligo, it would be as well to travel to Dublin as the road is better.  Where in the north west is the SATU unit?  I welcome the pilot scheme to train nurses in forensic examination.  Perhaps Sligo could be the pilot site for such training.</P>
        <P>I thank the Minister of State for attending to take this Adjournment matter and for the information he has supplied.  There is a need to move <Col N="2051"/>urgently.  Perhaps the medical room at Sligo Garda station could be made more comfortable in order that women could be treated in their own town.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrankFahey"><NameTxt>Mr. Fahey</NameTxt>
	<P>The unit is located in Letterkenny General Hospital.  As I said in my reply we are anxious to train clinical nurse managers to take over the role.  The intention is that we will be in a position to appoint clinical nurse managers to various regional hospitals throughout the country and that will include Sligo.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="GeraldineFeeney"><NameTxt>Ms Feeney</NameTxt>
	<P>Letterkenny General Hospital has refused to take victims from Sligo.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Third Level" RHead="Fees"> 
    <Title>Third Level Fees. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House to take this important matter, namely, the need for the Minister for Education and Science to clarify the position regarding the inequity of charging fees of more than &euro;6,000 for a student repeating a college year, with the allied loss of third level grant provision, in circumstances where she is relying for funding on a widowed parent whose sole income is disability benefit and who cannot afford such an excessive outlay, and to outline how, under natural justice, such a punitive measure can be enforced.</P>
        <P>What can the Minister of State say to me about a system that gives free fees to students whose parents can hypothetically afford a private jet, a large yacht, two or three houses, here and abroad, and a holiday to the most exotic places on earth while a student who relies on a widowed mother, whose sole income is disability benefit of approximately &euro;170 per week, is expected to pay more than &euro;6,000 to register for a repeat first year in university as well as losing her maintenance grant?  The student&rsquo;s only fault was that she had made the wrong course choice last year but was dutiful enough to finish the year and pass her exams.  Had she known that her application to her work was to cost her and her mother so dearly, she would have taken the easy option and dropped out.  However, she did not do that.  She is a hard-working girl who has mistakenly learned to finish what she started.  The upshot is that she has not been able to register for her new course.  She is in no-man&rsquo;s land in regard to her future educational prospects.</P>
        <P>I realise that according to the Department of Education and Science guidelines, each student is entitled to only one year&rsquo;s free fees for each year of study.  If students wish to repeat a year, they must pay the fees in full.  Following on from the loss of free fees, the maintenance grant is also removed for the year in question.  This is where we must begin to question the system.  Such a black and white ruling leaves no grey areas and <Col N="2052"/>cases of extreme want are ignored.  The Minister should examine cases such as this.</P>
        <P>To return to the concept of natural justice, no student should be so harshly penalised for making an honest mistake.  If this student had failed her exams and was not serious, I could understand that it would be impossible to do anything to help her.  However, this student&rsquo;s only problem is financial and unbelievable pressure is being put on her and her widowed mother who is ill and unable to work.  Dickens would have been shocked at such Scrooge-like treatment of an honest and deserving case.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The student&rsquo;s mother was widowed at an early age, her husband having died suddenly left her with a young family.  To be caught in an unbending system must be the ultimate nightmare for any parent.  I plead with the Minister on behalf of this young student and her mother, and other students in similar positions, to put in place a facility to accommodate them in their third level education.  This happened through no fault of the student.  There are huge anomalies in the system given that fees are paid to students whose parents have yachts and three or four homes, here and abroad, while a widow cannot be accommodated in respect of fees for her daughter.  I plead with the Minister to intervene and ensure that cases such as this are dealt with in a compassionate and humane manner at a time of plenty and much wastage in other areas.</P>
        <P>We have seen what has happened with PPARS and electronic voting, where millions of euro of taxpayers&rsquo; money has been wasted, while the education of an innocent girl cannot be looked after by the State.  There is something wrong with a society that allows that to continue.  I plead with the Minister to deal urgently with this matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TomParlonPD"><NameTxt>Mr. Parlon</NameTxt>
	<P>I am taking this Adjournment matter on behalf of the Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Hanafin. </P>
        <P>Under that Department&rsquo;s free fees initiative, the Exchequer meets the tuition fees of eligible first-time undergraduate students attending approved full-time courses.  The criteria for eligibility for free tuition fees includes the provision that tuition fees will not be paid in respect of students undertaking repeat years or in respect of students repeating a year-level having changed, but not completed, their undergraduate course.  Discretionary exceptions are provided for in cases where students are required to repeat a year as a result of certified medical grounds.</P>
        <P>It is understood the student in this case pursued the first year of a degree in nursing in an institute of technology, subsequently deferred her second year course of study and has now commenced a science degree in a university.  The student concerned received free fees for the first year of her nursing degree.  In keeping with the terms of the <Col N="2053"/>free fees initiative, the student in question is not eligible for free fees for year one of her new course of study.  However, she will be eligible for free fees from year two onwards.</P>
        <P>As the Senator can appreciate, the terms of the free fees initiative must be adhered to for all students and it is not open to the Department of Education and Science to make exceptions in individual cases.  The Senator will be aware that universities are autonomous bodies and, as such, may determine the level of fees to be charged in any case where the free fees initiative does not apply.</P>
        <P>The Department funds three means-tested maintenance grant schemes for third level education students in respect of attendance on approved courses in approved third level institutions and one maintenance grant scheme in respect of students attending approved post-leaving certificate courses in approved PLC centres.  These are the higher education grants scheme, the vocational education committees&rsquo; scholarship scheme, the third level maintenance grants scheme for trainees and the maintenance grant scheme for students attending post-leaving certificate courses.</P>
        <P>The higher education grants scheme is administered by local authorities.  The other three schemes are administered by vocational education committees on behalf of the Department.  The process of assessing eligibility for third level or further education grants is a matter for the<?oasys _jy ?>relevant local authority or VEC in the first instance.</P>
        <P>The position is that, generally speaking, students who are entering approved courses for the first time are eligible for grants, that is, maintenance and tuition fees, where they satisfy the relevant conditions as to age, residence, means, nationality and previous academic attainment. A student is not generally eligible for grant assistance in respect of a second period of study at the same level, irrespective of whether a grant was paid previously.  Officials of the Department of Education and Science have determined that the student referred to by the Senator was awarded the non-adjacent rate of grant, including the special rate of grant, in respect of the first year of a nursing degree course pursued in the academic year 2004-05. The candidate will become eligible for consideration for grant assistance again upon progression, for the first time, to year two of an approved course, subject to the terms and conditions of the scheme.  The Senator will appreciate that it is not open to the Department to depart from the terms and conditions of maintenance grants schemes in individual cases.</P>
        <P>Apart from the maintenance grant schemes and the free fees initiative, financial support is also available to students in approved third level institutions through the student access fund.   The <Col N="2054"/>objective of the fund, which is ESF-aided, is to assist in a sensitive and compassionate manner students who might otherwise, due to their financial circumstances, be unable to continue their third level studies.  Information on the fund is available from access offices in third level institutions.</P>
        <P>Section 473A of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997 provides for tax relief on tuition fees at the standard rate in respect of approved courses at approved colleges of higher education, including certain approved undergraduate and postgraduate courses in EU and non-EU member states.  Further details and conditions of this tax relief are available from the student&rsquo;s local tax office.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">The Minister of State&rsquo;s reply sounds ridiculous.  It has been managed by an official in the Department.  The Minister of State refers to section 473A of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997 but it does not apply in this case.  This student is depending on her widowed mother who is in receipt of a mere &euro;170 disability benefit.  How can such a woman provide for and look after her child and another member of the family in those circumstances?  There is something wrong with a system that allows this to happen in this day and age.  I plead with the Minister of State to examine the matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should put a question.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>He stated that &ldquo;a student is not generally eligible for grant assistance in respect of a second period of study&rdquo;, but is there not some leeway or flexibility in the guidelines in this regard?  Is there any way people in such circumstances can be accommodated or must they opt out and go on the dole for a year?  Does the Minister agree there is something wrong with a system that allows this to occur?  If she had known about these details, the student could have taken the easy option and opted out.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I have allowed the Senator to put a question.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TomParlonPD"><NameTxt>Mr. Parlon</NameTxt>
	<P>I outlined the details comprehensively.  I am not sure how many students qualify for free education every year but it must be hundreds of thousands.  The free fees initiative is paid for every year and the student in question will qualify.  Clearly, whatever mistake she made in terms of changing her mind, she was fully funded for her first-year course in nursing.  She deferred her course for a year and then decided to take up science.  Strict criteria are laid down in such circumstances.  There is a massive fund for free education but it is a sensitive issue for the individual concerned.  In the third last paragraph, my reply stated that the candidate will become eli<Col N="2055"/>gible for consideration for grant assistance.  She can contact her college&rsquo;s access office concerning the student access fund, which assists students who, due to their financial circumstances, may be unable to continue their third level courses.  Obviously, that is a very private matter and something the student may wish to avail of herself.  The information is quite comprehensive, however.  She can contact the access office in her third level institution.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="2056"/>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>She has already done that and got nowhere.  This is the last resort.  </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should allow the Minister of State to reply.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TomParlonPD"><NameTxt>Mr. Parlon</NameTxt>
	<P>My reply, on behalf of the Minister for Education and Science, was quite comprehensive.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <adjournment>The Seanad adjourned at 7.45 p.m. until<?oasys _jy ?>10.30 a.m on Thursday, 2 November 2006.</adjournment><Col N="2055"/>
    <HtmlBk SectId="0" />
  </MainHeading><?oasys _te ?><!--Fix-->
</Debate><!--Fix-->
