<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Tue" Date="5" Month="Dec" Year="2006" Vol="185" No="11" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 5 Nollaig 2006" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 5 December 2006" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="953">
    <Col N="953"/><HtmlBk SectId="1" />
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title></Title>
        <P>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar<?oasys _jy ?>2.30 p.m.</P>
        <Line />
        <P Just="Center"><i>Paidir.</i><br /><i>Prayer.</i></P><Line />
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad"> 
    <Title>Business of Seanad.  </Title>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I have notice from Senator Wilson that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Education and Science to make a statement on the future of the Tanagh Outdoor Education Centre, Dartrey, Rockcorry, County Monaghan.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Coghlan of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Health and Children to address the long-promised delivery of the 14-bed extension to Kenmare Hospital, County Kerry, given that this extension was a priority for the Southern Health Board in 1999-2000 but has not since been prioritised.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Feighan of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Health and Children to give an update on the proposed community hospital in Ballinamore, County Leitrim, the estimated number of beds and when it is envisaged work will commence on the project.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Bannon of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Education and Science to provide an update on the application by Scoil Etchen, Kinnegad, County Westmeath, for a proposed building project which is urgently required to facilitate the demand for places at the school caused by the increased population levels in Kinnegad.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Kitt of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Transport to clarify if the policy of printing numbers of motor insurance companies on insurance discs is necessary or if the policy numbers could be <Col N="954"/>printed on the reverse of the insurance discs to prevent fraud.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Kieran Phelan of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Transport to preserve and upgrade the existing rail service at both Ballybrophy and Templemore stations due to increased passenger demands.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I regard the matters raised by Senators Wilson, Coghlan, Feighan, Bannon and Kitt as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected those raised by Senators Wilson, Coghlan and Feighan and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.   Senators Bannon and Kitt may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.  I regret I have had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Kieran Phelan as the Minister has no official responsibly in the matter.  It is a matter for Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business"> 
    <Title>Order of Business. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Order of Business is Nos. 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5.  No. 1, a procedural motion to allow the Joint Committee on Arts, Sport, Tourism, Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs more time to consider the motion on the Official Languages Act 2003 (Section 9) Regulations 2006.  This motion will allow the committee to report back by 14 December, rather than 5 December as previously agreed, and is to be taken without debate.  No. 2 is a motion to refer motion No. 19 on today&rsquo;s Order Paper to the Joint Committee on Agriculture and Food for consideration.  This motion, which will be taken without debate, concerns the rates of disease levies applied to milk deliveries for processing and cattle slaughtered or exported and are paid by the farming community towards the cost of the eradication of TB and brucellosis in cattle.  Under the terms of the recent partnership agreement, Towards 2016, it was agreed with the farming bodies, subject to receiving the requisite approvals, that a further reduction of 50% in the current levy rates was appropriate from 1 January 2007. No. 3 is a motion, to be taken without debate, which deals with the establishment today of the National Economic and Social Development Office, as provided for in legislation passed by the Oireachtas early this year &mdash; the draft Order states the establishment date will be 1 January 2007 and this is the preferred date and will facilitate accounting and administrative procedures.  No. 4 is the Prison Bill 2006: Report Stage, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business and to conclude no later than 5 p.m. No. 5 is the Electoral (Amendment) Bill 2006: Committee and remaining Stages, to be taken at 5 p.m. , and to conclude no later than 7 p.m. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">In recent years the Leader of the House has organised a number of well-focused debates on mental health.  The Minister of State <Col N="955"/>with responsibility for that area, Deputy Tim O&rsquo;Malley, has addressed this House on the subject on a number of occasions.  Following last night&rsquo;s shocking and disturbing &ldquo;Prime Time Investigates&rdquo; programme, which highlights the level of child and adolescent mental health problems within the country, I ask the Leader to persuade the Minister of State, Deputy Tim O&rsquo;Malley, to return to this House before Christmas, if possible, to deal with a number of those issues.  It is accepted across the political divide that mental health is the Cinderella of the Irish health service.  It is astonishing the type of problems we face now in terms of child and adolescent care.  Allegations were made last night by the programme that in excess of 3,000 children under 16 are waiting to be diagnosed, one in five is suffering from a serious psychological disorder and one in eight has a behavioural problem.  It was also claimed there have been no new <?oasys _dc28- ?>psychologists employed within the country in recent years.<?oasys _dc0- ?></P>
        <P>The worst possible fact to emerge from the programme was the outrageous allegation by the Minister of State, who claimed, &ldquo;Some people like to have long waiting lists as it makes them look powerful.&rdquo;  It is time for the Minister of State, Deputy Tim O&rsquo;Malley, to either put up or shut up.  Can he substantiate the allegation he made on that programme, which he continued to make on &ldquo;Morning Ireland&rdquo; today?  It is an allegation which slurs a whole group of professionals who are doing their best to stem the tide in this area.  I ask the Leader, who has been very proactive as regards organising debates in this area, to once again invite the Minister of State to the House to ask him to substantiate that allegation and to stop blaming others for his deficiencies and those of his Government.  He made the claim this morning that he is in the office only four years.  If he cannot deal with it, it is time for him to head off.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, Hear. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Mr. O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>I fully support the call for a debate on this issue.  I was talking to a number of colleagues about it before lunch and I found the programme very troubling.  The Minister of State&rsquo;s comments were beyond belief, in that he is trying to shove the blame onto consultants.  I am as critical of consultants as any of us, but I do not believe anyone has until now subscribed to the view that they would deliberately keep people waiting in order to make themselves feel important.  The idea that consultants would make children of primary school age wait four or five years to make themselves feel important is an outrageous assertion by the Minister of State.  He should correct it, since I do not believe for one minute that it could be true.  If it is, then our sense of outrage will be even greater.  The Minister of State should come to this House and talk to us.  We have had this debate before.  </P><Col N="956"/>
        <P>For the past five years Members have raised the shortage of therapists of every kind in this House and in committees.  I refer to occupational therapists, speech therapists and physiotherapists.  These shortages pertain to a lack of college places and the non-recognition of therapists who gained their qualifications in the United Kingdom and elsewhere, neither of which helps us to make progress.</P>
        <P>In respect of the issue raised by Senator Brian Hayes regarding psychologists, in the past four or five years the Department has been interviewing people for the post of educational psychologist.  I understand it has a ready-made waiting list of up to 50 fully qualified psychologists who are willing to take up duty and whom it could appoint at any time.  This is quite appalling.  As the Exchequer received &euro;10 billion last month, surely no one who watched the suffering of those children would argue about such spending.</P>
        <P>The children in question, along with their parents, are still in the same position.  Perhaps they are struggling at school or may be queuing outside some consultant&rsquo;s waiting room.  It is appalling that this should be allowed to continue.  The Leader&rsquo;s arrangement of such a debate to take place before Christmas would show a great response to a topical matter and all Members would welcome it.  Everyone has views on this issue and Members could give some comfort and solace to those parents and others who appeared on last night&rsquo;s programme, to the unseen thousands and to teachers and school boards trying to cope with this issue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenOMeara"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Meara</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader is aware I have asked several times for a debate on youth mental health issues.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>That is correct.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenOMeara"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Meara</NameTxt>
	<P>On one level, I was pleased that &ldquo;Prime Time Investigates&rdquo; chose to take up the issue of youth mental health and to expose clearly and powerfully the extraordinary deficiencies in the system as well as their impact on many children.  It also displayed the Government&rsquo;s ineffectiveness and specifically that of the Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children, Deputy Tim O&rsquo;Malley, who has been charged with responsibility for this area.  While fine reports have been produced under his watch, virtually nothing has happened subsequently and last night&rsquo;s programme showed the consequences.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State should resign because of his ineffectiveness and because of his ham-fisted attempt to cover it up with the extraordinary charge that professionals who work in the system are deliberately creating waiting lists.  This is unbelievable.  I have spoken to professionals in this field, both in my own locality and beyond, who having worked so hard are burned out.  Such professionals are frustrated by the shortages in the system.  They are obliged to see children and <Col N="957"/>families every day to tell them how long they must wait and subsequently witness the consequences for those children and their families.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State should resign because his reaction to this matter.  His response to this serious issue, about which he is familiar, has been nothing short of scandalous.  This House must have a debate on this matter as soon as possible.  It cannot wait because it is urgent for too many people and I ask the Leader to arrange such a debate as soon as possible.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenOMeara"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Meara</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to raise a second important matter.  Many hundreds of people travelled from County Monaghan today to attend a demonstration at the Kildare Street entrance to Leinster House.  All political representatives from Monaghan, such as county councillors, town councillors and all the Oireachtas Members, including members of the Government parties with the obvious exception of the Ceann Comhairle, were present to support the people of Monaghan in their fight to retain acute hospital services in their county.</P>
        <P>I support them as a member of the Nenagh Hospital action group.  Others, such as representatives from Ennis, were also present because they know Government policy is to downgrade services in acute hospitals throughout the State.  The Minister for Health and Children must come to the House to defend her spurious allegation that hospitals such as Monaghan are unsafe for patients.  In fact, the reduction of services in such hospitals has made the health service unsafe for hundreds of people.  Seventeen people have died in Monaghan as a direct result of the removal of services there.  This is an urgent issue, especially as the Government is attempting to move the issue forward beyond the next general election.  The Minister should come to the House and should be straight with Members.  There should be a straight debate about this matter and people should be heard.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Mr. Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Leader to request the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform to come into the House as soon as possible to give a report on the tragic murder of Garda Dick Fallon in 1970.  He was the first<?oasys _jy ?>garda killed in over 30 years.  He hailed from <?oasys _dc28- ?>Mooneen outside Ballagh in County Roscommon,<?oasys _dc0- ?> which is outside Roscommon town.  During my years in public life it was not brought to my attention until Finian, his son, wrote to <i>The Irish Times</i> and it was raised on &ldquo;Morning Ireland&rdquo; the other day.</P>
        <P>I am not at this point calling for a public inquiry until I find out from the Minister exactly what is involved in this case &mdash; why seven men were named, three men were acquitted for the murder and nobody was convicted for the brutal murder by Saor &Eacute;ire of Garda Fallon, who was 40 <Col N="958"/>years old.  This is serious enough that the Minister should come into the House to explain exactly what has happened, what is on the files, whether they have been suppressed, are in the Department, why the three men were acquitted at the time and why the other members of Saor &Eacute;ire were not brought before the courts.  He was the first garda in 30 years to be murdered defending the State.  As a Roscommon man, this case has been badly handled by the State and it is about time there was an account given to this House on the circumstances surrounding the tragedy.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>It was great to see the unity of views on Monaghan General Hospital, as witnessed outside the gates this morning.  Some powerful contributions were made on an all-party basis.  I totally empathise with them and I hope that the much smaller request to the Minister for Health and Children in regard to the situation in Kenmare will be met because that is going on for almost as long.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Regarding what?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>The 14-bed extension at Kenmare Hospital.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Kenmare Hospital matter is on the Adjournment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I appreciate that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Coghlan must wait until then.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I coupled it, just for a mention, with Monaghan General Hospital.  I will not go into detail until later.  I appreciate the Cathaoirleach&rsquo;s concern.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Has Senator Coghlan another point?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I do.  It is a considerable while since I mentioned the Great Southern Hotels.  Members in this and the other House campaigned long and hard for all those grant-assisted paintings, many of which were beautifully on show in those establishments.  I am happy to report that with Senator Brennan, I had something of a sneak preview last week before the Minister opened the wonderful exhibition in the atrium of the Office of Public Works headquarters at 51 St. Stephen&rsquo;s Green.  There are many wonderful artists involved and it is a beautiful exhibition.  There must be over 100 paintings and at least 50 of them are on show there.  I would encourage the Cathaoirleach and, indeed, all of the Members to visit it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Has Senator Coghlan a question on the Order of Business?  Have you a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="959"/>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Is Senator Coghlan inviting me to it?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I am sure the Minister would invite the Leader.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>We unveiled all the CIE pictures in Athlone last night.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader should use her good offices to ensure it is a successful campaign, that people go and appreciate them.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde"><NameTxt>Ms Ormonde</NameTxt>
	<P>I, too, call for a debate on youth mental health.  I did not see the television programme last night but I received many telephone calls today from professionals who deal with many of the issues regarding childhood and adolescence, especially in the area of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, ADHD.  Particularly in their transition from primary school to second level school where they are assessed, there is a lack of educational psychologists to deal with the problem.  If there are psychologists being trained, I cannot understand why they are not being placed in the system.</P>
        <P>This worries me because these children are a huge problem at the school.  It also shows there is a total lack of co-ordination between the Department of Health and Children and the Department of Education and Science.  The two Departments must be involved in how one deals with those children in the classroom.  It is an impossible situation.  There is a significant lack of authority and a debate on the issue would bring clarity on where we go from here.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I  join with my colleagues in requesting the Minister to come into the House so that there should be a full debate on the issue raised by Senator Ormonde and previous speakers.  I commend the Senators on both sides of the House for making this request in a measured and balanced way.  We must remember that people can easily put a foot wrong.  The Minister of State made what seems to be a most extraordinary series of charges and we are entitled to investigate what lies behind them.</P>
        <P>If, as it appears, one fifth of children are suffering from some kind of psychiatric difficulty, it raises an important question about the nature of our society.  Was this always the case or has something changed in that such a significant proportion of children are deemed to be mentally unwell?  I would like to know if this is a fact.  If so, what kind of illness is involved and what is its source?  Does it reflect changes in society?  Is it related to the fact that in so many cases both parents have to go out to work?  I simply do not know.  I am not blaming parents because this is part of the economic reality with which we live.  I am sure that cannot be the reason for all such <Col N="960"/>cases but we need to examine what is wrong with society.  There certainly seems to be some kind of malaise in it.</P>
        <P>Members on both sides of the House have already raised these questions.  I have posed questions about autistic children, whose brave and gallant parents care for them, as well as the virtual absence of speech therapists.  It takes some time to train such therapists.  There is also the question of psychologists and, as Senator O&rsquo;Toole said, there are 50 to 100 of them waiting for appointments.  On the radio today, it was said that a 1% drop in the top rate of tax was a possibility in tomorrow&rsquo;s budget and that it would cost &euro;280 million.  That sum would be much better spent by immediately employing trained psychologists.</P>
        <P>I also wish to raise a matter which I have consistently raised here.  It concerns the rendition flights through Shannon Airport.  It is disgraceful that Independent Newspapers once again did not find itself able to tell the truth about this.  A headline in the <i>Irish Independent</i>, concerning the report of the European Parliament&rsquo;s committee on this matter, stated &ldquo;US torture flights never landed at our airports&rdquo;.  That is a deliberate and specific lie, because they did land here.  We know they did.  We have the flight patterns, log data and names of many of the people involved.  It has been expertly stated that a number of CIA personnel went through this country on false Irish passports.  That certainly is a crime and demands an investigation.  I ask the Leader to take up this matter with the Minister for Foreign Affairs and obtain further information on it.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I compliment the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Dermot Ahern, on a wonderful concert by the cross-Border orchestra in Dublin Castle last week.  It was such a hopeful sign that people from both sides of the Border became involved in this event.  There were even some Lambeg drums and Uillinn pipes.  I have always loved those pipes but I did not know their origins.  It was informative to discover that they came here as a result of Presbyterian ministers &mdash; who could not afford organs for their churches &mdash; importing this adaptation of the Scottish bagpipes.  Uillinn pipes are a quintessential Irish instrument but, given their origins, they make a wonderful symbol of the potential for cultural unity that is now within our grasp.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMauriceHayes"><NameTxt>Dr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Leader ask the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform to attend the House to outline the arrangements to prevent paedophiles and other sex offenders from seeking asylum in this country?  I also ask the Leader to refer the Minister to new regulations which are being introduced in Northern Ireland in this regard.  It is important that such arrangements here should be compatible with those in the North, so that people cannot dodge from one system to the other.  The Minister might wish to examine the Visor programme which the PSNI has introduced for tracking such people.</P><Col N="961"/>
        <P>I also wish to support a debate on hospitals and look forward to participating in it.  It is unfair for Members, even in a pre-election period, to keep reassuring people that one can maintain safe and efficient acute hospital services in all centres in this country.</P>
           </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenOMeara"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Meara</NameTxt>
	<P>Let us have that debate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMauriceHayes"><NameTxt>Dr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>It is time we re-examined the Fitzgerald report published all those years ago.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenOMeara"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Meara</NameTxt>
	<P>That was wrong too.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMauriceHayes"><NameTxt>Dr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>It would also be useful to hold a debate on mental health services.  I support the proposal by Senator O&rsquo;Meara and Senator Ormonde that any such debate should focus on the critical and crucial issue of youth services.  Otherwise, it would be all be over the place.  I have one comment to make to comfort the Minister of State.  I believe he was reflecting the fact that waiting lists are about the most fallible issue from which to draw conclusions.  Waiting times, which are intolerable, are important.  It is important to make interventions to assist young people in crisis.  Lord knows how much damage such interventions would avoid.  Sadly, the position in the North does not appear to be much better.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Leader hold a debate on the excessive costs of tribunals?  We have learned that the tribunals in hand have cost taxpayers between &euro;700 million and &euro;800 million.  At a time of great difficulty in securing funding for community care and mental health services, money can be found willy nilly for the tribunals.  The House should examine the costs of tribunals and debate how they can be curtailed.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">3 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>We have also learned that invoices are still being received for the beef tribunal which wound up 12 years ago.  Some barristers and solicitors have had an open door in terms of drawing down funding for tribunals.  It should be a requirement that invoices be submitted within a specified timeframe from the completion of a tribunal&rsquo;s work.  Invoices submitted by Oireachtas and local authority members are not paid if they are not submitted within a certain period and the same should apply to tribunals.  Regular reports should be published documenting the activities of tribunals because they can sit for half an hour, wrap up proceedings and not sit again for three weeks, during which time barristers and solicitors continue to be paid.  This is a shameful practice at a time when the health service is on its knees.</P>
        <P>Will the Government provide relief and funding for counties hit by flooding caused by the weekend storms?  Roads have been destroyed in some areas and local authorities will require funding to upgrade them, especially in low-lying <Col N="962"/>areas.  Several towns and villages were flooded in the west at great cost.  The insurance cover of some residents in the areas affected may not be adequate.  The Government must provide support and compensation for those affected by an act of God over the weekend.  The House should debate the issue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TimDooley"><NameTxt>Mr. Dooley</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Leader arrange a debate with the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government at the earliest possible date to discuss his Department&rsquo;s role in ensuring water quality in our municipal and county water systems?  An appalling situation is evolving in Ennis owing to the failure of a temporary treatment system, which was installed recently with departmental support at a cost of &euro;2 million.  Unfortunately, the system has not resolved the problem as boiling notices are being issued again.  This creates discomfort for parents of young children who must incur significant costs to buy water.  Many people are not confident that boiling water will make it safe.</P>
        <P>The Department needs to address the crisis in Ennis in the wider context of its role in ensuring water quality.  The problem has occurred at a time when the possibility of charging for water is being considered.  Charges should not be imposed until such time as strict policies are in place to ensure that when circumstances such as those I have outlined arise, the authorities have the capacity to intervene and resolve the problem quickly.</P>
    <HtmlBk SectId="2" />
    </Speaker><!--Fix-->
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I support the calls for a debate on health but this is such a wide area I question whether it is wise to cover it in one effort.  </P>
        <P>I draw the attention of Members to Dr.<?oasys _jy ?>Riste&aacute;rd Mulcahy&rsquo;s article on health published on Sunday and his book which was published yesterday.  He talks about the prevention of illness rather than just spending money on its cure.  When discussing the regional hospitals and the challenges facing them, it should be noted that significantly more can be achieved by the prevention of illness and by promoting health living, whether that be a fight against obesity or more exercise or a concentration on education in schools.  It is a case of keeping ourselves healthy rather than just curing ourselves whenever we fall ill.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>I, too, join with those who call for a debate on mental health.  Last night&rsquo;s programme highlighted not only the worrying scope and extent of the problem but also the waiting lists which seem to be so difficult to access.  Whatever the truth of that, it should be thrashed out in the House.  Senator Norris made the point succinctly that at a time of tremendous affluence there appears to be much more mental health problems than in times of abject poverty in the past.  The societal reasons should be identified and the problem needs to be tackled as a matter of urgency.</P><Col N="963"/>
        <P>It is not a case of lack of funding because it was announced yesterday that more than &euro;10 billion in revenue was received by the State in November.  It is more a case of the output of the public service at all levels.  There should be a separate debate on the vested interests within the health services and in other areas and on the ongoing negotiations with the hospital consultants.  The time has come for the State and its apparatus to take control of our public services and to ensure those who work in it give value for money.  If we do not succeed in doing this, we are doing a disservice to the taxpayer who is paying heavily for services which are not commensurate with the amount of tax being paid.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnPaulPhelan"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Phelan</NameTxt>
	<P>I join with other Senators who have requested that the Minister of State, Deputy Tim O&rsquo;Malley, comes to the House to discuss the issue of youth psychological services.  I agree with Senator Maurice Hayes on the point he made about waiting times and waiting lists.  County Kilkenny was highlighted as being the worst in terms of waiting times, with a waiting time of more than four and a half years.  The Minister of State made his astonishing comments that consultants were somehow beefing up waiting lists to make themselves more powerful.  It is my understanding that the reason for the four and a half years&rsquo; waiting time in Kilkenny is that the position of consultant psychologist was vacant for more than a year.  This was clearly a failure on the part of the HSE and by the Minister of State&rsquo;s Department.  I ask that the House has a debate on this subject as soon as possible.</P>
        <P>I wish to join other Senators in asking for a debate on the status of the Hanly report and local hospitals, a number of which have been referred to by other speakers.  I wish to mention my own local hospital, St. Luke&rsquo;s Hospital in Kilkenny&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>There is one for everyone in the audience.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnPaulPhelan"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Phelan</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not subscribe to the notion that in this day and age we cannot have major clinical services available in regional centres.  If it could be done 50 or 60 years ago when, as Senator Jim Walsh pointed out, the country was in a much more stringent economic position, I do not understand why it cannot be done now.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenOMeara"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Meara</NameTxt>
	<P>We are doing it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnPaulPhelan"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Phelan</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Leader to raise with the Minister for Education and Science the concerns expressed to me by a number of parents of Down&rsquo;s syndrome children.  Until two or three years ago, Down&rsquo;s syndrome children who attended regular primary schools were automatically entitled to resource hours.  Three or four years ago, a change was made by the Government <Col N="964"/>and now resource hours for Down&rsquo;s syndrome children attending national schools come from the total resource hours of the school.  Only 220 or 230 Down&rsquo;s syndrome children are affected by this change.  As a result, the  number of resource hours to which they were entitled have been cut dramatically.  Half an hour per day of resource teaching for a Down&rsquo;s syndrome child would have a dramatic effect on ensuring that he or she could remain independent into adulthood.  As it is the day before the budget, I ask the Leader to raise that concern so that perhaps something could be done when the budget is announced.  </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="GeraldineFeeney"><NameTxt>Ms Feeney</NameTxt>
	<P>I support the calls for an urgent debate on paediatric and adolescent psychiatric services.  The &ldquo;Prime Time Investigates&rdquo; programme should be congratulated.  Like myself, I am sure those who watched last night&rsquo;s programme have all been greatly affected by it.  I was lost in total admiration and emotion for the young people who were brave enough to go on the programme to tell their stories.  I was gripped by the young parents of the little nine year old boy who felt he was hanging over a cliff and that they were holding him by his hand but that he was slipping away all the time.  Nobody could be anything but moved by hearing the words of the father.</P>
        <P>Out of respect to all people suffering with mental illness, we should try to have a debate before Christmas and concentrate on adolescent and paediatric psychiatric services and perhaps even include anorexia.  We have three protected beds in this country for young people suffering from anorexia.  Over the next five to ten years, bulimia, obesity and anorexia will become bigger than anything any of us could imagine.</P>
        <P>As a member of the Joint Committee on Child Protection, I wish we had seen the &ldquo;Prime Time Investigates&rdquo; programme before we signed off on our report.  I hope that in the upcoming referendum on the protection of the child, we will widen our remit and look after children suffering with mental illness.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>At a time when the Government is awash with money, I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on the underfunding of local authorities, particularly in the areas of water pricing and waste water management.  Water pricing is leading to the privatisation of water throughout the country.  Farmers and business people will not be able to pay for water.  Something will have to be done because local authorities are using water to raise taxes by stealth.  Local authorities are so underfunded that they have no choice but to increase water charges and this will cost businesses and farmers.  At a time when the Government has taken in &euro;10 billion, will the Leader arrange a debate as a matter of urgency?  We are now trying to extract the last few euro from hard-pressed farmers and business people throughout the country.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="965"/>
      <?oasys _cl11.5- ?><Speaker pid="DonLydon"><NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I, too, support the call for the debate on the health service.  As Senator Quinn mentioned, we should narrow it to perhaps child or adolescent psychiatry.  Psychiatry has always been seen as the Cinderella of the health service and adolescent psychiatry as the Cinderella of the psychiatric service.  As long as 30 years ago, I called for investment in this area and successive Governments, including those comprising my party, have not invested in it.  There has been a dearth of investment in adolescent psychiatry and the problems in it can be solved.  One of the reasons it has been avoided is that it is so expensive and intensive.  There are psychologists, educational psychologists, psychiatrists and other therapists with the expertise but there are not enough of them and we need more.  I am not worried about what happened in the past and I look to what we can do in the future.  We can provide long overdue help for these young people.  I am sure the Government will examine this area.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrankFeighan"><NameTxt>Mr. Feighan</NameTxt>
	<P>I too was horrified by what I saw on the &ldquo;Prime Time Investigates&rdquo; expos&eacute; last night.  Perhaps we should ask the Minister for Health and Children to come to the House to explain where the regulators for our health system are.  For too long we have relied on &ldquo;Prime Time&rdquo; to expose such situations.  Some people working in the health boards are paid vast sums to produce reports and to regulate the system, but obviously they will not break up an old boys club.  We must ensure systems are put in place to put an end to this.</P>
        <P>Six people died horrible deaths from contaminated heroin in our capital city last weekend.  The situation is out of control.  I have often stated in the House that if we do not cut down on the availability of cannabis, cocaine or crack cocaine, we will have a dangerous crime epidemic.  We need real and frank debate on the ever-increasing dangers in society as a result of drugs.  Regional drugs task forces have been up and running for the past four years but are they doing the job they were set up to do or are they just talking shops?  Will the Leader invite the relevant Minister to the House to explain the situation?</P>
        <P>Last night, there were more than 1,000 farmers in the Royal Hotel in Roscommon.  They are very angry at what they perceive as another stealth tax.  The Government has claimed it is more than &euro;6 billion in the black, but it has clearly overcharged the people.  I ask it now to begin giving the money back.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney"><NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
	<P>I strongly support the view expressed by my colleague, Senator Feeney, who has articulated what is a widespread view.  I would hate people outside the House to think that we have only raised these issues in a knee-jerk reaction to last night&rsquo;s television programme.  Sometimes, especially at this time of year &mdash; we all <Col N="966"/>know that in terms of national issues, timing is everything, not just in politics &mdash; a programme like that shown last night should and does act as a catalyst to getting something done.  Senator Feeney&rsquo;s point was well made.  I urge the Leader to make time available before Christmas for a debate on mental health.</P>
        <P>The issue raised by Senator Phelan must also be addressed.  I have personal experience in this area because I have a daughter under the age of 18 with special needs.  We have found the support services in the north west to be superb, but I appreciate there may be inconsistencies as a result of the changes referred to by Senator Phelan.  I was opposed to those changes because I saw the possibility that there could be a reduction or withdrawal of resources for special needs assistance.  That has not been my experience, but that does not mean it does not happen.  Therefore, we should have a debate on the issue.</P>
        <P>I hope that the framing of a motion in that context will take account of people over 18 with special needs, a threshold we are close to with our daughter.  Increasingly parents have said to me that while support services are excellent for children up to 18, once these children become adults, the services are patchy, inconsistent, inadequate and under-resourced.  We need a debate that will encompass all those issues.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Brian Hayes, the Leader of the Opposition, raised the issue dealt with on the &ldquo;Prime Time Investigates&rdquo; programme last night.  I was home alone and saw the full programme.  I am not ashamed to say I cried over it because it brought back memories of a nephew of mine with autism who died many years ago.  People with autism, Asperger&rsquo;s syndrome, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder and similar conditions require intensive care from a range of professionals.  It is not only psychologists who are needed but a range of professionals, including psychiatrists, teachers and health professionals.  It was a moving programme.  I realise that Christmas, a moving time, is approaching but one could not watch the programme without being moved.  The programme was arranged by Mr. Paul Murphy with the involvement of Ms Keelin Shanley.</P>
        <P>Senator Brian Hayes and all other Senators who spoke on the issue expressed the position well.  We saw a mother and father &mdash; a plain, ordinary couple &mdash; who did not appear to have had any other children.  I suppose the experience of having Jordan and what happened had a telling effect on them.  I do not know how that mother kept her patience and sanity.  The father was very good and supportive.  I watched the entire programme because I felt it raised issues we should consider.</P>
        <P>Senators referred to the contribution of the Minister of State, Deputy Tim O&rsquo;Malley.  I <Col N="967"/>believe he meant to say he did not understand why waiting list times were one month in one area and five years in another area.  The disparity arises because some health areas would have a range of professionals while other areas would not.  I expect this is why the Minister of State got himself into the knot he did.</P>
        <P>Senators asked for a debate.  I agree we should have a debate but it should focus on youth.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>Youth and adolescent services.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde"><NameTxt>Ms Ormonde</NameTxt>
	<P>Youth mental health services.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The programme was about youth mental health.  A range of support services are needed in this regard.</P>
        <P>Many teachers are struggling to deal with those pupils suffering incipient or embryonic attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, ADHD, Asperger&rsquo;s syndrome or other disorders.  A great number of special needs assistants are now working in our classrooms but, notwithstanding this, there are always children just at the edge, although not quite certifiably suffering from ADHD, Asperger&rsquo;s or autism.  I know this from my own teaching days.  The strain such children put on the teacher and the whole class is huge.</P>
        <P>The child profiled on last night&rsquo;s programme, Jordan, is reported in today&rsquo;s <i>Irish Examiner</i> as having said: &ldquo;[It&rsquo;s] like someone is controlling me<?oasys _jy ?>. . . It&rsquo;s like a robot, someone else controlling me.&rdquo;  It is clear he is an extremely disturbed child.  I will endeavour to arrange the debate, which would be worthwhile.</P>
        <P>Senator O&rsquo;Toole called for the arrangement of a debate before Christmas on the issue of educational psychologists.  If that is possible, I will try to arrange it.</P>
        <P>Senator O&rsquo;Meara asked for a debate on youth mental health issues.  She has raised these issues in different guises.  The Senator said the Minister of State should go.  My view is that he should stay, attend to the issue and work it through.</P>
        <P>The Senator also referred to today&rsquo;s protest in support of Monaghan Hospital and asked that the Minister for Health and Children would come to the House.  The Minister has endeavoured to explain it is not possible to have the very best of acute services everywhere.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenOMeara"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Meara</NameTxt>
	<P>It is possible, but she refuses to provide them.  That is why she needs to come to the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>That is what she is saying.  As I travelled to Dublin this morning, I listened with interest to the BBC reporting that Tony Blair, who I accept we would not want to copy, delivered a major lecture today stating that cottage hospitals and smaller hospitals cannot provide every acute service.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="968"/>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenOMeara"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Meara</NameTxt>
	<P>That is not what is being asked.  I asked for the Minister to come to the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>We will ask the Minister to come to the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We cannot have a debate on the matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Leyden raised the issue of the mysterious circumstances surrounding the murder of Garda Richard Fallon over 30 years ago.  The Senator asked whether the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform could open the files and explain the outcome of any investigation of them, which would be worthwhile.</P>
        <P>Senator Coghlan commended the unity of those campaigning on behalf of Monaghan Hospital and then raised the matter of Kenmare Hospital.  He also referred to the paintings held by the Great Southern Hotels.  Last night, the paintings held by CIE were arranged in the Athlone Institute of Technology in a marvellous exhibition.  The two wonderful exhibitions are open to the public at present.  Senator Ormonde called for a debate on youth mental health issues.</P>
        <P>Senator Norris said that if the top rate of income tax is not reduced, the money that would have been spent would be better spent on psychologists, psychiatrists, teachers and professionals.  The Senator also castigated a certain branch of newspapers in this country for the headline it used in a report about flights into Shannon Airport.  He complimented the Minister for Foreign Affairs on arranging for the cross-Border orchestra to come here.  The Senator mentioned the importance of the music of Lambeg drums and uilleann pipes being played side by side, which was a lovely analogy.</P>
        <P>Senator Maurice Hayes called on the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform to ensure that paedophiles do not gain refuge or asylum here.  The Senator mentioned that there are strict laws in this regard in the North.  He said he would like to speak on the matter in the House.  He also referred to the issue of youth mental services.</P>
        <P>Senator Bannon spoke about the excessive cost of tribunals.  Perhaps the Senator was not a Member of this House when they were established by orders of the two Houses of the Oireachtas.  A further order of both Houses would be needed to change the tribunals&rsquo; arrangements.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I want the tribunals to be more accountable to this country&rsquo;s taxpayers, who foot the bill for them.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator knows he is not allowed to interrupt the Leader.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I am endeavouring to say it as it is.  Senator Bannon also asked for flood relief to <Col N="969"/>be allocated to the counties which suffered from flooding at the weekend.  He did not refer to any county in particular.</P>
        <P>Senator Dooley raised the issue of water quality in the context of the failure of a &euro;2 million water treatment system in Ennis, County Clare, to rectify the water problems there.</P>
        <P>Senator Quinn mentioned Professor Riste&aacute;rd Mulcahy, who has written a book about the need for people to be proactive about health matters.  I read the article in today&rsquo;s <i>The Irish Times</i>, in which Professor Mulcahy said one can be the master of one&rsquo;s quality of health by doing something about it, such as going for walks and eating the right food, etc.  Professor Mulcahy is an example of that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>He is.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Jim Walsh joined the debate on youth mental health.  He called for a debate on the vested interests in the profession.  Such a debate would be helpful.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Ms White</NameTxt>
	<P>He spoke about hospital consultants.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>That is right.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator John Paul Phelan mentioned that a consultant psychologist position in Kilkenny is vacant.  He asked about the status of the Hanly report.  The Senator also asked me to raise with the Minister for Education and Science some concerns which have been highlighted in respect of Down&rsquo;s syndrome.  I have not heard about any curtailment of the hours given to the education of people with Down&rsquo;s syndrome.  I do not mean to dismiss the Senator&rsquo;s query when I say this specific topic would be suitable for an Adjournment debate.</P>
        <P>Senator Feeney spoke about the emotion she felt when watching last night&rsquo;s &ldquo;Prime Time Investigates&rdquo;.  One could not have watched it without feeling intense emotion.  When one considers what some parents are going through, it is clear those of us who have reared children who turned out all right are lucky.  Senator Feeney also discussed obesity and anorexia.  She is a member of the Joint Committee on Child Protection.  It looks increasingly likely that there will be a referendum on the position of children in the Constitution.  Programmes like the one we saw last night are useful in adding to the debate on such matters.  When I watched the documentary last night, I wanted to start collecting money and doing things.  I wondered what we all could do about it.  I felt fired up about such awfulness.</P>
        <P>Senator Paddy Burke referred to the under-funding of local authorities. Senator Lydon highlighted the need for children with mental health problems to benefit from intensive services if they are to turn the corner.  I find it repugnant that young people are being placed in adult mental <Col N="970"/>hospitals beside elderly people who have been in such hospitals for many years.</P>
        <P>Senator Feighan asked who is regulating the health system.  He mentioned a huge meeting in Roscommon last night about water services.  Was he at the meeting in question?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrankFeighan"><NameTxt>Mr. Feighan</NameTxt>
	<P>I was.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Some 1,500 people attended the meeting to condemn the idea of water metering.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Mr. Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>He did not speak at the meeting.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>That is fair enough.  We cannot force the Senator to speak.</P>
        <P>Senator Mooney talked about a knee-jerk reaction to the television programme.  I am glad I had a knee-jerk reaction to the programme.  One could not but feel intensely emotional about it and if that is a knee-jerk reaction, what harm?  It is proper that we felt that emotion.</P>
        <P>The Senator said he had good experiences of the support services in the north west, which is welcome.  He talked about having a debate on the services for those over 18 but I would prefer to narrow the debate to mental services for youth.  We will endeavour to have that.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Official Languages Act Regulations:" RHead="Motion"> 
    <Title>Official Languages Act Regulations: Motion. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I move:</P>
        <P LI="1">That the Order of the 21st November, 2006 referring the proposal that Seanad approves the Official Languages Act 2003 (Section 9) Regulations 2006 in draft, to the Joint Committee on Arts, Sport, Tourism, Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs, shall have effect with the substitution of &lsquo;14th December&rsquo; for &lsquo;5th December&rsquo;.&rdquo;</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Bovine Diseases (Levies) Regulations 2006:" RHead="Motion"> 
    <Title>Bovine Diseases (Levies) Regulations 2006: Motion. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I move: </P>
        <P LI="1">That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Regulations in draft:</P>
        <P LI="2">Bovine Diseases (Levies) Regulations, 2006,</P>
        <P FLI="0"><?oasys _is0p10- ?><?oasys _ix ?>copies of which were laid in draft before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on the 1st December, 2006, be referred to the Joint Committee on Agriculture and Food in accordance with paragraph (1) (Seanad) of the Orders of Reference of that Committee, which, not later than 14th December, 2006, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing <Col N="971"/>Order 67, and Standing Order 69(2) shall accordingly apply.&rdquo;</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="National Economic and Social" RHead="Development Office Act: Motion"> 
    <Title>National Economic and Social Development Office Act: Motion. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I move:</P>
        <P LI="1">That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Order in draft:</P>
        <P LI="2">National Economic and Social Development Office Act 2006 (Establishment Day) Order 2006,</P>
        <P FLI="0"><?oasys _is0p10- ?><?oasys _ix ?>copies of which have been laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 1st December, 2006.&rdquo;</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
 <HtmlBk SectId="3" />
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prisons Bill 2006:" RHead="Motion to Recommit"> 
    <Title>Prisons Bill 2006: Motion to Recommit.</Title>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>I move:</P>
        <P LI="1">That Seanad &Eacute;ireann, pursuant to Standing Order No. 111,  directs that the Prisons Bill 2006 be recommitted in respect of amendments Nos. 24 to 26, inclusive.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prisons Bill 2006:" RHead="Report Stage"> 
    <Title>Prisons Bill 2006: Report Stage.</Title>
      <Speaker pid="JoannaTuffy"><NameTxt>Ms Tuffy</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 1: </P>
        <P LI="1">In page 6, line 16, after &ldquo;force&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;at a material time&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">We tabled this amendment because the definition of &ldquo;prison rules&rdquo; is somewhat flawed in that it applies only to rules in force.  Thus, if new rules were made repealing old rules the old rules would no longer be in force and would not be prison rules for the purpose of any ongoing disciplinary proceedings for the appeal tribunal.  I would like to hear the Minister&rsquo;s comments on that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><TitleTxt>T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I took advice on this matter and was told the insertion of the words &ldquo;at a material time&rdquo; are not usual and that it is not practice to insert them.  The Senator will be aware that, under the Interpretation Act, where something is repealed it does not have the effect of ending any proceedings taken under it unless a contrary intention appears.  I am disinclined to accept the amendment unless the Senator persuades me otherwise.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is the amendment being pressed?</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="972"/>
      <Speaker pid="JoannaTuffy"><NameTxt>Ms Tuffy</NameTxt>
	<P>I cannot make any further arguments about it.  I withdraw the amendment.  If my colleagues want to retable it in the D&aacute;il, they will do so.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 7, line 2, to delete &ldquo;Government&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;Oireachtas&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">The effect of the amendment would be to ensure that no contract for privatisation of the prison services would be entered into without the approval of the Oireachtas.  There should be some non-governmental scrutiny of such an important process.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the amendment.  Will the Minister indicate if the sniffer dog service in the prison system will be privatised?  I understand there are five or six horses in the city but there is only one dog in our prison services.  Is it the intention of the Minister to privatise that aspect of the business?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>I cannot see any sense in this amendment.  It would be cumbersome and unworkable if requests to move prisoners had to come before the Houses of the Oireachtas in cases where prisoner escort services were required.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not intend to avail of the powers provided under this section as long as the prison service, through its own internal escort service, provides a reasonably economic means of transporting prisoners to and from other places.  If a successor of mine were in a position where they had to do that due to an incapacity on the part of the prison service to provide that service, the question of entering into a contract would arise.  It would not be reasonable to get the prior agreement of the Oireachtas because if, for whatever reason, the service was unavailable, there would be a requirement to come back to the Oireachtas.  For instance, if a service was in existence and the company went bust, to say nothing could happen until the Oireachtas met might be very inconvenient and the Senators might be disinclined to be summoned back from their summer holidays to study a new contract or whatever.  I do not wish to be flippant but it is for the Government of the day to approve contracts.  I assure this House and the public, however, that as far as I am concerned this is very much a second best option.  It is only in the Bill to ensure that in respect of the agreement I have with the public servants in the prison system, they will arrange matters to ensure an economical service within the system to the State will be upheld.</P>
        <P>It is my intent to increase the number of sniffer dogs in the prison service because it is important <Col N="973"/>that they should be available frequently on a random basis.  We cannot have a situation where there is only one dog in the country and wherever that dog is located, everybody can be relatively sure no other dog will perform similar services.  Sniffer dogs are hugely beneficial adjuncts to security services in a range of situations and it is my intention to ensure they are within the service and that they are looked after by officers of the service.  Obviously they have to be trained by outside experts.  The training of them is not a matter for the service but in the long term I do not want them to have to have handlers from outside the service.  In a reasonable prison situation, if dogs are brought into cells to sniff out concealed drugs and the like, that is work prison officers should be doing.  It should not require the retention of independent contractors to achieve that type of searching facility.  As for horses, there is nothing I can say.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelKitt"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. Kitt</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendment No. 3 is in the name of Senators Cummins and Brian Hayes.  It is proposed to take amendments Nos. 3 to 9, inclusive, together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 3:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 8, line 12, to delete &ldquo;and&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">The objective of this group of amendments is to put in place safeguards for private prison custody officers.  We must be extremely cautious in framing this legislation as it outlines their statutory duties.  We must also bear in mind that if they act outside the scope of the Constitution or engage in unlawful behaviour the State  ultimately could be vicariously liable for their actions.  We need to ensure the highest possible standards are retained if privatisation occurs and that respect is at the core for private prison officers, as it is for those employed directly by the Prison Service.</P>
        <P>These amendments are also designed to create a responsibility on prisoner custody officers to protect a prisoner&rsquo;s safety and well-being.  This forms an important element of the job in hand and should therefore be listed in the legislation as a core function.  These amendments will put an onus on a prisoner custody officer to behave in an appropriate fashion and require him or her to act only within the bounds of the law.  It may well be argued that these statements go without saying particularly with reference to amendment No. 10.  However, there is an inherent value in stating them clearly and unambiguously in the relevant governing statute.  The Minister mentioned that many of these aspects are covered in subsections (6) and (7) of section 6, but they do not go far enough.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="974"/>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I indicated on the last occasion that I would consider all these matters and I have considered subsections (6) and (7) of section 6.  They adequately cover this matter.  They provide that my successors are expressly prohibited from issuing a certificate unless the person is of good character, is capable of performing the functions of a custody officer, has undergone such course of training relating thereto, or has such experience as would, in the opinion of the Minister, enable him or her to perform the functions of a prisoner custody office in an efficient manner, and is otherwise a fit and proper person.  It is a condition of the certificate that the person in the performance of his or her duties does not contravene an agreement under section 6 and complies with the provisions of this Act and any prison rules relating to the treatment of prisoners.  Prison rules relating to the treatment of prisoners will always provide for their proper and respectful treatment by all people, whether they are public servants or outsiders.  I want to emphasise yet again that it is not my intention to activate these provisions unless a set of circumstances, which I do not anticipate at this stage, comes into existence.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister has said, and I agree with him, that he does not intend to put in place these provisions but when this legislation is in place he may not be in office.  There are not adequate safeguards in that respect in subsections (6) and (7) of section 6.  They should be spelt out in more detail, as I outlined in some of these amendments.  </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>The level of protection envisaged by the Senator&rsquo;s amendments in primary statutory form is more demanding than that provided for in regard to prison officers.  Prison officers are bound by prison rules and by the terms of their appointment.  They are not set out in statutory form.  I do not see why we should assume that somebody who will conduct transport functions should have a higher standard of behaviour imposed on him or her by primary law than is imposed on prison officers generally.  Furthermore, the condition of the certificate is that any custody officer would have to comply with any prison rules relating to the treatment of prisoners.  I cannot imagine what new or higher standards would be provided for that is not already provided for under prison rules.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Amendments Nos. 4 to 9, inclusive, not moved.</P>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Amendments Nos. 10 and 11 are related and they may be discussed together by agreement.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 10:</P><Col N="975"/>
        <P LI="1">In page 10, between lines 33 and 34, to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="1">&ldquo;(4) A prisoner custody officer shall, in respect of any search conducted under this section, make a report to the relevant governor&mdash;</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>a</i>) explaining the reasons for the search,</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>b</i>) in the case of a search under <i>subsection (2)</i>, stating what grounds he or she had for believing that the prisoner had concealed a prohibited article beneath his or her clothing,</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>c</i>) detailing what, if any, prohibited articles were found, and</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>d</i>) providing any other details that the prisoner custody officer may deem to be relevant.</P>
        <P LI="1">(5) A prisoner custody officer shall give any prohibited article found pursuant to a search under this section, to the relevant governor.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">Searches of a person involve the violation of important rights.  I recognise that this is sometimes required for the safety of a prisoner or other prisoners.  I also recognise that prisoners necessarily submit themselves to a regime that involves violations of privacy at many levels.  However, in this context, the Bill once again falls short on safeguards that should be included to protect all prisoners from an unwarranted intrusion on their rights.</P>
        <P>This amendment represents a simple reporting structure, whereby there would be a record of every search and an explanation for same.  The effect of this amendment is to protect a prisoner&rsquo;s rights and to shield a prisoner custody officer from any unjustified accusations or unfounded complaints.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 11 is a technical amendment, which is dependent on the acceptance of amendment No. 10.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the amendment.</P>
        <P>Has the finding of drugs as a result of a search of a prisoner been reported to the Garda?  Has a case ever been taken against a prisoner on whom drugs have been found?  It is a serious offence for a person, wherever he or she may be, to be found in possession of drugs.  Has any case been taken against prisoners found to be in possesion of drugs, or are the Garda called to investigate in such circumstances?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>It is my understanding that the Garda is informed of attempts to smuggle drugs into prison whenever the prison staff can identify the person who has made the attempt.  When drugs are thrown in over walls, sometimes that cannot be done.  In those circumstances, it <Col N="976"/>would be wasteful of Garda time to involve it in something which is manifestly futile.  </P>
        <P>I wish to advise the House that in the course of the recent legislation on criminal justice a new offence of smuggling, or attempting to smuggle, drugs into a prison has been created as an express new offence with special punishments attached to it.  It is not as if the matter is simply let go.  I am aware people have been arrested when they were found by prison officers to be in possession of drugs.  My strong view is that present visiting conditions in most Irish prisons and present locations of prisons mean the Prison Service is facing an uphill battle in some institutions in keeping drugs out of prisons.  That is why in certain circumstances it is necessary to have screened visits and in other cases it is necessary to move the prisons in their entirety to places where it not possible to throw things in over the wall.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">4 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P Just="Left">When the mandatory drug testing, which is provided for in this legislation, comes into effect, there will be a firm basis for a drug free prison policy.  We have spoken about that in this House previously and I am a strong believer in it.  As I said on the last occasion, I cannot accept the proposition that we should take the view that because there are drugs in the world outside prison we should also expect to find them within prisons.  That is to surrender completely on the function of prison, which is to rehabilitate.  If we were to tolerate drugs, to have needle exchanges, to turn a blind eye to the presence of drugs in prison or to fail to have random testing of prisoners, we would make a mockery of the prison process, which is rehabilitative.  Our rate of recidivism is high enough.  We should use prison to initiate a programme to get every addict off drugs.  If an addict has been supplied with drugs throughout his or her stay in prison, the likelihood is that he or she will leave prison not merely with a habit that needs to be fed, but also a debt.  It will also mean other prisoners will have been corrupted.  Innocent prisoners who have nothing to do with drugs are frequently bullied into smuggling them in for high risk prisoners.  This is a very difficult situation and we cannot be naive about it.  Innocent prisoners who do not have a drug habit are subjected to threats in prison to act as mules to bring drugs into the prison.  Such people might be trustee prisoners outside on a prison works project in a community centre, and they come under pressure to smuggle drugs into prisons, which is a very serious matter.</P>
        <?oasys _cl11.5- ?><P>I will not comment on more topical events that happened recently.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I have been supportive of the Minister on the issue of drugs.  Last week on Second Stage, I spoke about two inmates in Wheatfield Prison who said the place was awash with drugs and that they were using their mobile telephones to get onto the airwaves.  However, <Col N="977"/>these matters are not relevant to the amendment that I have tabled, which I wish to press.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="978"/>
        <P>Amendment put.</P><Col N="977"/>
            <Vote>
        <Result>The Seanad divided: T&aacute;, 15; N&iacute;l, 23.</Result>
        <YHeading>T&aacute;</YHeading><Col N="977"/>
        <YesVote pid="JamesBannon">Bannon, James.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PaddyBurke">Burke, Paddy.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="UlickBurke">Burke, Ulick.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PaulCoghlan">Coghlan, Paul.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MauriceCummins">Cummins, Maurice.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="FrankFeighan">Feighan, Frank.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MichaelFinucane">Finucane, Michael.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrianHayes">Hayes, Brian.</YesVote><Col N="978"/>
        <YesVote pid="DavidNorris">Norris, David.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="KathleenOMeara">O&rsquo;Meara, Kathleen.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JoeOToole">O&rsquo;Toole, Joe.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JohnPaulPhelan">Phelan, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="">Quinn, Feargal.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="ShaneRoss">Ross, Shane.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JoannaTuffy">Tuffy, Joanna.</YesVote>
        <NHeading><Col N="977"/>N&iacute;l</NHeading><Col N="977"/>
        <NoVote pid="CyprianBrady">Brady, Cyprian.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MichaelBrennan">Brennan, Michael.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PeterCallanan">Callanan, Peter.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="BrendanDaly">Daly, Brendan.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TimDooley">Dooley, Timmy.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="GeraldineFeeney">Feeney, Geraldine.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="BrendanKenneally">Kenneally, Brendan.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TonyKett">Kett, Tony.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MichaelKitt">Kitt, Michael P.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TerryLeyden">Leyden, Terry.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DonLydon">Lydon, Donal J.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DrMartinMansergh">Mansergh, Martin.</NoVote><Col N="978"/>
        <NoVote pid="JohnMinihan">Minihan, John.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaschalMooney">Mooney, Paschal C.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PatMoylan">Moylan, Pat.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="LabhrasOMurchu">&Oacute; Murch&uacute;, Labhr&aacute;s.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FrancisOBrien">O&rsquo;Brien, Francis.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MaryORourke">O&rsquo;Rourke, Mary.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="AnnOrmonde">Ormonde, Ann.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="EamonScanlon">Scanlon, Eamon.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JimWalsh">Walsh, Jim.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MaryMWhite">White, Mary M.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DiarmuidWilson">Wilson, Diarmuid.</NoVote>
        <Tellers><Col N="977"/>Tellers: T&aacute;, Senators P. Burke and Cummins; N&iacute;l, Senators Minihan and Moylan.</Tellers><Col N="977"/>
        <Decision><?oasys _is0p10- ?>Amendment declared lost.</Decision>
      </Vote>
        <P>Amendment No. 11 not moved.</P>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendment No. 12 is in the name of Senator Cummins.  Amendments Nos. 12 to 15, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together, by agreement. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 12:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 12, line 21, to delete &ldquo;may&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;shall&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">This amendment ensures that the procedures for an inquiry will be listed in the prison rules so the prisoners can have easy access to them.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the amendment. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>This amendment makes it mandatory to set procedures in the prison rules.  I do not want to accept it because if every procedure is set out in the rules, it could mean inflexibility is introduced into the whole inquiry procedure, which would militate against trying to make the system work.  The term &ldquo;may&rdquo; is used in the legislation and of course there will be the outline of a procedure.  However, there could be unforeseen circumstances whereby a procedure has to be invented because of the nature of something or other.  All types of contingencies may arise and if there is to be a statutory instrument to cover every unforeseen procedure, unfortunately the system will get bogged down in bureaucracy and legalities.  I want a system that works, primarily, and given that there is an appeal mechanism <Col N="978"/>involved in the whole procedure and the fact that legally trained people will operate it, it is not necessary to stipulate that every single contingency the disciplinary system might run into has to be laid down in a statutory instrument, such as a prison rule. </P>
        <P>Amendment No. 13 is a Government amendment.  It forms a response to points made by Senators Tuffy and Henry on Committee Stage to the effect that a doctor is included in the list of persons who might visit a prisoner, despite a prohibition on visitors as a sanction, but that as a doctor might not always be the most appropriate person, other types of health care workers might be required.  I believe the amendment proposed is sensible, because anybody who is giving medical advice or treatment could include doctors, nurses, dentists, psychiatrists, psychologists and people of that type, who would be covered, and even those involved in the supply of basic procedures such as paramedical activities.  I thank Senators Henry and Tuffy for their suggestion.</P>
        <P>On amendment No. 15, I explained to the House on Committee Stage that the UN Committee against Torture does not actually visit prisons, unlike the European Committee for the Prevention of Torture and Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment.  The UN Committee against Torture monitors the implementation of the UN Convention against Torture and other cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment.  This monitoring function is carried out through the examination of reports submitted by states, parties and NGOs in terms of responses to them, on the rights under the convention, and how <Col N="979"/>these are being implemented.  Since this does not happen, there is no point for providing for it in law.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoannaTuffy"><NameTxt>Ms Tuffy</NameTxt>
	<P>In respect of the amendments I tabled, I welcome the Minister&rsquo;s effective acceptance in amendment No. 13 of the point I made in amendment No. 14, which I will withdraw.  As for amendment No. 15, Labour Party Members tried to include the United Nations Committee against Torture because they believed this section gives a right to visit a prisoner to the Council of Europe Committee for the Prevention of Torture and believed it might be appropriate to cover the United Nations committee as well.  Has the Minister a further opinion in this regard?</P>
        <P>The Minister&rsquo;s new wording in amendment No. 13 no longer mentions psychologists although the other categories are still present, as well as the Minister&rsquo;s additions.  Does he believe that psychologists are covered by the term &ldquo;medical advice or treatment&rdquo;?  While he may do so, psychologists might not be covered by it.  I ask the Minister to comment in this respect.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>On behalf of Senator Henry, who is unavoidably absent today, I thank the Minister for including in his amendment the points she raised.  She was very anxious to raise this matter and that dentists or health workers should be included.  However, given the Minister&rsquo;s comments in this regard, this amendment covers all such issues.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 13:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 13, lines 4 and 5, to delete all words from and including &ldquo;those&rdquo; in line 4 down to and including &ldquo;adviser&rdquo; in line 5 and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="2" el="5">&ldquo;visits for the purpose of giving medical advice or treatment to the prisoner or those from his or her legal adviser, a chaplain or member of the visiting committee to the prison&rdquo;.</P>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 14 not moved.</P>
      <Speaker pid="JoannaTuffy"><NameTxt>Ms Tuffy</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 15:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 13, line 8, after &ldquo;Commission&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;, United Nations Committee against Torture&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">Has the Minister anything to say in respect of this amendment?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>Is Senator Tuffy referring to the position regarding the UN?</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="980"/>
      <Speaker pid="JoannaTuffy"><NameTxt>Ms Tuffy</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.  Perhaps the Minister might also comment on my point about psychologists.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>On the question of psychologists, I will re-examine this matter before the Bill comes before the D&aacute;il to ensure that psychological advice is included in &ldquo;medical advice or treatment&rdquo;.  If not, I will deal with it.  The term would cover psychiatric advice.  However in this context, a psychologist would normally be provided by the Prison Service and would not be covered by the sanction.  Outside psychologists do not normally visit prisoners at their request.  However, I will check and if there is reason to make further amendments, I will consider it.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
	<P>As amendments Nos. 16 and 17 and 19 to 23, inclusive, are related and amendment No. 18 is an alternative to amendment No. 17, amendments Nos. 16 to 23, inclusive, may be discussed together by agreement.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 16:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 13, to delete lines 18 to 20 and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;(<i>e</i>) forfeiture of such sum of money&mdash;</P>
        <P LI="3">(i) in part, or</P>
        <P LI="3">(ii) in total,</P>
        <P FLI="0"><?oasys _is1p8- ?><?oasys _ix ?>as may be specified by the governor, provided such forfeited sum does not exceed an amount of money that has been credited or is to be credited to the prisoner for work defined by section 5(2) of the National Minimum Wage Act 2000 (as amended by section 36 of this Act) from public funds;&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0" el="5">I have changed this amendment slightly from Committee Stage in order that the Minister might be better minded to accept it.  Specifically, I have added the phrase &ldquo;from public funds&rdquo;, at the end of the paragraph in response to the Minister&rsquo;s remarks on Committee Stage.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 18 clarifies that a governor may not confiscate money under section 13(1)(<i>g</i>).  I am interested to hear the Minister&rsquo;s comments on amendment No. 17.</P>
        <P>Further to the discussion on the issues raised regarding amendments Nos. 21 to 23, inclusive, on Committee Stage, I have reconstituted them in order that they clarify the procedure for the prisoner to lodge an appeal.  Notwithstanding the Minister&rsquo;s defence of the section on Committee Stage, it is not properly drafted.  I have taken into account his point about such matters necessarily being directed through the governor of a prison and the amendments reflect this.  They place a clear legal duty on the governor.</P>
        <P>These amendments also redefine who shall be allowed to be a member of the appeals tribunal.  On Committee Stage, the Minister expressed concern that a person on a tribunal might not have <Col N="981"/>the requisite knowledge of procedures and doctrines.  However, to reject this amendment is to deny a significant corpus of knowledge and experience to the appeals process.  Consequently, I have updated the amendment to allow the Minister to prescribe the necessary legal training for that person.  I strongly believe, especially regarding amendment No. 23, that it should not be confined to the legal profession.  Has the Minister decided how many people should be involved in an appeals tribunal?  Will it be one, three or five?  The number should be spelled out.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I propose to deal with amendments Nos. 16 to 23, inclusive, together as they relate to sanctions and appeals.  Amendment No. 16 proposes that one of the sanctions that can be imposed by a prison governor on a prisoner for a breach of prison discipline is the forfeiture of some or all of the money credited or to be credited to the prisoner from public funds for work carried out in a prison, which is not subject to the National Minimum Wage Act.  I have consulted the Parliamentary Counsel and am advised the current text of section 13(1)(<i>e</i>) already deals with this point.  Hence, the amendment is unnecessary and I do not propose to accept it.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 18 tabled by Senator Cummins proposes the insertion of the phrase, &ldquo;denial, but not confiscation,&rdquo;, of a gratuity earned in section 13(1)(<i>g</i>).  On Committee Stage I indicated that I would reconsider the wording of this subsection and revert to the House.  The wording I now propose in amendment No. 17 replaces the word &ldquo;denial&rdquo; in this provision with postponement of payment of the gratuity earned, which I hope makes the meaning more clear.  The intention is that while the prisoner would not have the use of any gratuities for a period, such gratuities would not be forfeited.  Senator Cummins&rsquo;s suggested use of the word &ldquo;confiscation&rdquo; in this regard is not the best solution as confiscation can only apply to something already in the prisoner&rsquo;s possession and not to moneys that would normally be earned during the 60 day period.  The use of the word &ldquo;postponement&rdquo; removes any doubt as to the meaning of the provision.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Amendment No. 19 has been introduced following the tabling of an amendment on Committee Stage by Senator Tuffy to the effect that a governor would inform the prisoner of his or her right to any sanction imposed through an appeal tribunal.  At the time, I indicated that I had sympathy for that amendment because the Bill did not expressly state that a prisoner would be informed of an option to appeal.  Having consulted the Parliamentary Counsel on the issue, I have tabled this amendment to section 13 to the effect that when a sanction is imposed, the governor must explain, in ordinary language, that the prisoner may petition the Minister regarding a <Col N="982"/>sanction, and if the sanction includes forfeiture of remission of a portion of a sentence, the prisoner may appeal the decision to an appeal tribunal.  I am widening the provision in the manner suggested originally by the Labour Party Members.  Moreover, the provision will be better placed in section 13, rather than in section 15 as originally proposed.  I thank Senator Tuffy and the Labour Party Members for bringing this matter to my attention and for their proposed amendment.  This makes amendment No. 20, which deals with the same issue, redundant.</P>
        <P>I cannot deduce the need for amendment No. 21 tabled by Senators Cummins and Brian Hayes.  The use of the term &ldquo;request&rdquo; in this regard, as suggested by the Senators, indicates the governor would have some form of discretion in the process of allowing an appeal or that he could allow or refuse the request.  This is not the case.  An indication of a forthcoming appeal must be forwarded to the tribunal as is provided for in section 15(2) and it is not in the governor&rsquo;s power to prevent this.  Therefore, the amendment should not be accepted.</P>
        <P Just="Left">In respect of amendment No. 22, while I cannot accept the proposed amendment, the word &ldquo;request&rdquo; is not the most appropriate.  I will reconsider the wording in conjunction with the Parliamentary Counsel with a view to reverting to an appropriate amendment in the D&aacute;il.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 23 would have the effect of allowing persons other than barristers or solicitors of seven years&rsquo; standing to act as appeal tribunals.  I indicated on Committee Stage that I do not propose to accept this measure.  It is important that a member of an appeal tribunal should have extensive legal experience.  Moreover, as an appeal tribunal is a quasi-judicial authority, it is not appropriate that somebody with no legal background should take on a judicial role.</P>
        <P>It was suggested in the House that persons such as former prison governors or prison chaplains would be eminently suitable for the role.  Having considered that carefully, I am not in agreement.  It would be unfair to ask a religious person to sit in judgment in this fashion and probably not a role that he or she would relish.</P>
        <P>As for former prison governors, appeal tribunals must be independent in their functions and while a prison governor may have certain experience which I fully accept could be useful in the role, if I were to allow a former prison governor to consider lifting a sanction placed on a prisoner by a current prison governor, there would be many objections as to whether the procedure was truly independent.</P>
        <P>As appeals tribunals are being established to ensure that we are in compliance with the European Convention on Human Rights, it is important that they should be perceived as being wholly independent and of a legal nature.  Furthermore, if we were to stray outside the requirement for legal personnel, we would be looking at <Col N="983"/>something close to the existing visiting committee structure and that might not be appropriate either.</P>
        <P>The case law of the European Court of Human Rights and legal opinions obtained by the Office of the Attorney General point to the possibility that imposing loss of remission as a sanction might be regarded as the equivalent of imposing an additional sentence of imprisonment and therefore might require safeguards associated with due process, including the right to legal representation.  For that reason, it would be more appropriate to have a person with not just legal training but legal experience, rather that have somebody who had no such training.  I do not want a situation where a lay person is being bamboozled by lawyers and it is important that if somebody will act at the tribunal and if it is possible at all that lawyers will appear in that forum, it is better that the tribunal members should have some legal training.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Minister suggest that barristers bamboozle members of the public?  I still feel strongly about this matter.  It should not be confined to barristers or solicitors of seven years&rsquo; standing.  I changed my stance and asked that if the Minister felt it appropriate, proper training or instruction would be given to people being appointed before an appeals tribunal would be set up.  I have been reasonable in making this suggestion.  I also asked the Minister about the numbers he envisages involved in such a tribunal.  Perhaps he might reply on that matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>It all depends.  Tribunals can have a number of members or just one member.  For instance, at present the Refugee Appeals Tribunal has one member.  Other appellate bodies have a number of persons in them.</P>
        <P>The real point is that this is where a prisoner could be appealing, for instance, a forfeiture of a remission, which could be a quarter of the prisoner&rsquo;s sentence.  If that were to happen, let us be under no illusion that it is not a minor but a significant matter.  If it were to happen, I would like to have the confidence at least that whoever would make the decision would know the law, or at least could be presumed to know the law, and would be somebody who would have had experience of seeing the law administered and of participating in the administration of justice.  That is why I am doing this.  It is not to give jobs to my friends or anything like that.  It is purely because I strongly believe that it involves something of such importance to a prisoner.</P>
        <P>As Senator Cummins will appreciate, the term of imprisonment of a prisoner sentenced to ten years is reduced by a quarter if he or she behaves properly.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>Automatically.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="984"/>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>If the prisoner were to behave in a manner that could potentially lead to the reinstatement of that two and a half years, it is important that the person who does the job of deciding whether that decision was fairly made can see around corners and can see that due process requires X and Y to happen in the conduct of the appeal.</P>
        <P>This is not small beer.  If it were some kind of argument about whether a prisoner was rude to a prison officer and was losing his or her entitlements to a visit for a day, one can well imagine that this would be small stuff which any decent, honourable and commonsense person could carry out.  I agree with Senator Cummins that in those circumstances, it might be superfluous that only a barrister or a solicitor of experience could do it.  However, let us not forget that this is a serious function and one is dealing with significant remission as well.  If push came to shove and somebody faced an extra year in prison as a result of one of these decisions, the Senator may bet his bottom dollar on it being a situation in which any departure from the constitutional requirements, due process, natural justice or whatever would be challenged immediately, and it would be down to the High Court where an expensive judicial review would be unleashed on the State.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>Who carries out the function at present?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator has replied and cannot speak again.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I would not be introducing this if I thought that it were not advisable under the European Convention on Human Rights to provide for such an appellate system.  It is for that reason I want to do it.</P>
        <P>I ask Senator Cummins to consider the notion that I could stand up in public and state that a man or woman is about to lose a year&rsquo;s entitlement to liberty which has been determined by a prison governor, and that person now has a right of appeal to a former prison governor.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>Whether they should have that automatic remission is another day&rsquo;s work.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator has replied.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 17:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 13, to delete line 23 and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="2" el="5">&ldquo;(<i>g</i>) postponement, for a specified period not exceeding 60 days, of payment of&rdquo;.</P>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 18 not moved.</P><Col N="985"/>
        <P>Government amendment No. 19:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 14, between lines 22 and 23, to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="2" el="5">&ldquo;(8) On the imposition of a sanction under this section, the governor shall explain in ordinary language to the prisoner concerned the content of <i>section 14(1)</i> and, if the sanction consists of or includes forfeiture of remission of portion of his or her sentence, of <i>section 15(1)</i>.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Amendments No. 20 to 22, inclusive, not moved.</P>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 23:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 15, to delete lines 36 to 38 and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="1">&ldquo;(3) The Minister may appoint a person who is&mdash;</P><Col N="986"/>
        <P LI="2">(<i>a</i>) a practising barrister or solicitor of not less than 7 years&rsquo; standing, or</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>b</i>) in the Minister&rsquo;s opinion, suitably qualified for the position through that person&rsquo;s&mdash;</P>
        <P LI="3">(i) professional or academic experience,</P>
        <P LI="3">(ii) substantial experience of the prison system, or</P>
        <P LI="3">(iii) relevant international experience of penal systems,</P>
        <P FLI="0"><?oasys _is1p8- ?><?oasys _ix ?>to be a member of and constitute an Appeal Tribunal.</P>
        <P LI="1">(4) In the case of a person appointed under <i>subsection (3)(b)</i> of this section, the Minister may prescribe such training or instruction as he or she deems appropriate before such a person may be a member of an constitute an Appeal Tribunal.&rdquo;.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand.&rdquo;</P><Col N="985"/>
      <Vote>
        <Result>The Seanad divided: T&aacute;, 24; N&iacute;l, 14.</Result>
        <YHeading>T&aacute;</YHeading><Col N="985"/>
        <YesVote pid="CyprianBrady">Brady, Cyprian.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MichaelBrennan">Brennan, Michael.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PeterCallanan">Callanan, Peter.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrendanDaly">Daly, Brendan.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="TimDooley">Dooley, Timmy.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="GeraldineFeeney">Feeney, Geraldine.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="">Hayes, Maurice.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrendanKenneally">Kenneally, Brendan.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="TonyKett">Kett, Tony.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MichaelKitt">Kitt, Michael P.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="TerryLeyden">Leyden, Terry.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DonLydon">Lydon, Donal J.</YesVote><Col N="986"/>
        <YesVote pid="DrMartinMansergh">Mansergh, Martin.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JohnMinihan">Minihan, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PaschalMooney">Mooney, Paschal C.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PatMoylan">Moylan, Pat.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="LabhrasOMurchu">&Oacute; Murch&uacute;, Labhr&aacute;s.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="FrancisOBrien">O&rsquo;Brien, Francis.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MaryORourke">O&rsquo;Rourke, Mary.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="AnnOrmonde">Ormonde, Ann.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="EamonScanlon">Scanlon, Eamon.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JimWalsh">Walsh, Jim.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MaryMWhite">White, Mary M.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DiarmuidWilson">Wilson, Diarmuid.</YesVote>
        <NHeading><Col N="985"/>N&iacute;l</NHeading><Col N="985"/>
        <NoVote pid="JamesBannon">Bannon, James.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaddyBurke">Burke, Paddy.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaulCoghlan">Coghlan, Paul.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="NoelCoonan">Coonan, Noel.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MauriceCummins">Cummins, Maurice.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FrankFeighan">Feighan, Frank.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MichaelFinucane">Finucane, Michael.</NoVote><Col N="986"/>
        <NoVote pid="BrianHayes">Hayes, Brian.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DerekMcDowell">McDowell, Derek.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DavidNorris">Norris, David.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JohnPaulPhelan">Phelan, John.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Quinn, Feargal.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="ShaneRoss">Ross, Shane.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JoannaTuffy">Tuffy, Joanna.</NoVote>
        <Tellers><Col N="985"/>Tellers: T&aacute;, Senators Minihan and Moylan; N&iacute;l, Senators P. Burke and Cummins.</Tellers><Col N="985"/>
        <Decision><?oasys _is0p10- ?>Question declared carried.</Decision>
      </Vote>
        <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
        <P>Bill recommitted in respect of amendments Nos. 24 to 26, inclusive.</P>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 24 to 26, inclusive, are cognate and may be discussed together.</P>
        </Speaker><P>Government amendment No. 24.</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 16, line 35, before &ldquo;Prison&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;Director-General of the Irish&rdquo;.</P><Col N="986"/>
            <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 24 to 26, inclusive, are technical.  The reference in the section, as drafted, is to the &ldquo;Prison Service&rdquo; as an organisation.  This is a drafting oversight as the Prison Service is not an identifiable legal person who can issue directions.  The amendments clarify that reference to the &ldquo;Prison Service&rdquo; is to the director general of the Irish Prison Service, to whom certain functions have and may be assigned by the Minister under law.  The word &ldquo;Irish&rdquo; has been inserted because the full title of the organisation is the &ldquo;Irish Prison Service&rdquo; and it is normally referred to as such.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="987"/>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 25.</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 17, line 41, before &ldquo;Prison&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;Director-General of the Irish&rdquo;.</P>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 26.</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 17, line 45, before &ldquo;Prison&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;Director-General of the Irish&rdquo;.</P>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Bill reported with amendments.</P>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 27 to 29, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 27:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 18, between lines 4 and 5, to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;(<i>b</i>) the Oireachtas,&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I am pleased the Minister has accepted the proposal I made on Committee Stage imposing on the Minister a statutory duty to inform the Oireachtas of his or her plans.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 28.</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 18, between lines 10 and 11, to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="2" el="5">&ldquo;(2) The Minister shall cause a copy of the notice to be laid before each House of the Oireachtas.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 29.</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 18, line 11, before &ldquo;shall&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;of the development&rdquo;.</P>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 30 and 31 and 33 to 35, inclusive, are related.  Amendment No. 32 is an alternative to amendment No. 31 and amendment No. 36 is an alternative to amendment No. 35.  Amendments Nos. 30 to 36, inclusive, will be taken together.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 30.</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 24, lines 9 to 12, to delete all words from and including &ldquo;the&rdquo; where it secondly occurs in line 9 down to and including &ldquo;appropriate.&rdquo; in line 12 and substitute the following:</P><Col N="988"/>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;any one or more of the following persons, as the Inspector considers appropriate:</P>
        <P LI="3">(i) the governor of the prison concerned;</P>
        <P LI="3">(ii) the Director-General of the Prison Service; or</P>
        <P LI="3">(iii) the Minister.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">The Minister indicated on Committee Stage that he would consider this amendment.  As it is largely technical in nature and improves the readability of the Bill, I ask him to accept it.  Notwithstanding his prolonged protestations on Committee Stage, I also ask the Minister to accept amendment No. 32 which proposes to increase and improve the accountability of the Government before the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
        <P Just="Left">On amendment No. 33, one of the criticisms laid against the Bill by experts on penal matters is that it does not provide for an independent prisons ombudsman whose function would be to investigate individual complaints made by prisoners.  It is not necessary to fetter the Inspector of Prisons and Places of Detention in the manner prescribed in the Bill.  Section 31(6) effectively prevents the inspector from investigating a complaint from an individual prisoner.  While I do not suggest that responding to every complaint should be one of the inspector&rsquo;s functions, the purpose of the amendment is to ensure the inspector&rsquo;s hands are not tied in any way.  The amendment provides that he or she could examine issues raised by a prisoner and hence fulfil one of the inspector&rsquo;s important functions.  Amendment No. 34 creates a specific offence of failing to co-operate with the inspector and, as such, provides important support for his or her work.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 36 addresses an issue I have raised on several occasions during debates on the Bill.  It is important to provide statutory timescales within which the Minister must lay documents before the Houses.  Without such a provision, it is, as we have seen, too easy and convenient to ignore the Oireachtas and delay publication of a document indefinitely or publish such documents at a time which precludes a debate being held in the House.  While I understand the reasons the Minister set out on Committee Stage in respect of the delay in publishing the most recent report of the Inspector of Prisons and Places of Detention, nevertheless the Bill should stipulate a timescale for the publication of reports.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the amendment.  Has increased overcrowding in prisons resulted in a rise in the number of complaints made by prisoners?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>Overcrowding in prisons was much worse in the past than it is now.  In so far as temporary release is an indication of overcrowding in prisons, in the mid-1990s between <Col N="989"/>15% and 20% of prisoners were on temporary release at any given time.  This is no longer the case.  I intend to continue to provide adequate prison space, not in the hope that it will be filled but in the confident expectation that no prisoner will be released in circumstances in which he or she should not be, that is, owing to the absence of prison space.  That is the policy I am trying to pursue.</P>
        <P>I indicated on Committee Stage that I would review amendment No. 30.  Having re-examined it with the Parliamentary Counsel, I am advised that I should not accept it as it does not improve the text.</P>
        <P>On amendments Nos. 31, 32, 35 and 36, amendments Nos. 32 and 36 provide that time limits be inserted into the provisions relating to the publication of reports.  Having indicated on Committee Stage that I would re-examine this issue before Report Stage, I have tabled amendments Nos. 31 and 35 to address the matter.</P>
        <P>As I indicated, unforeseen issues sometimes arise in respect of the publication of reports.  I noted on Committee Stage, for example, that legal advice had to be sought in a particular instance.  For this reason, it would be wrong to impose an inflexible and unachievable deadline for exceptional cases.  However, I do not want it suggested that a Minister would purposely delay publication, which I have never done.  The amendment I propose provides for a statutory duty that the reports concerned be published as soon as practicable.  This provision has a legal meaning as it imposes a duty on the Minister to publish reports as soon as it is practicable to do so.  In drink driving legislation, for instance, a sergeant must send off samples as soon as practicable, although one might require that this be done in 24 or 48 hours.</P>
        <P>My amendment imposes a strong duty on the Minister to publish reports as soon as practicable and makes it improper for him or her to leave them unpublished for no good reason.  I assure the Senator that the formula stated is a strong requirement that it is not open to any Minister in future to leave a report unpublished because it is politically inconvenient for the Minister or because the Department is administratively burdened by publishing the report.  This will no longer be possible.</P>
        <P>Precedents exist for that wording.  For instance, in the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act, the Minister must lay before the Oireachtas a three-year review from the Garda Commissioner for the efficiency, effectiveness and the management and deployment of resources of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and this must be done as soon as is practicable.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 33 proposes an addition to section 31(6) to clarify that the Inspector of Prisons and Places of Detention can examine the circumstances surrounding a complaint by a Minister for the purpose of fulfilling his or her functions under the Act.  I indicated on Committee Stage that I would review this proposal and revert <Col N="990"/>to the House.  I have received advice that there are good grounds not to do it but I am persuaded by the Senator&rsquo;s amendment that it is reasonable to say that if the inspector receives a particular complaint, in certain circumstances &mdash; although his function is not to investigate the complaint, he can do it along the lines suggested by the Senator&rsquo;s amendment &mdash; he shall have the right to examine the circumstances surrounding the complaint for the purposes of fulfilling his other functions.  I think this is a reasonable statement of the law as I would like it to be and I will accept that amendment.</P>
        <P>I do not propose to accept amendment No. 34.  I do not wish to start creating offences because there would be all sorts of arguments whether the request was reasonable or not.  I do not wish to criminalise this.  The Inspector of Prisons and Places of Detention has the moral authority to ensure compliance with his or her directions and requests.  I do not want a situation in which people are being arrested for failing to comply with his request as that is not usual in these circumstances.  Inspectors are not usually given that kind of power to impose criminal liabilities on others.  This would almost make him into a judge with a contempt jurisdiction and I am not happy to go that far.  However, I believe the present inspector has, as a matter of course, received every co-operation from the Prison Service.  If he arrives at any given time and asks to see any particular place, he will be shown it.  I do not believe that he is being held out or obstructed in the carrying out of his duty.  I prefer not to introduce an element of criminalisation into this issue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister for accepting amendment No. 33.  I accept the Minister&rsquo;s bona fides with respect to the other items, including a timescale of three months.  I accept the Minister&rsquo;s argument and the legal standing of the phrase &ldquo;as soon as practicable&rdquo;.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 31:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 24, to delete lines 17 and 18 and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">&ldquo;(3) As soon as practicable after receiving the report, the Minister shall, subject to <i>subsection (4)</i>, cause a copy of it to be laid before each House of the Oireachtas.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 32 not moved.</P>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 33:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 24, line 31, to delete &ldquo;prisoner&rdquo; and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;prisoner, but he shall have the right to examine the circumstances surrounding the <Col N="991"/>complaint for the purpose of fulfilling his functions under this Act&rdquo;.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 34 not moved.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 35:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 25, to delete lines 11 and 12 and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">&ldquo;(3) As soon as practicable after receiving a report under this section, the Minister shall cause a copy of it to be laid before each House of the Oireachtas.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 36 not moved.</P>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 37, 38 and 42 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 37:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 25, line 22, after &ldquo;prison&rdquo; to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;or designated centre (within the terms of the Criminal Law (Insanity) Act 2003)&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">In the case of amendments Nos. 37 and 38 I have pleasure in proposing them on behalf of Senator Henry.  We are all agreed that the notion of giving evidence by video link is a positive development and that it should be used as widely as possible wherever the circumstances are appropriate.  It would be ironic if some people who perhaps stood to benefit most from such an arrangement were to be excluded simply because the legislation did not apply to the place where they were detained.  The Bill as it stands discriminates between two classes of detainees and I see no possible reason for discriminating in this way.  I urge the Minister to accept amendments Nos. 37 and 38 as they discriminate on the basis of the place where somebody is detained rather than on the basis of the individual himself.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I second both amendments.  They are very worthy amendments as tabled by Senator Henry and explained by Senator Quinn.  These amendments would improve the Bill if accepted.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>On Committee Stage in this House Senator Henry proposed amendments to the effect that video-conferencing facilities in the Bill would also apply to persons in designated centres under the Criminal Law (Insanity) Act 2006.  I indicated at the time that I had some considerable sympathy with the Senator&rsquo;s views and <Col N="992"/>that I would examine the matter prior to Report Stage.  I am now bringing forward amendment No. 42 to section 34 which provides that the video-conferencing provisions in section 33 can apply to a designated centre if the Minister for Health and Children so directs after consultation with the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">5 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>While I hope my proposal meets the concerns of Senator Henry and Senator Quinn, it also meets some concerns which were expressed by Senator Norris, which I shared, about extending the concept of prisoner in section 33 to the category of persons detained in designated centres.  In this regard, my proposal for an amendment to section 34, which extends the provisions of section 33 to persons in remand centres or to children&rsquo;s detention in schools, meets the point raised by Senator Henry while at the same time avoiding the difficulty in terminology regarding prisoners which would be implicit if that route were taken.</P>
        <P>On a point of clarification, the amendment refers to the Act of 2003 instead of 2006.  The Bill was introduced in 2003 but it took its time to get through the Houses, as is always the case.</P>
        <P>I thank Senator Quinn for proposing the amendment and Senator Henry on the previous occasion.  I have taken on board their concerns.  I just want it to be the case that the Minister for Health and Children remains the lead Minister in respect of an initiative of this kind and that it is not suggested that the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform has an interfering role in the extension of these facilities to centres of the kind in question.  The Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform has an interest and therefore he would need to be consulted on the matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I appreciate the Minister&rsquo;s concern.  I did not quite understand the need for the Minister for Health and Children to be involved but the Minister has explained it very well and I am happy to withdraw both amendments.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 38 not moved.</P>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 39 and 40 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 39:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 26, line 16, to delete &ldquo;prisoner or&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;prisoner,&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">These two amendments will ensure that both the prisoner and his legal team will receive notice of the application.  There is no reason a prisoner should be disenfranchised from the legal process and he or she should be copied on all relevant documentation.  I would be grateful if the Minister could shed some light on the reason the <Col N="993"/>notice is only issued if the judge in question is of the view that it is desirable in the interests of justice.  Why are notices not automatically provided to all parties to a case?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the amendment.</P>
          </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DerekMcDowell"><NameTxt>Mr. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>The judge has the decision in the matter.  Clearly a prisoner cannot participate unless the prisoner is somehow involved.  I want to avoid a person saying a testimony is invalid because a notice was not served on the prisoner and his legal representative when both were well aware of what was happening and it was adequate to serve it on the legal representative.  Physically serving a notice would require handing it to the prisoner.  I want to make this workable without in any way diminishing the prisoner&rsquo;s rights.  If the prisoner&rsquo;s legal representative is aware of the situation, to co-notify the prisoner and to require the opposite to be done is an unnecessary impediment to making the system work.  If somebody in Portlaoise has to testify in a court in Dublin, I do not want a judge saying the Seanad amended this Act so that he or she cannot actually hear the person because somebody did not hand him or her a notice before the hearing started.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad"> 
    <Title>Business of Seanad. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>According to the Order of Business, we are to adjourn this debate now.  Would it be possible to complete the amendments in ten or 15 minutes?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>They could be completed in ten minutes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I propose we extend this debate until 5.10 p.m.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
     </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prisons Bill 2006:" RHead="Report Stage (Resumed) and Final Stage"> 
    <Title>Prisons Bill 2006: Report Stage (Resumed) and Final Stage.</Title>
              <P>Debate resumed on amendment No. 39:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 26, line 16, to delete &ldquo;prisoner or&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;prisoner,&rdquo;.</P>
        <P Just="Right" el="5">&mdash;(Senator Cummins).</P>
            <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I accept what the Minister has stated in regard to the notification and I will withdraw both amendments.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 40 not moved.</P>
      <Speaker pid="JoannaTuffy"><NameTxt>Ms Tuffy</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 41:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 26, line 33, after &ldquo;law&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;or order of any court&rdquo;.</P><Col N="994"/>
        <P FLI="0">The Minister indicated he might be supportive of this amendment so we resubmitted it.  The purpose of the amendment is to make it clear that the accused will also be present for the purposes of any court order in addition to being present for the purposes of any enactment or rule of law.  For example, if a person gets bail in the High Court which remands him or her to appear before the Circuit Court which then allows for a video link, he or she should be deemed to be present for all purposes at that stage.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I accept the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 42:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 27, line 26, after &ldquo;2001&rdquo; to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="2" el="5">&ldquo;or, where the Minister for Health and Children, after consultation with the Minister, by order so directs, a designated centre within the meaning of the Criminal Law (Insanity) Act 2006&rdquo;.</P>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 43 to 46, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 43:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 29, line 4, to delete &ldquo;shall&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;shall, subject to subsection (2),&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">Amendment No. 43 is a technical one and dependent on acceptance of amendment No. 44.  Amendment No. 44 gives the vital discretion to the governor of a prison to decide whether he or she wants to demand a payment for services described in the Bill.  There could be a number of reasons he or she would not want to do so but the Bill currently requires governors to charge for services and appears to leave no room for movement in this area.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 45 is an important insertion which guarantees that none of the provisions under section 37 will be used to prevent access to medical treatment for prisoners.  It may be argued by the Minister that such a subsection is unnecessary but it is an important safeguard of the rights of prisoners and I urge him to accept its insertion into the Bill.</P>
        <P>While the Bill is clear that prisons may not profit from provisions of goods or services to inmates by stating in section 37 that payments or deductions shall not exceed the full cost of providing the goods or services, it is not clear that there could not be other methods of revenue generation.  I table this amendment to make the position clear and to ensure there is no loophole in <Col N="995"/>this section which would allow governors, prison wardens or other prison officials to take advantage of a situation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoannaTuffy"><NameTxt>Ms Tuffy</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I will first deal with amendment No. 44.  This would insert a provision to the effect that nothing in the section could be used to deny a prisoner medical treatment prescribed by a medical practitioner.  At present under the rules, prisoners are provided with access to health care services on a basis equivalent to those in the community covered by the medical card system.  Section 37 would allow for prison rules to provide facilities where necessary for access to elective health care outside the public system.  The prisoner will be responsible for the costs associated with such elective care.  However, provision of health care under the public health system for all prisoners will continue to be funded by the State.  Section 37 merely paves the way for another option.</P>
        <P>All prisoners are entitled to medical card level medical services while in prison.  This provides for something which would be elective health care over and above that level of care.  This section is being included to enable it to happen and not to prohibit it.  It makes it clear that, for instance, private medical treatment over and above what would be available to prisoners as of right would not be obstructed by some requirement that payment be made.  That is what this is about.  The last two lines of the section state that the payment is confined to the full cost of providing the goods or services in question.</P>
        <P>If, for whatever reason, a prisoner decided he or she needed a treatment which was not normally available to prisoners, such as cosmetic surgery or some procedure generally not available to medical card holders, this would permit the governor to allow that to happen provided the charge did not exceed the cost of rendering the service to the prisoner.  It cannot be a question of revenue generation if the payments or deductions cannot exceed the cost of providing the goods or services.  By definition, it is netted out in the section.</P>
        <P>I assure the Senator that there is no question of this being made into some kind of money spinner for the Prison Service.  On the contrary, what is happening here gives prisoners an element of dignity.  For example, if a prisoner was doing an Open University course and had to contact Hong Kong as part of it, that could be done.  However, I will not state that every prisoner has the right at the expense of the State to telephone an academic in Hong Kong for a chat.  I must have this kind of flexibility.  It is only for the ease of prisoners; it is not to put them at a disadvantage.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>As long as the Minister can guarantee that is the case, I am prepared to with<Col N="996"/>draw the amendment.  My concern is that prisoners would not be denied proper medical attention as advised by their medical practitioner.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Amendments Nos. 44 to 46, inclusive, not moved.</P>
        <P>Bill, as amended, received for final consideration.</P>
        <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><TitleTxt>T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Members for their courtesy.  I also thank the Leader for extending the time for the debate.  This Bill has been substantially improved as a result of the careful consideration it has been given line by line.  I am grateful to the House for the way it has dealt with the Bill.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister for accepting a number of amendments and for debating every line of the Bill.  Some of the amendments put forward will improve the Bill.  I also thank his officials for the expeditious manner in which they brought it forward and for their hard work.</P>
        <P>The subject of prisons is always an area of concern.  Now that Christmas is approaching I am sure the media will home in on the number of temporary releases that may be granted.  I understand that because of overcrowding many temporary releases have been already granted in Cork to make way for other prisoners.  Perhaps the Minister will return at a later date to let us know how many people are unlawfully at large having received temporary releases.  This is a matter of concern to the general public.</P>
        <P>The Bill will improve the lot of prisoners and the operation of the prison system.  I am delighted the Minister came to an agreement with prison officers on transfers and other issues.  I hope this will continue and that we will not have to privatise the system.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>I join Senator Cummins in complimenting the Minister and his staff.  This Bill introduces significant and substantive prison reform.  The provision for inquiries into breaches of discipline is timely.  The Minister is right to try to eradicate drugs from our prisons, but that may lead to discipline problems until the systems to deal with it are up and running.</P>
        <P>The provisions of the Bill also demonstrate the Minister&rsquo;s propensity to be accountable.  The Houses of the Oireachtas Commission is up and running and I welcome that we will now have a clear say with regard to the construction or extension of prisons.  This is good and will help the democratic process.</P><Col N="997"/>
        <P>I also welcome the initiation of inspectors and video links etc.  The Bill provides for many improvements in the prison system.  In many ways it illustrates the significant amount of work on the part of the Minister and those in the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform that goes into reforming the Minister&rsquo;s wide remit.  I thank him for bringing the Bill before the Seanad.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister and his officials for the manner in which they listened to the Second Stage and Committee Stage debates.  I thank him also for the number of amendments he has accepted and for those amendments he substituted to deal with concerns expressed in amendments he did not accept.  I thank him for the personal attention he gave to the Bill.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoannaTuffy"><NameTxt>Ms Tuffy</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister and his staff for their work on this Bill and for the amendments he accepted from me.  </P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
 <HtmlBk SectId="4" />
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Electoral (Amendment) Bill 2006:" RHead="Committee and Remaining Stages"> 
    <Title>Electoral (Amendment) Bill 2006: Committee and Remaining Stages. </Title>
        <P>Sections 1 and 2 agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 1: </P>
        <P LI="1">In page 4, subsection (1), lines 27 to 31, to delete paragraph (<i>b</i>) and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;(<i>b</i>) the application shall be&mdash;</P>
        <P LI="3">(i) signed by the applicant, or</P>
        <P LI="3">(ii) if the applicant is unable to write, he or she shall place his or her mark on the application form, or</P>
        <P LI="3">(iii) if the applicant is unable to place his or her mark on the application form, it shall be signed by a person designated for that purpose by the applicant,</P>
        <P FLI="0"><?oasys _is1p8- ?><?oasys _ix ?>and, in any case, the form shall be completed in accordance with the instructions provided thereon;&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0" el="5">This is a technical amendment which allows for someone who cannot write to get on the electoral register.  It proposes on page 4, subsection (1), lines 27 to 31, to delete paragraph (<i>b</i>) and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="2" Just="Left">(<i>b</i>) the application shall be &mdash; signed by the applicant, or if the applicant is unable to write, he or she shall place his or her mark on the application form, or if the applicant is unable to place his or her mark on the application form, it shall be signed by a person designated for that purpose by the applicant, and, in any case, the form shall be completed <Col N="998"/>in accordance with the instructions provided thereon.</P>
        <P FLI="0">Perhaps a peace commissioner or somebody else could sign.  There are only a few people who cannot sign or make their mark, but this amendment should be accepted to provide for them.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><TitleTxt>Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>I am at something of a loss to understand the basis for the amendment.  The provision as it stands provides under section 3(1)(b) that the application form must be either signed by the prisoner or if the prisoner is unable to sign, the applicant can make a mark which somebody will witness.  Therefore, the provision exists already.  I fail to understand how a situation would arise whereby somebody would be in prison and not be able to make his or her mark.  I understand a person in prison might not be literate, but it is unlikely that somebody would be so incapacitated that he or she could not make some mark.</P>
        <P>I apologise I had to leave the Seanad when the Bill was being discussed on Second Stage and did not get the opportunity to make this point.  This provision is not appropriate for a person who requires specialised medical or other care.  I am convinced the existing arrangements are sufficiently flexible to take into account all the circumstances we can foresee.  A person can sign or make a mark.  The amendment goes a step too far as the provision concerns only the completion of the form and not the actual voting.  The point is the amendment has no great practical impact.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Does it involve just the application form?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes, the application form to get on the register.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>To be clear, the current arrangement is that a person who cannot sign can make a mark.  This covers all the practical situations likely to arise.  We are talking about a person getting on a postal vote system in a prison.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Sections 3 to 9, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">NEW SECTION.</P>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 2 to 5, inclusive, are related and will be discussed together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 10, before section 10, to insert the following new section:</P>
        <P LI="1">&ldquo;10.&mdash;The Act of 1992 is amended by the substitution of the following for section 7:</P><Col N="999"/>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;7.&mdash;(1) A person shall be entitled to be registered as a presidential elector in a constituency if he has reached the age of eighteen years and if he was, on the qualifying date&mdash;</P>
        <P LI="3">(<i>a</i>) a citizen of Ireland, and</P>
        <P LI="3">(<i>b</i>) ordinarily resident in that constituency.</P>
        <P LI="2">(2) A person who reaches the age of eighteen years and is or shall be, on the qualifying date&mdash;&mdash;</P>
        <P LI="3">(<i>a</i>) a citizen of Ireland, and</P>
        <P LI="3">(<i>b</i>) ordinarily resident in that constituency,</P>
        <P FLI="0"><?oasys _is1p8- ?><?oasys _ix ?>shall be automatically registered as a presidential elector in the constituency referred to in paragraph (<i>b</i>), unless he or she instructs the registration authority otherwise.</P>
        <P LI="2">(3) For the purposes of&mdash;</P>
        <P LI="3">(i) the Presidential Elections Acts, 1937 to 1992,</P>
        <P LI="3">(ii) the Referendum Acts, 1942 to 1992, and</P>
        <P LI="3">(iii) this Act,</P>
        <P FLI="0"><?oasys _is2p6- ?><?oasys _ix ?>&lsquo;presidential elector&rsquo; means a person entitled to vote at an election of a person to the office of President of Ireland.</P>
        <P LI="2">(4) In the Presidential Elections Acts, 1937 to 1992 &ldquo;elector&rdquo;, when used alone, means a person described in subsection (1).&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I propose in these amendments that all citizens should be added to the register automatically on turning 18 years of age.  This is something on which we spoke in great detail on Second Stage and it would be a logical and self-regulating proposal.  I have repeatedly called on the Minister to use PPS numbers to update the register which would be the simplest method.  The equivalent of PPS numbers are used in Northern Ireland and the system there works in a very satisfactory manner.  There have been no complaints with regard to registration in the northern part of this island.  The Minister agreed the register here is a mess, a point we cannot move away from.</P>
        <P>The electoral system belongs to the people and one political party should not have dominance over the electorate.  It is the responsibility of the Minister of the day to preserve and enhance it as a driving mechanism for democracy.  It is an important issue.  The various amendments deal with presidential elections, general elections, European elections and local government elections and allow for the automatic registration of voters when they turn 18, which would allow those who do not wish to be on the register to opt out if they wish to do so.</P><Col N="1000"/>
        <P>Registration is not happening.  A person contacted me today to tell me they had been on the register in my county of Longford for the best part of 45 years but were no longer on the register.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>We have all heard such tales.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>That person had submitted a claim form and so on, and checked the Internet, but was not on register.  I told the person I had written on their behalf but nothing happened.  This is what is happening in many cases.  It is not fair that such people will be disenfranchised at the next general election.</P>
        <P>I know others will not make the same effort in this regard.  I am working hard in my constituency.  People think much of the Fine Gael team in the Longford-Westmeath constituency and they are enthusiastic to register to ensure we get two out of the four seats at the next general election.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Why is Fine Gael not showing up in the polls?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>The situation will be three to one in favour of the Opposition.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator must be joking.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CyprianBrady"><NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>We had this discussion on the use of the PPS number on Second Stage.  Given there are 5 million PPS numbers but 3 million people on the register, who will collate the information?  The comparison with Northern Ireland does not stand up, given they started from scratch there.  The Senator knows the problems and issues we have had with regard to the changes we are trying to make to the register at present.  He can imagine the furore that would result if we suggested we should scrap the current register and start from scratch.</P>
        <P>A certain amount of personal responsibility arises in this regard.  God be with the days when we are at school and were taught civics.  One of the first things we were taught was that when a person reached 18, he or she would register to vote.  Unfortunately, over the years that practice has dwindled but there is still a responsibility in this regard.  The present debate has shown that people are interested in registration and have a concern whether they are registered.  If anything good has come from this debate, it is that it has highlighted the effect of not being on the register.  The information coming from the Department is clear.  It included the campaign to &ldquo;have your say&rdquo;, which explained that people are not in a position to complain if they are not registered and do not vote in elections.  As public representatives, that is an issue of which we all have experience.</P>
        <P>A substantial number of foreigners have come to Ireland for employment and so on.  Many of <Col N="1001"/>those are from other EU countries and will eventually be able to vote in local elections, which will give them an opportunity to have their say.  It will be found that many of them take that opportunity, a point we, as Irish people, will have to consider.   The amendments do not help the situation.  The Bill is framed correctly at present.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>We can belch all we like, give out about the personnel on councils and all the rest, but for the first time since I have been involved in the electoral process, somebody has taken the matter of the electoral register by the scruff of the neck and decided to do something about it.  While I might not like how some of it is unfolding owing to the slowness of council officials to believe the Minister with regard to third parties &mdash; people are quick to blame the Minister &mdash; his guidelines stated we were not to accept recommendations from third parties.  The Minister said we should authenticate them, and it will then be seen how right they are.  The amendments would have people from EU countries such as Poland, Slovakia and the Czech Republic, who have PPS numbers, on the register although they cannot vote in general elections.  On my rounds, I have told many Poles to register for the local elections so they will be able to vote.  However, the amendments do not help the situation.</P>
        <P>Under legislation it is the duty of county councils to enforce the correct register.  Senator Bannon&rsquo;s county council is a wonderful one, which has been chaired by his party for many years.  The council must have been very slothful in performing its duties when it did not tackle the register.  I accept the amendments are well-intentioned but they would mean that 2 million more people than are on the register would have the right to vote, including those of other nationalities who should be entitled to vote in local but not in general or presidential elections.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator probably missed the point.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>No, I did not.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>The amendments refer to the automatic registration of voters, which is a matter we should simplify for local authorities.  We live in an era with modern systems of communication which can simplify the registration process.  This should be done rather than going around, knocking on doors.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I did not know the Senator had a problem going around, knocking on doors.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>At present, people leave home at 6 a.m. and do not return home until 8 p.m. or 9 p.m.  Local authorities work normal hours and we do not expect their staff to work more than the normal nine-to-five hours which they do.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>They are out at night.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1002"/>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>People are away from their homes all day, including in Dublin.  In recent days a woman told me she spent four hours in a traffic jam.  She left Dublin at 4.15 p.m. and did not get home until almost 9 p.m.  That is the fault of the Government, which is responsible for jams throughout the city.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>We are talking about the electoral register.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>There are traffic jams throughout the country.  People are not at home when public representatives call owing to the neglectful way our transport system, including the public transport system, operates.  I want a simpler system of automatic electoral registration, which the amendments call for.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I am surprised the Senator does not like knocking on doors.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator O&rsquo;Rourke, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Bannon said he does not like knocking on doors.  How awful.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I did not say that.  I said one cannot expect staff of local authorities to knock on doors outside their normal working hours.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CyprianBrady"><NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>Yet they do so.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>I am delighted the Senator has given me the opportunity to touch on a number of points.  There is no silver bullet solution to preparing an electoral register.  A quote I made in the other House pointed out that one of the international bodies that considers this area states the most difficult and intractable area, and the one most fraught with difficulties, is the preparation of the electoral roll.</P>
        <P>It is important to deal with the specific points.  A view seems to have taken hold that somehow the use of PPS numbers is a simple way of drafting the electoral register.  The unfortunate truth is that this is not so, for the following reasons.  First, there are well in excess of 5 million PPS numbers.  Second, PPS numbers are frequently given to people who are under the age of majority, or the age at which they can vote.  Third, PPS numbers are not directly related to one&rsquo;s address so there is no way of automatically relating one&rsquo;s PPS number to the place where one should be entitled to vote.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>We would not know where the person is from.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>Exactly.  I have changed my address several times, as many of us have done.  There is no automatic way for the PPS number system to note that one has changed one&rsquo;s address, or moved in or out of the country.  I accept that Senator Bannon&rsquo;s amendments are well-<Col N="1003"/>intended, but they are simply not practical.  They would not work for the reasons I have given.</P>
        <P>Over 250,000 people from the ten new EU member states have been added to the PPS number system since 1 May 2004.  Some of them have come to this country, worked for six or seven months and left again.  Such people do not necessarily stay at the same address.  If they are over the age of 18, they are entitled to be on the register of electors and to vote in certain elections, although not in D&aacute;il elections, referendums or presidential elections.  The idea that the PPS number system can be used to solve this problem is false and mistaken.  If it was operating successfully elsewhere, it would be operating here.</P>
        <P>The North of Ireland has been mentioned on several occasions in the context of this debate.  The authorities there stood down the entire register of electors in that jurisdiction, in effect, as Senator Brady said.  They then invested tens of millions of pounds in the development of a new register.  At the end of that process, approximately 85% of people in Northern Ireland over the age of 18 were registered.  There was chaos because hundreds of thousands of people had been disenfranchised.</P>
        <P>The fascinating and attractive proposition that people should be automatically registered to vote when they reach the age of 18 has been made by some speakers.  Such a system could not be brought into operation, however, for practical reasons.  Even if we had a device, such as some form of tracking system, which would allow such records to be kept, we would still need a debate on the concept of compulsory registration.  As the issue does not arise &mdash; we do not have such a tracking mechanism &mdash; it is an argument for another day.</P>
        <P>I was born in one part of County Wexford, but I spent most of my early life in another house in a different part of that county before moving to a third place.  I subsequently moved to seven or eight addresses in Dublin before I moved to three addresses in County Wicklow.  I mention that to illustrate the fact that most people change addresses several times during their lives.  How could the automatic registration process be secured in that context?  Who would tell who what and when?  If a person who was born in Senator Bannon&rsquo;s home county is living in Dublin by the time he or she reaches the age of 18, how would the system work at that time to ensure that the person is automatically registered to vote?  It would be difficult to put in place a system that would track automatically every citizen from the moment of his or her birth to the moment he or she turns 18.</P>
        <P>While this proposition is theoretically attractive, there are real and practical reasons for opposing it.  Which registration authority would receive the information leading to automatic registration?  How would the process be triggered?  This country does not have a system of <Col N="1004"/>personal identification that tracks people automatically from the cradle to the grave.  There is an argument for providing for a national identity paper, or a national identity number.  Even if we had such a number, we would still have huge practical difficulties in tracking people through different stages of their lives.  Automatic registration would probably work if a large proportion of the population was static, but that is not the case.</P>
        <P>I have never subscribed to the argument that local authorities, which have legal responsibility for preparing the register of electors, have been lazy or lethargic in fulfilling that duty.  That suggestion is not fair.  When the local authorities argued they did not have enough resources, I doubled their resources for 2006.  When they said there was not enough publicity about registering to vote, I allocated &euro;1 million of taxpayers&rsquo; money for such publicity this year.  If we establish a system of automatic registration, we will have to underpin it with an elaborate system to track the movement of every voter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>We would have to track every movement.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>Ireland does not have such a system.  It exists in some continental countries, at least in theory, but it does not apply here.</P>
        <P>I would like to debunk the myth that some marvellous work was done in Northern Ireland and that it worked.  When the work that was being done there encountered some very serious difficulties, tens of millions of pounds had to be invested in it.  Hundreds of thousands of people in Northern Ireland were disenfranchised at the end of that process.</P>
        <P>Senator Bannon made a final point about people who have submitted their forms since 1 November.  Such people have been unable to use the automatic on-line system &mdash; <i>www.checktheregister.ie</i> &mdash; to track whether they are registered.  The on-line system, including the registration system on the websites of individual local authorities, is based on the draft register, which was published on 1 November.  There is no continuous tracking and updating.  The draft register is not updated every day.  There may be an argument for updating it every day, but such an approach would necessitate the use of a great deal of resources.  I told the local authorities to use their resources to prepare the best register of electors we have ever had.</P>
        <P>It seems to have been forgotten in this debate that over 370,000 people have been added to the register of electors since we started to review it.  Such people had been disenfranchised because they were never on the register.  There have been 507,000 deletions from the register, including 170,000 people who received written notice that they were about to be deleted because the local authorities could not track them.  Tens of thousands of people who are dead were removed from <Col N="1005"/>the register.  The local authorities cannot be blamed for the fact that they were on the register, because until this process was started they had no way of automatically tracking dead people.  Local authority officials were doing their best in this regard, for example by tracking the death notices in local newspapers.  It just did not work.  When the officials in the city of Waterford undertook the review process, they discovered that 1,400 dead people were on the register.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>That is right.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>When one considers that an average of 30,000 people die in Ireland every year, that last year, 90,000 new homes were sold, a further 50,000 homes changed hands and that 45,000 people over the age of 18 came to this country to work, it is likely that there were over 500,000 changes of address in 2005.  I am not sure that all those changes could be tracked by some kind of automatic system without the use of substantial resources.  The only way it could be done would be to give everybody a unique number &mdash; a discrete number like a PPS number &mdash; and then to put in place a system to track automatically their changes of address as they happen.  Such a system would have to differentiate automatically between the different types of people who reach the age of 18.</P>
        <P>Another problem with PPS numbers is that a small number of elderly people who have been through the system do not have PPS numbers.  The cost of producing a system that would automatically edit the details attached to PPS numbers every time a person changes address would be astronomical.  It may well be a good way to proceed, but we need to debate whether we want to provide for a national identification system.</P>
        <P>I would like to mention one set of circumstances in which PPS numbers would be useful.  I have already said I would be disposed to consider this approach in light of further reforms.  When one fills out one&rsquo;s registration form at present, there is no requirement for one to cite one&rsquo;s PPS number.  We may well provide for such a requirement in the future, but it is not currently intended.  While the suggestion that the PPS number system could be converted to be used to update the register of electors is attractive, vast investment would be needed before that could be done.  It has been suggested in the media that we could provide for automatic updating by establishing some sort of automatic national computer.  I have been around for long enough to know that if one really wants to make a mess of something, one should use a great big computer system.</P>
        <P>While a great deal has been written and said about this issue, we should bear in mind that at the end of this process we will have the most up-to-date register we have ever had.  I do not think anyone should be blamed for the fact that the register has been in a disgraceful condition for <Col N="1006"/>the last 20 or 30 years.  When the Irish people went to the polls in 2002 to elect a D&aacute;il, over 330,000 people who should not have been on the register of electors were on it.  I estimate that 250,000 people who should have been on the register were not on it.  We need to consider how such errors arose.</P>
        <P>The local authorities have the legal responsibility to prepare the register but it is not fair to blame the local authorities because, as Senator Brady said, there is personal responsibility on us all in that regard.  We would be the first people to complain if we lived in a Big Brother state where we were all tagged, measured and &ldquo;barcoded&rdquo; through everything, and rightly so.  As a person who has an interest in civil liberties, I would not like the idea of automatic tracking of all movements, which would be costly.  When we take time to analyse it, there is, regrettably, no easy solution to preparing the register.</P>
        <P>I started this process last year and I said then I did not intend to allow the problem with the register to continue because it was a scandal.  <i>The Sunday Tribune</i> did excellent work on this, although I would quibble with it about its methodology, suggesting that there were up to 800,000 errors and omissions on our register.  We cannot accept that.  We must give the councils credit for what they have done.  We must also give them, as I have done, a doubling of the resources to do it this year because it would not be fair to expect councils to put in place that kind of work.  It should be noted that I also gave them the authorisation to employ the census enumerators to do the job.  It would not have been a good idea to try to do that work and the census at the same time for practical reasons.</P>
        <P>I ask the Senator to accept my word that if the PPS number was the magic bullet I would have gone for it as someone who has some technical interests but it would not work.  Sadly, unless we put in place an automatic tracking system for every citizen from the cradle to the grave, it will not work.  That happens in France.  When someone moves to a new area in France they are supposed to register.  We have not done that here and until we do, we cannot do what is proposed.  I regret I cannot accept the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister is the first Minister to admit, albeit indirectly, that the Government is in power by default when he said the register has been a disgrace for the past 30 years and accepted there were many anomalies and problems with it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator&rsquo;s party should have been in power then.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>They got into Government by some form of default.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator must have been very slow off the mark.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1007"/>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>On another issue, the Minister said there are a number of elderly people who do not have PPS numbers.  When a person reaches the age of 70 he or she automatically qualifies for a medical card and is required by the Health Service Executive, and prior to that by the health boards, to ensure he or she has a PPS number.  There are people in their 90s, however, who never claimed anything.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>That is right.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>Not everybody in the State has a PPS number, although I do not know of anyone who does not have one.  </P>
        <P Just="Left">I would be concerned about our national security.  The Minister talked about not being able to track everyone.  Some years ago there was a serious default in the Department of Social Welfare to do with people claiming and at the time the Government was able to track people by their PPS numbers.  It is only a myth that people cannot be tracked.  Less than a decade ago evidence was produced in the media that people were collecting pensions in one city and then moving to another city and collecting pensions there.  The Government told us at the time that it had addressed that problem by tracing people through their PPS numbers.  I would be concerned about our national security if it remained the case that the Minister was unable to track the movements of certain people.  I would be concerned also if people were still ripping off the State in various forms if they cannot be traced from one part of the country to another.  The Minister said a person born in Wicklow, Longford or Westmeath but who may be living in Dublin cannot be tracked down.  I ask the Minister to examine in the future the idea of automatically putting people on the register of electors.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>As someone who is from Waterford city, I was surprised to hear that the names of more than 1,400 people who had died were still on the register.  I can understand how it can happen but the large number was surprising.</P>
        <P>Will the Minister indicate if the council field officers who went out to many areas revisit those areas after the draft register was compiled or did that happen in some areas and not in others?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>The responsibility for the field work lies with the councils.  I recognised that this was a huge task for councils, and I appreciate that councils are working very hard.  For all the negatives one hears about local government, much good work is going on in the local government sector.  I would not blame a small city council like Waterford for the names of 1,400 people who have died being on the register.  It should not have happened.  Incidentally, the Senator will be interested to know that Waterford city has the lowest proportion of registration to population over 18, at approximately 67%, whereas in other <Col N="1008"/>parts of the country it is 97%.  We must come up with an explanation for that.  It may be that people are living on the outskirts of the metropolitan area where there are issues about boundaries and so on.</P>
        <P>I make the point to Senator Bannon that there is no automatic registration of people&rsquo;s addresses.  If we did what Senator Bannon is proposing, we would create something equivalent to the automatic system of registration with one&rsquo;s local authority which applies in law in parts of the Continent.  We would have to have a debate before we go in that direction.  It is a different issue from the voting register.  The voting register is a compilation of people who are over 18 collected in a particular area at a particular time.  If we are to go the direction suggested by the Senator, we would have to have a different debate.</P>
        <P>Senator Cummins made the point that the guidelines were universal.  That was one of the strange findings I made when I decided I would tackle this long-running problem.  Senator Cummins made a good point.  When I raised the issue first and we began to have discussions about it, I discovered to my amazement that no common system was adopted from local authority to local authority.  Over the years and through generations, each local authority went about it its own way.  They went about their business because legally the responsibility of preparing the register lies with the councils and, quite correctly, the Ministers were not interfering with or micro-managing the work of any individual council, which would be wrong.  One of the reasons for the anomalies, and there were different levels of registration from place to place, was that different principles and guidelines were put in place.  We prepared a set of guidelines which the City and County Managers&rsquo; Association and its representatives signed off on to ensure a common approach was taken for the first time to preparing the register.</P>
        <P>Senator Cummins asked if there were two levels of visit.  The answer is &ldquo;yes&rdquo;.  The specific instructions to the enumerators were that they were to take the register and check houses.  If they found people were not at home, they were to put the written notices in the letter-boxes.  If they could not track the people they were told they had to write a letter to those households.  It is extraordinary that when we do something progressive in this country people fall on our heads because they do not take the time to listen to what was done.  When people were crossed off the register previously, they did not get letters informing them of that.  They will on this occasion.</P>
        <P>What is unique now is that the councils have not just the staff to do the field work but the staff to do the back office work, which is the major part of compiling the register.  They sent out 170,000 letters.  Analysis of those letters, and analysis I have done also because I visited a few estates to check them out&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1009"/>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>What did the letters state?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>They stated that the occupant had until 9 December to contact the council indicating he or she was off the register.  Those letters went out in early November.  The response to those letters has been huge; replies to 20% to 30% of them are being received.  That does not mean the remainder are disenfranchised.  Some of the remainder of those 170,000 are people who have changed address.  I did an analysis of a number of estates in Arklow, a town that has not experienced a great deal of change until relatively recently, and the field work was uncannily accurate because the field workers were able to trace people who had changed address.  These people&rsquo;s names at their old addresses were removed from the register but prior to that being done, the field workers followed the guidelines correctly.  They wrote to inform the elector, say, Joe Bloggs at No. 6,  XYZ Street, that he would be taken off the register.  The fact that Joe or Josephine Bloggs is now living up the road in a new estate means that he or she is properly registered.  </P>
        <P>There is no simple way of compiling the register properly other than field work.  We do not have a system of automatically tracking every citizen through his or her entire life.  I have changed my address more than a dozen times and there is no way of automatically recording a change of address on the register.  I had an interesting experience recently in tracing prize bonds I bought when I was 21.  I had to think back to where I was living when I was 21.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Did the Minister win some money?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>No, unfortunately.</P>
        <P>With regard to Senator Cummins&rsquo;s question on whether the field work has been followed up, I issued a circular letter to councils advising them that when I checked the list of deletions in respect of cases in my area &mdash; a list which Senator O&rsquo;Rourke has not yet received which I regret because local authorities should operate within the spirit of this process &mdash; I noted that in some areas there were a disproportionate number of deletions.  For example, in one housing estate of 100 houses, there may be 30 deletions, in another housing estate of a similar size, there may be 30 deletions, which is proportionate, but in another housing estate of a similar size there may be 60 deletions.  Clearly, there could not be twice the number of deletions in one estate proportionate to the number in another estate of a similar size.  In areas where a disproportionate level of deletions have been recorded, we have told the field workers to return to those areas to check the register.</P>
        <P>I, like Senator Bannon, am diligent in the matter of the voting register.  One of my field workers, a good hardworking cumann member, was in Wolfe Tone Square this morning and dis<Col N="1010"/>covered council staff were doing precisely what Senator Cummins asked about.  Where disproportionate deletions have been recorded councils should exercise prudence.</P>
        <P>I wish to mention another matter to Senator Bannon, although my colleagues might not agree with my mentioning it to him but I will mention it to him because I like him and I want to give him every possible opportunity&mdash;&mdash;-</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister likes Senator Bannon.  That is good.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>I do, he is a nice man.  We also gave an instruction to councils that before they deleted, for example, the name of a person from the register living as a tenant in a council house, they should use the other resources available to them.  Where they had access to other databases, they should have been prudent and used those, particularly in areas where a disproportionate level of deletions have been recorded.  </P>
        <P>Regrettably, there is not a simple way of compiling the electoral register.  To the credit of local government, if there was a simple way, it would have been done.  We can all point the finger and lay blame but that is what people find maddening about politicians.  We know that for a variety of regions the register has been a mess for years.  We are all complicit in that.  The stories concerning the register told to those of us who canvassed in the by-elections in Meath and Kildare were appalling.  Whole areas were disenfranchised.  That is unacceptable.  If I were the kind of Minister who wanted to play it safe, I would leave the register unchanged as it was previously.  However, none of us would respect democracy if we know that something so fundamental is wrong and did not try to correct it.</P>
        <P>Senator Bannon made a point, which has been made by Deputy O&rsquo;Dowds on several occasions, namely, that the register belongs to the people.  That is true and the people should take a great interest in it, which is a positive outcome of this process.  We need an electoral commission, but it will not be put in place before the next general election.  I will call for ideas in that respect.  Nobody on any side of the House should claim that he or she knows everything.  We should listen to each other, learn from that experience and put in place a register that will work.  That is the way I would approach this.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>May I respond?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We have given this section a good airing.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>The county register records the registration of all births, marriages and deaths.  Every church body, whether it be the Roman Catholic Church, the Church of Ireland or the Methodist Church must make such registrations. <Col N="1011"/> Has the electoral register been cross-checked against parish registers?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Until this process started, the straight answer to that question is &ldquo;No, they were not&rdquo;.  When the guidelines were being put in place I created a link between the register of births and deaths and each council office.  Now when a registration form indicating a person is dead is received in the central office in Dublin, an automatic electronic list is passed to each council indicating a Mr. X or Mrs. X died in a council area.  Council staff will then use that information to delete the name from the register.  They will have the name, address and the date of birth of the person, which will allow them to automatically correct the register by deleting that person&rsquo;s name.  It is extraordinary that was not done previously.  This development is a positive outcome to this process.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Amendments Nos. 3 to 5, inclusive, not moved.</P>
        <P>Section 10 agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 11.</P>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 7 to 12, inclusive, are related to amendment No. 6, therefore, amendments Nos. 6 to 12, inclusive, may be discussed together by agreement.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 6:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 11, subsection (1), between lines 25 and 26, to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;(<i>a</i>) in paragraph 4, &ldquo;20th December&rdquo; for &ldquo;25th November&rdquo;,&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">Amendments Nos. 7 to 10, inclusive, are dependent on the acceptance of amendment No. 6.  It proposes extending the deadline to the end of January.  The Minister extended the deadline by a mere two weeks following much pressure, but that is not enough time.  I have spoken to the staff in various local authorities throughout the country and they are at their wits end trying to amend the draft register by that deadline.  Voting registration is a problem, which is blatantly evident in some areas.  The Minister was made aware of this problem by myself, other spokespersons in this House, local authorities and the media but he refused to act.  He only consented to extend the deadline by a short period at the eleventh hour.</P>
        <P>I have called in recent years for the Minister to act on this matter in time to avoid total confusion.  We now face a situation where thousands of people are at risk of having to go to the revision court to get their name restored to the register of electors in time for next year&rsquo;s general election.  That is not fair.  All I ask the Minister to do is to extend the deadline to the end of January.  This <Col N="1012"/>could and should be done.  We make the rules and regulations.  The decision to extend the date rests with us, the politicians.  I would very much appreciate if the Minister took on board this proposal.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">6 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>It is not acceptable today for the register of electors to be in its current state.  The Minister admitted that today and in the past but it was at the eleventh hour.  He was arrogant about the register in some of his earlier statements to the effect that it was as good as could be expected.  We are only months away from a general election and it is important to ensure the register is correct.  This is typical of how the current Administration operates; it delayed extending the deadline and extended it by only a mere two weeks after much pressure.  The Minister did not do that voluntarily but as a result of pressure brought to bear from the Opposition.</P>
        <P>I am a foot soldier on the ground and I have listened to people and staff who are compiling the register and they want the deadline to be further extended.  The Minister might take on board this proposal and extend the deadline until the end of January.  That is what this amendment seeks.</P>
          </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CyprianBrady"><NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>This issue was discussed at length at the Joint Committee on the Environment, Heritage and Local Government.  The bottom line is that we must have a complete register by 14 February and the next general election will depend on that.  The Minister&rsquo;s extension is to be welcomed and I understand that it was at the behest of a small number of local authorities who were not in a position to provide the required information.  Whether it is the media or the Opposition that is putting pressure on him, this Minister caves in to neither.  The bottom line is that we must have the register in place.  The further one pushes out these deadlines, the less likely the register will be in place.  It is crucial that we get as much of this work done now.  It is open to everyone to apply to go on the supplementary register for the next general election.  We use that fact in my own constituency to encourage people to put themselves forward for the supplementary register.  It is quite a simple process.  They must get it signed by a garda, but that is not an issue for most people, especially if they have nothing to hide.  The bottom line is that we need a register.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I agree.  We could ask for two weeks, another two weeks and another two weeks.  I smile when I see &ldquo;massive U-turn&rdquo; written in the newspapers.  The Minister just responded that an extra few weeks were needed.  I congratulate him for having done that.  Having pressed for and got a couple of weeks, people could ask for another two weeks and another two weeks.</P><Col N="1013"/>
        <?oasys _cl11.7- ?><P>When I left the House a while ago my director of elections called to say that he got a list of the deletions from the county council.  I do not know whether the Minister&rsquo;s magic wand was at work, because I could not get that list for ten days, yet it has now miraculously appeared.  My director of elections was told it was because the council was waiting for the issue to be made law.  If we kept on deleting names, we could be here for a long time.  The election would be upon us and there would be no register at all.</P>
        <P>Every day we go out, we receive more and more names, and one must wonder how they will all fit in.  Senator Brady does not mind, but I find the Garda aspect irksome.  The person who wishes to register must go into the barracks and the garda in charge of the register may not be there, so the person must come back again.  One would want to have a big ambition to get on the electoral register before all those conditions were fulfilled.  However, to push back the date again would be a negation of justice for many people.</P>
        <P Just="Left">There is now a great interest in the electoral register which never existed before.  Ordinary people are now talking about the register all the time.  One woman told me that she found her name on the register after checking the Internet and that she was delighted about that.  People who were not on the register before felt it was the fault of the politician who landed on the person&rsquo;s doorstep.  I think we will have an accurate register.</P>
        <P>Since I have the Minister at close quarters &mdash; close enough, anyway &mdash; I must tell him that I do not agree with the &ldquo;two strikes and you are out&rdquo; policy, for when the enumerator calls to a house twice but there is nobody there.  Senator Bannon is right about that.  People are gone from dawn to dusk in many houses, and if an enumerator calls twice and they are not there, people on the councils are automatically taking them off the register.  It is vital to get the list of deletions so that we can work through that list and put forward the names that should not have been deleted.</P>
        <P>I fully approve of the deletion of the names of those who have passed away.   We know the old adage that dead men do not vote, but unfortunately they did in some areas.  However, the &ldquo;two strikes and you are out&rdquo; policy is harsh.  It all depends on the enumerators.  Some of them are utterly zealous and they wish to follow through on whatever orders they received by the Minister, as translated by the county council.</P>
        <P>People should appreciate that we got the two extra weeks, and much work has gone on in that time.  We had a county council meeting last Friday week and I could not believe that everybody was bent over the pink sheets.  The room was full and everyone had a pink sheet in front of them.  They were ticking, checking and shouting.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1014"/>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I hope the Senator was not striking people off.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>We did if they were dead, or gone to Kildare, Wicklow or one of those places.  There was great work being done and that is what an organisation should be doing.  I do not agree with the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator O&rsquo;Rourke made the point well.  When the register was being drafted previously and the field worker took the view that the person was not there and should not be eligible for the register, the person was struck off and no written notice was given.  This time we gave councils the resources to recruit additional field personnel, and I specified that the councils should recruit the census enumerators as they had been around the houses and they knew different areas very well.  Previously, people got no notice and they would only know that they were off the register when politicians knocked on their door when canvassing.</P>
        <P>I had two complaints about field workers during this process.  One was from a lady who called me when the Mayo versus Dublin football match was being played.  She was incensed because an enumerator had just called to her house trying to check the voting register, which shows that great effort went into this.</P>
        <P>We have a terrible habit in this country of long-fingering everything and not doing anything.  We do things badly because of that.  Deadlines mean nothing and we wait until the last minute to do anything.  At the joint committee meeting on this, I said on several occasions that if I received any request from a local authority for an extension of time, I would look on it sympathetically.  I do not want to put the gun to the head of any local authority.  At the eleventh hour, I got three separate requests from councils for time extensions and I said I would grant them.</P>
        <P>However, our electoral law is not very prudently drafted.  The exact dates are specified in law, which gives a degree of inflexibility.  I had said to the committee that I would grant a request if I got one.  Rather than granting the requests only for the three councils involved, I granted it for every council.  That is why my amendment was introduced, namely, to give everybody the additional chance.</P>
        <P>I do not believe that there is any benefit in putting the date back from 9 December to 20 December.  A number of years ago, the voting register process was brought forward so that it would not coincide with the Christmas period.  Very few people would be thinking about the voting register on 20 December.  Any of those 170,000 people who have got written notices will have made their submissions back to the councils if they are really interested.  I do not believe that <Col N="1015"/>there will be many people five days before Christmas suddenly deciding they should quickly submit forms to the council office.  It is a reasonable enough ploy for the Opposition to put forward, but it does not have practical benefit.</P>
        <P>There is one good reason why we should not do this.  We know that the current voting register was compiled in November 2005.  The current register for 2005-06 was compiled over 12 months ago.  To leave us in a position where that is the only extant register, beyond 15 February, would be an act of political irresponsibility.  I am not anticipating a general election between 15 February and 15 March.  However, it would be politically irresponsible to create a situation where we know the best part of 500,000 names have to be deleted and that some 400,000 people who should be on the register are not.  That is a total of 900,000 deletions or errors.  If we were to allow that to continue, it would be wrong.  There is no practical benefit in extending this further.</P>
        <P>The Senator is concerned about the back office process such as the work of the councils.  The councils will have until 2 January to do the back office work.  It will not be a big deal to sign off on this since everything is on computers these days.  The register will then transmit to the county registers who will have access to the electoral court, as it is called.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>What date will that be? </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>The deadline for the local authorities is 2 January.  The completion date for work on the register will be 12 January.  That gives until 15 February for the hard copy to be produced.  The register, of course, will be published on 1 February.  </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>It will be between  the 1 January&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;and 1 February&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>For the court&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>No, the court will have to complete its work by 12 January. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>So the courts will be in early January, then.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>The courts will all have to be in the early part of January.  Under the existing arrangements they had to be, effectively, the week before Christmas.   One can always say there is never going to be a good time, but the reality is that there is no practical benefit from a further extension.  All that happens is that we do what is normally done in this country, namely, that everything is put on the long finger. </P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1016"/>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Procrastination.  </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>We procrastinate and matters are not improved by doing so.  It would be much better to tell the councils they have until 2 January, that they have the resources and can get the back office work done.  They should therefore get the job done.  Once there is a proper register the big challenge for the politicians to maintain it in that condition.   When we are back in Government, we shall do that. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister is being political now.  I want to come back on a couple of issues.  If the Minister had acted on time and given the resources to the local authorities we should not now be in the mess we are in.  I mentioned on Second Stage that there was a role for the involvement of the local post offices and postal personnel.  Those people are very familiar with who lives where and the residents of particular areas because they visit them on a daily basis.  </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>What about the Asian community, and the numbers of apartments? </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I still feel there is a role for them in carrying out this work in conjunction with other service providers within communities.  It would mean more work for the post offices which would be of use in keeping them open.  As the Minister knows, without making a political point, a quarter of the post offices around the country closed under the term of this Administration.  Local authorities are very prudent, and he knows that.  I was a member of a local authority for 17 or 18 years. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>They are very what? </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>They are very prudent and conscious about taxpayers&rsquo; money.  They hold one meeting per month.  I am told by councillors throughout the country that they tabled motions at these meetings regarding the extension of the deadline.  Unfortunately, they had been expecting action from the Minister and had not anticipated matters reaching the 11th hour.  That is why only three local authorities had time to submit a motion before the deadline.  My local authority as well as Westmeath County Council and several others had tabled motions and were looking for an extension of the time deadline.  Unfortunately, it did not happen. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>It does not matter.  </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Brady referred to another issue.  He said there was no problem about going to Garda stations to get a garda signature. </P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1017"/>
      <Speaker pid="CyprianBrady"><NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>It is just putting matters on the long finger. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>That is all right for those in the cities.  However, it is not true for rural parts of Ireland.  I have to travel 16 miles, but I have transport. However, there are elderly people who depend on public transport, which is not accessible, to visit a Garda station&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CyprianBrady"><NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>It should be possible for a garda to call to a person&rsquo;s house.  </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;in order to sign forms.  That is a serious problem for people in rural areas.  There is no public transport to Granard or several other smaller towns.  If people have to go the Longford, the county town, the garda&iacute; there cannot sign forms for people who are not resident in that immediate area.  That is something the Minister needs to look at.  People must sign in the Garda area in which they reside and this should be reviewed.  For example, people in Ballycarriga, County Westmeath&mdash;&mdash;-</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Deputy Penrose&rsquo;s town. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>If the green man is in operation there, they will be there for an hour.  However, if it is not convenient and they are working, and the garda&iacute; are occupied during normal working hours, they must go to Garda headquarters in Granard to get forms signed.  The same is true of Ballymahon, and I am only referring to the local territory I know.  People in Ballymahon must go to Athlone to get the forms signed.</P>
        <P>It is often not convenient for people to sign, and the Minister should look at this in respect of rural areas because it is a major problem that needs to be addressed.  It is not helped by the poor public transport in such areas.   He should perhaps review matters so that any garda in one&rsquo;s county can sign.  It should not be confined to a particular Garda station.  I know of an elderly woman who, in the run-up to the last local elections, had to get a form signed because her name was not on the register.  She went to a Garda station fairly close to her home.  A garda there said he could not sign the form and that she would have to go to her local Garda station, which was 16 miles away.  Perhaps this is something the Minister could look at.</P>
        <P>Hands off the rural post offices.  The Minister should give them a role in this area.  It would be an extra service they could provide, and it would help to keep the rural post offices open.  They are a vibrant part of the rural community and it is important that he does what he can.  I see that Senator O&rsquo;Rourke agrees with me on that.  It is important they be kept open.  We have called for more work for them, and this is an ideal oppor<Col N="1018"/>tunity, which will also give them a role in maintaining the register.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>As a former postal worker, I tend to agree with the Senator.  There is a small point to be considered, however, namely, that we could not take the job away from the councils without causing some difficulties.  I did not exclude the idea of postmen and postwomen being recruited.  However, there were some industrial or human relations issues that had to be dealt with. </P>
        <P>To return to the general point, there is no benefit in further extensions.  We must start being decisive in this country in terms of getting things done, setting up timetables and working on them.  With regard to the supplementary register, this only kicks in when all of this process is over&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The election has started.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;and that is a cogent reason for people getting on the register now.  The Senator will be surprised to learn that for the last general election, 50,000 people used the device of the supplementary register.  The supplementary register was introduced because people were changing houses, and also because young people were reaching 18 and being disenfranchised, in effect, for long periods of time.  However, there is no purpose or benefit to continually pushing out this.  One must put in the effort and get the job done well, which is what is happening.  Councils have until 2 January to carry out all their back office work.  They have more resources than ever before and this year a sum of &euro;12 million has been put into this task.</P>
        <P>While Senator Bannon made the point that councils do not have sufficient resources, I must disagree because councils determine their own budgets.  Councils that were serious about democracy would devote sufficient money to preparing the register.  As for the registration process, I am critical of councils in one respect, namely, their failure to assign sufficient priority to this task.  Preparing the electoral roll, which is fundamental to democracy, is one of the councils&rsquo; most important tasks.</P>
        <P>I was somewhat angry with one or two councils that stated they lacked resources to so do.  I made the point to one or two council officials that, while there are never problems as far as going to the St. Patrick&rsquo;s Day parade in New York is concerned, there is something of a problem when it comes to doing the democratic thing in Ireland.  As I did not wish to quibble with the councils this year, I doubled the amount of money.  No Minister in the history of the State has ever put resources into this issue.  Although Ireland will have the best register it has ever had by the conclusion of this process, it will not be perfect.  No country in the world has a perfect register <Col N="1019"/>because as soon as one finishes preparing one&rsquo;s register, people will die or move house and it goes out of date.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Or there is a tsunami.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>No one will be disenfranchised.  The supplementary register will be available to every citizen from 9 December up to the 15th day before voting.  There is adequate capacity to get on the register.</P>
        <P>The Senator is correct to state that going to a Garda station is more inconvenient than simply filling out a form.  However, the Senator must be cognisant of another issue, of which his party is aware.  If one has a supplementary system in which people add themselves to the voting register, some protections must be put in place to ensure electoral fraud is not intended.</P>
        <P>As the Senator can see, the issues are not that simple.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="UlickBurke"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. U. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>Is the Senator pressing the amendment?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>Two weeks will not be sufficient for local authorities to get it right.  I have received representations from local authority staff nationwide.  I am a former general secretary of the Local Authority Members Association and I had built up networks with local authorities.</P><Col N="1020"/>
        <P>On another issue, I am disappointed the Minister stated that local authorities are not introducing enough stealth taxes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Who mentioned stealth taxes?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>Local authorities are forced to introduce stealth taxes because they are not given sufficient funding by the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government.  A meeting was held last night in Roscommon&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Bannon should confine himself to the amendments under discussion.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;at which 1,500 people turned up to protest against the water charges being imposed by local authorities.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Bannon, the House is not dealing with that issue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>Planning charges are being introduced by local authorities.  The Minister blamed local authorities.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>He did not.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>He did.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator intend to press amendment No. 6?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment put.</P><Col N="1019"/>
      <Vote>
        <Result>The Seanad divided: T&aacute;, 12; N&iacute;l, 27.</Result>
        <YHeading>T&aacute;</YHeading><Col N="1019"/>
        <YesVote pid="JamesBannon">Bannon, James.</YesVote>
       <?oasys _mv-2- ?><YesVote pid="PaulBradford">Bradford, Paul.</YesVote>
        <?oasys _mv-2- ?><YesVote pid="PaddyBurke">Burke, Paddy.</YesVote>
        <?oasys _mv-2- ?><YesVote pid="UlickBurke">Burke, Ulick.</YesVote>
        <?oasys _mv-2- ?><YesVote pid="PaulCoghlan">Coghlan, Paul.</YesVote>
        <?oasys _mv-2- ?><YesVote pid="NoelCoonan">Coonan, Noel.</YesVote><Col N="1020"/>
        <YesVote pid="MauriceCummins">Cummins, Maurice.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="FrankFeighan">Feighan, Frank.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrianHayes">Hayes, Brian.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="KathleenOMeara">O&rsquo;Meara, Kathleen.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JohnPaulPhelan">Phelan, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JoannaTuffy">Tuffy, Joanna.</YesVote>
        <NHeading><Col N="1019"/>N&iacute;l</NHeading><Col N="1019"/>
        <NoVote pid="CyprianBrady">Brady, Cyprian.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MichaelBrennan">Brennan, Michael.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PeterCallanan">Callanan, Peter.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="BrendanDaly">Daly, Brendan.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TimDooley">Dooley, Timmy.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="GeraldineFeeney">Feeney, Geraldine.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Hayes, Maurice.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="BrendanKenneally">Kenneally, Brendan.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TonyKett">Kett, Tony.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MichaelKitt">Kitt, Michael P.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TerryLeyden">Leyden, Terry.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DonLydon">Lydon, Donal J.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DrMartinMansergh">Mansergh, Martin.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JohnMinihan">Minihan, John.</NoVote><Col N="1020"/>
        <NoVote pid="PaschalMooney">Mooney, Paschal C.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PatMoylan">Moylan, Pat.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DavidNorris">Norris, David.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FrancisOBrien">O&rsquo;Brien, Francis.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MaryORourke">O&rsquo;Rourke, Mary.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="LabhrasOMurchu">&Oacute; Murch&uacute;, Labhr&aacute;s.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="AnnOrmonde">Ormonde, Ann.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="">Quinn, Feargal.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="ShaneRoss">Ross, Shane.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="EamonScanlon">Scanlon, Eamon.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JimWalsh">Walsh, Jim.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MaryMWhite">White, Mary M.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DiarmuidWilson">Wilson, Diarmuid.</NoVote>
        <Tellers><Col N="1019"/>Tellers: T&aacute;, Senators Bannon and Cummins; N&iacute;l, Senators Minihan and Moylan.</Tellers><Col N="1019"/>
        <?oasys _cl11.7- ?><Decision><?oasys _is0p10- ?>Amendment declared lost.</Decision>
      </Vote>
        <P el="3">Amendments Nos. 7 to 12, inclusive, not moved.</P><Col N="1020"/>
        <P el="5">Sections 11 to 20, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
        <P el="5">Title agreed to.</P><Col N="1021"/>
        <P el="5">Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
        <P el="5">Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><TitleTxt>Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the House for the interesting contributions here today.  As ever, I thank Senator Bannon for his interesting contributions.  He shares my passionate interest in democracy and, of course, in returning a good Government to office next June.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CyprianBrady"><NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister and his officials for bringing the Bill through the House.  This worthy legislation has been dealt with very efficiently. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesBannon"><NameTxt>Mr. Bannon</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I also wish to thank the Minister and his officials for bringing the Bill before us.  It is important that it be enacted as soon as possible.  We all look forward to the general election and this Bill, when enacted, will ensure that as many eligible voters as possible are on the electoral register.  Hopefully, the Minister will take on board my comments, especially the proposal that any member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na can sign a form to ensure that a person can be included on the supplementary register.  This matter needs to be examined because currently it may be difficult, particularly for those in remote rural areas, to access a garda.  If a person is properly identified to a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, however, they should be facilitated in adding their name to the supplementary register.  The Minister should ensure that will happen.</P>
        <P>I again thank the Minister and his officials for bringing the Bill before the House.  I wish him well.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenOMeara"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Meara</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CyprianBrady"><NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment" RHead="Matters"> 
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. </Title>
  </MainHeading>
  <Line /><MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Outdoor Education" RHead="Centres"> 
    <Title>Outdoor Education Centres. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to share time with Senator O&rsquo;Brien, who represents the same constituency as I do.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
	<P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>The Tanagh outdoor education centre was established in 1992 by County Monaghan Vocational Education Committee.  It <Col N="1022"/>is situated in Tanagh, on the Cavan-Monaghan border just outside Cootehill.  It is set in the heart of the Dromore water system, adjoining Dartrey forest.  The centre is located 112 km from both Dublin and Belfast.  The original building served as a residence for the land steward of the nearby Dartrey estate, later becoming a seminary and later still an army barracks.  Since 1992, it has served as a centre for outdoor pursuits, under the auspices of County Monaghan VEC.  </P>
        <P>I have tabled this Adjournment matter because the lease on this building comes to an end in September 2007.  In any event, the existing building is coming to the end of its useful life and a new centre is required.  In 2004, there were 6,059 visitors to the centre and that figure rose to 8,691 in 2005.  So far this year, there have been 10,000 visitors to the centre.  Some 2,000 potential visitors had to be refused because the centre did not have the capacity to deal with them.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Coillte has agreed to sell County Monaghan VEC five acres of land for &euro;106,000.  The site is located in the centre of Dartrey forest, which comprises 2,000 acres of afforestation.  The Tanagh centre serves a useful purpose for communities both in Counties Cavan and Monaghan, as well as other counties North and South of the Border.  It is a vitally necessary piece of infrastructure.  In September this year, I understand that County Monaghan VEC received a letter from the Minister for Education and Science.  The letter stated that capital investment in the outdoor education centre at Tanagh, or indeed any other education centres, is likely to fall into a band 4 rating, which is not a high priority, in dispersing the Department&rsquo;s capital allocation.  The letter stated that, accordingly, the Department is not in a position to approve the proposed expenditure in this regard.  This is unacceptable, however.  County Monaghan VEC would like permission to purchase from Coillte the five acres needed for the future expansion of the Tanagh outdoor education centre.</P>
        <P>I wish to pay tribute to the hard-working committee in charge of the centre, as well as its 18 dedicated volunteers.  The committee managing the centre represents the whole community in that area.  I urge the Minister to do his best to accede to these demands.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancisOBrien"><NameTxt>Mr. O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>Like Senator Wilson, I wish to impress upon the Minister for Education and Science the importance of this venture on the Cavan-Monaghan border.  As Senator Wilson stated, the Tanagh outdoor education centre has been operating there since 1992 and has grown to a position where it attracted 10,000 visitors this year.  Over 2,000 others were turned away from it in 2006 due to a lack of capacity.  Large numbers of young people are visiting the centre annually.  The Tanagh centre is a great asset for vocational <Col N="1023"/>schools in counties Monaghan and Cavan, as well as schools across the Border in the neighbouring counties of Armagh and Fermanagh.  It would be a shame to see it being closed down at the end of 2007 because the Minister will not allow the purchase of the five-acre Coillte site for &euro;100,000.  Such an expenditure is quite small given the Department&rsquo;s overall budget, so I am surprised that the Minister cannot see her way to approving this purchase.  I hope she will re-think the matter and support the project in order to be fair to everybody.  Over the past 15 years, a huge effort has been put into running the centre, which has been of great benefit to the community.  </P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator Wilson mentioned the Dromore water system, which is renowned both in Cavan and Monaghan.  It flows through the town of Ballybay, on to Dartrey and into the Erne in County Fermanagh.  In recent years, many young people have made great use of the Tanagh facility.  They have enjoyed various outdoor pursuits there, including water-skiing.  I have seen the facilities at first hand, as has Senator Wilson.  I live closer to the area than the Senator but, nevertheless, I am delighted that he has raised this matter on the Adjournment.  It was refused a few weeks ago, but I am glad that the Cathaoirleach accepted this matter for discussion today.  I support the proposal and I hope the Minister will see fit to allow the VEC to purchase the site from Coillte.</P>
    <HtmlBk SectId="5" />
    </Speaker><!--Fix-->
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><TitleTxt>Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Senators for making a coherent case in respect of Tanagh outdoor education centre.  I apologise for the absence of the Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Hanafin, who is unable to attend the debate.  As Senators will learn, I have a personal interest in this matter.  </P>
        <P>Outdoor education centres, such as the centre in Tanagh, County Monaghan, have been developed by vocational education committees in the interests of providing outdoor education programmes to enhance the quality of the educational experience for young people.  The core areas that outdoor education programmes aim to facilitate include fostering greater environmental awareness; breaking down of social barriers and prejudices; developing personal competencies and enhancement of life skills; and promoting healthy lifestyles.</P>
        <P>The VEC outdoor education centres cater mainly for primary and post-primary students, including young people from disadvantaged backgrounds, third-level students, youth groups, special needs groups and adults.  During periods when centres are not fully utilised for educational purposes, school holidays in particular, they generate additional income by providing courses on a commercial basis for the leisure and tourism <Col N="1024"/>market.  More than 100,000 activity days are provided by the outdoor education centres for school pupils.</P>
        <P>The nine recognised VEC outdoor education centres are Gartan, County Donegal; Achill, County Mayo; Petersburg, County Galway; Burren, County Clare; Kinsale, County Cork; Shielbaggan, County Wexford; Birr, County Offaly; Kilfinane, County Limerick; and Cappanalea, County Kerry.  A further three centres, Tanagh in County Monaghan, Baltinglass in County Wicklow &mdash; hence my personal interest in this issue &mdash; and Schull in County Cork, are not recognised by the Department.</P>
        <P>Funding was originally approved for the outdoor education centres on the basis that they would be self-financing and their financial activities would be separate from the overall VEC finances.  Accordingly, the Department&rsquo;s annual grants are contributory in nature and the allocations are made mainly towards the core staffing costs involved in running the centres.  The funding provided by the Department of Education and Science for the centres, including Tanagh outdoor education centre, has increased considerably in recent years and now stands at approximately &euro;2 million annually.  Tanagh outdoor education centre has also benefited from a significant increase in its allocation, which has been increased from &euro;98,000 in 1998 to &euro;130,000 this year.</P>
        <P>I understand County Monaghan VEC has requested that formal recognition be given by the Department to the Tanagh outdoor education centre.  Discussions have taken place between the Department and the VEC in the matter and the Department anticipates that once governance, management and financial arrangements to apply in the centre have been finalised with the VEC, the matter of the recognition of Tanagh outdoor education centre can be addressed.</P>
        <P>I thank Senators for raising this matter.  I will pass on their positive comments about the role of Tanagh outdoor education centre to the Minister for Education and Science, specifically their point that a bargain appears to be on offer.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Hospitals Building" RHead="Programme"> 
    <Title>Hospitals Building Programme.</Title>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I was momentarily confused and wondered whether I was to discuss with him the issue of Dingle-Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is.  I realise, however, that we are both here in a different capacity, namely, to discuss the 14-bed extension to Kenmare Community Hospital in County Kerry.  Unfortunately, despite the long-standing commitment to build the facility, we have had a litany of broken promises.  The extension was a priority of the former Southern Health Board in 2000 and two Deputies from the Kerry South constituency, Deputy Healy-Rae and the Minister for Arts, <Col N="1025"/>Sport and Tourism, Deputy O&rsquo;Donoghue, published literature prior to the 2002 general election in which they made commitments to the project.</P>
        <P>I am confused because Deputy Moynihan-Cronin, speaking in County Kerry recently, indicated the project would not proceed.  For this reason, I look forward to clarification from the Minister.  As I indicated, the project has been put on the long finger despite being a priority in 2000, if not earlier.  I was a member of a deputation which met the Minister for Health and Children, Deputy Harney, last June.  Deputy Healy-Rae was also present, having helped organise the meeting, and Deputy Moynihan-Cronin was either present or represented at the meeting, which we left with high hopes.  I look forward to the Minister enlightening me on the position regarding the project which, I hope, will be delivered.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>Dingle-Daingean U&iacute; Ch&uacute;is is another issue which lands on my shoulders.  </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I have several more subjects I could raise with the Minister. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>I am pleased to have the opportunity to respond on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Health and Children, Deputy Harney, who apologises for her absence.  I thank the Deputy for raising the question as it provides me with an opportunity to outline to this House the current position with regard to the extension to Kenmare Community Hospital in County Kerry.</P>
        <P>It is the Government&rsquo;s policy to maintain older people in dignity and independence at home in accordance with their wishes while, at the same time, providing high quality residential care for older people when living at home is no longer possible.  The Government&rsquo;s commitment to the development of a comprehensive range of services for older people has been clearly demonstrated by the significantly increased resources made available in recent years. From 1997 to 2005, inclusive, additional spending on health care services for older people amounted to more than &euro;302 million.  In the budget package for 2006 additional revenue funding of &euro;150 million in full year costs was allocated for services for older people.</P>
        <P>The prioritisation of all health capital developments is a matter for the Health Service Executive under the Health Act 2004.  The HSE has advised that the provision of a 14-bed extension to Kenmare Community Hospital has been considered for inclusion in its multiannual capital programme for the period 2006 to 2010.  The Kenmare project involves the re-planning of existing accommodation and addition of new accommodation to provide an integrated 40-bed <Col N="1026"/>hospital to meet current standards of care.  The HSE has completed a draft accommodation brief for the enlargement of the hospital.</P>
        <P>The HSE has confirmed that this project did not commence in 2006 due to competing demands for capital funding, including other significant capital projects in County Kerry which required investment in 2006.  However, it has also advised that the capital programme will be reviewed and reprioritised annually.  Depending on available resources and the progress of other projects, proposed developments such as the extension to Kenmare Community Hospital will be reconsidered by the HSE for inclusion in its revised future capital programme.  The programme for 2007 is due to be submitted by the HSE to the Department shortly.  I will ensure the case made by Senator Coghlan is brought to the Minister&rsquo;s attention.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrankFeighan"><NameTxt>Mr. Feighan</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House and thank him for agreeing to discuss this issue.  The provision of a community hospital in Ballinamore was promised 20 years ago and the people of the town are anxious to secure a state-of-the-art facility.  Given that the nearest hospital is 17 miles from the town, a new facility similar to a day hospital would be welcome.  Has progress been made on this vexed issue?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
	<P>I am pleased to have the opportunity to reply on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Health and Children, Deputy Harney.  I thank the Deputy for raising this matter as it provides me with an opportunity to outline to the House the position regarding the community hospital in Ballinamore, County Leitrim.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">7 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>In 2001 the former North Western Health Board carried out a consultation and planning process for service developments in the south Leitrim area.  An assessment of utilisation of residential services in south Leitrim by older people, including physical infrastructure, formed a core part of the process.  The recommendations from this comprehensive review indicated that while the level of residential services, including home and community based services in the south Leitrim area, was adequate, existing infrastructure was significantly inadequate for modern service delivery.  The former workhouse facility at Carrick-on-Shannon and St. Patrick&rsquo;s Hospital in particular, need to be replaced with a new purpose-built residential services such as the development proposed for Ballinamore and a new unit in Carrick-on-Shannon which would ensure an accessible service for people in the eastern part of the region.</P>
             <?oasys _cl11.7- ?><P>The Ballinamore project incorporates a 20-bed care managing nursing unit as well as a primary care centre.  The project is an approved project in <Col N="1027"/>the 2006 to 2010 capital plan of the HSE.  A design team has been appointed to carry out the development control plan on the site acquired by the former North Western Health Board.  This process commenced in September of this year and involves consultation with Leitrim County Council.  The HSE anticipates that this stage will <Col N="1028"/>be completed by the end of the year.  The next stage will be the procurement of design consultants which should be completed by the first quarter of 2007.  The HSE has stated that construction is expected to start late next year.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <adjournment>The Seanad adjourned at 7 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 6 December 2006.</adjournment><Col N="1027"/>
    <HtmlBk SectId="0" />
  </MainHeading><?oasys _te ?><!--Fix-->
</Debate><!--Fix-->
