<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="3" Month="Jun" Year="1970" Vol="68" No="5" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 3 Meitheamh 1970" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 3 June 1970" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="255">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="255" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Business in the following order: Nos. 1, 2 and 3.  It is proposed to take No. 7 tomorrow morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>At what time tomorrow morning?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>10 a.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Will that allow the Senator time to attend the adjourned meeting tomorrow evening?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Let not the Senator worry about the adjourned meeting.  He should worry about his own outfit and I will worry about mine.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Censorship of Films (Amendment) Bill," RHead="1970: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Censorship of Films (Amendment) Bill, 1970: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we take up consideration of the Committee Stage of this Bill I should like to indicate that I have ruled out of order amendments Nos. 2 and 4 in the name of Senator Alexis FitzGerald on the grounds that they are outside the scope of the Bill as read a Second Time.  The Senator has been notified accordingly.</P>
      <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Miss Bourke Miss Bourke">
      <NameTxt>Miss Bourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>To add to the section a new subsection as follows:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;( ) Notice of every application made to the Official Censor under this section, and his decision thereon, shall be published in a manner to be prescribed by order of the Minister in the exercise of his powers <Col N="256" /> under section 12 of the Principal Act.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I move this amendment as a result of the debate we had last week and in consideration of the reply made by the Minister when suggestions for such publication came from all sides of the House.  Senators will recall that Senator Horgan, who will second this amendment, said during the course of his contribution that:</P>
    <P>Some system of publication (a) of films rejected and (b) of cuts made in films passed should be made available to the public.</P>
    <P>When concluding his speech, the Leader of the House said and I quote from the Seanad debate:</P>
    <P>I support this Bill for the resubmission of these films but I do so with grave misgivings.  I support it in the hope that the Minister will see to it that the censor will give us and the public generally an indication of what films were submitted to him and what films were rejected.</P>
    <P>I mentioned that under section 12 of the Principal Act of 1923 the Minister would have power to make orders regulating the duties of the official censor and that he would have power to require the censor to make a list of this nature.  The Minister, when replying to the debate, mentioned this request from both sides of the House for the publication of an official list and his argument was that the films submitted to the censor were the private property of film distributors and that if they did not accept the cuts suggested or if they did not wish to have the film shown in such cut form, they had the right as owners of such private property to have privacy.  In other words, the public need not know about what films they submitted.  I quote from the Minister's reply as reported at page 222 of the Seanad debate of the 27th May:</P>
    <P>Therefore, in my opinion, since it is entirely a matter within the province of the renter whether he will submit a film to the censor, if he does so he is entitled to do so in privacy without having the fact published later that the film was rejected or cut.  The comparison <Col N="257" /> between a person who is submitting a film for censorship and the author or publisher of a book, which already has been on sale publicly before it is submitted to the literary censorship board, is therefore invalid.</P>
    <P>In other words, the Minister is making a distinction between the publication of a list of banned books and the publication of a list of banned films. On consideration of the Minister's remarks, I believe that he is viewing the censorship of films from too narrow a viewpoint.  It is not solely a matter of public property of the renter: there is a public interest involved.  There is involved the constitutional rights of the citizens of Ireland.</P>
    <P>Last day we considered the constitutional right under Article 40, section 6.  Under this section there is a right to see any film which is not banned on the grounds that it is either offensive, seditious or blasphemous. The Minister, being a lawyer, will be aware of the recent Macauley case in the High Court which laid down that the citizen had a right to vindicate in the courts his constitutional right and I would submit that one of our constitutional rights is freedom of expression &mdash;freedom to see any films which do not fall into the category of being blasphemous or obscene under the Common Law or which do not attempt to deprave or corrupt or are contrary to public order and morality.  It is only within this rather narrow framework that the censor can act.  The citizens of this country have a constitutional right to see any films which are not within this category which have been submitted to the censor.  I feel it is not vindicating the constitutional rights of the citizens not to publish the list of the films submitted.</P>
    <P>This fulfils two purposes.  It safeguards our constitutional right by providing us with the knowledge of which films have been submitted and the decision thereon and it also furthers the interest of those who are distressed at films such as Joyce's <i>Ulysses</i> which was banned and has not appeared in this country.  Those of us who have seen it outside the country may feel, when it comes up for reconsideration, <Col N="258" /> that we would like to know what the decision of the censor was and whether this is one of the films, I take it as an example at random, which came up before the censor.  Therefore, on those grounds, and because I believe it is not just a matter of private property, that there is a constitutional issue involved that I beg leave to move this amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. O'Malley) Desmond J. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. O'Malley)</NameTxt>
      <P>With reference to Senator Bourke's remarks here today regarding, if I heard her rightly, the alleged constitutional rights of a citizen to see any film he or she wishes to see&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Miss Bourke Miss Bourke">
      <NameTxt>Miss Bourke</NameTxt>
      <P>Submitted to the censor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;which was submitted to the censor and presumably not passed by him, although I make no claim to be a legal expert in those matters I fail to see that any such right exists.  If Senator Bourke feels such a right exists I invite her to institute an action for such declaration. I should have thought the whole point of the censorship of films, of at least the political aspect of which Senator Bourke was very keen the last day, is in fact accepted generally and there has been no suggestion that the 1923 and 1925 Acts and this Bill, which is at present before the Seanad, are or might be unconstitutional.</P>
      <P>Now, to deal with the amendments in general, I am sure the House will appreciate from what I said in my reply on the second reading that I must oppose this amendment.  There are, as I see it, both objections in principle and practical objections to the amendment. There is the initial objection in principle that it would be impossible to defend the proposed publication in relation only to applications made by virtue of this Bill.  If there should be publication at all, it is surely plain that it should apply to all applications. I should say in fairness to the Senators who have put down amendments that their amendments are necessarily confined, through no fault of their own, to proceedings under this Bill and not under the Acts in general.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The second but much more important <Col N="259" /> objection in principle is the one I mentioned here the last day.  The fact is that what is in question here is private property, a film which is privately owned and which is not yet released for public showing in the State.  It is important to bear in mind that if the censor is required to disclose that such a film has been presented for censorship, he is thereby also disclosing, even if indirectly, that other films have not been so presented.</P>
    <P>A suggestion was made here the last day that film renters were unwilling, or may be unwilling, to disclose information about their dealings with the censor lest they offend the censor and suffer in the long run.  I think I should place on the records of this House that when a similar suggestion was made by a film critic in a newspaper about 12 months ago a full public apology was subsequently made to the censor. This kind of suggestion, implying as it does that the film trade do not trust the censor, is a reflection on the integrity of the censor and is without foundation. Most of the film renters, that is to say the people who bring in the films and let them out to the cinemas, are represented by an association and the association, who were consulted again on the occasion to which I have just referred, reaffirmed their position, which was that, as far as they were concerned, it was for them to release or not to release information about the products which they own.  They are, and at all times have been, fully aware that, as far as the censor is concerned, they are quite welcome to publish any information they wish about the censor's decisions.  They acknowledged that fact and in face of that acknowledgment, which they repeated in the full knowledge that it was going to be published by the censor, I think it is not too much to ask that the censor should not again be subjected to this innuendo.</P>
    <P>I repeat that a film, as presented for censorship, is a single piece of property. There are not, as in the case of books, thousands of copies owned by many different people.  As I have explained, the owner of the property asserts, and in my view legitimately <Col N="260" /> asserts, that it is for him and not for any State authority to release information about it.</P>
    <P>That is the main argument of principle.  There are also, as I have said, practical arguments.  If the censor publishes information, what precisely is he to say?  Obviously he cannot give descriptive particulars of what he excludes since to do so is to publicise that very material which by his own decision he has held to be unfit for publication.  If he just says that the film is &ldquo;subject to cuts&rdquo; he is giving no really useful information for cuts may range from something very short to something quite extensive.  Considerable commercial damage, as I pointed out on the last day, could be done to a renter, and quite unfairly, by a statement that cuts have been made as this would give the impression, perhaps quite wrongly, that the film bears little resemblance to the original film and was a mutilated product.</P>
    <P>Another point is this.  Supposing a renter, on hearing the censor's reaction, withdraws the film and does his own cutting to avoid publication of an announcement of cuts, is this not going to be highly misleading to the public? Worse still, from the point of view of the public, suppose renters, afraid of the commercial damage of such publication, became afraid to take the slightest risk of an adverse decision, the inevitable result is that the renters will do their own cutting before they approach the censor at all and will necessarily be much more severe than he would be in such circumstances.</P>
    <P>Accordingly the net result would be that the public would get no information of any value while, on the other hand, the legitimate interests of the renters could be adversely and unfairly affected and, as I have explained, the renters, in order to protect their legitimate interests, might have to impose on their products a censorship far more severe than the censor would wish to do.</P>
    <P>These particular arguments, important though they be in practice, must take second place to the objection in principle that I mentioned earlier namely, that the film, at the point when <Col N="261" /> it is presented for censorship, is private property and, in my view, there is no answer to the claim consistently made by the renters and reported fairly recently, that the release of information about a film is entirely a matter for them as the owners or representatives of the owners.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment being withdrawn?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Miss Bourke Miss Bourke">
      <NameTxt>Miss Bourke</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the Minister's very full reply, although I am not quite in agreement with him because he is advocating the renters' commercial interests rather than the public interest, I withdraw the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 2 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 2 has been ruled out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 3:</P>
      <P>Before section 3 to insert the following new section:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Before 1st January, 1971, and from time to time thereafter at intervals of not more than ten years, the Minister shall appoint a committee to inquire into and report to him on amendments (if any) to section 2 of this Act which, in the opinion of the committee have become desirable by virtue of changed circumstances or which the administration of the section has shown to be desirable.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I should have preferred to address the House on the amendment which has been ruled out of order: it would have been easier for me to get the House, in particular our guest, the Minister, to consider what is in fact a new concept and which I think it would be desirable to introduce into legislation, particularly legislation of this kind.  When the Minister was introducing the Bill he said that since January, 1965, a number of films had been passed for adult viewing which up to then would have been refused a certificate.  He added:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="262" /> Conversely, it may be assumed that a number of films that were refused certificates before January, 1965, would have qualified for a limited certificate if such a system had been in operation at the time they were submitted.  There is, therefore, a very good case, in principle, for altering the present law so that a film that was cut or rejected in, say, 1964 should now be eligible to be reconsidered.</P>
    <P>If in the earlier legislation, the Censorship of Films Act, 1923, section 7 had allied to it or as a subsection of it provisions such as the amendment I have moved, we would have reports made to the Minister by a committee concerned to examine this situation which the Minister has now found it desirable to amend; we would have had this amendment long before now and we would have had a body of persons empowered to consider the operation of that section and whether it was desirable to amend that section in the light of the changing standards and the various other considerations that properly would have had to be considered in the drafting of this Bill.</P>
    <P>While technically in this amendment I am suggesting that a committee should sit and report to the Minister on amendments, if any, to section 2 of the Act which in the opinion of the committee had become desirable by virtue of changed circumstances, I was impressed by what the Minister said on Second Reading in regard to the cutting of films and also with the manner of his saying these things.  However, I should like to see that hereafter we would have a body who in the operation of this section would consider whether the censor or the appeal board were operating in a manner which seemed to them fair and just&mdash;whether the balance was properly being kept between the liberty of the public and our duty to preserve public order and morality.  I ask the Minister if he would be prepared to open his mind to this amendment.  I do not press for the acceptance of this amendment in this form but I suggest an amendment would be open to him on the lines of the amendment which has been ruled out of order:</P>
    <P>... a committee to inquire into and <Col N="263" /> report to him on amendments (if any) to the Censorship of Films Acts, 1923 to 1970...</P>
    <P>We have had the 1923 Act, amended in 1925 and in 1930, and 40 years have passed.  Perhaps this Bill should have been introduced much earlier.  I leave my amendment to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator FitzGerald's idea of a periodic review of the working of the film censorship Acts is one that, on the face of it at all events, seems reasonable in principle.  Whether the kind of review proposed, namely a review by a committee at least every ten years, is attractive in principle is another matter and one I propose to comment on in a moment, but before doing that I think it worth mentioning that there probably would be in any event considerable practical difficulties in the way because it would be impossible, I should think, to have a review of any value unless the committee were in a position to see the films or portions of films that were rejected, and since even the studios that make the films may have only a few copies altogether, it might be quite impossible for them, at any given time, to produce a copy of a particular film to such a committee.  In fact, I should think that the odds would be against it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Leaving those practical difficulties aside, however, I think there are quite serious objections in principle.  First of all, I do not think the need for a formal review every ten years or oftener has been established or could possibly be established.  Our experience to date is that, apart from a couple of minor amendments that do not invalidate what I am saying, our 1923 Act has remained adequate for close on 50 years.  We have had arguments, of course, about standards of censorship but the standards were not fixed by the Act but by the official censors and the appeal boards and thus were amenable to change corresponding with change in the general pattern of what was acceptable to the general body of the public.  But the Act itself, as I have said, was regarded, both by the public and the trade, as perfectly adequate until fairly recently when the need for the present Bill became apparent.  Incidentally, <Col N="264" /> the need for it was established and recognised without recourse to any such committee as is proposed in this amendment so that the fact that we have this Bill now is not, in itself, an argument in favour of a committee.  I suggest, therefore, that experience to date does not support the proposition that a formal review at ten-year intervals is at all necessary and, as a matter of principle, I do not think committees should have to be established unless the need for them is established beyond doubt.</P>
    <P>I have thought it right to mention these objections because I think they are valid ones and worth pointing out. I have left aside until last, however, what in my view is by far the most serious objection, and indeed an insurmountable objection, to what is proposed. To explain what I mean, I would ask the House to consider our present system.  We have an official censor and, as an appellate authority above him, we have an appeal board. At present, the chairman is a judge of the circuit court.  The members are persons selected because of their ability to represent and express different points of view.</P>
    <P>I am afraid that, whatever gloss might be put on it, the reality behind Senator FitzGerald's proposal is that we would have another committee reviewing and reporting on the work of the committee which comprise the appeal board.  Frankly, I do not see how any self-respecting appeal board could tolerate such a situation for a moment.  I think they would say: &ldquo;Who are these people who are set up to pass judgment on us?  If they are competent to do that, let them take over and act as the appeal board themselves.&rdquo; I should like to be quite clear about this.  I do not mean that the work of the appeal board is above all criticism. Any and every person or body exercising functions affecting the public must be open to some form of criticism.</P>
    <P>My point is that we cannot have one committee superimposed on another. The appeal board are answerable to me as Minister for Justice.  I am answerable to the Oireachtas.  If the appeal board were incompetent it <Col N="265" /> would be my responsibility to replace them.  We could not have an appeal board which we accept as comprised of fit and proper persons to act on the board and at the same time have their work made subject to periodic reports by another board or group.  Their standing in the scheme of things is such that they can be made answerable only in the one way and that is to the Minister and through him to the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>That leads inescapably to the conclusion that Senator Alexis FitzGerald's idea is in substance already given effect through the existence of the appeal board.  The appeal board are a committee and because of the qualities and background which led to their members being selected in the first place, and because of their experience in film censorship, they are the people who are the most suitable committee to report to me on an amendment of the law if such amendment becomes necessary. While I feel that it is important that the right of the appeal board to communicate with me in confidence must be preserved, I feel they would not mind if, without going into detail, I say on this occasion that they contributed to the formulation of proposals now before the House.  I am certain that they would do so again if and when the need arose.</P>
    <P>In these circumstances, while I have approached the matter with an open mind, I regret I could not agree to the amendment because it would diminish in a most serious way the status of the existing appeal board.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad the Minister referred to the persons who compose the appeal board.  Some of them are friends of mine and it would be miserable for me if my proposal were seen to reflect on them as persons.  There is an important aspect which the Minister might look at.  The proceedings of those well-qualified gentlemen are held <i>in camera</i>.  These proceedings are private in the most complete sense.  In the Supreme Court the judgments are given in public and when given can be subjected to, and are subjected to, criticism by legal critics. The whole process of our law generally <Col N="266" /> involves this feature of constant criticism of the judicial system.  This system helps the judges themselves to revise views which they have embodied in previous judgments.</P>
      <P>It is all very well for the Minister to say that he is responsible to the Oireachtas and that the appeal board are responsible to him.  The Minister's source of information about the operations of the censor and of the appeal board is the censor himself and the appeal board themselves.  We have no information at all.  There is no publication at all about their procedures.  From studying the composition of the board I would have thought that the balance would be weighted in favour of public order rather than in favour of private liberty.</P>
      <P>There is a case for the Minister to have an opportunity of getting information as to the procedures of the censor and the appeal board.  The Minister would be able to see whether anything defective was developing in their procedures through habit.  The system of doing something and repeating it can produce compulsive habit. This happens with bodies and people can be unaware of the fact that they are acting in a reflex way to a situation. If another point of view were presented to them it might mean that they would have a different attitude to a problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are property interests involved and these cannot be ignored.  One of the virtues of this sort of procedure is that there would be no need for detailed publication in <i>An Iris Oifigiúil</i> which has a counter-productive effect.  I would ask the Minister to reconsider the possibility that generally in regard to our legislation it might be wiser for the Oireachtas if one had independent committees, and committees independent of the gentlemen behind the Minister who are heavily burdened with other duties all the time, and committees whose special functions might be to consider whether certain legislation needed to be revised in the public interest. Such an independent body would be able to indicate the degree of urgency which they attached to the particular version thought desirable.  I would ask the Minister to give this the <Col N="267" /> necessary thought between now and the Report Stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I should be glad to give a great deal of thought to this matter between the end of the Committee Stage and the beginning of the Report Stage but I had hoped that the interval would be extremely short.  The points which Senator Alexis FitzGerald makes have always a certain degree of validity at least.  They are worthy of thought by me and by others interested in these matters.  I might refer briefly to some of what the Senator has said now.  The Senator felt that the appeal board, because it carried on its proceedings <i>in camera,</i> was free of criticism. That, in fact, is not so.  As I said earlier in my reply when the Senator was moving the amendment, I do not suggest for one moment that the appeal board should be free of criticism. Any body or persons exercising functions by which the public are affected must from time to time be subject to some criticism.</P>
      <P>It happens in practice that the appeal board are not subjected to a great deal of criticism.  Although this may seem an over-simplification, I believe the reason they are not subjected to a great deal of criticism is that they do not deserve it.  If a person or persons feel they have been unjustly treated by the censor or the appeal board, as I pointed out earlier today on a previous amendment and as I pointed out in my Second Reading speech, the censor and the appeal board have absolutely no objection whatever to such dissatisfied persons making public the reason for their dissatisfaction.  If a certificate is refused by the censor and the appeal board for a particular film, and the renter or distributor of the film feels aggrieved, there is nothing to stop the aggrieved person writing a letter to a newspaper, or raising the matter in any other way.  The censor or the appeal board would no doubt defend themselves as they saw appropriate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think the point the Senator makes about the procedures of the appeal board is covered by what I have already said.  The point about these independent committees which he suggested <Col N="268" /> is, in a wider context than the particular one we are discussing here under this amendment, a bone of some contention, which goes to the root of the whole Parliamentary procedure of this country.  I should not like to make any pronouncement on it at this point in time on this particular Bill because I think any committee which might concievably be established arising out of this Bill would only be a minor one when one takes into account all the committees of that nature which might, if it were so decided, be formed in conjunction with the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 4 has been ruled out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 5:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(1)  The appeals board shall present to the Minister annually a report of their proceedings under section 2 hereof during the previous year and a copy thereof shall be laid before each House of the Oireachtas.</P>
      <P>(2)  The appeals board shall furnish to the Minister such information with regard to the exercise of their functions under section 2 hereof as the Minister may from time to time require.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This amendment speaks for itself.  I should point out that I cannot take credit for the drafting of this amendment because it was taken from the Arts Council Bill with appropriate amendments made to make it relate to this particular section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think the censorship of films code is the only one of its kind where no report of proceedings is made to the Minister or laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas.  If this were done the censor and the board would be saved a great deal of criticism.  In principle I think we should by right receive a report about what the board are doing. The Minister is bringing a detached mind to this.  Perhaps not all his predecessors had the same concern as he has and perhaps not all his successors will.  I think Members of the Oireachtas have a duty to satisfy themselves that <Col N="269" /> any institution which they create is watched by them.  I think my Second Reading speech indicated that I am no libertine, in principle at any rate.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say a few words on this amendment mostly by way of asking questions regarding the present procedure.  The Minister's Department kindly made available to me a document called &ldquo;Film Censorship Annual Returns, 1968&rdquo;.  I am not sure if this document is the annual report of the censor and the appeal board but if it is it would appear to me that we are already, to some extent, in possession of an annual report from the censor and appeal board.</P>
      <P>I would not be keen about pressing this matter any further because the information in which I and many other Senators have an interest is the publication of the titles of films which go to the censor and appeal board.  I hope the Minister will not mind if I make one final plea and ask him to reconsider this matter because while this document on the annual returns is of considerable interest, it gives the number of films submitted and the cuts made, it does not refer in any way to the titles of the films which were put before the board.</P>
      <P>I very much regret that some Senators asked for information regarding specific cuts in specific films.  The Minister has dealt exceptionally well with those points and his arguments have been extremely interesting.  He has emphasised that the film is the private property of the renter and that the relationship between the renter and the censor and the appeal board is a private and confidential one.  I accept that that is quite true but the reason a number of Senators are interested in the titles of the films going to the appeal board has nothing to do with this.  Our difficulty is that we feel the judgments made by the censor and the appeal board are matters which should be open to public debate and matters where the public should be aware of the criteria being used.  Under the principal Act, the instructions given to the censor are that he shall certify it,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>... unless he is of the opinion that <Col N="270" /> such picture or some part thereof is unfit for general exhibition in public by reason of its being indecent, obscene and blasphemous or because the exhibition thereof in public would tend to inculcate principles contrary to public morality or would be otherwise subversive of public morality.</P>
    <P>The only evidence we have of the criteria used by the censor and appeal board is by virtue of what appears; we have no evidence of what is excluded. This means there is no way in which we can objectively attempt to assess the criteria being used by the censor and the appeal board in our name. Until a list of the full titles of the films submitted to the censor and appeal board is published in the annual report we cannot assess the standard of rejection.</P>
    <P>We know the standard of acceptance but we also need, if we are to assess the merits of the working of our censor and appeal board, to know the standard of rejection.  I do not think the publication of an annual report would necessarily lead to the type of abuse which the Minister fears, such as the situation which existed when books which were banned in this country were displayed abroad with a label on them which said, &ldquo;Banned in Éire&rdquo;. We have nothing to fear about any film being given the label, &ldquo;Banned in Éire&rdquo; if we as a community are quite happy that the censor and the appeal board acting in harmony used criteria and standards of which we approve.  In some circumstances we should be proud of the fact that books or films have been banned in this country.  The reason why we are rather ashamed of this and the reason why we look back on it is because I think the censorship board made some rather foolish mistakes with regard to literature and quite rightly we regarded it as a matter of regret that some books which did not deserve the title were published abroad with a label on them, &ldquo;Banned in Éire&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Another point I should like to make, which is separate from the general point about the publication of titles, is that historians of the cinema or film, archivists, may find that the only available <Col N="271" /> list of film titles, perhaps even films written by Irish authors or produced by Irish producers, will be in the hands of the censor and the appeal board.  It is a pity that historical information of this kind, because of the present way our censorship legislation is administered, should be denied indefinitely. We have had the Censorship of Films Act since 1923 and if the Minister could see his way to releasing the titles of films which went to the censor or appeal board in the first 20 years of the legislation, which would bring us up to 1943, that would be some help.</P>
    <P>It may be that such a list might reveal Irish films of historical interest which have been lost or forgotten.  If the Minister every 20 years were to release the titles of films which appeared in the previous 20 years that would be some help.  This may sound a trivial matter but I am raising it because there are people with a specific interest in it.  I understand it is not permitted at the present time but I feel it may be of genuine historical interest in the future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Miss Bourke Miss Bourke">
      <NameTxt>Miss Bourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the amendment put forward by Senator FitzGerald. I feel statutory bodies should present an annual report.  I agree with the arguments put forward by Senator Keery.  Already it raises what I consider to be an argument which many Senators would endorse, that is how can we know the standard set by the official censor and by the appeal board and how can we know what considerations they take into account if we do not know what films are being submitted to them or on which grounds they are being rejected?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I agree with the Minister that it would be wrong to expect them to give details of cuts that have been requested if the film is to be distributed here but I think it would be an important contribution to public opinion in this country and it would also be the type of accountability which we ought to have from a statutory body such as the appeal board if they would make a report to the Minister&mdash;a report that would be put before the House.  The arguments in favour of the amendment <Col N="272" /> have been very well put by the Senators and I should like to support it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the amendment I should like to say firstly that, due to no fault of the proposer, if the amendment were accepted by the House it would relate only to films which came under the operation of section 2 of this Bill.  I am sure the proposer would have wished, as is quite obvious from amendment No. 4, that it would apply to all films.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister could take that on Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but whether he will is another matter.  If I may take the two subsections of this proposed section separately I should like to take the second one first.  As drafted, the subsection may be open to the interpretation that the board would be required by the subsection to furnish to me as Minister information in the nature of an explanation for particular decisions.  In other words, they would be asked to justify particular decisions to me as Minister.</P>
      <P>I accept that the Senator probably did not intend this because any such provision would at one and the same time seriously diminish if not destroy the independence of the board and, to a corresponding extent, would impose on me a function which I could not imagine the House wishing to impose on me&mdash;a function which I could not imagine any Minister in his senses being willing to have imposed on him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Without wishing to interrupt the Minister, may I point out that, as I said, this is the type of information the Minister and the Government are entitled to get from the Arts Council.  I would happily amend this to include a proviso that there would not be any interference on their liberty as censors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>This difficulty may arise to some extent by the fact that I am discussing the second amendment first, but when I reach the first amendment the Senator will realise that a report of the type mentioned by him is provided by the board.  The point that I was about to make in relation <Col N="273" /> to me or any Minister appearing to ask an independent statutory board for some comment which might seem to amount to a request for a justification of their decisions is that this is a provision which this House would do well to avoid.  If the precedent is created whereby a Minister, no matter how trivial a matter is involved, can go to an independent statutory board and ask them the justify their decisions, it does not need a fertile imagination to realise what such a precedent could eventually lead to.  I should not care to establish such precedents in any procedures under this Bill.</P>
      <P>I take it for granted that Senator FitzGerald did not intend it in that way, and therefore we are left with the other interpretation&mdash;that what is intended is factual information that does not amount to the defence or justification of decisions in particular cases.  On that basis I would agree with the Senator's view but the difficulty is that his view is so obviously right that I cannot see how anyone could dispute it.  It is inconceivable that the appeal board could refuse to give information of that kind.  They have always done so, as I shall be mentioning later when commenting on the first subsection.  I do not think that the appeal board would be offended by the Senator's amendment since the Senator had no direct knowledge of the way in which the board operate, but they would be offended if I were to adopt the attitude that it was necessary to impose on them a legal obligation to do what they have always done without question.  Therefore, I assure the Senator that his second proposed subsection is unnecessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The first proposed subsection, in so far as it relates to the presentation of a report, is also unnecessary because the appeal board make an annual report already.  This report includes comments which have been made in the knowledge that it is not customary to publish the comments and which, perhaps, may be all the more freely made on that account, but I should like to emphasise that the statistical material relating to the board's working is published and, indeed, it receives substantial press <Col N="274" /> publicity at the time of its release each year.</P>
    <P>The document which my Department supplied to Senator Keery at his request is, in fact, the statistical information from the board's report.  It has always been customary to publish such information. It was published not very long ago in respect of last year and was commented on in the newspapers.  In future years the report will have to refer to applications made by virtue of section 2.  Such applications are covered by Senator FitzGerald's amendment.</P>
    <P>I do not know whether I could agree that the body of the report as opposed to the statistical information contained therein could be published in future years.  There is a difficulty that I have already mentioned of its being mainly a document prepared specifically for publication.  If the board were to be more cautious their report would become less useful to me and, ultimately, less useful to the Oireachtas than if they published a document in which is written what they feel should be written in the knowledge that it will be treated with the greatest confidence.</P>
    <P>The best I can do at the moment is to consider the matter without any preconceived idea about where lies the balance of advantage.  I assure the House that I will do this before the next annual report of the board is due. This is not for almost 12 months from now.  Meanwhile, Senators will appreciate that if the board have already made an annual report it would be wrong of me, knowing that, to support an amendment which purports to require them to do what they have already done quite recently and what they do each year.  I give an undertaking to the House that I will discuss with the board the advisability or otherwise of publishing their report next year.</P>
    <P>Senators will appreciate that in justice I am bound to inform the board of this and to consult with them because their report this year and reports for many years past have been written and submitted to my predecessors on the basis that they would be regarded as confidential and I would not propose to depart from that practice <Col N="275" /> without putting up to the board the arguments which have been so well adduced in this House today that their report might in fact be made public.  If they are agreeable I feel I should give them sufficient notice to enable them to prepare their report in the light of that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say a few words on this.  The Minister has made an effort to deal with this matter reasonably and I hope he will not regard me as in any way slighting when I say that I think his arguments in relation to this particular amendment are entirely fallacious.  As I understand the Minister's approach it is this: the board already give a report and therefore it is not necessary to have it in the legislation that they should be obliged to give a report.  That is precisely what this amendment is about.  Senator FitzGerald takes the view, and it is one I share with him, that this is a statutory body set up by legislation of the Dáil and of this House and that in those circumstances, and having regard to the fact that other statutory bodies of a roughly similar character have, under the legislation establishing them the legal obligation, to produce a report annually, there is no reason why the appeal board, which we are concerned with now, should be relieved of a similar legal obligation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That is valid.  It is a coercive argument. It is all very well for the Minister to say that the appeal board make a report to his Department.  That does not come to the Oireachtas which by legislation establishes the appeals board.  As I see it, the Oireachtas are entitled to get that information. One of the purposes of this amendment is to ensure that those reports will be laid before each House of the Oireachtas.  I have no doubt at all that the Minister himself would be courteous enough and that his officials would be courteous enough to give information of the sort that Senator Keery apparently obtained when he got what amounts to a statistical abstract of the work done by the appeal board.  I have no doubt that courtesy would be extended to Members of the Oireachtas but it is only a courtesy.  They are not entitled as of <Col N="276" /> right to that.  The suggestion in this amendment is that they should be entitled, as of right, to have the report laid before them so I do not consider it is any answer to this amendment to say that the board already produce a report and therefore that it is not necessary to legislate in order to make them do it.</P>
    <P>The Minister then went on to argue that the report which is furnished by the appeal board to him or to his Department at present contains information that might be regarded as of a confidential nature and that in any event if it were a statutory obligation on the appeal board to furnish an annual report it would be a much more cautiously produced document and that the appeal board might not be as expansive in their comments.  I do not think the Minister used that expression but it was the sense of his argument. I consider that also is fallacious.  Even though this House or the Oireachtas in general imposes an obligation on the appeal board to produce an annual report&mdash;let them be as cautious as they like about it&mdash;there is nothing to prevent them, in addition to producing their annual report, giving whatever confidential comment or information they want to the Minister.  That situation of a confidential inflow of information need not be interfered with one way or the other by the obligation to produce a report of this sort.</P>
    <P>The Minister, as I say, is trying to deal with this matter reasonably and if he wants to get the Bill today, as apparently he does, I can understand that if he has any doubt about the wording of this particular amendment that he is naturally put on the spot. He has little option but to resist any change in the Bill unless he is prepared to accept the amendment <i>in toto</i> as it stands.  That is exactly what I would urge on him to do.</P>
    <P>The other point he made is not real. I remember at one time the Minister's party used to claim to be the party of reality.  The suggestion was that the second part of this amendment would seem to give grounds anyhow for believing that the Minister might be entitled to demand of the board information which would be tantamount to <Col N="277" /> a demand or a request to them to justify decisions which they have made. The Minister has made it quite clear that in so far as he is concerned he would not want to do that.  Even if that interpretation were open on the second part of the amendment, the remedy for the situation rests entirely in the Minister's hands.  He need not request any information which would be in any way, or could be in any way, interpreted as request to the board to justify their decisions.</P>
    <P>In any event, as Senator FitzGerald has pointed out, he has his precedent under the Arts Council legislation for the actual wording of this amendment. There is not the slightest danger that the second part of it could be interpreted or could be operated in such a way as to be taken as a request to the board for justification of their decisions. I would urge the Minister very strongly to accept this amendment as it stands.  I do not believe he is weakening the Bill in any way in doing that.</P>
    <P>The Minister made another point which I think is a valid and an obvious one, namely that the amendment, because it is an amendment to this Bill, can only, if it is accepted, relate to the functions of the appeal board under section 2 of this Bill.  That is so but the Minister can remedy that situation too and make it applicable to the film censorship code generally by introducing a very simple amendment either on Report Stage or introduce a very simple further amending Bill to extend the provisions of this amendment to the rest of the film censorship code.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Higgins should bear in mind when he draws the parallel of the Arts Council that the very nature of the appeal board's work is basically extremely different from the nature of the work of the Arts Council or indeed the work of many other statutory bodies which produce and submit annual reports to the Government to be laid on the Tables of the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As Senator O'Higgins pointed out, the amendment as it stands, even if I were to agree to what is urged in principle in it, I could not accept.  I would <Col N="278" /> not be prepared even on Report Stage to introduce an amendment in the more general terms which would be necessary if the thing were agreed, without first having the opportunity of considering the matter at greater length.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not like intervening, but while the Chair does not rule on the question of a hypothetical amendment, it is doubtful if an amendment in the terms suggested would be in order because it is likely to be outside the scope of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;The Act is an Act to amend and extend...&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair is not prepared to rule on a hypothetical amendment.  The Chair is merely giving a hypothetical warning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>And I am giving just a hypothetical answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I have gone so far and I think Senators might accept it as being a reasonable effort on my part.  I have said that I am prepared to discuss these matters with the appeal board and to put the views of Senators to them to see whether they would be agreeable in the future to having their annual report made public.  It would be, as the House well appreciates, absolutely unfair of me, even if I personally wanted to do it, to publish their current or any previous reports because they were prepared and submitted to my predecessors on the basis that they would be treated as confidential.  At the same time, I think Senators are not being very realistic in their approach that it does not matter at all if the board do not say anything worthwhile so long as we get a report from them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As far as I know, the reports consist mainly of statistical abstracts, which are published, as I said earlier, and which are available to any Member of the Oireachtas.  The remainder of the reports consists of comments on current trends in films and on certain types of films.  Those have been issued up to now on the basis that they will not be published and I would be in <Col N="279" /> breach of that confidence if I were to publish them.  I will go this far, and I respectfully suggest that it be accepted, that I will discuss with the appeal board the possibility of publishing their full report in future even if this has the effect of their producing a less valuable report than they have done up to now.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Although I do not say that what the Minister has said is entirely acceptable to me, I accept his mentality&mdash;perhaps we share the same mentality on this question&mdash; but I find it impossible to defend the position that when discussing this matter with people who are not Irish we adult people have to say this is determined for us by private trafficking between the censor and the appeal board on the one hand and property owners in particular films on the other as to whether films are to be shown in public without any reason being given other than that the principles of the basic Act are being applied by them.</P>
      <P>I suggest it is difficult to justify this from the point of view of the reputation of our country.  I think it is not adequate to say that the appeal board might produce a less full annual report in future if they choose to do so. Any Minister can give them the necessary power to do it.  This is not a satisfactory position.  The Oireachtas should be given an opportunity to consider the larger argument in respect of enlightening the public and of giving people generally an opportunity to consider questions of taste, art and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to subsection (2), I am not happy with the language I have used in the amendment and the Minister has drawn my attention to it.  I should like the Minister to consider even at this stage reintroducing it in language of his own, containing an appropriate proviso protecting the appeal board and the censor in these matters, which are very important.  I think it is an indefensible position for Irish people to have to say that even parliament is not able to know the actual procedures, practices and principles of the censor and the appeal board&mdash;that these should be a matter of confidence between the private property <Col N="280" /> owners, the censor, the appeal board and the Minister.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Higgins, the Minister will agree, made a valid point when he said that everything the Minister is told by the appeal board is not in the annual report, which is an agreed document.  One knows that in exchanges between other Departments, State bodies and Ministers, much of that which is said does not and should not appear in their reports.  It might not be in the public interest that it should.  In any case, a clever draftsman could get a new section drafted here by tomorrow morning.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Did I understand the Senator to say that he was against private property&mdash;that a renter who rented a film must show that film, that whatever the censor did he must show the film?  If the censor made cuts, I understood the Senator to say that the renter could not withdraw the film, that he must show it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what the Senator understood me to say, but I did not say that.  My position as far as private property is concerned is to be found in the Constitution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Miss Bourke Miss Bourke">
      <NameTxt>Miss Bourke</NameTxt>
      <P>We have reached an impasse to some extent in so far as the Minister has made known his attitude, which I consider to be rather flexible. Purely on a point of information, I wonder if he considers he has the power mentioned under section 12 of the principal Act:</P>
      <P>The Minister for Home Affairs may by order, from time to time, make, and when made vary and revoke regulations for carrying into effect the objects of this Act, and in particular for regulating the conduct of the office of the Official Censor, the making of applications to him, the granting of certificates by him, and the bringing of appeals to the appeal board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Under the terms of that section, does he consider he has power to have the reports made available in the Houses of the Oireachtas to such an extent that it would meet the genuine desire <Col N="281" /> of Senators to have some sort of accountability or information process set up between the statutory body and Parliament?</P>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not really studied section 12 of the 1923 Act with a view to ascertaining whether I have the power which Senator Miss Bourke suggests.  What the Senator has suggested may be a way out of our impasse.  It might well be that after I had discussed the matter with the appeal board I would consider making regulations under that section.  I would not undertake to do that until I had a full discussion on the matter with the appeal board.</P>
      <P>In reply to Senator Alexis FitzGerald, I might say that in dealing with a film one is dealing with a piece of private property, as Senator Ó Maoláin has pointed out.  There may have been one copy of that particular film in the country at a time for the purpose of giving it to the censor.  The censor and the appeal board may have objected to the film.  The person who submitted the film may live in the United States or elsewhere.  Presumably the film is sent back to him.  It is unlikely that a copy could be obtained again.  The rather foolish position could exist&mdash; although it is not unknown in this country&mdash;where members of the public or of the Oireachtas would form judgments and make criticisms about something they had never seen.  That is another reason why I feel that the view I have taken on this particular matter is the correct one.  The appeal board are in the advantageous position, which no Member of the Oireachtas or the public are in, in that they have viewed the film in question.  I would go so far as to say that 99 out of 100 times it would not be possible for any Member of the Oireachtas or the public to view such a film.  For that reason, <i>ipso facto,</i> no member of the Oireachtas or of the public is in a valid position to dispute with the appeal board about their decision in the matter.  When legislating we need to be competent&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>There might be a question of consistency here.  I understood the Minister was arguing strongly <Col N="282" /> originally that it was not necessary to have this amendment because such a report was already made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>That was in connection with one of the subsections.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment stands as a whole.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The report is there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister does not want a report in case some members of the Oireachtas might not be able to read it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a complete twist.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think what Senator O'Higgins says is correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be very satisfied with all the Minister said if the Minister had stopped at the point where he said he was prepared to consider making an order under section 12 of the principal Act.  The Minister was tempted to go on to an entirely irrelevant discussion with regard to property.  The Minister was yielding to a temptation.  In putting it in that way I am in a difficulty in that I do not know whether or not to invite the Minister to restate what he was saying at one point in the discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Or to restate it without help from Senator Ó Maoláin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us have a vote and be done with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I was inviting the Minister to repeat what he seemed to be offering the House.  The Minister seemed to move away from it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I will restate as follows: I am prepared, having heard the views of the appeal board and subject to my having power under section 12 of the 1923 Act, to consider making an order.  I am not prepared to give a blanket undertaking that I will make an order.  Having heard the views of the appeal board and of other interested parties&mdash;but principally of the appeal board&mdash;I should be prepared to consider making an order.  It depends <Col N="283" /> firstly on whether I have the power and whether having heard such views I consider it the proper thing to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister considers the matter and finds he has not the power to make an order the Seanad are deprived of their opportunity of making their voices heard on this amendment.  It has been said that we will sit tomorrow.  Would it inconvenience the Minister to have the Report Stage tomorrow?  We can assure the Minister that there will be no discussion tomorrow on the Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will appreciate that it would be impossible for me to consult with and to obtain the considered views of the appeal board on such short notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Between now and tomorrow can the Minister establish whether he has powers to make such an order under the principal Act?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should be as good a judge as I am on that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBelton" hpid="Dr. Belton Dr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister has not that power we want to give it to him so that we can blame him for exercising it incorrectly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Having looked at the Act, I have concluded on balance that the Minister has not the powers. One of the objects of the Act is not to produce an annual report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>A further point occurs to me that, whether I have the power or not, there is nothing to stop me publishing the report if I thought fit to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no obligation on them to give the Minister a copy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already received one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has given them notice that there is no obligation on them to do so.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 3 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="284" /> Title agreed to.</P>
    <P>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Merchandise Marks (No. 2) Bill, 1969:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Merchandise Marks (No. 2) Bill, 1969: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLalor" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lalor) Patrick J. Lalor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lalor)</NameTxt>
      <P>The object of this Bill is to provide additional protection for the consumer by enabling me to make orders requiring that prepacked goods should carry an indication of the quantity of contents and that, goods should be packed in standard quantities.</P>
      <P>There is, of course, already in existence a wide range of legislation designed to protect the consumer.  The principal measures administered by my Department which provide safeguards for the consumer are those relating to weights and measures, merchandise marks, restrictive trade practices, hire-purchase and credit-sales and industrial research and standards.  In addition, Statutes administered by the Ministers for Health and Agriculture and Fisheries provide for the maintenance of standards of quality for medical preparations and agricultural produce and for the control of poisons.  A number of these measures date back almost a century while others belong to recent decades and reflect the changing commercial conditions and to some extent the changing attitudes of our own times.  The need for the present Bill arises similarly from altered trading practices.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Bill is made necessary by the phenomenal growth of pre-packaging in recent years.  In the days when the customer could watch his purchases being weighed or measured with the scales or measuring equipment on the shop counter, it was sufficient to provide that the scales and weights and measures should be accurate, leaving it to the purchaser to see that they were correctly and honestly used.  This is just what the Weights and Measures Acts sought to do.  But nowadays, when goods are so often pre-packed, either in a back-room of the shop or much <Col N="285" /> more often in the manufacturer's or packer's premises, it is no longer practicable for the customer to check the quantity of what he is buying by simply watching the weighing or measuring operation as it takes place.  New forms of protection are thus necessary.</P>
    <P>The minimum requirement is that the consumer should know what quantity of goods is in each package so that he or she may have a basis for assessing the comparative values of competing products.  The simplest and most effective way of securing this is to require that each package should carry a statement clearly setting out the quantity of its contents.  Such information would not of itself, however, enable an assessment of relative values to be readily made if goods are packed in a wide variety of sizes.  A shopper would have to be very good at mental arithmetic to compare the prices of 1 lb packages with others which contained 15 ozs.  or 17 ozs.  Clearly, it should be possible to fix standard sizes such as ½ lb and 1 lb which would take into account the characteristics of individual products and the amount of each which it is convenient to buy or sell in a package.</P>
    <P>The Bill now before the House provides that I should have the power to make orders, subject to the over-riding authority of the Oireachtas, which would enable me to achieve these objectives on behalf of the consumer. This method has been chosen as the practicable one.  It would, in my opinion, be impossible to frame an Act requiring that packages carry an indication of quantity of contents which would apply to all goods and which would, at the same time, take into account the different requirements of the wide variety of products which are available to-day.  Such an Act would give rise to difficulties, some of them unforeseeable at this stage, for manufacturers and distributors.</P>
    <P>It is obvious that the marking of quantity on packages of tea or sugar is a straightforward operation as compared with the marking of tins of fruit or vegetables which contain, in addition to these commodities, liquids and preservatives.  There may be technical difficulties operating in regard to the <Col N="286" /> packaging of certain commodities which would render it impossible to ensure that an exact quantity was put into a package and, in these cases, it would be necessary to provide for tolerance. The Bill provides that orders may deal with matters such as these, and, in my opinion, they could only be dealt with satisfactorily after full consultation with manufacturers, distributors and consumer representatives.</P>
    <P>The Bill also provides that orders may require that the name and address of the packer or importer of the goods be marked on the package to facilitate enforcement and to encourage packers and importers to comply with the other provisions of an order.</P>
    <P>The Bill does not apply to pre-packed goods intended for export because, if the requirements prescribed by an order differed from those in any export market, an exporter could find himself faced with additional costs and might even be faced with the choice of breaking the law or foregoing export. This dilemma could occur if an order specified that the notice on a container should be in a form which was not acceptable in the export market.</P>
    <P>It will be necessary when drafting orders to determine the extent to which provision should be made for the use of metric units of measurement. Clearly, the standard quantities prescribed in the initial orders would have to be in imperial units and will be in metric units when that system is in general use.  Even when the initial orders are being drafted, consideration will have to be given to the requirements of packers who may wish to pack in round metric quantities or exact metric equivalents of imperial quantities.</P>
    <P>Before I conclude, I should like to make it quite clear that the Bill is aimed only at the very small minority of manufacturers or traders who either deliberately or through negligence mislead or defraud the public.  Certain safeguards are included in the Bill to protect the trader who in all good faith, and despite reasonable precautions, may occasionally handle underweight packages.  At the Committee Stage in Dáil Éireann I accepted an Opposition amendment designed to provide safeguards <Col N="287" /> for a packer prosecuted for inadvertent breach of the legislation.</P>
    <P>I am glad to say that representatives of industrialists and distributors have welcomed the principle of this Bill, rightly regarding it as a protection for the conscientious manufacturer or trader as well as for the consumer. Following consideration of representations by the manufacturing interests, I introduced an amendment at the Committee Stage in Dáil Éireann which has the effect of making it obligatory for me to consult the interests concerned before I make any Order under the Bill.  At the same time, it is my intention when the Bill is passed to press forward vigorously with the making of Orders, and I am sure I can count on the co-operation of all trading interests in doing this.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I should say that I have in the course of preparation a further Bill to provide a code of protection for the consumer generally.  I commend this Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>As this is the Minister's first appearance in the Seanad I should like to take the opportunity of welcoming him here and wishing him a peaceful, successful and short term in office.  As the Minister indicated in his concluding remarks, this Bill is a limited measure.  If one has reference to the Acts of 1887 and 1931 one will realise that the measure we are considering this afternoon will give only limited protection to the consumer. Nevertheless, it is a useful and necessary Bill and the Minister is to be complimented on bringing the previous legislation reasonably up to date.  As the Minister has emphasised in his speech, the aim of this Bill is to protect both the consumer and, what is very important, to protect the <i>bona fide</i> manufacturers, wholesalers and importers. From his own knowledge of business, the Minister will agree with me when I say that nowadays the conscientious trader is experiencing very severe competition from large traders whose methods of trading are not, to say the least of it, either fair or completely honest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill is limited in its objectives <Col N="288" /> and is concerned only that on the container as such there is a notice which is easily visible and which states clearly the quantity of the goods in the container by weight, measure or number, as may be specified in the order.  It is clear that a greater measure of protection relative to the actual quality of the goods in the container is required and it is hoped that the Minister will push this legislation that was promised by his predecessor.  It is hoped that the Minister will bring comprehensive legislation before the Oireachtas to protect consumers' interests.</P>
    <P>As the Minister has said, packaging of all types and sizes of products has been expanded enormously in recent years and with the increasing tempo of life and the necessity to save labour and ease the drudgery of the housewife, it will increase even further in the years ahead.</P>
    <P>In the Bill a container is described as something in which goods are packed at any time before being offered for sale and include a bag, bottle, box, can, carton, envelope, net, sack or wrapper. It is interesting at this stage to refer to the 1887 Act in which a container was described as a cover which included any casket, bottle, vessel, cover, capsule, case, frame or wrapper.  The House will note that there have been certain deletions.  For instance, the words &ldquo;frame, case&rdquo; have been deleted and I am wondering that if the word &ldquo;box&rdquo; as referred to in the present Bill, is intended to cover a case or frame.</P>
    <P>The Act of 1887 was specifically intended to prohibit the forging of trade marks.  To an extent, it was a negative provision.  Its sole purpose was to ensure that a manufacturer or trader did not forge a mark on a bag or wrapper or some such container.  The Act of 1931 updated the 1887 Act to some extent but did not cover the necessary protection of the consumer. Therefore, what the Minister is doing in this Bill is updating the Merchandise Marks Bills of 1887 and 1931 without dealing comprehensively or widely enough with the problem as it affects the buying public today.</P>
    <P>The Bill defines goods as anything which is the subject of trade, manufacture <Col N="289" /> or merchandise.  This is a very wide description and I trust that when he is replying the Minister will cover this point.  Is it intended that the Bill will cover such goods as imported grain that is now largely handled in bulk, as well as other feedstuffs such as oil cakes and so on?  Does it cover such goods as shirts and other articles which are now offered for sale in cellophane containers?  Does it cover hardware items such as nails?  Does it cover bacon which is now often packed in cellophane wrappers?  Does it cover newspapers and magazines which come in wrappers?  Is it intended to cover the import of cars, CKD &mdash; completely knocked down?  I hope the Minister will clear this point when he is replying.</P>
    <P>A further difficulty which was mentioned during the Dáil debate and which was appreciated by both the Minister and his predecessor was that of the small size of the Irish market.  Are exporters from foreign countries who deal with a vast home public likely to conform to the Minister's quantity and sizes to conform with our legislation? It is most unlikely that they would. Perhaps the Minister has already considered this point and made provision for it in the Bill.</P>
    <P>The Bill contains a number of sections permitting the Minister to make orders in certain circumstances.  I foresee a difficulty in making such orders particularly if the goods in question are perishable.  I am thinking of the possible delays that could occur if the procedure in making the order were to be held up in regard to the importation of articles of a perishable nature.  I notice that the Bill provides for the publication of Ministerial orders in at least one daily newspaper. Why not in at least two daily newspapers?</P>
    <P>Further on in the Bill there is reference to prior consultation with such persons as appear to the Minister to be substantially interested in the general subject matter of the order.  That section was discussed at some length in the Dáil and I should like the Minister to clarify the expression in the section which says persons who appear to him to be substantially interested.  Does this mean groups of traders or does it mean <Col N="290" /> traders' associations, or bodies like the Confederation of Irish Manufacturers? Would the Minister elaborate on the phrase &ldquo;substantially interested&rdquo;? What does &ldquo;interested&rdquo; mean?  Does it mean the interest of the manufacturer or of the importer or does it mean the interest of the public?</P>
    <P>The Bill goes on, in section 3 (1), to refer to an authorised officer and confines the officer to mean a person authorised in writing by the Minister or by the council of a county or corporation of a county or other borough. What qualifications will such an officer require?  It is not stated in the Bill. I wonder if the Minister has any specific officer in mind, such as a health officer.  Would the Minister, having regard to recent legislation bringing the new health authorities into existence, not consider an officer attached to a health authority would be a more appropriate officer, or at least as appropriate an officer as an officer employed by a corporation or county council, to deal with those matters?</P>
    <P>The Bill goes on, in section 4 (1), to refer to a person who contravenes, or is deemed to contravene.  What does the expression &ldquo;deemed to contravene&rdquo; mean?  Deemed by whom? Those are specific points in the Bill that I should be grateful if the Minister would advert to in his reply.</P>
    <P>Generally, on a wider basis, I should like to refer again to the urgent necessity for bringing in comprehensive legislation.  As the Minister is aware, this is an age of gimmicks, impulse buying, price saving, real or alleged, lost leaders <i>et cetera,</i> all calculated to make the consumer buy more than he or she wants.  In the rat race, which a large section of the retail trade has become, the big operator, often foreign-owned and controlled, is spreading rapidly at the expense of the smaller trader who cannot afford the costly ballyhoo of TV and press advertising which the big companies indulge in.</P>
    <P>That is an aspect of the unfair trading and unfair competition which I referred to at the outset.  I hope the comprehensive legislation which the Minister has in mind will deal with that.  Furthermore, the small man cannot <Col N="291" /> afford to produce his own packs in non-standard weights and sizes which are part and parcel of the highpowered campaign to persuade &ldquo;Mrs. Citizen&rdquo; that she is getting better value for money.  In this regard the Bill has done a good service to the small trader in that a 1b pot of jam is a 1b pot of jam and it is not just good value because it happens to be 12 ozs at the same price or slightly less.  Those unfair and near fraudulent practices can be stopped only by comprehensive legislation in the interests of the consumer, the honest manufacturer, importer and packer.</P>
    <P>The Bill should also put a stop to the practice of offering certain commodities, such as butter, at an under-cost price to entice the consumer in to pay more for other goods, possibly non-food lines.  In the final analysis every business, every corporation, every trader, however large or small, must make a profit.  It is obvious, even if they sell certain everyday commodities such as butter, bread, tea or sugar at under-cost prices, &ldquo;Mrs. Citizen&rdquo; will pay something more for something else.  Those generally are the points I have to make on this Bill.</P>
    <P>The Bill, as I said, and I do not think the Minister claims anything more for it, is a limited measure.  It brings the preceding legislation on merchandise marks up to date but I suggest to the Minister that what is required in this country today, having regard to the enormous development in trading of all types, particularly the new type of gimmick trading, what the consumer needs for his or her protection more than anything else is a measure which will guarantee not only the size of the package, the weight of the contents or the number of items in a package but more than that the quality of the article in the package. Until such time as we have comprehensive legislation covering this particular aspect of packaged goods we cannot guarantee a fair deal to the consumer or indeed to the <i>bona fide</i> manufacturer and trader.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Like Senator Russell, I begin by welcoming the Minister to the House, but unlike Senator <Col N="292" /> Russell I would not hope his stay would be a short one.  Neither does the country hope that his stay will be a short one.</P>
      <P>We can all welcome the Bill before us as giving a certain measure of protection to the consumer.  Indeed it is something which is largely overdue in view of the many gimmicks that are at present being used in merchandise.  The Minister's idea of standard packages is a good one if it can be workable, where he has taken the power to lay down by order standards which will suit different commodities.  This becomes of urgent importance now when we are faced with changing over to the metric system because once we start on grammes, kilogrammes and so on it is God help the poor housewife where she sees that a 1b will no longer be a 1b but will be 454 grammes. You would not miss a few grammes out of a package with that amount on a label.</P>
      <P>I suggest to the Minister that the preparation for the change-over is of course now urgent and he should go a bit further than he goes in the Bill before the House, and if he could see that all packages for at least some eight or ten years after the change-over date carry, as well as having the price displayed as so much for this tin or this package, also on the same tag the cost per 1b of the commodity.</P>
      <P>The lb is the only yardstick that the housewife will understand for at least the next eight or ten years.  She can appreciate what a 1b means, whether it be tea or sugar, and consequently when we are having packages labelled in various sizes like a ¼ 1b, maybe some packages might be 10 ozs or when the metric system comes in we will have 200 grammes, 300 grammes and maybe 500 grammes.  Those are the standard sizes you will find displayed in continental shops, so obviously we will have those displayed quite quickly after the metric system comes in.  The labels should have on the packages, say, 300 grammes so much, 1 1b so much, so that the housewife can look at the standard and make her judgment based on that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is, of course, the necessity for quality control.  I know that is not difficult but surely the quality that we <Col N="293" /> are most interested in, or should be most interested in, is the place of origin of the product, because it is very noticeable at present that Irish goods are played down in all merchandising, especially in the super stores which are in many cases controlled largely from outside Ireland.  One finds that the foreign product is put in the best selling position and our own products are jumbled together so that no longer is it possible to be confronted with the fact that one product is Irish and another is not Irish.</P>
    <P>Our future survival depends on getting that confrontation to the buyers. Let us face facts.  The Buy Irish campaign has been a dismal failure during the past three or four years.  The methods used have been completely ineffective.  They have been pitched at too high a key.  In new legislation the Minister should see that above all else the origin of the goods is made clear and that the Irish language is not used to conceal a Danish product&mdash;that the origin of the product is marked clearly.  I suggest it is urgently necessary for the Minister to look again at our position in this respect and see what he can do to revitalise the Buy Irish campaign for the days ahead.</P>
    <P>I do not think there is anything else I wish to say except that allied to the metric system is the use of the decimal coinage.  An advertisement which states &ldquo;Interest at 5½ per cent&rdquo; does not attract, but the use of 5.5 per cent seems to mean an enormous amount. Everybody knows that 5½ is between five and six but if an article carries on the outside the information that its weight is 5.5 ounces, the housewife is confused by it.  I wish the Minister well when he comes to tackle both the transition to the metric system and the restoring of the Buy Irish campaign to its rightful place.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeggyFarrell" hpid="Mrs. Farrell Mrs. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to join in the welcome to the Minister and I wish him well in his new position.  He has a heavy and onerous task as Minister for Industry and Commerce.  I hope he will be there, I am sure he will be there, for many years to give us the service of the legislation we want in this country.  I speak as one of the few <Col N="294" /> housewives in the Seanad and I welcome the Bill, narrow as it is.  I have one objection to it but the Minister has promised us much wider legislation which I suggest will not come before its time.</P>
      <P>One of the points I should like made clear is how the weights of tinned food will be displayed.  I do not consider the present method sufficient in relation to tins or packages.  Tinned fruit is a commodity which has enjoyed a boom period in this country. As we get more affluent we are inclined to use these foods more.  The weights vary enormously and I should like to see some system introduced to show us the volume of liquid contained in tins.  This may seem to be an impossible task but if the weight of the fruit in the tin could be displayed it would be a good thing because a little bit of subtraction would then ascertain the weight of the liquid. Housewives are not always as gullible as people lead us to believe.</P>
      <P>There is one practice which I have noted.  Frequently I pick up a packet and see &ldquo;threepence off&rdquo; or &ldquo;sixpence off&rdquo;.  The price at a number of shillings is mentioned and when I ask the attendant if there is threepence off the packet I am blandly told no.  I suggest that the price should be displayed without any gimmickly.  This &ldquo;threepence off&rdquo; and &ldquo;sixpence off&rdquo; is being used unfairly more and more in the sale of products.  It is something the Minister should note and if he cannot do anything about it under this legislation he should do it in the comprehensive legislation he will be introducing in the near future.  If this were a comprehensive piece of legislation I could talk for a very long time on many of the problems we are faced with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is not confined to what is in the Bill.  On the Second Stage she is entitled to talk about matters not in the Bill, if she wishes to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeggyFarrell" hpid="Mrs. Farrell Mrs. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, but I have not a great deal prepared.  I will not enlarge on what I intend to say. I should like, however, to refer to the surfeit of misleading advertisements and to the gimmicks being used. <Col N="295" /> Not alone should the Minister investigate the matter of weights on packets and tins but he should also look at the advertising being done in publications and on television and radio to sell articles.  If you follow manufacturers' instructions on some things&mdash;I am not referring to anything specific&mdash;you find that the product does not bear out the claims of the manufacturers.  The best that can be said for this practice is that it is misleading and some broad comprehensive Bill is necessary to do something about it.  Such a measure was brought in in England two years ago but we need our own type of legislation here.  I understand that in England it has not been too easy to get convictions under the Act in spite of the care being taken.</P>
      <P>For too long consumers have been exploited.  This has not been done by every manufacturer but as it goes on more and more and women in particular are subjected to great pressures to buy products.  Something should be done about pressure advertising in this country.  A lot of women will say they are not subject to this but if we listen often enough to an advertisement we are inclined in the end to say there is something in it.</P>
      <P>I should like to refer to clothing, particularly.  A lot of clothing is being sold in packets, packed, and when one goes to look at a garment one is told not to remove the garment from the packet.  One is told: &ldquo;There is one open for your inspection&rdquo;.  This is tantamount to buying a pig in a poke. Although it is hygienic, it makes it easier to sell merchandise when it is in polythene packs and some written guarantee should be given that such garments will be taken back if something is wrong with them.  One can come up against a situation where a garment is sold packed in a polythene bag.  One buys it in good faith, takes it home and opens it and finds it is soiled.  It is very difficult to persuade any shopkeeper that one did not soil the garment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the package there should be some declaration of intent on the part of the manufacturer of the merchandise to replace goods to be found not to be <Col N="296" /> up to standard and which are returned within a specified time.  I welcome this Bill but I feel it is a bit narrow.  As far as it goes it is very good.  We hope we will have the broader legislation which is required for the protection not alone of the consumer but also of the honest trader.  We hope this legislation will come along shortly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with the other Senators in congratulating the Minister on his appointment and I wish him every success while he continues as Minister.</P>
      <P>There are four main points which I wish to make on the Bill before the House, before I take advantage of the ruling of the Leas-Chathaoirleach with regard to the general matter of merchandise marks legislation.  My first point has been pretty well made.  It was written in 1952 when the first report of the well-known Moloney Committee on Consumer Protection was published.  The report stated with regard to the matter which is in this Bill:</P>
      <P>After undesirable advertising and door to door sales practices, the most common source of our representers' complaints was the use of deceptive containers for prepacked goods.</P>
      <P>Since 1952, 18 years ago, the Minister, his predecessors and their advisers have had the opportunity of considering that report among others, and among other literature published on this subject.  The report found that a high proportion of the housewives' weekly purchases were prepackaged.  It drew attention to the various forms of deception which resulted from the lack of control.</P>
      <P>In this Bill it is now proposed to impose such necessary control.  One form of deception was to have a non-transparent jar or box which contained less than the full quantity but which was marked &ldquo;3d off&rdquo;.  The 3d was well covered by what was not in the non-transparent jar.  The second deception was where the container was so designed and had such thickness that it would seem capable of holding more than it did hold.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Our colleagues across the sea sometimes do not move fast either.  It took them 11 years to adopt the particular <Col N="297" /> recommendation of the Moloney Report on this matter.  They adopted the recommendation having regard to the words of that report with regard to this matter which were:</P>
    <P>We are bound to regard the problem as one of weights and measures.</P>
    <P>In fact, the legislation which provides for this matter in Britain, enacted in 1963, is not merchandise marks legislation at all.  It is weights and measures legislation.  If Senator Farrell wants to know how they treated fruit she will find it in their 1963 Act.  It may be expected that this is how fruit will be treated here.</P>
    <P>We have delayed enacting legislation. This form of the legislation does not seem suitable.  Why was this introduced as merchandise marks legislation?  This may be because of the personnel available to enforce it.  I do not wish to make a technical point about this.  I am merely curious to know why this legislation has the form of a merchandise marks Bill when it would seem to be a weights and measures Bill.</P>
    <P>The third point is that the Bill is lacking in one matter which is important. I propose to put down an amendment on the Committee Stage. There is no provision in this Bill for any civil remedy.  There is no provision whereby anybody damaged personally, by reason of the fact that somebody committed a crime for which he can be prosecuted under this Bill, can seek a civil remedy.  There is no provision whereby such a person can recover damages.  I do not think there is any general law which would give a litigant any right civilly to recover damages if he lost a considerable sum of money as a result of a crime.  We may be talking about considerable sums.  Perhaps one might order a large quantity. I do not know who might be packaging or who might be buying.  This information is available to the Minister.</P>
    <P>The Minister might feel disposed to accept an amendment on those lines, but I should prefer if he drafted it rather than I did.  The effect of the existing merchandise marks legislation would certainly need to be provided for.  Under the existing legislation if one bought goods under a particular trade <Col N="298" /> description and was handed an appropriate piece of paper, whereby the seller chose to do so, the seller could opt out of the obligations of the Act. In fact, under the Merchandise Marks Act there were provisions for civil remedies but persons with those civil remedies were summarily deprived of them because the vendor sometimes handed a piece of paper, which was never looked at, which would mean that the provisions of the Merchandise Marks Act were being excluded.  If there is to be a civil remedy under this Bill to be given to the purchaser of goods which are being sold in breach of this Act there should be a provision to the further effect that nobody selling would be entitled to oblige the other chap to contract out of it.  There should be no right in a purchaser to contract out of his remedies.</P>
    <P>The fourth general point is by way of preface to very strong urging on my part on the Minister and the Department to expedite, even at the risk of making wrong decisions in relation to what might be enacted, the enactment of the comprehensive codification of the merchandise marks code which has been notoriously deficient in the extent to which it has been enforced.</P>
    <P>We will have to become very shrewd about our own affairs.  The increasing freedom of trade will mean that our producers and manufacturers will be faced with more competition from large international units.</P>
    <P>We could protect our home market not by tariffs which are prohibited but either by closing the back door or by making it more difficult to get inside it. One of the ways to make it more difficult for foreign producers and manufacturers to compete with home producers and manufacturers would be to have a very stiff merchandise marks code which they would not be in the habit of complying with.  The merchandise marks code in Britain is in the same need of revision, codification and improvement as our own.</P>
    <P>Firstly there is a provision in existing legislation whereby a vendor can warrant the accuracy of the trade description yet can in fact contract out of his liability.  I think this should be provided against in any new legislation. <Col N="299" /> Secondly, a retailer who incurs a liability to a customer in respect of a breach of the merchandise marks code and is found guilty should be in a position to pass back the liability to the person who originally broke the code so that the true offender can be punished, because under the existing code the final retailer is responsible. Thirdly, the definition of trade description in the Merchandise Marks Act, 1887, states that&mdash;</P>
    <P>a trade description means any description as to the number, quantity, measure, gauge or weight of any goods.</P>
    <P>It does not include any description of the size of any goods.  It does not include any description as to the newness or otherwise of the goods.  Those goods may have been bought at a CIE auction yet they can be described without breach of the merchandise marks code as &ldquo;new&rdquo;.  It does not include giving a wrong date of manufacture An old date may be good if one is selling an antique and likewise a new date may be good if one is selling an up-to-date product.  It does not include any description as to who the previous owners were or its history whether, for example, it was bought from a sale of bankrupt stock.  It does not include any description which would involve a claim that there was a genuine marking down of the goods.  A shop can, without being in breach of the merchandise marks code, sell at the same or at a higher price goods which it has previously had on offer at the same or at a lower price.</P>
    <P>I think the question of advertising should be made a subject of the merchandise marks code so that an advertiser when he is advertising his product would be aware that the language he is using may be applied as a language for a trade description of the goods he is selling and he may become liable, because of his application of that language under this code, for an offence.</P>
    <P>It has been suggested, and this is the sort of matter which Senator Farrell would be particularly interested in, that care should be a general legal requirement.  That is to say goods <Col N="300" /> could not be sold without saying whether or not they were washable, at which temperature they should be washed and at what temperature they should be ironed, what tolerance or shrinking would be.  Statutory definition should be given to words such as &ldquo;pre-shrunk&rdquo; or &ldquo;shrink resistance&rdquo;. These matters are of considerable importance to consumers and necessary for their protection.  There are a whole range of new fibres and established terms are applied to them whereas they require entirely different consideration. Statutory powers should be conferred so as to promulgate definitions of textile terms which could not be used without the parties using them being in breach.  The Moloney Report stated that worsted which has always been closely associated with wool technically means arranging the strands of the fibre in a particular fashion.  If manufacturers do not give a particular definition they are not in breach of the code.</P>
    <P>I think the whole question of labelling should be considered.  The requirement to give in words a full description of what the consumer is getting should be extended so as to give legal protection to the public.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FarrellMcElgunn" hpid="Mr. McElgunn Mr. McElgunn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McElgunn</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom fáilte a chur roimh an Aire, ar a theacht anseo in a phost nua mar Aire Thionscail agus Tráchtála.  Tá súil agam go mbeidh toradh fónta ar a shaothar.</P>
      <P>I welcome this Bill which, as the Minister said in his opening speech, is for the protection of the consumers. Although I feel the Bill is rather narrow, it is a step in the right direction. For far too long the public have been exposed to advertising abuses and false competition.  I know one particular produce where approximately one-fifth of the cost goes towards the contents of the package and the rest is spent on advertising, packaging and merchandising.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister mentioned in his speech the change in the methods of merchandising from the days when one watched the assistant weigh everything on the scales to the present days of pre-packaged food.  I think the Bill is trying to get back to the old sense <Col N="301" /> of values.  I do not know what the benefit will be.  Other Senators have mentioned Irish goods offered for sale in supermarkets.  I should like to comment on this because I have noticed that in most supermarkets, especially those belonging to big chains, very often Irish goods are pushed into the background while British manufactured goods are kept at the forefront. I am glad that Senator FitzGerald referred to the necessity for a strict measure of control as regards honesty in packaging and so on.</P>
    <P>The last point I wish to make is that in this country, in which by and large there are large families, food still plays a large part in the budget of the average housewife.  I cannot understand why the housewife cannot buy goods in bulk when such goods are available in large quantities to hotels and institutions.  Since hotels and institutions can buy in catering packs I take it that those packs are available but they are not available in our shops or supermarkets.</P>
    <P>Another commodity about which I should like to comment is baby foods. These baby foods are available only in tiny packages.  Many families who live in my district have twins&mdash;one have triplets&mdash;and when these parents, as well as those having only one healthy child, go along to purchase baby food they find that they must take home a separate basketful of these small packets.  I cannot see why these foods cannot be purchased in larger and more economic packs.  A lot of what I had intended to say has already been said by other Senators.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnNash" hpid="Mr. Nash Mr. Nash">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Nash</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom fíorchian fáilte a chur roimh an Aire ina phost nua.  Táim cinnte go nobróchaí sé go dian diachallach agus táim cinnte go néireochaí leis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome this Bill.  I should have liked to have seen it presented on a much wider basis but I hope that in the near future it will be followed by much more comprehensive legislation. There are a few comments that I should like to make on the Bill.  Section 2 (1) (c) provides that the goods will bear a notice which states specifically the <Col N="302" /> quantity of the goods in the container by weight, measure or number and, if the Minister thinks fit, the name and address of the importer of the goods. That provision may help to cut out the practice of goods being offered for sale as having being manufactured in Ireland while, in fact, they were manufactured abroad.  If the Minister could see his way to putting an addition to that subsection to the effect that if the goods are imported it should be specified that they have been manufactured abroad.  This, to some extent, would mitigate against the practice of many supermarket owners who import vast quantities of goods from factories which they own abroad.  It would mitigate against the damage which those supermarkets do to Irish manufactured goods which are at least equal to and sometimes better than the quality of the imported ones.</P>
    <P>Reference was made to the fact that certain tinned fruits are offered for sale for which the amount of fruit is not specified as distinct from the liquid. From my reading of the Bill that is covered in subsection (2) of section 2 because it is stated in that subsection that the goods shall not include any quantity of liquid or other substance added to the goods at the time at which they were packed in the container.</P>
    <P>However, there are other ways in which some of those supermarkets play confidence tricks on the unfortunate purchasers.  For instance, a price is quoted for a particular commodity and the purchaser may believe that that is the net price, but when he goes to the check-out he will find that he must pay turnover tax.  This tax has now been increased to 5 per cent so that on goods amounting to £5 he will have to pay £5 5s.  It is my belief that the price quoted should be the net price, to include turnover tax.</P>
    <P>In more comprehensive legislation I should like to see a provision inserted whereby the implied convenant under the Sale of Goods Act should be stated very precisely.  One of the biggest frauds in the sale of goods in Ireland relates to the motor trade.  The average purchaser of any car receives what he considers to be a guarantee.  He gets a document on which the word &ldquo;guarantee&rdquo; is written in big lettering at the <Col N="303" /> top but in smaller lettering further down he will notice that he forgoes any claim whatsoever which he may have under the Sale of Goods Act. The Sale of Goods Act, by implication, gives to every purchaser a very specific guarantee that what he buys is up to a certain standard and is reasonably fit for the purpose for which it was bought.  However, this so-called guarantee merely states that if a complaint is made within six months of purchase the defective part will be supplied free of cost.  If, therefore, one purchases a motor car and finds that that car has a defective cylinder or piston, this may mean that the unfortunate man is put to the expense of £50 or £80 for having his entire engine taken down, but under this so-called guarantee all he gets is the price of a new piston, ten shillings or 15/-, and he is at a loss of his £80.  This in my view is little better than fraud.</P>
    <P>If the protection which a customer has under the Sale of Goods Act is removed from him in the sale of any particular type of goods it should be expressed in no uncertain terms that the purchaser is forfeiting his rights under the Sale of Goods Act and forfeiting the normal guarantee which applies to every purchaser.  Time after time and month after month I meet unfortunate people who are put to enormous expense in the purchase of mass manufactured motor cars and mass manufactured motor cycles which many of them can ill afford.  They are entitled to compensation of anything from £1 to 30/- and they have been put to an expense of anything from £80 to £100.</P>
    <P>There is not very much else I wish to say about this Bill.  It is very good in so far as it goes.  It is very useful but I should like if the Minister could see his way on Committee Stage of this Bill to introduce an amendment which could very easily be added, as I say, to section 2 (1) (c) which would provide that if goods are manufactured abroad that should be clearly stated on the label or on the notice that is attached to the goods.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLalor" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lalor) Patrick J. Lalor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lalor)</NameTxt>
      <P>First of all I must <Col N="304" /> say I am very pleased and happy to find myself welcomed to this House from all sides by all of the Senators who have spoken.  I appreciate the welcome extended to me and irrespective of the length of time, I hope as Minister for Industry and Commerce that during my term of office I shall be in a position to live up to the high standards this House might expect from such a Minister.</P>
      <P>As I anticipated when speaking earlier, this measure has received the welcome of the House as a whole.  I appreciate the fact that the Bill does not go to the extent to which some Members of the House would want it to go.  As conveyed in the final part of my statement, there is a further Bill in course of preparation concerned with the protection of the consumer as such.</P>
      <P>Senator Russell, the first Senator who spoke, went into a number of details in connection with certain sections of the Bill that might possibly be dealt with more comprehensively on Committee Stage.  Senator FitzGerald and Senator Nash mentioned the possibility of amendments in relation to the Bill, so perhaps it might be as well for me to deal with those matters while they are fresh in my mind.  Senator FitzGerald said that there is no provision in the Bill for any civil remedy in the event of the purchaser being at a serious loss.  Let me say that the Bill specifically deals with the items being offered for sale by retailers.</P>
      <P>Senator Russell dealt with definitions as such and dealt pretty extensively with the description &ldquo;container&rdquo;. In that definition it is pointed out that &ldquo;container&rdquo; means a container in which goods are packed at any time before being offered for sale by the retailer.  I do not think Senator FitzGerald envisaged a situation whereby some housewife could see herself suing the retailer for any great amount because of the fact that the goods in the container did not measure up to the particular weight or content which was described on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think he visualised a situation where by that retailer, acting as the middleman between the manufacturer or the packer, might find himself very seriously out on a limb and that he might need to take action against the <Col N="305" /> supplier to him arising from a prosecution under this Bill for selling something which was deficient to a consumer.</P>
    <P>Senator Nash referred to action it is possible to take under the Sale of Goods Act.  My understanding is that a private purchaser can take action under that Act but as I have said I do not think this particular type of private action would arise under this Bill and because of that I do not see the necessity for that particular amendment to the Bill.  The Senator might care to follow this matter up or enter into it in a more involved way on the Committee Stage if he so desires.  This aspect of the matter which the Senator fears is covered under the Sale of Goods Act.</P>
    <P>Senator Nash referred specifically to section 2 (1) (c) and suggested that an addition be added to this subsection indicating that if an importer's name is given it may give the impression that the goods are Irish produced and therefore that it is necessary to have an additional subsection there to indicate that those goods have been imported or are of foreign origin. I refer the Senator to section 20 of the Merchandise Marks Act, 1931, which provides that if the name of an Irish manufacturer, trader or dealer appears on an imported article it must be accompanied in a not less conspicuous manner by an indication of the country of origin.  That covers the trader or dealer.</P>
    <P>Senators Quinlan, McElgunn and others referred to a matter which is not covered in the Bill, the down-playing or apparent down-playing by a number of business people in this country of Irish products.  It was also said that foreign produce was upshelved or presented in a more attractive manner &mdash; that great emphasis is placed by those people on the selling of foreign products rather than the Irish counterparts.  Senator Quinlan appealed to me to re-stimulate, in a more realistic way, in a more productive way, the Buy Irish campaign.</P>
    <P>Let me say that any opportunity I have had since I became Minister, when I was contributing by way of speech, I have used to stress the <Col N="306" /> economic need, the economic advantage and the industrial advantage, of purchasing quality Irish goods.  I have spelled out the fact that I do not intend to qualify specifically my Buy Irish campaign enthusiasm by simply and solely suggesting that we just buy Irish goods irrespective of their quality.  I am satisfied&mdash;this has been proved by the expanding exports of many of our manufactured articles&mdash;that we have produce which exceeds in many cases and at least equals much of the material being imported here and being sold here in competition with Irish goods.</P>
    <P>I will use every opportunity to encourage the purchase of quality Irish goods and I will stress the economic advantages of so doing.  I will stress the advantages of buying and selling Irish goods, because both go together. Unfortunately I find there is a degree of justification for the claims made by Senators who condemn or criticise the selling of foreign manufactured articles here against home produced goods.  I do not want to be taken as defending any Irish produce which does not measure up to the standard of the equivalent imported, but I have no hesitation in saying that there is need to remind and to encourage people to buy quality Irish goods which are at least equal in quality to the imported article.  I assure the House that I do not need any pushing in this respect. On the other hand, I welcome all constructive suggestions as to how I can best effect this.  One of the obvious advantages is that it will keep more Irish people employed at home and at the same time improve our balance of payments.</P>
    <P>Senator Russell spoke of the goods covered by the Bill.  The Bill covers all goods, not specifically groceries. The orders will be applied to specific goods and initially, following the enactment of the Bill, they will probably largely be made in relation to groceries.  However, all goods may be covered.  Of course an order would not apply to imported grain in bulk because the Bill relates only to goods in packages.  If grain came in containers or packages an order could be applied to it.</P>
    <P>The Senator mentioned that protection <Col N="307" /> in relation to the quality of goods is required.  This was referred to by a number of Senators.  The matter of informative labelling of goods will be dealt with in the Consumer Protection Bill which I will be introducing in the near future.  I am mindful of the general demands of Senators to have this legislation introduced as soon as possible.</P>
    <P>I wish to state that there is no ulterior motive, no peculiar background, to the removal of &ldquo;case&rdquo; or &ldquo;frame&rdquo; from the definition of containers. The definition is designed to cover all forms of package in general use today.  Senator Russell queried whether the Bill could embrace imported articles, whether it could lay down that goods in retail packets might be marked before importation.  I have power to admit goods which arrive unmarked at a port subject to condition that the goods be suitably marked immediately on importation.</P>
    <P>Senator Russell asked about one section&mdash;I thought some of the sections lent themselves more to Committee Stage &mdash; and said that insertion of Government notices should be in at least two daily newspapers.  This section follows the normal pattern of insertions of this nature.  Publication is usually effected in all daily newspapers and there is no specific reason for making provision for at least one.  It is the usual form and I do not see any reason why we should make it a provision of the Bill that more than one newspaper be spelled out.</P>
    <P>Senator Russell asked what authorised officer we have in mind in relation to the work to be carried on under section 3.  That inspector would be an officer of my Department or of a local authority especially selected for the purpose of enforcing the legislation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>Would that officer have any special qualifications?  Would he be a health officer?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLalor" hpid="Mr. Lalor Mr. Lalor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lalor</NameTxt>
      <P>Not specifically.  In relation to what Senator FitzGerald mentioned there would be a point of making use to a great extent of local authority officers who at present handle weights and measures.  Senator FitzGerald <Col N="308" /> asked why this was a merchandise marks Bill rather than a weights and measures Bill.  The reasons are purely technical ones.  The Weights and Measures Act deals with weights and measures equipment.  The Merchandise Marks Act deals with marking on goods and their containers.  The present Bill is more appropriately called the Merchandise Marks Bill.  The Senator raised this in relation to the fact that the UK Government brought in a Weights and Measures Act to deal with similar problems.  In this country something is to be done which deals with packets such as giving their weight. This legislation deals with goods and their containers.  The Senator is welcome to his opinion on the title to be given to the Bill.</P>
      <P>I was interested to hear the Senator's observations on the Moloney Committee Report.  This was a British Government report.  The findings related to Britain.  I do not recollect clearly what the position was in 1952 but at the present time there does not seem to be evidence of widespread abuse here.  The introduction of this Bill might be regarded as more preventive than curative.  The report of 1952 in relation to Britain would not have been applicable here even at that time.  Eighteen years ago pre-packed goods were not making any great impact here.  At that time consumers could see most of their goods being weighed and balanced on scales.  The Moloney Report related to consumer protection in Britain, not to the position here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Farrell mentioned her problem in relation to tinned foods and expressed the hope I would hasten the introduction of a further Bill in relation to that and further matters. I am conscious of the &ldquo;3d off&rdquo; gimmick. Under this Bill I hope to be able to make orders concerning some of the gimmicks.  In relation to canned produce I refer Senator Farrell to section 2 (2) of this Bill.  I can make an order requiring that the quantity of a container, excluding juice or water, shall be put on the container.  I am taking powers under this Bill to deal with that point.  One must understand that a great deal of consultation is envisaged in this Bill with consumers, <Col N="309" /> manufacturers and suppliers in order to arrive at a suitable formula for such marking.  This is one of the things aimed at under this legislation.</P>
    <P>I wish to thank the House for the personal welcome I received and to thank the Senators for the welcome they have given to this Bill.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage ordered for the next sitting day after tomorrow, 4th June, 1970.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Business suspended at 6.10 p.m. and resumed at 7.30 p.m.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Sea Fisheries (Amendment) Bill, 1970:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Sea Fisheries (Amendment) Bill, 1970: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackieFahey" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries (Mr. Fahey) John (Jackie) Fahey">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries (Mr. Fahey)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this short Bill is twofold.  Firstly, it is to enable An Bord Iascaigh Mhara to continue to borrow money from the Central Fund as it has been doing for many years and secondly it is to broaden the general powers of the board to borrow from other sources.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Sea Fisheries Act, 1952, under which the board was established enabled the Minister for Finance, on the recommendation of the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries, to advance money to the board from time to time out of the Central Fund but the Act also restricted to £500,000 the aggregate amount that could be so advanced. After some years it became clear that the upper limit of the borrowings was no longer high enough.  The limit was, therefore, raised to £1 million by an amending Act in 1956 and to £3 million by a second amending Act in 1959.  The 1952 Act also provided that the board must repay to the Minister for Finance the advances from the Central Fund in half-yearly instalments with interest.  A 20 year repayment period is being operated for the repayment of each advance.  The board use the funds advanced to them from the Central Fund to give loans for the purchase of fishing vessels and the repayments by the vessel owners provide the funds that <Col N="310" /> enable the board to repay the advances from the Central Fund.</P>
    <P>The accumulated amount of the board's borrowings from the Central Fund since their establishment in 1952 has now reached the figure of £2,999,563 or for all practical purposes the limit of £3 million at present permitted by the Acts.  The fact that the sum of £1,281,328 has been repaid or written off leaving the board's net indebtedness at £1,718,235 cannot be taken into account because of the wording of the 1952 Act which relates the maximum permitted figure of £3 million borrowing to the aggregate of all the borrowings over the whole period irrespective of what has been repaid.</P>
    <P>For the continued development of the fishing industry it is essential that the board should be in a position to continue to make loans available for the purchase of fishing vessels and fishing gear.  For that reason it is proposed in this Bill to raise the maximum amount of the board's permitted borrowings to £5 million and to provide that the new figure relates not as heretofore to the total amount borrowed but to the amount the repayment of which is outstanding at any time.  The board's borrowings are at present running at about £500,000 a year and so the increase in the upper limit should provide for the board's needs for the greater part of the present decade.</P>
    <P>While the foregoing outlines the essential purpose of this Bill, the opportunity is being availed of to provide for a useful amendment to one other borrowing power of the board as it is thought that the amendment may possibly be of advantage at some time in the future.  Section 22 of the 1952 Act enables the board with the consent of the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries given after consultation with the Minister for Finance to borrow temporarily by arrangement with bankers for current purposes.  Those borrowings have in practice been limited to occasional small bank overdraft of sums not exceeding £50,000.</P>
    <P>It has been felt that the provisions of Section 22 of the Act are too restrictive in confining the board's borrowings (other than its borrowings <Col N="311" /> from the Central Fund) to borrowings that are temporary, that are only through bankers and that are only for current purposes.  In case that at some time in the future more flexibility may be needed, the opportunity is being taken in the Bill to relax these restrictions by means of the provision in Section 2 of this Bill which will enable the board, if it so desires, to negotiate both long term and short term loans. It will also remove the restriction that borrowings must be arranged through bankers and finally it will make it possible for the board to borrow for capital as well as at present for current purposes.</P>
    <P>For the benefit of those Members of Seanad Éireann who may not be fully familiar with the role of An Bord Iascaigh Mhara in the fishing industry, I would like to outline briefly what the board's functions are at present.  The general powers of the board were set out in the 1952 Act in very broad terms but the primary purpose of the board's establishment can be described as the assistance and improvement of all facets of the sea fishing industry.  In its early years the board actively engaged in a number of aspects of the fishing industry including the purchasing, processing and marketing of fish but as the years went by it gradually became clear that some of the board's activities were no longer necessary and that it should concentrate more on promotional and advisory activities.  In 1962 the board's role in the furtherance of Government policy in modern conditions was set out in a White Paper entitled &ldquo;Programme of Sea Fisheries Development&rdquo;. As a result the board has withdrawn completely from active participation in fish processing and marketing and now operates in the role of a development body for the industry. The board's present functions include the administration of a Marine Credit Plan under which grants and loans are given for the purchase of fishing boats and gear; the provision of an advisory service to fishermen to improve fishing techniques and promote co-operation among fishermen: the development of a system of speedy inspection and repair of fishing vessels; the development <Col N="312" /> of markets at home and abroad for fish and fishery products; the encouragement of private investment in worthwhile fish processing undertakings; the operation of three boatyards for the building and repair of fishing boats; and the operation of ice-making plants at some fishing ports where such facilities are not provided by private enterprise.</P>
    <P>The success of the board in these fields can be measured by many sophisticated yardsticks but surely the best indication of the thriving nature of our sea fishing industry at present is the ever-increasing demand by fishermen for more and bigger fishing boats. Many fishermen with the requisite experience of sea fishing are anxious to invest their savings in boats of their own while many others who have proved successful in operating their own boats are now anxious to turn over to larger vessels.  This active demand for boats is without any doubt the best evidence one could wish to get of the progress being achieved in the industry and of the future that lies ahead for our progressive fishing community. There is no question but that this demand for boats must continue to be fostered by the grants and loans scheme operated by An Bord Iascaigh Mhara.  The grants can continue to be made available from funds provided in the Fisheries Vote each year but the scheme of loans for the purchase of fishing vessels can be continued only through the provisions of the present enabling Bill.  It is for this purpose that I recommend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to welcome the Parliamentary Secretary on his first visit to the Seanad and to wish him well in his important post. I should also like to welcome this opportunity of reviewing the progress of An Bord Iascaigh Mhara&mdash;the first time we have had an opportunity of doing so since 1963.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I feel the greatest need in the country, especially in the midlands, at present is that An Bord Iascaigh Mhara should go back in and organise orderly marketing of the end product.  In a small country like this it is deplorable <Col N="313" /> that 20, 30 or 40 miles from the coast it is not possible for the housewife to acquire a supply of fresh fish daily. She might have a chance of getting fish in some state or other on a Thursday evening or Friday.  This is not good enough.  The policy of having a limited number of markets is not one which helps the industry and helps to make fish readily available.  I understand that fish from southern and western ports must be transported right across the country to the markets in Dublin and then brought back on the same route.  That adds to the cost.  It is most distressing for the housewife to hear each morning the very excellent fish market reports when she cannot get fish.  This is a good policy on the part of the board and certainly advertises fish and gives many useful hints but the prices announced over the radio are far from the retail price which the consumers pay over the counter.  All this unnecessary transport certainly adds to the cost.  We have now reached the stage when the cost of transport is greater than the cost of the fish landed on the pier.  The board should look at the decision taken in 1962 and endeavour to reorganise the orderly marketing of fish to ensure that the consumption of fish on the home market will vastly increase.  I should like to ask the Parliamentary Secretary what the possibility will be of supplies being readily available.</P>
    <P>Looking over the recent reports of the board I was more than surprised to see that a large number of trawlers had been seized by the board.  Surely if the situation arises where trawlers which the board originally financed skippers to purchase must be seized in the good old-fashioned way of the last century there must be something radically wrong with the system under which these skippers and fishermen get these boats.  I would ask that the board should seriously re-examine their policy in this respect and ensure that as many of our young and qualified fishermen or people with skippers' licences as possible should be able to work and pursue their livelihood in this way.</P>
    <P>I see from the report also that the number of people employed in this industry, only something like 1,600 <Col N="314" /> people in full-time employment, is indeed very small considering the fact that we have such a very long coastline.  In addition there are only 3,700 in part-time employment.  That is a total of 5,400 between people in full-time and part-time employment.  The board's target should be to greatly increase this figure.  The earning capacity of the industry is disappointing.  From the figures supplied by the board, approximately £3 million worth of fish were landed this year.  To most of us in the midlands the big shock was the fact that the cost of imports of fish amounted to £1.8 million last year.  I quite agree that the Senator and John West salmon may have accounted for the greater proportion of this but I feel that a very serious effort must be made to reduce this high proportion of imports.</P>
    <P>The few people in this country who, in the past, have helped to foster and build up stocks of fish and game have got little or no recognition from the Government and in fact no protection at all.  I very much doubt the sincerity of those who hold fish-ins and shoot-ins. Stocks must surely become depleted if some authority does not look after them and see that the proper nets and so on are used.  This highlights the necessity for an improved fishery research programme.  The board or the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries should spend more money on fishery research.  For our coastline we should have more than one semi-lame vessel attached to this important work. I would ask that the Department and the Parliamentary Secretary should take steps to provide more up-to-date research services so that not only will our fisheries be protected from the point of view of stocking but that these people could also keep an eye to the ever-growing problem of pollution and the effect it is having on the inshore fishing industry.  I also feel that our fisheries and our trawlermen should get better protection from the fishery protection service.</P>
    <P>Perhaps it may be argued this is a matter for the Minister for Defence but nevertheless adequate protection must be an important element in this industry.  It is my opinion that this <Col N="315" /> industry is not being dealt with as enthusiastically as it might and that many of us do not realise the full potential of the industry.  It is not that the Department for Defence are not dealing adequately with the matter but rather that our fisheries protection system is not adequate.  When I was on holiday last year I saw foreign trawlers fishing within sight of our shores.  This is a deplorable situation.  The onus is on the Government and on the Department of Defence to provide adequate protection for those young men who are prepared to undertake the purchasing of fishing trawlers which may cost £30,000 or £50,000.  Young men who put themselves in that sort of debt are very brave and deserve all the help they can get.</P>
    <P>The Department of Agriculture and Fisheries should impress on the Department of Defence the necessity for equipping the Navy to provide adequate protection for the people engaged in this industry.  Figures in the last report show that there has been a 50 per cent increase in home consumption of fish since 1953.  It is my belief that if distribution were organised in orderly fashion, the figures could be dramatically increased.  There appears to be a move away from the theory of fish on a Friday only.  People have become more conscious of the high protein content of fish.</P>
    <P>If the board are to be congratulated the only activity for which I would congratulate them is on the success they have made of the seafood competitions in the secondary and vocational schools.  Those competitions have helped more than anything else to highlight the many attractive ways in which fish can be presented.  During the past few years they have instilled into every young lady in those schools a greater appreciation of the very excellent dish that fish can be.  At competitions in my own county I have been amazed at the number of entries as I have also been amazed at the expertise which these young girls bring to bear in the preparation of fish dishes.  The board and all those girls concerned deserve our appreciation.  Those competitions, which are run under the excellent <Col N="316" /> guidance of our teachers, have helped to get away from the fish on Friday only theory.</P>
    <P>I hope the board will ensure that as many people as possible will be able to retain their boats.  From reading the report of the Dáil debate on this Bill I reached the conclusion that the debate must have been very unsatisfactory because many of the questions posed were not answered by the Minister.  I do not propose to ask the same questions here but I hope that when the Parliamentary Secretary is replying to this debate he will give us an assurance that his Department and An Bord Iascaigh Mhara will do all they can to ensure that those of our people who are engaged in the fishing industry will get a fair crack of the whip and that they will ensure also that a greater part of the profits of the industry will go to the people who catch the fish.</P>
    <P>It cannot be said that this has happened in the past and the time has come when the board must re-enter, to some degree at least, into the distribution of fish.  Markets should be reopened at some of the other ports. This will have the effect of reducing transport costs.  I do not wish to complain about the price of meat which I consider to be still good value for money but, nevertheless, it is my belief that there would be greater consumption of fish if it were more readily available throughout the country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DermotHonan" hpid="Mr. Honan Mr. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>Like the previous speaker, I should like to welcome the Parliamentary Secretary to the House. I am sure he will be able to deal with this Bill very satisfactorily.  It is very important for us as a nation that we should concern ourselves with the development of a most valuable industry that is readily available to us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBelton" hpid="Dr. Belton Dr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DermotHonan" hpid="Mr. Honan Mr. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not an industry for which grants for fertilisers or drainage or anything else are required.  The great Atlantic Ocean and its ancillary seas provide this very remarkable product for us but herein arises a problem. I should like to pay a tribute to An Bord Iascaigh Mhara.  In the <Col N="317" /> days when there was no organised fishing business, I, as a youngster, remember reading in the papers the advertising campaign &ldquo;Let next Friday be a hake Friday&rdquo;.  Every paper carried an advertisement to that effect.  It must be 30 years since I saw a hake. I wonder where they have got themselves to.</P>
      <P>There is a feeling abroad that An Bord Iascaigh Mhara and the people engaged in catching fish and those engaged in marketing them are more concerned with the export market than they are with providing fish for the home market.  Many people would say that in providing the money we are being asked to provide this evening, greater attention should be paid to the home market.  The board have sizeable sales organisations working outside the country, particularly in the sales operations of shellfish.  It has been practically channelled into an export market.  Some time ago most people could afford lobsters but they are almost prohibitive today.</P>
      <P>However, there were sizeable difficulties in the way of development of the fishery industry here if we consider other countries like Norway and Portugal where they go from there to the coast of Canada and where they follow the cod from one end of the world to another.  We have not got the type of boats, the trained personnel or the tradition to do this.  I once met a Swede on the west coast of America who was amazed that we could not recruit the expertise which is required here to activate ourselves in the development of the great Atlantic shelf which goes from 50 to 60 miles off the coast of Ireland.  Many continental boats find it profitable to come and fish those waters.  We find ourselves in the position that while those people are operating outside the new 12-mile limit we have neither the boats nor the people who are capable or willing to undertake the rigours of the Atlantic to pursue this trade.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In Clare we have the Atlantic coastline of something like 90 to 100 miles and we have one of the safest estuarial anchorages possible in the west of <Col N="318" /> Ireland.  It was the haven of the continental fleets which came a long time ago from France and Portugal and you could see as many as a couple of hundred boats anchored there in times of storm.  However, in our 90 miles of coastline we have not one developed fishing port notwithstanding that we had seamen who sailed around the world in the old wind-jammers a long time ago.  We have nobody there now who is prepared to take up fishing because there are no suitable boats available.</P>
    <P>It does not matter how much money is provided in this Bill, the fishing grounds available will be the determining factor whether people will take on this hazardous work of fishing off the Atlantic shelf.  If we do not provide them with the necessary equipment, such as radar stations from which they can take bearings, and boats suitable for the rigours of the Atantic, they will not take up fishing.  Bord Iascaigh Mhara have done a wonderful job in providing inshore fisheries but if we want to get into the big fishing industry we must be prepared to go further afield and we must provide the fishermen with proper equipment, various navigational aids and with the marketing services.</P>
    <P>I know there are skippers of many boats who fished off the west of Ireland who could not hope to get ashore on particular days, have their fish prepared and marketed, and who sold their fish on the high seas to some of the people we accuse of invading our territorial waters because they have a better market out at sea than they have ashore.</P>
    <P>Take the herring harvest for instance. I should like to say that most of the herring is found in the spawning ground and every herring you get is full of roe.  This is the seed they will sow.  We are destroying our herring grounds by allowing those areas to be over-fished.  The day is not too far distant when we will not have any herring ground at all.  I am very fond of herring and I go into one of the fish shops where we get fish, as Senator McDonald said, once a week and I find only tiny little herring there which are only the leavings of what the foreigners <Col N="319" /> buy.  When we are talking about providing money for fishing there is also an obligation on some service, whether it is provided by Bord Iascaigh Mhara or otherwise, to see that the people here who provide the money are at least given an adequate supply of fresh fish rather than have us eating the bits and pieces which are left over after the foreigners have taken the cream of the market.</P>
    <P>The amount of money provided in this Bill is so small that it is not worth arguing about here.  If Bord Iascaigh Mhara want to make a success of the fishing industry they must realise that the Atlantic Shelf is the home of sea fishing and unless we provide harbours, safe anchorages and marketing services along the west coast we will never achieve what this country is capable of achieving in taking our small share from the great fishing industry which exists along the Atlantic Shelf.  I know there are quite a number of profitable fishing operations going on in the more sheltered quarters, but when the Portuguese, the French and Spaniards go off to Canada we are here struggling around the coast while all those other fishing people have boats and gear that could provide us with great wealth.  We have no great expenditure in this other than helping the fishermen to get trained, providing them with the gear and providing them with the types of boats they want.</P>
    <P>This must come out of a tradition which unfortunately we have not got in the west of Ireland.  We have not the boats there to create this.  I know some of the best sailors in the world went out of the Shannon estuary because we had not safe anchorages there and there was no provision for helping them.  All those young people have now left the west coast.</P>
    <P>I, as a member of a vocational education committee, know that when scholarships were offered by Bord Iascaigh Mhara to provide young lads along the coast with special training to equip them to be skippers, and thereafter to provide the means for them to become owners of their own boats, they were unable to take advantage of it because there were no shore-based <Col N="320" /> organisations.  I mentioned the Clare coast because it is the one I know best, but I am sure there are other places on the west coast in the same position.  The Atlantic Shelf is the prize in international fishing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>True.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DermotHonan" hpid="Mr. Honan Mr. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill but I regret it does not go far enough. While the export market seems to be everybody's prize, Bord Iascaigh Mhara should do everything possible to organise a sales service thus providing that the people who invest the money will get at least a reasonable proportion of catches, in the same way as boat skippers give it to their crews.  If we really intend to tackle this matter we must be prepared to make far more money available, to employ more experts with a knowledge of deep-sea fishing, people who are prepared to go to sea and to stay at sea in all kinds of weather.</P>
      <P>It is important to realise that the west, the south and parts of the north coasts are exposed to Atlantic gales and that it is in those areas that the great prize is to be taken, not in ducking in and out of small places.  With the limited resources various Governments have given to them Bord Iascaigh Mhara have done admirable work. Indeed we are not being over-taxed today by the demands they are making on us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDLyons" hpid="Mr. Lyons Mr. Lyons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lyons</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish first of all to welcome the Parliamentary Secretary to the Seanad and to congratulate him on his appointment.  I have known him as a Deputy for some time.  I know he is a decent man and I hope he will listen to the arguments made on behalf of Bord Iascaigh Mhara.  The remarks I will make relate to the whole question of fisheries.  I might as well admit at the beginning that a lot of what I intended to say has been covered by Senator Honan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I see no reason why we on this side should not accept the Bill but I should like to add to that my belief that the board are only scratching the surface of an extremely difficult but extremely rewarding project.  The silver harvest <Col N="321" /> of the sea has never been reaped here.  Everybody has talked about it during the years because everybody knew that around our shores people from other nations have come to rob us of our birthright and we have been able to do very little about it.</P>
    <P>Senator Honan was correct in what he said about deep-sea fishing.  There is no doubt that unless we are prepared to go into deep-sea fishing we will not reap the rewards.  For that, we must have adequate boats with adequate equipment like radar.  Otherwise we shall never reap the full harvest that should be ours.  Inland, 40 miles from the coast, one rarely sees fresh fish. We do not see it in Mayo and this should make everybody think.  When we do get fresh fish we pay exorbitant prices by comparison with what fishermen get after all the hazards they have to brave.</P>
    <P>Bord Iascaigh Mhara may say they are not involved in the marketing of fish.  I agree they are not involved but I suggest they should set up a body that would first and foremost investigate marketing possibilities and secondly the question of the method of distribution so that fish can be on the plate of everybody who wants it and not on Friday only.  Unless we are prepared to approach this problem in the widest possible context, unless we are prepared to do the thing right, unless we are prepared to invest enough money to make fishing not alone a commercial proposition for the people who engage directly in it but also something which is viable in the social sense, we will not get anywhere. The food value of fish is realised to be second to none and it is unfortunate that we should have allowed our opportunities to pass us by.</P>
    <P>Even inshore fishing has not got the facilities it should have been given. Boats on the west coast are exposed to the wide Atlantic but no Department have assumed responsibility for providing the piers, the harbours, the landing slips for those boats.  Mayo and other county councils, already overburdened by rates, have to contribute to the maintenance of piers.  Admittedly piers are renovated and reconstructed by the Board of Works but <Col N="322" /> their maintenance falls on the unfortunate ratepayers.</P>
    <P>Many boats have been lost because they could not tie up in sheltered conditions, because the method of tying up boats is hazardous and out of date. We shall never improve our fishing to any appreciable extent unless we are prepared to invest considerably more in harbours so that boats can come in and unload quickly in modern conditions and so that the fish can be handled quickly in modern conditions and so that storage facilities are brought up to date.  Until we begin to do these things we are only nibbling at the problem.</P>
    <P>There has not been any worthwhile overall survey of the fishing industry to my knowledge.  The Parliamentary Secretary may correct me if I am wrong.  We have had no advisory service that could say to individual fishermen: &ldquo;Here is a field of operations for you.  We know that fish abound in a particular area of the coast at particular times.  We can tell you the best time to go out.  We can give you the navigational safeguards you will need and last but not least we will give you the protection you need when you go out.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I may be told that I am out of order when I speak of protection because it is the Minister for Defence who deals with it, but there is a necessity for the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries and his Parliamentary Secretary to learn that we cannot afford to continue to dally with this problem.  I know the cost of protection vessels is immense but if we are to do the job properly we must ensure that the best possible type of protection vessel is purchased.  I have no doubt that it is possible to train personnel to man such vessels.  We already have personnel capable of operating the type of protection vessels we have.</P>
    <P>We have a naval vessel carrying out fishery protection.  I do not wish to say anything at this stage about our neighbour but the protection of our fisheries is so important that the expenditure of much more money on protection vessels is warranted.  Such expenditure is necessary if the Department <Col N="323" /> decide that fishing shall be a viable industry in the future.</P>
    <P>Something has been said about our imports of fish and fish products.  We ought to export fish.  An island country like ours should not import any kind of fish, processed or otherwise.  We should be able to meet the requirements of the home market and to export to other countries.</P>
    <P>Senator Honan mentioned that the traditional fishermen along our sea coast have lost the art of fishing.  They never had the art of deep-sea fishing. They fished from small vessels like currachs which were not fishing vessels at all.  Their art was important in its day.  Today with all the modern devices and aids like radar people can be trained properly.  It is possible to train young fishermen to do any kind of job.  They can be prepared for fishing in the most modern way.</P>
    <P>Bord Iascaigh Mhara must be complimented on the establishment of the fish cookery competitions.  This was an excellent idea.  It is one thing to have people trained in the preparation and cooking of fish but quite another thing to get the fish into the household so that people can prepare and cook it. There cannot be any great development in Bord Iascaigh Mhara in the immediate future with the amount of money we are asked for today.  I would ask that Bord Iascaigh Mhara should set their sights higher.  Bord Iascaigh Mhara should consider what has been said by the other speakers today.  The Parliamentary Secretary should bring the views expressed to the notice of the Department and should request them to attempt to do something in the best interests of the fisherfolk and of the nation as a whole.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>I was somewhat nervous of speaking on sea fisheries. Until eight months ago I lived a long way from the sea.  I have lived in a sea-port for the past eight months.  I have learned a little about the problems which exist.  Some of these problems have been touched on already.  Bord Iascaigh Mhara have been rightly complimented on the way they have encouraged the use of better and bigger boats.  If we are going to fish in earnest <Col N="324" /> we must take more advantage of the Atlantic shelf.  We must go out further into the Atlantic.  This cannot be done without bigger boats.  There is no use having bigger boats unless there is somewhere safe for them to come into. We must examine what has been happening. Last year the amount of money voted by the Dáil for fisheries and harbours was not expended.  Money was left over.  It is no good saying that the money is not there.</P>
      <P>I am living near what was a very great fishing port.  As a port it is now practically non-existent.  That happened partly because of an unfortunate accident to a foreign vessel.  Lloyds refused to insure any boat going to that port. There are thousands of pounds' worth of machinery lying in sheds.  This machinery is for dealing with fish. Nobody is doing anything about the situation.  Between Killybegs and the Swilly there is only one place with deep water at all times and that is Kincasslagh.</P>
      <P>I recommend that the Parliamentary Secretary take a look at the report by the Agricultural Institute on the survey of West Donegal.  There is reference to fishing.  According to their report the only hope for Donegal is the fishing. Donegal is not suitable for the planting of trees or for agriculture but it is certainly suitable for fishing.  This position is dealt with fairly enough in one way and yet, considering it is so important, the report rather slides over it.  Sufficient attention is not paid to the fact that there is deep water at all times at Kincasslagh.  Mention is made that the lowest tide is 15 feet at the pier.  This is in contradistinction to Burtonport where the high water point is 16 feet and the low water point six feet.  At Kincasslagh it is reported that the lowest point is 15 feet or even 18 feet.  There would be safe anchorage there if there was a breakwater there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We are not fishing adequately if we are only fishing around the islands on our coast.  We must be able to go out west of Tory.  At the moment men are risking their lives going out west of Tory in 50-foot boats.  It takes seven hours to steam from Killybegs to Tory. A journey to and from Tory takes 14 hours from Killybegs and this is not <Col N="325" /> economic.  It takes three hours to steam from Kincasslagh to Tory and yet nothing is happening there.  There are many reasons for this.  There are many rumours and I am finding it difficult to sort out fact from rumour.  The engineers from the Office of Public Works know that Kincasslagh is the only place between Killybegs and Swilly which has deep water at all times.  It really only needs a breakwater. The estimated cost of the breakwater varies from £50,000 to £1 million, depending on whom you are talking to and whether they think the breakwater should be built or not. Someone must take a hard look at the position.  There are many men in the district who are willing to fish.  It would be good if the fishermen had somewhere safe to go.  I have spent one winter there.  The gales which hit west Donegal are tremendous.  One can appreciate the fishermen looking for safety at some stage of their journey.</P>
    <P>There is an appalling difference between what the housewife pays for fish and what the fisherman gets for it.  This is true of most products.  The situation is becoming worse all the time. The housewife demands more packaging and more processing before she will buy and this has all to be paid for.  There was a study recently of the various items which went to make up the price of fish on the Dublin market. Some of the items were rather odd. I understand that when one knows the full story a great many of the items seem even more odd.  I understand the fishermen are charged 2s for the use of a box.  There is nothing to stop them using the same box 20 times, yet every time they have to pay for the box as though it were a new one.  Old-established practices like this are hampering our fishing industry.</P>
    <P>The board have done a great deal to encourage people to eat more fish by teaching them how to cook it, but there is no point in doing this if the people never see any fish.  In County Donegal one is lucky if one sees fish four or five times a year and then only when they were being dumped at the fish meal factory.  I do not think we can blame our fishermen for the poor quality of the herrings because <Col N="326" /> most of the herrings which come near the coast are spent.  When I lived in Donegal I always managed to find myself a good sized fish but the vast majority were spent.  It did not matter greatly to us because most of the fish were marinated and sent abroad.</P>
    <P>If we want people to eat more fish &mdash;and certainly, economically, we should all eat more fish because it is much cheaper than meat &mdash; we must ensure that the present system whereby fish are sent from Donegal to Dublin and then sent back to Donegal again, is stopped because this to me is the last word in stupidity.  This is yet another old-established practice which should be broken and I hope the Parliamentary Secretary will do something about it.</P>
    <P>Every time the board organises a competition it is not only teaching people how to cook fish but it is increasing the interest in fish.  I understand one of the reasons why all the really good brains come from the west coast is because of all the fish caught there.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBelton" hpid="Dr. Belton Dr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to welcome the Parliamentary Secretary on his first occasion in that capacity here. I hope that what I have to say will not offend him.  Like Senator McDonald I support the idea behind this Fisheries Bill.  I do not know that we as a nation are educated about the values derived from eating fish.  I have relatives all over the country who do not like eating fish and whether this is from lack of education or lack of advertising of fish products I do not know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Sheldon referred to the monopoly position of those who distribute fish in this country.  I feel there is a closed shop in relation to the distribution of fish not only in the country but in Dublin.  I do not know whether this is because there is not a sufficient market for the produce or whether the price is so high because of this monopoly that people do not eat fish.  It may be that as most people in this country are of a religion which obliges them to eat fish on Friday that they do not want to eat fish.  I have some unionist friends in the North of <Col N="327" /> Ireland who eat more fish than we do; in fact, they prefer to eat a fish than meat on many occasions.</P>
    <P>When the Parliamentary Secretary is replying I should like him to tell the House the position of the fishmeal industry at the present time.  I should also like to know its uses as animal food and fertiliser.  Senator McDonald told me that he thought fishmeal used as a fertiliser is too expensive.</P>
    <P>Not one speaker referred to the smoked fish industry.  I may be peculiar but I like to eat a kipper for my breakfast, but I cannot buy a smoked herring.  I do not know why we cannot have a proper smoked fish industry here.  I would certainly prefer to eat Irish kippers than Isle of Man kippers but the Isle of Man kippers are more tasty and more palatable.  I think I am not an exception.  We all do.  We even eat tinned stuff at present whether it is palatable or not.</P>
    <P>There are many points I should like to make, not alone about our sea fishing but about our inland fisheries also. For instance, we export eels and they come back to us as smoked eels.  This is true.  I do not understand the logic of this situation.  It is quite wrong.  When I was in Paris many years ago one of the favourite dishes was pike.  Yet we throw pike away.  We throw away some of our greatest assets.  Rough fishing in this country is not dealt with in the proper way at all.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should not remain inland too long.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBelton" hpid="Dr. Belton Dr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I was waiting for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair wants the Senator to get on to the cod.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Come back from Paris.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBelton" hpid="Dr. Belton Dr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Sheldon and, I think, Senator Honan said that harbours were not adequately equipped and that boats are not adequately equipped for deep-sea fishing.  Perhaps they are putting the cart before the horse in this matter.  Dunmore East, which I know, is a reasonable harbour and yet it is frequently foreign vessels which come in and land fish there.  We <Col N="328" /> had our navy running after them a few times.  I am not sure that it is harbours that should be provided at all. I accept that if boats are provided maybe our fishermen will have enough energy to go out and fish and then we should have harbours.  This I would accept, but in Dunmore East it is the foreign vessels which land the fish.</P>
      <P>What is happening to our 12-mile limit?  Are we really entitled to have this 12-mile limit?  If we are, surely we should be better equipped to prevent foreign vessels fishing within that 12-mile limit?  It is not sufficient to have a 12-mile limit unless we can enforce that limit.</P>
      <P>I am very interested in the fishmeal business and I ask the Parliamentary Secretary to deal especially with it because I really want to know about it. It is like the potato alcohol industry in County Louth.  We do not know exactly what is happening to that either. I should like the Parliamentary Secretary to refer to this in his reply.  I welcome him here and in general I welcome this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBoland" hpid="Mr. J. Boland Mr. J. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a fair amount of sympathy always with people who must make their living from the sea which surrounds the Irish coast.  I feel that to some extent they suffer because of the fact that the organs of Government which administer the affairs of the sea are the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries and the Department of Defence and, consequently, in the view of many people, the fishery service administered by the Department of Agriculture and the coastal protection service administered by the Department of Defence usually end up as rather the poor relation in the operation of those Departments.  This may or may not be true but it is certainly the view held by many members of the general public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In common with many other Members who spoke I would, of necessity, have to speak on this problem very much as a layman with a layman's approach to the whole business of fishing and indeed viewing it from the consumption end rather than the end at which the product is produced, although there is quite a sizeable part <Col N="329" /> of County Dublin which adjoins the sea and there is a fairly big fishing industry in parts of County Dublin. One of the things we should remember is that fish is one of the few harvests we can reap without having to sow. The product is there for us and so long as we can utilise the best methods of reaping that product and properly marketing it we are getting something for which we do not have to pay.</P>
    <P>I agree with the many speakers who have deplored the absence of a proper deep-sea fishing industry around this coast.  It is rather galling for all of us, as Irish men and women, to go to virtually any of our ports and see boats from other countries unloading fish which was, more likely than not, caught in Irish waters, being bought by Irish or other middlemen and being sold, perhaps to the Irish public usually at a better price than the Irish fisherman has got and from a boat which is obviously far superior and crewed by people who are obviously far better off than their Irish counterparts. This is what is concerning most Members of this House and perhaps most Members of the other House who spoke on this problem.</P>
    <P>We must ensure that the methods whereby fish are caught and marketed and the price obtained for the fish are at an optimum.  I do not think that situation obtains at present.  I agree very strongly with the Members of this House who spoke out against the seemingly unfair practices which still prevail in this industry in relation to the way fish is purchased from the fishermen and eventually placed on the market for the consumer.  It seems to many members of the general public, whether this is right or wrong, that the people who make most money with the least amount of effort out of the fishing industry are the middlemen and the people who have to work hardest at this most dangerous and hazardous occupation and who make least out of it are the fishermen.</P>
    <P>Obviously, this is the type of problem with which those Senators who have spoken are concerned.  An Bord Iascaigh Mhara should direct their thoughts towards the idea of endeavouring to have controlled retail <Col N="330" /> prices for various types of fish at various times of the year or, alternatively, to having a guaranteed price for various types of fish to be paid to the fishermen.  This price should obtain all the year round and if it should appear that the middleman is then exploiting the market the board should purchase the fish at the ports and harbours and place it on the retail market.</P>
    <P>I was amazed to hear the Parliamentary Secretary say that some years ago the board drew out of the business of fish marketing so that they could concentrate on the development of sea fishing.  Allied with this is the problem of the revision of adequate harbour facilities.  I know that this responsibility does not rest with the board or, indeed, with the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries but as a public representative for County Dublin I am aware of the delays in carrying out such improvements.  There is a scheme presently in progress at Skerries but that scheme is the result of 25 or 30 years of constant representation and complaints.  If we are serious about developing the fish industry we cannot have a situation whereby development of harbours is held up.</P>
    <P>There is also an important social aspect of this industry.  Many of our small coastal towns and villages rely on the fishing industry to a large extent. When deciding on schemes in order of priority, the Board of Works and An Bord Iascaigh Mhara should consider this social aspect.  I support Senator Honan on the suggestion of developing our fishing industry into a deep-sea industry, an industry in which would be employed the most modern techniques so that our fishermen could compete with foreign trawlers who are at present fishing in Irish waters.  We must face the fact that the 12-mile limit as far as the general public are concerned, and, indeed, as far as most of the fishermen are concerned, is a complete farce.  We have not the ships to enforce the limit and many of our own trawlers would not think of venturing out much further than that limit anyway.</P>
    <P>Senator Belton referred to a matter which at first may have seemed a little <Col N="331" /> strange but in which, I realise, there is a fair amount of truth.  It relates to the problem of marketing.  A characteristic of Irish people is that they naturally rebel if they are told what they should do.  I often think that if the representatives of an alien power a few hundred years ago had told us that we must be Catholics, by this stage, we would at least be members of the Protestant faith and, in all probability, we would be agnostics.  However, because we were told that we must not be Catholics we took to the hills and valleys to practise our religion.  In the same way, because we are told that we must eat fish on Fridays, a natural reaction has built up in the Irish people against eating fish on any other day of the week.  The Irishman will ask himself why he should eat fish on a Wednesday when he must eat it on a Friday.  Anything that smacks of compulsion is abhorrent to many Irish people and I would hope that the representations which, I understand, one of the Minister's parliamentary colleagues made recently to the ecclesiastical authorities will not go unnoticed.</P>
    <P>The Parliamentary Secretary said in his speech that a sum of £1,281,000 has been repaid or written off from the board's borrowing from the Central Fund.  I would be interested to know how much of that amount had been repaid rather than written off.  Too often statements like this are made about two matters that have no bearing whatever on each other.  There is a great difference between an amount borrowed and repaid and an amount borrowed and written off and to bulk the two together is not very enlightening as to how efficient a State or semi-State body may happen to be.</P>
    <P>When he is replying, the Parliamentary Secretary may be able to tell us approximately how many boats are now in operation in Irish ports and how many are operating or have operated with the financial assistance of the board either in the present or in the past.  What is even more important, perhaps he can tell us how many of these boats are capable of venturing out and engaging in deep sea fishing.</P>
    <P>Finally, I should like to agree with <Col N="332" /> the other Members of the House who spoke of the difficulty from the point of view of the general public living as someone suggested, 40 miles or more from the coast, in obtaining fresh fish. I live a lot less than 40 miles from the coast and the only time that I enjoy really fresh fish is when I or some member of my family drives out to Howth and buys the fish from the fishermen as they come in.  Apart from the satisfaction of knowing that the fish is really fresh I also have the satisfaction of cutting out the middleman. The Parliamentary Secretary should endeavour to do the same.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeggyFarrell" hpid="Mrs. Farrell Mrs. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>First of all, I should like to welcome the Parliamentary Secretary to the House and to congratulate him on his appointment.  As a land-lubber from an inland county he has a problem on his hands when dealing with fisheries.  However, I have no doubt that he can go to Waterford and study everything about fishing that can be studied there.</P>
      <P>I speak as an admiral of the Nebraskan Navy's landlocked fleet and so I am in a very unique position here this evening as I also come from a seaport town.  I grew up in a town where there is a song about the fishing fleet at anchor.  I remember as a young child going down with my basket for what used to be handed out then, free prawns. Now when we go to buy prawn cocktail we pay dearly for it.  I am very pleased to see the advances that have been made in the fishing industry in this country since I was a child in that seaport town.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Bord Iascaigh Mhara are to be congratulated for the work they have done for the fishing industry but a lot of work needs to be done for the fishermen. Many of the Senators who spoke have mentioned the high price of fish as distinct from what the producer gets but I think this is common to all producers.  We have farmers with exactly the same complaint.  I believe the answer lies in the co-operative fishing ventures which are now being started but since the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries handle fisheries and are also in a way responsible for the co-operative movement of <Col N="333" /> this country, the fostering of fishermen's co-operatives is something which should be engaging the active attention of the officials of the Department.</P>
    <P>When we talk about the silver harvest of the sea and the fact that fish are there and all we have to do is go out and pick them up we are neglecting perhaps a very important facet which is that the research services are there to examine the fishing industry and make recommendations on it.  We have various centres around the coast where there is a certain amount of research carried out but I feel in this respect the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries are not doing as much as they might. I understand that certain recommendations have been made about this and the actual people in the service do not approve of a number of those recommendations, that they themselves have prepared a case as to how the research service should be implemented and developed. I would recommend to the Parliamentary Secretary, if that report has not yet reached his desk, to make an effort to get a copy of it.  If he cannot get it I will give it to him because it is a document which is well worth studying.</P>
    <P>When we in this House speak about fishing we forget about the indiscriminate dumping of nuclear fall-out and we also talk about conservation.  This is Conservation Year.  Are we protecting the waters around our coast and conserving them?  There is a large amount of dumping being done and if it is not controlled and if we are not informed of what is happening we could finish up with contaminated fish and then no matter how good you cook it it is still contaminated.</P>
    <P>I support the Senators who say that if Bord Iascaigh Mhara are not now concerned with the marketing and processing of fish then a board should be set up to deal with this because it is, as some Senators have said, rather ludicrous to see us sending fish out of the country, not alone our eels but our herring, and seeing them come back processed.  Surely this is a valuable industry where we could set up our own processing plants and export our fish processed.  The continental countries bought our herring salted in barrels <Col N="334" /> down through the ages.  We should certainly be gone past salting the herrings and sending them out in barrels.  They should be sent out in a sophisticated manner.</P>
    <P>May I say in congratulating Bord Iascaigh Mhara for teaching the people how to use fish, that in the compliments there were two bodies forgotten?  The board might dream up a scheme of promotion but unless they have the co-operation of the Irish Countrywomen's Association &mdash; I never fail to get a plug in for them when I can &mdash; and the domestic economy teachers in the schools throughout the country who worked hard to teach those children and to help those women to put on their competitions, Bord Iascaigh Mhara could be trying from now until doomsday to promote the eating of fish and they could not do it.</P>
    <P>The Irish Countrywomen's Association have played a large part in this and I would like this placed on the records of this House.  I am sure anybody who speaks to the officials in Bord Iascaigh Mhara will be told this is true. I speak now as an ICA woman.  We have put on courses in our adult education colleges of a week's duration and taught the people how to cook and present fish but then we come back to our own towns and find the distribution of fish is very bad indeed.</P>
    <P>I was reared on fish but I am now at a stage when I very seldom eat it.  It is not because I do not like fish but because by the time the fish reaches us on a Thursday afternoon or Friday morning I often wonder how often it has been thawed out, frozen and thawed out again.  I am afraid sometimes to eat it.  We have taught our people how to cook fish.  Even with the prices which are now being charged for it is still a cheap food but we cannot get it readily available and we cannot get many varieties of fish.  Very often we are sold dabs for plaice.  This has often happened to me.  We are not always getting the product we are told it is.</P>
    <P>Senator Sheldon made a point that the housewives were looking for more packaging and more sophisticated products and that this is why you cannot get fresh fish.  I doubt this because <Col N="335" /> the housewife is presented with sophisticated packaging and either she buys that or she has not anything to buy.  I perhaps am an old-fashioned housekeeper in that I like to see what I am buying.  Although we welcome processed food, easy-to-prepare food, we also welcome food in its natural state when we can get it.  This is not always possible.</P>
    <P>I am glad to see that money is being made available for trawlers.  I was in Killybegs recently and it was heartening to see all the trawlers there.  For too long we regarded the fishing industry as a Cinderella.  There is no doubt that fishing could be the source of one of our greatest exports in years to come but if this is to be so we will have to get serious about it and see how many millions of pounds we can allocate to fishing.  When we think of the total amount allocated to the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries, the subvention to fishing is not very big.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mr. Mícheál Cranitch Mr. Mícheál Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mícheál Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>Ar dtús ba mhait liom fáilte a chur raibh an Rúnaí Parliaiminte.  Fear maith é agus sé an rud a deirfhinn ná go bhfuil súil agam go mbeidh seal fada buan aige in a phost.</P>
      <P>It is running late and practically every aspect of the fishing industry has been dealt with.  There are some points I should like to make, however. Somehow, fishing has not been very prominent in our literature, in our poetry, our songs, even though we are an island.  Most islands have some wonderful fishing lore, fishing songs, fishing ballads, <i>et cetera</i>.  Somehow we seem to be particularly bereft in this respect, in spite of the fact that we have off our coasts what one would call a silver harvest.  I was glad to hear a couple of years ago, when it was decided as part of major policy to develop five of our principal fishing ports, Castletownbere, Dunmore East, Howth, Killybegs and Galway, of the wonderful development that has taken place in those places.  It augurs well for those in charge of fishing development and for those who have to do the fishing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="336" /> Other fishing ports, too, have been very active, places where the tradition still lives of the naomhóg and the currach. When I think of the extraordinary feats of endurance of those in the lonely naomhóga off the Kerry coast and the curracha off the coast of Galway, I believe that, given the gear, our fishermen would rank among the best in the world.</P>
    <P>Bord Iascaigh Mhara are to be congratulated on the work they have done since they were established in 1952. For that reason I welcome the Bill and I say that whatever money is voted towards the board by way of assistance is indeed money well spent.</P>
    <P>There are two main points I wish to make.  The first is concerned with one of the greatest dangers to us and to the fishing industry.  Everybody seems to be speaking about pollution, pollution at sea as well as on our rivers and on our land, pollution from factories and big industries now situated along our coast and, one might say, on our islands.  I have in mind Bantry Bay.  Pollution will occur in these places to an ever increasing degree.  Cognisance will have to be taken of it and the earlier the better so that if a remedy can be found it will be found in good time.</P>
    <P>The second point is in connection with the three-mile, the six-mile and the 12-mile limits.  It is a burning question at the moment.  It is something that will have to be faced because we are very vulnerable.  We need a number of high grade boats specially built for protection purposes and even with a good fleet of those boats &mdash; I have in mind ten, 12, 15 or maybe 20 &mdash;cruising around the coast it will be very difficult to keep an eye on those enterprising trawlermen from certain countries which I will not name.  It is a matter for the Department of Defence but I suggest, and I am sure the Parliamentary Secretary will take note of it, the necessity to keep in close touch with the Department of Defence because there is little use having a silver harvest off our coast and fishermen anxious to reap it if they cannot be protected from the 20th <Col N="337" /> century marauding of our fishing preserves.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KitAhern" hpid="Cáit Ní Eachthéirn Cáit Ní Eachthéirn">
      <NameTxt>Cáit Ní Eachthéirn</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl a lán le rá agam.  Ba mhaith liom i dtosach fáilte a chur roimh an Rúnaí Parlaiminte. Fear stuamach, ciallmhar é agus tá súil agam go ndéanfhaidh sé go sármhaith ina phost nua.  Baineann an Bille seo leis na daoine sna báid móra, ach ba mhaith liom cupla focail a rá i dtaobh na ndaoine mbeaga, na daoine sna sráid-bhailte le hais na fairrge.</P>
      <P>I want to make a plea for the small men.  It has been said that the money being provided is for the bigger trawlers. One of the points I wish to make is that Bord Iascaigh Mhara should be asked to earmark some of the money for the provision of piers in our smaller coastal villages.  It is no use having 60-footers off the Kerry coast if we have no piers for them.  I compliment the board on the great work they have been doing.</P>
      <P>I suggest that when a decision has been made as to who should get a boat the man with a fishing background should get priority.  There can be men from inland who have been trained, but at the same time I think those who have fishing backgrounds, whose parents have made a living from fishing, should get priority.  I hope the Parliamentary Secretary will bear these points in mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelGallanagh" hpid="Mr. Gallanagh Mr. Gallanagh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gallanagh</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, welcome Deputy Fahey and the Bill.  I was reared in a fishing village in that picturesque county, Donegal, in Swilly, and as a boy I went out to the harbour in the morning when the herring boats were in.  There were 60, 70, 80, sometimes 150 herring boats from Scotland, England, France, and a few from Ireland, tied up there.  It was a very flourishing industry.  A lot of the herrings were exported to Germany.  There were local kippering stations.  Two fishings a year took place, one in May and one in December.  A lot of employment was given because all the fish were processed there and exported.  Coopers and others concerned in the business were there.  It is a sad thing to say that today if Lord Ullin's daughter came <Col N="338" /> there would hardly be a man to row her over in a ferry.  There is no activity except for the odd man who owns his own boat and goes out occasionally to fish.</P>
      <P>While we are talking about fishing, fishing boats and fishery protection we must get down to fundamentals.  We have not got any fishermen in this country.  If we had 100 boats tomorrow I do not think we could get crews to man them.  There are small men around the coast who own boats.  It does not pay the fishermen to send their fish to the market except in places like Dunmore East and Killybegs.  One meets local fishermen who sell their fish locally at the best price they can get.</P>
      <P>We must do a complete survey of the fishing industry.  We must have surveys of the coastal waters and of the harbours.  A survey of the manpower available for those extra protection ships, if provided, must be made.  Training schemes could be started in co-operation with our neighbours.  If boys realised that there was a good living for them &mdash; and it would need to be a good living for them when they must spend days and nights fishing&mdash;they would become fishermen.</P>
      <P>Fishermen used to fish on all nights except Fridays and Saturdays.  They generally went off on Sundays.  Men would need to be well paid for such work.  People regard fishing as a pleasant pastime like fishing for salmon or fishing along the coast for pleasure. Fishing competitions and festivals are popular but they are not the things that matter.  We must try to combat the fact that in this country today a great deal of fish is being imported in the form of fish-fingers.  If we have to compete with a market like that we must have sturdy boats to go far out and the fish they catch must be properly processed.  We must look into the other possibility of doing something about this industry and of being serious about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TerenceOSullivan" hpid="Mr. O'Sullivan Mr. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to congratulate the Parliamentary Secretary on his appointment.  I wish him every success. I welcome this Bill.  A sum of £5 million is a clear indication of the progress which has been made in our fishing industry.  It is a tribute to Bord <Col N="339" /> Iascaigh Mhara and their employees. They must be congratulated on the efficient manner in which they are carrying out their duties.</P>
      <P>I come from a seaport area at Castletownbere in West Cork.  I am particularly interested in the fishing industry.  The greatest single step in improving our fishing industry and in making it a worthwhile one was the selection of the major fishery ports. Castletownbere has been selected as a major fishery port.  I cannot remember the early 1920's but I am told it was then a port which was extensively used for mackerel and herring fishing. When the American market was withdrawn from this country that industry died.  As a result of the Government decision to select major fishery ports around the coastline Castletownbere, Dunmore East, Killybegs and Howth have given the fishing industry a great and wonderful prospect.  It is gratifying to go down to Castletownbere in the evening and see there a port which was dead in the 1930's and the 1940's today busy with 15 to 20 trawlers coming in and landing their catches.  They have still to send the majority of the catch to Dublin to be marketed.  That has always been a major problem.  I feel that a marketing system can be established.  At present in Castletownbere the fishermen have formed themselves into a co-operative society for the marketing of their produce.  The Government have given considerable assistance by way of grants and technical advice for the establishment of auction sheds.  This is a wonderful achievement.  I believe the same position applies at Dunmore East.  The fish from Howth naturally goes to the Dublin market.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not agree with the Senator who said that we do not have fishermen to man our boats.  In my own town, where fishing was almost extinct, we have 15 to 20 trawlers operating from the harbour each employing five or six fishermen at very lucrative rates of pay.  We are hoping that with the introduction of a fishmeal plant at Castletownbere there will be an all-round improvement for those men.  During the months from November to perhaps March they have to go to the fishing grounds <Col N="340" /> off Dunmore East or to west of Cork harbour and land their catches there. With the provision of a fish processing factory which is being provided with the help of State grants there will be no fears for the fishing industry in Castletownbere.  The fishmeal plant will be able to cater for the entire fishing needs of the area.</P>
    <P>The selection of the major fishery ports was the greatest single step taken to provide properly for the fishing industry. The fishermen engaged in the industry are more than satisfied and are loud in their praises of the selection and development of these ports.</P>
    <P>There is a point which applies very much in seaboard areas and that is the shellfish industry.  This is one industry which is being very badly hit at the moment.  During the years it has been the practice for the small farmers to engage in shell-fishing such as lobster fishing, cray-fishing <i>et cetera,</i> as an extra means of helping their finances. The Department of Agriculture and Fisheries have failed to provide landing facilities.  If piers and slips were erected this could be a very lucrative industry and of immense value to small farmers because it would help to raise their standard of living.  I understand the Department are carrying out a survey of the whole coastline but it is taking a long time and because of the magnitude of the problem it will take a considerable time to implement the recommendations.  As we have so much coastline I think the Department should allocate a specific amount of money annually to the various county councils for piers and slips.</P>
    <P>Another industry which could be very lucrative to small farmers is salmon drift net fishing.  Here again small farmers are restricted because most of our rivers and coastline are owned by absentee landlords.  The Kenmare River which runs from Kenmare to the Bull Rock is owned by three absentee landlords.  There are at least 250 small farmers who could benefit considerably if they were allowed to operate drift fishing nets there.  I would ask the Parliamentary Secretary to look into this question.</P>
    <P>In relation to fishery protection, I think it would be a good thing if a <Col N="341" /> fast speed boat were to be provided at each of our major fishing harbours.  We have to accept that our fishing fleet fishes out of the major harbours and a fast speed boat would be able to patrol the coastline and thereby protect our industry.  I have no doubt that the development of major harbour fishery boards will mean that the fish will not have to go to Dublin and then be distributed all over the country afterwards.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackieFahey" hpid="Mr. Fahey Mr. Fahey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fahey</NameTxt>
      <P>First of all I should like to thank the House sincerely for the welcome it extended me on my first visit here.  Indeed, the Senators' kind words made my visit all the easier.  I should also like to thank those who spoke for the constructive way they approached this Bill.  I was particularly pleased to hear that all Senators were so keen to develop our fishing industry in a way I too believe it should be developed.  There is a silver harvest waiting to be reaped.  I believe if our fishermen are given proper equipment and proper training they will leave nothing for the foreign boats to come in and take from us.  I sincerely hope we will be able to develop things so that this may become a reality.</P>
      <P>A large number of points were raised by Senators and as it would be impossible for me to deal with all of them in any detail I shall do my best and I hope I will satisfy the House with my replies.  Senator McDonald referred to the necessity for having a constant supply of fish available, especially in the midlands.  I am glad to be able to tell the Senator that this is something which is being dealt with.  We know it will take some time to find a complete answer to the problem but the situation where fish come to Dublin and then go down to the midlands arises because of the difficulty that the fishermen are in.  The fish are their property until they are sold and as far as Bord Iascaigh Mhara are concerned they are trying to get advice across to them to try and get the fish sent directly to the best markets available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator McDonald and others mentioned the imports of fish into this country.  All I can say is that there is not one fishing country in western Europe, with the exception of Iceland <Col N="342" /> which has a very small population, that does not import fish.  When one talks about importing fish one must remember that it is not just one product but a wide range of species which are imported either during times of local shortage due to bad fishing conditions or because the particular species are not available.  It is not a matter for criticism: what really matters is that we have good home and export markets for all the fish we catch.  I do not agree that research is neglected.  This is something which is going on all the time and is being given constant attention.  The Department have two fishery research vessels and employ an inshore team to work with them.</P>
    <P>Reference was made to the number of boats seized because of repayment problems but I should like to point out that the numbers involved are very small in proportion to the total.  Of course, there will always be failures in any industry and many reasons can be given for the failures.  It may be because of the crew and the skipper of a particular vessel or it may be some other reason.  One cannot expect everything to be a 100 per cent success.</P>
    <P>Senator Sheldon mentioned the orderly marketing of fish.  As I have said, we are dealing with this problem, perhaps not as speedily as we would like to, but nevertheless we believe we are making good progress. Senator Sheldon also mentioned the question of ports and landing places in Donegal.  He suggested that I should have a special look at that problem.  I assure him I certainly will.</P>
    <P>Senator Belton mentioned foreign vessels landing herrings at Dunmore East.  I should like to point out to the Senator that no foreign fishing vessels land herrings at Dunmore East. The landings are by the Irish fleet and any foreign boats there are luggers and they are there for the purpose of transporting Irish caught fish to the continent after it is landed at Dunmore East.</P>
    <P>Senator Belton also mentioned the question of the fishmeal factories.  The Killybegs fishmeal factory has been in operation for many years and has been <Col N="343" /> working at full capacity.  We have no fish supply difficulties there.  The Mornington fishmeal factory was opened only last year.  Fish supplies there have been meagre but we hope the supplies will increase.  We hope they will increase because we import fairly substantial amounts of fishmeal.  I want to say too that we import eels for smoking in this country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBelton" hpid="Dr. Belton Dr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>We import them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackieFahey" hpid="Mr. Fahey Mr. Fahey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fahey</NameTxt>
      <P>We import them.  Senator Belton also asked whether we are entitled to our 12-mile fishery limit. We are, of course, legally entitled to our 12-mile fishery limit.  The maintaining of this fishery limit has been a problem, I know, but I will bring the Senator's remarks to the attention of the Minister for Defence who is responsible for this end of the business.</P>
      <P>Senator Boland referred to the accounts of Bord Iascaigh Mhara.  I should like to say, for his information, that the accounts as presented to both Houses of the Oireachtas for the year ended 31st March, 1969, give the figure of the amount written off on the board's loans from the Central Fund as £403,584 and that the Fisheries Vote for the current year provides for an additional £387,000 to clear off all the bad debts on the board's books.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Farrell spoke of the co-operation Bord Iascaigh Mhara have been getting from the Irish Countrywomen's Association and from the domestic economy instructresses throughout the country.  I assure the Senator this is greatly appreciated by Bord Iascaigh Mhara.  She also mentioned the question of dumping.  This dumping is only being done under international supervision and the health authorities are also keeping the matter in check.  As far as the board are concerned at present there are no fears <Col N="344" /> whatever with regard to the contamination of fish.</P>
    <P>Senator Honan mentioned the size and quality of herrings.  All I can say is that this is, of course, a free economy. I suppose if the Irish price were better preference would be given to the home market.  As it happens we are very small consumers of herring and so the vast bulk of herring landings go for export.  Senator Honan also mentioned the size of our fishing vessels and their ability to compete with foreign vessels off our shores.  All I can say is that Irish fishing vessels are gradually getting bigger, the majority of them are now 75 feet long.  Taking our fishing vessels as a whole, they are on a par with other European vessels.  The same applies to gear.</P>
    <P>I hope I have covered the main points that were made.  Again I want to thank Senators for the way they received me here and to say that I look forward to coming here as often as I possibly can during the next four years.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBelton" hpid="Dr. Belton Dr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a very good point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBoland" hpid="Mr. J. Boland Mr. J. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>Hope springs eternal.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the next stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Now, if there is no objection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBoland" hpid="Mr. J. Boland Mr. J. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>During the next four years.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages now.</P>
      <P>Bill put through Committee, reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 9.50 p.m. until 10 a.m. on Thursday, 4th June, 1970.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>