<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Tue" Date="18" Month="May" Year="1926" Vol="15" No="15" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 18 Bealtaine 1926" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 18 May 1926" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1607">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1607" /> Do chuaidh an Ceann Comhairle i gCeannas ar 3 a clog.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS. -" RHead="RIVER LERR (KILDARE AND CARLOW) DRAINAGE">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - RIVER LERR (KILDARE AND CARLOW) DRAINAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConlan" hpid="Mr. JOHN CONLAN Mr. JOHN CONLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHN CONLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he is aware that in a letter dated 11th October, 1925, the Secretary of the Board of Public Works informed the County Council of Kildare that certain work involving an estimated expenditure of £4,300 was about to be carried out on the River Lerr in Counties Kildare and Carlow, to the cost of which work the County Council was invited to be contributory, and for which landholders in the drainage district would be liable to the extent of 4/9 per acre; that at the meeting of the County Council several members acquainted with the district expressed the opinion that, inasmuch as the stream had been kept in good order by annual expenditure of money through the Lerr Drainage Committee, the proposed operations were unnecessary; that their conclusions were confirmed by the Committee named and also by their engineer; that without any further communication the Board of Works began the work, upon which over £4,000 has already been spent and a further sum of £1,500 is estimated for its completion; that landholders bordering the river assert that no benefit has accrued or can accrue to them on account of the undertaking, and if he will cause inquiry to be made as to the reason for proceeding with the work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Kildare County Council were informed on the 4th July, 1925&mdash; not 11th October&mdash;that the Commissioners of Public Works had been authorised by the Minister for Finance to carry out a general restoration of the rivers and streams in the River <Col N="1608" /> Lerr Drainage District, under the Drainage Maintenance Act, 1924.  The work commenced on the 25th of that month and was continued until the 9th December following, and the expenditure for that period amounted to £2,500.</P>
      <P>On the 23rd March, 1926, the Secretary of the Kildare County Council forwarded to the Commissioners a copy of a resolution passed on the 16th idem, protesting against the expenditure as unwarranted and inquiring on whose initiative the work was undertaken. On the 7th ultimo the Council were informed that the Commissioners were satisfied from the information they had that the district was not properly maintained, a conclusion which was confirmed by their engineer's report after inspection.  It was at the same time intimated to the County Council that if the latter thought it desirable the Commissioners would recommend the extension of the period of repayment from 10 to 15 years and thus reduce the average annual charge from 4/9 to 3/7 per acre.  There is no reason to expect that the estimate for the work&mdash;£4,300&mdash;will be exceeded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConlan" hpid="Mr. CONLAN Mr. CONLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of that answer, will the Minister inform the County Council at whose instance the work was initiated?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>The work was initiated at the instance of the Commissioners of Public Works.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConlan" hpid="Mr. CONLAN Mr. CONLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>And against the wishes of the people concerned?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>No, sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughColohan" hpid="Mr. COLOHAN Mr. COLOHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. COLOHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that there are over 3,000 unemployed in the Co. Kildare, will the Minister give instructions to the Commissioners of Public Works to improve all the other drainage districts in the county? From what I have heard, the work carried out in the Lerr Drainage District has been exceptionally well done, notwithstanding what Deputy Conlan says.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - VACANT HOUSES IN DUBLIN">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - VACANT HOUSES IN DUBLIN.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="TOMAS MAC EOIN TOMAS MAC EOIN">
      <NameTxt>TOMAS MAC EOIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he can state in respect of the Dublin metropolitan area <Col N="1609" /> and any other area or areas the number of vacant dwelling houses of rateable valuations not exceeding £30, £40 and £52, respectively, in the Dublin metropolitan area, and £26, £30 and £35 respectively in other areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I have made inquiries in this matter.  So far as I can ascertain the information is not at present available in any Government department. The Deputy might be able to obtain it direct from the local authority for any area in which he may be interested.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - BANNAI DHAIL EIREANN">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - BANNAI DHAIL EIREANN.</Title>
    <P>D'fiafruighe</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="PADRAIC O MAILLE PADRAIC O MAILLE">
      <NameTxt>PADRAIC O MAILLE</NameTxt>
      <P>den Aire Airgid cia'n uair a foill-seochar an Clár de Lucht Síntiúisí do Bhannaí Dháil Eireann de réir Acht Iasachtaí agus Cistí Dháil Eireann, 1924; cad chuige nach ndeárnadh an obair roimhe seo agus cia'n uair a bhéas na Cairteacha Coigiltis le fáil aca so a bhéas cláruithe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="EARNAN DE BLAGHD EARNAN DE BLAGHD">
      <NameTxt>EARNAN DE BLAGHD</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl aon tsocrú déanta in Acht Iasachtaí agus Cistí Dháil Eireann, 1924, chun ainmneacha Síntiúsairí d'Iasacht (Inmheánach) Dháil Eireann d'fhoillsiú agus toisc ana-chuid síntiúsairí a bheith ann (timpal 150,000) níltar ar aigne na hainmneacha d'fhoillsiú.</P>
      <P>Maidir leis an dara cuid den cheist, na síntiúsairí a mbeidh a n-ainmneacha sa Chlár atá á ullamhú do réir forálacha an Achta tabharfar Cairteacha Coigiltis dóibh roimh an dáta ar a mbeidh na cairteacha so iníoctha, eadhon, 1adh Meitheamh, 1927.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="PADRAIC O MAILLE PADRAIC O MAILLE">
      <NameTxt>PADRAIC O MAILLE</NameTxt>
      <P>An gcuirfidh an tAire fógra san pháipéir á chur in úil do na daoinibh a thug sintuisi do Chiste na Dála gur feidir leo eolas a fhághail i dtaobh na hainmneacha atá ar chlár de lucht sintiuisí?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="EARNAN DE BLAGHD EARNAN DE BLAGHD">
      <NameTxt>EARNAN DE BLAGHD</NameTxt>
      <P>Cuireadh fógra sa pháipéir cheanna agus tá fógra eile le cur ann.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS." RHead="- KILDARE COMPENSATION AWARDS (APPEALS)">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - KILDARE COMPENSATION AWARDS (APPEALS).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConlan" hpid="Mr. JOHN CONLAN Mr. JOHN CONLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHN CONLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Justice if he is aware that appeals by the Co. Council of Kildare against awards of compensation on account <Col N="1610" /> of malicious injuries have been pending since February, 1925; that the delay in hearing same is causing serious loss and inconvenience to persons to whom awards have been made, inasmuch as they are precluded through want of means from reconstructing dwelling houses and farm buildings maliciously destroyed; and if he can ensure that the hearing of such cases be taken up without further delay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a fact that there has been considerable delay in the hearing of Circuit Court appeals in the High Court.  The delay is attributable to the volume of business in the High Court generally, both civil and criminal.  The present arrears can only be worked off gradually unless the number of High Court judges is increased.</P>
      <P>I have made inquiries and I find that the case to which the Deputy refers may be reached in July.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - CURRAGH ROADS MAINTENANCE">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - CURRAGH ROADS MAINTENANCE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="HughColohan" hpid="AODH O CULACHAIN AODH O CULACHAIN">
      <NameTxt>AODH O CULACHAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that the Lurrig Lane road and the adjoining Northern and Eastern Boundary Curragh Roads, at the back of the Rifle Ranges on the Curragh, have not been maintained in good condition by his Department, in accordance with the agreement entered into, under 6 and 7 Wm. 4, cap. 116, and 55 and 56 Vic., cap. 43, between the Grand Jury of the County Kildare and the British War Department during the years 1893-1896, viz., that the War Department shall, at their own expense. make to the satisfaction of the County Surveyor and keep in repair to his satisfaction, the roads marked A.X.O. and X.B. (Lurrig Lane), on the Ordnance Sheets 23 and 28 deposited with the Secretary to this Grand Jury; further, whether he will give instructions to have those roads improved immediately and maintained regularly, as, owing to their present condition, the residents and the public generally are at considerable inconvenience.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="MINISTER for DEFENCE (Mr. Hughes) Peter Hughes">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for DEFENCE (Mr. Hughes)</NameTxt>
      <P>The liability for the maintenance of the roads in question is being inquired into.  The documents embodying the agreement mentioned by the <Col N="1611" /> Deputy are not in the possession of the Department of Defence.  Representations are, however, being made to the British War Department for their transfer with a view to my considering the arrangements which might be made with the Kildare County Council in regard to the road services in question. I shall communicate with the Deputy on the matter as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughColohan" hpid="Mr. COLOHAN Mr. COLOHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. COLOHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister get into communication with the Secretary of the county council, who will give him the information he is looking for?  The information required is contained in the query books of the Spring and Summer Assizes for the years 1893-1896.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="Mr. HUGHES Mr. HUGHES">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HUGHES</NameTxt>
      <P>If there was an agreement entered into between the council and the then War Department, it would be better to have the original documents and we will endeavour to get them.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="ORAL ANSWERS. - NAAS MAILS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - NAAS MAILS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConlan" hpid="JOHN CONLAN JOHN CONLAN">
      <NameTxt>JOHN CONLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs if he is aware that letters and newspapers posted in Naas shortly after 8 p.m. on Friday evenings are not despatched from the local post office until 4 p.m. on Saturdays; that the delay in despatch causes serious inconvenience, and, in the case of newspapers, actual loss, and if he will direct that in future arrangements shall be made by which mails can be sent out in reasonable time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesJosephWalsh" hpid="MINISTER for POSTS and TELEGRAPHS (Mr. Walsh) MINISTER for POSTS and TELEGRAPHS (Mr. Walsh)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for POSTS and TELEGRAPHS (Mr. Walsh)</NameTxt>
      <P>Correspondence, including newspapers, may be posted at Naas up to 9.50 p.m. for inclusion in the general night mail despatch. On the 7th instant, however, a large number of newspapers which are ordinarily posted between 5 p.m. and 7 p.m. were not posted until shortly before the latest hour for posting&mdash; 9.50 p.m.&mdash;and, as they could not all be dealt with in the limited time available, some had, of necessity, to remain over until the following day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The latest hour for posting is fixed with regard only to the average traffic arising; it does not, and cannot, provide <Col N="1612" /> for abnormal last-moment postings.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="SCHOOL ATTENDANCE BILL," RHead="1925&mdash;FROM THE SEANAD">
    <Title>SCHOOL ATTENDANCE BILL, 1925&mdash;FROM THE SEANAD.</Title>
    <P>The Dáil went into Committee.</P>
    <P>Seanad amendment.&mdash;In Section 24 (2) before paragraph (b) a new paragraph inserted as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(b) limit the application of the order to attendance at school for instruction in one or more specified subjects.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJohnMarcusOSulli" hpid="MINISTER for EDUCATION (Professor O'Sullivan) John Marcus O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for EDUCATION (Professor O'Sullivan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Committee agree with the Seanad in the said amendment.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>The Dáil went out of Committee.</P>
      <P>Agreement with the Seanad amendment reported.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Dáil agrees with the Committee in its report&rdquo;&mdash; put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Ordered: That a message be sent to the Seanad accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ENFORCEMENT OF COURT ORDERS BILL," RHead="1926&mdash;FROM THE SEANAD">
    <Title>ENFORCEMENT OF COURT ORDERS BILL, 1926&mdash;FROM THE SEANAD.</Title>
    <P>The Dáil went into Committee.</P>
    <P>Amendment 1.&mdash;In Section 2 the words &ldquo;or delivering to him specific property&rdquo; added at the end of the section.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Committee agree with the Seanad in this amendment, which was inserted at my own request.  The position is that in addition to a writ of <i>fi fa</i> which directs an under-sheriff to levy an amount by distress and sale of the goods of a person, another writ known as a writ of delivery is sometimes issued by the High Courts to the under-sheriff directing him to take a specific article and return it to the lawful owner.  The amendment is introduced for the purpose of including a writ of delivery within the definition contained in the Bill of an execution order.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Amendment 2.&mdash;In Section 6, line 9, the words &ldquo;forty-eight&rdquo; deleted <Col N="1613" /> and the words &ldquo;twenty-four&rdquo; substituted therefor.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Committee agree with the Seanad in this amendment.  It was inserted in response to representations from the Seanad that the under-sheriff ought to be able to give an inventory of the chattels seized within twenty-four hours of such seizure.  I consider the suggestion a reasonable one and I accept the amendment.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment 3.&mdash;In Section 8, lines 22-23, the words &ldquo;twenty-four&rdquo; deleted and the words &ldquo;forty-eight&rdquo; substituted therefor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a cognate amendment.  It was urged that the debtor should be allowed a longer period than 24 hours after the seizure in which he may redeem his property before sale.  I considered that suggestion reasonable also and I accepted the amendment, the effect of which is that the under-sheriff cannot sell until after a lapse of 48 hours.  I move that the Committee agree with the Seanad in the said amendment.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment 4.&mdash;In Section 13 (1), line 19, the words &ldquo;other place of residence&rdquo; deleted and the words &ldquo;tenement of which the debtor is the occupier, either alone or jointly with another or others&rdquo; substituted therefor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>This is an important amendment.  Some considerable discussion took place on Section 13 in the Seanad.  It was pointed out that the section as it stood would render a father liable for debts contracted, without his knowledge, by a son who happened to reside with him. There were several amendments suggested and finally I agreed to accept an amendment moved by Senator Brown, the effect of which was to restrict the portion of the section to goods found in the house or on the lands of which the debtor is occupier &ldquo;either alone or jointly with another or others.&rdquo;  Occupation in the legal sense is distinct from mere residence and the <Col N="1614" /> word &ldquo;occupier&rdquo; in the context means the person having the actual use and enjoyment of the house or the land. The amendment, therefore, has the effect of removing any doubt as to whether the under-sheriff can seize the goods of the father in respect of a debt contracted by his son who resides with him.  In many cases, although there may be one rated occupier of land, two or more persons, in fact, are in occupation of the land as, for instance, where they are tenants in common who are joint tenants of the property.  To cover such cases the words &ldquo;either alone or jointly with another or others&rdquo; are used to qualify the word &ldquo;occupier.&rdquo; I move that the Committee agree with the Seanad in the said amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister explain whether the effect of this amendment is to make impossible the seizure of the husband's property because of the wife's debts or vice versa, if the wife is the occupier?  Does joint occupation imply occupation by husband and wife in the legal sense?  The Minister has explained it could not be held to be joint occupation if the son resided with the father on the premises.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>The effect of the amendment is to secure that where credit is given to a person other than the apparent owner and the actual occupier of the house or land, that where it is given, say, to a junior member of the family, then the property in the house shall not under the section be liable to seizure as the property of the son.  It was contended here, and in the Seanad, in connection with Section 13 that the effect would be to make people less careful about the standing of the person to whom credit was given, that it was enough that he lived in a house in which there was property and that, presumably, that property could be seized under the Act.  This amendment goes some way to remove any danger of that kind.  If the debtor is not the occupier, not necessarily the rated occupier, but if he is not the head of the house, so to speak, and the apparent owner, then the goods of some other member of the family, such as a son, cannot be made liable.  The Deputy asks does our saving clause, &ldquo;either <Col N="1615" /> alone or jointly with another or others,&rdquo; render the property of the wife liable for the debts of the husband? It does not.  It was not intended to and has not that effect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Does it preserve the property of the wife in respect to the debts of the husband?  Does it maintain the married woman's property rights?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not infringe or rescind it.  If the goods of the wife are, in error, seized in respect of debts, there are open to her the ordinary processes that existed before this Act at all of serving her statutory declaration on the under-sheriff, who would interplead.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment 5.&mdash;In Section 13 (1), line 24, the words &ldquo;other place of residence of the debtor&rdquo; deleted and the words &ldquo;tenement of which the debtor is the occupier, either alone or jointly with another or others&rdquo; substituted therefor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move that the Committee agrees with the Seanad in this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment is the same as amendment 4, so I take it it is agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment 6.&mdash;Before Section 19 a new section inserted as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1) Any proceedings under Part III. of the Enforcement of Law (Occasional Powers) Act, 1924 (No. 20 of 1924) which were pending in the District Court immediately before the expiration of that Act may be continued under this Part of this Act, and all steps lawfully taken and things lawfully done in such proceedings before the passing of this Act shall be deemed to have been done under this Part of this Act as if this Act had been in force at the time when such steps were taken or such things were done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(2) Nothing in this section shall operate to render any person liable to any punishment or penalty for any act (whether of commission or omission) done by him in the period between <Col N="1616" /> the expiration of the said Enforcement of Law (Occasional Powers) Act, 1924 and the passing of this Act which would have been lawful if this section had not been enacted.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>At the expiration of the Enforcement of Law (Occasional Powers) Act, 1924, on 31st March last, proceedings under Part 3 of the Act for the examination of debtors were pending in many cases.  Examination orders had actually been obtained in some of the cases, but by reason of the expiration of the Act the examinations could not be proceeded with.  In a few other cases the examinations had been concluded and instalment orders had been made, the instalments spreading over a period later than the 31st March, 1926, when the order to pay could not be enforced.  The execution creditors have incurred costs in bringing proceedings before the court and in obtaining the necessary orders, and it is thought that where the proceedings were pending on 31st March last these execution creditors should not lose the benefit of any orders already obtained by them and be compelled to start <i>de novo</i> and that on the passing of the present Bill they should be permitted to continue the proceedings originated under the 1924 Act, as from the stage they had reached when the 1924 Act expired.  The present section makes possible the continuance of such proceedings in that way.  I move that the Committee agree with the Seanad in the amendment.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Committee agree with the Seanad in the following:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before Section 25 a new section inserted as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>All rules made and forms prescribed by the Minister under Section 28 of the Enforcement of Law (Occasional Powers) Act, 1924 (No. 20 of 1924) and in force immediately before the expiration of that Act are hereby re-enacted and shall continue in force and apply to proceedings under this Act in the District Court <Col N="1617" /> until rules of court made under Section 91 of the Courts of Justice Act, 1924 (No. 10 of 1924) and applying to such proceedings come into force.</P>
    <P>Under Section 28 of the Enforcement of Law (Occasional Powers) Act, 1924 the Minister for Justice is empowered to make rules for the conduct of proceedings authorised by the Act to be brought before the Justice of the District Court and to prescribe the forms to be used in the course of such proceedings. In August, 1924, rules were made and forms were prescribed by the Minister for the conduct of the proceedings as to the examination of debtors in the District Court.  The rules have been found quite satisfactory and the amendment proposes that they should be continued pending the making of the rule by the District Court Rule-making Committee and their approval by the Dáil.  The District Court Rules will be ready to be laid before the Oireachtas on the passing of the Court Officers Bill, but in view of the fact that some little time will elapse between the passing of this Bill and the approval by the Oireachtas of the District Court Rules, it is considered advisable to continue the rules made by me so that there should be no hitch in the proceedings for the examination of debtors.  This new section will provide for the transition period between the passing of this Enforcement of Court Orders Bill and the approval of the new rules for the District Court.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreement with the Seanad amendments ordered to be reported.</P>
    <P>The Dáil went out of Committee.</P>
    <P>Agreement with Seanad amendments reported.</P>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Dáil agree with the Committee in its report&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Message ordered to be sent to the Seanad accordingly.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE BILL," RHead="1926&mdash;REPORT STAGE">
    <Title>UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE BILL, 1926&mdash;REPORT STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesNicholasDolan" hpid="Mr. DOLAN Mr. DOLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the following amendment:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In page 4, Section 7, line 47, to <Col N="1618" /> delete the word &ldquo;paragraph&rdquo; and substitute therefor the word &ldquo;paragraphs&rdquo; and after paragraph (ee), line 50, to add a new paragraph as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(eee)  Employment as a teacher in any of the following capacities:</P>
    <P>(a)  a junior assistant mistress in a National School;</P>
    <P>(b)  a recognised lay assistant in a Convent or Monastery National School;</P>
    <P>(c)  a work mistress or an industrial teacher in a National School.</P>
    <P>This amendment is moved to give effect to the principle of an amendment moved by Deputy O'Connell on the Committee Stage.  It is an agreed amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T. O'CONNELL Mr. T. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment meets with my wishes.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill, as amended, be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Fifth Stage ordered for Friday, May 21st, 1926.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COURT OFFICERS BILL," RHead="1926&mdash;REPORT STAGE">
    <Title>COURT OFFICERS BILL, 1926&mdash;REPORT STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Amendment 1.&mdash;In page 6, Section 15, line 63, to delete the words &ldquo;of the High Court.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The functions of the Accountant-General extend, in fact, to the Supreme Court, and also to the Chief Justice's court in lunacy and minor business. For that reason it is considered that the title &ldquo;Accountant&rdquo; is more suitable than &ldquo;Accountant of High Court.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 2:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 7, Section 16, line 6, to delete the words &ldquo;of the High Court&rdquo; and substitute the words &ldquo;who shall be styled the Accountant of the Courts of Justice.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 3:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In page 7, Section 19, to delete the word &ldquo;and,&rdquo; line 53, and substitute the word &ldquo;or,&rdquo; and to add at the <Col N="1619" /> end of the section, line 55, the words &ldquo;or in any other office attached to the former Supreme Court of Judicature.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The point in this amendment is that certain business other than that covered by Section 19 as it stands will be transacted in the office of the registrar to the Chief Justice, namely, the business relating to the appointment and control of solicitors and of Commissioners to take affidavits.</P>
    <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 4:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 11, Section 30, line 46, to delete the words &ldquo;this Part&rdquo; and substitute the words &ldquo;Part II.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>As a matter of fact it is Part 2 and not Part 1 that affects the local registration of title offices.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 5:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 12, Section 33 (6), line 44, to delete the words &ldquo;sixty-eight&rdquo; and substitute the word &ldquo;seventy.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>It is thought desirable to allow a county registrar, if his health and capacity are good, to remain in office until he reaches the age of 70.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 6:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 13, Section 36 (1), line 20, to delete the words &ldquo;official assignee&rdquo; and insert at the end of the line the words &ldquo;except the official assignee.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>It was explained on a previous occasion that the local registrar and the local official assignee cannot be one and the same person.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think amendments 7 and 8 might be taken together:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Amendment 7.&mdash;In page 13, Section 36, to delete sub-section (4).</P>
      <P>Amendment 8.&mdash;In page 13, before Section 37, to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(1)  All expenses, allowances, and fees heretofore payable or receivable under the Electoral Act, 1923 (No. 12 of 1923), the Local Government <Col N="1620" /> Electors Registration Act, 1924 (No. 7 of 1924) and the Juries Acts, 1871 to 1924 respectively to or by the Clerk of the Crown and Peace (whether as registration officer or otherwise) shall be payable to and receivable by the county registrar in the same manner in all respects, as the said expenses, allowances, and fees were heretofore payable to or receivable by the Clerk of the Crown and Peace.</P>
    <P>(2)  The amounts of the said expenses, allowances, and fees shall be calculated in accordance with the scales for the time being in force for the purposes of such calculation under the said Acts mentioned in the foregoing sub-section respectively and for the purpose of such scales all such expenses, allowances, and fees as were heretofore actually incurred by the Clerk of the Crown and Peace shall be deemed to be actually incurred by the county registrar although in fact not so incurred. (3)  Save asis hereinafter mentioned every county registrar shall surrender to the Exchequer so much of the expenses, allowances, and fees paid to and received by him by virtue of this section as is not required by him to meet disbursements and expenses payable or incurred by him under any of the said Acts mentioned in the foregoing sub-section and not payable or paid out of moneys provided by the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>(4)  Notwithstanding the provisions of the foregoing sub-section, the fees and other sums mentioned in sub-section (4) of Section 12 of the Electoral Act, 1923, shall be accounted for and paid by the county registrar in accordance with that sub-section and no portion of such fees or sums shall be surrendered to the Exchequer under the foregoing sub-section.</P>
    <P>Amendment 8 is really substituting a new section to remove certain ambiguities that might arise from the section as originally drafted.  The amendment does not alter the meaning or the intention of the section, but it is intended to remove any doubts that might arise.</P>
    <P>Amendments put and agreed to.</P>
    <Col N="1621" />
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 9:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 14, before Section 38, to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1)  The Minister may by order prescribe the places at which and the post office savings banks and other banks in which money hereafter paid into the circuit court in any proceedings or heretofore paid under Section 39 of the County Officers and Courts (Ireland) Act, 1877, into the former county court or into the circuit court shall be deposited in each circuit and may by the same or any other order make in respect of each circuit rules and regulations in respect of such deposits, and may by such rules and regulations make such provision as may appear to him to be necessary for the transfer of money heretofore paid into the former county court or into the circuit court as aforesaid to the bank or banks and into the names prescribed by such order for money hereafter paid into the circuit court.</P>
      <P>(2)  No order shall be made under this section without the concurrence of the judge of the circuit court assigned at the date of the order to the circuit to which the order relates.</P>
      <P>(3)  No order made under this section shall authorise the payment out otherwise than on an order of a judge of the circuit court of any money deposited under this section.</P>
      <P>This new section gives to the Minister for Justice, with the concurrence of the Circuit Judge, the power formerly vested in the Lord Chancellor as regards the manner in which money paid into the Circuit Court shall be invested while in the custody of the Court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask the Minister to give us some assurance whether questions that may arise under this section regarding the financial procedure have been approved of and generally discussed with the Department of Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 10:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 14, Section 38, to delete all from the word &ldquo;and&rdquo; in line 37 to the end of the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1622" /> The words to be deleted are covered by the general section at the end of the Bill, and, therefore, it is not necessary to have them included at this stage.</P>
    <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 11:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 14, before Section 39, to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1)  In addition to the persons employed under this Act in circuit court offices there may be attached to the circuit court such and so many officers and servants as the Minister shall, with the sanction of the Minister for Finance, from time to time determine and all such officers and servants shall hold office on such terms and conditions as the Minister for Finance shall prescribe.</P>
      <P>(2)  Every officer and servant attached to the circuit court shall be assigned by the Minister to a particular circuit and any such officer or servant may with his own consent be transferred from one circuit to another circuit and every such officer and servant shall perform and fufil in the circuit to which he is for the time being assigned such duties and functions in relation to the circuit court as the Minister shall from time to time prescribe.</P>
      <P>(3)  In addition to the officers and servants mentioned in the foregoing sub-sections of this section there may be attached to any judge of the circuit court by direction of the Minister and with the sanction of the Minister for Finance one servant to perform such duties in relation to such judge as the Minister shall prescribe, and every such servant shall be appointed by the Minister and shall hold office on such terms and conditions as the Minister shall, with the sanction of the Minister for Finance determine, and the Civil Service Regulation Act, 1924 (No. 5 of 1924) shall not apply to the situation of any such servant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(4)  The Minister for Finance may out of moneys to be provided by the Oireachtas pay to any judge of the circuit court to whom a servant is not attached under the foregoing sub-section an allowance of such amount <Col N="1623" /> as the said Minister shall determine in lieu of such servant.</P>
    <P>This new section is to provide for persons employed in the Circuit Court, but not attached to any particular county registrar.  It really covers such persons as court criers and court stenographers appointed by the judge himself.</P>
    <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments 12 and 13 go together.  I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Amendment 12.&mdash;In page 14, Section 39 (1), line 42, after the word &ldquo;Minister&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;and (as regards numbers) of the Minister for Finance.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment 13.&mdash;In page 14, Section 39 (2), line 46, to add after the word &ldquo;Minister&rdquo; the words &ldquo;and shall be paid out of moneys to be provided by the Oireachtas such salaries as the Minister shall, with the sanction of the Minister for Finance, direct.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The point as regards these two amendments is that if summons servers are to get salaries it is thought proper to have specific statutory authority for payment of such salaries, and if salaries are to be paid, that the Minister for Finance should have a voice as to the number of men to be appointed.</P>
      <P>Amendments put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Amendment 14.&mdash;In page 14, before Section 40 but in Part II. (relating to the Circuit Court) to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Nothing in this Act shall apply to the office of official assignee attached to a local bankruptcy court established under the Local Bankruptcy (Ireland) Act, 1888, before the passing of the Courts of Justice Act, 1924.</P>
      <P>(No. 10 of 1924).</P>
      <P>This amendment is consequential on Amendment 6.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 15:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 15, Section 40 (3), lines 4 5 and 6, to delete the words &ldquo;and in any such case is at the commencement of this Act under the age of sixty-five years.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1624" /> There is at least one existing district court clerk who is just over sixty-five, but who is quite capable of carrying out his duties satisfactorily.  It is to cover such a case as that that the amendment is introduced.</P>
    <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Amendment 16 not moved.</P>
    <P>Amendment 17.&mdash;In page 15, before Section 41, to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(1)  The Minister shall divide every district prescribed by him under Section 68 of the Courts of Justice Act, 1924 (No. 10 of 1924) into such and so many convenient areas (in this Part of this Act referred to as district court areas) as he shall think proper and shall appoint one convenient place in each such district court area or within one mile of the boundary of such area at which the district court shall be held for such area.</P>
    <P>(2)  It shall be lawful for the Minister from time to time, as he shall consider expedient, to do all or any of the following things, that is to say&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  vary or abolish any district prescribed by him under the said Section 68 of the Courts of Justice Act, 1924,</P>
    <P>(b)  create any new such district,</P>
    <P>(c)  vary or abolish any district court area,</P>
    <P>(d)  create any new district court area,</P>
    <P>(e)  alter the place appointed for holding the district court in or for any district court area.</P>
    <P>(3)  The district court areas created under this section shall for all purposes take the place of and be substituted for the court districts created under Section 3 of the District Justices (Temporary Provisions) Act, 1923 (No. 6 of 1923) and the district court in and for each such district court area shall be held at the place appointed therefor under this section.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to Amendment 17, district court areas, I would like to have some explanation as to how it comes within the scope of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1625" />
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>The object is to define the particular area in which a given district court clerk will work.  The definition of &ldquo;area&rdquo; is as necessary to the district court clerk's existence as the definition of, say, any office is to the holder of the office.  The clerk without an area of operation is held up, and scarcely can perform his functions. When a clerk is appointed he is necessarily appointed to a defined area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The areas must be defined here, and they are not defined elsewhere.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>No, they are not defined elsewhere.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we will accept the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move Amendment 17.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 15, Section 41 (1), line 23, to delete the words &ldquo;court districts&rdquo; and substitute the words &ldquo;district court areas,&rdquo; and in line 26 and line 31 to delete the words &ldquo;court district or districts&rdquo; and substitute the words &ldquo;district court area or areas,&rdquo; and in sub-section (2), line 41, to delete the word &ldquo;district&rdquo; and substitute the words &ldquo;district court area.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This amendment is consequential on the preceding amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 16, Section 43, to delete sub-section (4) and substitute a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;(4)  If any person who immediately before the appointed day is employed in a pensionable capacity in the office of the registrar of district court clerks is appointed after the appointed day in a pensionable capacity to a situation in the Civil Service of Saorstát Eireann, the Acts which immediately before the appointed day authorised the grant to him of a pension or other allowance (from whatever fund or moneys such pension or allowance could have been granted) shall on his ceasing to hold a situation in a pensionable capacity <Col N="1626" /> in the Civil Service of Saorstát Eireann apply to him in the same manner and to the same extent as they applied to him immediately before the appointed day but with and subject to the following modifications, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(i)  in computing the period of his service for the purpose of those Acts he shall be entitled to reckon as continuous service for those purposes his period of service in a pensionable capacity in the office of the registrar of district court clerks and his period of service in a pensionable capacity in a situation in the Civil Service of Saorstát Eireann and</P>
    <P>(ii)  the Minister for Finance shall be substituted for the person authorised by those Acts to grant to him a pension or allowance, and</P>
    <P>(iii)  any pension or allowance granted to him shall be paid out of moneys to be provided by the Oireachtas.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>This is merely a rewording of the existing sub-section so as to make it quite clear that any such re-appointed officer will get precisely the same, and no other, pension terms than those he is entitled to at present.</P>
    <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 16, Section 44 (1), line 40, to add at the end of the sub-section the words &ldquo;or paid into any fund.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Some fines are at present payable into a particular fund, such, for example, as the Road Fund.  The words now proposed to be added appear at the end of line 62 and should appear here also.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, on the Committee Stage, said that this particular clause would be inquired into, and that he would let us know on the Report Stage regarding the fines it was intended to divert from the local authorities into the Central Fund.  The Minister also promised to let us know, as far as possible in the time, the amount of these fines.  This is a serious matter from the point of view of the local authorities.  The local authorities receive a certain number of fines at <Col N="1627" /> the moment.  They are not very remunerative from the point of view of the local authority, because the local authority has to incur a certain amount of expense in connection with these particular cases, and then the fine leaves, from the point of view of the local authority, the matter more or less a line ball.  That is, that the income accruing from the fines meets the expenditure incurred, but what happens under the proposal in the Bill is that these fines are taken away from the local authority, and still the local authority has to bear the expense of bringing these claims before the court and getting the delinquents fined.  Having achieved that object, the fines go into the hands of the Finance Minister. As I have said, this is a rather serious matter for the local authorities.  I have had communications from local authorities in different parts of the country, and there seems to be a consensus of agreement that the taking away of the fines as proposed under this section will mean imposing a burden on the local authorities to the extent of about ½d. in the £.  At present that seems to be the position, to cast further burdens on the local authorities and to take from these authorities the sources of income which they have been enjoying for a number of years.</P>
      <P>It will be within the recollection of the House that within the last few days I asked why a particular income the local authorities had been enjoying for some years, that is, the surplus of the dog tax, had not been forwarded to the local authorities during the last couple of years, as had been done for a number of years previously.  To show the policy that is being pursued by the Government with regard to local authorities, I will read an answer I received from the Minister:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;Orders have been made under the Petty Sessions Clerks (Ireland) Act, 1881, diverting into the District Court Clerks Funds all the proceeds of the sale of dog licences up to the end of 1924, save such amounts as have already been distributed to local authorities.  The 1925 collection, the final collection under the old <Col N="1628" /> law, will be similarly diverted.  The Acts under which the dogs' duty was formerly collected and distributed were repealed by the Finance Act of 1925.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I do not know whether any of the other Deputies in the House were aware of a section to that effect in the 1925 Finance Act.  I have no recollection of the Minister having explained to the Dáil that under this particular Act the local authorities were to suffer to this extent.  It is only as time goes on we find out difficulties with regard to these Acts.  The answer goes on to say:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The dog duty is an Excise duty payable into the Exchequer, and no part of it can be paid to the local authority.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That means, in connection with the particular local authority with which I have been associated a loss of about £180 per annum.  In addition to that we have this particular section, which will mean casting on the same local authority a burden of almost an equivalent amount.  There are two classes of fines local authorities receive.  In one case the average expense would amount to about £74 per annum, and in the other case to a lesser amount.  I offer the strongest protest against the policy embodied in this Bill of taking from the local authorities incomes which they had been in receipt of for a great many years&mdash;I will not say how long, but I will ask the Minister to enlighten us on that point, and on the other hand casting on the local authorities these burdens in Act after Act which we have had before us.  Only the other day we were dealing with pensions accruing under the technical instruction scheme. The local authority pays only about one-fourth of the salaries of the technical instruction officers, and yet as the officers become pensionable the whole pension is cast on the local authority.  That seems to be the policy of the Government: on the one hand to take from these local authorities the different sources of income of which they have been in receipt, and on the other hand to cast on them year by year additional burdens which in the past were discharged by the State. There seems to be no hesitation in <Col N="1629" /> placing these burdens on the local authorities.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>On Committee Stage, as Deputy Good reminds us, there was considerable discussion on Section 44, and I undertook to bring for Deputy Good and Deputy Hewat as much information on the matter as I could collect between the Committee Stage and Report.  I find that the total amount of the fines, using the word in its broadest sense, imposed by the district court in the Saorstát, including the Dublin Metropolitan area, and actually collected, may be taken at £22,000 per annum.  Of that, £7,500 comes from Dublin, and the balance, £14,500, from the rest of the Saorstát. Fines in the Superior Courts are so rare as to be negligible, except as regards fines on jurors for non-attendance and which would come to the State irrespective of this particular provision. I have a table here showing how this money, when collected, is distributed, and showing also how much of it comes from the Dublin area on the one hand and from the remainder of the State on the other.  Of the fines inflicted in the Dublin area, a total of £7,500, the disposal is as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="40*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Towards the upkeep of the Gárda Síochána</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">£3,250</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>To the Revenue Commissioners</entry>
            <entry>200</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>To the Road Fund</entry>
            <entry>2,500</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>To the local authorities</entry>
            <entry>1,300</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>To the General Cattle Diseases Fund</entry>
            <entry>200</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>To the Conservators of Fisheries</entry>
            <entry>50</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>The total of fines inflicted elsewhere than in Dublin is £14,500, and the disposal is as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="40*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Into the Fines and Fees Fund</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">£8,000</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>which of course goes to the upkeep of the district court clerk system.</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>To the Revenue Commissioners</entry>
            <entry>2,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>To the Road Fund</entry>
            <entry>2,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>To the local authorities</entry>
            <entry>1,700</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>To the General Cattle Diseases Fund</entry>
            <entry>200</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>To the Conservators of Fisheries</entry>
            <entry>200</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <Col N="1630" />To the Gárda Síochána Reward Fund</entry>
            <entry>£400</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>The total then for the whole country would be:&mdash;</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="40*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Fines and Fees Fund</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">£8,000</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Upkeep of the Gárda Síochána</entry>
            <entry>3,250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Revenue Commissioners</entry>
            <entry>2,200</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Road Fund</entry>
            <entry>4,500</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Local authorities</entry>
            <entry>3,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cattle Diseases Fund</entry>
            <entry>400</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Conservators of Fisheries</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>The Gárda Síochána Reward Fund</entry>
            <entry>400</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Making a total of</entry>
            <entry>£22,000</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>From that table it will be clear that of the total collection of £22,000 the following sums are, already, under the existing law, appropriated in fact for the Exchequer&mdash;that is, they are under the existing laws used towards defraying expenses for which the Exchequer is liable&mdash;a sum of £8,000 to the Fines and Fees Fund; £3,250 for the Gárda Síochána; £2,200 for the Revenue Commissioners&mdash;total, £13,450.</P>
    <P>As regards this £13,450, the present proposal would make no change whatever. It would certainly not affect any private individual or any local authority, but it would put in clear form what is at present dispersed over several Acts, some of them 70 or 80 years old.  Deducting that £13,450, we find ourselves dealing with the balance of £8,550 made up as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="40*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Road Fund</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">£4,500</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Local authorities</entry>
            <entry>3,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cattle Diseases Fund</entry>
            <entry>400</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Fisheries Conservators</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Gárda Síochána Reward Fund</entry>
            <entry>400</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Take the first item of that&mdash;I am sorry if I am boring Deputy Hewat&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister does not bore me on this subject at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>The existing law is that certain fines for road offences&mdash; what may be called motoring fines&mdash; are, by statute, payable to the registrar of district court clerks, who is bound to pay them into the Exchequer, and the Exchequer is bound in turn to make them over to the Road Fund.  The <Col N="1631" /> amount of the fines, as I have stated, is £4,500, and the other income of the Road Fund is over half a million per annum.  If it be assumed that the Minister for Justice and the Minister for Finance, under the powers that are taken or proposed to be taken under this section, will take the unfavourable view, namely, that no special order should be made under sub-section (4) continuing the existing system as regards these fines, then the proposal is to deprive the Road Fund of something less than one per cent. of its income. But it need not be assumed that the order will not be made under Section 4, sub-section (4), continuing that payment&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Do you mean sub-section (4) of Section 4?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  It should be remembered that the theory on which these fines were made payable to the Road Fund was presumably that offences would be detected by the officers of the local authorities, and would be imposed by local unpaid Justices of the Peace, assisted by the local appointed Petty Sessions Clerk, who was not paid by the State.  In fact, the offences are detected by the Gárda Síochána, fines are inflicted in a State court by a State paid Justice, assisted by in future a State paid and State appointed District Court Clerk. In some counties the only way in which the local authority has been active in the matter of these offences is to remit or reduce the penalty after the offender had been, without their co-operation, detected and punished.  It was found necessary during the past year, on account of the feebleness of local authorities in this matter, to give to the Gárda Síochána direct right of prosecution and to provide that in cases so prosecuted local authorities would not have any right to reduce the fines. That was done under Section 39 of the Local Government Act of 1925.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In face of facts like these, added to the desirability, which I think will be agreed, of getting the law as to the appropriation of fines into a simpler form, it does not seem excessive to ask that we should have discretion either <Col N="1632" /> to keep these fines or by express order to allow them to continue to go to the Road Fund.  In any case the existing scheme must be changed, because under the existing scheme these fines go into the Road Fund, through the registrar of the District Court Clerks, an officer for whose suppression this Bill provides.</P>
    <P>So much for the Road Fund.  Let us take then the next item&mdash;the Local Authorities £3,000.  Of this sum £1,200 goes to the Dublin Corporation, and £50 in relief of the impoverished rate-payers of Pembroke and Rathmines.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>£50 each?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>No; £50 in all. Fifty pounds, Deputy Good will agree, is scarcely a serious contribution towards the rates, although the Pembroke Council has taken the trouble to submit a statement showing no less than ten different classes of Acts of Parliament which have to be invoked in order to produce the £50 per annum. When it is remembered that the same area was, by a recent Act of the Oireachtas, on the occasion of the amalgamation of the Dublin Metropolitan Police with the Gárda Síochána, relieved of the special police rate, being a relief of about £7,000 in the first year and increasing by the same amount every year, until it becomes and remains an annual relief of over £50,000 per annum, it scarcely seems a serious argument that the Government should not be given the power to take over fines of £1,300 per annum, if it so desires, in the interest of simplicity and uniformity, rather than because the sum itself is worth coveting.  Fifty pounds a year is in the balance for Pembroke Urban Council, and Deputy Good holds up the Dáil for half an hour with his protest!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Of the remainder of the sum of £3,000 £1,700 goes to local authorities outside Dublin in the following proportions:&mdash; Cork City, £600; Limerick City, £350; Waterford City, £200; other places. £550.  So far as I can find, each of the three cities mentioned gets all the fines inflicted in the city because of an Act which has attained the respectable age of 86 years&mdash;the Municipal Corporation <Col N="1633" /> Act, 1840.  We cannot know now what the motives underlying that particular enactment were, but we are aware that the conditions in which the fines were then imposed were very different from the conditions which now exist.  The court, for instance, was a local court and not part of one State-maintained court.  We do not regard the Act as having any particular sanctity such as would make us slow to revise it after such a lapse of time and such a change of circumstances.  The remaining item &mdash;£550&mdash;is divided amongst a great number of places.  There are, for instance, rather more than 100 towns in the State which, under an Act passed 72 years ago&mdash;the Towns Improvement Act, 1854&mdash;have special rights to fines inflicted in these towns.  On that point, I may add that these towns formerly enjoyed two local courts&mdash;the ordinary petty sessions court and a town court, the latter being constituted under that Act of 1854.  If an inhabitant of the town happened to be apprehended in an advanced state of intoxication and disorder, he might be brought either before the petty sessions court or the town court, under the Towns Improvement Act.  If he were brought before the petty sessions court and fined 5/-, the town got 2/6.  If brought before the town court and fined 5/-, the town got the whole 5/-.  That, in itself, was sufficiently complicated, but when, by our Courts of Justice Act, 1924, the authority of both courts was transferred to the District Court, the position became a rather curious one.  The District Justice is now the town court and the petty sessions court in one.  It would be a difficult task to decide whether the town is now entitled to the five shillings inasmuch as the District Justice is the continuation of the Town Court under the Towns Improvement Act, or only to the sum of 2/6 inasmuch as the District Justice is the continuation of the petty sessions court.  In some places the matter has gone even a step further&mdash;that is where the Commissioners were dissolved, by order or other process, and their powers vested in other bodies or persons, which were not in existence when the Act of 1854 was passed.  We have to decide, therefore, on the question of how these funds are to be <Col N="1634" /> divided over one hundred claimants whose claims cannot, on the average be as high as £2 per annum each and whose rights arise under an Act passed 72 years ago, before the present courts, before the present police, and before the present policy as regards local authorities was dreamt of.  The State-paid police arrest a disorderly drunkard. He is fined 5/- by the State-paid justice.  The conviction is entered and a warrant issued by the State-paid clerk.  The fine is paid and reaches the Registrar of District Court Clerks. That official has then to send the money back to the district court clerk, pointing out that this place is, or was once, covered by the Act of 1854, and directing the clerk to find out who are the town commissioners there or the person or body acting as such.  Sometimes they are easily found; sometimes they are not.  When found, they are very pleased to get 2/6 on a transaction of which they heard for the first time.  The whole affair is somewhat on the ludicrous side, and the final and satisfactory allocation of that 2/6 costs the State more than it costs the drunkard.  The figures which I have given as paid to local authorities include the fines so payable under the Public Health Acts, the Weights and Measures Act, the Food and Drugs Act, and several Acts of that character.</P>
    <P>As to the General Cattle Diseases Fund, that fund gets £400 out of fines. The General Cattle Diseases Fund, of which I heard for the first time when Deputies Hewat and Good became interested in this matter, was set up by the Act of 1854, and is used by the Department of Agriculture as a fund out of which to repay the local authorities half of their expenditure in connection with these diseases.  The fund is kept up to strength by the levy at irregular intervals of a rate of a farthing in the £.  Fines imposed in prosecutions under the Acts dealing with cattle diseases go into that fund.  I am informed that the Department of Agriculture does not regard this income from fines as a very serious contribution. The payment into the Fines and Fees Fund of these fines, their earmarking in that fund and their payment out again take a good deal of time and attention.  It is one of these things that <Col N="1635" /> tend to distract activities of the staff from more serious work.  This is one of the cases where, I think, the Government might have a discretion to alter the system or not to alter it, as seems on the balance and after consideration the proper course.</P>
    <P>There is a sum of £300 per annum paid to fishery conservators as fines or portions of fines.  The law as regards penalties in fishery cases is anything but clear.  The net result when each case has been argued out is that £300 per annum is distributed between the various boards of conservators.  There are rather more than a score of such boards operating at present, which gives a total of rather less than £15 per annum per board.  It is not considered that that constitutes a serious help towards the object of these boards, but if we receive convincing representations to the contrary and if there is not a less troublesome way out of the difficulty, I should certainly ask the Minister for Finance to concur in an order which will preserve the present benefit without the present complications.</P>
    <P>The last of the classes of fines in the table is a sum of £400, consisting of payments made into the Gárda Síochána Reward Fund.  All fines awarded to a Gárda as an informer, to use the words of the statute, are paid into the fund.  The particular informer gets no immediate benefit.  After we have exhausted these classifications there is still left a miscellaneous class of fines so small in amount that no sum can be set down as their average annual value.  Deputies will perhaps realise the position more clearly in this way: There are over 160 district court clerks, each of whom accounts quarter for all fines received by him. Generally the fine itself is sent up with the account, but when the fine is payable to somebody outside the Department, that is, when it does not come to the Department, either to keep or to distribute, the clerk hands the money over to the proper person and sends up, instead of the money, the receipt he gets from that person.  The Department sees that the receipt is in order and that the fine was properly paid over, and there the matter ends.  If all <Col N="1636" /> these receipts for the past sixty years had been taken out of their files and properly indexed they would form the subject of an interesting booklet on the appropriation of fines.  Deputy Cooper told us that under a private Act he is entitled to some fishery fines, and possibly we have a record of a receipt from himself or from one of his predecessors in title.  Deputy Hewat spoke of a similar right vested in the Dublin Port and Docks Board.  We have actually a receipt for 5/-, being the Board's revenue for a year from that source.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Hewat only made a reference to it.  He did not make a claim for the money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Pembroke Urban Council, £50; the Dublin Port and Docks Board, 5/- per annum!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Nothing when you say it quickly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I am trying to say it quickly.  I could entertain Deputies Good and Hewat at greater length, but possibly I have said enough to convince the Dáil, if not to convince these two Deputies, that there is nothing wrong in the proposal in the Bill, that we should be allowed to abolish these special distributions out of fines, and then deal with each case for continuance on its merits, and make or not make an order at our discretion.  If there is a substantial case for reviving any of these by special order there is power to do that in sub-section (4) of this section.  But these distributions, under Acts 86 and 72 years old, passed in an entirely different set of circumstances, passed in circumstances which might justify some special allocation such as we have considered, ought not to be considered sacrosanct and stereotyped for all time, now that the circumstances have entirely changed.  There is no question of looting the exchequers of the local authorities, as has been suggested.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any guarantee on that point?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>If Deputy Good can put up a good case for his £50 per annum he will get it by special order <Col N="1637" /> under sub-section (4).  I give him a most solemn undertaking to that effect, and the same applies to Deputy Hewat's five bob per annum.  What we are really striving to get free from is a complex and cumbersome system, making demands on staff out of all proportion to the importance of the matter or the largeness of the amounts involved. If any good case can be put up for making a special order that some proportion of the fines for a certain offence should be paid to some person or body, that order will be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>But there is no guarantee that such an order will be made. That is my objection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>None whatever. The Deputy will only have to take our word for it, and he apparently holds that lightly.  Really, the time that this matter has taken in the Dáil is as unwarranted as it is out of all proportion to its importance, but these two Business Deputies wanted to get the facts, and I felt it was incumbent on me to prepare and to bring along the facts. I have endeavoured to give them. Having heard them, I trust that the Dáil will share our view that that which is proposed in the Bill is the sensible, even the business-like thing to do, and to leave it to our well-known sense of equity to make an order in any case where the making of an order is warranted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>As we spend our time here we learn very many things, but I am beginning to learn that it is a mistake to ask the Minister for Justice for any information, because he floods one with such an amount of it that one is really submerged in one's argument. He has taken up the line that we, particularly Deputy Good and myself, have made the claim that this matter of distribution was all wrong.  I am not clear that I ever made any such claim.  As regards the principle that underlies this, the simplification of the question of fines, so far from being in disagreement with the Minister for Justice to the extent of calling forth the mass of information we have got on the subject, I happened to interject the remark that I knew some private <Col N="1638" /> interests were concerned with the fines, and instanced the Port and Docks Board, and the Minister now tells me they are to the extent of 5/-.  I did not know what it was.  Whether it is a matter of 5/- or £5,000 the principle underlying the thing is just the same. One must remember that the Minister for Justice knew very little about this when it was last before the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Nothing at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>And all this collective information has been obtained by him subsequent to the introduction of the Bill.  The Bill provides for the taking over of fines, which, rightly or wrongly, have been going to different local bodies, and to that extent the revenues of these bodies will be reduced. I agree that perhaps this matter has taken longer to discuss than is justifiable in view of its importance, but I do suggest that the time has been unnecessarily taken up by the Minister, because he could in two minutes have given us a synopsis of the information which he has given in such a very elaborate form.  It comes to this: that under the arrangement in this Bill all these fines are going to the Central Fund.  The simplification that will obviously take place, by the reconstitution of the law on the subject, is all to the good.  I do not disagree with the Minister on that.  I heartily agree with him.  Pembroke Urban Council has been referred to.  For some considerable time it has been getting £50 a year for nothing.  If it is to lose that £50 now the loss is just as much to that Council as the loss would be to another person whose property you would take.  It is portion of the revenue of the Council.  The Minister rather jeers at the idea of £50 being of any importance to Pembroke Council.  I agree that it is not, but what is the principle?  Is the Government standing for the confiscation of even £50?  The Minister, I think, stated that circumstances have changed.  If Pembroke Council got the £50 a year, even if it was nothing but a subsidy, it shows the trend of the mind of the Executive when the Minister evades the issue, which is, the loss of £50 to the Pembroke Council. <Col N="1639" /> The question now is, whether the Government is prepared to compensate the Council for that loss?  On the other hand, is the Executive, as has been done in other cases, going to take away arbitrarily from the Council a privilege that it enjoyed, rightly or wrongly, in the past?  I say that the Dáil should be chary about arbitrarily taking away sums of this kind, even if they are insignificant sums.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>As I listened to the Minister I could not help coming to the conclusion from the attitude he adopted, that he was anxious to establish the right to become the funny man of this House.  I think the House agreed previously that that right had been held, and would be held, during the term of this Dáil, by the Minister for Education.  I do not object to the Minister dealing with these serious matters of principle in this jocular way, but when he tells us that it only affects Pembroke and Rathmines to the extent of £50, he is telling us what is inaccurate.  Pembroke district is very much smaller than Rathmines.  I have a return from an official of the Pembroke Council showing the income that accrues to it from prosecutions under the Food and Drugs and other of the Public Health Acts.  This shows that taking an average of nineteen years, the amount was £51.  It is well known to the Minister, because he represents County Dublin constituency, which embraces Rathmines, that Rathmines is a very much larger area than Pembroke.  If Pembroke district is affected to the extent of £51, Rathmines is affected to a very much larger extent.  To say that the section only affects these two districts to the extent of £50 is to say what is not true.  It is all very well to deal jocularly with a matter in which £50 is involved.  I do not know to what extent the Dublin Corporation is affected.  It must be a serious matter for the Dublin Corporation.  In order to obtain this £50 by taking the steps necessary for the protection of the public health, the local authority has to incur an expenditure of £100.  In the district I am concerned with the expenditure on these particular matters <Col N="1640" /> amounts, on an average, I am informed, to £100 per annum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What is the Minister's proposal? His proposal is that the £50 which the local authority has recovered is to be taken away, but the local authority is still to be left with the liability of £100 per annum in order to recover the £50 which is to accrue to someone else. Does the Minister tell us there is nothing wrong about that?  In the past he told us that figures were not his strong point.  If there is nothing wrong in putting a local authority to an expenditure of £100 per annum in the interests of public health, and of taking away the £50 recovered from fines as a result of such expenditure, it seems to me a most extraordinary transaction from the business point of view.  If the Minister had said: &ldquo;We are going to take the fines from you but, on the other hand, we are going to take away the expense you are put to in recovering them,&rdquo; I think that would be a fair proposition that no one would object to.  To take away from local authorities something that accrues to them as a result of expenditure they incur is, to my mind, immoral.  What will be the effect of this on the local authorities? These local authorities incur expenditure in the interests of the public health.  If they are not going to receive any benefit by that expenditure, is it likely that they are going to be as active as they were?  That is bound to be the effect of this proposal.  These local authorities have done their work well in the past, but if the Government is going to act as a deterrent, do not blame the local authorities if they are not as active in the future in these particular matters.  The Minister has pointed out that it is within the province of the Minister for Finance to say that a certain sum recovered from the fines shall be paid to the local authorities.  Let us have some clause to that effect.  We know the Ministers we now have on the front Benches, but they will not be here for all time, much as we would like to have them.  That is more than we could hope for.  We want something more than what one would call personal undertakings in these matters. We want some protection on the part of these local authorities that if <Col N="1641" /> they incur this expenditure at least the Minister for Finance, under the particular section of this Bill, will recoup them.  If that is done, I am satisfied, but until that is done I will not remain silent.</P>
    <P>Amendment 20 put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 21:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 16, Section 44 (4), line 58, and also in line 61 after the word &ldquo;fine&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;or penalty,&rdquo; and in line 58 after the word &ldquo;fines&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;or penalties.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This is really a drafting amendment. Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 22:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 17 to delete Section 47, lines 12 to 31.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I put down this for the opportunity it affords me of placing before the Minister and the House certain representations made to me as to the effect of the abolition of the office of under-sheriff, and to ask the Minister to consider the matter from the point of view that I intend to place before the House.  The duties of the under-sheriff, it is intended shall, as time passes, be transferred to the county registrar.  He is a civil servant who will have very many duties which will occupy his close attention and, as is suggested to me, will not enable him to undertake the personal supervision of the work accruing to an under-sheriff.  As a consequence, it will be inevitable that the work of the office of under-sheriff, which will henceforward be transferred to the county registrar, must be undertaken by a subordinate official under that registrar. The effect of that transfer of the actual work of the office will be to make the activities of the county registrar in this respect much more formal and rigid than hitherto it has been.  The position of the under-sheriff who has had judgment placed into his hands for execution is that he acts for the plaintiff in the case and hitherto there has been, I think it is fairly well known, a good deal of discretion as to the manner and the time of the execution of the judgment.  Debtors have been interviewed <Col N="1642" /> and the circumstances of the case have very often been taken into account by the under-sheriff.  He has used his discretion as to the manner of enforcing judgment and has thereby very often collected the money without breaking up the home and eased the position of the debtor.  That has made the work of the under-sheriff easier and has lightened the burden, to a very great extent, upon debtors. The sheriff, in doing that, has undertaken a personal responsibility.  He has undertaken certain risks but being in the position of personal contact with the case in question he has considered it desirable and worth the risk, and has considered that the circumstances were such as to justify him in taking it.  It is suggested with a good deal of force that that discretion ought to be continued if possible, but the effect of this proposal in the Bill will be to make the action of an under-sheriff&mdash;it will be in the future that of the county registrar&mdash; much more like that of a machine, and the discretion will not be and dare not be operated by the subordinate officials of the county registrar, inasmuch as he has no personal liability.  The liability remains with the county registrar who is not in a position, by virtue of the other duties of his office, to undertake the observation and inquiry into the case which would enable him to exercise the discretion hitherto exercised by the sheriff.</P>
    <P>The effect is to make much harder the position of debtors, to almost ensure that there will be a sale of the goods of every debtor without any question of time or easing the operations of the machine and generally it will make it harder for the work of the office to be carried through.  It is also pointed out that the exceptionally powerful position of the county registrar in relation to solicitors will make it very difficult for any solicitor to take action against the county registrar.  As I have said, there is a personal responsibility at present on the under-sheriff for the carrying out of those duties and a liability on him if he exceeds his duty.  The consequences of that liability will have to be drawn attention to.  Action will have to be taken by a solicitor, but a <Col N="1643" /> solicitor would be slow to take action against a county registrar who, in the daily operations of the solicitor's profession, would be in a position to help or retard the work of that solicitor, and generally the position of the solicitor, who sought to take action, would be difficult if there were imposed on the registrar liability for any action in excess of his duties.</P>
    <P>In a general way a case has been made for me, and I think it ought to be considered that the transfer of the duties of an under-sheriff to a civil servant is not advantageous for the carrying out of the law judicially, safely and humanely, but is in effect placing the debtor in a machine and the machine must operate without regard to any considerations of humanity or discretion of any kind.  Once they get into the hands of a subordinate official it will be the duty of that official to let the law take its course. I think that is a case the Minister ought to take into account, and consider whether it is strong enough to warrant any alteration in the proposals of this section.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy's amendment is a direct negative to the proposal that the duties of the under-sheriffs, as they die or retire, shall be transferred to the county registrar, the officer who under the new system will correspond to the clerk of the crown and peace of the past.  That proposal was given very careful consideration in my Department, and I am inclined to regret that, if the Deputy had a case to suggest against it, he did not do it at an earlier stage when we might have given fuller consideration to his objections.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not know of the case then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I can assure the Deputy that the change was not arrived at in any hasty or haphazard way.  It was arrived at only after consultation with many prominent practising solicitors up and down the country, and in no case where I consulted persons of that kind was there any anxiety or any disapproval expressed.  What we find <Col N="1644" /> in regard to the position of under-sheriffs is that in many counties the position is not big enough to attract the really big first-class energetic solicitor, and, as we know, three-quarters of his work is not properly solicitor's work at all, though admittedly it needs the general control and supervision of a person with a legal mind and some legal experience.  The position of under-sheriff within the last two or three years has been vacant in one county for some months with no applicants. It was becoming difficult to find men who would accept the work and the responsibility, and one county was without an under-sheriff for a considerable time.  I see no point in the Deputy's objection.  I think he said that this proposal would transfer the work and responsibility of the under-sheriff to a civil servant.</P>
      <P>If he insists in referring to the county registrar in the future scheme as a civil servant, may I point out that he would be no more nor no less a civil servant than an under-sheriff, inasmuch as we have decided to create the position that there shall be Parliamentary responsibility through a Minister in respect of all the officers attached to our courts system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Minister if there is a personal liability in the case of a county registrar as there is at present in that of an under-sheriff?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  I am glad to say that we are fortunate in having amongst the under-sheriffs many very capable and energetic men.  I may, perhaps, say that we have some who are not so good, and I think it would be increasingly difficult in future to get competent, highly-qualified men to accept that position, and that position alone.  Clearly, we will have no dearth of competent and highly-qualified applicants for the position of county registrar, and I do not think that it is a mistake, or that it will be found in practice to be a mistake, to devolve this work and responsibility of the under-sheriff in the county registrar's office according as the under-sheriffs disappear in one way or another.  It will ensure the supervision and control by men who will probably be selected for <Col N="1645" /> the position by being the best, or amongst the best, of the local practitioners. You will have no reluctance on the part of solicitors of good practice and standing to apply for the position of county registrar.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think it will be in the interests of both judgment debtors and judgment creditors to have this work and responsibility vested in men of that kind.  It may be interesting to the Deputy and the Dáil to know that we reached this change simply by the light of pure reason, and we were unaware that it, or anything resembling what we propose to adopt, existed elsewhere.  Yet when certain officials of my Department crossed to England for the purpose of understanding the system of courts and court officers there, they found that this very condition exists in Britain in regard to the county courts.  The under-sheriffs still exist there for high court purposes, but the work of the execution of decrees of the county courts is now vested in the officer who would correspond most closely to our county registrar.  It is, to some little extent, an economy.  It is a pruning of the total number of officials who will be in the employment of the State.  It provides for the disappearance of the office of under-sheriff, but it was not on grounds of economy that that decision was reached.  I believe it will make for efficiency and greater satisfaction&mdash;greater satisfaction, I fully believe, not merely to judgment debtors but to judgment creditors also.  For one thing we, perhaps, will not allow the Minister for Finance to have all the fruits of the economy caused by the disappearance of one particular officer.  I would hope that something of the saving effected by the disappearance of the under-sheriff would be used to ensure that the position of court messenger, as it has been decided to call it, would be made a better position than the position of the bailiff at present; that a better salary would be offered which would attract a better and more reputable type of man than we sometimes have to accept in that capacity to do that particular kind of work.  On that count, amongst others, I think that the balance of gain and desirability lies with this proposal <Col N="1646" /> that is embodied in the Bill.  We have not been entirely satisfied in the last few years that this work was proceeding as smoothly or efficiently as it might be in every county.  I hesitate to go very fully into that, lest these under-sheriffs, who are performing their work with the utmost competence and the greatest energy, might feel in some way slighted by my remarks. But there has not been complete satisfaction in every county, and, looking ahead, taking the long view, and considering what kind of man will be coming forward, if there was any coming forward at all, for the position of under-sheriff in the future, I think the change is desirable.</P>
    <P>Amendment 22, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 23:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 19, Section 53, line 50, immediately before the words &ldquo;shall apply&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;and every Act for the time being in force amending that Act.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 24:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 19, Section 54 (2), line 59, after the word &ldquo;may&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;with the sanction of the Minister for Finance.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The Minister for Finance considers that he should be consulted when it is being decided what officer shall give security.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment 25.&mdash;In page 20, Section 55, lines, 3, 10 and 25, to delete the word &ldquo;may&rdquo; and substitute in each case therefor the word &ldquo;shall.&rdquo;&mdash;(Deputy C.M. Byrne.)</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment 25 is rather peculiarly drafted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ChrisMByrne" hpid="Mr. C.M. BYRNE Mr. C.M. BYRNE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. C.M. BYRNE</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the amendment.  I should say that the object I had in mind was to provide that district court registrars would have the same rights as other registrars.  I would appeal to the Minister to accept the amendment.  I think it is only fair that these whole-time officers who gave good service to the State at a critical <Col N="1647" /> time should have the same rights as their predecessors; they should have the pensionable rights that other officers of the State have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>As the section stands, apart from the Deputy's amendment, the Minister for Justice, the Minister for Finance, and the Civil Service Commissioners may discriminate between those clerks who have a good claim to establishment and those who have not.  There might be such discrimination on a variety of grounds. The amendment is designed to remove any such power of selection.  If the amendment were accepted the Commissioners would be obliged to certify every whole-time clerk, even if they were to find on inquiry that he is totally unfit for the public service, and the certificate would have to be back-dated, although, apparently, it is left an open matter as to whether it is to be back-dated by one day or by a very much longer period.  The amendment is one that I would not be willing to accept.  Simply a reference to their predecessors is not a sufficient argument. It is better, I submit, that things should be considered on their merits, in the existing situation, than that they should be done by a vague reference to some state of affairs that existed here in the past and prior to the establishment of the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister say, in the case of a registrar who acted for two years in a parish court and who has since been appointed as registrar to a district court and who, after seven years' service, is found by some person in authority to be unfit to occupy the position, is it right or fair that he should be put out without a pension while the persons who occupy positions similar to his are entitled to pensions? We must have some respect for the men who carried on the work when it was not easy to do so.  The amendment simply tries to see that justice is done, and I think the Minister should reconsider the attitude he has taken up with regard to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. BYRNE Mr. BYRNE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BYRNE</NameTxt>
      <P>May I take it from the Minister that an officer who has given <Col N="1648" /> good service and who is proved to be efficient will be certificated?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>To accept the Deputy's amendment would be equivalent to a vote of no confidence in the Civil Service Commission.  I have confidence that in the case of a whole-time clerk who is, in fact, efficient in the public service, a certificate will issue. That, of course, is simply an expression of opinion from myself, but as between the &ldquo;may&rdquo; and the &ldquo;shall,&rdquo; I stand absolutely for the &ldquo;may.&rdquo;  I do not think the Dáil should seek to impose on the Civil Service Commission an obligation to issue a certificate in every case.  I would not be prepared to say, for instance, that there are not at the moment whole-time district court clerks in the country with regard to whom it is quite questionable whether they are fit to remain in their positions, but a clerk who is at once whole-time and efficient will, I believe, be certified under the section as it stands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. BYRNE Mr. BYRNE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BYRNE</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not wish to press the amendment.  In fact, I put it down for the purpose of raising the question of the status of these men.  I quite see the Minister's difficulty in the matter, and I am quite prepared to accept what he said, that a whole-time man who is efficient will probably be certificated.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 26:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 20, Section 55 (1), line 3, after the word &ldquo;may&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;on the recommendation of the Minister with the concurrence of the Minister for Finance.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That is: &ldquo;The Civil Service Commissioners may, on the recommendation of the Minister, with the concurrence of the Minister for Finance, grant to any person (whether paid or not paid out of public moneys) who at the passing of this Act is employed during the whole of his time in an office attached to a court of justice a certificate of qualification...&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 27:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In page 20, Section 55 (3), lines <Col N="1649" /> 23 and 24, to delete the words &ldquo;and attained the age of fifty-five years before the 1st day of January, 1924.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>As the section stands, there is no provision made for men who had not attained the age of 55 on that particular date.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 28:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 20, Section 56 (4) to delete all from and including the word &ldquo;analogous&rdquo; in line 63 to the end of the sub-section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister would give us some information on this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>On the face of it this amendment might appear to be a departure from or a repudiation of the policy several times stated, of retaining all existing court officers so far as possible.  It will be noticed, however, that even after the proposed deletion has taken place the section declares that so far as conveniently may be, and subject to the age limit, all existing officers shall be offered re-employment. What is deleted is that the new situation shall, so far as conveniently may be, be analogous to the former situation and that the new salaries shall be not less than the old salaries. I pointed out quite definitely when speaking on the Second Reading of the Bill that in the case of certain existing sorts&mdash;four or five of the clerkships of the Crown and Peace, for instance&mdash;it was not proposed to pay the same salaries as formerly, even if the same man was employed, because the old salary was absolutely impossible in the new system, perhaps £1,000 per annum more than we are prepared to pay. There will be some of the clerks of the Crown and Peace who were in receipt in the past, in that position, of a higher salary than we are prepared to pay to any county registrar.  There will be a maximum salary for each county registrar, even those who have been clerks of the Crown and Peace and who come on into the new system. There are some whose present salaries are so high that we would not be prepared to continue them at that level <Col N="1650" /> when they accept positions as county registrars.  If the section were to stand it would be compulsory to pay all these men, even those whose salaries were at a level which we consider impossible to pay in the future, the salaries which they held in the past.</P>
      <P>The only argument that we could have in defence of an action to compel us to do that would be to attempt to make use of the clause &ldquo;so far as conveniently may be&rdquo; and simply say that it was not convenient to pay salaries so high.  It is not right, I think, to avail of what would be regarded as a subterfuge of that kind, and consequently I am asking the Dáil to accept the deletion.  Except in the case of those three or five clerks of the Crown and Peace, subject, in fact, to a maximum of about £1,450 per annum, we are prepared, and we do in fact propose, whether this amendment is carried or whether it is not, to reemploy every man who is under the age limit and who is not obviously and hopelessly incapable or invalided&mdash;perhaps there might be two or three&mdash;and to pay to him his old salary or scale of salary and to give him the same class of work so far as that class of work continues to exist.  That is so important that perhaps it should be repeated.  Except in the case of those three or five clerks of the Crown and Peace of whom I speak, subject in fact to a maximum of about £1,450 per annum, we are prepared and we propose, whether this amendment is carried or whether it is not, to reemploy every man who is under the age limit and who is not obviously and hopelessly invalided&mdash;there might be two or three of those&mdash;and to pay to him his old salary or scale of salary and to give him the same class of work so far as that class of work continues to exist.  Deputies may ask, in the light of that assurance, why the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Or why the sub-section?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I suppose the sub-section was put in because we were legislating after all to define in precise terms the position of existing officers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1651" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Exactly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I have shown at any rate that if the text were to stand we would be compelled to pay inordinately high salaries to certain clerks of the Crown and Peace if they were to accept office as registrars.  There must be some kind of relativity between salaries in a State system, and to have salaries up to and even upwards of £2,000 per annum when the head of the Department is in receipt of £1,200 per annum would not be right.  We are, in fact, prepared to pay to an existing clerk of the Crown and Peace, who accepts office as a county registrar, up to a maximum of about £1,450 per annum, but there must be some maximum.  We are not satisfied with the text as it stands.  If it means, as we think it does mean and as it probably does mean, that we are under no obligation, that we can always say in reply to any request or complaint that it would be inconvenient for us to do this or that and that we need not do it, and if that is the position under the present wording&mdash;I am advised that it probably is&mdash; then the present wording is really almost fraudulent.  It seems to give a legal security which in fact it does not give, so looking at it in the most charitable way it is merely a pious expression of opinion, but not a binding expression of what the Government means to do.  If that is all it is, such a statement which can be repudiated at law though not in honour, should be made by way of a statement in the Dáil&mdash;such a statement as I have very deliberately and very emphatically made just now&mdash;and it should not be made by way of a clause in an Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the other hand, there is the possibility that the text, as it stands, may be capable of being put into suit, as the saying is; that a clerk could bring the Government before the High Court to show cause why he should be employed in the Examiner's office rather than in the Probate office, let us say. A position of that kind is wholly unacceptable to us.  We are not prepared to assist or to participate, in any such law-suit, and we think the Dáil ought not to create a position in which any such law-suit would be thinkable or <Col N="1652" /> possible.  We will do our best to reconcile the new system and the old staff, but, if we think that the public convenience requires to give official A B, who has hitherto had an easy time in an overstaffed part of the courts a more strenuous time in some other part of the courts, then we ought never to be put in the position that a State case can be made out of that, or that there can be legislation as between the official and the Government.  So that whether we are to take it that this text as it stands is a mere pious expression of intention that could be evaded merely by the subterfuge that it was inconvenient, or whether we take it that it would have a real and binding effect which would enable the official to litigate as against the Government in connection with the work he is asked to do&mdash;in either case we object to the text and ask for its deletion.</P>
    <P>My own advice is that the former is the position, and really means nothing or next to nothing, that it would be a complete reply on the part of the Department to plead inconvenience.  I would not like that position.  I would not like that we should write into any of our statutes simply any ineffective pious expression of that kind.  On the other hand, if there is even the possibility of litigation, arising as between the official and the Government, under the section, I think the Dáil should take steps to remove that possibility.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister has made a case for the deletion of the sub-section as a whole&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The assurance he has given the members of these staffs is, in his view, adequate, being quite definite, as speaking with the responsibility of the Minister in charge of the Bill.  If that is sufficient, then it seems to me there is no need for the sub-section. On the other hand, I think it is desirable that there should be a sub-section in the Bill safeguarding the position of those servants, and the case that the Minister has made would, I suggest, be met if he were to delete <Col N="1653" /> those words &ldquo;so far as conveniently may be,&rdquo; and to add a proviso fixing a maximum salary and deleting also the words &ldquo;analogous to.&rdquo;  Then the sub-section would read: &ldquo;Subject to the provisions of this Act prescribing the qualifications and retiring ages for particular officers, every existing officer and servant who is not a temporary officer, or servant, shall be offered employment in a situation under this Act, carrying not less salary than the situation held by him as such existing officer or servant, at the passing of this Act, provided it shall not exceed such sum as the Minister may allow.&rdquo;  That, I think, would satisfy all the claims the Minister made in his speech in support of the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>took the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the position of civil servants if the amendment is carried?  There is no guarantee whatever of continued employment, because, as is possible, though unlikely, the Minister can safeguard himself by saying it is not convenient to offer employment, and the purpose of this sub-section, as I read it, is to ensure that the employment to be afforded would be analogous, and carry an equivalent salary.  There may be only half a dozen men affected who are at present receiving more salary than it is intended to pay, but there are very many more people who will be affected by this section, and if the amendment is carried, as the Minister proposes, they have no protection except the statement that the Minister has made here to-day. If that statement is sufficient there is absolutely no need for this sub-section at all, but if it is desirable to embody in the Bill these assurances and guarantees, then, I say the guarantees should be such as would ensure within certain limits, those limits being the amounts over £1,400 a year, that the staffs in the new employment would receive a salary not less than that which they are receiving at present.  I think all the intentions of the Minister would be secured very much better than by an amendment if he would delete the words &ldquo;analogous to&rdquo; and give some guarantee in the Bill that <Col N="1654" /> the new employment will carry a salary not less generous than that which they are now receiving within those limits of £1,400 a year, or whatever sum may be fixed.  I am afraid if the amendment is carried, as proposed, it means removing every guarantee, except that which the Minister has stated in the course of his speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a good deal of substance in what Deputy Johnson urged, and my position in the matter is this: that if the amendment is accepted I am prepared to introduce an amendment in the Seanad that will meet his point of view.  I am quite willing to secure in their salaries the staff that is taken over, and there is no desire to leave that matter fluid at all. I would like if the amendment was now accepted, and if I were left free to bring up in the Seanad an amendment that will meet the point of view that Deputy Johnson has expressed.  That would, of course, come back here, and the Deputy would have an opportunity of saying whether or not the amendment did in fact fully meet his case. I am just wondering whether it is possible to secure acceptance of the amendment in the light of the undertaking given on my part.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>This is one of those amendments that makes things worse. Even in view of the undertaking given by the Minister, I am doubtful whether we ought to pass this amendment now.  If the Minister is going to bring forward amendments in the Seanad they will have to be more or less root and branch amendments.  It is possible the Seanad may not accept such amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>What does the Deputy mean by &ldquo;root and branch&rdquo;?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I was trying to be brief but now I will make a lengthy statement.  What I mean is that there will have to be a drastic remodelling of the whole of sub-section 4 if you are to meet the fears of the existing staff. That remodelling may fail to find acceptance from the Seanad.  In that case we shall have passed this amendment and shall have no opportunity of reconsidering it.  It is an extraordinarily <Col N="1655" /> drastic amendment, if it is intended to cover only the three or four cases the Minister spoke of.  Let us take the extreme case the Minister mentioned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>It is meant to cover more than that.  May I say a word or two by way of clarification?  It is meant to cover more than that case. It is meant definitely to remove the possibility that a court official can cite the Government's representative before the High Court or the Supreme Court to show cause why he is not in a soft position in office X, where he was prior to the change, instead of being in a strenuous position in office Y.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I note the Minister's point.  That, in effect, means that the official will not run the risk of being placed in that position, and will insist on going on the pension list. Take the text of the amendment: it simply says that the existing official shall be offered a situation in the courts of justice.  It does not say that he shall be offered a situation of the same grade or the same character as he had heretofore.  I accept the Minister's assurance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>He will have an analogous position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us take an extreme case.  Suppose, for instance, the Minister were to go to a taxing master and offer him the position of hall porter, that would be quite possible under the sub-section.  Perhaps the taxing master would consider that it is better to be a door-keeper in the courts of the law than to dwell among the unrighteous. I do not say that the taxing master dwells among the unrighteous, because he generally dwells among solicitors.  It may be desirable to be a door-keeper in the courts of law, but I know no authority, scriptural or otherwise, that says it is better to be a door-keeper in the courts of the law than to be a taxing master.  The Minister would have power to alter a man's position in that way.  I do not say that he would do so, but he has the power.  This amendment goes much further than anything the Minister requires. <Col N="1656" /> I would suggest to the Minister that his amendment in the Seanad should take the form of scheduling the posts in which it is proposed to impose new conditions.  I am not at all anxious to encourage litigation in the Civil Service, and I think the way to avoid litigation is to remove fears, even though they may be unnecessary, and make the position of the Civil Servant perfectly clear.  Therefore, I think we would be unwise to assent to this amendment.</P>
      <P>The Minister said the salaries of some Clerks of the Crown and Peace were £1,000 more than they ought to be.  The maximum salary for a Clerk of the Crown and Peace is £1,200, inclusive. There are one or two more who may be paid higher than that, with a bonus.  I am going now by the Estimates.  The total bonus for 27 Clerks of the Crown and Peace is £7,000.  I do not think the Minister is going to lay down a rule that the standard salary of the Clerk of the Crown and Peace should be £200. That would not keep a capable professional man such as the Clerk of the Crown and Peace.  This whole matter should be gone into very carefully by the Dáil and Seanad and not merely by the Minister.</P>
      <P>I would be reluctant to sweep away the safeguard to officials without a more precise and definite assurance than the Minister has given.  I accept his assurance, of course, but I would like it to be more definitely defined; otherwise you will swell the pension vote.  It must be remembered that these fears do exist.  The Minister knows that as well as I do.  There is the fear that officials will be placed in an inferior position.  There is not much fear from the point of view of having to do harder work; but there is the anxiety that officials will be made subordinate to people formerly subordinate to them and that these officials will be placed on a lower grade. Amongst many officials that fear exists.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>These officials have rights under the Treaty and they are entitled to go on pension.  The pension list is already far too big and we all want to avoid making it bigger.  That can be avoided much more readily by retaining safeguards in the section or inserting alternative words that will give some <Col N="1657" /> safeguard other than the amendment of Deputy Duggan, which gives no safeguard at all.  I agree with Deputy Johnson that the sub-section might as well be withdrawn as agreed to with the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Cooper may take it that I am not any more anxious than he is to swell the pension list.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I quite agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>But there is a limit to which all this talk about fears and anxieties and so on can be catered for. There is a point at which the suggestion or threat of swelling the pension vote reaches almost the stage of blackmail and when you have got to say: &ldquo;Well, if you are going to swell the pension vote, unless you get an exorbitant salary for the remainder of your life as long as you are able to cling on to office, then you better be off and swell it.&rdquo;  I have said that we are willing to pay up to a maximum of £1,450 to a county registrar who has been a Clerk of the Crown and Peace, but not higher.  If Clerks of the Crown and Peace who are at present drawing more than that sum&mdash;and there are such men &mdash;say: &ldquo;Our fears and anxieties will get the better of us if you insist on that, and we will go and swell your pension vote,&rdquo; we say to them &ldquo;Go and swell it.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The suggestion of Deputy Johnson as to changes in the text was attractive to me, and, when I asked for the amendment on the understanding that I would consider the insertion of an amendment in the Seanad that would meet the point of view embodied in the Deputy's suggestion, I meant what I said.  As a matter of fact, it is only just caution which one acquires that makes me unwilling to say here and now that I would accept Deputy Johnson's alternative suggestion to the amendment.  I have nothing against it and I see nothing against it.  It is only a desire to examine it.  I do not want this amendment defeated now.  In fact, I suppose if I have to I will face a division on it and try to secure a majority.  I do not want to be defeated now, but I am not at all sure that the <Col N="1658" /> Deputy's suggestion is not a better solution, and I would undertake, if the amendment is passed, to consider the introduction of an amendment in the Seanad; in fact, I would undertake definitely to introduce such an amendment to give effect to the point of view embodied in the suggestion.</P>
    <P>I do not want the amendment defeated, because if I may put it this way: I want the Dáil to agree with me in the spirit in which I am moving the amendment and from the point of view that I am moving it, namely, that it is a wholly undesirable position to bring about that an official in the courts can say: &ldquo;Well, I had a soft time for the last five years in that office.  It was a bay; the backwater of the troubled stream passed us by and I was not overworked.  You have taken me out of that and put me into this other office where things are quite uncomfortably strenuous.  I will bring it before the court for a decision as to whether that is analogous duty.&rdquo;  It would be an utterly impossible position if, in our disposal of the staffs there, consequent on the passing of this Act, we were to be threatened by this official and that official that unless he got a particular position he would ask for a decision of the courts as to whether it was analogous duty or not.  So far as I can I have tried to explain my position to the Dáil.  I see nothing against Deputy Johnson's suggestion.  It is just caution that makes me desire to examine it further, I want my own amendment passed, but I undertake to bring in, in the Seanad, an amendment that will fully meet the point of view underlying Deputy Johnson's suggestion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to make a suggestion to the Minister.  It is obvious that he desires to do what I think the Dáil desires in this matter, but there is a great deal of point in Deputy Cooper's statement that once the Bill passes the Dáil it goes to the Seanad as the considered opinion of the Dáil as to what ought to be in the section.  The Minister knows better than anyone else that the Seanad may exercise its discretion and refuse to accept his amendment, and then we <Col N="1659" /> have no remedy.  He could not come back to the Dáil and say: &ldquo;Alter the Bill in the way that the Dáil gave an indication of its desires.&rdquo;  I suggest to the Minister that inasmuch as this is an amendment of substance, that we are in practice, if not in fact, in Committee, and that as the Seanad is not to meet for a fortnight from to-morrow, we should have a further Report Stage when the Minister could bring forward his improved amendment for the acceptance of the Dáil.  I think that would be the right way to treat this. It would avoid the risk of the Bill passing without this assurance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to assure the Minister that I am not standing up for the lazy official any more than he is.  I am prepared not to push my opposition to this amendment to a division if the Minister can do as Deputy Johnson says, and if he will also undertake to have a consultation with these officials or their representatives who are affected by the amendment in the hope that we may get agreement among all parties.  That will remove fears which may be unreasonable and unnecessary, but fears which undoubtedly exist.  I appreciate the work the Minister is doing in this Bill.  I think reform of the courts is desirable and necessary.  I do not want to embarrass him, but equally I do not want to see the pension vote swelled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that we might pass from this amendment and proceed with the further amendments. Possibly by the time we have completed them I would be in a position either to make a suggestion or to define my own position in the matter more fully.</P>
      <P>Consideration of amendment postponed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 29:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 21, Section 56 (5), lines 30 to 56, to delete paragraphs (f) and (g) and substitute one paragraph as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;(f) the Acts which, immediately before he ceased by virtue of this section to hold office, authorised the <Col N="1660" /> grant to him of a pension or other allowance (from whatever fund or moneys such pension or allowance could have been granted) shall on his ceasing to hold a situation under this Act apply to him in the same manner and to the same extent as they applied to him immediately before he so ceased to hold office, but with and subject to the following modifications, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(i)  in computing the period of his service for the purpose of those Acts he shall be entitled to reckon as continuous service for those purposes whatever period (if any) of service he was or is deemed by virtue of this sub-section to have been entitled immediately before he so ceased to hold office to reckon as service for those purposes and his period of service in a situation under this Act, and</P>
    <P>(ii)  the Minister for Finance shall be substituted for the person authorised by those Acts to grant to him a pension or allowance, and</P>
    <P>(iii)  any pension or allowance granted to him shall be paid out of the moneys provided by the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>This amendment merely consolidates two paragraphs into one new paragraph, the sense of which is identical with the two originals.  The only difference is that it is explicitly declared that the Minister for Finance shall be substituted for the person authorised by the Acts referred to to grant a pension or allowance.</P>
    <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 30:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 21, Section 56 (5) (h), lines 62 and 63, to delete the words &ldquo;the commencement of this Part of this Act&rdquo; and substitute the words &ldquo;he ceased by virtue of this section to hold office.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This part of the Act comes into operation for a definite purpose on different dates, and this is really a drafting amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 31:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In page 21, Section 56, to add at <Col N="1661" /> the end of sub-section (5) a new paragraph as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(i)  he may on the recommendation of the Minister be retained, with his own consent and the sanction of the Minister for Finance, in a situation under this Act until he attains the age of seventy years.</P>
    <P>It is thought desirable that an existing court officer should in a particular case be retained for, say, a period of five years beyond the ordinary civil service retiring age of 65.</P>
    <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 32:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 22 to delete Section 59 and substitute a new section as follows:</P>
      <P>(1)  Every officer, servant, and other person holding or employed in any office or situation under this Act shall be paid out of moneys to be provided by the Oireachtas such salary as the Minister shall, with the sanction of the Minister for Finance, determine.</P>
      <P>(2)  All expenses (other than the salaries aforesaid) of carrying this Act into execution shall, to such extent as may be sanctioned by the Minister for Finance, be paid out of moneys to be provided by the Oireachtas.</P>
      <P>This is a more explicit statement of what was intended by the section in the Bill as drafted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that the last two lines in sub-section (1) of the amendment have some relationship to the section that we have just deferred for further consideration.  &ldquo;Every officer, servant or other person holding ... any office of situation under this Act shall be paid out of moneys to be provided by the Oireachtas such salary as the Minister shall, with the sanction of the Minister for Finance, determine.&rdquo; That may be a contradiction of the proposal that the office shall carry with it a salary not less than is existing.  I think that all that is required there is &ldquo;subject to the provisions of the other sections of the Act.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>If we insert here this new sub-section it seems to me that there would be need for the saving <Col N="1662" /> clause referred to in sub-section (4) of Section 56.  It may be that sub-section (4) of Section 56 is so specific and explicit that it would override the effect of this, but in view of the fact that there may be some little doubt about it I would undertake to clear it up after consultation with the Attorney-General, and if there is need for a saving clause to have it inserted.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment 28. (Discussion resumed).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>On amendment 28, our proposal would be very much on the line of what Deputy Johnson suggested:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In line 61 to insert after the word &ldquo;servant&rdquo;&ldquo;other than the Clerk of the Crown and Peace&rdquo;; in line 62 to delete the words in brackets &ldquo;(so far as conveniently may be)&rdquo;; and in line 63 to delete the words &ldquo;analogous to, and,&rdquo;</P>
      <P>So that the sub-section will read:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Subject to the provisions of this Act prescribing the qualifications and retiring ages for particular officers, every existing officer and servant other than a Clerk of the Crown and Peace who is not a temporary officer or servant shall be offered employment in a situation under this Act carrying not less salary than the situation held by him as such existing officer or servant at the passing of this Act.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That is open to the objection that we really only want to make exception in the case of the Clerk of the Crown and Peace in the matter of salary, and not in regard to the other matters specified. but I do not think that this proposal will be open to any misunderstanding, because these officers have been circularised and the proposals of the Government in their regard have been fully explained to them, so that I think a saving phrase there &ldquo;other than the Clerk of the Crown and Peace&rdquo; would not create any misapprehension I would be willing to withdraw my own amendment, and substitute these changes as a new amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>That would meet my case.</P>
      <P>Amendment 28 withdrawn.  New amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1663" /> Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill as amended be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That the provisions of Standing Order 88 as to the giving of notice for the taking of the Fifth Stage of a Bill be suspended to permit of the Fifth Stage of the Court Officers Bill, 1926, being taken to-day.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>On this point, I do not think the Minister can show urgency. If the last stage of the Bill is to be taken to-day there is no opportunity provided for the Dáil to amend the Bill in any particular.  There may be some small errors that have to be corrected on the last stage.  A very large number of amendments have been introduced on this Report Stage&mdash;no less than 32.  I think that unless cause is shown for urgency the last stage of a Bill of this kind ought not to be taken on this motion.  I do not think that urgency has been or can be shown.  The Seanad does not meet for a fortnight, and in the interest of the legislative process I think it is undesirable except in very special circumstances that the regular stages set out in the Standing Orders should be evaded.  In this case there is more reason for delay because of the necessity for going over the Bill as amended with a view to the correction of errors.  I think we should not pass the motion unless the Minister can show good reason for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Seanad were to meet this week I certainly would press the motion.  There is a certain urgency about the Bill.  It deals with important administrative matters that have been for a long time hanging fire, and there is a further urgency that the Rules of Court cannot be introduced until this Bill becomes law, for the reason that they deal with offices that will not have statutory existence until this Bill has become law.  It really, does not matter now in view of the fact that the Seanad does not meet, I think, until to-morrow fortnight.  I can take the Fifth Stage on Thursday, and the Bill can be in the hands of Senators in sufficient time.  I hope that between this and Thursday every <Col N="1664" /> Deputy will read the Bill carefully and search for grammatical errors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Committee Stage there was an amendment in my name which sought to confine the position of examiner to a solicitor.  I think the only remedy I have at the moment is to get an amendment moved in the Seanad.  The matter was discussed here in the Dáil, and I would like to know if the Minister has given the matter any consideration, or would he be favourably disposed to such an amendment as I have indicated if proposed in the Seanad?  The experience that a solicitor gets, in the ordinary course of his work, specially qualifies him for the position of examiner.  While I take it that I am out of order in raising the matter now, I do so with your permission, simply to ask the Minister for Justice if he could in any way lean towards accepting the amendment I have referred to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not a leaning in the direction that the Deputy would wish.  We gave pretty close consideration to the question of what offices would be confined to persons with professional qualifications, and I see no reason to extend it beyond the Master of the High Court confined to a member of the barrister's profession and the taxing masters confined to solicitors. The further suggestion that these examiners should be confined to persons qualified as solicitors is not really attractive or cogent.  For instance, they are not held at present by persons with that qualification, and yet I think there is no dissatisfaction with the present occupants.  If a trained official competent to perform that work has been produced, as it is admitted he has, there is no reason to believe that he will not be so produced in the future and that a man who has worked his way up in the service of the court, without the professional stamp on him, will not give entire satisfaction to the public.  It is always discouraging to a staff to find offices marked off for persons with professional qualifications. Frankly our aim was to reduce that to a minimum and to throw the maximum number of offices attached to the courts open to the ordinary process of promotion, <Col N="1665" /> so that a clerk coming into the service would feel that by industry and application to his work he could reach very high office, that he could reach to every position except Master of the High Court and Taxing Master.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to assent to that if the appointment is going to be absolutely confined to members of the staff.  But does the Minister not see that occasion might arise in which it would be advisable to import into that position a man with experience of the solicitor's profession?  Of course the Minister is not answerable if there is no occasion and never will be an occasion for anybody other than a member of the staff being promoted to that position.  I was only visualising its being necessary or desirable for the Minister's purpose to go outside the staff.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The motion by the Minister for Justice &mdash;No. 5 on the Orders of the Day&mdash; has been withdrawn.  The Final Stage will be taken on Thursday next.</P>
      <P>Sitting suspended at 6 p.m. and resumed at 6.45 p.m., <b>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</b> in the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="INCREASE OF RENT AND MORTGAGE INTEREST" RHead="(RESTRICTIONS) BILL, 1926&mdash;THIRD STAGE">
    <Title>INCREASE OF RENT AND MORTGAGE INTEREST (RESTRICTIONS) BILL, 1926&mdash;THIRD STAGE.</Title>
    <P>The Dáil went into Committee.</P>
    <P>Sections 1, 2 and 3 put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 4.</P>
    <P>The Principal Act shall as from the 24th day of June, 1926, be construed and have effect as if sub-section (1) of Section 3 thereof were amended as follows, that is to say, by the deletion of the first paragraph of the said sub-section, which paragraph begins with the words &ldquo;This Act shall&rdquo; and ends with the words &ldquo;a dwelling house to which this Act applies&rdquo; and the insertion of the following paragraph in lieu of the paragraph so deleted, that is to say:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(1) Subject to the provisions of this section, this Act shall, in respect of any particular house or part of a house let as a separate dwelling&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a) apply to such house or part <Col N="1666" /> of a house until and only until the 24th day of June, 1927, if either the amount of the standard rent or the rateable value of such house or part of a house does not exceed&mdash;</P>
    <P>(i) in the county borough of Dublin and the urban districts in the Dublin Metropolitan Area £52, and</P>
    <P>(ii) elsewhere £35, or</P>
    <P>(b) apply to such house or part of a house until and only until the 24th day of June, 1928, if either the amount of the standard rent or the rateable value of such house or part of a house does not exceed&mdash;</P>
    <P>(i) in the county borough of Dublin and the urban districts in the Dublin Metropolitan Area £40, and</P>
    <P>(ii) elsewhere £30, or</P>
    <P>(c) apply to such house or part of a house until and only until the 24th day of June, 1929, if either the amount of the standard rent or the rateable value of such house or part of a house does not exceed&mdash;</P>
    <P>(i) in the county borough of Dublin and the urban districts in the Dublin Metropolitan Area £30, and</P>
    <P>(ii) elsewhere £26;</P>
    <P>and every such house or part of a house shall until the date hereinbefore mentioned in respect thereof be deemed a dwelling house to which this Act applies.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. B. O'CONNOR Mr. B. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete paragraphs (a), (i) and (a) (ii), and to insert in line 44 after the word &ldquo;house&rdquo; where it secondly occurs, the words &ldquo;situated elsewhere than in the county borough of Dublin and the urban districts in the Dublin Metropolitan Area,&rdquo; and to add after the word &ldquo;exceed,&rdquo; line 48, the figures &ldquo;£25.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In Section 4, where the Minister proposes that the Restrictions Act shall not apply after June, 1927, to houses outside the Dublin Metropolitan area with a valuation of £35.  My amendment is to make it apply only to <Col N="1667" /> houses with a valuation of £25.  The object of the Bill is to make decontrol gradual.  The Rent Restrictions Act was first put in force as a war measure, but now, after eight years of peace, I think it is time that the restrictions should be removed.  I appreciate the line that the Minister has taken, that the removal of the restrictions should be gradual.  He has spread it over a period of three years, but I submit that with a valuation of £35 this Bill scarcely touches the fringe of the question at all.  I am dealing with houses outside the Dublin Metropolitan area.  If in Cork, Limerick, Galway, Sligo, or any other town where there is a house with a valuation of £35, it is almost a mansion.  In a country place a house with a valuation of £35 has about twelve or fourteen apartments, and it was never intended that such a house should be let to tenants.  The people who built them usually owned them, and they own them at present. Therefore I think it is only reasonable that the figure &ldquo;£35&rdquo; should be changed to &ldquo;£25,&rdquo; so that the decontrol will be felt gradually.  I think this is a reasonable proposal&mdash;I would not like to cut across the Minister with anything that is not reasonable&mdash;and that is why I propose the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It might help in the discussion if we took amendments 1 to 5 together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamEThrift" hpid="Professor THRIFT Professor THRIFT">
      <NameTxt>Professor THRIFT</NameTxt>
      <P>I also recognise that the Government may be wise in deciding to bring decontrol into effect gradually, and at the same time that those who have put forward these amendments have, in the main, accepted that as their conclusion, and that the question between the Government and themselves is really one as to the rapidity with which decontrol should take place.  Deputy Johnson, on Second Reading, spoke very much in favour of the continuance of control. I think it is hardly possible to discuss any of these amendments without referring to the fact that to many people &mdash;to me for one&mdash;it seems that the effects of control have been, in the <Col N="1668" /> main, harmful, harmful not alone to the landlords, but harmful to the tenants. I have put forward my amendments largely because of a very wise remark of the President's, a real challenge to everybody who is interested in this very important problem to contribute anything to arrive at a solution of what is a pressing question.</P>
      <P>This policy of control has been at work for a number of years, and I do not think anybody can argue that its effects have been good.  To my mind the effects have never been very good. From all the evidence that I have been able to get it seems to me that the policy of control is very largely responsible for the pressing nature of the housing problem to-day, that because it has killed private enterprise in this matter to a very large extent we are faced with our present difficulties.  I quite recognise that the Government may be wise in deciding on gradual decontrol, but it does seem to me that at this stage we might make a much big ger step towards decontrol than this Bill proposes.  If I am correct as to the meaning of Deputy O'Connor's amendment, he proposes that houses outside the Metropolitan area, if their valuation does not exceed £25, shall still remain under control.  The amendment does not refer to houses inside the Metropolitan area, but I take it that that is covered by his amendment No. 4, that he will propose, as I shall, that houses inside the Metropolitan area should also remain under control if the valuation does not exceed £30.  I take it that he means that that should apply to such houses, not alone for the year 1927 but for the year 1928.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have put figures in my amendments which seem to me to be exceedingly moderate&mdash;too moderate&mdash;and I am really more in favour of Deputy O'Connor's figures than I am of my own, if I interpret his two amendments correctly. I think it is urgently necessary that we should do something to encourage those who would be disposed to provide houses for others, and that we should encourage those who want to keep their houses in proper repair.  I think that this policy of control has contributed to a very large extent to some of our unemployment, that it has <Col N="1669" /> caused people to be thrown out of employment, because owners of house property have not been able to undertake the work required to keep their houses in a proper condition.  I know very many cases where small owners of house property have suffered most severely from this policy of control.  I think we ought to take a very big step in the direction of decontrol to show definitely that we mean to bring control to an end on the termination of this Act.  There are some other points to which it may be necessary to refer later, but inasmuch as the amendment before us is simply on this question of reducing the figures for houses outside the Metropolitan area, and implicitly, I think, reducing the figures for houses inside the Metropolitan area, which go from £52 to £30, I will content myself with these remarks at present.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to provoke a Second Reading discussion on this stage as to the wisdom or unwisdom of control.  At the same time I think it would be a mistake on my part to allow Deputy Thrift's statement to go unquestioned, that control has been, in the main, harmful.  Before one could subscribe to such a statement as that it would be necessary to envisage as clearly as possible the situation as it would have been without control, to remember that a housing shortage which was chronic in Dublin, at any rate, was accentuated and intensified by almost seven years complete cessation of building.  To suggest that it was not the business or the duty of the State to come in under these circumstances and try to keep down rents of houses below what the free play of the factors of supply and demand would bring them to, is a rather peculiar suggestion. Before I would say that control has been, in the main, harmful, I would have to try to envisage that other situation and guage the social reactions of the rents of houses left to the free play of economic factors, soaring widely above the resources of tenants and prospective tenants.  I would have to envisage hundreds of tenants evicted by process of law from their houses because of their inability to pay a rent which the landlord deemed the housing shortage would enable him to get in a <Col N="1670" /> free and open market.  I must differ from the Deputy.</P>
      <P>I am aware that control in individual cases produced anomalies, inequalities and injustices, but I am not prepared to say that it has been, in the main, harmful.  I can be told that it is a very serious state of affairs when a person is compelled to go on letting his house at a particular figure when, if he could get vacant possession and sell it, the proceeds of such sale invested at 5 per cent. or thereabouts would bring him in very much more than the annual rent.  I know that is the position, and that quite genuine cases can be shown of people who are compelled under this restrictive legislation to let their houses at a particular figure, who are prevented from raising that figure and who would, if they were free to sell their houses, realise an amount which, if invested, would bring them in substantially more than the controlled rent.  Recognising all that I still strongly query the suggestion that, in the main, control has been harmful.  It is impossible to deal with a situation such as that of the housing shortage, resulting from seven years' cessation of building, without inflicting some injury on individuals, but I think this step was necessary for the protection of the general community, and because of the social position which the absence of control would have opened up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think it is a good suggestion to deal with all these amendments bearing on the figures together.  The position which I have reached, after considering these amendments and discussing the matter with deputations, is that I am not standing pat on the figures in the Bill.  I make this offer to the movers of the various amendments, maintaining the idea of breaking the period of the Bill's operation into three parts.  Under the Bill the figures in Dublin are: for the first period a valuation of £52; for the second period, £40; for the third period, £30; and I offer instead, £40, £30, and £25.  For instance, I recognise that the houses that would be above £52 valuation in Dublin are not very numerous, and that there is rather an apparent than a real decontrol in the first year, at <Col N="1671" /> any rate, if I were to adhere to the figure of £52.  At any rate it is something more substantial to take a figure of £40 in the first year, £30 in the second year, and £25 in the third year. The figures in the Bill elsewhere than Dublin are £35, £30, and £26, and I am prepared to make a bargain with those interested on a basis of £30, £25, and £20.</P>
    <P>I got from the valuation office some tables bearing on average residential districts in Dublin, Pembroke, Rathmines, and so on, and some tables on typical provincial towns, such as Carlow and Kilkenny, and, as a result of a study of that kind, I came to the conclusion that the amounts prescribed by Section 4 of the Bill were rather on the high side.  Decontrol can only be brought about by coming down the scale of valuation in this way over a period.  It may be that whoever has the responsibility in 1929 will be able to face the situation on the basis of not legislating further in this way, and I think we should leave the position open to be considered in that time. But, in the meantime, I think the proposal as to valuation over the period of the Bill's duration, is, perhaps, the wiser course. That is my proposal over the period, Dublin £40, £30 and £25; elsewhere, £30, £25, and £20.  It is a considered proposal, and it is put forward in that way and in that spirit.  The fact that I am putting it forward may be taken as indicating that I will oppose the amendments if they are pressed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>I may state that I accept the proposal of the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamEThrift" hpid="Professor THRIFT Professor THRIFT">
      <NameTxt>Professor THRIFT</NameTxt>
      <P>I also am quite ready to agree to and accept the Minister's proposals.  I think he has met us very fairly.  I want to make one comment with reference to his criticism of my remark.  I intended to say that experience had shown that the working had led to evils that could not have been foreseen at the time the Acts were passed.  I did not intend to suggest that the Government in introducing those Acts had not been more or less constrained to pass them by the situation that existed.  My argument <Col N="1672" /> was that when those Acts were passed the evils which followed in their train had counterbalanced the advantage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder whether Deputies who have put down those amendments on their own account have considered the effect of their amendments or of the Minister's proposals. A case has been made on the Second Reading of the Bill that restrictions have prevented building.  I want to have some explanation of that, because there is nothing to prevent any house-builder or owner from getting whatever rent he likes for any new house in the present Act or in this Bill.  There is nothing in this Bill to deter builders from building houses, but with reference to the interval there is no information available in any Government Department indicating how many houses in the Dublin area either in the city or townships are at present vacant and available for tenants.  So we may take it that the proposals in the Bill are not based on any recognition of the supply of houses or are not going even in the direction of meeting the demand.  The demand is greater than the supply, and consequently the prices are high. People are forced, if they have any means at all, to pay more rent for their houses than they can afford, and the evidence of sub-tenants is to the effect that they are prepared to pay exorbitant rents for rooms.  That is a proof to me of the necessity for building more houses and having very many more built before you begin to remove restrictions, but by these proposals in the amendments to the Bill we are going to impose upon the occupier or tenants of the larger houses that are at presen controlled the obligation to pay a heavier rent than they are paying now or of getting out.  The middle-class section of the community&mdash;and perhaps this applies to a greater extent in Pembroke, Rathmines, and Dun Laoghaire&mdash;are occupying houses in the area which the Bill affects and will be obliged to pay a rack-rent or quit possession.  Their demand for smaller and cheaper houses will raise the cost and the rent of the houses upon the poorer section of the community.  By this very removal of restrictions you are imposing a greater pressure upon <Col N="1673" /> the poorer section in respect of houses whether as purchasers or renters than there exists at present, and that pressure is very heavy at present.</P>
      <P>As will appear when we are discussing later amendments, every removal of restrictions, whether in the Bill as presented, in the amendments moved by Deputy O'Connor or Deputy Thrift or in the compromise the Minister has now offered is going to have the effect of raising the rent of the larger houses and if the tenants of those larger houses cannot afford higher rents, it is going to put those tenants into competition with the poorer people who are applicants for the smaller houses, and you are consequently raising the rents of such houses as may be let under the operations of the present Bill.  To my mind the proposal in the amendments is to worsen still further than the Minister's proposal the position of the tenants whether they are actually tenants of those houses or applicants for smaller houses against whom those tenants who are being displaced will come into competition.  I will oppose the amendments, and I regret the Minister has gone as far as he has gone to meet the case which is being made on behalf of the landlords.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Johnson expressed some doubt as to whether the restrictions on rents have prevented the building of houses.  I thought we all had arrived at this stage, eight years after the War, that we were satisfied that the one result at all events that was obvious from the Rent Restrictions Act was that it prevented us getting houses.  I think there are very few Deputies here who participate in the view expressed by Deputy Johnson.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>Question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>As it has been questioned now, let me explain how the Act stops people from building houses.  Take any road in the city or outside Dublin.  You will find on one side of it what are known as houses which come within the Rent Restrictions Act.  That means that under the Act as enforced the landlord cannot charge more than ten per cent. of the rent as it existed in pre-war days. That is what is known as the standard rent.  On the other side of the road, let <Col N="1674" /> us picture in our minds a large, vacant building site.  Many people are anxious that houses should be built on that site opposite these restricted houses.  The houses built on that side of the road cost from two and a half to three times the money which the restricted houses cost to build.  Consequently, anybody who builds in such circumstances is compelled to charge from two and a half to three times the rent that is allowed to be charged under the Rent Restrictions Act for the houses on the other side of the road.  In such a condition of things it is obvious to anybody that if you can get accommodation on one side for one-third of what it is going to cost you on the other side, the whole tendency will be for people who are compelled to live on the dearer side to watch for a vacant house on the other side and rush into it.  Naturally, one says: &ldquo;Why should I invest my money in a class of property that is going to cost three times that of similar accommodation on the other side of the road?&rdquo;  Who is going to invest under these conditions?  Somebody has said that foolish people erect houses for wise men to live in.  Generally there is some truth in these old proverbs, and that is obvious from the condition of affairs, as we find them to-day.  Deputy Johnson would lead one to think, though he did not say so, that the restriction on the cost of housing was, to some extent, responsible for the high cost of building.  One would infer that from what he said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know why.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>The cost of building to-day is not due in any sense to the Rent Restrictions Act.  The absence of houses is more due to the Rent Restrictions Act than to any other factor, because it shakes that confidence that is essential to the investment of money in house property.  Houses will never be produced until we get into the minds of people that they are a safe and desirable investment.  Does anybody consider, with the Rent Restrictions Act in force, an Act which has shaken and weakened that confidence in houses as an investment, that you are likely to get what a large section of the community wants, namely, houses?  Therefore, <Col N="1675" /> though it may be desirable from the Minister's point of view to continue the restrictions for a further period of three years, you may take it from me that until those restrictions are removed and until we have a clear statement on behalf of the Government that they are removed and that people may look on housing in the future as an investment that will not be interfered with any more than any other investment, you will not get houses except by the means you are adopting at the moment, namely, by largely subsidising those who put money into houses, both from national and local funds.  The Minister, in making his proposal towards meeting the views of those who put forward the amendments, referred to the necessity for control.  I admit that during the War period it was necessary that there should be control.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Why?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>The reason why it was necessary that there should be control was because across the water&mdash;the same conditions did not exist here&mdash; housing was practically stopped because labour, normally engaged in building houses, was commandeered for other national purposes, but as soon as that factor ceased to exist there was no longer necessity for control.  The same point occurred not alone in connection with housing but also in connection with materials, food-stuffs and all other items controlled during that period.  There was necessity for control then, but that necessity no longer exists.  Things that are desirable during a period of crisis may become a serious hindrance later, and I am satisfied that control in the matter of housing has now become a hindrance rather than a help.  Therefore, so far as I am concerned, I am prepared to support any proposal that will get rid of control at the earliest possible moment, and I am in favour of any proposal that will lighten that burden of control during that period.  Control, as has been pointed out, confers a benefit on a privileged few, on those few who happen to be tenants of those controlled houses which derive benefits under the <Col N="1676" /> Act.  But we are rapidly reaching the stage, if we have not already reached it, in which, in order to confer a benefit on a few we are doing an injury to an enormous number, because the number of applicants that we find amongst all classes to-day for houses far outweighs the benefit that a comparatively small number, speaking generally, are deriving from control.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. B. O'CONNOR Mr. B. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Johnson asked had I considered that houses built since 1914 are not controlled, and had I that in view in moving my amendment. I know well that houses built since 1914 are not controlled.  He stated that by removing control of houses of a valuation of £30 and upwards the people living in these houses would have to clear out.  I think it would be pretty good if they did, because it is hardly fair to house-owners that tenants living in those good houses should have them at much less than their value, and if they are asked to pay a rent equal to their value or a fair rent that will give a fair return of interest to the owner, it will be an inducement to those well-off people to build houses themselves, and it will create employment which is much needed in the country.  It will certainly stimulate building.  Take the class of tenant living in houses of a valuation of £40, or even of £30 and upwards.  Take the North Circular Road, a fairly decent, residential street, or St. Lawrence Road, Iona Road, or Iona Drive.  Those are very nice residential streets.  In those places it is surprising what a low percentage of houses are valued at £30.  In the Pembroke area, take Waterloo Road, Marlboro' Road, and Morehampton Road. These are residential streets.  Look up the directory and see the valuation of those houses.  It is surprising the few of them that have a valuation of over £30.  Still, we are told if we raise the rents of those houses we will throw the tenants out in the streets.  I say that people who live in such houses are well able to build houses.  The proposal we have made in regard to the houses that control would be removed from will not touch in any way the class of people that Deputy Johnson <Col N="1677" /> has in mind, that is, the working-class people who live in houses of a valuation of well under £16.  If Deputy Johnson will look up the directory he will learn that what I say is true.  Therefore, if we decontrol houses with a valuation of over £30 we will not in the least be injuring the working-classes and we will be inducing tenants who live in those good houses to build houses for themselves.  This will create employment and there will be houses for all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>I heard a good many cures proposed for unemployment but I think the one just suggested by Deputy O'Connor is a new one. Listening to Deputy O'Connor, and particularly Deputy Good, what appears to be hurting them is the fact that the builders and the landlords for whom they speak are not allowed a free hand to fleece the people who are looking for houses at the moment.  Deputy Good spoke of the great number of applicants for houses at the moment. He emphasised that.  I think what is really at the back of Deputy Good's mind is that here was a very fine market for the landlords who wished to get the highest possible rents for their houses&mdash;the fact that thousands of people in this country are without houses and that they would be allowed to charge any rent that they could get. Let us consider what actually happens when a house becomes vacant.  The house, we will say, was let at £25 a year.  The landlord has perhaps 20 applicants for the house, each applicant doing his or her best to get it and prepared to offer any rent in order to secure it.  We know that what actually happens is that one applicant offers a higher rent than another with the result that in many cases, if we had not the Rent Restrictions Act in force, the landlord would not only be getting the value of his house but he would be getting a rent out of all proportion to the value of the house.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the point made by Deputy O'Connor that workers do not live in houses of this valuation, I think Deputy Johnson showed pretty clearly that if people in houses of a higher valuation have their rents increased to figures that they cannot afford to pay they will look for smaller and cheaper <Col N="1678" /> houses and as the result they will be in competition with the poorer people for these houses.  I know very well that both Deputy O'Connor and Deputy Good are authorities on this matter, and I suppose it is rather dangerous for a novice in the house-building or landlord business to enter into the matter, but it seems to me to be perfectly clear that what Deputy Good and those for whom he speaks want is to get a free market wherein they can command the highest possible rent for the houses they are going to let.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>I share the views of Deputy Johnson in regard to these amendments. To my mind the Bill was introduced at the direction of the landlords in the Saorstát.  In 1923 I was completely against the Rent Restrictions Act.  I wanted the Dáil to allow the people in the Saorstát to form themselves into an organisation&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not discussing the principle of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>I am discussing the amendments.  If those amendments or the amendments by the Minister for Justice are accepted what will we find in the city and in the smaller towns? We will find according to these amendments, that the landlords of houses rented at £25 or £30 will be allowed to charge probably £40, notwithstanding the fact that the tenants in many of these houses cannot afford to pay even the standard rent at the present time. As regards the statement of Deputy Good that the Rent Restrictions Act has prevented building, the President stated on the Second Reading on the Act that from 1914-15 to 1920-21 there were practically no houses built, and that from 1920-21 there were about 10,000 erected.  In the face of that I think it is absolute nonsense to say that the Rent Restrictions Act has prevented building.  From the landlords' point of view it sounds like logic, but from the workers' point of view it is a ridiculous statement to make that the Rent Restrictions Act prevented people investing money in houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to point out that houses erected in 1914 or 1912 and costing, perhaps, £200&mdash;I am speaking of the <Col N="1679" /> country districts&mdash;were let then at a rent of from 2/6 to 3/- per week.  The same class of house will cost, perhaps, £600 to-day, but what is the rent?  Twelve and sixpence per week.  Then we are told the landlords are not profiteering, or that they do not want to profiteer, that they would not be guilty of such a thing as profiteering.  It is a well-known fact that houses erected here in the city of Dublin since 1916 have been let at 250 per cent. above the rent at which houses which were erected in pre-war days were let.  Are the landlords or the builders serious at all, or do they want to get an absolutely free hand, so that all the unorganised citizens of the Saorstát may be victims in their grasp?  To my mind that is what is wanted by the landlord section of the community.  I think if the Dáil agrees to accept the amounts, even suggested by the Minister for Justice, that they will not be acting in accordance with the wishes of the majority of the people of the State, that they will be acting, in fact, quite contrary to the wishes of the majority, but acting in common agreement with the minority, the landlord section.  I certainly will oppose the amendments from No. 1 to No. 5, and if no division is called, I will guarantee to call one.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAlexanderNagle" hpid="Mr. NAGLE Mr. NAGLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NAGLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I was rather surprised to see amendment No. 1 down in Deputy O'Connor's name, and I would be very much obliged if we could get a reason for the change in his views as between now and about three years ago.  About three years ago when the question was asked of Deputy O'Connor as to what he would think would be a reasonable figure for the city of Dublin as the valuation of controlled houses, his answer was £70.  Now he has gone down to almost one-third of that figure.  I am sorry I did not hear the Deputy when he was moving the amendment; perhaps he gave his reason on that occasion.  If he has not done so I would certainly like to hear the reason, because if I got the reason &mdash;and he must have some reason&mdash;perhaps I might be induced to vote for the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no recollection <Col N="1680" /> whatever of making that statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy O'Connor was not in the Dáil three years ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAlexanderNagle" hpid="Mr. NAGLE Mr. NAGLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NAGLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It was made before the Departmental Committee which considered the expiry of the old English Act and before the Government brought in the 1923 Act.  I was a member of that Committee and Deputy O'Connor gave evidence before it.  It was there he made the statement I refer to.  I was rather interested to hear Deputy Good.  Deputy Good, of course, can prove anything he wants to prove to his own satisfaction.  He made a peculiar statement regarding a man who would build houses on one side of the street and who would find that to get a decent return for the money he expended he would need to charge two and a half times the rent that is being charged now under the Rent Restrictions Act for houses on the opposite side of the road.  He went on to suggest that as soon as the houses opposite became vacant all the tenants of the new houses would be rushing for them. Does the Deputy not think that it is asking us to draw on our imaginations or stretch our imaginations a long way to suggest that any of the houses opposite would become vacant?  I certainly think that he might wipe that out as a reason why he could not build houses on the opposite side of the road. I think the argument for the abolition of the Rent Restrictions Act from Deputy Good's point of view is really an argument for people to invest money in houses, because if people were found willing to pay the rents that would be charged after the Act were abolished, then I see no reason why the man who wants to build new houses should not do so.  If the people are willing to pay these rents for houses on which the rent is at present restricted, they should be willing to pay more again for houses built now or in the future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There was one remark which Deputy Good made, though I may not have understood him correctly.  He said that in England, but not in Ireland, there was a reason for the original Rent Restriction Act.  That was that a great deal of labour in England was <Col N="1681" /> commandeered for war purposes, with the consequence that there was a reduction in the number of dwelling houses that were being built.  That certainly did not apply to Ireland. Most of the building tradesmen from Ireland were engaged on war work in England, with the exception of some very few small jobs, one of which Deputy Good himself had control of. I did not see even before the Rent Restrictions Act was introduced here a great deal of activity in house-building in this country.  Certainly there was not much activity in Dublin, and I would like Deputy Good, as he is so anxious to get the support of Deputies for his point of view, to explain to us the difference between the number of houses built in the last four or five years, apart from the houses built under the 1924 and 1925 Acts, with the number of houses that were built in the days prior to the imposition of the rent restrictions.  If he can prove that there is a big difference between the number built during the last four or five years and the number built prior to the imposition of the restrictions, then certainly he might be able to convince a good many that there is a reason for his views on this matter.</P>
    <P>I was speaking to a friend of mine only a fortnight or three weeks ago in regard to this question.  I happened to accompany a visitor to the houses built on Tenter's Field on the South Circular Road.  We happened to pass a number of houses built 20 years ago. We met a man there, and he said that if there was a possibility of one of these houses becoming vacant, even the small houses, the three or four-roomed cottages, the outgoing tenant would get a dozen or more offers of sums of money ranging from £20 to £25 for the key of the house in order to get in there.  I think that is a scandalous state of affairs.  It just shows how much people would be willing to pay to get a house in the present shortage. If people are willing to pay money like that in an illegal manner certainly it shows that they would be willing to pay an economic rent for houses built by private speculative builders, even though the rent did not compare in actual pounds, shillings and pence with <Col N="1682" /> the rent paid for similar houses in the neighbourhood controlled by these Acts.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>resumed the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAlexanderNagle" hpid="Mr. NAGLE Mr. NAGLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NAGLE</NameTxt>
      <P>There was one thing Deputy O'Connor said that surprised me very much; he must have said it without thinking. He said that, in his opinion, it would be a very good thing that some people should be compelled to clear out of the houses they are living in.  I think it would be a very bad thing to compel people to do so; it would be bad not alone for the people who would have to leave the houses, but for the Government that would allow such a state of affairs to exist.  I am in favour of the clause as it stands in the new Bill.  I will not hold Deputy O'Connor down to a £70 valuation.  I think a £52 valuation for Dublin City is a reasonable figure. Most of the houses over £50 valuation are houses owned or rented by people who can afford to pay a decent rent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>In what streets are the houses of £50 valuation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAlexanderNagle" hpid="Mr. NAGLE Mr. NAGLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NAGLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not looked up the Directory lately.  As I might make a mistake I will refrain from mentioning the streets.  In regard to business houses there was a demand on the part of some people for their inclusion under the Rent Restrictions Act. There is a lot to be said for it.  I remember at the wonderful Departmental Committee at which we heard so many injudicious statements made one gentleman gave evidence to the effect that it was desirable that business premises should be included in that Act. He instanced one house in Grafton Street which, prior to 1914, fetched what everybody will agree is a fairly decent rent&mdash;£200 per annum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I am wondering whether the Deputy is in order.  It is scarcely relevant to the amendment to talk on the subject of whether business houses should or should not come under the Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I was wondering whether the Deputy would be in order even on the Second Reading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1683" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAlexanderNagle" hpid="Mr. NAGLE Mr. NAGLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NAGLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not much more to say.  In 1920 that same house was rented for £1,400 per annum.  That is profiteering, if you like.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the tenant still in occupation at that rent?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we taking amendments 2 to 5?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>It was understood we would take the amendments which seek to change the figures in Section 4 together, and I have made a proposal in regard to that, that we would take amendments 2 to 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>If the amendment had reference only to the houses valued at £52 I would not have very much to say, because I realise, with Deputy O'Connor, that there are not very many and the probable effect of releasing these houses from any control would be that some of them&mdash;there are not very many&mdash;would be reconstructed into flats.  That will probably give some work to joiners and carpenters and will relieve certain people who have sufficient money available to pay rents such as flats are commanding.  I am not very much concerned with the few houses that are affected by the first portion of this section; that is to say, the houses of £52 valuation or standard rent.  I am not very much concerned even if that section were extended to houses of a valuation of £40.  The other amendments which we are discussing along with this come down to the houses at present valued at £30, and according to the Minister's new proposal, we would come down to the house with £25 valuation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I realise that a large number of people&mdash;it is impossible to say how many&mdash;in the city and in the urban districts around the city are living in houses of this type and are paying rents which are the utmost they can bear out of their incomes.  If in three years' time you release these houses from restriction you are immediately inviting a very big addition to the rent because of the excessive competition for those houses.  Consequently, you are going to place a burden on a very large number of people in Pembroke, Rathmines, Ranelagh and other districts <Col N="1684" /> as well as in the city of Dublin, a burden which they cannot bear and which is practically a gift to the landlord at the expense of the tenant.  That is more than an economic rent, because it then becomes a rack rent.</P>
    <P>We had some discussion a day or two ago in reference to the necessity for control of other commodities which might be short in the country, in view of emergencies that were then feared. There was unanimity that it might be necessary to control articles of necessity of which there was a shortage in the country.  Why?  Because the owners, without control, would be tempted to seek the highest prices they could get for those necessities.  Therefore, it was proposed even this year to control the price of those necessities. Here you have a necessity&mdash;houses.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not the control of houses producing a shortage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Here you have the necessity of houses.  The demand is very much greater than the supply. Deputy Good can speak with authority on this.  In those circumstances, given no control, prices would rise to the limit of the capacity to pay and people will pay for housing accommodation far beyond their real ability to pay, even though they have to deprive themselves of the normal needs of our civilization.  We know that is a fact, because the people are doing it to-day. They are paying exorbitant rents&mdash; Deputy Good himself has complained of exorbitant rents&mdash;as sub-tenants for meagre accommodation.  But they must have somewhere to sleep in&mdash;some house in which to live.  It is now proposed to cover the £25 valuation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I say that the principle that ought to guide us in this matter is that decontrol should be regulated according to the supply of houses and not the other way round.  I think it is pretty well accepted that if there is a five per cent. shortage of any commodity, the price of 95 per cent. of that commodity will rise.  There may be 10,000 occupiers of houses paying a given rent to-day, but if control is removed, even if there is only another 1,000 people clamouring for houses beyond the number of houses available, the price of everyone <Col N="1685" /> of these houses occupied by the 10,000 tenants will rise.  By these proposals, having no regard whatever to the supply of houses available, you are simply imposing a burden quite incalculable at present, but certainly an additional burden, of many pounds a year upon the whole of the community, at the end of this period of control.  I feel that while for large houses, of which there are quite a few in and around the city of Dublin, it does not matter very much, but when you come to the smaller valuation houses in question there ought to be no departure from the proposals of the Bill, and I hope the Dáil will not agree to any alteration in the proposals originally put forward apart from the £52 valuation, which I do not think matters very much.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know that Deputy Johnson has been altogether happy in the analogy he has drawn between control, in the case of certain commodities, and in the case of houses.  In the case of commodities there were two reasons for control: one was shortage and the other was to prevent profiteering.  Now it is very doubtful that any question of profiteering is likely to arise here.  Certainly it will be a gradual procedure if it comes at all, and I do not see that profiteering by landlords is likely to come.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Why the Bill then?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Johnson really put his finger upon the reason for releasing houses of £52 valuation. I think we ought to be honest about this question of houses.  It is a question that will require all the honesty that we can muster in order to solve it, and I think we had better admit pretty frankly between one another that we cannot afford in the future to be housed as we were in the past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>I can give you a solution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy has got a divine solution for this the sooner he delivers it the better.  Everybody is looking for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>I will give you a solution all right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1686" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy was at a loss, a few moments ago, to know the difference between a house in the country that cost £200 pre-war and that costs £600 now, and that for which only half-a-crown rent was charged in pre-war and for which 12/6 is charged now. If the Deputy went carefully into the figures he could find the reason.  I will tell him the reason.  The house erected for £200 pre-war in the country was erected on borrowed money at £2 1s. 7d. per cent.  The price of money for the same house to-day is over 5 per cent.  The difference between twice £2 1s. 7d. and five times six is very much more than the difference between two and six.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it as great as the difference between 2/6 and 12/6?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I will try to explain it a little further.  Twice £2 1s. 7d. is £4 3s. 2d. and five times six is thirty.  The difference between four and thirty is very much more than the difference between two and six.  I hope that point will in due course penetrate the Deputy's mentality.  Now, with regard to the house of £52 valuation. That class of house in my opinion will not be built in the future. I do not think that anybody can afford to pay for the building of a house the valuation of which in the future will be £52.  Apart from the cost of building, the cost incidental to the upkeep of a house of that sort will be beyond the income of anybody except a plutocrat.</P>
      <P>The next question is, on whom really is the principal burden of rent falling at the present moment?  It falls more heavily upon the small wage-earning people.  Rent to them forms a greater proportion of their outgoings than it does with persons who have incomes.  A man with £500 or £600 a year can afford to pay one-fifth of that in rent without depriving himself of many of the necessaries of life. whereas to the other people one-fifth would be a very considerable proportion of their earnings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In 1919 in the county borough of Dublin it was calculated 22.000 houses would be required to deal with the housing problem.  From the year 1922 up to date something like 2,800 houses have been built under the various <Col N="1687" /> housing facilities provided by the Government during those four years.  That is a pretty considerable contribution, but as far as the balance of the 22,000 people are concerned who are not being provided with houses they are faced with the certainty of having to pay what Deputy Johnson has described as a rack-rent.  What is the reason for that?  The reason is, that the cost of building has increased beyond all contemplation, certainly beyond the cost of anything else to the community, and while Rent Restriction Acts and Bills may be palliatives in connection with the matter they are not an end, but a means to an end, and the means can be abused to a very considerable extent. If there are people living in houses who cannot afford to pay the rents charged, the houses are not going to be destroyed. They are still there for somebody, and the relief from control in certain cases may not mean actually a crisis in connection with housing accommodation. There is a crisis in housing accommodation at the present moment.  There are people paying for portion of a house of a valuation of £25 and under rent far in excess of what would be charged for one of those houses for which subsidies are provided by the Government.  So the regulation of supply and demand has not been even reached at the present moment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>That is my case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>How are we to reach it?  Every possible inducement is given to the local authority and private individuals to provide houses. Now the contribution from private persons in the last four years is very small compared with what has been done by local authorities.  That is one of the faults we have to find in connection with this business&mdash;people looking too much to the State and to the municipality to do the work.  In the county borough of Dublin 450 houses have been built by private persons under the facilities provided under the Building Acts.  That number ought to be greater. Persons ordinarily interested in house property have not come into building in connection with this matter.  I am not going to follow either Deputy</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1688" /> Good or Deputy Johnson as to the reason for that.  The fact of the matter is that they made a big contribution towards the solution of provision of houses before 1914, but so far they have not come into play.</P>
    <P>It has been alleged that these Rent Restrictions Acts have operated to some extent in keeping them out.  Now if it be possible to bring them in very good work will have been done.  There is only one answer to this question of rent restrictions, and that is the provision of more houses.  In looking over a list supplied by the Local Government Department I find that there are extraordinary disparities in various counties as to the number of houses that have been built under that Act, and I do not think it would be possible to follow any particular line of reasoning with regard to it.  It may be that there is a shortage in particular counties, and that it is not so marked in others.  It is rather extraordinary that County Kerry built something like thirty times the number of houses built in other counties.  One county got only two built.  It is possible that the question of supply and demand came in there. The only other matter which, I think, Deputy Johnson or Deputy Nagle raised was, what was the proportion of houses that had been provided during a few years past as compared with a few years pre-war?  I got figures for one particular year, and as far as I could gather the number of houses provided in 1925 was three times the number provided in 1914.  The only other remark I have to make in connection with this matter of rent restriction is, that whether we like it or not, within the next ten or fifteen years, practically every working-class family in Dublin will be faced with having to pay the rent of some new dwelling. The older habitations in which they are at present housed will have passed out of commission.  New accommodation of some sort or other must be provided, and no matter how one controls rents during the years that will elapse between now and that particular time, these people will be faced with having to go into newly-constructed houses, the cost of which will be practically three times what the pre-war cost was, <Col N="1689" /> and no amount of control will lower the rents that they will be called upon to pay.  Some contribution must come from three or four parties to the transaction: the State or the municipality or the builders or the persons engaged in labour on the building.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamEThrift" hpid="Professor THRIFT Professor THRIFT">
      <NameTxt>Professor THRIFT</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to ask how we stand exactly.  Amendment 1 has been moved, but Deputy O'Connor expressed himself as being satisfied with the response of the Minister for Justice to his amendment.  In view of the offer made by the Minister for Justice, I do not propose to move amendments 2, 3, 4, 5 and 8.  We are discussing I think five or eight amendments at the same time.  I would like to know how we stand exactly in the matter of procedure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We seem to be discussing the Bill.  Amendment 1 would not need to be put if the other amendments were being moved. Everything that is in amendment 1 is in the other amendments.  It seems to me that the best amendment to take the discussion on is amendment 6, which seeks to have control for a longer period than is contemplated by the Bill, and then to take the Minister's amendment on Report unless the idea is to propose the Minister's amendment now instead of these amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamEThrift" hpid="Professor THRIFT Professor THRIFT">
      <NameTxt>Professor THRIFT</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister is prepared to put forward his figures on Report Stage, and if Deputy O'Connor agrees to withdraw amendment 1, I will not move amendments 2, 3, 4, 5, or 8.  Amendment 6 would then be the only one left.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Shall we take amendment 6 now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>I am agreeable to that.  I ask for leave to withdraw amendment 1.</P>
      <P>Amendment 1, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I will bring up on Report Stage an amendment embodying my proposals.</P>
      <P>Amendments 2, 3, 4 and 5 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We will now take amendment 6.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I <Col N="1690" /> would like to know how it is that amendments 1 to 5 have been withdrawn without the leave of the House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>They have not been moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister for Justice moving an amendment in place of them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment 1, which was moved, has been withdrawn by the leave of the House. Amendments 2, 3, 4 and 5 have not been moved.  The Minister for Justice has given notice that, on Report, he will move certain amendments.  That is the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 6:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 3, line 11, to delete the figures &ldquo;1929&rdquo; and substitute the figures and words &ldquo;1933 or such earlier date as may be determined as hereinafter provided.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The proposal in my amendment will not touch the figures that are in the Bill down to houses of a value of £30 in the Dublin metropolitan area, but in respect of all houses under £30 valuation&mdash;that is to say, the great majority of houses which are occupied by people who earn their living as wage-earners or salary-earners&mdash;there would be no removal of the restrictions until the year 1933 unless the Minister were satisfied, and as will appear by a later amendment, the House were prepared to approve of an earlier date for the removal of these restrictions.  The idea is that at least we shall have one other Parliament completed before any removal of these restrictions is decided upon in respect to the great majority of houses in the country.  The factor which would determine whether it was wise to remove the restrictions would be the existence of house accommodation to meet the demand.  The President made a contribution to the discussion which goes far to prove the case that I am asking the House to agree with.  He showed us that in the city of Dublin, in 1919, there was estimated to be 22,000 houses required to meet the existing demand.  There is no sign of a decline in the population of Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1691" /> There has been no movement away from the city.  Perhaps by 1933 with the operations of the Shannon electrical supply we may have a springing up of industrial activities in other parts of the country, drawing off from this congested city a proportion of the population. But so far there has been no sign of a decline of population&mdash;rather the other way.  If in 1919 22,000 houses were required that will give an indication of the pressure of the demand for houses.</P>
    <P>The Minister also told us that since 1922 up-to-date, which in effect means from 1919 up-to-date, for practically speaking no houses were built from 1919 to 1922&mdash;2,800 houses have been built in the city.  At that rate of contribution, apart from any question of any increase in the demand for houses in the city, it is going to take 21 years to overcome the demand by the supply.  The President also informs us that in the period of 15 years from now there will be a falling in of the present habitations, increasing the need for houses enormously, so after 1929, which this Bill refers to, there is to be no control of houses or of rents, but there is to be free trade in houses, the supply being very much in excess of the demand.  The consequent conclusion to that operation would be that every house in the city, once decontrol comes, will rise in rent, and be dependent upon the ability to pay, and the extent of the demand will be the amount of that rise.  I have given the date as 1933, because it will at least give time for the next Parliament, and the one after that, to consider the situation afresh in the light of the circumstances then prevailing.  As it is desirable to give a date I gave the date 1933, with the proviso that if, in the meantime, there is any sign that the demand does not exceed the supply, and that there is something really economic in the matter, not a rack-rent, not a squeezing of the people to the utmost by the operations of this law of supply and demand that is so often invoked, there might be some justice done to the people who rent houses.</P>
    <P>I cannot understand, notwithstanding <Col N="1692" /> Deputy Good's attempt at explanation, how the operation of rent restriction has prevented house-builders from building when that restriction does not apply to houses at present being built, or to any houses built for the last few years.  The extension of the period during which this Rent Restrictions Act will apply will not prevent the building of a single house, but whether that is so or not, I maintain that unless we are prepared to say to the average workman or workwoman in the city, or the county, or the country towns: &ldquo;We are prepared to raise your wages by the extent of the rise in rents,&rdquo; we ought not to place on these people the necessity of having to pay higher rates for their house accommodation.  The President said there was no analogy between the control of commodities under the Emergency Powers Bill, and this question of the control of houses and rents.  As far as I can understand the situation it is an absolutely perfect analogy, and I entirely dissent from the President's statement that there was not and could not be any profiteering in houses.  This Bill proposes to invite every house owner after 1929 to enter into competition for profit.  It is an invitation to profiteering after 1929, as I say, without regard to the supply of houses.  Whatever case may be made for controlling the price of bread in the time of shortage, for controlling the price of milk in the time of shortage, or for controlling the price of any necessity in time of shortage, that case applies to the control of houses in time of shortage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment 6 is before the Committee. Amendment 12 arises.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I am inclined to agree with Deputy Johnson that whatever case arises for the control of a necessary of life in time of shortage such a case arises and exists for control of houses in time of shortage, but it is a question of the acuteness of the shortage. I at least would take the view that only a very acute shortage, creating a situation fraught with the gravest social reactions, would justify the interference of control&mdash;something that is. after all, like other commodities simply <Col N="1693" /> the product of labour and capital. We have said, and despite the expressions of views to the contrary I think rightly and wisely said, that for the last period of four or five years houses should not be allowed to fetch that price in the market which the free play of factors of supply and demand would make for.  Now that we have made at least some inroad on the housing shortage, we are beginning to face towards decontrol.  Taking a period of three years, we are beginning to come down the scale of valuation, and to fix periods at the close of which a certain number of houses come out from under the pressure of our legislation.  Deputy Johnson says our period is not long enough. He wants an extension of it to 1933. I think the three years' period is as long as this Dáil should attempt to look ahead.  After all, we passed an Act in 1923 which will expire on 24th of next month.  We did not attempt to pierce further into futurity than that.  In 1923 we were prepared to leave it to the Government and Oireachtas of 1926 to say whether or not any continuation of control legislation was necessary.  I ask the Dáil to take the view that it is not wise now in 1926 to look ahead any further&mdash;that is in a practical way &mdash;with our legislation than 1929.  We may well leave it to the Government and Oireachtas of 1929 to deal with the situation as it is then found to be.  Many things may happen between this and 1929.  There may be changes in the sphere of housing.  There may be, for instance, a change of heart in trade unions.  It may be realised that lower prices and lower rates and increased output would be found to be the true economy even from their own point of view.  We may have the steel house, which is so much discussed elsewhere, and discoveries of one kind or another may take place which will revolutionise the position with regard to houses.  But from whatever source relief comes for the housing problem, if relief does, in fact, come, we are dealing with the position that we see and that we know. We are finding time to legislate on that position.  It is not too much to ask that the Government and Dáil of 1929 will find time to deal with the situation as it is then found to be.  It will be for <Col N="1694" /> them to decide whether they will simply allow this legislation, which we are now considering, to expire, resulting in total decontrol of housing, or whether they will consider it necessary to continue to any extent legislation restrictive of rent or houses.  We cannot forecast the 1929 position, and I think we are doing just about all that we can wisely do in legislating for a period of three years.  To attempt to go further, as Deputy Johnson asks us in this amendment, and in amendment 12, to legislate as far as 1933 or, at any rate, to make an Act of the kind that can be extended to 1933, if necessary, is really unduly pessimistic.  I wish to be taken as asking the Dáil, further, not to accept these amendments, and to rest satisfied with the proposal embodied in the Bill that it shall have effect until 1929, and that it shall then expire, leaving the situation to be met and dealt with by the legislature of that date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that the position has been put fairly well before the Dáil by the Minister.  In this Bill to ask a further extension of time to 1933 would not, in my opinion, be in the interests of the situation that is disclosed by Deputy Johnson's demand, that a large number of extra houses are still to be erected to meet the needs of the people.  The figure of 22,000 was given as the number of houses required.  One must imagine, at all events, that that is a very exaggerated figure.  But the very fact of the growth of these new houses is accentuating the different treatment meted out to householders as between two sets of buildings, the new houses and the old houses.  That very difference with the greater growth and the larger number of houses erected is going to be exaggerated in the direct ratio of the building of new houses. Because you have all over the place your working men living side by side, one man paying, say, 15/- for a new house, and the other man paying, say, 4/6 for a house practically as good, and possibly a great deal better, because a good many people think that the older houses are better constructed than the new houses.  Even from the workers' point of view, continuance of that situation is going to create difficulties <Col N="1695" /> even amongst the working men themselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I put it forward as the main argument for the discontinuance of this Bill at the earliest possible moment that this course would be in the interest of house-building and would tend to increase the number of houses to be erected.  Thereby, it would get over whatever reason there was for the restriction of the rents of the older houses.  It cannot be overlooked that the Rent Restrictions Act has brought about a state of affairs in which only a very small fraction of the houses being built are being built for the purpose of letting.  One finds on looking around that the houses being built with the aid of subsidies supplied by the rest of the community are being built with the deliberate intention of sale as soon as erected.  Under no circumstances would those houses be put up for renting.  That is the class of growth that is being fostered by this subsidy for houses.  Under former conditions, blocks of houses were put up at a certain cost which were estimated to yield a certain rent.  The people responsible for the building were willing to invest in these houses as an ordinary investment, for which they expected a return.  That class of business has disappeared and will not return until the industry is free from restrictions.  The inclination of people with money to invest has turned from house property, for the time being.  The best contribution we could make towards house supply and the resumption of old conditions as regards house-building would be to give everybody to understand that house property is not going to be the plaything of Ministers and that the position under which a person who owns a house has no control over it and no control over the rent he is going to receive will not continue.  The sooner that condition disappears the better for the industry. More houses will be provided when the people recognise the determination of the Government to terminate the present state of affairs within a reasonable time.  If Deputy Johnson's amendment to extend the operations of this Bill to 1933 were accepted, it would do more damage as far as house supply is <Col N="1696" /> concerned than could be calculated. Even if the report got about that it was the intention now, or was likely to be the intention, to extend at the end of the period in 1929 the restrictions in this Bill, it would have a deterring effect on anybody about to invest money in house building.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>In my view and in the view of many other people there will be a necessity for extending this period after 1929, and all the evidences are that this Bill, or some copy of it, will be before the Dáil in the year 1929.  There should be no mistake about that and people should not be deceived by thinking that this is to be the final Bill dealing with the restriction of rent.  It is just as well there should be no misunderstanding on that point.  It is not only members of the Labour Party who have the conviction that there shall be a Rent Restrictions Act after 1929.  Eminent members of the Conservative Government in England have stated in respect to England &mdash;it can be repeated in respect to Ireland with emphasis&mdash;that house-building for working people is never again going to be an economic proposition. Unless there is a revolution in the minds of the employers generally as to the rates of wages they are prepared to pay, there is no likelihood, while the price of money remains anything like what it is at present, that houses will be built for letting to wage earning people as an economic proposition. Deputy Hewat instances the case of one man paying 15/- per week for a new house and his neighbour paying perhaps 4/6 for a similar house.  That is the position.  The difference may be even greater.  But there are 30,000 householders on one side and there are 3,000 on the other side.  I wonder would Deputy Hewat, Deputy Good and Deputy O'Connor, who desire these restrictions to be removed, think that the 30,000 people should have their rents raised to the 15/- because the 3,000 are paying 15/-?  I can understand the logic of the case if they say &ldquo;yes.&rdquo;  That is going to be the effect of this Bill as soon as the restrictions cease.  I want these Deputies to tell us whether it is their desire that the restrictions shall cease so that the <Col N="1697" /> owners of the existing houses shall be able to charge the rates current for new houses.</P>
      <P>The Minister in his opposition to the amendment asked us to consider the possibility of a revolution in the position with regard to houses&mdash;new methods, the possible extension of the steel house to this country, produced no doubt at a much cheaper rate than it is being produced and being much more satisfactory than it promises to be.  He says that I am unduly pessimistic when I state that this revolution may not take place before 1933.  Supposing the revolution took place before 1929&mdash;suppose the supply of steel houses was available in 1928&mdash;the Minister's proposition would not allow any freedom for charging rents until 1929.  My proposition quite clearly states that if the revolution takes place at any time between now and 1933&mdash;if this supply of steel houses is available even at an earlier date than 1929&mdash;the restrictive period may come to an end.  The Minister seems to be, not unduly pessimistic but unduly optimistic, if he thinks that the whole situation regarding the supply of houses is going to be remedied before 1929.  If you go to the people with a Bill of this kind, intimating to householders and prospective tenants that their period of restriction will cease in 1929 rather than intimating to them that there is no likelihood of its ceasing in 1929, then you are placing those people in a false position.</P>
      <P>Unless we have some reason for believing that the supply of houses will be available by 1929, we ought not to suggest to house-owners that they will be free at that time to draw any rent they can out of their tenants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>There will not be many houses left by that time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>That makes the position even worse.  I suggest to Deputy Hewat that it would be a very important matter for him, in view of what the President has said, and what he has now suggested, that he should consult with his colleagues of the Chamber of Commerce, and consider whether it would not be better generally <Col N="1698" /> to increase the ability to pay, and then you might have some reason for releasing house-owners from these restrictions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>Does Deputy Johnson imagine that if wages were increased to-morrow there would be any more inclination amongst working men to pay increased rents?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That question is irrelevant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder would my reply be irrelevant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid it would.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, it is relevant to say that there is a very practical relationship between the ability to pay and the rents to be charged, and if at the end of 1929 you are going to add a charge upon the wage-earner in general by an inevitable increase of rent, then you are laying up for yourself trouble, and I think it is inadvisable to prepare for it so long in advance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Johnson asks if it is the intention that rents should be increased on houses that it is proposed to now decontrol to the level of houses built since 1920, and I say it is not.  If that were the case the rent should be increased three times, or at least two and a half times, because it now costs between two and a half and three times more to build a house than in pre-war days.  It is not our intention that the rent should be increased two and a half times.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>How would you prevent it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>It is our intention that people who own house property should get a fair profit for the money invested in the property.  I would say that a fair profit would be five per cent. on the value of the house, or that the rent charged would be equal to a dividend of five per cent. on the present value of such property.  I say that would be a reasonable rent.  I think that meets his point.  Control and interference with house property is detrimental to the building of houses.  Not very many years ago people invested <Col N="1699" /> money in house property because it was looked upon as a very safe investment. I knew a man who had money invested in other business, but he watched the stock and the money markets so closely that his health broke down.  He suffered from insomnia.  His doctor advised him to give up that business and to put his money into house property. He did so, and invested £40,000.  I built a good deal of property for him.  Perhaps he is suffering from insomnia to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>He is dead.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>The point I want to make is that with the rent restrictions there is no inducement to people to build houses to-day.  The sooner we allow free play in this matter and make the building of houses an attractive investment, the better it will be for the tenants and for those looking for houses.  As I said, it is not our intention that the rents of old houses should be increased to those of new houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy O'Connor mentioned five per cent.  Does he mean to restrict the house-owners to five per cent.?  If so, how does he propose to do it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1700" />
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>The point I was making was that if a house becomes vacant, and if it is sold, the money on investment would realise five per cent., or a much higher profit than the rent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Deputy propose to control the landlords to the extent that they should only receive five per cent.?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>I say that house-owners should be allowed at least a profit of five per cent. on the value of the house.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Deputy want to limit them to five per cent.?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>When we are going into other questions as to what other controls ought to be put in force, we are getting into some difficulties that Deputy Johnson does not see.  So far we have only discussed control from one point of view.  There are other sides to it on which very much might be said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>Will Deputy Good answer the question about the five per cent.?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>If we have one question we may have another</P>
      <P>Amendment put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Committee divided:&mdash;Tá, 9; Níl, 49.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Seán Buitléir.<br />David Hall.<br />Tomás Mac Eoin.<br />Tomás de Nógla.<br />Tomás O Conaill.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Aodh O Cúlacháin.<br />Seán O Laidhin.<br />Domhnall O Muirgheasa.<br />Tadhg O Murchadha.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl.</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Earnán Altún.<br />Pádraig Baxter.<br />Earnán de Blaghd.<br />Séamus Breathnach.<br />Seoirse de Bhulbh.<br />Próinsias Bulfin.<br />Séamus de Búrca.<br />John Conlan.<br />Bryan R. Cooper.<br />Máighréad Ní Choileáin Bean<br />Uí Dhrisceóil.<br />James Dwyer.<br />Desmond Fitzgerald.<br />John Good.<br />Thomas Hennessy.<br />John Hennigan.<br />William Hewat.<br />Liam Mac Cosgair.<br />Séamus Mac Cosgair.
<Col N="1701" />Mícheál O hIfearnáin.<br />Aindriú O Láimhín.<br />Séamus O Leadáin.<br />Fionán O Loingsigh.<br />Séamus O Murchadha.<br />Pádraig O hOgáin (Gaillimh).</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Séan Mac Curtain.<br />Maolmhuire Mac Eochadha.<br />Pádraig Mac Fadáin.<br />Patrick McGilligan.<br />Risteárd Mac Liam.<br />Seoirse Mac Niocaill.<br />Liam Mac Sioghaird.<br />Pádraig Mag Ualghairg.<br />Martin M. Nally.<br />John T. Nolan.<br />Peadar O hAodha.<br />Mícheál O hAonghusa.<br />Seán O Bruadair.<br />Parthalán O Conchubhair.<br />Máirtín O Conalláin.<br />Eoghan O Dochartaigh.<br />Séamus O Dóláin.<br />Pádraig O Dubhthaigh.<br />Eamon O Dúgáin.
<Col N="1702" />Pádraig O hOgáin (Luimneach).<br />Máirtín O Rodaigh.<br />Séan O Súilleabháin.<br />Mícheál O Tighearnaigh.<br />Caoimhghín O hUigín.<br />Liam Thrift.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers:&mdash;Tá, Deputies Morrissey and Nagle.  Níl: Deputies Sears and B. O'Connor.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That disposes also of Amendment 12.  Amendments 7, 8 and 9 are not moved. Amendments 10 and 11 appear to be directed to the same object, and I think 11 is the better amendment.  I would like to hear Amendment 11 first.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>I move&mdash;</P>
      <P>To add at the end of the section the words&mdash;&ldquo;Provided always that where a dwellinghouse to which the Act applies becomes vacant by reason of the surrender or other determination of the tenancy, the Act of 1920, the Principal Act and this Act shall cease to apply to such dwellinghouse as and from the date of such surrender or other determination of the said tenancy.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The object of this amendment is to decontrol a house when it becomes vacant.  I think it would be wise and advisable, in the interests of those looking for houses to rent. if the owners of such houses were allowed to let them at reasonable or fair rents, rents that would bring them the equivalent of five per cent. on the money that they would get for the sale of the houses.  I think that that would be wise, and I am sure that the House will agree with the amendment.  If we are heading for decontrol&mdash;and that is the object of the Bill&mdash;I think this would be a good way to aim at it, and it would then come gradually.  There would be very few houses vacant from time to time, and this would be a good way to meet decontrol and to prepare for its arrival.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>I oppose this amendment.  It seems to me that Deputy O'Connor in this matter is only thinking of the city of Dublin and perhaps some of the townships, but if this amendment were to be passed it would impose a great hardship on people in small country towns, because small houses, particularly the class of house in which poor people live, are not usually sold when they become vacant; another weekly or monthly tenant, as the case may be, is put in, and if this amendment is passed, with the present demand for houses, it will mean that in many cases rent will be increased a hundred or perhaps two hundred per cent.  People are so anxious to get houses, and are so much in need of them, that they would be prepared to pay such rents and would outbid each other in order to do so.  Therefore, I submit if this amendment is passed it will impose a great hardship on the poorer tenants in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment has been urged on me and amongst other arguments used in support of it is the one that a provision, identical with or similar to this, is contained in the British legislation.  I take it that Deputies would not consider that an all-sufficient argument, and that they would not wish to ask themselves, quite apart from that, whether it is a proper provision or not.  My objection to the amendment is that it runs counter to what we may call the philosophic basis of such legislation as exists.  It runs counter to the principle underlying the 1920 Act and our own Act of 1923, because what we aimed at in that legislation was not so much the protection of existing tenants as the control of houses.  We did not advert merely to the position of the tenant in occupation at any given point of time.  We were considering all tenants, prospective as well as existing tenants, and the basis of the legislation was this: owing to the war and causes incidental to the war, there had been a complete cessation of building activity for a period of from five to eight years.  There was here, at any rate, quite apart from that, an almost chronic shortage of houses.  That shortage was, of course, <Col N="1703" /> accentuated by the cessation of building activities, and if houses were left to their natural market price, the price they could fetch if no such restrictive legislation as this were introduced, they would rise beyond the reach of the pockets of the people, and we said, with regard to houses built prior to April, 1919, built back in the cheap period before building costs rose to or beyond their present level, there would be a restriction and a limitation on the amount of rent that could be charged. That was the basis of our legislation. It may be challenged, and it may be said it was unwise to interfere at all.  I do not agree with that.  It was not protection of individual existing tenants, but restriction and limitation which could be charged to any tenant, existing or prospective, that was aimed at.  Is it consistent with that view, apart from the question whether control is right or wrong, wise or unwise, to say, as we are asked to say, by this amendment, that let a house once fall vacant, it shall come out from the pressure of control and soar at its letting price to whatever level may be determined by the factors of supply and demand? I do not think it is, and to accept this amendment would be mixing our principles, a bad thing to do in legislation.  A particular philosophic basis, I may revert to the word, exists for the 1920 and 1923 Act, and we propose to continue that kind of legislation, not identical legislation, for a further period of three years.  Are we to say that if by accidental circumstances a house falls vacant it shall be released from control, and shall rise from its letting price to whatever may be determined by the free play of the factors of supply and demand?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is this aspect to which I should like to draw the attention of Deputies. A provision of this kind would create a serious temptation to a householder, to harass his tenants, so that he could secure vacant occupation of his house because thereby his house, by the fact of falling vacant, would be released from control.  When I put that point to a deputation of people interested in this matter, I was met with a retort a pertinent reply, that there was always an inducement, since rent restriction <Col N="1704" /> came, for a landlord to struggle hard for vacant possession of his house, so that he might sell, because selling, and I am quite satisfied that this is so, in a great many cases, he could realise an amount which, if invested, would bring him in a larger sum than what he is allowed to charge by way of rent without any of the worry and anxiety which the possession of house property, I am told, involves. He could put it into National Loan or any other investment to bring him in five or five and a half per cent. and, without any trouble, secure an income from that greater than he could charge by way of rent.  I am satisfied that is so.</P>
    <P>There is just this.  The number of people who could buy their houses is limited in contrast to the number of people who, we may assume, are anxious to rent houses, and it is a question of difficulty.  If the temptation were there since rent restriction came along, for a landlord to struggle by a variety of methods, to secure vacant possession of his house, he cannot deny that, to accept this amendment, would increase this temptation because if he could secure vacant possession, his house is free not merely from the competition of those who can buy houses but also free from the unrestricted competition of the very much greater number who are anxious to rent houses.  It flies out from under our control pressure and rises to whatever level the competition of prospective tenants can bring it to.  For those two reasons, for the reason that I thin it conflicts with our principle of legislation, and for the reason that it constitutes a very serious temptation to a landlord to secure possession by any means in his power, or, as was said long ago, in a particular connection, by the most effective means, I hesitate to accept this amendment and I ask the Dáil to take my view on the matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamEThrift" hpid="Professor THRIFT Professor THRIFT">
      <NameTxt>Professor THRIFT</NameTxt>
      <P>I had an amendment down in somewhat different words, but preserving the same principle. I have no love for my own particular words, but I think the principle in this is quite against the Minister.  I do not feel at all as if he had justified his objection to this amendment.  He <Col N="1705" /> says that the amendment is based against the idea of control in the Act. In what way is that so?  The control under the Act is in the hands of the tenants, and we know that the way in which it works out is that really the tenant and not the owner controls the property.  If the house becomes vacant that principle of course lapses.  There is no hardship on any individual, but there is a definite hardship removed from the owner of that particular property. It works out in this way, namely, that the owner will become more anxious to let a house to a tenant than to sell it.  If this amendment is not passed you will have a continuance of what occurs to-day, namely, that a house is not offered for letting but is sold, and in many cases the selling of that kind of property leads to the loosening of the bond between the owner and the property, and it frequently leads to money going out of the country.  We want to encourage the letting of houses, and the refusal to accept the amendment means a definite refusal to utilise in a certain small number of cases that opening that would arise by the offering of property to rent.  That is what we want to encourage. One of my objects is that we should, as far as possible, put an end to this persistent selling of houses. Whenever an occasion arises the owner will offer a house for sale, instead of offering it for rent.  That tells against would-be tenants, as unless they put up the money they cannot get a house. Though they could pay a reasonable rent per annum they do not get a chance of renting a house.  What we want to aim at, I take it, is to get more and more houses offered for rent, and this amendment is a simple way in which that could be secured in a small number of cases without doing hardship to anybody.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrThomasHennessy" hpid="Dr. HENNESSY Dr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>I think there is a good deal to be said for the principle of the amendments put down in the names of Deputy B. O'Connor and Deputy Thrift.  As Deputy Thrift has just said, the great grievance of would-be tenants is that they cannot get a house to rent, and that the landlord, from one reason or another, either from <Col N="1706" /> fear of the Rent Restrictions Act, or from the offer of a better investment, is disposed to sell.  Another point is this, namely, that when a house becomes vacant there is often a question of internal repairs.  The house has to be kept in repair by the tenant, but we all know that in practice he generally leaves the house in bad repair, and it is not practicable to make him responsible for the repairs.  The owner of a house very often has to spend on internal decorations and repairs as much as £150, and if he is subject to the Rent Restrictions Act, I do not think that that is a paying proposition for him.  He will adopt the better paying alternative, and sell the house. Nearly all of the newly-built houses, which have been erected by State money, have been sold by the builders, but the purchasers are not at all pleased with their bargain because they have had to borrow money at 7 or 8 per cent., and have had to pay a higher rent than they would have to do if the houses were decontrolled.  I would ask the Minister to give the amendment favourable consideration, as it is as much in the interests of those who want houses as of the owners of house property.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>We learn as we go along.  We learn from Deputy Doctor Hennessy that owing to the great need of houses people are induced to buy houses at a price far more than they are worth when put in the market for sale.  We know that people who buy houses, even under present favourable conditions, pay more for them than they can afford.  I think that the discussion of this amendment has to be related, not merely to the situation in the city and county of Dublin, or rather, in the adjacent boroughs of the city of Dublin, but in the country as a whole, and to the conditions of the tenements in Dublin.  If we were only considering the townships I think I could be brought to support this amendment, but I realise that many people are inhabiting dwelling houses, as defined by the Act with which we are dealing, that include part of a house which is let as a separate dwelling.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1707" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Deputy tell us under what conceivable circumstances this could apply to a tenement house?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>If the front and back rooms on the third floor in a particular house in the city of Dublin are vacant, they constitute a separate dwelling and the landlord is then free to get any rent he can.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>It would not be a vacant house within the meaning of this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy would listen to what I am saying and read the Act which we are dealing with he would learn that the Act applies to any part of a house let as a separate dwelling as well as a house, so that all the tenements in the city of Dublin, when they become vacant, would be free and the owners of those tenements could get whatever rent they could squeeze out of the incoming tenant.  So it is with small houses in small towns in the country.  We do not hear in those places of the practice that takes place in Dublin and in the townships about Dublin where, as soon as a house becomes vacant, it is sold at an exorbitant price.  The small houses in the country are not sold in that way.  They are re-let and there is no possibility or probability of their being sold.  If this amendment is carried the owners of small houses now let in the country districts at 3/-, 4/- and 5/- a week, when they become vacant, will be able to extract any rent they wish.  The houses will not be put into the market for sale.  They are not even now under the Rent Restrictions Act put into the market for sale.  They are re-let at a standard rent plus such additions as are allowed.  I think if the amendment were carried it would do harm to every tenant of every tenement which becomes vacated, and every tenant of every small house in the country towns.  The movers of the amendment seem to have in mind only places, like Ranelagh, Rathmines, Terenure, parts of Dublin City, and Pembroke, in which houses are usually sold when they become vacant.  If the Deputies could concoct <Col N="1708" /> a formula which would only bring in the class of houses which, apparently, they have in mind, then a good deal could be said for the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamEThrift" hpid="Professor THRIFT Professor THRIFT">
      <NameTxt>Professor THRIFT</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to point out to the Deputy that amendment 10 definitely puts in a proviso at the end of the clause, &ldquo;Provided that any house becoming vacant.&rdquo; The amendment actually under consideration is more specific.  It refers to dwelling houses to which this Act applies.  I think there is a real point of difference between the two amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Right through the Act that we are dealing with a part of a house which is let as a separate dwelling is a house for the purpose of the Act.  That is my interpretation, and all the interpretations that have been recorded are in favour of my interpretation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamEThrift" hpid="Professor THRIFT Professor THRIFT">
      <NameTxt>Professor THRIFT</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to persist, but would the Deputy just put together the beginning of the section and then the proviso: &ldquo;Subject to the provisions of this section this Act shall, in respect of any particular house, or part of a house let as a separate dwelling&rdquo;&mdash;then certain things come in.  Then you have at the end: &ldquo;Provided always that any house becoming vacant.&rdquo;  If he does I think his interpretation will be the same as my own.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I will leave that to the lawyers.  Apart from the question of tenements, there is the question which I will touch upon and which Deputy Morrissey has touched upon, that it is not the practice in much the greater part of the country&mdash;nor has it been the practice during the last three years&mdash;for small houses on becoming vacant to be put into the market for sale.  That might be the practice in the townships near Dublin and in Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>Or in Cork?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>It might be the practice in Cork, but over the greater part of the country it is not the fact and this legislation deals with the whole country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1709" />
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I can only say, as far as my somewhat limited knowledge goes, that I disagree entirely with Deputy Johnson, so far as, at any rate, County Sligo is concerned.  In the first place, I disagree that houses becoming vacant are not put up for sale.  Whenever a landlord has an opportunity of selling a house, either to the tenant or when it becomes vacant, he generally takes that opportunity.  In the second place, Deputy Johnson thinks that houses let at 4/- or 5/- a week, on becoming vacant, are let at very much higher rents.  I can only say in my own experience I find it hard enough to get four or five shillings a week.  I find it quite impossible to get a tenant who would pay 10/- or 15/- a week.  I have one case in mind that I was dealing with this morning.  It is the case of a house that is used as a hotel of which I am landlord.  The rent is 6/- a week. That rent has not been paid for eight years, though when I stayed in the hotel&mdash;it is a six-roomed house&mdash;they charged me 7/6 a night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Deputy propose to reduce the rent or to raise it&mdash;that rent which he does not receive?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I am proposing to sell, which Deputy Johnson says is never done, and to have the arrears taken into consideration in the purchase price, if I can get a reasonable price.  I know nothing about what happens in Minister, but I do not think Deputy Johnson's statement, so far as the conditions in Sligo are concerned, is an accurate one, and I support the amendment of Deputy O'Connor, both because it meets a very urgent need in our common constituency and in Deputy Johnson's constituency, and also because I believe it will be useful to the rest of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Deputy say how poor tenants who are paying anything from 2/6 to 5/- a week can buy their houses if they were put up for sale.  I mean men earning from 32/- to £2 a week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>In the case that I referred to the tenant is also a teacher <Col N="1710" /> of Irish in the technical school and he is obtaining a substantial income in addition to the money he gets from visitors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>Take the case of a man working on the roads.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>His rent is generally 1s. 3d. a week in my case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to oppose this amendment.  I think Deputy Thrift and Deputy O'Connor had in mind some very large houses, probably in the city, which, when they become vacant, are put up for sale.  Like some of the Labour Deputies, I have had some experience of small dwellings in the country occupied by workers where the rents have been increased on the incoming tenants on their becoming vacant. Those houses are never put up for sale, because the people who live in these houses have not the money to purchase them.  I agree with the mover of the amendment that the Act might apply to houses of a certain valuation, say of £35 or £40, but as regards the workers I think the amendments put forward by Deputy O'Connor and Deputy Thrift are purely in the interests of the landlords. To my mind this Bill was hatched&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not discussing the Bill as a whole now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>Those two amendments have been hatched, not in an incubator, but, probably, by the real old clucking hen of the landlords' party, who is out all the time to get the very best clutch of eggs that he possibly can.  On this occasion the only eggs he is going to get, the best profits, are in taking restrictions off the houses as they become vacant, and letting the incoming tenant be the game bird, he wants to hatch, by way of charging a far greater rent or trying to sell the houses at an exorbitant price. I have been a member of the Dáil since 1922, and I have to say that I have never appreciated so much before the action of the Minister for Justice as I have on this amendment.  Let us sincerely hope that he will continue his good work by saying he will not accept this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1711" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to throw out a suggestion to which probably we might get the Labour representatives to agree. A fact that experience has shown is that during the operations of the Rent Restrictions Act houses, in the city at all events, are for a long period kept vacant during the period in which the owner tries to find a buyer.  That state of affairs operates against these people who want houses, and I contend that the acceptance of this amendment would leave a greater number of houses at the disposal of people who wish to rent houses.  In order to meet Deputy Johnson's objections, I would suggest that we should say &ldquo;provided always that in the county boroughs of Dublin or Cork that any house become vacant.&rdquo; That takes away the small houses in the rural areas, and that is the real cause of objection the Labour Party have to the amendments.  I contend that you are doing wrong to allow these houses to remain empty from the point of view of the interests of the tenants, in whom the Labour Party are very much interested.  It is wrong to have houses vacant when nobody can rent them.  Their owners are waiting for buyers, and they often remain vacant for six or eight months or even for a year.  This amendment would leave them at the disposal of new tenants, and it will take away the objections which exist in the cases of small houses in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="FIONAN O LOINGSIGH FIONAN O LOINGSIGH">
      <NameTxt>FIONAN O LOINGSIGH</NameTxt>
      <P>Nílim ar thaobh an leas-rún so, acht ba mhaith liom mo thuairm a thabhairt&mdash;tar éis bheith ag éisteacht leis na Teachtaí do lobhairt&mdash;gur féidir crot níos fearr a chur ar an leas-rún gan mórán troblóide.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I suggest that the Minister for Justice might see his way to look into the amendment in the light of what has been said from the different parts of the House, before the Report Stage of the Bill.  I think that it is rather clear that the amendment could, by a considerable amount of amendment in itself be made such as would satisfy all Deputies, or nearly all.  I do not agree with the amendment as it stands.  I believe in the points put up by Deputy Morrissey and Deputy Johnson, that houses in the rural areas and in the <Col N="1712" /> small towns would be affected by this amendment.  I say the amendment could be very deleterious from that point of view, but I am perfectly convinced that as far as the townships of Dublin are concerned, the effect of the Rent Restrictions Act is that it is absolutely impossible for a person who is prepared to pay £70 or £80 a year to get a house.  When the house becomes vacant the houseowner can get a fancy price, and he will not let on the conditions imposed by the Rent Restrictions Act.  I have had experience of it myself, and I am satisfied about that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidHall" hpid="Mr. HALL Mr. HALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HALL</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not at all satisfied with any argument that has been put up here to the effect that when a house becomes vacant in an urban area or in the city the owner is all the time out to dispose of that house.  I know a particular case that has come under my own notice in the course of the past eighteen months&mdash;a case of twelve houses in the town of Trim, and the rent paid for them is only 2/- a week. The houses contain from three to five rooms, and there is a garden of half a statute acre at the rear.  The tenants were anxious to extend the houses. To get authority to extend them it was necessary for them to purchase the houses.  I was approached on the matter, and I accompanied them to the landlord with a view to making an arrangement with him for the sale of the houses to the tenants.  He would not hear of it under any conditions. I went a second time and discussed the matter with him, and he agreed to give it consideration.  The local parish priest was apprised of the matter.  The landlord declined.  He did not make any move at all to dispose of the houses.  Four of these houses became vacant in the course of the last eight months.  He did not sell them, but he let them again at 2/- a week.  He did not ask to increase the rent.  Now there is talk about disposing of houses in the city of Dublin and the townships. Take a house in Botanic Avenue which is let at £1 per week.  These are only four-roomed houses.  They are let at £1 per week, and assuming that one of them becomes vacant to-morrow, and the control is taken off those houses, <Col N="1713" /> instead of a rent of £1 for the houses, the owner will probably be demanding about £1 15s.  There are some of the tenants who earn only £2 15s. per week and that would leave them £1 to live on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Deputy sure that there is any control on these houses at all?  If they are new houses they are not of course controlled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidHall" hpid="Mr. HALL Mr. HALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HALL</NameTxt>
      <P>They are not new houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>If they have been built since 1919 they do not come within the Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidHall" hpid="Mr. HALL Mr. HALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HALL</NameTxt>
      <P>They have not been built since 1919.  Some of the people are living in them for the last 9 or 10 years.  It is an extraordinary state of affairs if we can be made believe here that to take control off a house when it becomes vacant is not going to re-act against the working classes in the city and townships of Dublin and other townships throughout Ireland.</P>
      <P>It is ridiculous.  If these houses in Botanic Avenue were vacant to-morrow the next thing one would hear about is a demand for a rent of £1 15s. per week instead of £1, the amount that is now paid.  I know some of the people who live in Botanic Avenue and I am aware they are earning only £2 15s. a week.  They cannot afford £1 15s. a week rent.  The amendment, in my opinion, is a bad one and whether the chickens were hatched out or not, as Deputy Lyons says, at all events they chipped the eggs at the wrong end.  Just as in the case of Trim, we have other cases around the country where tenants have been asking landlords to sell houses to them and they have not agreed to do so: the landlords would not even answer the requests.  In the town of Navan, if a house became vacant and if control was off, the landlord would raise the rent to such an extent that a working-class man would not be able to enter as tenant; you would have, as you have at present in Navan, working-class dwellings occupied by bank clerks and others who can afford to pay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The amendment is bad from the <Col N="1714" /> point of view of the working classes or those of the community who are paid low wages.  It extends little sympathy to the unfortunate tenants who are not well-off.  It is an amendment that should not be accepted by the House, because it is a landlord's amendment.  The landlords have been considering this situation for a length of time, and ultimately they got Deputy O'Connor, who might, for all I know, be a landlord himself, to push this through the House.  This will not assist in the direction of erecting more houses, and it has little bearing, to my mind, on the scarcity of houses or on the failure of would-be house contractors. As I stated here last year, what did affect the erection of houses was the high charges of the contractors; their high tenders had a big effect on house erection.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Why have the contractors to make such high charges?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidHall" hpid="Mr. HALL Mr. HALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HALL</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not quite catch the Deputy's statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Why are the contractors obliged to make such high charges?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot go into the question of wages now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidHall" hpid="Mr. HALL Mr. HALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HALL</NameTxt>
      <P>It is no use trying to make anyone believe this is a democratic amendment.  Deputy O'Connor endeavours to make us think that. From his point of view it is an amendment that will assist in giving more employment, and building more houses for the people who require them.  If a five-roomed house becomes vacant to-morrow, and its rent is raised from £1 to £1 15s., I believe you might have an assistant cashier of the Bank of Ireland looking for it, because the ordinary class of people, such as those who lived in it before, would not be able to pay the higher rent asked.  It is ridiculous to suggest that a man working at manual labour in Dublin, and earning £2 15s. a week, would be able to pay £1 15s. for rent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Deputy was listening to me, judging by his remarks.  In moving my amendment, <Col N="1715" /> I made no reference to giving more employment.  I had the welfare of the tenants much more at heart than the welfare of the house owners.  It is from the tenants we hear most grumbling; they are very anxious to know where they can get a house to rent. When I put down the amendment I had the tenants in mind.  A Deputy on my left stated that when he was looking for a house to rent he could not get it even at £70 or £80, and he had to buy a house.  I do not press the amendment at all; if it is not pleasing to the Labour Party I do not want them to accept it.</P>
      <P>Deputy Lyons made a remark about people in the country; he talked about egg-hatching and so on, and made reference to houses of a valuation of £35 and £40, in which poor people had to live.  Just imagine poor people living in a house with a valuation of £35 or £40!  The statement is absolutely ridiculous. However, that is beside the question.  I will address my remarks to the Minister now, and, as the Minister has heard the speeches from different parts of the House, I think he should leave the amendment to a free vote.  I think he should take an open vote on this matter, and it would give him a good indication of the general feeling in regard to this question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of explanation. I did not wish to interrupt the Deputy, but I did not refer to houses of £35 or £40 valuation being occupied by poor unfortunate persons in the country.  I said they might be occupied if houses of that valuation had their valuations altered; then the control over the rent might be removed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamEThrift" hpid="Professor THRIFT Professor THRIFT">
      <NameTxt>Professor THRIFT</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder would the Minister consider looking for a formula which would definitely exclude the operation of this in regard to tenement houses or small houses in the country, and make it apply to a house over £20 valuation, or something of that kind?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>Make it apply to houses of £10 valuation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the labourer's cottage in the country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1716" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAlexanderNagle" hpid="Mr. NAGLE Mr. NAGLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NAGLE</NameTxt>
      <P>As the amendment stands, I am against it.  I was going to suggest something similar to what Deputy Thrift has suggested.  There is a great difference in the minds of Deputy Johnson and myself and in the minds of Deputy O'Connor, Deputy Thrift and Deputy Dr. Hennessy as to the meaning of the amendment as it stands.  For instance, we claim it will apply to very small tenement houses and cottages that would be inhabited by the very poor.  The statements made by the Minister for Fisheries and Deputy Dr. Hennessy prove conclusively that they had no such ideas in their minds.  The Minister for Fisheries said that he found it impossible to get a house at a rent of £70 or £80 per year and was forced to purchase a house to live in.  There is no worker in Dublin or elsewhere who would rent a house like that.  If the section applied to houses of that nature we would not object.  Deputy Dr. Hennessy talked of houses that became vacant and upon which £150 would be spent for repair and decoration.  You could buy one of the houses we have in mind for £150.  If the Minister is going to consider this matter on Report he should take into account the suggestion made by Deputy Thrift.  I agree with Deputy O'Connor that if you make it a matter of £10 valuation you would be much nearer the mark. As the amendment stands I will oppose it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Deputy Johnson was correct in his contention that the amendment as it stands would apply to tenements, and to any rooms let separately in a house.  Turning to Section 12 of the present Bill we find &ldquo;This Act may be cited as the Increase of Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restrictions) Act, 1926, and shall be construed as one with the Principal Act, and that Act and this Act may be cited together as the Increase of Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restrictions) Acts, 1923 and 1926.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the Act of 1923, Section 3, the following occurs: &ldquo;This Act shall, subject to the provisions of this section, apply to a house or a part of a house let as a separate dwelling where either <Col N="1717" /> the annual amount of the standard rent or the rateable value does not exceed: (a) in the County Borough of Dublin and the Urban Districts in the Dublin Metropolitan Police area sixty pounds, and (b) elsewhere forty pounds; and every such house or part of a house shall be deemed to be a dwelling-house to which this Act applies.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I take it that that runs through, not merely to the Act of 1923, but would apply, also, in this Bill.  However, apart from that there is the question of the advisability of taking the line that a house, falling vacant, shall be automatically released from control. Deputy O'Connor asked me would I be prepared to leave the matter to an open vote of the Dáil.  Of course the answer to that is this amendment does not raise any issue which could properly or fairly be regarded as a matter of confidence, and I do not really care what way Deputies vote upon it.  I, myself, do not favour it as it stands, for the reasons I have already gone into. I think it is in conflict with the principle of this control legislation, and I think it constitutes a very real temptation to landlords to secure, by any and every means, vacant possession of their houses, so that houses may thereby be released from control.</P>
    <P>One suggestion is that that, possibly, might be met to some extent by a provision saying that only in the case of voluntary surrender by a tenant, and making some provision for evidence that the surrender was, in fact, voluntary, would decontrol apply.  But there has been a suggestion not to apply this amendment in the county boroughs of Dublin or Cork, and to let it simply apply throughout the rest of the State&mdash;or was it that it should only apply in the county boroughs of Dublin or Cork?  (Deputies&mdash;Yes.) The mover of the amendment can have it whichever way he likes.  If he wishes to have it out now, and left simply to the vote of the Dáil, that is one way of dealing with it.  If he likes to withdraw it on the understanding that we would, between this and Report Stage, give further consideration to the points that have been deduced, and the arguments that have been urged. we can deal with it that way.  But the only argument <Col N="1718" /> that was urged that influenced me to any extent was this point that houses tend, in the position as it stands, to lie vacant for the reason that the houseowner acquiring vacant possession of his house will not again let under the condition of our restrictive legislation, and will be prepared to wait even a considerable time for a buyer.  As against that, I think, we have put in some provision making the owner of empty houses liable for rates.  That was intended to check the tendency that was there, and was manifesting itself of allowing houses to lie idle rather than let them under the provisions of the control legislation.  That is one argument that has weighed with me.  No one wants to see houses lying empty in times of housing shortage, and if the release of houses from control, once they became vacant, would end that situation, then, that is one definite thing that can be urged in favour of such a course.  If the amendment is now put I, myself, will vote against it. If it is withdrawn I will consider between this and Report Stage if we can bring up an amendment that will perhaps be more satisfactory without going the full length of the Deputy's amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>resumed the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamEThrift" hpid="Professor THRIFT Professor THRIFT">
      <NameTxt>Professor THRIFT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am prepared to accept the second suggestion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quite agreeable, too.  I ask leave to withdraw amendment 11.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendment 10 (Deputy Thrift) not moved.</P>
      <P>Amendment 12 (Deputy Johnson) not moved.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That Section 4 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>As there is so little time at our disposal, it is scarcely worth while proceeding with Section 5, and I move that we report progress.</P>
      <P>The Dáil went out of Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1719" /> Progress reported, the Committee to sit again to-morrow.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Seanad has passed the Protection of the Community (Special Powers) Bill. 1926, together with the Resolution <Col N="1720" /> exempting it from the provisions of Article 47 of the Constitution.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 10.20 p.m. until 3 o'clock on Wednesday, 19th May.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>