<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="7" Month="Apr" Year="1954" Vol="43" No="9" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 7 Aibreán 1954" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 7 April 1954" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="745">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="745" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Sir Patrick Dun's Hospital" RHead="Bill&mdash;Message from Dáil">
    <Title>Sir Patrick Dun's Hospital Bill&mdash;Message from Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The following Message has been received from Dáil Éireann:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has passed the Sir Patrick Dun's Hospital Bill, 1953, without amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Business will be taken as set out on the Order Paper except that No. 6 will not be taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Superannuation Bill, 1954&mdash;Second" RHead="and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Superannuation Bill, 1954&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee) Seán MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill can be very simply stated.  It is to provide women civil servants with superannuation benefits on retirement similar to those available to men civil servants.</P>
      <P>The cost of the Bill in the immediate future cannot be calculated but it will not be significant and, in the long run, it will impose no additional charge on the Exchequer as the benefits which women civil servants will enjoy under the Bill have been actuarially equated to those which at the moment they do enjoy.  It is merely a case of giving an equal amount but in rather a different way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>When women began to be employed, the implication of that employment was not understood. This Bill seems to me to be merely a step upon the road which inevitably must be travelled when women are employed, as they are, in the Civil Service.  I think it is a step towards justice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am very interested in the Minister's <Col N="746" /> methods.  It would appear from his remarks that the Department have arranged that women civil servants will appear to get benefits but that, in fact, they will not: that is what I understood from the Minister.  If that could be done with other people what a wonderful scheme it would be.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>If I am in order&mdash;I would point out to the Senator that he is under a misapprehension.  It is not a case of giving the people the same and appearing to make it more; it is merely a case of conceding that these benefits be given in the form in which the beneficiaries desire them to be given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>In fact then, they are getting no more than they got before?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>They are getting it in a different form and they did got ask for more.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining stages now.</P>
      <P>Bill passed through Committee without recommendation, reported, and received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be returned to the Dáil.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. D. Burke Mr. D. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to say a word in a general way about superannuation. I believe with the increase in the number of years&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Would not that come under the next Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the Superannuation Bill, and if the Senator wants to discuss something arising out of the contents of the Bill he may do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you not allowing me to say briefly a few words on this?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, if it arises out of the contents of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to say briefly that the increase in the expectancy of life was referred to recently at a discussion in Dublin&mdash;I think the chairman <Col N="747" /> of the Bureau of Statistics was at that meeting, as well as some other people eminently qualified to speak on that subject.  They referred to the increase in the expectancy of life. They did not refer to this pending Bill, but I do think in framing future legislation we might consider allowing people to work on longer in the public service.  This question has been troubling people not alone in this country but also in Britain and other countries, and I think it is very much more pertinent here than anywhere else, because the time when people get married is later in Ireland than in any other country in the whole world. Very often the time when people reach the age of 65 and are forced to resign from the public service is just the time when their sons and daughters are the heaviest burden on them, and when these people could be of most benefit to their sons and daughters in matters of education, and so on.  I would ask the Minister and officials that these matters should be borne in mind when future Bills of this sort are being considered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the public will be gratified at the speech of Senator Burke.  I assume, of course, that he is speaking for his Party. Now, we find&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is going to pick holes in Senator Burke, obviously.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not instructed like the Government Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>We now appreciate that despite all its protestations Fine Gael have become the Party of the old men.  I am in that category myself and I have heard with a great deal of personal sympathy the plea which the Senator has made for people approaching patriarchal age.  I understand now that the policy which Fine Gael is going to put before the electorate in a very short time&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The general election&mdash;no, no.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="748" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;is that so far as the Civil Service is concerned their policy is going to be to keep the old men in and the young men out.  We do not subscribe to that policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>It is time some of you were let go out, then.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>And the Minister can go back too, sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Imposition of Duties (Confirmation of Orders)" RHead="Bill, 1954&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Imposition of Duties (Confirmation of Orders) Bill, 1954&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass) Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is similar in form to others that have from time to time been submitted to the Seanad. Its purpose is to confirm eight Orders which were made under the Emergency Imposition of Duties Act over the past eight months.  Orders made under that Act have to be confirmed by legislation. This Bill would have been time enough in May or June next but in view of the pending dissolution of the Dáil it was thought desirable to bring it forward now and get it enacted so that no complications would arise by reason of the fact that the Dáil would not be meeting during the month of May.</P>
      <P>There are eight commodities affected by the Orders scheduled to this Bill. None of them is of major economic importance.  They include berets, pot scourers, oils and fats, welding electrodes, single yarns of cotton and artificial silk, asbestos draining boards, milk cans and agricultural tractor tyres.  The only new duty imposed in this Bill is that on welding electrodes. The Orders relating to pot scourers, oils and fats, single cotton yarns amended duties already in operation. The duty on berets was increased.  The duty on milk cans which had been in operation previously but which was suspended was restored at a lower rate.  The Orders relating to asbestos draining boards and agricultural tractor tyres revoked duties previously in operation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="749" /> So far as berets are concerned this form of headgear has increased in popularity among certain people and berets are manufactured here by two firms, one in Cork and one in Mayo. Competition between them is fairly keen and prices are fully competitive with the prices of imported berets. While I understand there were some technical difficulties associated with the manufacture these have been overcome and production is now proceeding on a scale capable of meeting the full demand for these products.  There are over 50 people employed in the manufacture of berets, which seems to be an indication that their popularity is increasing.</P>
    <P>There was a duty on pot scourers made of metal and that was extended to include pot scourers made of artificial plastic and also to cover steel wool.  The Order really effected an amendment of the definition of pot scourers to which the duty applied.</P>
    <P>The position is the same in regard to oils and fats.  That duty operated for a number of years and covered within its scope a number of oils which were not in fact produced here.  At the time when the duty was originally imposed it was considered that definition difficulties would arise if these oils were excluded from the scope of the duty. Since the duty came into force duty free licences for these oils have been issued on application.  On reconsideration of the duty, however, it was found possible to get over the definition difficulty and actually to exclude these oils from the scope of the duty so that the necessity to issue licences for importation would no longer arise.  The Order also amended the duty to provide that the mere addition of water would not invalidate the duty and that, again, was a small measure taken to make good the original decision and to prevent evasion of the duty.</P>
    <P>As I said, the only new duty arising out of this Bill is on certain welding electrodes.  Welding Electrodes (Ireland) Limited have commenced production of these commodities.  They are associated with a firm in Britain which formerly supplied most of the market.  That firm has given them the technical assistance and marketing <Col N="750" /> advice which they required and they are producing these welding electrodes at prices similar to those prevailing in Britain.  This firm when established planned to develop an export trade from the beginning and they have installed capacity which represents about twice the requirements of the Irish market.  They will need to get export business if the whole of the capital is to be remunerated and they have had ample testimony as to the quality of the production and evidence that the prices at which welding electrodes are being sold here are comparable with the prices of those selling elsewhere.</P>
    <P>The Order with regard to single cotton yarns was designed to amend the scope of the previous Order which related to single cotton yarns.  That duty upon single cotton yarns was imposed for the purpose of protecting firms engaged in production here. There are four such firms operating in the country.  It was found that the market was being seriously affected by the importation of yarns composed of a mixture of cotton and rayon to which the duty did not apply.  It was decided then to extend the scope of the duty.  That step was taken more readily when the firms engaged in the production of single cotton yarns undertook to supply these mixture yarns as well and are now doing so, I understand, in a reasonable degree.</P>
    <P>There was a duty upon asbestos draining boards which are not now made here and, so far as I can discover, not used here, and, therefore, we are revoking the duty.</P>
    <P>So far as milk cans are concerned, this duty applies only to milk cans under 12 gallons capacity.  Most Senators will know that the majority of milk cans used here are of a larger size than that.  The duty was brought into operation before the war but it was suspended during the war years. The manufacture of these 12-gallon milk cans and smaller milk cans has been resumed and the firm which is making them has entered into undertakings with us that the cans will be sold in this country at the British domestic prices; that is to say the same prices at which similar cans are sold in Great Britain.  There was, <Col N="751" /> however, some reason to apprehend that supplies of cans might be imported for the purpose of getting rid of surplus stocks, particularly from continental countries, at the time of the year when seasonal demand was greatest.  There is a seasonal element in the demand for these cans and it was thought desirable to keep that position under control by imposing a small duty.  The customs duty, which was previously fairly considerable, has been lowered to 15 per cent. full rate and 10 per cent. <i>ad valorem</i> and that is merely to ensure that this firm making the cans will be able to enter upon production for meeting the whole market requirements for the cans and, therefore, to fulfil its price undertaking.</P>
    <P>The position in regard to agricultural tractor tyres was somewhat anomalous. The House is probably aware that, following the commencement of the manufacture of rubber tyres here, an excise duty upon Irish-produced tyres was brought into operation.  The purpose of the excise duty was to secure revenue for the Exchequer, or, rather, to prevent the loss of revenue to the Exchequer which the commencement of manufacture at home would otherwise have occasioned.  There was a limited range of agricultural tractor tyres produced by the Dunlop company in Cork.  These tyres were subject to an excise duty while at the same time agricultural tractor tyres could be imported without duty.  We had, therefore, the anomalous situation that home-produced tyres were subject to a duty while imported tyres were not subject to it, and that was resolved by revoking the excise duty on agricultural tractor tyres.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not propose to go into a full-dress debate about the wisdom or otherwise of the policy enunciated in these Orders of the Minister, but I am particularly concerned with this duty on creamery cans to which I addressed myself on a previous occasion.  It is the generally-accepted policy of every Government here to impose duties on the importation of foreign goods.  When I went <Col N="752" /> into the other House in 1923 as a member of the Farmers' Party, we were confronted with somewhat similar Orders by the Government of that day and we filled columns in the records of the Dáil in the succeeding years on the burdens which were being imposed on the agricultural community arising from the tariffs which were then being imposed.  We have come a long journey from that.  We are conscious of the fact that these extra duties are being paid by our consumers here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>We will let Senator O'Donnell talk for himself.  If a farmer has to pay 15 per cent. more than he paid before for creamery cans by virtue of an Act of this Oireachtas, the Senator will have to prove to me that what I said is not true, when I know it to be a fact.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has said they are being sold at the same price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I know he did.  This is an important matter to the section that I am concerned about, that is, the dairy farmers.  I am speaking on behalf of the dairy farmers.  I know it is the policy of national Governments to help to develop native industry, but there is a point at which we must stop, we must hesitate and examine what are the implications and the consequences of a particular duty. You are imposing here in this Bill a duty of 15 per cent. <i>ad valorem,</i> 10 per cent. preferential, on the importation of certain milk cans.  They are only certain milk cans of 12 gallons and under, but they are milk cans used by the small farmers in the small farming districts in the country.  They are not the milk cans that the 40 cow man in Limerick or South Tipperary would be concerned about at all.  They are the cans used in my county and in the dairying districts and small farming areas of the country.  We are going to pay, and we ought to know exactly what the situation is at the moment with regard to the importation of these cans.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="753" /> I do not want to be misinterpreted and misrepresented on this matter.  I am merely telling what the fact is.  I do not think in the first place that this matter has been very well handled at all in so far as the Minister or his people are concerned over taking the decision in conjunction with the people who are going to set this development going.  I do not think that what has taken place as a result of the original decision of the Minister is a compliment to them.  My information is that some people in business in this country who were very anxious indeed to assist the people who are engaging in this new development were awaiting the day when they would be able to supply this particular commodity.  They waited and waited, and the tariff was imposed after a bit, but in the meantime other people who were not much concerned about what the native industrialist was going to provide were able to stock up with cans; and then we had a position that some of those other people who were in the business and could not get the product from the new firm had to go out and buy and had to pay the duty, so that those people who are trying to encourage the native concern have got a tariffed article in their stores and are trying to compete with the other people who have it in minus the duty.  That sort of situation does no credit to anybody. It is not the kind of way a law like this should be imposed.  It should apply equally to all citizens on the same day, and particulars and facilities should not be given to one that cannot be enjoyed by the other.  If this particular firm advised that they required this tariff, in my judgment anyhow it should not have been imposed until they were in a position with their equipment to put their goods on the market, but so far as I understand it that was not the situation. That is my first complaint.</P>
    <P>The second point I want to make is this.  The native product is to be sold at the same price as the foreign commodity plus the tariff.  That is the position at the present time, and there is this further to be said, that the native product is not as good.  One does not like saying this, but we are the <Col N="754" /> people who are buying, and these are very expensive commodities to-day. You do not get very much for a couple of pounds now.  Creamery cans are very expensive, and if they do not give the service the farmer is being taxed, and it is the small farmer who is being taxed.  I do not know is it worth it. I do not think it is.  I have no experience, and I am not acquainted with the conditions in this industry with regard to raw materials or anything else, but I do not like the farmer to be made the guinea pig for an experimental process in regard to some new development here.  The farmer, and especially the small farmer, the man in my county with four or five or six cows, will be able to put his milk in a ten-gallon can and certainly in a 12-gallon can, and he is the man who is going to pay. There are thousands of these in my county.  It is a creamery area from one end of it to the other.  We are going to pay more for this article coming out of an Irish industry or to buy a foreign imported creamery can. Again, if we are going to buy the imported creamery can we are going to buy it because if both are the same price and it is regarded as a superior product we cannot be blamed.  I do not know that the Minister in having a position like this is justified.  I think the hardship imposed, the extra tax imposed, on the small producer is a discouragement in these days when that particular man is going to face very considerable difficulties in his production and undoubtedly going to have to sell against a falling market.  It will be difficult to hold his prices, and in a situation like that he will have to pay more for the raw materials.  My view of this matter is that a tax like that demands more study, and it is just not sufficient, it is hardly justifiable, to impose a tax like this on a section of the community, and a certain section who are less well able to bear it.</P>
    <P>I am not against the general policy of tariffs.  I am not against the policy of trying to provide our own needs when those needs are something that is generally consumed; but when there is just a limited market and a limited number of purchasers, less well able to bear a burden like this, I am not <Col N="755" /> for it, especially because I am satisfied that the thousands of small farmers in my county who are dairy men, sending their milk to the creamery as we do all over the county, and in other parts of the country, are the people who are going to pay the tax.  I want at least to record my disapproval of this whole matter and the way it has been handled originally, and in the second place the unwisdom as well as the injustice of the imposition of this tax.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>It is deplorable that Senator Baxter has got back on his old bicycle, attacking, by innuendo, new Irish industries.  It is particularly a pity because the firm concerned is a very old established firm here and I understand it is extremely well equipped to turn out the type of can to which Senator Baxter refers.  It lost the market to some extent due to causes not under its own control and it did not find it very easy, at least at first, to sell its product for some time. Due to the fact that certain people apparently were aware or guessed that the tariff might be going on, they had stocked up to some extent.  Statements of the nature that Senator Baxter makes should not be accepted at all by the public&mdash;that because an industry starts here the resultant article made here is dearer to the consuming public. The Minister himself has stated that a guarantee has been given in this particular instance by the company concerned that the price will not exceed the current domestic price in the external market.  I think that is right in this case as far as I know of the firm concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I rather deplore the innuendo here that a firm here is being bolstered up to produce an article which the Senator suggests is not as good as the imported article.  On that I am not prepared to argue, because I have not seen the articles and even if I had seen them I would not be competent to judge which was the better, but the insinuation here is that because an industry is started here under a protective policy the article as a result has necessarily to be dearer and the consuming public must of necessity pay more for <Col N="756" /> it, and pay more as a result of being mulcted, as it were, by a protective policy.  That is what this whole argument comes down to.  It would be no harm if we had some declaration by some people here whether they stand for a free trade policy or a protection policy in this country.  It is obvious that the Minister stands for a protective policy.  The repercussions of that affect all the sections of society.  He had put a tariff here on a thing known as a beret which is not used mainly by farmers.  Senator Baxter's argument is that because a can is used mainly by farmers it is an unfair tariff.</P>
    <P>I think it deplorable that at this stage of our lives we should have the sort of argument that because an article is protected by the Government it is, <i>ipso facto,</i> a poorer article and a dearer article than the imported commodity and that it must inflict a penalty on the farming community.  I think it goes without saying that any measure likely to affect detrimentally agricultural consumers would not meet with the approval of industrialists generally.  We, as industrialists, are alive to the necessity of having a complementary arm in our agricultural community, and the enactment of anything that may bring a sense of frustration to industrialists or to the farmer is not a good day's work for the nation.  I deplore any attempt to use this House to broadcast the suggestion that the can that is being made by an Irish firm is not as good as, or is dearer than, the imported article and that we are penalising the farmer by reason of the fact that the Minister is forcing him to buy the Irish manufactured article.  That sort of statement is a statement which is to be deplored and is one which should not be made.</P>
    <P>On this occasion I am not going to enter on a field which might lead to a much bigger sphere of discussion on the whole question of the principle involved&mdash;as to whether the duties which have been imposed by the Government are justifiable.  If we accept the fundamental premise that they are necessary and sound in the national interest, then we must support them.  If we do accept that, then <Col N="757" /> Senator Baxter is wrong and this house should not be used to attack the quality of any article made by an Irish industry unless there is absolute and positive proof that the article is of poorer quality, that the methods pursued in its production are inefficient or that the service to the community is not such as would justify the Minister giving protection to that article. Unless such proof is forthcoming, it is deplorable that a statement of that nature should be made in this House.</P>
    <P>As regards the duties on berets, I think I can say that the farmer has no cause for complaint, because even the raw material for these articles is of Irish production.  The berets are made of Irish wool so that the process of manufacture is entirely Irish.  The only trouble that I see there is that the duty refers to articles made of felt or felt material.  There is a possible chance of evasion because, as I understand it, the actual definition of the material used in the manufacture of berets is knitted material that is not felt.  That might give a loophole to people who might like to import articles made of materials which would not be exactly defined as felt made of felt material.  I should like the Minister to deal with the point as to whether berets the material of which is made of felt would come within the scope of the duty.</P>
    <P>As regards the duty on cotton and silk yarns, I hope the Minister will extend the licensing facilities because I understand that these mixture yarns are essential in the production of certain types of low-grade textile articles or rather low-grade textile articles which are necessary to meet demands by the poorer sections of the people. I do not know whether the cotton mills or the spinning mills have been producing this mixture yarn so far.  I doubt very much if they have.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>You are quite wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very glad to hear that they are.  If we are in a position to supply these yarns, it furnishes a further justification for the Minister's action in imposing these duties, but I understand that, some <Col N="758" /> time ago, some of my friends who use this mixture yarn found it rather difficult to get it in the Irish mills.  The one thing I deplore is the fact that, as I understand it, the imposition of the duty came at such a late period that it has not yet effected any benefit for the firm concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>Much of what I should like to say on this Bill has been already said by Senator O'Donnell, but I wish to go on record in protest against the nature of the speeches we get from Senator Baxter every time there is a suggestion here of a tariff affecting anything used by the farmers.  I feel that I am correct in saying that if we were to go back on all the speeches made by Senator Baxter in recent years, we would find that he has got one set type of speech. Quite recently, we had the same speech that we heard in the last half-hour from the Senator on a Bill dealing with buckets.  It cannot be that Senator Baxter is always right and that the rest of us are always wrong. If it is admitted that in the initial stages of the creation and development of an industry some measure of protection is necessary to enable that industry to get on its feet and to protect it against the competition of heavy imports from other countries with a long tradition of industrial efficiency, it will be generally recognised that these duties are justified. A striking fact is that practically every farming village and town in Ireland is eager to get some of these constantly maligned industries.  I wonder if Senator Baxter is speaking for the farmers when he talks about the allegedly evil effects of the imposition of these duties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I know what I am talking about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Baxter is a Pooh-Bah&mdash;he knows more about industry than those who specialise in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I spoke of one tariff only.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>I am in possession now.  I did not interrupt Senator Baxter when he was speaking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="759" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not exaggerate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>He comes here and makes a positive statement without proof.  He made a very long speech from which we are to infer that the poor small farmer is in danger of extinction, because of a tariff of 10 or 15 per cent. on a certain type of milk can.  Was there ever anything more ludicrous?  Nobody says a word about the degree to which this Government have seen to it that the lot of the farmers of this country has been greatly improved, and we all are delighted that it has.  Senator Baxter takes it on himself to speak for the farmer but many of us on this side who have country contacts doubt whether the farmers of the country generally would like to be fitted with the cap that Senator Baxter seeks to put upon them&mdash;that, because of this measly little protective tariff to help a new industry, the farmer is in danger of extinction.  I protest against the fact that every time a measure is brought before this House dealing with duties we get the same type of speech here from Senator Baxter.  Senator Baxter may think he is helping the farmer.  I say he is not and he is certainly not helping the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Have I not the right to make my speech?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope that Senator O'Donnell did not mean that this subject was so sacrosanct that one dare not speak on it.  As one who would like to keep to the middle of the road, to avoid being hit by the missiles thrown from one side or the other, by either Senator Summerfield or Senator Baxter, I should like to say something on behalf of an industry which may be affected by one of the tariffs imposed by this Bill.  There is a very large assembling industry in this country using metal generally as a material. There is the assembly of motor-cars, the assembly of small ware of various sorts, enamelled and galvanised.  There is also the manufacture of such articles as rainwear tanks and of dozens of other things in which these electrodes are used to weld.  It is a very highly specialised job in which a knowledge <Col N="760" /> of physics and chemistry is necessary, if one is to do the job in a proper way.</P>
      <P>If major industries which are exporting goods and which require certain types of electrodes to assist them in their manufacture find that the home electrodes are not suitable for the job, I would like an assurance from the Minister that the proper type of electrodes will be made available to them.  I have no information that what is being made in the country is not suitable, but it would be a great safeguard if the Minister agreed to insert a licensing provision to enable these various highly technical types of industries using electrodes in a very big way to get permission to import their requirements, so that they will not be hindered in the development of the export business in which many of them are engaged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>The House is well aware that my point of view on measures of this kind differs considerably from that of Senator Baxter and my only reason for speaking is to say that I disagree also with Senator O'Donnell's attitude and to some extent the attitude of Senator Summerfield. I have been engaged in industry over a fairly long period and I am not in the least frightened because there is some criticism when Bills of this kind come before the House.  Irish industry is now sufficiently well established that it can stand up to that criticism and can welcome it and answer it, when it comes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If there is criticism outside.  I would prefer that it should come from Senator Baxter or Senator O'Donnell, who incidentally made some criticism on his own inaccurately, than that it should simply be whispered outside. Senator O'Donnell, while horrified about milk cans, put in a little aside to the effect that mixture yarns were not being produced here.  In that, he just was not correct and I could make a very eloquent speech about the iniquity of using this House to suggest that certain types of yarns which are being produced here are not being produced here.  No harm at all is done by that and it may even do good, because it makes clear that they are <Col N="761" /> being produced, a fact which Senator O'Donnell did not know.</P>
    <P>Let us be realists about this and let us not be afraid of a little criticism. I can truthfully say that I am speaking on behalf of the vast majority of Irish industrialists when I say that if our industries are being whispered around as being inefficient or if it is suggested that something is wrong in relation to their prices, the sooner that comes out where somebody can answer it, where the Minister can answer it, or where, if necessary, the industries can answer it, if the Minister is not in a position to do so, the better.  I think that is all healthy and for my part I am not a bit afraid of it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>If only to make clear that it is not a case of Senator Baxter against the rest, I should like to say a few words on this Bill.  It has always struck me that on occasions when we have a Bill of this kind dealing with the imposition of duties, with protection, certain Senators&mdash;sometimes Senator O'Donnell and at other times Senator Summerfield&mdash;doth protest too much.  They complain without having any reason to complain.  We here are perfectly entitled to give expression to criticism without causing any grievous offence to people who really only think we are causing offence.</P>
      <P>We may not all accept what Senator Baxter has said and we may not all think that his criticism was quite in point in a number of instances, but I do not think he has been in any way unfair, and it is wrong for any person, interested in particular matters or not, to complain, or pretend to complain, grievously when criticism is directed towards such matters.  They are very important matters for some sections of our people&mdash;the section of our people who make the articles and the section who purchase them.  I believe the Minister tries to keep evenly between these sections.  I am satisfied from observations he has made in public from time to time that he feels he has a duty to help industry, but he has also made it clear that the people who purchase these articles have rights and that manufacturers have obligations to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="762" /> The Minister will have to give me a great deal more information before I agree to give him the Second Stage of this Bill.  He has made no case for it.  It is a Bill which seeks to confirm Orders, in the nature of temporary Orders, imposing duties and I should have thought that the Minister would have gone into great detail to justify the permanent imposition of duties which heretofore were only temporary. When I say he has not made any case for the Bill, I have perhaps made an over-statement.  He has certainly made a case for the removal of the duty on asbestos draining boards which, apparently, are not used at all here now and indeed for the removal of the duty on motor tractor tyres.  What was happening in that case was ridiculous and it may be that other similar things are happening unknown, to us.</P>
    <P>If we look at the particular objects for which this Bill is designed, we find that there is a variation of the duty on berets.  By all means, let us have that duty, if we are satisfied that we shall be doing some good to the manufacturers and purchasers of these articles. It did occur to me, however, to ask myself if there is a gesture to any particular person in regard to berets.  Are they becoming particularly popular these days?  I should like the Minister to give us details to show what benefits are being conferred on industry and on the public in the permanent imposition of that duty on berets.  I should have expected the Minister to give us in some detail the number of people employed in making these articles and generally the benefits conferred on the people in the matter of price by the production of these articles here.</P>
    <P>I do not complain very much if we must pay a little more for articles manufactured here than we would have to pay for imported articles.  I have no grievance on that head.  I would have a grievance if we had to pay very much more for the homemade article, but I have no real grievance where there is no great difference in price, but we should be told by the Minister in sufficient detail to enable us to make up our minds what benefits are conferred on the particular industries and on the public by <Col N="763" /> the permanent imposition of these duties.  Until the Minister gives us that information and, by that information, satisfies us that we should agree to impose them, I cannot consent to giving him this stage of the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>The manufacture of milk cans and other dairy equipment is a natural corollary to a prosperous and successful dairy industry. The great countries in which dairying equipment is manufactured are Denmark and Sweden and they are great precisely because the dairying industry in these countries is also great.  We have in this country a dairying industry which is not prospering and which has to be heavily subsidised at the expense of other sections of the community, including the consumer.  It is typical of the whole industrial policy that we should be taxing the equipment of the dairying industry and making dairy production more expensive.  It is another example of the besetting sin of putting the industrial cart before the agricultural horse.  Unless we reverse that in the near future we will never have a prosperous agriculture or a prosperous industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I recognise it is an unusual political situation which requires Senator Baxter to go through the formality of declaring that he is not against the general policy of protection. If he approached his Party committee he might get the same privileges as are extended to Deputy Dillon, who makes no secret of his hostility to protection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not.  I never said I was against the general policy of protection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has repeated the formula of saying that he is not against it even though he never seems to agree with its application in an individual case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>In some individual cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="764" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to milk cans, the position is that there was a duty of 45 per cent. full and 30 per cent. preferential on milk cans of all sizes imposed before the war.  That was suspended when the manufacture of milk cans became impossible.  It has been reimposed but only in respect of milk cans under 12 gallons capacity. The duty is now 15 per cent. full and 10 per cent. preferential instead of 45 per cent. full and 30 per cent. preferential.</P>
      <P>With regard to Senator Baxter's complaints in respect of stocking up of milk cans, I was not quite sure whether he was complaining because some people foresaw the possibility of the duty being imposed and began a stockpile or because the duty was brought into operation before the Irish firm was in a position to supply the whole of the market requirements. It was a combination of both.  It is true that there was some evidence of stockpiling during the time the plant for the manufacture of milk cans was being installed.  In fact, the firm was in production and putting the cans on the market before the duty was brought into operation.  That was due to my desire to be completely satisfied as to the capacity of the firm to produce cans of good quality and at competitive prices before imposing even this low rate of duty.  I was quite satisfied they were doing so.  Samples of the milk cans were submitted to the Department of Agriculture which certified to me that they were up to the highest standard of imported cans. I have received no complaints that the price undertaking given by this firm has not been fulfilled.  If Senator Baxter does, in fact, know of any case where the Irish cans are being sold at the price of the imported cans, plus duty, I will be glad if he will give me the information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Both as to the quality and the price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Let the Senator make sure it was an Irish can that was defective in quality before he complains about it.  There is no reason that I know of why there should be any difficulty in getting <Col N="765" /> immediate delivery of Irish-made milk cans.  In fact, I have been told there is quite a substantial stock, that the firm has not yet been able to get into full production and that, consequently, they can meet orders as they come in.  No traders in these cans need have any difficulty by reason of the coming into operation of this duty.</P>
      <P>With regard to the mixture yarns, our estimate is that present requirements of these yarns are about 2,000,000 lb. weight per year, and of that requirement of Irish manufacturers about 75 per cent. can at present be met by the Irish mills.  At the present time, the duty free licences for the balance are being issued, and the licence given to any individual firm is related to the orders placed by it with the Irish manufacturers.</P>
      <P>So far as the berets are concerned, the application from the manufacturers was for the imposition of a duty upon felted berets.  There never has been any suggestion from them that the duty was being evaded by the bringing in of berets made of anything other than felted material.  I do not think it is practicable to make berets except from felted material, otherwise they would not last through a shower of rain.</P>
      <P>With regard to electrodes, I am not quite sure what Senator Burke's complaint was.  The electrodes produced are, so far as I know, regarded as quite satisfactory by all the firms using them.  If any situation should arise in which proper types of electrodes were not being produced and were not available to any Irish manufacturer, then we would do something about it. I think that is not a situation we are likely to be confronted with.  Also, those electrodes are produced from wire which is drawn here, so that the establishment of this industry represents a further extension and a further market for another industry which was recently brought into operation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The other duties to which reference was made, particularly the excise duty on tractor tyres, does represent a situation which had to be rectified.  It only became a matter of importance <Col N="766" /> recently.  As soon as it became obvious that an unsatisfactory situation existed, the excise duty was repealed and the present position is that agricultural tractor tyres, either of Irish manufacture or imported, are available here without any duty of any kind being charged upon them.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take the remaining stages to-day.</P>
    <P>Bill considered in Committee, reported without recommendation, received for final consideration and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Electricity (Supply) (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1954&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Bill, 1954&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>In its main purpose this Bill is not dissimilar from other Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Acts which were previously debated by the Seanad, all of which had the main object of providing for the growing capital requirements of the E.S.B.  The main purpose of this Bill is to increase from £65,000,000 to £100,000,000 the statutory limit of expenditure which the E.S.B. may incur for capital purposes other than rural electrification.</P>
      <P>This Bill is different from those that preceded it because it proposes to change the method by which the capital needs of the E.S.B. will be met.  Heretofore, the board secured the capital required for development, within the limits fixed by statute, from the Exchequer.  In future it is proposed to permit the board to have direct access to the public for its capital requirements. That change in the method of financing the board's development involves certain other consequential steps to which I will refer later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The other main purpose of the Bill is to raise from £8,000,000 to £16,000,000 the statutory limit of advances which may be made to the board from the Central Fund for its rural electrification activities.  The White Paper which was circulated with the Bill gives in considerable detail the programme of capital works upon which the board is now engaging or works <Col N="767" /> in respect of which they have already entered into commitments.  The full cost of these capital works already approved will involve the sanctioning of expenditure by the board up to a limit of about £120,000,000.  The £100,000,000 limit fixed in this Bill will secure the position of the board until 1956.  Before some date in 1956 another amending Act will be necessary, but it was not considered desirable to make the provision for the whole of the estimated expenditure on the present programme of the board in this Bill, in the belief that the Houses of the Oireachtas would prefer to have another opportunity of looking at the programme, at the progress made and the general situation prevailing in about two years from now.</P>
    <P>I have said that advantage is being taken of this Bill, and it was necessary to do so because of the proposed change in the method of financing, to tidy up certain loose ends in the board's finances.  The first and most important of these relates to the position of the Shannon works.  The agreed liability assumed by the board in respect of the Shannon scheme which the Minister for Industry and Commerce was authorised to construct under the Shannon Electricity Acts was something over £6,000,000: to be precise, £6,030,066.  The money required for the construction of the Shannon scheme was made available to the Minister for Industry and Commerce out of the Central Fund and, although the works were transferred to the board by the Electricity Supply Act, 1927, they remained vested in the Minister.  It is now proposed to vest them in the board.  One of the reasons for taking that step, apart from the desire to regularise the position, is that it is necessary to enable the board to make a charge upon all its assets as security for any stock it may issue.</P>
    <P>In addition to the £6,000,000 representing the agreed liability assumed by the board in respect of the Shannon works, there is a further sum of something over £38,000,000 which represents the total of repayable advances made to the board from the <Col N="768" /> Central Fund for purposes other than rural electrification from the date of the establishment of the board up to the 31st December last.  That money has been expended upon various works which the board was authorised to undertake under the different Acts.  Of the total liability representing the sum of these two amounts, £38,000,000 and £6,000,000, the board has already repaid £1,961,000, but for the purposes of this Bill no account is taken of such repayments in calculating the authorised total of capital expenditure.</P>
    <P>Apart from its right of access to the Central Fund to meet its capital requirements, the board has two other sources of financing available to it: one is the board's own depreciation reserves and the second is the superannuation funds.  The board is, as the House is aware, because it was a matter of some debate at the time, under a statutory obligation so to adjust its charges for electricity as to make adequate provision not merely for its day-to-day expenses but also for the repayment of the moneys borrowed by it and for the replacement of its wasting assets.  In accordance with that statutory obligation to replace its wasting assets the board sets aside every year out of its revenue sums which, accumulating over the life of these assets, will, it is estimated, be sufficient to provide for their replacement when they reach the end of their useful life.</P>
    <P>The board is authorised by existing legislation&mdash;in fact, by an Act which was passed for that purpose in 1941&mdash; to invest these reserve funds in trustee securities or in such other securities as may be approved by the Minister for Finance.  But, in fact, the board has not availed itself of that power and has used these reserves for the provision of new capital assets according as they were authorised under the successive Acts.  In other words, the board's depreciation reserves have been invested in its own undertaking, which is a desirable practice both from the point of view of the board and from the point of view of the Exchequer. Again, it is, of course, to be understood that all sums used by the board <Col N="769" /> in that manner must be included in the authorised total of the board's capital expenditure at any particular time in order to calculate whether or not the level of that expenditure is within the limits sanctioned by legislation.</P>
    <P>The Electricity Supply Board (Superannuation) Act, 1942, provided for the introduction of superannuation schemes on a contributory basis by the board's employees and for the management of those funds by trustees.  That Act authorised the trustees of those funds to lend to the board such sums as they thought proper to lend and the board was authorised to borrow from these funds for any purpose arising out of the performance of its function. That arrangement is mutually advantageous. It provides for the trustees a very convenient and a very easily realisable form of investment, the value of which remains constant, and for the board it provides a convenient, additional source of finance.  The total amount which the board has borrowed from the trustees out of the superannuation funds to date is £1,646,500.</P>
    <P>I do not propose to go into detail now on the board's development programme. The House, as I have said, has an opportunity of considering that on the basis of the White Paper.  The primary object of all this development is to increase electricity generating capacity to meet the growth in demand for electricity.  The board now estimates that the demand for electricity will double in every period of five or six years.  It is clear, therefore, that we have to contemplate continuous additions to the board's installed generating capacity, at any rate so long as that expansion in demand is anticipated.  From the point of view of the state of development of this country, it is clear that that development can go on for a very long time because we are still well behind most European countries either in terms of installed generating capacity or in the consumption of electricity per head of the population.</P>
    <P>The main aspect of the new generation programme, to which it is perhaps desirable to direct attention, is that it is based almost entirely on <Col N="770" /> the use of our native resources.  The programme puts emphasis on turf fired stations and on water power stations.  In so far as the turf fired stations are concerned, the board's programme is, of course, complementary to the Bord na Móna development programme which I outlined here last year when the Turf Development Bill of 1953 was before the Seanad.  When that co-ordinated programme has been completed, the generating stations using only turf or native coal will use annually, it is estimated, about 2,500,000 tons of milled peat, about 400,000 tons of machine-won sod peat, and about 120,000 tons of hand-won turf which will be consumed in four small stations which are being set up, mainly for social reasons, along the western seaboard.  The average annual output of all our native fuel stations will be over 1,500,000,000 units, which compares with the total output of 1,300,000,000 units from all the stations of the E.S.B. in 1953.  Indeed, I may say, that if our past experience is any guide, these estimates are likely to be exceeded.</P>
    <P>In the two turf-fired generating stations which are now operating, not merely was the output of current considerably in excess of the original estimates, but the consumption of fuel is also, consequentially, in excess of the quantity originally estimated to be required.</P>
    <P>On the completion of this programme we will have at least 63 per cent. and, possibly, more of the total installed electricity generating capacity of the country based upon native resources, either upon native fuel or water power, so that our dependence on imported fuel for electricity requirements will be very considerably reduced.  That will be a happy position to be in when one considers our experience during the recent emergency.</P>
    <P>The board, as I have said, has since its establishment been financed from the three sources which I have mentioned: the Central Fund, its own depreciation reserves and the superannuation funds.  These sources will still be open to the board, but, as I have mentioned, it is proposed to <Col N="771" /> confer new borrowing powers on the board.  The principal new borrowing power is that contained in Section 4 of the Bill.  That section authorises the board to borrow money by the issue of its own securities.  It enables it to obtain its capital requirements in future from sources other than the Central Fund.  The total of £25,000,000 which the board has been authorised to borrow under that section is, as I have said, estimated to be sufficient to meet the board's requirements in respect of actual expenditure upon projects, other than rural electrification, until the end of March, 1956.  In each case, the terms and conditions of the issue will have to be approved by the Minister for Industry and Commerce and the Minister for Finance, and it is stipulated that the uses of the moneys to be obtained by the issue of the board's securities will also be subject to the approval of the Minister for Industry and Commerce.</P>
    <P>These provisions are designed to provide the assurance that the board's development programme will be along the general lines of which the Government has approved, and that there will be no departure from that programme without the approval of the responsible Minister.  In view of the magnitude of the programme and of the large proportion of national capital investment which it will absorb, I think it will be accepted as essential that such an assurance should be given in statutory form.  From the investors' point of view, there are distinct advantages in the existence of a provision which will ensure that the programme for which they are being asked to subscribe has the approval of the Government.</P>
    <P>I do not think that any fears may be entertained that the board will not now be able to finance its future development in the way proposed.  The undertaking has developed to the stage at which it should be possible for it to obtain its capital requirements from the public and it need no longer rely on the Central Fund save in exceptional circumstances.  The liabilities of the board are amply covered by its fixed and liquid assets, and it, of <Col N="772" /> course, enjoys the great advantage of being the sole producer in a market which is constantly expanding and in which the scope for expansion is, as I have indicated, almost unlimited.</P>
    <P>The securities issued by the board will be trustee securities and may be underwritten by the Minister for Finance.  The Bill also empowers the Minister for Finance to guarantee these securities.  To the extent, of course, that the board can obtain its capital requirements other than from the Central Fund, the State will be correspondingly relieved from the necessity of providing for its requirements. The House, no doubt, is aware that a considerable proportion of the proceeds of recent issues of Government stock have had to be earmarked for the Electricity Supply Board.  It will also make available, on our rather limited security market, a new and attractive type of security which it is hoped will attract an additional class of investor who may not normally invest in Government issues but who, it is hoped, would be prepared to invest in the board's issues.</P>
    <P>The type of securities to be issued will, of course, be governed by the statutory position of the board.  That position does not permit of the issue of stock with voting rights, but the board will nevertheless have considerable freedom of action and these issues should be of the type to make a wide appeal to investors.</P>
    <P>I mentioned that the Central Fund will still be available to the board, and the Bill authorised the Minister for Finance to continue if necessary to make advances to the board within the authorised limit.  The sole purpose of that provision is to ensure the board will have available to it at all times the moneys required to enable its development programme to go ahead without restriction.  It is intended, however, that the Central Fund will only be a secondary source of finance, and that in future advances will be sought by the board from the Exchequer only for the purpose of tiding the board over a period during which it might not be convenient or desirable for one reason or another to seek capital from other sources.  The <Col N="773" /> Central Fund will, therefore, be the lender of last resort, and is not likely to be called upon to any great extent.</P>
    <P>We have kept rural electrification outside all these financial arrangements. The Bill provides for an increase from £8,000,000 to £16,000,000 in the total of advances that may be made to the board for rural electrification and, as I said, the board will continue to draw on the Exchequer for its capital requirements for the rural electrification scheme.  The reason for that is that the rural electrification service will continue to be subsidised and it is, therefore, thought desirable that it should be financed exclusively by the State.  Aside from the fact that it would be inappropriate to seek money from private investors for a subsidised service, the continuation of the present arrangements is more convenient and simple from an administrative point of view.</P>
    <P>I mentioned in the Dáil that there were two developments in relation to rural electrification to which it was desirable to attract attention.  The first was that a change has been made in the method of determining the priority of areas selected for development under the scheme.  Up to the present the system was that the area which gave the board the best financial return got priority over other areas. While there was justification for that arrangement from the board's point of view it was often unfair to many rural areas where the financial return was not dependent upon the number of residents willing to take supply.  On the other hand there was objection to going completely on the basis of the number of the local residents willing to accept supply because in a very thinly populated area 100 per cent. acceptance might be possible whereas in a thickly populated area the more normal level of 60 per cent., 70 per cent. or 75 per cent. acceptance would be regarded as good.</P>
    <P>A formula has now been worked out which brings both factors into the calculation, the financial return from the area to the board and the percentage of local residents willing to accept supply and on that basis the order of priority is determined.  The <Col N="774" /> new system gives an added argument to those who are canvassing a rural area to get the scheme extended to it, pointing out that the larger the number of residents who accept supply the better are the prospects of early connection; at the same time it tends to weigh the selection in favour of the more densely populated areas as against the more sparsely populated.</P>
    <P>The second point I mentioned in that regard was that the rate of development under the electrification scheme has been speeded up considerably. Last year, following discussions with the board, they agreed to increase the rate of development by 50 per cent. and so organise themselves as to get a further 50 per cent. increase this year. Therefore, from this year on the rate of development under the rural electrification scheme will be double what it has been previously and that holds out the prospect of the whole scheme being completed in five years' time.  It also involves a very considerable increase in the number of people employed on rural electrification work which is not an unsatisfactory consequence either.</P>
    <P>Those are the main provisions of the Bill but there are some other minor provisions to which reference should be made We are excluding the board from the application of the Public Authorities Protection Act.  The Government is at present considering the possible amendment or perhaps even repeal of that Act but it has been decided that in so far as these statutory bodies are concerned that Act should not apply.  Provision in that regard was made some time ago and advantage has been taken of this Bill to provide for the exclusion of the board from the application of that Act, that is, an Act which limits the time in which actions for tort may be taken against public authorities.</P>
    <P>The second point I want to mention refers to the pension provisions for members of the E.S.B. itself.  I am not quite sure what considerations induced me when introducing that legislation in relation to superannuation for board members to provide that they should get the very awkward calculation of 20/48ths of retiring salary, but when that legislation was being framed it was assumed that 20 years' service <Col N="775" /> would be the normal in so far as men would go to the E.S.B. usually late in life and would not be able to give effective service longer than that period.  The whole-time members of the board have now over 20 years' service. Apart altogether from adopting the normal provisions in relation to superannuation arrangements, that alone would justify changing this 20/48ths to the more usual 50 per cent., 24/48ths.  I am taking advantage of this Bill to make that change which will provide that members of the board will receive half their salaries on retirement.  These are the main provisions of the Bill.  The Bill was, I am glad to say, received enthusiastically by all sections of the Dáil and I am sure that, having regard to its character, it will be received equally enthusiastically here.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>The last few remarks of the Minister puts one in the position in regard to this Bill at least that he expects one to follow the general trend.  After my experience on the last measure one is almost fearful in this House of saying anything that appears to be in any way questioning any line of national policy being pursued. In fact, you whisper to yourself: &ldquo;Have you the right to speak, or why did you come here or why were you sent here?&rdquo;  One must say for the Minister that he is more rational than some of the people who appear to follow his policy or to drive him along the road on a particular line.  He recognises that it is a good and healthy thing for the people, for the House and for the country, to make a rational examination of national policy in a big problem like this.  We are all agreed on the importance of electricity development.  Some are converts.  The Minister was converted to that point of view after I was.  I had the privilege of being a member of the other House when his predecessor in office introduced the original Bill.  The Leas-Chathaoirleach was a colleague of mine there.  I can recall some of my colleagues in the Farmers' Party in those days being very doubtful and critical and conservative about what this young and <Col N="776" /> enthusiastic Minister was going to put across the country, but I was just as enthusiastic as the Minister himself was about the development of power from the Shannon.</P>
      <P>We have marched a long way since those days.  The Minister can cast his mind back and think about what he thought about electricity development then.  It might be of interest to the Minister to know that I took home to my own home a German paper some years later, I think a year after the completion of the scheme.  That German paper&mdash;I think it was the <i>Berliner Tageblatt</i>&mdash;carried a balance sheet of the Siemens Schuckert Company, which revealed losses of a considerable amount on the work they carried out on the Shannon.  Our Irish engineers and supervisors watched the Germans so well that they made them do their job and apparently it did not pay the Germans too well to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That is past history and we are considering to-day the future of this immense undertaking.  Immense it is: one feels that it is almost greater than the State itself.  It is growing at such a pace and the capital commitments are so very large in relation to our total assets, our total income and our total productivity, that the E.S.B. to-day is just a colossus straddling the whole country.  It is a very great enterprise and the nation can be proud of it and proud of the contribution successive Ministers have made to its development.  I wonder whether the State and the people and especially the members of the Oireachtas should not now sit down and study the future of this organisation.  We have a great deal of the national capital invested in it.  There are demands for increased power in every field which can hardly be met out of our present resources. There will have to be further development. There is this truth, recognised by everybody, that the cost of electricity to-day in every field&mdash; whether industrial, agricultural or in domestic circles&mdash;is a very considerable drain on the national income.  The proportion which we have to pay away for the production and sale of this commodity, which is so valuable and attractive for all of us, is a rather heavy charge on the total expendable <Col N="777" /> income which is available to us.  We are going on and on.</P>
    <P>There is a great deal which is not known to the populace about this development.  We get the report of the E.S.B., we get periodic statements of policy from Ministers&mdash; this Minister, to a great extent&mdash;on future development; but whether what we are doing is the wisest policy in regard to the production of power for the future or not, is something about which I think some of us have certain doubts.  The nation has now reached the stage when it would be very wise for the Oireachtas to do something like setting up an all-Party committee to study the proposals, and the implications of those proposals, for the further development of electricity within the State.</P>
    <P>The Minister is telling us that this legislation for which he is asking our approval will enable him to put the securities of the E.S.B. on the market, a new type of security; but it is important to recognise that the value of a security, the security behind a security, is dependent not only on the production but on the cost of the production and the capacity to sell and the capacity of the purchasers to buy. The cost of electricity to-day in this State is relatively high, in relation to our income and in comparison with prices outside.  The cost is made up by the capital charge, the labour that goes into the work, the labour of producing the raw material, the labour on mechanical and electrical work that goes into the production of power from peat, and all of the other processes that have to be entered into in setting the machinery going, including the sale of the current and the collection of the payments by the E.S.B.  All these added up make a position here where, taking into account the cost of money and of the raw materials and so on, the charges are such that I at least am convinced that the future development of electricity in the country requires re-examination.</P>
    <P>When the first scheme came along, the Minister for Industry and Commerce in those days was only able to get it across with great difficulty, and only because he was able to produce <Col N="778" /> the evidence of foreign experts.  I do not know that we want foreign experts on this.  I am not against having them, it might be good to intersperse some foreign experts with people we know; but I would seriously suggest to the Minister that the cost of production of electricity in the future, with our resources being developed close to the point where we may have to look for new sources of power, into new fields that may make the whole undertaking much more economic than the kind of development that has been done up to the present, indicates that the time has come for a fresh survey.</P>
    <P>I have supported the Minister in his peat development schemes in this House.  I am prepared anywhere to state my view on that.  But when the Minister points out that his new development of four small hand-won turf stations on the western seaboard is being done mainly for social reasons&mdash; that was what he said and we accept it that that is so&mdash;it seems to me that we have reached the stage when we must contemplate whether we are justified in a capital development in regard to electricity that is going to consider social conditions, and be engaged for social reasons rather than because it is an accretion to the total development of electricity which is essential.  I know we could not have the power that we are utilising to-day but for the development of our peat bogs.  I want to suggest to the Minister&mdash;as I said on another occasion, when he had his Bill before this House&mdash;that, in my judgment anyhow, social conditions would be best served by another type of utilisation of our peat resources in these western areas and that that ought to be carefully studied before we engage in the utilisation of peat in a rather uneconomic way for the production of power.</P>
    <P>I seriously suggest to the Minister, with the fact behind me that I have enthusiastically approved of his endeavours for the development of our peat resources, that in the work that is being done elsewhere in the country, down in the bogs of Gowla, therein lies a medium upon which the social uplift of the people in the western seaboard can be much more effectively <Col N="779" /> brought about and in a way that will be much more lasting than what he is attempting at the moment.  It was that phrase of the Minister's that suggested to me that we have reached the stage in electricity development when the whole position should be studied anew.  Between the Minister and the E.S.B. and the people who are producing power there must be a great deal of discussion of which the public know nothing.  I am not charging the Minister or the E.S.B. or Bord na Móna with conspiring to take out of the pockets of the taxpayer or the consumer money that should be left in them but I am convinced that in regard to the whole national position we have reached a point when we should study the situation anew.  While we have established that we can produce power from native resources we ought not to close our minds to the fact that the cost of all this may be such that the consumers may not be prepared to continue to pay.</P>
    <P>The development in rural electrification is encouraging.  Many districts are making valiant efforts to avail of this service.  There are difficulties to be overcome.  I do not know that any of the methods adopted by the board have been complete.  Although there may be people in a district who are not prepared to sign a document asking for the service, they will be influenced to avail of the service when it is brought to the district and they see it in operation in their neighbours' homes.  I would have no hesitation in making whatever contribution can be made to extending the scheme throughout rural districts.  There has been a falling down in some areas.  In Cavan there are some districts in which efforts have been proceeding for two or three years.  If the board were not so exacting with regard to the number of possible subscribers before making the service available they would find that when the wires would be brought across a district everyone would want to avail of the service.</P>
    <P>That is all I have to say on the matter at this stage.  There is a number of matters that we can discuss on Committee Stage.  At the moment <Col N="780" /> we are glad to support the Minister in this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an extraordinary thing that whenever Senator Baxter speaks in this House he is almost always enthusiastically in favour of something or other but unwilling to do anything about it.  He told us early this afternoon that he was enthusiastically in favour of industry but objected strongly to the imposition of certain duties.  He has told us now that he is enthusiastically in favour of turf development but he thinks we should do nothing about it and should sit down and reconsider the whole matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>That is ridiculous.  I said nothing of the kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>He said no such thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>He said that before proceeding with the present scheme by means of turf&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Hand-won turf&mdash;that is all&mdash;hand-won turf&mdash;that is what I said.  I have it written down.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>That was not the impression I got.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will accept Senator Baxter's statement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very pleased to hear it.  I understood Senator Baxter to say what most of the members on that side of the House said on a previous Bill that came before us, the Turf Development Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I am prepared to accept the Minister's view of what I said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted to hear that Senator Baxter is, in fact, in favour of this because I remember, when the Turf Development Bill came up here, what a number of speakers said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>What did I say on that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no memory of what Senator Baxter said.  I remember Senator Hayes expressing the greatest doubt as to the possibility of producing electricity from milled peat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="781" />
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you quoting from what he said?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that Senator Hayes would deny for a moment that on the Turf Development Bill he expressed considerable doubt as to whether the milled peat process was sound.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator would come to the Bill before the House it would be just as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>What about my character?  I do not remember what I said about the Bill but I did not say that I had doubts as to the possibility of getting electricity from peat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>The possibility economically.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Ah well, now.  That is another question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Will Senator Yeats deal with the Bill before the House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator expressed doubts, in regard to the scheme as it stands at present, of producing electricity from milled peat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>If every single one of the Senators on the far side of the House who has ever spoken about turf were to say now that he is 100 per cent. in favour of it, we still have the position as to what happened when they were in power.  Actions speak a great deal louder than words.  However enthusiastic they were, however much they were in favour of the production of electricity from turf, in fact the position is that when those Senators or their Party were in power, between 1948 and 1951, not one single turf-generating station or hydro-electric station, in addition to the programme as it then existed, was sanctioned by that Government.  Instead of that, a most retrograde step was taken.  Even as long ago as before the war the Fianna Fáil Government of the day gave instructions to the E.S.B. that all future electricity development was to be done out of Irish fuel resources, <Col N="782" /> by means of hydro-electric schemes or turf schemes.  That instruction was given.  Yet the position was that the only two additional generating stations sanctioned in the three and a half years from 1948 to 1951 were two big stations, one in the City of Cork and the other in the City of Dublin, designed to use imported coal or imported fuel oil.  I do not care what Senator Baxter, Senator Hayes or any other Senator said either to-day or any other day, the fact remains that was the position when their Party were in power.  I have always felt that it was a most unfortunate and most retrograde step that those two big stations in Dublin and Cork should have been sanctioned.</P>
      <P>The Minister has told us to-day that, when the present programme has been completed, 63 per cent. of all our electricity supplies will be generated from Irish fuel resources.  That is undoubtedly a satisfactory figure.  It could have been so much better; it could have been, possibly, 75 per cent. or even higher, if the Government that was in power between 1948 and 1951 had stuck to the previous decision, had in fact acted upon their apparent enthusiasm for Irish turf development and had gone ahead with the turf development schemes instead of going back to the system of producing electricity from coal or fuel oil.</P>
      <P>Be that as it may, I should like to congratulate the Minister on bringing in this Bill to-day.  It is a very great thing for the country that all this development should be taking place, a great deal of it taking place in parts of the country where very little development of an employment-giving nature has been carried out.  It will be a very great thing for very many remote areas.  It will produce electricity which is very badly wanted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are one or two points which Senator Baxter, in his enthusiasm, mentioned, and that I think it is desirable to deny.  He suggested that electricity is very dear in this country.  I have no idea what it costs in other countries, but the increase since before the war has been in the region of 40 or 55 per cent. as against a general increase <Col N="783" /> in prices of about 100 per cent. Bearing in mind the fall in the value of money, it would therefore appear that electricity is somewhat cheaper now than it was before the war.</P>
    <P>Here, again, I may have misunderstood Senator Baxter but I took him to be worried as to whether perhaps this form of electricity development was liable to be more expensive than other forms.  I think it should be made clear that there is every prospect that the cost per unit of producing electricity from milled peat will be cheaper than any other form of production. Certainly, the schemes so far in operation for producing electricity from sod turf have been extremely successful from the point of view of the cost per unit.  With regard to the hand-won turf, Senator Baxter suggested that perhaps it was undesirable to bring in schemes of this kind for largely social reasons.  There might be a difference of opinion on that matter.  The areas where it will be in operation are very badly in need of&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I think General Costelloe's scheme for Gowla bog would be better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>It could not be applied to the particular area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Yeats, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>The areas where these stations will be located are quite different from those served in the general scheme.  The point I want to make is that the total production of electricity from these small stations will be minute in quantity compared with the production under this programme. I have not gone into the figures, but I understand that it will be a small fraction of 1 per cent. of the total production.  It can have no possible effect on the price of electricity. These are very small stations, producing very small quantities of electricity compared with the total amount required.  Senator Baxter need have no fears that these schemes will have an ill effect on the general price level of our electricity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="784" />
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Undoubtedly, this is the most important industry in our country. Ours is a small country and the E.S.B. will have, when this new Bill becomes an Act, permission to raise their capital to £100,000,000.  It is an enormous sum of money and whether this business is well run or badly run will affect, in large measure, the future living standards of all our people.</P>
      <P>I think Senator Baxter is quite right in asking that there should be a permanent parliamentary committee of both Houses of the Oireachtas to stand over a semi-State undertaking of this enormous magnitude.  I also think he is right in asking for the fullest information that can possibly be received with regard to the efficient management of the company and, further, I think he is right in inquiring whether the various projects to be embarked upon are sound from the economic point of view.</P>
      <P>I should like to know&mdash;and these figures have not been given to us by the board&mdash;how the present cost of electricity for industrial purposes compares with the present cost of electricity supplied to industries in other countries in Western Europe.  Obviously, if we are to have a decent standard of living here we must be able to export&mdash;and cheap power is very important to business.  Cheap power is a very important item in every industry and we should have information on that matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the question whether we should generate our electricity from turf or from imported fuel, I think that is a matter in regard to which the various pros and cons have to be balanced. I remember that, when the national paper mills were being established in this country, it was the intention to build the mill on a bog so that they might use the turf.  The position that was presented to the people about to develop that project was that the turf in any bog on which they would build the mill would be all used up in 25 years and that, by that time, they would have built around the mill a town with a population of anything maybe from 5,000 to 8,000 people. When the local turf resources for the purposes of that industry would have been exhausted, they would have found <Col N="785" /> themselves with, if you like, a white elephant of a town.  It was then decided that it would be better to erect the mill on another site.  I want to know if there is an analogy there in regard to the development of electricity in the same way.  Would we use all the turf in the bogs and then have to move the power stations to other sites?  I realise that electrical power generating plant wears out and it is possible that the plant would be worn out by the time the bog is cleared.  Maybe a middle-of-the-road policy might be better&mdash;to use a considerable amount of fuel oil during peace-time, when the cost of transport is low and the commodity can be bought at a cheap price. Then, when world conditions change and uncertainty takes the place of peace, we could use a considerable amount of our peat resources.  I believe we would be driven into that position ultimately.</P>
    <P>I should hate to think that we should be wedded to one particular Party because we are for turf and that we should be wedded to another political Party because we are against turf. That would not be looking at this very large and national problem in a straightforward way.</P>
    <P>I should also like some information from the Minister on the state of development in this country of the gas turbine.  The E.S.B. in the North of Scotland got that famous engineering firm in the Clyde Bank, John Brown and Company, to manufacture gas turbines.  I understand that, for about half the cost, they would give a greater output of electricity than steam turbine generation.  If we could generate 50 per cent. more electricity with the same amount of peat, naturally our peat bogs would last very much longer and the cost of production of our electricity would be very considerably reduced.</P>
    <P>Another matter recently suggested is the development of a chemical industry based upon cheap electricity generated in isolated parts of the country where it would not be necessary to distribute this electricity over long distances, because the cost of our overhead distribution system and of supplies at long distances is a very heavy problem.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="786" /> I will end this speech on the same note as I started by saying that this is such a large and important problem for the future of all of us that there should be a parliamentary committee of both Houses of the Oireachtas to supervise the legislation, examine the annual reports and go into the matter in a businesslike way.  I believe that they would be able to help whatever Minister would, from time to time, be charged with the introduction of legislation to deal with this problem. They would act as a supervisory body to see that we were given service efficiently and that the national economic interest was being safeguarded.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to be among those who heartily congratulate the Minister and all concerned with the introduction of this scheme.  I feel that nothing in our time has been more valuable to our general economy than the rapid development of a national electricity scheme.  At the same time it is well to point out, as the Minister did, in his remarks here to-day, that this highly efficient board has two privileges&mdash;well, I will not say privileges&mdash;but it enjoys two fundamental things.  The Minister stressed that the board is permitted to use its reserve funds for the &ldquo;adequate provision of the replacement of wasting assets.&rdquo;  The Minister by stating that pins his faith to the necessity for that and I heartily agree with him, and so does every other businessman in the country, but general business is not permitted to make that wise provision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Look at the tariffs they have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish Senator Baxter would keep his mouth shut when another Senator is speaking.  I do not resent criticism but I would like it to be informed and constructive. That is all I ask of Senator Baxter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Another thing the E.S.B. is permitted to do is to fix its charges, and here again there is a big principle involved. It leads me to say this, that when there is a board of this kind with a capital now to be increased to <Col N="787" /> £100,000,000&mdash;that board will be there and the scheme will be there when this Government and all of us here are no longer on this earth&mdash;it is necessary that the State itself, represented by the elected representatives of the people, shall have some control over the policy of a board of that magnitude. Even the fixing of charges is something that should not be left entirely to this board.  It is competing here in the City of Dublin for instance with the publicly owned Gas Company which cannot raise its charges at all or increase its dividend without having to go through a very tedious process with a Department of State.  This is fair criticism.  In general, all of us are proud of the E.S.B. and what has been done to date.  We are all delighted to see its extension into the remotest parts of the country and it is up to the people for whom this service is being provided to make it possible to give them speedier and cheaper services by coming wholeheartedly in and availing themselves of the scheme.</P>
    <P>But the scheme has done a lot of good things that have not been mentioned in the short debate we have had to-day.  Among these things, it has given very badly needed outlets&mdash;as Senator Hayes and others involved in university education will know&mdash;for many young university graduates who without some scheme like this would have to emigrate and give their services to other countries.  Is it not amazing that we now have a permanent market for 3,000,000 tons of native turf?  God was good to us when he gave us our turf banks. Because of them we are now in the position that through this one industry alone 3,000,000 tons of turf will now be necessary to feed electricity generating stations in this country.</P>
    <P>I do not think that this Bill calls for any long or detailed speeches.  I am delighted to hear that it was received by the other House with enthusiasm and left it in that atmosphere. I would like to feel that it would get the same treatment here and that we all wish God-speed to the board.  The little criticisms that I made <Col N="788" /> were intended to be helpful, when I said that its power to make provision for wasting assets should be extended to industry generally and should not be confined to this mammoth, the E.S.B.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to join with Senator Summerfield and other Senators in welcoming the Bill. It is the first evidence that I have seen on the part of a Government of willingness to hand back to private enterprise a successful public utility.  I have neither seen nor known of any similar enterprise where such a proposition has been advanced in connection with its future development.  I think it is advisable, and I think it is a worthy thing, that where under certain circumstances certain types of industries had to be established under Government auspices they should when they come to a particular stage of fruition, revert to private ownership. It does mean, of course, the issuing of shares in a public utility, and one question that does arise is: what was the reason for the change in the method of financing?  The Minister told us what it was proposed to do, but he did not tell us why it was necessary to do it.  Some years ago when industrialists complained about the price of power it was found on investigation that the E.S.B. was paying interest at the rate of 5½ per cent. on moneys lent to it from the Central Fund.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Money at that time was lendable generally through the banks at 5 per cent. but the E.S.B. was paying ½ per cent. extra.  I would like to know at what rate the E.S.B. has been paying in recent years and if, as a result of this new method of finance, in its future extension it will be able to sell power at cheaper rates.  It is absolutely imperative for the Minister as Minister for Industry and Commerce to see that power, above all things, would be sold at a very low rate if we are to develop our export trade.  There is very little that industrialists can do about this because industry has no control itself over certain fundamental costs such as the cost of power.  Even money costs are <Col N="789" /> going to imperil the development of the export trade.</P>
    <P>We should be very careful to see what is proposed to be done.  It is proposed that £25,000,000 would be the extent of the new issue.  Could not the Government itself, through some new method of finance, issue guarantees to the public without having to go through the ordinary channels to finance an undertaking of this nature? Why should the public be asked to subscribe now to an issue which will, presumably, be a trustee stock and which will, presumably, be issued at 4½ per cent., because I cannot see any other reason for the change?  Why should the public be asked to provide finance at 4½ per cent. while the banks and other organisations are financing industry at 6 per cent.?  I wonder would the Minister tell us what is the reason and the justification of the reason.  I am not opposed at all to the change.  I am just asking what the change-over is for.  What is the purpose of it?  In what way did the lending facilities of the Central Fund prove inadequate or in what way did they prove too expensive?  Remember, I am not at all critical in any way of that development.  I appreciate, as does&mdash;I am sure&mdash;every other member of the House what has been done and I congratulate the board and the Minister, and his predecessors, and all who contributed to the great national development of electricity here.  But I am rather worried about this new method of finance.  If it is a matter of transferring charges from Billy to Jack at public expense, then I am not in favour of it, if that is the only reason for it.</P>
    <P>While we appreciate the necessity for developing power from bog sources, I wonder will the Minister tell us something about the life of our bog resources.  I understand that persons associated with Bord na Móna and with the production of turf in this country assess the life of an average bog at 25 years, that at that point you come down to clay foundations.  I am quite sure that a survey has been made of bog resources here and I wonder will the Minister tell us how long he can count on bog supplies and whether <Col N="790" /> there was not some point in the argument made by some Senators that during times of peace it might be wise to import fuel oil and, taking the long view, preserve our bog supplies for times of crisis.</P>
    <P>Will the Minister give us the comparative cost of production between electricity produced from bog sources and electricity produced from water sources and oil sources?  It would be interesting to hear these comparative costs.  While bog development has given great employment and workers have been getting a lot of work, I should like to know what extraordinary benefit has been created by electricity supplied from our turf resources.</P>
    <P>Will the Minister tell us why reserves were used by the E.S.B. to offset the wasting assets?  I understand that the E.S.B. also has profits.  What did happen to the profits?  Were the profits all expressed in terms of reserves?  Will he tell us what percentage of capital investment has been paid off over the years, what percentage of profit the E.S.B. has been making and whether the increased charges are in his opinion a national advantage?  It is assumed that as a result of the new method of assessment the E.S.B. will have a higher income.  Senator Yeats wags his head.  I have to be very careful because I have learned my lesson from hearing the Minister so often.  I assume that what I say is correct in this case. If it is not correct, it can be answered in the negative.  I should like to know what happend to the E.S.B.'s profits, if they have been handed back to the State or spent in the repayment of interest charges.</P>
    <P>I do not agree with the statement made by Senator Baxter, supported by Senator Burke, as to the necessity for an overriding committee to control the E.S.B., any more than there should be an overriding committee to control any other industry in this country.  We are hemmed in with all sorts of dictatorial powers of one sort or another whereby any company which is not efficient goes through a sort of crucible either in the Fair Trade Commission or the Prices Tribunal or the Department of Industry and Commerce, so that there should not be any necessity for an overriding committee to control the powers of the <Col N="791" /> E.S.B.  The Minister, I am sure, has sufficient power already to control the E.S.B.</P>
    <P>Taking the long view, I am wondering if the Minister has given any thought to atomic and solar energy developments and what reactions they may have on the development proposed in this Bill.  We already have evidence from two recent explosions with hydrogen bombs that new forms of energy are being created every day and that, in fact, forms of energy are now being created which are probably getting out of control.  In the course of time, it is possible that our scientists here may discover some method of adapting the present methods of atomic energy for the purpose of creating power and light.  That is not a fairy tale, it is quite an ordinary possibility of commerce that power and light may come to this country inside ten years in forms of atomic or solar energy.</P>
    <P>Finally, I would ask the Minister my crucial question: why is there this change in the method of financing; what is the necessity for it?  I should like to ask him if it will have any effect on costs, as this will affect power charges mostly, and what reaction it will have on the goods made.  Anything I have said has not been said in any carping spirit.  It is only a case of inquiring, because I appreciate the great work being done by the E.S.B. in the development of electricity in this country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to join with the various Senators who have expressed the feeling that they would like to congratulate the Minister.  Personally, I feel that throwing any bouquets at the Minister would be like carting turf to Curraun or some place like that.  The record of the Minister as far as the turf industry or the E.S.B. or any other industry is concerned is well known.  The only thing I am amazed at is the ignorance of certain Senators who have spoken as far as the turf industry is concerned. Notwithstanding all the speeches which have been made, all the articles and all, the books which have been published on one thing or another, there are still people who apparently do not know the <Col N="792" /> first thing about one of the most important industries in the country.</P>
      <P>I was amazed to hear Senator Burke, for instance, talking about the turf industry and pretending he knew something about it.  He talked about how important it was that all the pros and cons should, be carefully examined before we would embark on any extensive scheme as far as turf development is concerned.  He went on to say that it was serious to realise in connection with the production of milled turf that 5,000 or 8,000 people might be collected around a certain area and that the mill might close down in 25 years, which he understood was the life of a bog.  It is a terrible state of affairs to think that anybody who has any interest in the turf industry or any other industry in this country would not know that the production of milled turf has nothing whatever to do with mills; and that the term &ldquo;milled turf&rdquo; means turf harvested in a particular way and that the fact that it is harvested in this way makes it suitable for use in the development of electricity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It would be much better, before some of these people go to the country and make speeches criticising the turf industry, that they should read something about it and be in a position to talk sensibly and not talk about the white elephant that will be left after the bog has been used for 25 years. Some of those in what we might call the Opposition in a non-political House said that the life of a bog is 25 years.  If the life of a bog depended upon the activities of a Coalition Government or a Fine Gael Government, it would be 25,000,000 years, because they would not have done anything. Every time the question of the development of bogs arose, whether it was a question of drainage or of building roads into bogs in order to develop the turf industry, or whether it was a question of hand-won turf or milled turf or machine-won turf or briquettes, it was opposed tooth and nail by the people who formed the Coalition Government in the past.  They come along to-day, and while they do not want to admit that they were wrong over the years they want to warn the possible Government&mdash;knowing very well that it will be a Fianna Fáil Government <Col N="793" /> and that the present Minister will be still in charge of turf development in this country after the general election&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>You are an optimist.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>It is better to build castles in the air than dungeons in the air as you have been building all your life anyhow.  They want to warn us of the dangers of this thing, and the dangers of the position that there will be when the turf is cut away.  Surely anybody in his sane senses knows that the life of a bog depends on the number of machines working on it or the number of people working on it as individuals.  If, as I said before, the policy of the other party were to be put in operation the question of the life of the bog would not arise.</P>
      <P>Senator Burke with an air of super-intelligence suggested that we should purchase a lot of fuel oil.  I wonder does anybody on the other side of the House know the amount of fuel oil which would be necessary to take the place of the turf now being produced. I say, by all means, purchase and store all the fuel oil that can possibly be purchased and stored, not to take the place of turf but to ensure that the machines run by fuel oil for the production of turf would be able to continue in action over a possible period of war or emergency in this country.</P>
      <P>I believe that the question of experimental work on turf is only in its initial stages, and I believe that anybody in his sane senses will now realise, regardless of what he said in the past&mdash;we heard people saying that they would not be found in a bog hole, and that we were throwing the people's money into the bogs&mdash;that they made a mistake.  They should realise that they were wrong.  It takes a good fellow to admit that he was wrong.  Admit that you were wrong over the years, that a good job was done in the development of turf and that you are prepared now to row in with the people who knew all the time that turf was one of the most important industries of this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I believe that experimental work on turf is only in its infancy.  If we are <Col N="794" /> going to ensure the safety of this country in the event of an emergency or the outbreak of another world war we will have to get down to the stage where we will be able to ensure eventually that even a considerable amount of our transport which has not been used before under the power of turf will be adapted to use either by vehicles used directly by turf fuel or by electricity developed as a result of the development of the bogs of this country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanRuane" hpid="Mr. S.T. Ruane Mr. S.T. Ruane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S.T. Ruane</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I am quite correct in stating that any Bill or measure introduced here that has for its objective or design to extend or develop the hydro-electric scheme of this country will meet with a very sympathetic and helpful hearing.  That is as it should be, for no other State-sponsored scheme, as has been pointed out by many speakers, has been so successfully administered or brought so many benefits to the people of this country as the Shannon hydro-electric scheme has.  The benefits are many and far flung, and they have been responsible for converting those who in the initial stages were very obstructively critical of the efforts made and the idea of having hydro-electric power developed in this country from the most pessimistic to the most enthusiastic about the extension of the benefits at the present time.  The greatest credit is due to the administrative staffs and to the technicians employed in extending the benefits of this scheme to the country; and that credit goes out also to those engaged on the actual labour, for I know no body of public workers in this country that works so regularly and so hard as those engaged in extending rural electrification to the remote districts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If I have any criticism to offer to this Bill it is due to the vast amount of money that is being borrowed, but of course it is necessary to bring about the developments that the Bill is designed to achieve.  That money, of course, has to be borrowed at a high rate of interest.  It has been represented in many quarters that the profits earned by this service are largely going to the paying off of <Col N="795" /> interest and that something should be done with those profits to reduce the capital debt.  I am not going to go into that.  I certainly welcome this Bill, and I trust that the areas so far deprived of the many benefits that rural electrification can bring about will soon have the benefits which the Bill is designed to give.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Having heard the remarks of the opening speaker on the Opposition Benches, Senator Baxter, one would be inclined to believe that many of us were opposed to the development of electricity supply, particularly because of a reference to the development of the Shannon scheme. If Senator Baxter or his colleagues wish to take us back to those days in which proposals were placed before this and the other House in relation to the establishment of what was then known as the Shannon Scheme Development Electricity Board, we perhaps could convince him now that the proposals contained in that Bill would not be accepted by those people but would be accepted by us now as being persons who were in a position to give very responsible advice on a proposition and a suggestion of that kind. When Senator Baxter and those others associated with him suggest that the development of this country started with the inauguration of the Shannon development scheme, one must examine these proposals in relation to the difficulties in which they now present themselves.  Senator Baxter is a member and a representative of the farming community in this House, and as such he would like to present himself, and I am sure that when he examines the difficulties that have been created by the inauguration of this particular scheme and the impediments it has created in the further development of arterial drainage development of the country he will not be as enthusiastic as he might have been otherwise in putting forward the Shannon development scheme as the first.  I will admit that it was the first, and the only scheme that was put forward by the then Cumann na nGaedheal Party; but it was then put forward against the advice of the most <Col N="796" /> learned and the people who have given the most thought to the difficulties that it might have created; and if statements were made at that time that this scheme was not one that should have been accepted by the people, I think Senator Baxter and those people associated with him will agree with me now that if that scheme was put forward as a serious scheme to-day it would not be accepted either in this or in any other House of an Irish Parliament.</P>
      <P>Be that as it may, it is there now and there is very little we can do about it.  It has created very serious difficulties not alone for the further development of electricity in this country but also for the great national scheme of arterial drainage.  It has created difficulties in another very important sphere of national development &mdash;our sea fisheries development.  I think that these are two facts which, if presented to any Irish Parliament as they should be, would prevent that Parliament from accepting the proposals that were put forward by the then Minister for Industry and Commerce in connection with the development of the Shannon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have seen that it has been necessary in order to supply all the demands that have been made over a number of years for power and light, to undertake a number of other schemes.  One of the reasons that I have intervened in this debate is to tell the Minister that we in Galway, particularly in Connemara, appreciate very much the decision that has been arrived at to erect a generating station in that area.  We have heard a considerable amount from every Party in the State as to what should, and should not, be done in the Gaeltacht. In the Connemara area we have very little to offer except a very vast amount of bog.  I think that even members of the Opposition will agree with me that it is about time we brought before the people the possibility of the development of this area. So far back as 1932, we caused to be passed through the Oireachtas a Bill known as the Turf Development Bill in which facilities were provided to assist our people to develop the <Col N="797" /> resources at their disposal.  Here we have something even more important to our people.  As I stated, although we have very limited natural resources in Connemara there is a vast area of bog there.  There is no other source of employment, apart from the seasonal employment derived from tourists who come to see the scenery with which God has blessed us.</P>
    <P>Employment must be found by the development of the resources that are there&mdash;the development of the bogs. Here we have a proposal to utilise these resources in providing power and light.  In providing that power and light we are doing something more.  We are providing an incentive to people to come in and build factories and to do the things that hitherto have been done in Dublin and elsewhere.  I hold that that is one of the biggest possibilities held out by this Bill.</P>
    <P>I think it was my friend, Senator O'Donnell, who also comes from Galway, who asked the question why we are now placing, as it were, the resources of the E.S.B. on the market, why we are asking people who have money to come forward and invest their capital in the development of something that means much more than any Act we could pass here because that, in the last analysis, is what it does mean.  Hitherto, since the E.S.B. was first established, the Government provided all the funds necessary for the development of the various schemes undertaken by the board, but an effort is now being made to induce our people to provide the capital necessary for further development in rural Ireland.  The sum involved is, no doubt, big; that is a matter that can be debated further when the Estimate comes before this or the other House, but it is very necessary that it should be made available because it is proposed to give to the people of rural Ireland, at least, some of the facilities hitherto enjoyed by their sisters in the towns.  I say &ldquo;sisters&rdquo; because it is the womenfolk mainly who have had to endure the day-to-day drudgery of household work in rural Ireland.  It is hoped that the facilities provided under this Bill will considerably lessen that drudgery.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="798" /> I think it was Senator Baxter who asked why the same thing could not be done in Connemara as has been done in Gowla bog.  I have known Senator Baxter for quite a number of years.  I first met him when he was leader of the Farmers' Party, more years ago than I should like to recall now.  I always like to associate Senator Baxter at least with a little bit of common sense, but when he tries to equate the conditions in Gowla bog, with which Senator O'Donnell has more intimate associations than I have, with those of Connemara, Senator Baxter shows that he knows very little about the particular proposition of which he speaks, to say the least of it.  I should like to pay tribute to the manager of the Irish Sugar Company, General Costello, for the enthusiasm, direction and energy which he has displayed in taking over the Gowla bog.</P>
    <P>There is no Gowla bog area in West Connemara and there is nothing we can offer to these people except what we have offered&mdash;the development of the handown turf scheme and the tomato and these other schemes.  There is nothing else we can do for these people, except migrate them to the richer lands of Meath and these lands are not there available for them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Baxter said he had some grave doubts about the policy being pursued in this matter of electricity development and urged that an all-Party committee should be established to review the position in a fundamental way.  Personally, I do not think that would do any good.  We are committed now to a ten-year programme which is based upon the policy of utilising native resources exclusively. The only problem that faces the technicians of the E.S.B. at present is how best to complete that programme in the least expensive and most efficient way.  I do not think there is anything to be gained by diverting their minds to the consideration of the economics of utilising fuel oil, coal or any other alternative fuel.  In my experience it was necessary to make it clear to the board that there was no alternative to working on native resources in order to get them down to the tasks of solving the technical problems associated with the implementation of that policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="799" /> Senator Burke said we should inquire as to the cost of industrial power in other countries as compared with this country.  I am sure that somebody can give him that information but why should we seek it?  What happens if we find, as we probably would find, that the Swiss and the Swedes have electricity much cheaper than we have it?  Do we then call the whole thing off?  I do not understand that mentality.  We have resources here such as they are.  We have men with the technical knowledge capable of making the best use of the resources we have and that is as much as we can do&mdash;make the best use of these resources&mdash;and that is the policy we are going to pursue and we do not want an all-Party committee to complicate it.</P>
    <P>Senator Baxter need not be so perturbed about the cost of electricity produced here or the possibility of consumers not wishing to take electricity at that cost.  On that point, I may say that the trouble has been that consumers wanted more electricity than the E.S.B. were able to supply and in fact the whole programme of the board had to be sharply stepped up to ensure that they would always be one step ahead of the growth in demand and I think we are still a long way from the date upon which the E.S.B. will be sending out its commercial travellers to sell electricity and to cultivate the market which is undoubtedly there, because, as I have already pointed out, the consumption of electricity per head of population in this country is one of the lowest in Europe.</P>
    <P>So far as costs are concerned, Senator Yeats did less than justice to the E.S.B.  He said that current costs only 50 per cent. more than it was before the war.  The average price in pence secured per unit sold in 1953 was only 28 per cent. higher than it was in 1939 and it may solve all problems for Senator Baxter if I tell him that in 1953 the E.S.B. sold current at a lower price per unit than that at which they sold it in 1930, 1931 or 1932.</P>
    <P>I tell Senator Summerfield straight <Col N="800" /> away that the E.S.B. pays income-tax on exactly the same basis as a private producer and the accumulation of reserve funds for depreciation of wasting assets is not a tax provision.  It is a statutory obligation which the board have to fulfil for the benefit of future generations of Irishmen.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Donnell is completely wrong when he describes the Bill as a device for handing over the E.S.B. to private enterprise.  I tried to make it quite clear that the sale of securities by the E.S.B. will not carry with it any power of controlling the undertaking. The whole undertaking will still be controlled by the board, the members of which will be appointed by the Government and private enterprise will have nothing whatever to do with the administration of the undertaking. Private citizens will be given an opportunity of investing in E.S.B. stocks and the inducement to them to invest will be the security they are offered and the rate of interest attaching to it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>They are getting their foot inside the door.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>No, not even a finger, so far as control is concerned.  It is just as well that that should be quite clear.  There is nothing in the Bill which involves any alteration in the system of control and if Senator O'Donnell buys up the whole first £25,000,000 issue of stock, he will have no more right to go into the head offices of the E.S.B. than he has at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Why are we giving the E.S.B. this power of going to the market for their capital needs?  There are a number of reasons.  It is the normal method of financing national development projects of that kind in other countries. In this country, we could not resort to the normal method because of the lack of an investment tradition amongst our people.  We have succeeded in building up some sort of investment tradition now and we think it is possible now to do what would have been the normal thing earlier and let the E.S.B. go to the capital market for money as they require it.  It is possible, and I think probable that they will be able <Col N="801" /> to raise money through the issue of their own stocks at a slightly lower rate than they obtain it at present from the Exchequer.  The Exchequer charges the E.S.B. administration expenses and I think up to the present has made a slight profit on the reissuing to the E.S.B. of money which it has borrowed from the public.</P>
    <P>Furthermore, the State's obligation in respect of national development, the very big investment programme on which we are embarking, is creating undoubted problems.  Every year, the State has to go to the public for a national loan and is not always able to get, through such loans, the amount it requires for the national development programme in which it is engaging. Not all the money available for investment can be attracted into Government stocks and we think there will be an addition to the total investment in national development, if the State is released from the obligation of financing the E.S.B. and the board is allowed to go to the capital market in its own way; in other words, we think there are investors who will invest in an E.S.B. issue who will not be attracted by a Government issue.  Logic does not always apply in these matters, and, even on a logical basis, there would be a reason to expect that result.</P>
    <P>We have not had an actuarial survey of the life of a bog, but we have an engineering survey which we thought would be more appropriate. The life of a bog depends on three factors&mdash;the area of the bog, its depth and the rate at which you exploit it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>That has already been stated by somebody, but that is not what people have in mind when they talk about the life of a bog.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Most bogs have been there for 2,000,000 years and probably, as Senator Quirke said, will probably be there for another 2,000,000 years, unless somebody does something about it.  What the Senator has in mind is the number of years for which, at the present rate of development, these bogs will provide fuel before being worked out.  In the case of the bogs <Col N="802" /> now being developed in relation to power stations, for the provision of power for these stations, the aim is to keep the bog in immediate production of fuel so long as the station will last without replacement, which is roughly 20 to 25 years.  There is a whole lot of other bogs not being worked at the moment at all.  I am quite sure that by the end of 20 or 25 years the research department of Bord na Móna will have devised a technique for exploiting the resurces of blanket, mountain and other bogs which cannot be worked by their present methods and which represent the largest area of bog in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The tea interval is at 6 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I have only two other matters to refer to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we should let the Minister finish.  I should like to hear something about the use of atomic energy for power purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The board does not make a profit.  It is barred by statute. Its obligation in law is to so frame its charges that its income in any year will equate to its outgoings in regard to administration, capital liability and reserve appropriations.  Some years they had a surplus on revenue account and in other years a deficit, but by and large there is no profit.  If the board has a surplus in any year it appropriates that surplus to the various reserve funds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>So far as the development of atomic energy for power purposes is concerned that is obviously a technical problem.  The British Electricity Authority is establishing a station in the North of Scotland to utilise atomic energy.  That is being watched with interest.  The indications are that it is not the most economic method of developing power at present.  I am quite certain that technical improvements will result and that it would be advisable for us to contemplate the utilisation of atomic energy for power purposes at some time in the future. We are dealing now only with the ten-year programme that will keep the <Col N="803" /> E.S.B. in the position to meet the electricity needs of this country up to 1961.  As I pointed out when bringing the Bill to the Dáil, long before 1961 the next ten-year programme will have to be considered and the necessary plans made for it.</P>
    <P>I should not like to be taken as agreeing with all that Senator Hawkins said so far as the Shannon scheme is concerned, particularly when I am bringing in a Bill which proposes to develop a number of other rivers for power purposes in a way which we hope will avoid all the drainage and other problems which result from efforts to harness water power.</P>
    <P>We recently brought into production the Erne scheme which is slightly bigger than the Shannon scheme in actual output capacity.  It involved more political problems than those which arose in connection with the Shannon scheme.  We are working on the Lee River scheme, and other rivers are capable of being developed for power purposes.  From the point of view of the unit cost of production water-power is the cheapest source available to us.  Once the capital expenditure on a hydro-power station is completed there is very little further expenditure.  The day-to-day operation charges are negligible.  The Shannon scheme is operated with a very small staff.</P>
    <P>There are very considerable advantages in getting power from turf stations even if, while the capital costs are lower, the operational costs are higher.  It means employment for thousands of people.  New stations are being erected in Mayo and the total investment, making allowance for the changes in the value of money, will be less than in the Shannon scheme, but the total output will be greater than from the Shannon scheme.  Immense benefits are conferred on the whole area in the form of permanent employment for many hundreds of workers.</P>
    <P>It is not necessary to make a contrast with one form of development as against another.  Both are necessary. There is no form of development <Col N="804" /> which is better to associate with waterpower development than turf development. When you have plenty of water you have difficulty in getting turf in a wet year, but in a dry year the turf should be easy to win.  There is a natural association between one type of development and another and that is an argument I have been using in favour of turf all the time.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the next stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Not now.  Let us take it next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A Senator A Senator">
      <NameTxt>A Senator</NameTxt>
      <P>Budget week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>We could, if Senators wish to be present on that occasion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I would prefer the following week myself, if it was not inconvenient for the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The following week is not likely to be convenient.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not wish to hamper the Minister but I think the Bill should pass through all its stages before the present Seanad concludes its career.  Certainly we should fix a date for the Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Wednesday after Easter would suit me.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage fixed for Wednesday, 21st April, 1954.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Business suspended at 6.10 p.m. until 7.15 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Housing (Amendment) Bill," RHead="1954&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Housing (Amendment) Bill, 1954&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Minister for Local Government (Mr. Smith) Patrick Smith">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government (Mr. Smith)</NameTxt>
      <P>The general purposes of this Bill are to continue and extend the policy of encouraging the provision of new dwellings and the reconditioning of existing dwellings by private individuals and public utility societies, with the assistance of State grants and, where appropriate, supplementary grants from the housing authorities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="805" /> Section 6 proposes that grants for the erection, purchase and reconstruction of houses and the installation of sanitary services be continued at the present rates for a further two years.</P>
    <P>The grants under the 1952 Act terminated on the 1st April but, in order to avoid a break in building operations, it has been arranged to continue the payment of grants in anticipation of the authority sought in the Bill.  The Seanad is aware from published statistics that there is at present a satisfactory level of housing activity by private enterprise.  The combined total of new house and reconstruction grants allocated in the 11 months of 1953-1954 to 28th February last is higher than the total in any complete year since the war.  There are indications that this trend will be at least maintained in the coming 12 months.</P>
    <P>The Bill aims to widen the scope of the reconstruction grant provisions of the Housing Acts.  It is proposed in Section 14 that even if a previous grant was made for erection or reconstruction of a house, a further grant will be available after 15 years for the carrying out of any approved scheme of reconstruction, whether or not the work includes the provision of a new roof or that additional accommodation provided is essential for the relief of overcrowding.</P>
    <P>At present, a grant is available ten years after payment of a previous grant where a thatch roof is replaced by slates or tiles.  Section 14 would make this grant available for the replacement by tiles or slates of any type of roofing. Under this section, also, the occupier of a house which had been damaged by storm, flood, fire or other causes outside his control would be eligible for a grant towards re-building it without reference to the period since a previous grant was made.</P>
    <P>Section 12 is an important new provision. Reconstruction grants are already available to farmers of up to £50 valuation and agricultural labourers in rural areas reconstructing houses in their own occupation. Members of the working classes and agricultural labourers in urban areas whose valuation does not exceed £12 are eligible for grants for the reconstruction <Col N="806" /> of houses in their own occupation. A grant of £80 is also available in urban and rural areas to persons having control of unfit houses who repair them by direction of the housing authority.  All the foregoing grants may be supplemented by grants from the housing authority.</P>
    <P>No grants are at present available in urban areas to occupiers over £12 valuation or to landlords, unless the houses are unfit for human habitation and repairs specified in a notice served by the housing authority under Section 19 of the 1931 Act have been carried out.</P>
    <P>The Housing Acts require unfit housing conditions to be eradicated.  The process is so costly both on private and public account, that it is a matter of national importance to prevent as many houses as possible from becoming unfit. It is also important to discourage haphazard tenementing which quickly adds to the liabilities of the local authorities for the relief of overcrowded and insanitary conditions.  In the case of single family houses the state of repair may be reasonably good, but the houses may lack amenities with the result that the owners or occupiers are not inclined to maintain them.  The improvement of such houses would be a desirable contribution to better housing standards.</P>
    <P>It is proposed in Section 12, therefore, that a grant from State funds not exceeding £80 per dwelling, or one-third of the cost of the works (excluding decoration) whichever is the smaller should be payable to the person executing repair or improvement works whether or not he is the occupier.  The grant would be payable for each separate dwelling in the repaired house.  The housing authority would be free to pay a grant not exceeding the amount of the State grant, and rates remission would be available. The existing provisions relating to grants for the reconstruction of houses of up to £12 valuation and for the repair of houses by direction of the housing authority would no longer be required as the new grants would embrace the type of reconstruction and repair work hitherto covered by these provisions.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="807" /> There has been an insistent, though small, demand for lump-sum grants for houses built for letting in place of the grants payable by annual instalments over ten years under Section 19 of the 1948 Act.  Section 13 of the Bill would give a trial for two years to the alternative form of grant, which would be of an amount equal to that payable for an owner-occupied house.  The housing authority would be empowered to allow rates remission of two-thirds for seven years where a grant is paid under this section.  Houses qualifying for these grants would be subject to the same conditions as to resale which apply to houses for which letting grants under the 1948 Act are paid.</P>
    <P>Section 7 makes it clear that the recipient of a grant for an owner-occupied house must occupy the house as his normal place of residence, not, for instance, as a holiday or summer home.  Section 8 makes it clear that letting grants under the 1948 Act may be made to a local authority&mdash;for example, a mental hospital authority&mdash; though not to a housing authority providing houses which are otherwise subsidised by the State.</P>
    <P>Sections 9, 10 and 11 propose to give effect to representations made to me that housing authorities should have discretion to make supplementary grants of amounts less than the maxima specified in certain sections of the 1952 Act, rather than that some authorities should feel obliged to make no grants at all on the grounds of cost.</P>
    <P>Some further amendments of the supplementary grant provisions of the 1952 Act are desirable.  In the Dublin City and County areas, for instance, a high proportion of the applicants under Section 11 have been clerical and similar workers whose incomes exceed £416 and thus render them ineligible for grants under Section 10 of the 1952 Act.  Many of these applicants have been rejected by the housing authority on the grounds that they are not of a class whom the corporation or county council, for example, ordinarily re-house.</P>
    <P>It is proposed to increase the family income limits in the four county <Col N="808" /> boroughs, the borough of Dún Laoghaire, Dublin County and those portions of Cork County which are included with Cork City for the purpose of the higher loans to borrowers under the Small Dwellings (Acquisition) Acts.  Housing authorities in these areas would therefore be enabled to make to any person having a family income of less than £10 per week at the time of his application, a supplementary grant graded according to the amount of such income.</P>
    <P>No change in the valuation limits set out in Section 9 of the 1952 Act is proposed, as the £35 limit brings in the vast majority of farmers.</P>
    <P>Doubt has been expressed as to whether a housing authority which benefits by the surrender of a tenancy can pay a supplementary grant if the tenant builds his new house in the functional area of another authority and it is proposed to clarify the matter in Section 11.</P>
    <P>Section 8 of the 1948 Act which prohibits the demolition in whole or in part or the use otherwise than as a dwelling-house of any habitable house, unless with the permission of the housing authority, or on appeal, of the Minister, is extended to 31st December, 1956, by Section 15 of the Bill.</P>
    <P>The Rent Restrictions Acts by virtue of Section 3 (2) (c) of the Rent Restrictions Act of 1946, do not apply to houses provided by a local authority, of which the local authority is for the time being the landlord.  By virtue of Section 3 of the Landlord and Tenant Act, 1931, the Landlord and Tenant Acts do not apply where buildings on any land or premises are provided by a local authority, if such property is held by the local authority in fee simple.</P>
    <P>Housing authorities from time to time acquire private dwellings and other buildings for reconditioning or conversion under the Housing of the Working Classes Acts and the Labourers Acts.  House property also becomes vested in a housing authority as a result of boundary extensions and otherwise.  Arising from a number of court decisions, considerable doubt exists as to whether the housing <Col N="809" /> authorities can be deemed to have &ldquo;provided&rdquo; the houses acquired by or transferred to them.  It is proposed to remove these doubts in Sections 16 and 20.</P>
    <P>Section 17 of the Bill makes provision for the continuance of the Labourers Acts until 31st December, 1960.</P>
    <P>Section 18 of the Bill incorporates the principle of the Labourers Bill, 1953, introduced in the Dáil by Deputy Lehane.  I would like to have been in a position to propose a wider measure of amendment but the subject requires further detailed examination owing to the complexities that exist in all matters pertaining to land law.</P>
    <P>Section 11 of the Labourers (Ireland) Act, 1906, enables housing authorities to treat as absolute owners for the purposes of compensation for acquisition of land, certain persons who have been in possession of the land for not less than six years.  The section applies only where the compensation payable does not exceed £60.  Because of the fall in the value of money since 1906, it is considered reasonable to increase this sum to £250.</P>
    <P>Sub-section (8) of Section 11 enables housing authorities to pay into the Circuit Court compensation not exceeding £100 in certain cases where there are title or similar difficulties. The jurisdiction of the Circuit Court generally in similar matters has recently been increased to £600 and it is proposed to amend sub-section (8) accordingly.  The amendment proposed would apply also to operations under the Housing of the Working Classes Acts, to which the 1906 Act provisions were applied in the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act, 1931.</P>
    <P>Section 17 (2) (d) (iii) of the Labourers Act, 1936, provides that a vested cottage &ldquo;shall not be alienated otherwise than by operation of law or by sale with the consent of&rdquo; the housing authority.  There is doubt as to whether this empowers a tenant-purchaser to dispose of his interest by will or bequest, and Section 19 of the Bill is designed to clarify the point.</P>
    <P>Where advances under the Small Dwellings Acquisition Acts are made <Col N="810" /> to farmers, some local authorities are prepared to take a charge on the entire holding, while others insist on subdivision for the purpose of protecting their charge in the event of sale of the holding.  One of the principal objections to subdivision is that it divorces the occupier's residence from his holding and another objection is that the grant of the advance under the Small Dwellings Acquisition Acts is delayed.</P>
    <P>The proposal in Section 21 is that protection should be available to local authorities in respect of advances on holdings in the same way as protection is afforded in respect of Charging Orders under sub-section (5) of Section 9 of the Housing (Gaeltacht) Act, 1929, in order to encourage local authorities to take a charge on a complete holding without insisting on subdivision. At the same time it would facilitate farmers who object to subdividing their holdings to avail of the Small Dwellings Acts procedure for the erection of new houses.</P>
    <P>The time is approaching when the housing code seems incapable of much further expansion or amendment except in matters of detail.  The foregoing is a brief summary of some important aspects of housing policy which require early attention and which I, therefore, commend for the consideration of the Seanad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>Everybody in the Seanad will, I think, join with me in welcoming this Bill.  It extends the number of beneficiaries under the Housing Acts, and for that reason it is generally welcomed.  There is just one point in the Bill which I would like to draw attention to in the hope that the Minister might consider making a further extension of the class of people to benefit under the Small Dwellings (Acquisition) Acts.  The Bill does extend in Section 2 the number of people to receive grants under the Small Dwellings (Acquisition) Acts, and it increases quite substantially the grants above the 1952 figure.  The cost of living has risen since 1952, but not by as much as the grants in the Bill. Therefore, I think that the figures in the Bill do represent a substantial <Col N="811" /> increase in the number of people benefiting by the Housing Acts; it not merely increases the number but brings the present situation into line with the rise in the cost of living.</P>
      <P>I suggest to the Minister that if there is a means test in this Bill, as there is, that it is not perfectly logical.  If the means test is based on the gross income of people as defined by the 1952 Act, then some allowance should be made for the burden of dependent children when allowance is made for the benefit derived from the presence in a house of non-dependent children who are earning their living.  Under the definition of gross income in the 1952 Act, provision is made for taking into account all persons living in the house and contributing to the family income. That, no doubt, is proper, but it seems to me, on the face of it, unfair if that principle is not extended in the other direction so as to make some allowance for dependent children living whose presence in the house takes away from the net income rather than adds to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The first of the Small Dwellings (Acquisition) Acts in force to-day came into operation in 1948.  A number of people, for one reason or another, have been unable to take advantage of that Act or of the subsequent amending Acts.  A number of salaried employees, those who are now known as the white collar classes, found it very difficult during the war years from 1939 until 1948 to save sufficient out of their incomes to obtain a house. Houses were in short supply and money was short.  The incomes of a great many salaried people were pegged down much below the rise in the cost of living during that decade, so that a number of people were unable to obtain a house because of the fact that it was not possible for them to put aside enough money which would act as a deposit for a house when houses became more plentiful and cheaper after the war.  The fact is that in those years a number of people were not in a position to put anything aside and, therefore, were not able to take full advantage of the Act of 1948.  Many of these people have since been married and now have dependent <Col N="812" /> children.  The result is that, with the rise in the cost of living, they still find themselves unable to get enough money together to form a deposit for the purchase of a house.  There are many people to-day with £700 a year or more who are not at all as well-off as people were when the original Act was passed in 1948, even though they had a much lower money income.</P>
    <P>I do not myself see an answer to the point which I am making, that if children who are earning and adding to the family income are to be taken into account in assessing the eligibility of a parent to obtain a grant, the fact of children subtracting from that family income by being a charge on it should not have its effect in the opposite direction.  The Act of 1952 makes it perfectly clear that if children are bringing money into the house it must be taken into account. The result of taking it into account may be that the family ceases to be eligible for a grant under the Small Dwellings (Acquisition) Act.  On the other hand, there are other families where the children are, say, just two years younger and, instead of bringing money into the house they are a charge on their parents.  Their education, their upbringing, their nurture and the provision of clothing for them all add up to reduce the net family income, so that those children, instead of being an addition to the income of the house constitute a burden on their parents.  In that way, they make it extremely difficult for the parents to accumulate a deposit to help them to purchase a new dwelling.</P>
    <P>The proposal which I am putting forward to the Minister for his consideration is, I suggest, a very reasonable one, that is that every person with dependent children should have the same allowance for this purpose as he has under the income tax code. For example, under Section 10 of the Bill the maximum income that a person may possess to be eligible for the supplementary grant under the Small Dwellings (Acquisition) Act is now raised to £520.  If a married man with one dependent child had an income of £600 and was given the same allowance for this purpose as he would <Col N="813" /> be for income-tax he would be brought down to the £520 bracket.  If he had a child over 16 years, let us say, who was bringing in £100 a year the presence of that child might make him ineligible for the grant under the Bill.  What I suggest is that every person's income for this purpose should be the net income for income-tax purposes. That would be a very simple method of applying a logical means test instead of a means test which seems to me at any rate to cut in one direction but not in the other.</P>
    <P>The present position is, as I have said before, that a man whose children have grown up finds himself excluded possibly from eligibility owing to the fact that his children are bringing something into the house.  I suggest that it is a logical corollary of that principle that when a man has dependent children who are a severe charge on him at the present time, he should be brought into the eligibility bracket as a result of the presence in his family of those children.  The simplest way of doing that in practice would be to extend the income-tax code to the eligibility provisions in this Bill.  That is the only criticism I have to make of the Bill and I hope the Minister will not dismiss my suggestion without full consideration.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the provision in this Bill to extend for a period of two years the present payment of grants to persons who are building and to utility societies.  I particularly welcome the encouragement in the Bill to those persons who are prepared to build houses for letting purposes and I think we should devote all our efforts in the next two years to encouraging our farming community especially to build such houses.  The fact that provision is being made in this Bill to give a lump sum grant to those persons who are prepared to build houses for letting purposes, should be an inducement to our agricultural community, particularly to those people who are employers of agricultural workers, to provide housing accommodation for their agricultural workers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In this regard I would like to draw attention to the fact that over a <Col N="814" /> number of years a suggestion has been made by the head of the State that we might have provided in this country what we would term a second house. The Minister has gone some small way in encouraging the provision of that housing accommodation.  If a farmer feels that he is about to get in a lump sum what in the ordinary way would be spread over a number of years, it will encourage him to erect a house either for an agricultural worker or for the young family that may grow up after him.  That is a step in the right direction.</P>
    <P>In regard to the encouragement of local authority housing, I would direct the Minister's attention to something that has grown up, particularly in urban areas.  Most urban authorities have co-operated in housing the people and have encouraged development of house building on virgin soil in new areas.  Having done that, however, they have left derelict sites behind them and these in many cases have been turned into storage of one kind or another.  I have in mind such sites in Galway City.  That is a bad thing and I would ask the Minister to avail of whatever powers he has&mdash;and if he has not power, to secure it immediately&mdash;to ensure that premises which were originally occupied as dwellings, and from which people were removed to accommodation in other areas, would not be turned into storage areas, particularly in the centre of a town or in the centre of a city like Galway.  That is one of the things to which immediate attention should be given.</P>
    <P>We make very generous contributions to the local authorities to provide houses for those who cannot pay an economic rent.  There is not sufficient inducement given to the local authority to provide houses for those who are in a position to pay an economic rent.  We should encourage local authorities more than we have done in the past to engage in this type of work.  A very heavy burden has been placed on them over a number of years and they now find they are compelled to provide houses for persons who could and should contribute more to the provision of such accommodation than they do under present circumstances.  I <Col N="815" /> would like to see provision in the present Housing Bill for a contribution to local authorities whereby they would get at least the contribution the private individual would get when he provides such accommodation for himself. That is only fair, but I understand that it is not the position at the present time.</P>
    <P>This Bill extends the facilities for the improvement of houses, more than any other Bill in the past.  Grants are being made for reconstruction otherwise than by providing a roof.  There is also an extension of the conditions where the normal circumstances could not be taken into consideration, that is, for flooding, fire, and so on, rendering a dwelling unfit for habitation.  We have provision here for a grant in such circumstances.  That of itself is a very great advance.  Under former Acts if you provided a new roof, if you substituted a tiled roof for a thatched roof, you were entitled to a grant provided you had not received a grant inside 15 years.  Now, whether it is a new roof or an extension of accommodation, you are entitled to a reconstruction grant. These are all things in the Bill that we should appreciate.  During many discussions on these matters here and in the other House, we have heard many tributes to the Minister.  No doubt the Department of Local Government has contributed its share to the encouraging position we have arrived at to-day. The local authorities also have done their bit and, though there are some lagging behind, in most cases they have done what was expected of them. That entails acceptance of the responsibility for ensuring that the people are housed.  It means placing a heavy burden on the rates in that particular year.</P>
    <P>There is one section of the community about which, so far, I have not heard any appreciation from any person or society for their contribution to this great housing effort.  It is in particular to express my appreciation of their contribution that I have risen here to-night.  The people I refer to are the builders providers.  Without their encouragement and assistance, the Government, the local authority <Col N="816" /> and the utility societies throughout the country could not have achieved what they have achieved.  It is the builders providers, it is the local merchants, who of their own accord have accepted credit notes from the utility societies. They have accepted the credit of the particular applicant and the credit of the local authority which has guaranteed to pay a grant in a particular case. When we take into consideration that the acceptance of such a grant over a number of cases&mdash;particularly having regard to the high cost of materials at the present moment&mdash;may mount up to some thousands of pounds in very small cases, we must realise that these merchants have made a very serious contribution to the solution of the housing problem.</P>
    <P>I would like to add my appreciation of what they have done over a number of years.  They made that contribution even during the war years.  I have known merchants, particularly in Galway, who have refused to accept cash clients in order to give preference to people with credit notes from a utility society.  In that way the builders providers have shown their appreciation of the position and have made their contribution to the drive we are making to solve this great problem.  Without their co-operation and assistance in the past&mdash;and which we hope to have in the future&mdash;we could not have achieved the objects we have achieved.</P>
    <P>Senator George O'Brien in his very brief statement referred to the Small Dwellings Act.  His suggestion was that it was something that was passed by the Dáil or Seanad in 1948.  I have gone to the trouble to look that up&mdash; it was not very much trouble, as I am very familiar with all these things in relation to housing.  The Small Dwellings Acts was first passed by a British Parliament as far back as 1891, not 1948.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know how to meet briefly the point that has been made by Senator O'Brien, but I will start in this way.  There are three sections in the Act of 1952 that are <Col N="817" /> being continued in this Bill. Section 9 deals with farmers, land owners, and sets out the valuation limits inside of which the local authority may pay supplementary grants.  Section 11 deals with persons who are in occupation of local authority houses or who are accepted by the local authority as people for whom houses should be provided.  Section 10 was designed to meet a lower income type of applicant, irrespective of whether or not he belonged to the class or classes for whom a local authority was obliged to provide housing.  That being the case, it is only natural that the income limits would be low.  The income limits as set out in the Act of 1952, Section 10, and as amended here, are low.  There is no need for me to attempt to justify these limits or to analyse the arguments adduced by Senator Professor O'Brien, to show the justice or injustice of what is proposed, for the simple reason that these are permissive sections; the local authority may, if it so desires, adopt them.</P>
      <P>To give an idea of the justification for the limit set out, all I need say is that until recently very few local bodies adopted them, low as they were. It was only recently that Dublin Corporation got the idea of giving supplementary grants.  The same applies in the City of Waterford, the City of Limerick, the City of Cork, and all the boroughs.  If there had been any inclination on the part of local bodies to give supplementary grants, they would have given them immediately on the passing of the 1952 Act.</P>
      <P>I know what Senator O'Brien is complaining of, but I am trying to show that there is not much justification for it.  Low as the limits have been, local bodies were slow to give supplementary grants even within these limits.  If we raise the limits sky-high or if we remove the limits, what would it mean?  It would mean that there would be permissive sections, that the sky would be the limit and local authorities would be so afraid that they would not give any supplementaries at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="818" /> One can play about with arguments that, if the family income is to be determined on the basis of the earnings of the head of the family plus the earnings of members of the family living in the house, there should be a reduction in respect of those who are a charge upon the head of the house, who have not reached the stage when they are capable of earning&mdash;in one case you add; in the other case you deduct.  One can play about with these arguments to show that some injustice is being done here but, in designing these three sections, we had to bear in mind that, even without this additional burden, local authorities have tremendous problems to discharge, that rates are high and that local authorities were hesitant to give supplementary grants within the framework of these three sections and therefore would be frightened of giving grants if there were no limit at all in respect of classes of persons for whom they had no responsibility in the matter of providing housing.</P>
    <P>I do not think I need go any further than that.  I could make the same sort of case as Senator O'Brien has made.  I could see the arguments he has made.  To some minds they may appear forceful, but we are dealing here with machinery that is being handed to local bodies to implement and we must think in terms of their difficulty.  In raising the limit to a maximum of £10 a week, I know that that will not bring in quite a number of very deserving people but I also know that, if I do not have a limit somewhere near that figure, I am being too generous, in the knowledge that the local authority will not implement it, for the reasons I have given.</P>
    <P>It would cost the State nothing to be generous about this.  I need not argue about this.  I could simply say that I would eliminate the limit but that would not get us anywhere.  We have gone this far in order to provide for a type of person who belongs to the lower income group who would not be covered by Section 11.  We have inserted Section 10 so as to ensure that persons in the lower income group, irrespective of the class to which they <Col N="819" /> belong, can be given a supplementary grant, if the local authority decides to give it.  That is a very substantial reason for our taking this line.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the next stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senator O'Brien has an amendment, he should be given an opportunity of tabling it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>We could discuss it now. In fact, we have been discussing it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not wish to incommode the House or the Minister. I have made my point and if the House and the Minister are prepared to take the amendment now, I have no objection to going on with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If we take the Committee Stage now, when we come to the appropriate section Senator O'Brien could read out the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>This is very awkward.  I had a notion that perhaps I might put down an amendment or two.  I do not want to cause any inconvenience. The points I have to consider are not of any great importance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator care to raise them on the sections?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Committee Stage were postponed I would be able to put down my amendments in the ordinary way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any difference for the Minister between now and the 21st April?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>We are endeavouring to convenience the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>The only thing is that we are paying grants at the moment without legal sanction of any kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Legal sanction will be forthcoming.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="820" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to pretend that it is a serious matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly Mr. P. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>A fundamental objection to our not passing this Bill to-night is that there is a fair amount of uneasiness among people down the country.  Apparently it has got around that the 1952 Act has expired and that there is no legal sanction for the payment of any further grants.  As a matter of fact, only yesterday I attended a funeral in County Leitrim and, at that funeral, a man asked me about current claims in respect of reconstruction grants.  He said that people feel there is a doubt about the matter and, with a general election pending, they wondered if an enabling Act such as this would be passed in time.  They fear they may be debarred in respect of payment of grants to which they are entitled.  So long as there is this un-easiness&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator can take my opinion to the man in County Leitrim that it will be all right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly Mr. P. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>They take an intelligent interest in public affairs there, Sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>We should have a fundamental objection here to putting Bills through almost as a matter of form and we should be enabled to consider things fully&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we not take it tomorrow?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments to be handed in before&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>We will leave it until the 21st of this month.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>What will the men in Leitrim do in the meantime?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly Mr. P. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall have to tell them that the Bill will be passed. That is all.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 21st April.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Defence Bill," RHead="1951&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Defence Bill, 1951&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="821" /> Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. Traynor) Oscar Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. Traynor)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the Bill is to provide permanent legislation in relation to the defence of the State and the Defence Forces.  As Senators are aware, the existing statutory provisions governing these matters are contained in the various Defence Forces (Temporary Provisions) Acts, 1923 to 1954.  While it may be said that these Acts operated successfully, it was very difficult from the administrative standpoint to have to deal with a large number of Acts containing many provisions of an amending nature.  These Acts include also many provisions requiring amendments to bring them into line with modern conceptions and practice.</P>
      <P>An effort has been made in the present Bill to retain all the provisions of the existing Acts, amended and modified where necessary, that are considered suitable, in the light of experience, for a permanent measure such as this.  The Bill also includes a number of new provisions designed to improve the position of members of the Defence Forces and to provide much-needed additional powers for defence purposes. Some of the provisions enacted during the last emergency, for example, those relating to the precedence of military traffic on transport undertakings during an emergency, are considered to be more suitable for inclusion in any future emergency legislation that may be necessary, and are, accordingly, omitted from the Bill.</P>
      <P>The Bill is divided into 12 parts and there are ten schedules.  The more important provisions of Part I relate to the date on which the Act will come into operation; to the declaration of a state of emergency and to active service. Many new regulations, changes in existing regulations and other administrative arrangements consequent on the provisions of the Act will require to be completed before it can be brought into operation.  The operative date must, accordingly, be left to be fixed by the Minister for Defence when these matters have been dealt with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Power is taken in Section 4 for the declaration by the Government of a <Col N="822" /> state of emergency and for the revocation of any such declaration.  The state of emergency referred to in this section is in relation to defence purposes only and should not be confused with a national state of emergency under the Constitution.  All that it gives power to do, apart from a few minor matters, is to declare the Defence Forces to be on active service under Section 5; to billet members of the Defence Forces in private houses or elsewhere under Section 37; to enlist men under Section 54 for the duration of the emergency, and to call out the Reserve on permanent service under Section 87.  The section is similar to Section 4 of the Defence Forces (Temporary Provisions) (No. 2) Act, 1940.  The circumstances in which the Defence Forces will be on active service are set out in Section 5.  A similar provision is contained in existing legislation.</P>
    <P>The provisions relating to the Council of Defence, the Chief of Staff, the Adjutant-General, the Quartermaster-General and the Judge Advocate-General are contained in Part II.  The existing provisions governing the Council of Defence are contained in the Ministers and Secretaries Act, 1924.  Under that Act the Minister is a member and chairman of the council. The purpose of the council under Section 11 of the Bill is to aid and counsel the Minister on all matters in relation to the business of the Department of Defence on which the Minister may consult the council.  It would be anomalous that the Minister should be a member of a body advising himself as Minister.  Accordingly, he will not be a member of the council provided for in the Bill.</P>
    <P>Hitherto the maximum continuous period of office of the Chief of Staff, the Adjutant-General and the Quarter-master-General has been three years. Experience has shown such a period to be too short and provision is now being made in Section 12 for a five-year period of office.  The qualifications for the post of Judge Advocate-General are set out in Section 15.  A person filling that appointment must now be a practising barrister-at-law of at least ten years' standing.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="823" /> Part III provides the power for the raising, maintenance and command of the Defence Forces and deals with the constitution, general organisation and military education of these forces.  The Defence Forces will, as at present, be divided into a permanent force and a reserve force, each consisting of army, air and naval components.  Members of the Army Nursing Service will now be members of the Permanent Defence Forces under Section 19.  It is necessary to give them military status in order to ensure that, in the event of war, they would, as part of the Army Medical Corps, have the protection of the Geneva Red Cross Convention.  They will not, however, be commissioned or enlisted and under Section 290, they will, for the present at least, be subject to the provisions of this Act only to the extent mentioned in that section.</P>
    <P>Under the direction of the President&mdash;in whom the Constitution vests the supreme command&mdash;the command of the Defence Forces is exercisable by the Government, through and by the Minister, who is given power to delegate command, subject to such exceptions and limitations as he thinks fit, to officers.  Existing legislation contains similar provisions.</P>
    <P>Part III contains also a number of miscellaneous provisions, the more important of which relate to the compulsory acquisition of land for defence purposes.  The need for such powers has, on occasion, been badly felt and this might be the case to an even greater degree in future, particularly if the necessity for a number of aerodromes arose.  Similar powers of acquisition are given to the Minister for Industry and Commerce in the Air Navigation and Transport Act, 1936.  Further new provisions on the lines of the Air Navigation and Transport Act, 1950, permit of the erection of apparatus on lands adjacent to military aerodromes and places certain restrictions on the use of such lands. These facilities are necessary to assist aircraft flying to or from the aerodromes.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="824" /> The provisions in Part IV deal with the appointment or enlistment and conditions of service of the personnel of the Defence Forces.  Generally speaking there is little departure from the corresponding provisions in existing legislation.  Power is, however, being taken to retain men in service during the whole of a period of emergency even though they are due to be transferred to the Reserve or to be discharged during that period.  This very reasonable power, which will apply only to men enlisted on or after the operative date of the Act, differs from the existing position to the extent that at present men may be retained for a period of only 12 months.  A new provision is proposed in Section 88, which empowers the Minister, when so authorised by the Government, to call out reservists on permanent service for a maximum period of three months in anticipation of an emergency.  Only men who have agreed in writing to this liability may, however, be called out.  The intention here is to provide key-men to prepare for the general calling up of the Reserve.</P>
    <P>The circumstances of forfeiture of pay or in which penal deductions may be made from pay are set out in detail in the existing Acts.  Other deductions of a non-penal character may be made in accordance with regulations.  It is now considered preferable that all these matters should be dealt with by regulations and provision is made accordingly in Section 97.  The power to make such regulations is, however, circumscribed as the forfeitures and deductions to be prescribed must fall within the limits of the heads detailed in the section.  In addition either House of the Oireachtas will have an opportunity of annulling any of the regulations made.</P>
    <P>In Chapter V of Part IV, which deals with disqualifications, exemptions and privileges of the Defence Forces, the provisions of existing legislation are, to a large extent, followed. Members of the Reserve Defence Force will, in ordinary circumstances, be free to take part in political activities, but it is now proposed <Col N="825" /> to prohibit participation in such activities when they are called out on permanent service, as they will then be in the same position as members of the permanent force.</P>
    <P>If a member of the Reserve happens to be a member of a local authority when called out on permanent service, he must remain inactive during the period of permanent service, but his membership of the local authority is preserved in so far as absence from its meetings is concerned.</P>
    <P>Under existing legislation an N.C.O. or man can appeal only up to the Adjutant-General.  In Section 114 dealing with redress of wrongs, an N.C.O. or man is given the right to require the Adjutant-General to bring his complaint to the notice of the Minister, who must inquire into the complaint and give his directions thereon.</P>
    <P>Part V, which deals with discipline, takes up a large portion of the Bill. The provisions relating to persons subject to military law are on the lines of existing legislation.  The offences against military law have been drafted in such a way as to provide a code of law which will be common to all members of the Defence Forces, whether army, air or naval personnel.  With a few exceptions relating principally to wartime offences, aircraft and military transport, no new matters constituting additional offences have been introduced. There is very little change from existing legislation in the provisions relating to the investigation of charges against officers and men. Additional safeguards for the accused person are contained in Section 191, which sets out the officers who are disqualified from acting as a member of or Judge-Advocate at a court-martial. An officer who has examined into or advised on the matters on which the charge is based or who sat on a court of inquiry into the subject matter of the charge or who, in an advisory capacity, dealt with the charges or the evidence to be produced or the conduct of the prosecution will not now be eligible for such membership.</P>
    <P>Some important changes in favour of the accused or sentenced person are introduced in the provisions relating <Col N="826" /> to the action to be taken following a court-martial.  Confirming authorities may now substitute a lesser sentence for a sentence of death.  It may be mentioned here that under Section 227 a sentence of death cannot be carried out unless and until the execution of the sentence has been approved by the Government.  This will afford the Government an opportunity to advise the President, if such a course is considered desirable, to exercise his constitutional prerogative in such cases.  New authorities, known as superior authorities, are proposed to review sentences passed by court-martial and confirmed.  This is a new stage in the safeguards provided for persons tried by court-martial.  A person undergoing punishment may now have his sentence reviewed by these authorities who have power to mitigate or suspend the sentence. There is also a further new provision which will enable petitions to be presented by or on behalf of sentenced persons in accordance with rules of procedure.</P>
    <P>Part VI deals with the matters which are offences in relation to the Defence Forces and military property and concerns members of the public to some extent.  One of the few changes introduced makes it an offence, without lawful authority, to make or attempt to make any sketch, drawing or photograph of military defence works or establishments or to trespass thereon.</P>
    <P>In Part VII the powers and duties of the military and the public relating to manoeuvres are more specifically prescribed than in existing legislation. New provisions are introduced designed to protect the public from danger.</P>
    <P>Power is taken in Part VIII to make bye-laws as to land used for defence purposes.  The provisions of this part are mostly new.  By giving control over lands affected by firing, bombing or other military exercises it will be possible to regulate the public with a view to their protection against injury.</P>
    <P>Part IX is devoted to the Army Nursing Service.  As I have already stated in my comments on Part III <Col N="827" /> members of the Army Nursing Service are being given military status so that they may be protected by the Geneva Red Cross Convention.  Although it is not the intention, at present, that members of the service will be subject to the provisions of the Act except to the limited extent stated in Section 290 it is, nevertheless, necessary that there should be power, which is also provided in Section 290, to extend other provisions to them in, for example, circumstances of war when they would have to be made subject to military law.</P>
    <P>In Part X provision is made for the application of the Act to members of the Defence Forces established under the Temporary Provisions Acts.  Certain rights and privileges, for example the right to which I have already referred, regarding transfer to the Reserve or discharge during a period of emergency, will be preserved for those who are members of the Defence Forces up to the operative date.</P>
    <P>Part XI deals with the amendment and adaptation consequent on the provisions of the Act of a number of other Acts.  Part XII contains the miscellaneous provisions which are on the lines of existing legislation and which are not appropriate to the other parts.</P>
    <P>The First Schedule lists the enactments to be repealed on the operative date of the Act.  The Second Schedule specifies the commissioned Army ranks and Naval ranks and the Third Schedule the Army and Naval non-commissioned ranks.  Two new Naval non-commissioned ranks are proposed, namely, senior chief petty officer and senior petty officer.  These correspond to the Army ranks of battalion-quartermaster-sergeant and company-quartermaster-sergeant to which there has not hitherto been corresponding Naval ranks.</P>
    <P>The Fourth Schedule indicates the principal matters in respect of which the Minister may make regulations and the Fifth Schedule sets out the forms of commission to be issued to an officer.  The Sixth to the Tenth <Col N="828" /> Schedules set out the forms of oath to be taken by officers and men.</P>
    <P>I hope that the foregoing will have given Senators a general picture of the Bill which will be helpful in their consideration of it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I think a more appropriate picture for the Second Stage of a Defence Bill which has been so long delayed, and which is so necessary, would have been a general picture of quite a different character. However, I will not go into that. Ministers have fallen into the habit of giving a description of a Bill, section by section and part by part, which I think is wholly lamentable.  I remember very well&mdash;very few people do so, probably, now&mdash;when the first Defence Forces (Temporary Provisions) Bill of 1923 was introduced.  On that occasion, a permanent Bill was promised.  It has taken more than 30 years for it to get as far as this House.  I can remember the Minister himself, certainly a number of his colleagues, after 1927, protesting every year that we should have a permanent Defence Forces Act instead of temporary provisions Bills.  Be that as it may, we now have this enormous measure and there are certain things, at any rate, on which we have to congratulate ourselves.  The Bill is not a Party measure and it is not being discussed in a Party spirit.  The fact that it has come before us at all, I would agree with the Minister, is a very substantial step forward.  It was introduced by the late Dr. O'Higgins in 1949 and, I think, this particular Bill was introduced in 1952.  It has taken just two years to get out of the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Army has the distinction of being the oldest Irish institution of State we have.  It is older than the police force, because no police force was founded until after 1916, so that the Army has the distinction of being the oldest Irish institution of State which we have.  It has the right to boast that for 40 years, or a little more than 40 years, it has served this country very well.  It has had various trials and vicissitudes and stood up to various difficulties, foreign and domestic, but it emerged triumphant, respected <Col N="829" /> and competent within its limits and for its purposes.</P>
    <P>The Army, it seems to me, too, reflects credit upon its present members and on those who founded it and moulded it in the early days from 1913 onwards and after the setting up of the State.  There are comparatively few, I suppose, of the old type of officers left, but even the absence of a permanent compendious measure of this kind did not prevent the Army from doing its duty during the emergency. It is only right to say that during the emergency it did its business of developing and expanding rapidly extremely well and the way in which that was done drew praise from a great many people in this country who had a very varied military experience and showed that the Army we had at that particular moment in its personnel and officers, commissioned and non-commissioned, was a competent sound force.  My knowledge is mainly confined to the older officers, but I have been in touch with the newer corps of officers on the Curragh and I must say that they have made upon me a very good impression indeed.  There are very few jobs more difficult.  The Minister himself on more than one occasion has said that there are very few jobs more difficult than belonging to a peace-time army.</P>
    <P>I would like the Minister to have said something about the general functions of the Army.  It seems to me to have at least two.  It is the ultimate guarantor of order here at home, but we have to congratulate ourselves that for more than 30 years it has not been used.  It is necessary, also, to provide the framework around which can be developed a force during war or any other emergency.  For that it needs to be highly trained and I think it deserves our gratitude.</P>
    <P>This Bill is an enormous one.  It has 318 sections and, as is usual now with Bills of this kind, and I think it is inevitable in this particular case, not only is the Bill enormous and difficult to grasp in all its implications, but it is still not all here in spite of the fact that there are 318 sections and ten schedules. <Col N="830" /> There will be an enormous number of Orders and regulations to be made under it.  I think the Minister said there are two dates, the date upon which the Bill is passed through the Oireachtas and the date upon which the Bill is brought into operation.  I think the Minister said that in order that personnel in the Army and the Civil Service would become familiar with the regulations made under the Bill when it becomes an Act, and on account of the necessity to bring a number of regulations up to date, it would not be possible to put the Act into operation under Section 1 for quite a long time after the Act is passed.  I take it the Minister is right in regard to that point.  I wonder has the Minister any date in mind.  Presumably, this Bill when it becomes an Act will not be put into operation in accordance with sub-section (2) of Section 1 until, say, the 1st October.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>We were allowing about six months for the making of the regulations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>At the end of six months, sub-section (2) of Section 1 will be put into operation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Act will come into operation by an Order of the Minister for Defence.  Even that would be a very good thing.  The Dáil has taken two years to pass the Bill.  It has taken more than 30 years to reach the Second House.  I am wondering what one can do with such an enormous amount of matter in an expiring Parliament. I regret very much that we could not have had this Bill at a time when it could be examined in a proper spirit and gone through carefully and, perhaps, amended.  I do not know what the Minister intends to ask us to do, but, for my part, it seems to me that the state of mind which a dissolution induces and the state of affairs which obtains when the Dáil has been dissolved and the Seanad is, so to speak, making slow and, I suppose, unwilling progress towards its own end, is a very bad time in which to deal with a matter of this kind, a matter in which we would all be <Col N="831" /> interested and in which there would be no asperity of any kind.  It would need careful consideration and considerable thought and, frankly, I feel that very few people could give it that thought in the present circumstances.</P>
      <P>However, for the moment I am entirely in agreement with the Minister that it is a good thing that this Bill has been put together and that we certainly ought to pass it.  We certainly ought to examine it afterwards with a view to seeing that those who serve in the Army get the very best chance they possibly can get to perfect themselves to carry out their functions and that their rights should be preserved as far as these rights can be preserved in a military organisation. I suppose it is undoubtedly true that when one joins an organisation of this kind one has to abandon one's rights. For that reason I am entirely in favour of the Second Reading.  While I would like the Bill to be arranged in such a way that it would not be killed&mdash;I think the legal position is clear enough&mdash;I would like to have a different time in which to examine the Bill in detail.  Meantime I heartily support the Bill as a measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to join with Senator Hayes in recommending this Bill to the House.  As Senator Hayes pointed out, we have been waiting quite a number of years for it. We have had before the House an annual Army Bill and we have looked forward to the day when we could have presented to us a permanent measure.  We have that measure now. I think it is only right that at this stage we should be proud of those people who have composed our national services, particularly during the emergency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to say that during the discussion in the Dáil certain statements have been made which to my mind have not been very serviceable in so far as those statements may have created in the minds of those people who are serving in our forces an impression that the Government and the Parliament were not doing justice to them.  I think any member of any Party <Col N="832" /> who suggests a thing of that kind is doing an injustice not alone to the Party but to the country.  There is no Party, and no individual elected to this or the other House that I can visualise, who does not hold in the highest estimation those people who have given their services both in the period before the Army was a recognised Army and afterwards.  Any statement that has been made, whether it is for Party purposes or not, suggesting that the people and Parliament are not prepared to give an appreciation of the services rendered by our people is doing a very great disservice to both the people and those who have served in the forces.  It is regrettable that such statements have been made and have got some prominence in particular Press reports in relation to what has happened in the Dáil.</P>
    <P>As Senator Hayes has pointed out, we are a young State.  He has mentioned a period of 30 years, but after all&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Army is older than the State as it happens.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>That is true.  That is a point I would like to make.  I would hope in particular that our young people would bear in mind that it was not one section but it was those people who comprised the old volunteer forces who established this State and brought about the position of affairs in which we had the truce negotiated and which brought any semblance of freedom that Senator Hayes might claim we have.  I think Senator Hayes will agree with me in that.  Senator Hayes and other people sometimes say that our people are too much immersed in politics.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I never said that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I hold an entirely different view.  I feel that our people do not take sufficient interest in politics.  I would like to see more of our young people interested there.  If there is one appeal I would make to the Minister to-night it is this, that we should have more active encouragement given to our people particularly to become members of the F.C.A. force, that is the volunteer force, similar to <Col N="833" /> that which established our freedom; and I think that if we could go out on a recruiting campaign of that nature and encourage our people, particularly our young people, those of them who are university students, for example, to participate more in the building up of that F.C.A. force than they are doing at the present time we would be doing good work.  In doing that not alone would we be building up a young, trained and disciplined force but we would also be building up a disciplined people.  From my knowledge I find that those people, particularly the young people, who have taken an interest in the development of our armed forces, whether it is the F.C.A. or the Army in general, are better citizens.  We have to recognise this point whether we like it or not, that this State was built up by those people who came into public life in the voluntary organisations, whether it was Sinn Féin or the volunteer force&mdash;that the majority of us here are, if you like, politicians by accident.</P>
      <P>We see from day to day that a number of our colleagues who took part in that are pasing out, and if we are going to make an Army to ensure that the traditions they had were going to be maintained and that what we sought for was going to be built up we must ensure that those young people who come after us will be imbued with the same spirit and are going to come in to complete, if you like, the work which we set out to do and which we failed to complete.  We were brought into the national movement because for one reason or another we found ourselves in the volunteer movement.  If the Minister could enlarge his inducement to our young people to come in at the present time to the F.C.A. movement and from there to build up whatever volunteer force we might have and after that whatever national contribution you might have from that force I believe we would be doing very good work in that direction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>There are just one or two comments which I should like to make on the Bill.  As some Senators have already pointed out, the Bill is <Col N="834" /> such an enormous measure that the ordinary person can only feel that he is hardly competent to deal with it.  I however agree with the suggestion that having regard to the fact that the Bill has already received such a prolonged consideration in the other House, there would be little point in prolonging discussion on it here.  It seems to me that the Bill has been sat upon, so to speak, for such a lengthy period by a Special Committee of the Dáil, that it has gone through the sieve and run the gauntlet of such close artillery fire in the other House that a postponement of the discussion on it in this House could scarcely add to or detract from the Bill in any way. I feel as a member of this House that we all owe a debt to the members of the Special Committee of the other House who sat for two years week after week and went through the Bill section by section.</P>
      <P>I should like to comment briefly on those sections of the Bill which deal with the right to impose sentences of death.  I was hoping that, in this enlightened age, it might be possible even for our Defence Forces to forgo the right to impose a death sentence, as a solution or a preventative for any from of crime.  I was hoping that it would not be necessary to include amongst the list of punishments to be inflicted by our Defence Forces such a stringent punishment as the sentence of death.  I would ask the Minister to reconsider the matter to see if some other method could not be devised for dealing with crime and to examine the question whereby crimes such as our Defence Forces will have to deal with, could not be punished in some other way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One other matter to which I should like to refer, though I do not know whether it would come under the Defence Bill, is the question of compulsory military training for our youth generally.  It has been referred to before and it is a topical subject. Having regard to the manner in which it has been dealt with by other countries, I think the Minister might consider it.  Compulsory military service would undoubtedly improve the manners, the morals and even the <Col N="835" /> gait of our younger generation.  I should like to say a good deal more about this Bill, it is such a tremendous measure from every point of view, but I shall content myself at this stage by saying that it is a great achievement. It is a summing up of a lot of past history.  I would hope that Senators would not press too strongly for the postponement of its final passage as apparently it has been thoroughly discussed already in the other House and it is desirable that it should become law at the earliest stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. Traynor) Oscar Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. Traynor)</NameTxt>
      <P>The fact that the Bill has arrived at this stage means that it will continue in existence.  If this House decided, in its wisdom or otherwise, to hold up the Bill after this stage, it would, I understand, nevertheless, continue to live and could be dealt with by a succeeding Seanad.  I think we can congratulate ourselves on having got the Bill out of the other House safe and sound and on having arrived at the stage when we are now ready, so to speak, to launch it.  I think it would be a pity if this House did not conclude the enormous task that we had to undertake in getting it to this stage by reason of the belief expressed by Senator Hayes that, because this is an expiring Parliament, Senators would not be competent to set their minds down to the task of dealing with it.  I should be rather surprised if Senators' minds were exercised to that extent by the fact that this House is now a unit of an expiring Parliament.  I am satisfied myself that this Seanad can deal with the Bill in the stage at which it has arrived at the present moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I can give this assurance to the Seanad, though I do not wish to be positive about it, that I do not think that any Bill dealt with since the Oireachtas was established, has received such a minute and meticulous examination as this Bill has received over the long period of time during which it was being examined by members of the other House.  From that point of view, one could come to the <Col N="836" /> conclusion that there is little more that could be done to it by way of improvement. I should like to emphasise that by saying that on every occasion on which a doubt was expressed in respect of the constitutionality or the legality of any particular provision, that particular section, sub-section or clause was brought to the attention of the legal authorities for re-examination. Some of the statements that were made in respect of the legality of some of the sections were such that I was very anxious to make certain that whatever else the Bill might represent, it would not represent anything that would not be strictly legal, strictly constitutional&mdash;in a word, that it would be a Bill that could not be challenged.  From that point of view alone, I can say that the Bill was examined and re-examined by the officers of the Attorney-General's Department on numerous occasions. On several occasions I brought it personally to the attention of the Attorney-General himself.  On all of these occasions, I was satisfied that what we were doing was perfectly correct and that there was nothing in any sense unconstitutional or illegal in the Bill.</P>
    <P>Naturally Senators might be anxious to improve this Bill if it is possible to improve it.  Personally, I cannot see how it can be improved, but if the Seanad, in its wisdom, thinks that Senators should be given an opportunity for improving it, that question will arise in the course of succeeding stages.  The period which will elapse after this House passes the Bill will be devoted largely to the framing of regulations which will be a very important matter because, to a very large extent, the Bill will be operated under these regulations.  When Senator Hayes referred to the fact that this Bill was a voluminous type of measure and that it was not all here, I assumed that he was referring to the making of these regulations.  It is not all here from that point of view, because the regulations to be drawn up under the particular sections with which they deal will be the means by which the administrative officers will deal with personnel.  From that point of view, <Col N="837" /> the regulations will have to be examined just as strictly and as carefully, from the point of view of right and justice to the individuals concerned, as the Bill itself.  That is the only reason why a long period will have to elapse before the Bill can become operative.</P>
    <P>I can assure Senators that the Army itself is thirsting for the Bill.  It amazes me how any officer who has to deal with the existing legislation can deal with it, because it is just a book with a jumble of cuttings, representing the amendments brought in over the 30 years during which the Army has existed.  I am perfectly satisfied that the amendments which were passed during the emergency constitute a considerable part of the present Bill, but I would say that most of the other parts have weathered a long period of time.  They have survived for 30 years and have been found desirable for inclusion in the Bill.  To a very large extent, the Bill consists merely of the best of the 1923 Act, plus the Temporary Provisions Acts which have been introduced since 1923 to date.</P>
    <P>Some of the criticism directed towards the Bill was directed towards some of the sections which have weathered the storms of all these years and which were retained in the Act.  We were criticised also in relation to those cases where we were endeavouring to look into the future, but none of us can foresee the future to the extent that we can give guarantees that what we are doing is correct.  We can only hope that in what we are doing we are providing an instrument which will enable us to deal with the circumstances that might be likely to arise.</P>
    <P>My opening statement was a very detailed statement, designed mainly to give Senators as clear a picture as it was possible for me to give in order to guide them in any discussion, they might like to have on either this stage or the remaining stages of the Bill and whether it is necessary for me at this stage to say more than that is very doubtful.  We can all join in the praise which was given by Senator Hayes and added to by Senator <Col N="838" /> Hawkins to the Army.  There is, however, no necessity to paint the lily. The Army is there and it is a perfect instrument so far as it is possible for anything to be perfect.  That we now have young officers coming up who are the equal of any men in the world is proved by the fact that in the various courses they undergo in the various military establishments in England, establishments in which are represented officers from almost every army in Europe and America, these young men have not only been able to hold their own in the examinations, but on a number of occasions have secured the first places in these examinations. It is quite a regular thing for me to get reports that they have got second, third, fourth or fifth places and it always astonishes me how these young men are able to hold their own with officers who are members of long established armies, with perhaps very much greater facilities for perfecting themselves than we have here.</P>
    <P>I hope the example which the Seanad has given here to-day of expedition will be followed on the other stages and I should like to appeal to the Seanad to take those other stages and to hand on this Bill to whatever Minister for Defence may come along, without asking him to undergo, even in this House, the painful process which I have had to undergo in the other House.  I think the Seanad will in fact do that.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the remaining stages?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>What kind of time-table has the Minister in mind for the Bill?  Would he consider the end of May a good time to finish it, when the election is over?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we could get on with the Committee Stage on the next sitting day of the Seanad, and I suggest we put the Committee Stage down for April 21st.  If we are not in a position to take it then, we can wait.  The Committee Stage, however, could be long drawn out and then there are the Report and Final Stages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="839" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>Whether we deal with the Committee Stage on this day fortnight, which would be the next sitting day, or not, I think the Committee Stage should appear on the Order Paper.  It would be very bad if we adjourned that stage indefinitely after passing the Second Reading.  It is immaterial from the point of view of procedure whether it is taken that day or not, but we should not establish a precedent whereby we pass the Second Reading and, at the same time, refuse even to consider the possibility of taking the Committee Stage on the next sitting day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I had no intention of proposing an indefinite postponement, and I am prepared to agree to putting the Committee Stage down for 21st April.  I take it from the Minister's concluding remarks that he hopes to get the Bill through by the middle of May, so that he or some Minister for Defence will have the Bill in such a state that regulations can be made. Then, under sub-section (2) of Section 1, an Order would not be made until, perhaps, October bringing it into operation.  Is that the time-table suggested by the Minister?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the maximum period, but as we were getting the various sections through on Report Stage in the Dáil we had the staff working on them in the hope and the belief that they would not be altered when they came here.  The staff are <Col N="840" /> working on them at present, but it is a slow business which cannot be speeded up, because every regulation has to be very carefully examined before being framed and agreed upon.  The hope is that we might reduce the six month period I mentioned to four months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>That would still leave the position that the Bill would not be in operation until 1st August?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will there be other work for the Seanad on April 21st?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that this Bill should be concluded to-night. We do no injustice to ourselves by that, because it has been extensively and meticulously debated for three years.  I saw no indication from anybody that he intends to put down an amendment.  What is the difference between taking it now and on the next sitting day of the Seanad if there is no actual amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Mr. Traynor Mr. Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Traynor</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be satisfied to have the Committee Stage on 21st of April.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for 21st April, 1954.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 9.10 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 21st April, 1954.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>