<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="15" Month="Dec" Year="1954" Vol="44" No="6" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 15 Nollaig 1954" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 15 December 1954" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="495">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="495" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Finance desires that we should take No. 2&mdash;the National Monuments (Amendment) Bill&mdash;to which there are only two not very important amendments, first.  Then we will take No. 1, the Trade Loans (Guarantee) (Amendment) Bill, No. 3, the Solicitors Bill, and then the two motions.  There is a possibility of finishing on the motions to-day.</P>
      <P>There is on the Order Paper of the Dáil the Imposition of Duties (Confirmation of Orders) (No. 2) Bill which, it is thought, will go through all stages in that House to-day.  If that is so, instead of meeting next week, which is Christmas week, perhaps the House would agree to take it at 7 o'clock, if it is ready?  All the information will be given at 7 o'clock and the House need not go on with it, if it does not like to do so.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="National Monuments (Amendment) Bill," RHead="1954&mdash;Fourth and Fifth Stages">
    <Title>National Monuments (Amendment) Bill, 1954&mdash;Fourth and Fifth Stages.</Title>
    <P>Government amendment:&mdash;</P>
    <P>In page 5, Section 18, to delete &ldquo;common&rdquo; where it occurs in lines 43 and 47.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. Sweetman) Gerard Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. Sweetman)</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment and the following amendment arise in the same way.  The House will remember that the State Property Bill and the National Monuments Bill were both before the two Houses of the Oireachtas at the same time.  When we were drafting the Bills, we were not in a position to know which Bill would go through first and we therefore had to provide in both Bills for judicial notice of the seal of the Commissioners of Public <Col N="496" /> Works.  The State Property Bill having been enacted and, in Section 23, having provided judicial notice for the seal of the Commissioners of Public Works, it is accordingly unnecessary now to provide in this Bill also for the same thing.  I am, therefore, asking the Seanad to agree to these two verbal deletions: in one case, the deletion of the word &ldquo;common&rdquo;&mdash;the seal was described in one place as a common seal, and, in the State Property Bill and other legislation, it is described as the seal, and it is better that the same wording should be used here&mdash;and in the other, the deletion of the provision by virtue of which the seal of the Commissioners of Public Works will be judicially noticed, because, in fact, that has been provided by the State Property Bill passed here at the last sitting.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>The following Government amendment was also agreed to:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 5, Section 18, to delete sub-section (3).</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Trade Loans (Guarantee) (Amendment) Bill," RHead="1954&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Trade Loans (Guarantee) (Amendment) Bill, 1954&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: That the Bill be now read a Second Time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Crotty) Patrick J. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Crotty)</NameTxt>
      <P>Since 1924 there has been legislation enabling the Minister for Industry and Commerce to provide guarantees for loans to assist in industrial development both for new industries and for established concerns wishing to expand their activities where the granting of guarantees was calculated to promote employment.  The legislation also provided for the actual grant of loans for similar purposes although in fact this power has never been used.</P>
      <P>As a preliminary to the guaranteeing or granting of any loan under the Trade Loans Acts it is necessary to consult an advisory committee and the sanction of the Minister for Finance is also required before facilities can be granted by the Minister for Industry and Commerce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="497" /> The first legislative provision was made in the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Act, 1924, which provided that guarantees or loans might be granted to companies and public authorities for the purpose of meeting expenditure to buildings, plant and machinery and other fixed assets.  The operation of this Act was limited to one year but by a series of amending Acts from 1925 to 1932 inclusive the Minister's powers were continued.</P>
    <P>In 1933 the scope of the trade loans scheme was extended by the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Act of that year which enabled loans to be guaranteed or granted for the provision of working capital in addition to the acquisition of fixed assets.  At the same time individuals, as distinct from companies, became eligible for trade loan facilities.</P>
    <P>The duration of the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Act, 1933, was limited to five years and, on its expiry, the Minister's powers in regard to trade loans were renewed for another five years by the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Act, 1939, which also fixed £1,000,000 as the total of guarantees and loans which might be granted under that Act.  These powers were renewed for further periods of five years in 1944 and 1949.</P>
    <P>The Trade Loans (Guarantee) (Amendment) Act, 1953, increased to £1,500,000 the total of guarantees and loans which might be granted, and also removed the limitation of the period during which grants or guarantees might be given.</P>
    <P>Of the £1,500,000 provided under the Acts of 1939 and 1953 the Minister has given his guarantee or has indicated his willingness to give such guarantee to the extent of £1,241,000 and further applications in respect of substantial amounts are under consideration. Inquiries are constantly being received regarding the provision of financial assistance for industry by way of trade loan guarantees, and I am satisfied, therefore, that it is desirable, at this stage, to increase the existing limit of £1,500,000.</P>
    <P>The purpose of this Bill is, therefore, to increase by £1,000,000 the aggregate capital amount of loans which may be granted or guaranteed.</P>
    <P>It is very desirable that some <Col N="498" /> machinery should continue to exist to enable me, with a view to the promotion of employment, to afford financial assistance for industrial development which might not in the ordinary way appeal to the banks or to other financial institutions, including the Industrial Credit Company, Limited. The advantage of the trade loans (guarantee) system, as compared with ordinary commercial banking facilities, is that it provides a fixed long term period of repayment for which industrialists can budget in their costings. Banks normally require loans to be repaid over a short period, usually less than five years, whilst the Industrial Credit Company affords financial assistance to industry mostly in cases of large amounts where public issues can be arranged.</P>
    <P>Under the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Acts from 1924 to 1953 guarantees were given in the case of 117 undertakings amounting in the aggregate to £2,191,411.  In addition guarantees have been promised to the extent of £202,000 in six cases in which certain legal and financial arrangements have yet to be completed by the firms concerned. In the case of 71 undertakings the loans totalling £761,411 were fully repaid by the borrowers, while 19 undertakings, two of them public authorities, are actively operating at present with the assistance of guarantees totalling £827,500.  In the case of 27 undertakings involving guarantees totalling £602,740 it was necessary to appoint receivers and some of these companies ceased to operate.  Repayments to the Exchequer in cases where receivers were appointed amounted to £157,500.  Total losses to the Exchequer were £443,786 (including interest).</P>
    <P>The purpose of the Bill, as already indicated, is to increase by £1,000,000 to £2,500,000 the aggregate capital amount of loans which may be granted or guaranteed.  I trust that the House will see its way to approve of the Bill as an agreed measure.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl aimhreas ar bith ná gur scéim ionmholta an scéim seo.  Ceapadh an scéim chun cabhrú le gnóthaí go mbíonn riosc <Col N="499" /> mór ag baint leo, riosc cómh mór sin nach bhfeileann sé do na gnáth hinstitiuidí airgeadais an t-airgead atá riachtanach a chur ar fáil dóibh.  Is maith liom an ráiteas sin a rinneadh thar ceann an Aire, gur dóigh leis gur ceart go mbeadh slí ann le go bhféadfadh sé cabhair airgid a chur ar fáil le haghaidh gnóthaí nach féidir dóibh cabhair d'fháil sa ngnáth-shlí ó na gnáth-institiuidí airgeadais.  Rinneadh a lán casaoide ins na blianta atá caite nuair a luaigh an tAire Tionscail agus Tráchtála a bhí ann san am an prionsabal seo ach tá cruthaithe ag an aimsir go raibh an ceart aige.  Is maith liom go bhfuil an tAire atá anois ann ar an aigne leanúint do bheartas an Aire a bhí ann roimhe.</P>
      <P>Ba cheart dom an tuairim seo a lua ina thaobh sin, gur dóigh liom go bhfuil gá le i bhfad níos mó cabhrach faoi scéim an Bhille seo ná mar a tugadh go dtí seo.  Tá mé ag smaoineamh ar na ceantracha cúnga agus ar cheantracha na Gaeltachta go speisialta.  Tá mé tagaithe ar an aigne nach foláir rud éigin as an gcoiteantacht a dhéanamh ar son na gceantracha sin.  An tAcht um Limistéirí Neamhfhorbartha is Acht maith é; tá cuid mhaith déanta faoi agus níl aimhreas ar bith nach ndéanfar a thuille faoi.  Ach, ag an am céanna, ní mheasaim go mbainfear an oiread leasa agus is gá as an Acht sin chun cuidiú leis na ceantracha cúnga, má tá muid, sa chéad áit, leis an imirce a stopadh agus caighdeán maireachtála na ndaoine a ardú mar ba chóir.  Ar an ábhar sin, tá mé féin tagaithe ar an tuairim nach féidir bheith ag braith ar na banncana teacht isteach níos mó agus airgead a chur ar fáil i gcóir gnóithe ins na ceantracha sin, agus go mbeidh fós ar an Stát teacht isteach agus cuidiú le rathaíocht iasachtaí, ionas go bhféadfadh duine príobháideach agus an Stát teacht agus fiontraíochta a chur ar bun.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Is maith liom go bhfuil glactha ag an Aire leis an bprionsabal go mbíonn ócáideacha tábhachtacha ann nuair nach féidir le lucht gnótha agus lucht tionscail an chabhair atá riachtanach agus an t-airgead atá riachtanach d'fháil ó na banncana, ón gComhairle <Col N="500" /> Creidmheasa Tionscail, agus mar sin de, agus go bhfuil an tAire féin sásta teacht i gcabhair orthu.</P>
    <P>Tar éis a bhfuil luaite ag an Aire go raibh cailliúint ar an scéim sna blianta atá caite, sílim gur chruthaigh na figiúirí a tugadh sa Dáil agus atá tugaithe anseo trathnóna, gur éirigh go maith leis an scéim.  Ceadaíodh cabhair do 117 gnóthaí nó fiontraíochta. Agus tá rathaíocht geallta do sé cinn eile.  Bhféidir nach mór an méid sin, ach is fianaise é go bhféadfadh a leithéid do thionscail a bheith ann, agus gur fheil sé iad a chur ar bun; gur bhfiú iad a chur ar bun agus gur éirigh leis an oiread sin díobh a mbealach a íoc agus na hiasachtaí a aisíoc, agus gur éirigh le cuid eile díobh a mbealach a íoc agus go mbeidh siad ábalta na hiasachtaí a aisíoc.  Is cruthú é ar thairbhe agus éifeacht na scéime seo agus ar riachtanas na scéime chomh maith.  Cinnte, ní thaithníonn sé linn gur chlis ar 27 de na tionscail seo; is mór an truagh é gur gá deireadh a chur leo.  Ní thaithníonn linn gur raibh cailliúint leath-mhilliún punt ar na tionscail sin, ach nuair a chuimhníos duine ar an achar aimsire a bhí ann ó tosaíodh ar chabhair a thabhairt do na tionscail seo agus nuair a chuimhníos duine go mór bhór ar na deacrachtaí speisialta a bhain le bunú tionscal i dtús ré na scéime, féadaimis a rá nach cailliúnt as bealach é an leath-mhilliún, nó fá bhun leath-mhilliún, atá i gceist.</P>
    <P>Ar aon chaoi, tá mé fhéin go láidir ar an tuairim gur beartas ciallmhar an beartas seo.  Tá mé an tsásta leis an gcabhair a tugadh go dtí seo do thionscail agus ní bheidh ionadh ar bith orm má bhíonn éileamh níos treise ar chabhair na scéime.  Tá súil agam, má thagann a leithéid sin d'éileamh ar chuidiú do lucht tionscail in aon cheantar cúng, go mbeidh oiread cabhair le fáil ag lucht an bheartais sin agus is féidir a thabhairt dóibh. Táimid anseo an sásta go bhfuil an Bille ann agus tá súil againn go mbeidh tairbhe fónta air.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I would say that industry generally will be glad to see an extension of the guarantees which it is proposed to give under this Bill. <Col N="501" /> I think, however, that industrialists would be more pleased if the losses already sustained did not represent such a high percentage of the total amount lent.  I should be glad if the Parliamentary Secretary, when replying, would tell me whether the Government have tried to underwrite these losses, or if there is any way whereby it would be possible to have them underwritten.  The figure of £443,000 odd of a loss as against the total amount lent seems to me to be extraordinarily high.  I do not want to pinpoint the blame, but it seems to me to be a very high risk amount in proportion to the total amount</P>
      <P>This is the sort of Bill which could do small industries in this country a tremendous amount of good.  It was designed and devised mainly for the purpose of helping small industries. I am sorry that it has not got a great deal more publicity than has been given to it, because we still have in the country many industries which could avail of the services provided by it if they were aware of them.  In the very early years of this Parliament, industry generally had recourse to this method of getting loans under the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Acts, but for many years now industry seems to have found some other method of financing itself, so that the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Acts, have, to a certain extent, lapsed into abeyance. I wish that the Government would find some way of publicising the fact that the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Acts are still in operation, and that they are prepared to lend money to sound concerns, and sometimes to eoncerns not so sound, the establishment of which would be of advantage to our international trade.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the early days of the Sinn Féin movement this was the sort of Bill which people like Senator Hayes, myself and others considered could be of great assistance to small industrialists&mdash;to those who would be coming along in the future seeking help to enable them to establish themselves. I think it was to a large extent due to our agitation in those days that the idea arose for the introduction <Col N="502" /> and implementation of a Bill of this kind.</P>
    <P>I should be glad if the Parliamentary Secretary could tell me what are the average lending rates.  I understand that they compare more than favourably with the lending rates which are available from the ordinary financial institutions.  I should also like to know how these rates compare with the ordinary bank rates?  I understand that on long-term lending the rate of interest charged is very low.  From information given in the newspapers recently in regard to recent lending, I was rather astonished to observe the low rate of interest that is charged in the case of this particular lending.</P>
    <P>The only complaint which I have received as regards the operation of the Act is that the period of time which elapses between the making of an application for a guarantee and the date of sanction being given seems to be unnecessarily long.  I can fully under stand, of course, in view of the losses which have been sustained that very careful inquiries must be made in regard to every proposal put forward for a loan under these Trade Loans (Guarantee) Acts.  But even allowing for that and for the fact that there must be a careful review of the whole position in regard to applications put forward, I still think that the period of time that elapses is excessively long.  I should be glad if the Parliamentary Secretary could tell me whether I am right in the statement that I have made and if my information is correct or otherwise.  If my information is correct, then I think that something should be done to remedy the position to which I have adverted.</P>
    <P>I should like again to welcome the Bill.  I think that this increase of £1,000,000 may, to some extent, recoup the losses under previous lending and I hope, too, that it will help a number of our small industries especially in the rural areas which are badly in need of help.  I think that a great deal of good would accrue if the fact were publicised that these loans are available at low rates of interest, and if those who are operating the measure <Col N="503" /> were prepared to make that fact known.  They should not hide their offers under a bushel.  I think the Parliamentary Secretary did tell us that money had been lend to 117 industries and that quite a number of applications are at present under review.  The fact that an additional £1,000,000 is being made available under this Bill should enable industrialisation to go ahead, especially in the case of rural industries which could benefit to a great extent under a measure such as this.  It is of great consequence that they should get every help.  I hope that the House will give its approval to this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOCarroll" hpid="Dr. ffrench-O'Carroll Dr. ffrench-O'Carroll">
      <NameTxt>Dr. ffrench-O'Carroll</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very glad indeed to see the Parliamentary Secretary coming back to the House looking for more money to continue these Trade Loans (Guarantee) Acts. I am sorry that he is not looking for very much more money.  The first time that I became acquainted with legislation of this character, it struck me that there was behind it a splendid idea.  A measure of this kind can be of enormous benefit to the country. The thing that surprised me most of all when I looked into the operation of these Acts was the point which has just been made by Senator O'Donnell, namely, that there seems to be such extraordinarily little use made of the advantages which they offer.  People do not seem to know of these measures and consequently they are only availed of to a very limited extent.  I would be rather interested to know what are the reasons for that because it seems to me there must be some reason for it.  I do not think it is merely a matter of publicity.  It may be that perhaps people look at this legislation from the wrong angle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In my opinion legislation of this kind could be of enormous advantage to the country.  We know that it is very difficult to get capital to develop a business.  Perhaps I should not put the matter that way.  It might be more correct to say that certain people and certain business groups can get money at any time or practically all the time, but that, as far as <Col N="504" /> the ordinary business person is concerned, it is very difficult to raise capital.  Perhaps I should put it this way, that when he does succeed in getting it the rate of interest is very high or the term of repayment may be very stiff.  In this country we seem to have abundant confidence in those who have succeeded and, no matter what the amount may be, we are prepared to give it to them.  On the other hand, the powers that be, the banks, the lending public and everybody else seem to have very little confidence in the young man or in the small industrialist, in the man who wants to make a start in business or to enlarge an already existing small business.</P>
    <P>If his collateral is not very extensive he is not going to get the capital except on high terms of interest and repayment.  It all comes back to the view that this is an old man's country in business as well as everything else.  Then I suppose the younger people have not very much confidence in the older people either, so that I felt that legislation of this kind might be a great help because it might allow a far-seeing and progressive Minister in the interests of the country, employment and everybody concerned, to adopt a far less rigid attitude in regard to making capital available for new industries or for the extension of existing small industries.  I wonder if that has not, in practice, turned out to be the position.  I may say I have not had experience of many being successful. From the one or two I was interested in, I learned that when somebody went to the Minister for Industry and Commerce for a loan under the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Act it was just as difficult as going to the banks&mdash;in fact, I think the Department of Industry and Commerce required a much more searching inquiry in one respect than the banks.  I got the impression that this Department went into the running of business much more fully than the banks.</P>
    <P>I like Senator O'Donnell, would like to know what the rate of interest is and what the terms of repayment are. We have talked about the high rate of interest the banks charge and how enormous the security has to be.  This <Col N="505" /> is a question that rests in the Minister's hands&mdash;the encouragement of new industries or the extension of existing industries.  We would like a much more progressive and liberal financial arrangement than, for example, the banks.  I would like very much to see how big the discrepancy is between the financial attitude of the Minister in these things and the financial attitude of the banks if they were offered the same proposition.  I do not agree with Senator O'Donnell about this being worth £400,000.  If this is not a success, there are bound to be a certain number of losses on it.  While I welcome this Bill, I would like to be satisfied that the fault of its not being more widely used does not lie with the Minister or his policy.  Is the lack of initiative on the part of people due to the fact that they do not realise that such legislation is there?  Perhaps the Parliamentary Secretary would be good enough to clear up some of these points.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I approve of this Bill.  The only reason I want to speak is that I have had a certain amount of experience of the working of the Act.  I think it has worked admirably and has been most useful.  Senator O'Donnell has referred to certain losses that the Minister sustained.  I think it is only natural that the Minister might have to take some losses because the trade loan is for new industries only.  I think that the Minister is quite right in taking certain risks.  From my own experience I know of one successful industry which would not have been established but for the existence of the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Act.  I think that the successful industries which are established eventually more than repay the State for the losses that may occasionally be incurred in an unsuccessful venture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Several Senators have referred to the amount of investigation that takes place.  I must say that in my experience the investigation has never been unreasonable or unduly prolonged.  I think it is only right that the Department should look very fully into a particular industry before it grants the loan.  Several Senators have referred <Col N="506" /> to how greater use is not being made of the Act.  I would think that the reason for that is perhaps that the trade loan guarantees essentially provide for repayment over a comparatively short period, say, about 12 years.  I do not see what alternative there is.  It is, of course, a difficulty, particularly in a new industry which is starting up to look forward to providing both interest and capital to pay back the loan.  I think that is a difficulty that is inherent in any system of trade loan guarantees but, personally, I do not see how it can be got over. I think another reason is that if an industry of this same type runs after five years probably then it is sufficiently on its feet to be able to obtain accommodation elsewhere.  I support the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of explanation, I think that Senator Cox and Senator ffrench-O'Carroll misinterpreted what I said.  What I spoke about was disproporitionate losses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>It was exactly on that point I want to make one or two remarks.  I agree with Senator O'Donnell that the proportion of the losses is significantly high and as a taxpayer I would like to express some anxiety that £443,000 should have been lost out of a total of £1,500,000.  I should like to ask the Parliamentary Secretary to clarify two points&mdash;I may have missed some of his opening remarks and if so would he be good enough to repeat them for me.  I should like to ask him was this sum of £443,000 a total loss or will some of it be recovered eventually.  I should also like to ask him was the total amount of the £1,500,000 expended or was some of it not applied for.  I would like to support Senator O'Donnell's suggestion that it might be possible to insure against these losses.  It would seem public policy is inclined to favour raising the subsidies. We are raising them now to £2,500,000; perhaps next year it will be £3,500,000.  If our losses on each of these sums are to amount to almost one-third I think the taxpayer will view it with considerable anxiety, so <Col N="507" /> I would like the Parliamentary Secretary to reassure us on these points.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>I was rather surprised to hear the Minister coming in with arguments for increased trade loan facilities while we have at the moment the Credit Corporation Company and the Agricultural Credit Corporation, Limited.  Is it really necessary that we should have a third credit corporation in the country?  Surely the Minister made a statement that the reason the Trade Loan Act was asked for was that the Credit Corporation Company was not prepared to give money unless it was paid off in a certain period.  I understand that the money you are going to give to an individual or a group of individuals for the development of industry is money that will come eventually from the banks.  If that is so, I think that the financing of industry has perhaps a lot of unreality about it.  Here we have the Agricultural Credit Corporation, we have the Industrial Credit Corporation, we have trade loans and yet this House is not in a position to lend £100 to anybody in this country for development except they have recourse to the banks.  Is not that the position?  Is it not time for us to tell the people how helpless we are as a Government about the question of issuing money for the development of industry?  I could not agree with Senator ffrench O'Carroll when he said that people do not seem to know about this facility.  The fact that we have lost £602,000&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>I said the losses arising.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>We lent about £827,000 and we have a possible loss of £600,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>No, £400,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>Have we any indication why that loss was so severe?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>It shows the risk in giving money to businesses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>You have to borrow before you give the money to individuals. Is not that so?  The Parliamentary Secretary, representing the Minister for Finance, has to go to the <Col N="508" /> banks to get credit and then he gives it to individuals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>We guarantee in the bank.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>The State has to make good the loss.  If we want to deal seriously with this matter of financing industry, the sooner we start telling the people what should be done, the better.  We here are like children, depending on the banks to give us money.  I am anxious to learn from the Parliamentary Secretary what we pay the banks for the money and what the individual who will get this money from the trade loans will be charged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that I, in common with most Senators, would welcome any measure which would facilitate the investment of more money in our country for the provision of employment.  I have two regrets in regard to this particular measure.  One is that the Parliamentary Secretary is not asking for an increase to something far higher than £2,500,000 and, secondly, that we were not given the benefit of some White Paper on the subject.</P>
      <P>There seems to be wholesale confusion in the Seanad this afternoon about what we are doing.  Quite frankly, I am as confused as some other Senators.  It seems to me&mdash;I am open to correction&mdash;that the main purpose of this Bill is to increase the overall limit by which the Minister can guarantee loans to £2,500,000.  And whilst the overall limit previously was £1,500,000, I have certainly not taken the impression that £1,500,000 was spent and that £443,000 of that was lost.  It seems to me that the overall limitation to the guaranteeing of loans of £1,500,000 must have been exercised over and over again.  The £1,500,000 would be the limit that would be guaranteed at any one particular time.  It is not the spending of money.  It was the overall guarantee. As £443,000 has been lost in the years, it seems to me to be quite insignificant &mdash;insignificant if we have by the previous Act set up industries which have provided employment here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="509" /> I hope that the Parliamentary Secretary will give me some correction and education on this matter which might also be of assistance to other Senators.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní mór ná go bhfuilim ar aon-aigne le cuid den méid adúirt an Seanadóir atá tar éis suí síos.  Ar an gcéad dul síos, is mór an trua nach raibh an t-eolas a thug an Rúnaí Parlaiminte dúinn inniu againn sar a dtángamar isteach.  Dá mbeadh, is fearr go mór d'fhéadfaimis breithniú a dhéanamh ar an gceist seo.  Tá a lán figiúirí tábhachtacha i gceist maidir leis an mBille seo.  Ba mhaith linn a fháil amach conas a cailleadh an méid airgid adeir an Rúnaí Parlaiminte atá caillte. Níl mé á rá gur mór ar fad an méid é nuair a cuimhnítear ar an méid blianta atá caite agus ar an bhfás atá ar thionscal na hÉireann i rith na mblianta sin.</P>
      <P>Ach ba mhaith liom é seo a rá leis an Seanad: go bhfuilimid go léir ar thaobh a thuille tionscal do chur chun cinn sa tír ach mar sin féin ní mór don Aire agus don Rialtas, pé Rialtas atá i gcumhacht, a bheith an-chúramach i dtaobh conas a chaithtear airgead a mbeadh an tAire agus an Rialtas mar urrús leis.  Táimid anois ag cur leis an méid airgid a bheidh le fáil fé gheallúint an Rialtais.  Is mór an méadú é ceathracha faoin gcéad.  Do bheadh áthas orainn go léir dá mbeadh fás agus leathnú dá reir ar thionscal na tíre seo agus ar an méid oibre a bheidh le fáil as.  Fé mar adúirt mé, is mór an trua nach raibh an t-eolas a thug an Rúnaí Parlaiminte dúinn inniu againn agus sinn ag teacht isteach.  Dá mbeadh, is fearr d'fhéadfaimis an scéal a bhreithniú.  Táim i bhfábhar an Bhille agus do bheinn i bhfábhar an ruda adúirt an Seanadóir Ó Buachalla gur cheart dúinn, dá mb'fhéidir é, níos mó tionscailiú do dhéanamh sna ceanntracha cúnga.  Timpeall Bhaile Átha Cliath is mó atá an tionscal ag fás.</P>
      <P>Cuireadh Acht i bhfeidhm tamall gearr ó shoin chun an scéal do leigheas. B'fhéidir go dtiocfaidh tairbhe éigin as an Acht sin.  Tá súil agam go dtiocaidh. Sin a bhfuil le rá agam.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="510" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>There were a few points raised in regard to clarification. Except for that everybody seems to be quite satisfied with the Bill. Senator Ó Buachalla seems to be under a misapprehension about this Bill.</P>
      <P>He thinks that it came in in the 1930s.  The Bill was originally introduced in 1924.  The Senator also suggests that the terms of this Bill should be extended still further to the under developed areas.  Fóras Tionscail have been dealing with that matter as far as possible.  They give quite considerable advances by way of free grants to industries in the undeveloped areas.  However, in certain cases where Fóras Tionscail have given an advance, the industry can also get the benefit of a trade loan guarantee.  Therefore, as far as the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Act is concerned, I think it could be used, plus the other grant which is also given.</P>
      <P>Senator O'Donnell suggests that we might get some other way of underwriting these losses.  Under this Bill, the Government, actually, are underwriting the losses which occur.  It is because nobody could be got to underwrite certain losses that, originally, the Government had to step in and introduce the first Trade Loans (Guarantee) Act.</P>
      <P>There was general discussion on the rate of interest.  I might point out that the Government do not raise this money in the banks and hand it to certain industrialists.  They guarantee the industrialist in the bank.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>What does the bank charge?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>The rate is 4 per cent. when the Government give the guarantee but the bank rate is 5 per cent.  The term of repayment is spread over a period of from ten to 20 years and it is done by way of annuity. Therefore, the promoters of the industry for which a trade loan is given know the actual amount repayable over every period in that 20 years and they can make provision accordingly in their costings.  If, on the other hand, they get a loan from a bank, <Col N="511" /> repayable over five years, they could not possibly cover it in their costings over that period.</P>
      <P>I should also like to assure Senator O'Donnell that the purpose of this Bill is not to recoup the losses of £446,000 which have occurred over a period of 30 years.  The purpose of this Bill is not to recoup the losses but to extend the facilities.  At the present time, trade loan guarantees to the extent of £1,241,000 are in existence.  In addition, the Minister has promised guarantees for another £202,000 and these guarantees are awaiting final arrangements. That would bring the total amount guaranteed to £1,443,000.  That is practically the whole amount at present.  The purpose of this Bill is to extend the facilities so that the Minister does not have to close down on these trade loan guarantees.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>In other words, the credit of the nation is backing them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>Why charge 4 per cent.?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator ffrench-O'Carroll spoke of a small person developing an industry who has not collateral security.  This is really what the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Act is there for.  If the Minister and his Department can see that there is a prospect of progress and development&mdash;especially as regards employment&mdash;in an industry, then the Minister is very anxious to facilitate that industry.  If a person approaches the bank for a loan he must have guaranteed security but the Minister is prepared to take a risk in the type of case I have just mentioned, that is, for extending an industry, especially where there is a hope of increased employment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is necessary that there should be a full inquiry before a person gets a trade loan.  The average person will first go to a bank for a trade loan.  It is only as a last resort that he will come to my Department and look for a loan. This is the people's money and the Minister is the guardian of the people's money.  It is, therefore, essential that we should have a very minute research <Col N="512" /> before we give sanction.  However, that does not mean that because the research is detailed the sanction will not be given.  As I have said, the Minister is anxious to help if there is a reasonable prospect of success in the business and a reasonable prospect of more employment.</P>
    <P>Senator Stanford remarked that we have had one-third losses.  In point of fact, the losses were one-fifth, or 20 per cent.  The total amount guaranteed is £2,191,411 and, I think, the losses are something about £446,000. That proportion of losses, spread over 30 years, is very small.  We are aware that, when industries started, various proposals were made and it was only as things went on that they could be studied and gone into in a more severe manner.</P>
    <P>Senator Hickey has very many suggestions to make.  I think, however, that if he wants to avoid all these losses in industry the only way to do so would be to refuse altogether to sanction these loans&mdash;and I do not think any Senator would say that that should be done.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not suggest any such thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>If you want to extend your business you must use your money and you must take the risk of losing it.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>As this Bill is a Money Bill, could all stages be taken to-day?</P>
      <P>Agreed to take the remaining stages now.</P>
      <P>Bill considered in Committee.</P>
      <P>Section 1 put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>In his reply, the Parliamentary Secretary said that the bank charge to-day is 5 per cent. and that the rate under this Bill is 4 per cent.  Recently, I saw a certain trade loan guarantee on the Table of the House and the rate of interest was as low as 2½ per cent.  I do not know <Col N="513" /> when it was granted.  It was a 20 years' trade loan at 2½ per cent.  I was very interested in the Parliamentary Secretary's reply on the Second Stage and I hope his remarks will get all possible publicity because, if they do, there need be no bank strike: we shall all go for trade loans, if we can get them.  Why should anybody pay 5 per cent. if he can get the money at 4 per cent. or 2½ per cent., spread over a period of 20 years?  Is it the position that the rate of interest is always 1 per cent. below the bank rate?  May I say, in this connection, that a 20 per cent. loss is the type of loss that would drive bankers to commit suicide?  I do not think a Government should commit suicide any more than bankers should.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the actual rate of interest on these losses?  Senator O'Donnell has mentioned 2½ per cent.  I understood the Parliamentary Secretary to mention 4 per cent. as the rate of interest chargeable on these loans.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Minister granted any loans at all?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Guaranteed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>The rate chargeable to the borrower in respect of a loan of this nature is 4 per cent.  However, if the undertaking fails and the Minister has to pay back the loan to the bank, then any interest on that loan is charged to the Minister at 2½ per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>But who pays the balance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>The bank forgives it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not my point.  Last week I saw on the Table of the House particulars of a guarantee in respect of a 20 years' trade loan at a rate of 2½ per cent.  If the Parliamentary Secretary wants any further details I shall give them privately to him because I do not want to discuss anybody's affairs in public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>Where the undertaking <Col N="514" /> fails and the Minister has to repay the loan, the rate of interest charged to the Minister on that loan is 2½ per cent., but as regards getting an ordinary loan at 2½ per cent.  I do not know where you will get that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not a fact that the Minister has not granted any loans at all in the strict sense of the word?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>He has guaranteed the loans&mdash;there is no question of granting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>He is not liable for any interest, unless in the case of a failure, and then he is liable for part of the interest?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>He is liable for 2½ per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>And the banks charge 4 per cent. where there is no risk involved, where the credit of the State is the guarantee in respect of the main loan?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>And you pay only 2½ per cent., if there is a failure?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJCrotty" hpid="Mr. Crotty Mr. Crotty">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crotty</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope everybody will draw the proper moral from that.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 3 and 4 and the Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be returned to the Dáil.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to correct any misunderstanding which may have arisen in the mind of the Parliamentary Secretary from what I said.  I am saying that it is he, as representing the Minister for Finance, who should be in a position to lend money to people who want to develop industries. He should be in a position to do so, and I hope this House and the Dáil will ensure that the Government will be in a position to enable the Central <Col N="515" /> Bank to do the work it should be doing in this country.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Solicitors Bill, 1954&mdash;Committee" RHead="and Final Stages">
    <Title>Solicitors Bill, 1954&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete paragraph (a) and substitute a new paragraph as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a) Parts VII and VIII and Section 72 of this Act shall come into operation on the passing of this Act.</P>
      <P>Apparently it was intended originally that this Bill should come into operation long before now.  It is necessary that the regulations under the Act, under Section 5, should be drafted by the Incorporated Law Society, that they should be approved by the Chief Justice and laid before both Houses of the Oireachtas.  It appears to me that there is not sufficient time now to lay the regulations before both Houses of the Oireachtas, if the Oireachtas is to adjourn this week, and I suggest that we should permit the regulations to be studied by the members of the profession before they are accepted or before they become law.  If, for instance, the members of this House did not get an opportunity of making representations concerning the regulations made by the Government affecting them, naturally they would be much resented by the members, and accordingly the members of the solicitors' profession as a body should, in my opinion, have an opportunity to study the regulations which affect their activities to such a very large extent.</P>
      <P>If the Minister refers to Section 47, he will see that it sets out:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;A solicitor applying for a practising certificate shall, in person or by his agent, deliver to the registrar a declaration which&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(a) shall be in the form set out in <Col N="516" /> the Third Schedule to this Act or in a form to the like effect approved of by the society....&rdquo;</P>
    <P>If we refer then to the Third Schedule, paragraph (3) (c), it will be noted that the form of application sets out:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I have, to the best of my knowledge and belief, complied with the Solicitors' Accounts Regulations</P>
    <P Just="Center">(or)</P>
    <P>I have not complied with the Solicitors' Accounts Regulations in the following respects....&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Then, (d) sets out:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;A copy of the Solicitors' Accounts Regulations now in force is printed in full on the back of this form.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I suggest that the application cannot be in that particular form this year and it is mandatory under that section that the application should be in that particular form.  Accordingly I suggest that, unless the regulations can be brought into force before 6th January, Section 47 of the Bill could not apply. I ask, therefore, that Parts VII and VIII and Section 72 should be the only parts of the Bill which should be brought into force now and that the remaining sections should not be brought into force until 6th January, 1956.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I would hope that the Seanad would not adopt the amendment and, indeed, I would hope that perhaps the Senator might withdraw it.  The profession have been pressing this Bill for about 15 years and it is, in their opinion, a very urgent matter that it should come into operation as soon as possible.  Not only is the council of the Law Society in favour of it, but no representations have been received from any local Bar association&mdash;these are the local bodies &mdash;suggesting that there should be any adjournment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Senator has suggested that the accounts regulations should not come into effect until a year from now, but in fact it would not be the intention that they would be enforced until 5th January, 1956.  That has been carefully looked into and it is, I think, quite clear that there is no conflict <Col N="517" /> between the form of the certificate in the Third Schedule and the regulations that will be made.  If the amendment were carried, it would have the effect of bringing only parts of the Bill into operation, and would make it extremely difficult to operate it.</P>
    <P>I ask the Seanad to allow the Bill to come into operation immediately.  I do not know whether the Senator would withdraw his amendment to enable that to be done, but I can assure him that the difficulty he apprehends as to the regulations would not arise in practice.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be prepared to withdraw the amendment if the Minister would accept the amendment to Section 5, providing that no regulation shall be made by the council unless it has previously been approved by the society.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is another question which does not arise now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment refers to Section 72.  I should like to know to whom the £14 mentioned there is to be paid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to Senator Walsh's reference to the next amendment which deals with the regulations, as the Bill stands the regulations are made by the society, that is to say by the council.  The Senator is asking that they should be made by the society in general meeting.  I think that would be quite impracticable.  The council of the Law Society is a democratically elected body.  It consists of some 31 members who are elected by the body at a general election every year.  If the members of the council were to act in some way that was not thought proper by the profession as a whole, then the profession could deal very easily with them.  As I have said, I think it would be a quite impracticable proposal that the regulations should be made at a general meeting.  That would mean a general meeting of the members of the Law Society attended by a couple of hundred people.  I suggest that it would be quite impracticable to make regulations under those conditions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="518" /> Again, I say that the regulations must be made by a small body.  Under the Bill, when it becomes an Act, they are to be laid before both Houses of the Oireachtas, and the council which makes them is composed of the elected nominees of the society.  Perhaps the Senator would consider that point.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not intend that the general body should make the regulations but simply that they should approve of the regulations which are made by the council.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment dealing with that, Senator, is not under discussion.  What we are discussing at the moment is amendment No. 1 to Section 2.  Is the Senator pressing the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked a question about the £14 and I have not been told anything about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator can raise that on Section 72.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 2 not moved.</P>
      <P>Section 2 put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 3 and 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 3:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To add a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(4) No regulation shall be made by the council unless it has previously been approved by a general meeting of the society.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>All that I am asking in this amendment is that these regulations should be approved of at a general meeting of the society.  I think that is the democratic way of doing it.  These regulations will affect to a very great extent, and in many different ways, the activities of members of the profession. Regulations must be made under Sections 20, 40 and 66 and under No. 19 of the Fifth Schedule.  I feel, in view of the fact that these regulations must be laid before both Houses <Col N="519" /> of the Oireachtas, that they should be discussed after they have been drawn up by the general body of solicitors at a general meeting before they come into force.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already tried to deal with the point which the Senator has made.  I fail to see how regulations could be approved before they have been made.  The Senator's proposal reminds me of the Scottish remark: &ldquo;If you had seen these robes before they were made, you would bless the name of General Wade.&rdquo;  It seems to me that the regulations must be made before they can be approved. As I have already pointed out, if the council were to act in some arbitrary way, then the society, as a whole, has its remedy.  A general meeting could be called to deal with it.  I think that if the Senator's amendment were accepted, it would make the working of the Act extraordinarily cumbersome and, therefore, I would ask the Seanad not to adopt it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not see anything unreasonable about this amendment. It simply asks that, if the council of the Incorporated Law Society makes regulations, they should be approved of at a general meeting of the society.  I do not think there is anything unreasonable in asking the House to accept the amendment.  Its acceptance will not make the operation of the Bill, when it becomes an Act, any more difficult.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely the meaning of the amendment is that a general meeting of the society will make the regulations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>That they will approve of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>What are they going to approve of?  I suggest that this proposal would provide a cumbersome procedure.  It means that the council will frame regulations and suggest them to the society.  The idea then is, apparently, that if the society does not approve of them, the council will frame other regulations, or is it that a general meeting of the council is to be given a power which, by the <Col N="520" /> way, the Oireachtas is not being given in this case, of amending the regulations? It seems to me to be a more practical method that 30 people should frame the regulations.  May I say that in my experience 30 people would represent a very big meeting for the framing of regulations?  I think it would be too big.  The idea that a general meeting of solicitors who, I presume, would be worse than a general meeting of non-legal people, should get together for the framing of regulations, opens up an appalling prospect.</P>
      <P>I think that the Incorporated Law Society is wise in suggesting&mdash;and by the way the Minister has agreed to the suggestion&mdash;that the regulations should be made by the council of the society.  Senator Cox has pointed out that if regulations are made by the council which do not meet with the general approval of the members, there is machinery by which the council can be called together and other regulations made.  I think it is far better that, when regulations are to be made, they should be made by a small body.  When they are made they must be laid on the Table of both Houses, and if they are not approved of, some action can be taken about them.  The proposal in the amendment seems to me to be a peculiarly cumbersome arrangement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to point out that the amendment has been put down merely for the purpose of enabling the ordinary solicitor to make representations at the general meeting with regard to any regulation which he, as an individual, would regard as in any way cumbersome, wrong or unjust.  Accordingly, the council can still make the regulations, but this amendment, if accepted, would give the ordinary solicitor a right of audience.  Otherwise, regulations may be made of which the ordinary solicitor has no knowledge until they become an accomplished fact.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a general meeting of the Law Society twice a year. Therefore, there can be no question that a member will not have an opportunity of raising any matter that he <Col N="521" /> wishes.  I would remind the Senator that this council is composed of solicitors elected by their colleagues from all parts of the country.  I think it is quite inconceivable that solicitors, elected by their fellow solicitors from every county in Ireland, are likely to make regulations which would be injurious to the whole body of the members.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Everett) James Everett">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Everett)</NameTxt>
      <P>I would point out to the Senators that I am in favour of democratic control. That being so, the council of the Law Society have a right to make their own regulations, submit them to their general body which meets twice a year, and if the general body, the same as any other democratic organisation, does not like the rules made by their executive committee they have a remedy.  Just the same as Senators and Deputies themselves have to give an account of their stewardship to their electors, so will the council of the Law Society have to give an account to their members.  For that reason I do not like to tie them down in connection with it.  I am certain that the Law Society will act fairly to all sections.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>In answer to the Minister, there will be no general meeting of the society for at least five months and as these regulations must come into force within the next two or three weeks there would not be, as the Minister points out, any democratic method in which the members of the society as a whole would have any knowledge or be entitled in any way to make representations concerning any regulation which has been made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>May one inquire if there is any machinery for calling a special meeting of the society?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>There is, under the society's regulations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>In connection with Senator's Hickey's statement, the £14 stamp money is paid into the society in King's Inns under Section 28 of the Stamp Act, 1791.  The payment has been going on since the 18th century.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="522" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>Am I to understand that is not being passed on to the State?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>To the Revenue Commissioners.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I submit that £1 should be sufficient instead of £14.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator pressing the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 5 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 6 to 11, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 12.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 12 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to point out to the Minister that apparently it is mandatory that the Registrar of Deaths should inform the registrar of the society.  It might happen that a registrar was not aware of the occupation of a solicitor who had died and accordingly he may not be able to perform the duty that has been cast upon him under this particular section.  I thought that the Minister could, on the Report Stage, put &ldquo;whose occupation is given as a solicitor&rdquo; after the words &ldquo;whose name is on the roll.&rdquo;  That matter was raised already in the Dáil and that is why I am raising it again on this particular section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that it would really give rise to any difficulty. The position is the same as in the case of the Medical Council, the Veterinary Council, and other similar bodies.  In practice, I do not think any difficulty whatever arises.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 13.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 13 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>There is just one point upon which I do not feel quite satisfied.  It is in relation to sub-section (5)&mdash;the quorum of the disciplinary committee shall be three.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="523" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been changed to five.  The Senator is looking at an old copy of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry. I was wrongly informed.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 14.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 4:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), line 22, to delete &ldquo;shall&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;may&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The making of an application to the disciplinary committee should not be mandatory in my opinion and the word &ldquo;may&rdquo; seems more appropriate than &ldquo;shall&rdquo;.  It is clear that no person should be allowed to make an application against a solicitor unless the solicitor has acted as a solicitor for that particular person or body corporate.  I would ask the Minister therefore to insert the word &ldquo;may&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;shall&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>This is purely a drafting point.  It seems to me that &ldquo;shall&rdquo; is the appropriate word and it does not in the least imply that an application must be made at once to remove every solicitor from the roll.  All it implies is that when an application is made it shall be made to the disciplinary committee.  I think that in that it follows normal drafting practice.  If Senator Walsh considers that, he will probably see at once that &ldquo;shall&rdquo; is the correct word, otherwise there would have to be applications made immediately to remove everybody.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I am prepared to withdraw the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 5:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), paragraph (b), line 26, to delete &ldquo;another person&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;any person or body corporate for whom a solicitor has acted in the transaction of any legal business&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I suggest that the society has a right under the section and that the other person is the person for whom a solicitor acts or a body corporate.  The <Col N="524" /> words &ldquo;body corporate&rdquo; are not in that section as it stands and for that reason it would appear that it would require a person to make the application.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has opened up the point that complaints might arise against the solicitor by people who had never been actual clients of a solicitor.  There is a very obvious example. If I am acting in a trust estate and if I embezzle the money, the people from whom I embezzle it, the beneficiaries, may never have been clients of mine.  They may never have had any contact with me whatever, but I have done them a very grave wrong, and quite clearly they should be entitled to apply to the disciplinary committee against me.  I think the Senator has overlooked that to confine applications against a solicitor solely to persons aggrieved who had happened to be clients of his, would be a very great injustice.  If frivolous complaints are made by people, they can be dealt with very easily.  At the present time applications can be made against a solicitor to the present statutory committee by beneficiaries of people such as I have mentioned.  I think it has been overlooked that many complaints may arise from people justly aggrieved who could not possibly be debarred from making a complaint even though they never had actually been clients.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>It would appear, therefore, a body corporate and a local authority are still excluded under that section from making an application.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator refers to Section 64 (3) he will see the words &ldquo;body corporate&rdquo; are brought into that particular section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;In Sections 55, 58 and 59 of this Act, references to unqualified persons, and references to persons, include references to bodies corporate.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I thought that in view of the fact that Section 14 is not included amongst the three sections mentioned, the words &ldquo;body corporate&rdquo; should still be included here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="525" />
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>It is clearly established, and, in fact, it is statutory, that in a statute the word &ldquo;person&rdquo; includes body corporate and may include a partnership or bodies of that kind. The word &ldquo;person&rdquo; means much more than a single human being. If the Senator refers to Section 64 it provides that&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;a body corporate or director, officer or servant thereof, shall not do any act of such nature or in such manner as to imply that the body corporate is qualified, or recognised by law, as qualified, to act as a solicitor.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That is a wholly different matter, I think.  If the Senator will look at it, he will realise that in this section he is not dealing with the word &ldquo;person&rdquo; which automatically includes a body corporate.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 6:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), paragraph (b) (i), line 29, to insert &ldquo;professional&rdquo; before &ldquo;misconduct&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>At the moment as the section stands any misconduct ultimately would make a solicitor eligible to be struck off the roll.  I suggest that the word &ldquo;professional&rdquo; in front of &ldquo;misconduct&rdquo; should be permitted because the society have ample opportunity of striking a solicitor off the roll on too many different sections and subsections of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>It would seem to me that the word &ldquo;misconduct&rdquo; should remain as it stands.  It would be very difficult indeed to decide what was professional misconduct and what was other misconduct. There may be many matters in which a solicitor may commit serious misconduct even though it would not be professional.  He might, for instance, be a trustee of a fund; he might be a director of a company and utter some forgery.  We could have many instances even in financial matters in which it would be conceivable that a solicitor would be guilty of very serious misconduct and yet it might be very difficult to see that there was professional <Col N="526" /> misconduct.  I would ask that the House allow the general term &ldquo;misconduct&rdquo; to stand.  Again, the Senator should remember that the people who will judge this will be themselves solicitors just as the people who judge a doctor are themselves doctors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the later portion of that sub-section which states:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(i) that the solicitor has been guilty of misconduct, including conduct tending to bring the solicitors' profession into disrepute&rdquo;</P>
      <P>surely that would meet the Senator's expression of opinion as to the cases he has just cited?  If a solicitor acted in a way the Senator referred to, that in itself would be sufficient to bring the solicitors' profession into disrepute. I think that the word &ldquo;professional&rdquo; should still be included in the first line of that sub-section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>On the one hand, we are going to limit the word &ldquo;misconduct&rdquo; by adding &ldquo;professional&rdquo;, and then we are going to allow expansion as well.  I think that that section would become nonsense if we did that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>That was what I was going to say.  If the amendment were accepted the section would simply be meaningless.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister explain sub-section (c) of Section 14, which states:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(3)  The Chief Justice or any judge of the High Court may, notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, exercise any jurisdiction over solicitors which he might have exercised if this Act had not been passed.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a section which has been considered a good deal.  What really lies behind it is this.  A solicitor is an officer of the court and therefore a solicitor must always be subject to the order of the court in any case in which he is appearing.  If I am acting for a client in some case in the High Court I am an officer of the court; therefore I am subject to censure or order by the judge who is presiding. <Col N="527" /> That is common law jurisdiction which is vested in the judge, and it was therefore necessary, I understand, to insert that section to preserve that right.  If that was not so, then in the actual hearing of the case the judge could not order a solicitor about as he could order counsel about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would clarify matters very much, seeing the constitution of the disciplinary committee that is mentioned, if we were told how many members are on this committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>That information is contained in Section 13, which has been passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>It consists of not more than ten and not less than seven persons, with a quorum of five.  All these persons are, of course, solicitors. At present and in the past there has been what is called a statutory committee which has been appointed each year by the Chief Justice and which consists of about the same number of solicitors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>In connection with Senator Cox's reply, does he agree that it is not necessary to include the Circuit Court judge or district justice in that particular section?  Is the Chief Justice or judge of the High Court sufficient?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>Solicitors are officially solicitors of the High Court of Justice and therefore are subject to the judges of the High Court.  Whether we could really define judges of the High Court, I do not know.  I would not like to try.</P>
      <P>Sections 14 and 15 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 16.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 7:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), paragraph (b) (iv), line 23, to insert &ldquo;not less than twenty-one days&rdquo; after &ldquo;specified period&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In pleadings in the Circuit Court and High Court a defendant is permitted 20 days to lodge a defence.  As the affidavit which may be required under <Col N="528" /> this sub-section may take a considerable time and a good deal of research to prepare by the solicitor engaged, I am bringing in this amendment in order to allow a solicitor at least 21 days to put in an affidavit whether or not he had been struck off the roll or suspended for a time.  If in the case of an ordinary simple debt of, say, £55, the Legislature permits ten or 12 days, surely the Legislature should permit 21 days for the solicitors in a case like this?</P>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the answer to that is that the periods allowed for statements of claim and defences in actions are not fixed by statute.  They are fixed by the regulations made under the statute.  In the same way, the periods and times under this Act will be done under the Act and not by the Act itself.  The regulations under which the disciplinary committee will have to operate will be regulations made, as the Bill provides at present, by the disciplinary committee.  Again, I do not think the Senator need have the slightest uneasiness that reasonable periods will not be allowed.  After all, the members of the disciplinary committee are themselves solicitors and they might find themselves the subject of a complaint at any moment, so that it is very unlikely that anyone would draw up regulations which did not provide reasonable time.  I myself have been a member of the statutory committee for some time and there has never been a case in which any solicitor was not given a reasonable time when he asked for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good.  I am prepared to withdraw that amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 16 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 17 and 18 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 19.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 19 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>When this particular section was drafted the quorum for the disciplinary committee was then three.  It has now been increased to five.  In that section occurs: &ldquo;the offence of that person may, by certificate <Col N="529" /> signed by two members of the disciplinary committee....&rdquo;  Would the Minister consider making that three members because of the fact that it would now take at least three members of the disciplinary committee to come to a finding?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to support that suggestion.  It does look as if it has been overlooked as a consequential change.  It seems reasonable that it ought to be a majority of the quorum that should sign.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I think there is a misunderstanding. This section speaks of the certificate which is issued&mdash;the certificate that the disciplinary committee has done so-and-so and which may under this Bill be signed by two members.  That does not mean that five were not required in order to pass it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that this is the only evidence of the finding of the disciplinary committee and that it is necessary for three members of that committee to come to a conclusion, I would press the Minister to accept what I have said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Every single member of the committee might have been present and might have been unanimous.  Are not two sufficient to sign it instead of the whole lot?  What difference is there between two out of ten or three out of ten?  No difference.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the Bill as originally drafted the quorum was to be three and the certificate was to be signed by two, now increased by five, but that is no reason why the certificate should have to be signed by more.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 20.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 8:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), line 1, to delete &ldquo;disciplinary committee&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;society&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think these rules should be made by the society and not by the disciplinary committee.  It seems to me to be putting too much power in the hands of the committee that they themselves <Col N="530" /> should make these rules.  It would be preferable and desirable that the rules should be made by the society.  As the matter is an important one and as the society is the parent body it should make the regulations.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to me that this is very much the same point we had before.  If the word &ldquo;society&rdquo; was substituted it would mean the council. I would remind the Senator that whatever rules the committee draw up must under the Bill be approved. They require the concurrence of the Chief Justice.  The drawing up of these rules requires a little experience of the kind of work the disciplinary committee does.  It seems to me to be more convenient that the disciplinary committee, which understands that kind of work, should draw up the rules.  The Bill provides that the Chief Justice must concur.  If there was anything wrong or unfair with the rules that the disciplinary committee drew up the Chief Justice would not confirm them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I will withdraw the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 20 put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 21.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 21 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>The same applies to this section where it is a question of the number who shall sign the findings of the disciplinary committee.  Again, I suggest that that should be increased from two to three.  Senator Cox has already referred to the fact that the previous section only referred to the signing of a certificate, but here the question is one of the findings of the disciplinary committee.  It is, therefore, somewhat different from the mere signing of a certificate, and I will ask the Minister to increase the number from two to three on Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that I am a little bit confused.  I really thought that was the point already discussed. The Senator is speaking of sub-section (1) of Section 21?  Again this <Col N="531" /> is merely the authentication of the findings.  Under the procedure that exists at present the report of the statutory committee is signed only by one person and that is by the president of the statutory committee.  That has been the case for the past 60 or 70 years.  One signature was thought enough.  Now we have two signatures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>The committee in the old days was a very different committee from that which is now being appointed under this Bill.  Here the disciplinary committee has tremendous powers over the members of the profession. They do not have to refer the matter to the Chief Justice, who, prior to that, was the person who decided whether or not persons were to be struck off the rolls.  It is the disciplinary committee that largely takes the place of the Chief Justice.  The Chief Justice has only the right of appeal either by the applicant or by the solicitor.  As this is a question of the findings of the disciplinary committee, I respectfully suggest that the findings should be signed by three persons because it will take at least three persons to come to a definite decision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder if the Senator has given notice of this amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>Again, I suggest this is purely a matter of record.  Is it to be expected that two members of the committee are to sign some document which is absolutely false?  It is merely a certificate that such and such was found.  Surely that is merely a matter of record?  It is the kind of document which, in court proceedings, is signed by the registrar.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>In the District Court, it is the justice who signs the order.  As Senator Cox states, it is a matter of record.  I suggest, therefore, that the record would be the document which would have to be produced to the Chief Justice on an appeal as to the findings of that disciplinary committee. If that were the case and if it were the only evidence the Chief Justice would have as to the exact <Col N="532" /> findings of that disciplinary committee, I do not see why the Minister should not, on the Report Stage, accept the suggested alteration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask that the Bill remain as it stands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator asked that the matter might be considered on the Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>When shall we have the Report Stage?</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 22 put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 23.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 23 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>On this section, I should like to point out that apparently a solicitor can be put on trial twice&mdash; unlike the case of an ordinary court where, when a criminal charge is dismissed, it is sufficient to have the defendant declared a free man.  Here, the applicant who is dissatisfied with the decision of the disciplinary committee can apply again to the Chief Justice, and the Chief Justice can then have a complete rehearing and decide in a different way from the disciplinary committee.  I merely want to put on record that the Incorporated Law Society have agreed to subject their members to a much more severe discipline than the ordinary person would be subjected to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to put on record that this has been very carefully considered.  It is most unlikely that, after the disciplinary body set up by the statute has cleared the solicitor, the Chief Justice would&mdash;unless there were some very extraordinary cause or reason&mdash;decide otherwise.  However, after very long and careful consideration and consultation with the judges and consultation with the Minister, it was felt that this power should remain in the Bill.  I know it is not an amendment but, as Senator Walsh wants his remarks on the record, I, too, would like to record that this was <Col N="533" /> not arrived at in any frivolous spirit but was, rather, the result of long consideration and long discussion.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 24 to 39, inclusive, put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 40.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 9:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (4), paragraph (b), line 37, after &ldquo;solicitors&rdquo; insert &ldquo;which is so conducted and of such nature as to secure that persons who pass it have such a knowledge of law and legal practice as is sufficient to enable them act as solicitors&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The House will refer to sub-section (3) (c) and note, in connection with the Irish language examination, that the wording is somewhat similar to that of the amendment, namely, &ldquo;...for such second examination being so conducted and of such nature...&rdquo;  In the sub-section which I seek to amend&mdash;sub-section (4) (b)&mdash; there is no such wording.  In my view, the section is not complete until the words contained in the amendment are included in the sub-section in question. The meaning then will be that the examination will be an honest one, that questions will not be put in the examination which are unreasonable or too difficult and which may prevent apprentices from passing the examination if they are regarded as fit and proper and if they have a sufficient knowledge of law and its practice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely the Senator does not contemplate that the final examination conducted by the Incorporated Law Society shall be subject to some kind of appeal?  To whom? To me, the amendment does not seem to mean anything: I am saying that without offence.  It simply says that a final examination for solicitors shall be a final examination for solicitors. It does not mean anything else but that.  I did not know what the Senator meant when I first saw the amendment. However, having heard him discuss it, it seems he thinks that the papers set for the final examination should be <Col N="534" /> brought before a court and that the court could say that some of the questions would be too hard.  I am speaking as an examiner but not as a solicitor. I do not understand it at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not suggest that the section as amended should or could be brought before a court any more than the section as it is worded can be brought before a court.  I ask that in this sub-section (4) (b) the same words be used in connection with the final examination as are used in sub-section (3) (c) in connection with the Irish examination.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Irish examination is conducted on quite a different basis.  The question of what standard you will adopt in respect of a language is quite a different matter altogether. This purports to be a definition of a final examination.  I suggest you could not give one and that you must leave to the Incorporated Law Society the power to decide what they want for a final examination for solicitors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>The wording of sub-section (3) (c), which concerns the Irish examination, is taken from a separate Act which was passed about 1924 and which requires solicitors to pass these examinations in the Irish language, and that Act, being a separate Act, used these words.  I think that is the reason why these words were continued in the present section&mdash;probably merely just by copying&mdash;but I would very strongly support what Senator Hayes has said.  It seems to me that it would be merely tautology to say that the responsible professional body is to have a final examination for the profession, and then to add that that final examination should be such as would require sufficient knowledge to enable a person to exercise his profession.  I do not know if the College of Physicians or the College of Surgeons would like an Act passed saying that their final examination must be sufficient to enable a person to be a doctor or a surgeon.  As Professor Hayes has asked, who can judge?  I ask the Senator to withdraw the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="535" />
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I will do so.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 40 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to inquire in connection with this Irish examination, whether the examination comprises written and oral tests?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Written and oral.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>On both occasions? There is an Irish examination when the prospective solicitor is commencing his apprenticeship, and also an Irish examination when he is being admitted to the roll of solicitors.  Is there a written and an oral examination on both occasions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>There is both a written and an oral examination.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>On both occasions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>On both, and I may say that certainly the final one is an extremely difficult or severe examination.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 41, 42 and 43 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 44.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 10:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (3), paragraph (b), line 14, to insert &ldquo;practice and&rdquo; after &ldquo;of&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This is the section which relates to the knowledge of legislation in force in the case of a practising solicitor who has for three years held corresponding certificates in Northern Ireland.  Each year the difference in practice may become more marked and accordingly I think the word &ldquo;legislation&rdquo; may not be sufficient and that the word &ldquo;practice&rdquo; should be included.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Senator to withdraw this amendment.  The words &ldquo;adequate knowledge of the practice in force in the State&rdquo; would scarcely mean anything.  This relates to a <Col N="536" /> person who has obtained a certificate in Northern Ireland and it provides that before he can be admitted here, that is, if reciprocal provisions are made, he would have to pass an examination in the legislation.  I would suggest that the word &ldquo;legislation&rdquo; there clearly means legislation in the broad sense, in the sense in which the Romans used the word, that is, in relation to the law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I am prepared to withdraw it.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Sections 44 to 48, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 49.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 11:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), to delete paragraph (g).</P>
      <P>The section, as worded, appears to me to be too wide.  It would mean that if a solicitor fails to give an explanation, he can be suspended or his certificate can be withdrawn.  I suggest that there are sufficient subsections exercising discipline over the solicitor without the necessity for bringing in this sub-section, which relates to &ldquo;any matter affecting his conduct&rdquo;, for which he fails to give an explanation.  I respectfully suggest that that is too wide and should be deleted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>This sub-section is really one of the most important in the Bill, and, in order to understand it, one has to realise something of the solicitors' profession.  Solicitors have to do business with one another every day.  If something is going wrong with a solicitor, if he is getting short in his payments, if he is misbehaving or conducting cases unfairly or something like that, everybody else in the profession who comes in contact with him gets to know that.  In the past, one of the great difficulties has been that there has been no machinery, other than a report to the statutory committee&mdash;in future, the disciplinary committee&mdash;which really amounted to something like hanging, and very often <Col N="537" /> in the professional death of the solicitor concerned.</P>
      <P>What is sought by this section is that the council would have power, if it thinks there is something that would require an explanation on the part of a solicitor, to call on him to give an explanation and, if he does not do so, not to renew the practising certificate of that solicitor.  It gives the solicitor a right of appeal to the Chief Justice, so that, if the council were to exercise this power arbitrarily or unfairly, the solicitor concerned could at once go to the Chief Justice to obtain justice and fair treatment.</P>
      <P>I have been in practice for a long time and I have been a member of the council of the Law Society for a long time.  We all know that the profession of a solicitor is a very difficult one, particularly in this, that not alone has he to handle law but he has to handle business, and he is in the unfortunate position that, of necessity, the money of other people passes through his hands.  There have, naturally, been a number of cases in which solicitors have embezzled clients' money and have gone wrong, but I think that, in every one of these cases, it was known to other solicitors beforehand that things were going wrong, and I believe that a great number of these solicitors could have been saved, and their clients saved, if the council at that time had had power to write to the solicitor and ask him: &ldquo;Would you please explain what is going on?&rdquo; If that could have been done, I believe that there are a number of people, particularly young solicitors, who would have been saved from ruin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I certainly think that this section should be preserved.  All that it means is that if the council which, after all, is composed of a solicitor's colleagues, thinks that there is something wrong they can ask him to explain.  If he fails to explain they can then say that they will not renew his practising certificate.  If he thinks there is anything wrong in the decision of the council, he can go at once to the Chief Justice for a reverse of the council.  I certainly submit that this is a section which should not be struck out of the <Col N="538" /> Bill.  I really think it is a vital section. There is not in it the least danger to a solicitor.  Indeed, I think it is a protection for him.  I have come across cases myself of personal friends who got into great trouble when they found that they were short in their money dealings and were struck off the roll.  I believe that in every one of these cases those concerned could have been saved and everything put right if at an early date the council could have written to them asking: &ldquo;What on earth are you doing?  Will you pull yourself together and put things right?&rdquo;  I would ask the Senator to withdraw the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I am prepared to withdraw the amendment.  The reason why the amendment was put down was because I thought it was unreasonable that a person could be regarded as being guilty until he was proved innocent.  In view of Senator Cox's experience and knowledge as a member of the society, I am prepared to withdraw the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>In connection with paragraph (i) of sub-section (1) of the section, may I draw the attention of the House to the fact that, a judgment or a decree having been given against a solicitor, it involves the payment of money other than costs?  Again, the society may refuse to issue a certificate. I should like to draw the Minister's attention to this: suppose there was a motor accident in which a solicitor was the owner of the vehicle and through some oversight he neglected or defaulted in renewing his insurance policy and a decree for a substantial amount was given against him, there is no provision in the Bill whereby that solicitor would have time to pay the amount of the debt.  I appreciate the fact that the Law Society, or the disciplinary committee, would have power to renew his certificate, but I had thought that it would be no harm if in a case like that there was some kind of a stay put on the necessity of cancelling his certificate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>The only answer that I can make to the Senator is this: I ask him to remember that the members of <Col N="539" /> the disciplinary committee and of the council are the professional brothers of that solicitor, and to think that they would act harshly or in some unfair way is, I think, quite wrong. Again, these powers are for the protection of the solicitor and client, and certainly they would not be operated arbitrarily.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>The section gives the committee discretionary powers.</P>
      <P>Section 49 put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 50 to 57, inclusive, put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 58.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 58 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>On the section, would the effect of it be that a solicitor, say, in Australia would be debarred from sending a document to a person in the Republic for execution?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I think he would not. These are things which must happen in the ordinary way of business.  You have a provision similar to this in force in England.  That does not mean that I cannot send a document to someone in England.  The Senator has asked if a lawyer in Australia could send a document here to be signed. Of course, he could.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>The section refers to &ldquo;the drawing or preparing of a document relating to real or personal estate or any legal proceeding and to the procuring or attempting to procure the execution by an Irish citizen of a document relating to real or personal estate or movable or immovable property, situate or being outside the State and the United Kingdom.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>What really lies behind that provision is this.  There have been what are called &ldquo;heir chasers&rdquo; in the United States.  It very often happens that people of Irish descent who die in the United States leave considerable fortunes and perhaps leave no will. Now, in the United States there are genealogical experts who get after that sort of thing, and if the estate is of <Col N="540" /> any size they very often send over here a power of attorney to the unfortunate heirs to sign, or they may send someone over and try to get them to sign it.  The people concerned may be quite ignorant.  They may not consult a lawyer and they sign the document under which, let us say, half the estate goes to the genealogical expert for proving their claim.</P>
      <P>That has become a notorious abuse. In fact, it became so serious that our own Department of External Affairs has actually set up a section the purpose of which is to try and give advice and guidance to Irish claimants to fortunes abroad.  The Law Society has forbidden its members, that is to say, forbidden solicitors to act in connection with powers of attorney of that kind sent from the United States.  That, as I have said, has been a very serious abuse.  There have been numbers of cases in which people here have been very seriously robbed.  If they get a letter from one of these people in the United States saying that an aunt or some other relative has died in Chicago leaving a considerable fortune, those poor people, without obtaining any advice or guidance, sign the document and afterwards find that half the money is gone.  It goes to those genealogical experts.  It is felt that this section is a very important one if our people are to be protected against that sort of thing.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 59 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 60.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 60 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>This section means that the solicitor who has been struck off the rolls could not be employed by another solicitor without the permission of the society.  I think that is very severe.  It means that a solicitor is being treated as a sort of ticket-of-leave man because of some default. The only type of employment for which he is suitable is in a solicitor's office and in view of the regulations and this Bill, a solicitor has to be so terribly careful that if he himself takes <Col N="541" /> responsibility for employing a person like that surely that should be enough. There is another section here which makes it necessary for the solicitor who has been struck off the rolls so to inform the solicitor with whom he is being employed and if the solicitor, having that information, is prepared to take the responsibility, I think the onus should be cast on the employer. It should not be necessary to seek the permission of the society before that person can go into that employment, which may be necessary to maintain his wife and family.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Seanad will not strike out this clause.  In the ordinary case, where a solicitor gets into trouble there is really no moral blame. The solicitor is very unlike other people who may embezzle money, in that of necessity the money must come into his hands.  It is not like someone who has to forge books or something like that.  However, there can be the really black sheep and what this section is intended to protect is that a really black sheep cannot, after he himself has been struck off the rolls, get employment, perhaps from some young and inexperienced solicitor, and start off again under cover of that.</P>
      <P>The Law Society considers that this section is absolutely imperative.  If such a man can start off again, nominally as an employee but probably as really the guiding spirit of some young solicitor, it will be too late to repair the damage when there has been an embezzlement or something very wrong has been done.  I would very strongly urge that this is an essential section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Again, the solicitors who constitute the council are not going to exercise the power arbitrarily against the ordinary case, which is 99 per cent. of all such cases, where somebody has gone wrong in his accounts, has carried on, has gradually paid off one person out of another person's money, and ultimately crashes.  It is imperative that they should have this power where there is a really bad case, because otherwise the solicitor who has been struck off the rolls for something really wrong might easily induce <Col N="542" /> some young solicitor to take him into employment and in two or three months, before things would have been found out, irreparable damage might be done.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>He has the right of appeal to the Chief Justice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Could this mean that a man who is struck off the rolls has no moral right in the capacity in which his business lies?  There is a moral question arising, apart from the legal aspect.  It seems to me that a solicitor becomes a black sheep by force of circumstances, or something else, and is qualified from the good offices of the society.  He goes into a position again, in the vocation for which he is best equipped, and the society follows him to death and will not allow him the right to live.  I am just putting up that side of the case, that there is a moral aspect.  While I can see that the society must protect the public, it is at the same time doing an injustice to the individual, who may not be as bad as the society believes him to be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>The answer to the Senator is that the section gives a right of appeal to the Chief Justice, so that if the solicitor who was struck off the rolls thought he was unfairly hounded he could apply to the Chief Justice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>And those who would have to inquire into it all belong to his own profession.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>Originally they belonged to his own profession, but if they decide against him he can appeal to the Chief Justice, so he has double protection.  Furthermore, I would put a question to the Senator that if there were a bad case, how would he be satisfied if he went to some young solicitor and found out afterwards that that place was really being run by someone who had been struck off the rolls?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>The liberty of the individual to me is greater than the powers of a society and the right of an individual should transcend everything. <Col N="543" /> It is a very dangerous thing to give a right in an enactment under the law to deprive any man of the possibility of earning his living from any source whatsoever, particularly that source for which he is best qualified. As to the protection of the public, the individual has rights above the public and there is a very grave matter of morals to be discussed on this question.  I am not doubting at all that the society means this in the best interests of the people, and I quite agree with the hypothetical question of Senator Cox that if I found out I had used some man who was under cover and had performed a wrong, I would not like it.  Before finally deciding, we should find whether an individual himself is greater in importance and whether we should protect the society or not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I quite appreciate the force of what the Senator has said, but after all there are many similar cases.  The drunken driver of a motor bus has his licence taken away for being drunk. That is not considered to be unjust. You must remember that this section can only arise first if the ex-solicitor's fellow solicitors and brothers think it necessary; and secondly, subject to the right of appeal to the Chief Justice.  Surely there is no need of further protection in that case.  The alternative is that the moment a really black sheep is struck off the rolls, the society no longer has any power over him, he can hide himself in some other office under some other name, and it may be several months before that is all found out and then it is too late.</P>
      <P>After all, all legal rights depend ultimately on the courts and on the judges.  The liberty of that man to practise is before them.  He is protected by the Bill because he can go to the Chief Justice if his own colleagues have turned him down and surely there is no hardship in that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Cox drew an analogy between the person who has been struck off the rolls and a drunken driver.  I am afraid that analogy is not a very good one, because a drunken driver can have his <Col N="544" /> licence restored after 12 months and that is the usual procedure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>So can the solicitor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>But the solicitor who has been disqualified and whose name is put off the roll may never again get any employment.  If we examine Section 63, we will see that</P>
      <P>&ldquo;a person who is an unqualified person, by reason of the striking off the roll of his name, his suspension from practice or the suspension of his practising certificate, shall not seek or accept employment by a solicitor in connection with the solicitor's practice without previously informing the solicitor that he is an unqualified person&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>In other words, a solicitor who would take on this other solicitor whose name was struck off the roll would not be doing it with his eyes closed. Furthermore, there is then a good difference.  When a solicitor is taken on in the employment of another solicitor that other solicitor would have the responsibility for the conduct of his office, and would be responsible for seeing that all moneys would be carefully looked after.  I think this section is a bit harsh.  It could easily have the effect of depriving a person who had been struck off the roll, of ever again getting any employment, because a terrible bias exists against such a person even if he were thought afterwards to be the best individual in the world.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator not think that this section in fact, is in itself contrary to the Constitution?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I certainly would think not.  Surely it is necessary in a profession such as the solicitors' profession, to give safeguards to the public? You must remember that I have spoken beforehand on the curious nature of the profession.  It is a mixture of law and business dealings &mdash;dealings with other people's money, and all sorts of things.  It also deals with people's secrets.  I think it is vital in the public interest that he should be not merely off the roll of <Col N="545" /> solicitors, but deprived of the power of being consulted as a solicitor, and so I would strongly urge the House not to delete the section.  Again I have to repeat what I said several times before.  In the first place there has to be a decision by a number of responsible solicitors elected by the profession as a whole, if this man is to be dealt with in this extreme way.  Is it very likely that would happen?  Would the Medical Registration Council do a thing like that to a fellow member unless there were strong grounds? Solicitors would not do it to a fellow solicitor unless there were very strong grounds.</P>
      <P>This is, I think, quite a serious matter because if this possible hole is left, it is possible for a person who is honest in dealing with other people's money to fall short in some way.  That is technically embezzlement, even though it might not be a deliberate act.  We are trying to protect the public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be much more difficult, and I am sure Senator Cox would agree, for a solicitor to get employment if the employer must first of all make application to the society.  If the amendment were accepted, I believe that many of these solicitors would get employment much more readily.  I think, for a person who has been struck off the roll, it is such a dreadfully severe matter for him and for his wife and family, that he should for the rest of his life have to seek the permission of the society before he gets employment in the only type of business for which his training suits him. Senator Cox has referred to the fact that a young solicitor may employ such a person and may use him.  If any young solicitor does not exercise proper supervision over his office, if he fails to control his office properly, then the society has power under Section 49, sub-section 1 (f) to refuse to renew that young solicitor's certificate.  In view of that, and in view of the fact that the solicitor who employs this person, who has been struck off the roll, must take such a serious responsibility, surely an individual solicitor has as much opportunity, and as much knowledge of whether or not he should <Col N="546" /> employ him and take the responsibility of employing a solicitor who has been struck off the roll, as the society.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>It might happen with old solicitors.  Might I remind the Senators of a certain Uriah Heep in <i>David Copperfield</i>, who performed exactly this achievement of working himself into an old and respectable solicitor's office.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 61 to 64, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 65.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 65 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to Section 65, I would ask the Minister if he would include on the third line the word &ldquo;partner&rdquo;.  This section only permits a solicitor or his assistant a right of audience in any court.  That, in my opinion, would deny the partner in a firm of solicitors from acting in such a capacity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the Construction Act the singular includes the plural, so the word &ldquo;solicitor&rdquo; would clearly include a firm of solicitors.  I think you will find that under the interpretation of the Act the word &ldquo;solicitor&rdquo; includes the partner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely the Senator would agree that it is necessary to include the word &ldquo;assistant&rdquo;?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>No, no.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>If he is in this firm of solicitors he may not be a partner, but an assistant in the firm.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the Solicitors Act, if he employs a qualified solicitor as his assistant, that is to say, a person who is not a partner, that qualified solicitor would be an assistant of the acting solicitor, and would appear in court.  The point Senator Walsh suggested is that the partner of the solicitor who is acting in a case could not appear in court.  My answer is that the opening words &ldquo;were a solicitor&rdquo; could be interpreted as <Col N="547" /> meaning that a firm of solicitors and their partner are automatically included by the ordinary rules of construction.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 66.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 12:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To add a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>The regulations to be made under this section shall not be brought into force until the 1st day of January, 1956.</P>
      <P>These are in connection with accounts. Apparently the regulations do not come into force until the 5th January, 1955.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>An auditor's certificate will not be required until the year commencing 5th April, 1956.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Can I take it that in view of that the amendment will not be necessary?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not necessary.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Sections 66 to 72, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 73.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 73 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Under sub-section (4) of this section the quorum of the committee is three.  I would suggest that the quorum in that case should be five, the same as it is in connection with the disciplinary committee.  The disciplinary committee is one of the commitees of the society, and if it is necessary to have five there it might be inconsistent if there were not five in this particular sub-section.  Would the Minister agree to increase the quorum from three to five in sub-section (4)?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask that the section might stand as it is.  This section merely speaks of ordinary committees of the council.  We are no longer speaking of the disciplinary committee or anything of that kind. <Col N="548" /> We are talking about the ordinary committee which the council appoints for education, etc.  To make the quorum for such a meeting five would make it unmanagable.  The majority of the members of the council do not come from the City of Dublin.  It might impose great difficulty and hardship to make five statutory.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator satisfied that the disciplinary committee can still be five?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  The disciplinary committee is really not a committee of the council at all.  We are speaking here of the committees of the council.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>I am interested in Section 72.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that we cannot go back on Section 72. That has been disposed of.  If the Senator wishes to make a comment on anything contained in the Bill, he may do it on the Fifth Stage, provided it relates to something in the Bill.</P>
      <P>Sections 74 to 85, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 86.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 86 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>I am anxious to know what are the rights and privileges given under Section 86.  I notice that in Section 85 it says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;To remove doubt, it is hereby declared that the Attorneys and Solicitors Act, 1870, applies, and always applied, in the State.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Section 86 says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Nothing in this Act shall affect any rights or privileges of persons who are solicitors or assistant solicitors to the Revenue Commissioners or require any such person, or any clerk or officer acting for him, to be admitted or enrolled or to hold a practising certificate.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>What are the rights and privileges in question?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="549" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Of the Revenue Commissioners?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>Of the solicitors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>The position is that the Minister was anxious to protect the practice under which a barrister is for some peculiar reason called a solicitor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say that tradition and custom die very hard.  I think it is time we changed that now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>What would happen if the solicitor to the Revenue Commissioners were a solicitor?  I know we cannot legislate for the future but suppose he was not a barrister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the answer is that such a person would have no special rights or privileges.  Therefore, it is not necessary to protect rights and privileges that do not exist.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 87 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 13 not moved.</P>
      <P>Section 88 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">FIRST SCHEDULE.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the First Schedule be the First Schedule to the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the import of the section under the Irish Universities Act, 1908, which is being repealed?  I see that Section 12 is being repealed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I do not know, but I think the position is that solicitors have to serve a certain term of apprenticeship which is normally five years.  You can get a year off that if you get a degree.  There is a special provision in this Bill as to the colleges in which you could do that and get the degree.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Second, Third and Fourth Schedules put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">FIFTH SCHEDULE.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Fifth Schedule be the Fifth Schedule to the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="550" />
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 4 of the Fifth Schedule states:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;A grant may be made out of the fund whether or not the solicitor had a practising certificate in force when the act of dishonesty occurred.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That appears to me to be mandatory. I suggest it should be optional.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator state what his objection to it is?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>On which part of the Schedule is the question raised?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 5, which states:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;A grant shall not be made out of the fund unless notice of the loss is received by the society&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  in the prescribed manner, and</P>
      <P>(b)  within the prescribed period after the loss came to the knowledge of the loser.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>The idea there is to protect the public.  A person who loses money through the embezzlement of a solicitor must bring the matter to the notice of the society within a reasonable period, otherwise a position might arise where a person had lost money through embezzlement and said nothing about it.  Other people might then, perhaps, be led into the same trap.  It is very important that a person should not be compensated out of the compensation fund unless he himself acts with reasonable celerity in making his case and in doing it in the proper way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>It would mean that the society would have no option.  If, through oversight or neglect or because a person was under age, or for some other reason, the applicant failed to make application to the society within the specified period, the society has no power to award compensation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>Again, I think that is a question of the regulations.  Obviously, the regulations would provide and give some relief if the person were ill or out of the country or if the matter had not come to his notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="551" />
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>They are bound by the prescribed period.  Once the regulation specifically states the prescribed period, the society would have no discretion to alter the period set down by the regulation, irrespective of what the unusual circumstances might be in connection with the delay in making the application.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>That would depend, surely, on the regulations.  They might take the form that the prescribed period shall be (a) five years or (b) such longer period as the committee may, in their discretion, fix&mdash;or anything of that kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>The prescribed period is not mentioned here.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sixth Schedule and Title put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>As the date in the Bill is the 6th January, 1955, perhaps the Seanad&mdash;since no amendments have been adopted to it&mdash;would be agreeable to give the other stages now?  I ask for that.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take the remaining stages now.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to ask the Minister a question in connection with Section 72.  Sub-section (2) of Section 72 states:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;For the reference to £80 contained in the First Schedule to the Stamp Act, 1891, under the first of the headings &lsquo;Articles of Clerkship&rsquo;<Col N="552" /> there shall be substituted a reference to £14.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>To whom is the £14 paid?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>The Revenue Commissioners collect that money for the King's Inns.  Neither the Revenue Commissioners nor the State get any benefit from it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>That is hardly an explanation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurCox" hpid="Mr. Cox Mr. Cox">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cox</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a subject which has always been very painful with the solicitors' profession.  Centuries ago, solicitors had the right of members of the King's Inns and were subject to the discipline of the benchers.  For some reason which has never really been discovered&mdash;although long archæological researches have been made&mdash;in process of time it came about that, on admission, solicitors paid a heavy stamp duty which went to the benchers &mdash;which did not go to the Incorporated Law Society and which was not of any benefit to the solicitors' profession. That was a matter which always perturbed solicitors.  Now, to a very large extent, that has been put right and, in future, solicitors will have to pay the greatly abated stamp duty of £14 which will be received by the Minister for Finance.  Out of that we know he makes a grant to the King's Inns but solicitors are getting off much better than they used to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Much better than the barristers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that that be reduced to £1.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator cannot move that at this stage.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Business suspended at</i> 6 <i>p.m. and resumed at</i> 7 <i>p.m.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee of" RHead="Selection&mdash;Second Report">
    <Title>Committee of Selection&mdash;Second Report.</Title>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Committee on Standing" RHead="Orders (Private Business)">
    <Title>Joint Committee on Standing Orders (Private Business).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>In pursuance of Order 56 of the Standing Orders of the Dáil and the Seanad relative to Private Business, we, the Ceann Comhairle of the Dáil and the Cathaoirleach of the Seanad, jointly, hereby nominate Senator Liam Ó Buachalla to be Chairman of the Joint Committee on Standing Orders.</P>
      <P>That is signed by the Ceann Comhairle and the Cathaoirleach of the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Imposition of Duties (Confirmation of Orders) (No." RHead="2) Bill, 1954&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Imposition of Duties (Confirmation of Orders) (No. 2) Bill, 1954&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <Col N="555" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Imposition of Duties (Confirmation of Orders) Bill has been received from the Dáil and circulated. This was anticipated to-day, but the House did not make an order at that stage to consider the Bill. Could we have a motion from Senator Crosbie now in that regard?  Will he move that the House do now consider the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the House do now consider the Imposition of Duties (Confirmation or Orders) (No. 2) Bill, 1954.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Norton) William Norton">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Norton)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful to the Seanad for its kindness in agreeing to receive this Bill at such short notice. The Bill is the customary Bill for the purpose of giving legal effect to certain Orders imposing certain duties, Orders which must be confirmed within a certain period of time.  The time has not yet expired, but if the Seanad and the Dáil were in Recess it would not be convenient to have the Bill passed in such circumstances.  The Seanad is, therefore, being asked to do what it has kindly agreed to do, namely to take the Bill at short notice from the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I have said, this is the customary Bill to give effect to eight Orders which have been made under the Emergency Imposition of Duties Act, 1932.  One of these Orders, entitled&mdash; Emergency Imposition of Duties (Finance Act, 1954) (Consequential Provisions) Order, 1954&mdash;provided for amendments in certain customs duties consequent on the termination of other customs duties in the Finance Act, 1954. These amendments did not impose any new duty provisions.  They were necessary so as to prevent anomalies arising in duties which were related to the duties terminated in the Finance Act. The commodities covered by the remaining <Col N="556" /> seven Orders are as follows:&mdash; (1) Drive screws and drive screw nails; (2) metal coffin mountings; (3) disinfectants, antiseptics, insecticides, verminicides, vermicides, fungicides and weedkillers; (4) fireside companion sets; (5) felt hats and caps for men or boys; (6) electric smoothing irons; (7) knitted woollen cardigans, pullovers, jerseys, blouses and similar articles.</P>
    <P>The customs duties imposed on drive screws and drive screw nails and on fireside companion sets are new protective duties.  The firm engaged in the manufacture of nails and screws extended its production to cover drive screws and applied for and was granted protection for this development. In the case of fireside companion sets, the production of these articles was undertaken for the first time and a very wide range of sets at reasonable prices was put on the market by the firm concerned.</P>
    <P>In the case of metal coffin mountings, the Order extended the scope of the duty already in existence so as to include partly manufactured mountings and component parts of mountings. The object of this Order was to stop the practice which was developing of importing partly manufactured articles to the detriment of an existing firm which was carrying out the complete range of manufacturing operations.</P>
    <P>The Order dealing with disinfectants, etc., provided for a customs duty on disinfectants, antiseptics, insecticides, verminicides, vermicides, fungicides, and weedkillers.  These goods, other than antiseptics and weedkillers, had previously been subject to customs duty, but the duty was suspended in 1942 for supply reasons.  Owing to difficulties of definition a number of items not being manufactured here became subject to duty under this Order and, following consultation with the Irish manufactures and with the Department of Agriculture, arrangements were made for the issue of duty-free licences for articles which the Irish manufacturers are unable to supply or for which suitable substitutes are not available from home sources.</P>
    <P>The Order dealing with felt hats and caps for men and boys provided for an <Col N="557" /> increase in the minimum rates of duty already chargeable on these articles, as the existing rate of duty had proved ineffective in protecting the Irish factories against imports of cheap hats.</P>
    <P>In the case of electric smoothing irons, the customs duty already in existence covered irons up to 7 lb. in weight.  The present Order increased the dutiable weight limit from 7 lb. to 8 lb.  The reason for this was that certain importers were evading the duty by bringing in irons weighing slightly over 7 lb.</P>
    <P>The Order dealing with knitted woollen cardigans, pullovers, jerseys, blouses and similar articles provided for an increase in the customs duty already chargeable on those articles. The Order was made following a review of the operation of the customs duty and of the quantitative restrictions on the importation of the articles, carried out by the Industrial Development Authority under the terms of the Anglo-Irish Trade Agreement.</P>
    <P>As I explained at the outset, this is the customary Bill for the purpose of confirming the Orders which are set out in the explanatory memorandum, and I hope that the Seanad will see its way to facilitate its passage this evening.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, in his introductory statement, has pointed out the urgency of this measure.  It is because of that urgency, and of the fact that this House will now be adjourning for some considerable time, that we agreed to take this Bill to-night.  At the same time, I think it is only right that we should protest against the bringing in of a Bill of this nature at such short notice.  As the Minister has explained, this Bill is, if you like, a hardy annual, but at the same time we must remember that it covers no less than eight Orders which have been made relating to the imposition of certain duties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If this House is to fulfil the purpose for which it was established, I think it is only right that the members should have the opportunity of giving serious consideration to any measure which comes before them, and particular measures of this kind.  This Bill has <Col N="558" /> come before us at very short notice. That is a practice that we should not be prepared to set up as a precedent. The only reason why we are prepared to give the Minister all stages of the Bill to-night is because of the wide range it covers, and because it is essential that the duties imposed under it may be continued to help and to facilitate the industries concerned.  I should like to remind the Minister and the Government of not leaving measures of this kind&mdash;I am afraid it has been a practice now for quite a long time&mdash;over for an occasion like this when neither this House nor the other House, because of the circumstances, has an opportunity of giving them the consideration which they should receive and, particularly, the consideration which they should receive from this House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>Up to a point one might, perhaps, agree with Senator Hawkins were it not for two facts.  The first is the importance of this Bill, which is an annual Bill, as well as the importance of keeping the wheels of Irish industry turning smoothly. Secondly, the Senator appears to be slightly misinformed.  While this Bill is urgent, it is not absolutely so urgent that all stages of it must be passed to-night.  We are relying on the goodwill of the House to accept the Bill and pass it to-night, but it is not absolutely vital.  If we do not deal with it to-night it will entail a meeting of this House early in the new year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask that the Bill be passed through all stages, because there may not be any particular business for us to do here in the first week in January and I know that Senators would not like to have the House called for a formal matter like that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That question does not arise at this stage.  The Minister, to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>The only point raised was that by Senator Hawkins.  I do not think he gave me sufficient credit for being concerned with the well-being and comfort of Senators.  Although I asked for all stages to-night, it is sufficient <Col N="559" /> for my purpose if I get the Bill by the 14th January.  I do not want all stages to-night and it is sufficient for me to put it into the Seanad later and ask the Seanad to meet next week. It is sufficient also if I get the Bill by the 14th of May, which is the last day on which the Orders expire.  I did not wish to ask the Seanad to meet next week or bring the House back in the first or second week of January and I took the course of asking the Seanad with due humility if all stages could be passed to-night, as it is a very formal Bill.  It is a money Bill, a Bill which is giving effect to Orders some of which have been running for some time.  In asking the Seanad to pass it to-night, I was really having some regard for the well-being of members of this House, in not asking them to meet on these awkward occasions.  I do not want to press for all stages to-night, if the Seanad does not wish.  There is plenty of time to deal with the matter, but the time probably would not be more convenient.  I do not mind that as far as I am concerned personally, as it will do me on the 14th of January.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take the remaining stages now.</P>
      <P>Bill passed through Committee, reported without amendment, received for final consideration, and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Wheat" RHead="Prices&mdash;Motion">
    <Title>Wheat Prices&mdash;Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That, having regard to the severe losses that wheat growers have suffered in the present year and in view of the importance of wheat-growing to our nation's economy, Seanad Éireann deeply deplores the Government's decision to reduce the price of wheat and strongly recommends that the matter be reconsidered and that the price for the 1955 wheat crop be not less than that paid for the 1954 crop.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Having regard to the rather complex matters with which we were dealing <Col N="560" /> in the early part of the day, I may say that this is a very simple motion.  Lest any non-agricultural Senators might be confused by any particular terms mentioned, I may say that the cut proposed by the Minister in regard to Irish-grown wheat amounts to £5 per ton, that is to say, the top price for wheat is being reduced from £33 to £28.  It is no harm to mention in passing for the benefit also of non-agricultural Senators, that a barrel of wheat is one-eight of a ton, or 2½ cwt. or 20 stone.  It is no harm to mention, as acres are frequently mentioned in the comparison of costings and so on, that as far as I am concerned in this discussion I will be dealing with statute acres.  A great many farmers use the Irish acre in referring to such matters.</P>
    <P>The drastic reduction in the price of wheat has come as a shock to the farming community.  It is something for which they were entirely unprepared. It is true that over the past six months there has been poured into the daily provincial Press a stream of bilge calculated to misrepresent the wheat growers' position and prepare the way for a reduction in price.  Nevertheless, I think most farmers assumed that the Minister and the Government would have sufficient consideration for the interests of agriculture and would not take this drastic step.  Certainly it was felt that this step would not be taken by the Government without consultation, negotiation and agreement with responsible farmers' organisations.  In every civilised agricultural country, drastic decisions on agricultural policy are not taken without first having consultation, negotiation and agreement with representative farmers' organisations.  It is quite clear that no such agreements were reached here. The fact that the announcement of this severe reduction in the price of wheat was followed immediately by a storm of protest from all responsible farmers' organisations, is sufficient indication that those people were not consulted or, if consulted, their views were completely ignored.</P>
    <P>I think there is another reason also why farmers felt that this step would not be taken.  At the present time efforts are being made&mdash;and I think <Col N="561" /> they will be successful&mdash;to establish a national farmers' union.  It would have been a wise and prudent course for the Government to have awaited the establishment of that united agricultural organisation before taking this step. I think there is a general feeling throughout the country that agricultural policy should be kept out of Party politics.</P>
    <P>Agricultural policy could be kept out of Party politics if there is a willingness on the part of whatever Government is in power to negotiate and consult with responsible non-political vocational farmers' organisations.  I think the fact that we had a prospect of uniting agricultural organisations should have deterred the Minister from taking this step.  I have referred to the campaign which has been waged in the daily and provincial Press to misrepresent the wheat growers' position. I think it is only necessary to say that that campaign in the main has been waged by people who have no interest in agriculture and very little knowledge of it.  Few of them would know a buck rake from a puck goat, yet they take upon themselves to lecture not only to farmers but the community in regard to this particular matter.</P>
    <P>Was any attempt made before this injustice was inflicted upon farmers to ascertain costings in regard to wheat growing?  We know that fairly accurate costings are available in regard to sugar beet growing.  They were arrived at mainly through the initiative of the managing director of the Irish Sugar Company, working in agreement with the representatives of the growers.  As a result no one has dared so far to reduce the price paid over the last two years.  The case that existed and was accepted in regard to beet, that costings have not fallen to any degree and therefore the price could not be reduced this year, must also be accepted in regard to wheat. The same factors operate&mdash;cost of labour, fertilisers and raw materials of that kind&mdash;so that in itself establishes the case for preserving the price of wheat at least for another year.</P>
    <P>I have consulted not only with farmers but also with experts of the Department of Agriculture in regard <Col N="562" /> to costs of producing wheat per acre. While I find a certain divergence of opinion in regard to the actual figures, I find that there is more or less agreement that the minimum cost of producing wheat would be somewhere in the region of £20 to £25 per acre&mdash;and that is a modest estimate.  As we know, only in an exceptionally good year could we hope to secure more than one ton per acre, and as the top price for a ton for wheat under the Minister's new price is £28, it will be seen that the margin is very narrow.  It certainly does not leave room for much speculation.</P>
    <P>I have here some figures which were produced in the official organ of the Fine Gael Party, the <i>Irish Independent.</i>  In an article entitled, &ldquo;Down on the Farm&rdquo;, written, I think, by a distinguished kinsman of the Minister's in the <i>Irish Independent</i> of 11th December, 1954, I quote:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I have before me the accounts of a speculator in wheat growing. This man, who is not a farmer, had 40 statute acres of wheat on conacre last year, and this year at an average rent of £18 a statute acre. Here are the results:&mdash;</P>
    <P Just="Center">1953.</P>
    <P>Costs&mdash;Total, £1,555.</P>
    <P>Gross Return&mdash;£1,860.</P>
    <P>Net Profit&mdash;£305.</P>
    <P Just="Center">1954</P>
    <P>Costs (with extra labour, some drying, etc.)&mdash;£1,594.</P>
    <P>Gross Return&mdash;£1,235.</P>
    <P>Net Loss&mdash;£359.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>This speculator is not an ordinary farmer, and you may take it his costs would be higher than those of an ordinary farmer.</P>
    <P>Where that type of grower is concerned he is put out of business perhaps not by any action of the Minister but by weather conditions.  Those are the type of people who came into wheat growing without prior knowledge which the ordinary farmer had and I think that their interest in it will be short-lived. There is no substantial profit in wheat growing either for the average farmer or the speculator.  It is one of those operations which, like many other <Col N="563" /> farming operations, if carried out with efficiency and industry, leave a narrow margin of profit to the producer.  I think, therefore, it was very essential before taking any steps in regard to price fixing to make an investigation into costings.  Such an investigation was not made and we have now an attack made upon the farmers, an attack which is deeply resented by every section of those engaged in agriculture. If this had been a normal year, if we had not experienced the bad weather conditions which we have experienced during the past week or two, but during the past six months, the Minister might have had a better hope of carrying out this attack on agriculture.</P>
    <P>It is sometimes said by those who try to defend the Government's action that Fianna Fáil would have taken similar action if they had been in power.  Fianna Fáil was in power in 1953 which, according to the records I have before me, was one of the best years for wheat growing.  The yields, I think, in 1953 were on the whole somewhat higher than average.  That year was reasonably favourable and if ever there was a good time for making a cut, it was in 1953.  Nevertheless, Fianna Fáil in 1953 decided to continue the prices which had been in operation. It was only in the last week or two that those in authority&mdash;and by that I mean the Government and their advisers&mdash;became really aware of the abnormal weather conditions of this year, but farmers have been aware of them since last July.  The hay making season was extremely bad, the harvesting operations were prolonged and expensive and to a great extent accompanied by considerable loss. There are very few farmers this year who have got away with less than 20 per cent. loss of their grain crops.</P>
    <P>Some farmers and some good farmers have lost the greater portion of their grain.  It is not only the very rich farmers who suffered losses; it is not only the people who used combines who suffered but many of the people who tried to operate by the old traditional method, the old fashioned way, if you like, of cutting with a reaper and <Col N="564" /> binder and stooking and stacking, and going through all the operations have their corn in the fields and a very big portion may be written off as a complete loss.</P>
    <P>It was in this particular year that the Minister and the Government decided in their wisdom to slash the price of wheat and to inflict a cut of at least 15 per cent. upon this most hard working section of the community.  If a similar cut had been imposed upon those engaged in public employment and if a similar reduction had been introduced in regard to civil servants' salaries, agricultural wages and the remuneration of any other section of the community there would be a storm of protest that no Government could resist.  Yet, these farmers have been called upon to make a sacrifice for no valid reason that can be put forward.</P>
    <P>Can it be reasonably claimed that there is likely to be in the coming year any reduction in the cost of production of wheat growing?  Can it be reasonably claimed that there is any likelihood that agricultural wages, for example, will be reduced in the coming year?  I do not think so.  Nobody expects that agricultural wages could be reduced in the coming year having regard to the fact that the cost of living has risen and is still steadily rising. Is it likely that the cost of fertilisers will be reduced in the coming year? All the indications are that the cost of fertilisers will increase.</P>
    <P>The Minister, before he became Minister, was very eloquent in his denunciation of tariffs and taxes upon the raw materials of agriculture.  Has he attempted since he came into office to remove all tariffs on fertilisers? Nothing in that respect has been done and nothing is likely to be done.  The Minister's superior in the Government, the Tánaiste himself, has publicly announced that the fertiliser industry may expect that the protective tariffs on imported fertilisers will be rigidly maintained.  I think that if the Minister came back with me on a fair day to Tinahely, where he spoke very eloquently on that subject, he would possibly be inclined to regret his words because he informed the farmers of Wicklow at that time that all duties <Col N="565" /> on fertilisers would be abolished the moment he took office.</P>
    <P>But there is another aspect of this question which cannot be forgotten or passed over, and it is that before taking office the Taoiseach gave the most solemn guarantee to the farmers of Ireland that the price of wheat which was then in operation would continue for five years.  That guarantee was given over the radio.  It was given far and wide on the public platforms throughout the country and was repeated with greater emphasis by the candidates standing for the Government Parties in the elections.</P>
    <P>The farmers were told that under Fianna Fáil they had only a guarantee of the existing price for one year but that under Fine Gael and the inter-Party Government they would have a guarantee of the existing price for five years.  I will read a public statement issued by the Fine Gael organisation in the constituency of Carlow-Kilkenny. It is only one of the hundreds that were issued:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Wheat: Fine Gael, in 1948, gave a five years' price guarantee for wheat.  The price fixed for this season is in accord with that policy, and will be paid by Fine Gael.  Fine Gael, as a Government, will give another five-year guarantee.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There you have a clear and emphatic promise to the farmers that that price&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a distortion of the facts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator read it again so that he might understand it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon) James M. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is fior duit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that I am getting under the skins of some Senators.  I should like if the Senators on the other side would keep a little cool and listen more attentively while I am reading this promise given by Fine Gael.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Would <Col N="566" /> Senator Cogan state from what he is quoting and clear the air?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a public election notice published in the <i>Munster Express</i> of the 14-5-1954.  It is as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Carlow-Kilkenny Constituency. The tillage farmer and his man and Fine Gael.  Wheat: Fine Gael, in 1948, gave a five years' price guarantee for wheat.  The price fixed for this season is in accord with that policy and will be paid by Fine Gael.  Fine Gael, as a Government, will give another five-year guarantee.  If this market was guaranteed to you, what would it be worth?  Make sure it is. Vote Fine Gael.  Crotty, Fielding, Hughes, 1, 2, 3.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>What price?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Now I can see all the people on the Fine Gael side trying to quibble out of that public announcement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Every word of it is correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>They guaranteed that the price of wheat would remain for five years.  We had a repetition of the assertion that the wheat price was guaranteed for five years in 1948.  What happened in 1948?  The price of wheat, when the present Minister came into office in 1948, was £3 2s. 6d. and the Minister guaranteed to continue that price.  That example of a five-year guarantee, having been quoted, this public announcement goes on to remind the farmers of that five-year guarantee and to use these words: &ldquo;Fine Gael as a Government will give another five-year guarantee.&rdquo;  Could anyone read any meaning into that promise except that the price of wheat would not be reduced for five years? That was the meaning that was intended to be read into the announcement, and that was the meaning that Fine Gael tried to induce farmers to take out of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I know myself that a number of farmers took that meaning out of it and went to the polls happily reassured that the price of wheat would <Col N="567" /> not be reduced for five years.  It is easy for legal gentlemen to make those kind of promises and then by a legal quibble get out of them, but the reasonable meaning to be drawn from those words is that the price would remain unchanged for five years.  No amount of quibbling will convince the farmers that a swindle was not put over on them, that they were not deliberately misled by that promise, and that they were deliberately misled solely for opportunist Party purposes.</P>
    <P>I have dealt with the failure of the Fine Gael Party.  I am not including any other Party in this because I do not think they took any part in giving that guarantee.  I am not so sure about other Parties, but certainly I am charging Fine Gael with breaking faith with the farmers.  However, leaving all that aside&mdash;leaving aside the question of what Government or what Minister may be in power&mdash;viewing the matter purely from a national and economic standpoint, let us ask ourselves whether or not it is desirable to cut the price of wheat.  I have pointed out that it is undesirable to do so this year on account of the weather conditions which we have experienced, but even if we had had better weather conditions, would it be desirable, in the national interest, to cut the price of wheat?  What is the value of wheat to the nation?  That is the important consideration.  First of all, by growing at least two-thirds of our requirements here in Ireland, we safeguard the position of our people in times of emergency.  We cannot be compelled to crawl upon our hands and knees to any outside power to beg for bread so long as our people are prepared and enabled to use the land of Ireland to grow wheat.  There are individuals who will say that a sound insurance against an emergency would be to lay in a store of imported seed wheat and, if an emergency should strike this country, to set the farmers to work to grow the wheat. Does anybody think that that would be a practical proposition?  No farmer would, for a moment, countenance it. It might appeal to the armchair <Col N="568" /> economist&mdash;it might appeal to the man who does all his agricultural and economic calculations on sheets of clean paper&mdash;but it is not in accordance with realities.</P>
    <P>In order to get two-thirds of our wheat requirements grown here, it is necessary to build up the wheat-growing organisation.  You have got to have farmers with a knowledge of the technique of wheat-growing.  You have to have the varieties of wheat suitable for this climate.  You have to have the machinery for the sowing and harvesting of the crop.  You cannot turn the vast grass ranches, overnight, into efficient wheat-growing areas.  It is necessary that the organisation be built up and perfected.  At the same time, you must have your mills prepared to accept Irish wheat and you must have the facilities for drying wheat.  These things have all to be built up and perfected.  That cannot be done unless we have a very substantial acreage all the time under wheat.</P>
    <P>The Minister, I think, and his friends claim a good deal of credit for the manner in which our farmers have faced up to the problem of overcoming the appalling weather conditions we have experienced this year.  However, he omitted to give full credit to his predecessor in office who had pushed forward the wheat-growing policy, enlarged the acreage and expanded the drying facilities out of all recognition. In the past three years, the facilities for drying wheat were increased by at least 50 per cent.  That was done mainly at the insistence of the Minister's predecessor in office, and it was possible only because we had a definite, clear-cut and resolute wheat-growing policy.  If we were to abandon wheat, and cutting the price is a step towards the abandonment of wheat, the whole machinery in the growing of wheat would fall into disuse&mdash;the mechanical assistance which farmers have for their tillage operations and the drying facilities in our mills. Then, in the event of an emergency we should find ourselves completely unprepared.</P>
    <P>Remember that, from a national viewpoint, our agricultural industry is passing through a transition period. We are changing over from the old-fashioned <Col N="569" /> methods of horse-drawn implements to mechanisation.  Most farmers have modernised and reequipped their farms and they have done that at considerable expense to themselves.  It would not have been possible for them to do so were it not for the fact that they had at least one crop for which there was a guaranteed price.  Even at the present time, there are farmers who owe money in respect of the purchase of modern farm implements&mdash;tractors, combine harvesters, farm implements and the other equipment which is so essential in modern farming.  The farmers are depending on a guaranteed price for at least one of their tillage crops&mdash;for a few years, anyhow&mdash;to enable them to clear off those debts and to recoup themselves, to some extent, for the expenditure involved in changing over to modern methods.  Remember, modern methods are the best methods in agriculture, as they are in every other industry.</P>
    <P>Wheat-growing contributes and has contributed more than anything else to improving the quality of our land. Land does not improve if it is left to nature.  Land does not improve if it is left in permanent pasture.  Very soon, the greater portion of the soil deteriorates.  Every type of weed and of unprofitable grass develops in land that is left uncultivated.  In order to get the maximum production from the land, cultivation is essential.  A guaranteed price for at least one tillage crop is essential in order to carry out cultivation.  Therefore, it will be seen that wheat-growing is linked up with progressive farming. That is why progressive farmers' organisations such as the Beet Growers' Association and Macra na Feirme and all those other organisations which cater for the young, progressive element in agriculture are so determined in demanding that the wheat-growing policy be continued and preserved.</P>
    <P>The growing of wheat has advantages not only for the farmer but for all sections of the community.  It brings about a considerable expenditure of money in rural areas.  Money is expended in the local towns on the purchase of fertilisers, machinery, and so forth.  Money is put into circulation <Col N="570" /> in the local towns when the wheat is delivered to the mill.  Additional men are employed on the farms in the growing of wheat.  Additional men are employed on the transport of that wheat to the mill.  Furthermore, as a result of the wheat-growing policy, we have the security which is enjoyed by the smaller mills throughout the length and breadth of the State.  These small mills would be wiped out completely in three years if native wheat growing were abolished.  If we depended entirely on imported wheat, we should have mills only at the big ports, and the small mills throughout the country which are giving much-needed employment would disappear.  All these important factors hinge on wheat growing.</P>
    <P>To-day, we are witnessing a deliberate attempt to bring wheat growing in this country to an end.  We, in this Seanad, do not want to dictate to the Government but, for the very important reasons which I have mentioned, we should at least recommend that the Government reconsider their decision in this grave matter.</P>
    <P>There is, of course, the other aspect of the question.  Apart from the farmers' interest and apart from the workers' interest, there is the national interest in regard to the balance of payments.  If we are to send out of this country £15,000,000 or £16,000,000 for imported wheat, if we are to depend upon other nations for our entire supply of wheat, from what source is that money to be found?  Nobody can dispute the fact that we have to export the produce of two acres of Irish land under pasture in order to bring in the amount of wheat that we could grow here upon one acre.  That fact will not be disputed and therefore is it sound economic policy to export the produce of two acres in order to get back into this country what we could grow on one acre?</P>
    <P>There is no clash whatever between the growing of wheat and the growing of other crops.  There is no conflict whatever between the growing of wheat and the live-stock industry.  All can work in unity and harmony.  Most of <Col N="571" /> the alleged clashes in agriculture, in our economic system, are discovered, if you like, by those who have really no knowledge of the economic conditions in their practical effect.  We can grow the total amount of wheat that it is necessary for us to grow and that is not 100 per cent. of our requirements. If we could grow at least two-thirds of our requirements, we would be doing quite well, and, by growing two-thirds of our requirements, we do not need to put more than 5 per cent., one-twentieth part, of our arable land under wheat.  Does anyone seriously contend that the putting of one-twentieth of our arable land under wheat would in any way interfere with the cattle-raising industry, with the dairying industry, with the other branches of tillage farming which are so essential in their own way?  Viewed from every conceivable angle, no case can be made for reducing the price of wheat and thereby seeking to bring to an end wheat growing in this State.</P>
    <P>I hoped that, when the Minister came to make the case for the slashing of the price of wheat in the Dáil, he would make a reasonable case.  He did nothing of the kind.  Stripped of the patronising patter in which he usually indulges and the empty blather, there were two strong points.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I miss the Senator's customary courtesy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I missed it, too, from the Minister, but there were two points which I thought he tried to make.  I am going to deal with these and to deal with them seriously, and I am going to deal with them without any discourtesy to the Minister, I hope, and without any offence.  I hope I will not hurt his feelings in any way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister made two points, the first of which was that there was a possibility of a surplus.  This scare of a surplus has been held up to the public as something to put us off wheat growing.  He also referred to speculators.  I will deal with the more serious of these two points first, that is, the question of a surplus.  We all acknowledge that a surplus would be a serious matter, if it were something <Col N="572" /> that could reasonably be expected.  No one in this State would like to have the nation in the position in which it would have to export a quantity of wheat.  Nobody wants to do that and nobody, I think, intended that that should happen, but does anyone in this House at this time&mdash;whatever may have been the position when the Minister first made his decision&mdash;seriously think that there is likely to be anything like as much wheat grown next year as was grown this year, even at last year's price?</P>
    <P>Does everyone not realise that the experience of weather conditions over the last year will result in at least a 20 per cent. cut in the acreage of wheat?  Even if the price remained unchanged, that is absolutely certain. Men were encouraged by three fairly good wheat-growing years to expand acreage this year to an extent which they would not have attempted, if they had had the experience of the present year, and we may take it that at least a 20 per cent. cut in the acreage will occur in the coming year, even if the price were to remain at its present figure.  One has only to travel through the country, leaving aside the terribly devastated areas under floods&mdash;to cross any tillage field at present, to realise that no agricultural operations can be carried out for a very long time, and in any case the depressing effect of last year will certainly cut the total acreage under tillage in the coming year, so that we may take it as a foregone conclusion that the acreage will be down in the coming year, even if there were no reduction whatever.</P>
    <P>The Minister in connection with this in the Dáil tried to make the point that the Fianna Fáil Party were committed to some form of drastic restriction in wheat acreage.  He quoted a governmental decision made last February that the target in this State would be 300,000 tons of dried wheat. He tried to make it appear to those who were not acquainted with the facts that 300,000 tons of wheat was a very small amount and that it would entail a very drastic cut in wheat acreage.  In actual fact, it is probably the amount which we will secure from the very large acreage this year, and let us remember <Col N="573" /> that the conditions this year were exceptional to such a degree that they are never likely to occur again.</P>
    <P>It is true that in this year, 1954, farmers put under wheat an estimated acreage of 490,000 acres.  That acreage, that large expansion, if you like, in acreage, was due to certain factors which are never likely to recur in this State.  First of all, we had the decontrol of cattle in Britain, which had the effect of creating uncertainty among farmers as to the future of the cattle trade.  Many farmers felt it would be a safer investment to go into wheat rather than speculate with cattle, because, as we know, anything could happen, or a number of farmers felt that anything could happen, if control of the meat trade was removed in Great Britain.  Not only that, but at the time we had politicians who were then in opposition going through the country from fair to fair telling the farmers that the price of cattle was going to fall if Fianna Fáil remained in office, that the then Minister was so incompetent that he would not be able to negotiate a favourable trade agreement and that cattle prices would fall.</P>
    <P>We had, in addition to that, the uncertainty in regard to barley prices. We know that in the previous year our then Minister for Agriculture secured a fair price for barley by placing certain restrictions on imported maize. There was a vile and a vicious attack on him for so doing, both in the Oireachtas and throughout the country and there was a feeling that much as he wished to maintain a price for the barley grower he would be unable to do it in 1954.  That was another incentive to farmers to go over to wheat. In addition to that, we had a widespread whispering campaign, if you like, telling the farmers that 1954 would be the last year for wheat. Farmers were told that the wheat price would not be maintained after 1954.  I suppose a number of farmers also had a certain fear in their minds that the present anti-wheat Minister would succeed in getting back into office and that the price would not continue.</P>
    <P>All those factors operated to increase the acreage under wheat.  If the price had remained unchanged, <Col N="574" /> those factors would not operate again. We see, therefore, that if the Minister had negotiated and consulted with the farmers' organisations, if he had adopted their advice and had kept the price at the level of last year, there would have been a substantial reduction in the acreage, and there would be no possibility of a surplus.  I think that the Estimate made by the former Minister for Agriculture, Deputy Thomas Walsh, that the target to be aimed at should be somewhere between 400,000 and 450,000 acres, was a reasonable one.  It was one that was never likely to be exceeded, but even to go to the extreme and admit that after a couple of good years there would be the possibility of that acreage being exceeded, that there would be the possibility of more than 450,000 acres being grown, and in that way creating a difficulty for the Government, would it not have been better to have had the wheat grown under contract the same as beet and malting barley rather than to impose a cut?</P>
    <P>A reasonable way of delimiting the acreage would be to let farmers sign a contract for whatever amount of wheat they thought they could grow. If the total acreage contracted for exceeded the requirements of 450,000 acres then limit the acreage.  That could have been done without any difficulty. It is being done in regard to malting barley and beet and it creates no administrative problem of any kind. While it might not be necessary next year or the year after, if any circumstance arose in which it would be necessary, it would be a solution of the problem rather than a cutting of the price.</P>
    <P>The Minister, in making a case against the wheat grower in the Dáil, fell back on another line of argument. He launched a fierce attack on what he called the speculator.  Now as we all know the word &ldquo;speculator&rdquo; is what the yanks call &ldquo;a hate word&rdquo;. It is a word used by unscrupulous politicians to whip up public opinion against particular individuals.  We have the same use made of the words &ldquo;Jew&rdquo;, &ldquo;Freemason&rdquo;, &ldquo;banker&rdquo;, and even of &ldquo;politicians&rdquo; and in regard to their collaborators; but having no case and being unable to make <Col N="575" /> any case against the growing of wheat the Minister thought it would be a good thing to start a campaign against a small number of individuals.  We know that Herr Hitler in Germany thought it a very good thing to attack the Jewish minority.  Politicians in every country try that when they have no reasonable, moral or logical grounds for attacks and it very often works fairly well and even successfully.</P>
    <P>As far as speculator in the ordinary sense of the word is concerned, the farmer who grows wheat and carries on farming is a speculator in the broad sense of the word.  If you narrow it down, there are the men who take land by conacre.  There are tens of thousands of farmers taking land for tillage by conacre every year, and I do not think it would be fair to describe any of them as speculators.  Most of them are small farmers who have not sufficient land of their own; many of them are farmers' sons, with agricultural experience, who have not land and who take conacre in order to try and make a little profit for themselves.  But even if you were to take the particular type of speculators mentioned by the Minister, non-farmers in the city, for instance, who took land by conacre, in the same way as the men to whom I have referred, for wheat growing, is there not some better way of dealing with such people, if such a thing is recognised as an abuse, than by cutting the price?  Is it right or just to punish the small farmers throughout the length and breadth of the country because 2 or 3 per cent. of the wheat grown last year was grown under what might be known as an undesirable, or ranching system?</P>
    <P>What is the real evil, if you like, in regard to large-scale wheat growing? The evil, of course, is the growing of wheat in the same land year after year. That is the only real evil.  It is an evil and it is something that should not be encouraged by the Government. It is something which should be prevented.  By the growing of wheat year after year in the same land you exhaust the fertility of that land and you introduce disease into it which will make it impossible for that soil to grow any cereal crop.</P>
    <Col N="576" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there to be any limit to this discussion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already read 76 pages, in the Dáil Debates, of the discussion that took place there on this question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>It might be a good thing if the Senator had to read another 76 pages on the subject now.  It might provide some education for a lot of the Senators.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I sometimes feel sorry for people in the towns and cities who have no patience&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>It is hard to be patient with gloom.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and do not want to hear the views of those who have knowledge of agricultural conditions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>It is abuse and not views.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what is biting Senator Burke, but apparently he thinks that the farmers of the country ought to be penalised.  He thinks that their incomes ought to be cut by 15 per cent. while those of every other section of the community are being greatly increased.  That may appear to him to be a sound proposition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I grow more wheat than the Senator does, and I have made a success of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be better if Senator Cogan were allowed to finish his speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I can make my wheat pay even with the rain coming down on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have said that it would be better if Senator Cogan were allowed to continue his speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I know that what I am saying may offend some people who have no interest in agriculture, no interest in the farmer or the farm worker, but it is essential that the case should be clearly stated for the wheat growers who are so essential to <Col N="577" /> the nation.  The Minister was trying to ride off on the plea that there was an objectionable practice which he called speculation.  I am prepared to acknowledge that the growing of wheat successfully year after year on the same land&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has already said that on two occasions.  He must not repeat himself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I was trying to say it when I was interrupted.  Therefore, some measure should be taken to avoid that, but does anyone think that the cutting of the price is the best way to deal with it?  Remember this, if you take the moneyed man, the non-farmer who takes land by conacre to grow wheat, who has plenty of money to put into it, it is not a cut in the price that is the most serious deterrent to that person.  I think the weather conditions of the present year would probably deter that kind of operation much more effectively than any reduction in price, because anyone who introduces mass production into agriculture can manage perhaps to operate with a very much narrower margin of profit than the ordinary farmer and, therefore, the cutting of the price is not going to put an end to that undesirable practice. The most effective way, I would say, if that practice is to continue&mdash;and I hope it will not&mdash;would be to deal with it in the same way as beet, that is, on the contract system, under which every man is allotted a contract in proportion to the area of his holding.  That is done in regard to beet and malting barley and it has been found effective and satisfactory.  Therefore, neither on the grounds of a surplus nor on the ground that an undesirable farming practice has grown up on the guaranteed price, can this cut be justified.  Since the reasons the Minister gave in the Dáil were fallacious, were fraudulent if you like, we are entitled to ask&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Did he say fraudulent? Sir, is not that a curious word to apply to proceedings in the other House.  Perhaps the Senator does not understand it.  Surely fraudulent is not an orderly word?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="578" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to school to the Senator on the other side. Certainly, the reasons given could have no support in logic.  There is no possibility or likelihood of a surplus within the coming year and as far as speculation is concerned it can be dealt with much more effectively than by a price cut.  We are entitled to ask what were the real reasons for this slashing of the farmers' income.  I would suggest that the real reason, the true reason why the Government decided that this £1,000,000 or £1,500,000 or £2,000,000 would have to be taken from the farmers of Ireland, was that they wanted the money, they wanted it desperately, they wanted it badly and they had to get it.  That was the real reason and I do not think anyone can deny that.  Money was required to meet commitments which were not provided for in the Budget, which the present Government decided upon&mdash;increased bonuses and salaries to civil servants and increased subsidies and, perhaps, also to meet the demand which is being made for increased allowances for members of the Oireachtas.  All these demands have been put up to the Government.  Some of them are being met and money must be found from some source. There was no source available but the poor unfortunate farmer and he has to pay this levy when he grows his wheat</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That, I think, is the main reason, but of course, there is another reason which is perhaps an historic reason for the cut in the price of wheat.  The Minister for Agriculture and the whole Fine Gael Party have campaigned against wheat growing down through the last 20 years, campaigned vigorously, viciously and ruthlessly.  We are told that again and again, and I have listened to speeches made against the growing of wheat.  Wheat, we were told, was a &ldquo;cod,&rdquo; wheat was entirely undesirable and wheat and beet, we were told, even by the present Minister, would eventually go &ldquo;up the spout.&rdquo;  I think on one occasion the present Minister said: &ldquo;God speed the day,&rdquo; calling upon the Almighty to assist him in such a nefarious policy. This old hate of wheat and the wheat grower has asserted itself as every <Col N="579" /> reasonable person knew it would assert itself eventually.  I am reminded of the words of the poet in this respect:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I dread the drugged cup, not the open blow,</P>
    <P>I dread the old hate in a new disguise.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The Minister approached wheat growing in a new disguise since he came into office.  He pretended to be favourable, but when the opportunity arose he took advantage of it to slash the price, hoping that by so doing he would cut down the acreage and would send wheat growing into oblivion as he often promised he would do in the past.  Here are his words on the 18th June, 1947.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A Senator A Senator">
      <NameTxt>A Senator</NameTxt>
      <P>Quote some of your own words about Deputy Dr. Ryan when he was Minister for Agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am prepared to give the Senator in question all the time he likes to quote anything I have ever said on agricultural policy and I stand over every word of it.  I am quoting from the Dáil Report of the 18th June, 1947:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;I want to say again with emphasis that once wheat from abroad is available to this country I would not be found dead in a field of wheat on my land in this country because I know that that whole rotten fraud&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>I notice the word &ldquo;fraud&rdquo; being used here&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;&mdash;&mdash;in fact was invoked to permit the Rank interests and the other milling interests in this country to charge our people 30/- a cwt. for flour when they were selling it in Liverpool for 19/-.  I will not have to worry because the wheat scheme is as dead as a door nail.  Take off your compulsion to-morrow and see how much wheat will be grown.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The compulsion was taken off.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator oblige me with the reference?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the Dáil Report of the 18th June, 1947 on the Vote for <Col N="580" /> Agriculture.  On the 9th July 1948, when the Minister was Minister for Agriculture, with all the responsibility of ministerial office on his shoulders, he said:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;I hold precisely the same views now as I have always held about growing wheat on Irish land in times of peace when supplies are available from other sources&mdash;in my judgment it is a &lsquo;cod&rsquo; and a waste of land.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Though the Minister has been absolutely consistent in this vendetta against wheat growing down through the years to the present day, I would ask the House not to be influenced by the fad or whim of a Minister who hates a particular crop.  The average farmer, regardless of political views, is not prejudiced against any particular crop.  He will grow any crop provided it gives him a reasonable profit.  He is a practical man, and I ask the House to be practical in dealing with this matter.  Judge the matter on these issues, regardless of what the Minister's personal feelings may be in regard to wheat; judge the matter in a logical way.  If you do, I think you will be satisfied that it is desirable, at least for one year, that the price be continued.  This motion only asks for the price to be effective for one year. It is desirable that this should be done, and in the course of the next year, perhaps, if the price remains unchanged, as I hope it will, that this House will recommend that it remain unchanged, and that the Minister will accept that recommendation.  I hope that during the course of the next 12 months a national farmers' union will be established, and that that organisation will meet the Minister, and, by peaceful negotiation, arrive at an agreement in regard to wheat and other crops.  There is no need to be deceived by the suggestions the Minister makes in regard to substitutes for wheat.  There is no need to substitute any crop for wheat.  Wheat growing can be continued at an acreage of between 400,000 acres and 450,000 acres. That crop is only one-twentieth of our total agricultural acreage, and we can grow in addition to wheat, oats, barley and potatoes.  I hope there will be an increase in the acreage of these <Col N="581" /> crops, and that we steadily push our tillage area up to approximately 3,000,000 acres, and that we will have a well-balanced agricultural economy based on fair play for the farmers, and for every particular commodity produced on the farm.  Therefore, I ask the House to accept this motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanHartney" hpid="Mr. Hartney Mr. Hartney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hartney</NameTxt>
      <P>I formally second this motion.  I will intervene in the debate at a later stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I am included in the vocabulary of &ldquo;hate&rdquo; words in the mind of the mover of the motion because he talked about my being an armchair economist.  Whether I am a very good economist or not I am obliged I think to plead guilty to that description.  I hope to deal with this question in a very detached way.  I am not going to discuss the particular terms of the motion because the actual price is one upon which I am unfit to express an opinion.  When the motion was moved the whole question of the propriety of subsidising wheat growing was raised.  I realise that the price this year will disappoint the farmers who naturally want to get as much as they can.  Similarly perhaps it will disappoint the Minister for Finance who wants to give as little as he can.  It is a matter for the Minister to disentangle himself as well as he can from the embarrassing legacy that has been left to him by his predecessors and by the election promises of his own Party, and to try to get back some sort of sanity in agriculture with the least cost to the taxpayer and to the land of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The views which I am about to express I want to say are not a new point of view.  I have had the misfortune of having to study this question in a professional capacity for over 30 years.  The first time I had to tackle this question was at the Agricultural Commission which was reported in 1924. The whole question was then debated and the majority came down on the side of not subsidising any particular cereal crop.  The matter was discussed in detail in the first committee on which members of the Fianna Fáil Party cooperated with the then Government in 1928, and again the majority of that <Col N="582" /> committee recommended against subsidising wheat.</P>
    <P>In the Dáil debate on wheat prices on 2nd December&mdash;I refer you to column 1557 in which Deputy Allen makes a reference to this.  He said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Down in the Library there is a document which should bring a blush of shame to the cheeks of anyone who reads it.  There is a document down there published by the Cumann na nGaedheal Government at the expense of the taxpayers proving why wheat should not be grown here.  Young Deputies in this House should go down to the Library and read that document.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I take it that the document he referred to was the report of the Economic Committee on wheat growing which sat in 1928.  I would point out that that committee did not say that wheat should not be grown here. What the committee did say was that wheat should not be subsidised, which is a very different thing.  The matter came up again in the Banking Commission of 1934-38.  This commission which devoted considerable attention to Irish agriculture, expressed the view against artificial encouragement of cereal crops at the possible expense of other types of production.  The circumstances in the '30s when the Banking Commission was sitting did to some extent, I think, justify the policy at that time.  When the economic war was raging certain artificial support for agriculture may have been necessary.  I would draw attention to the fact that the cereal policy of the Government in the '30s was one of raising the production of all cereal crops and not of one at the expense of the others.</P>
    <P>On these separate occasions, I had the misfortune to devote a great deal of time to studying this question.  I had no personal interest of any kind whatsoever, and studied it with detachment and objectivity.  I came to the conclusion on those three occasions that wheat subsidies in peace-time in this country are not justified.  The case for subsidising wheat in the '20s and '30s was based on slogans and false history.  People seemed to believe <Col N="583" /> that there was something mystical about wheat which was not present in other crops.  For instance, such slogans as &ldquo;The staff of life&rdquo;, &ldquo;The food of the poor&rdquo; were freely bandied about in those discussions and reference was made to self-sufficiency and remarks of that kind.  A good deal of false history was invoked.  It is true that since the time of the Famine there has been a fall in the area under wheat.  The change is one which took place in other European countries as well. Actually I think that was a condition of the progress of the 19th century that Europe was getting some of its food cheaper from abroad and was turning over its own agriculture to the production of more profitable foodstuffs. As I said, that all belongs to the past.</P>
    <P>The circumstances of the war, of course, brought about undoubtedly a different situation.  From 1949 to 1955 any Government that was in power had the duty to try and grow as much wheat as possible at home.  My objecttion to this motion and to the general thought behind it is that it is an attempt to continue a war-time policy in peace-time.  The war has been over for nine years.  We have disarmed in every direction.  All our other war-time policies have been rejected and scrapped except the wheat policy.  This security measure taken in war-time is still continued to-day.</P>
    <P>Senator Cogan dealt with the question of wheat growing.  I know it is a matter on which there is a difference of opinion, but I would like to give my reply to it at any rate.  I quite admit that in case of war it is necessary to try to grow as much wheat as possible, but it is possible to expand wheat production in war-time without keeping up the wheat area in peace-time. It seems to me that the best way to ensure that wheat would be produced in war-time would be by keeping land in good heart and fertility during peace-time in order that it could be rapidly turned over to wheat.  Secondly, it would be desirable to maintain a large supply of first-class seed wheat.  Finally, we should encourage mechanisation, production and <Col N="584" /> milling of other cereal crops.  In that way all the land, the skill and the machinery would be available for a rapid turnover to wheat production if circumstances required it again.</P>
    <P>For any country to continue its war-time policy in peace-time is an unhealthy policy to pursue.  I always think that it is like a healthy man with an invalid's diet.  When a man is sick, he has to keep to a certain diet.  He has to limit himself and he has to avoid certain types of food, but for a strong healthy man to confine himself to an invalid's diet is the surest sign of a hypochondriac.  If he does that long enough his natural health will be impaired.  I suggest that turning over agriculture to one particular crop in this country prevents that country's natural healthy growth just as the healthy man who sticks to an invalid's diet does himself more harm than good.  He undermines his constitution. A diet which is good for him in illness may be bad for him in health.  That, generally speaking, is to my mind the case against wheat growing.  The Minister in the Dáil debate on this subject put the matter so well that I would like to quote a few sentences from his speech because it seems to me to be the pith of the whole discussion.  I quote from Volume 1523 of the Dáil Debates, dated 2nd December, 1954:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Do not let us forget that Ireland has 12,000,000 acres of arable land and the people who live on it and nothing else.  It is that which is setting the standard of living for every individual in this country whether they live in town, city or countryside.... I must try, as my predecessor and his predecessor before him have done, to help the people who are living on the land of Ireland to get, not for themselves alone but for us all, the standard of living we enjoy and, more than that, the raw materials and the means to provide industrial employment for between 100,000 and 200,000 of our people who if they are thus employed must go elsewhere to seek a living.  Bear this in mind, that if we fail to export agricultural produce profitably, it is not the farmer who will feel the first <Col N="585" /> blast.  When we have not the means to pay for the raw materials of industrial employment, the man who was thrown out of work in the cities and towns has no cottage to go home to where he would at least find milk, eggs and oatmeal to assist him over the lean period; he has nothing to go home to but his unemployment pay.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>May I say with respect that that passage to my mind summarised the whole situation?  The 12,000,000 acres of land must be employed with the maximum of intelligence and the minimum of waste.  We must apply our minds to that 12,000,000 acres of land with the same ingenuity that an engineer approaches an engineering problem.  We must use the land with the utmost efficiency in the sense that we get the maximum return with the minimum of effort.</P>
    <P>The report of the Banking Commission was mainly concerned with financial problems but in the course of dealing with those financial problems it had to have regard to the balance of payments.  The Banking Commission were very strongly of the opinion that this country should concentrate on the production of crops which it could export.  A large amount of industry now requires materials from outside this country and unless agriculture is in a position to export in large quantities at competitive prices the whole superstructure of industry, as the Minister stated, would topple down.  Therefore, from a purely general point of view and merely regarding the matter as an engineering problem, it seems to me that to try to deflect agricultural production into any artificial direction requires very strong justification.</P>
    <P>I do not say that such a justification could not exist.  I think it exists in war-time but in peace-time I do not think the case has been made for deflecting Irish agricultural production into the growing of wheat.  To deflect it into wheat seems to me to require particular justification.  I am not animated, as the mover of the motion suggested, by hatred of the crop but by a certain calm and objective study <Col N="586" /> of the matter in which I have no personal interest of any kind whatsoever.</P>
    <P>In the first place, it seems to me that the guaranteed price of wheat benefits only a very small minority of the farmers themselves.  As far as I can understand, only one tenth of the farmers in this country derive any benefit from the high price of wheat. It seems to benefit minorities of farmers in every section of the country. The farmers who have a particular type of soil and who are situated in a particular part of the country derive a greater benefit than the farmers situated in a different way.  The price definitely assists the large rather than the small farmer.  A policy which is designed to encourage wheat growing is definitely a policy which is designed to assist the large and not the small farmer.</P>
    <P>It leads, as the mover of the motion admitted, to over-cropping.  Although he would not agree with me in this, it also leads to speculation and to the abuse of the subsidy by the conacre system.  Incidentally, it has the effect of putting up the price of conacre land for other farmers who want to use it for other purposes.</P>
    <P>The real objection is something that I mentioned before in connection with the policy of the 1930's.  To subsidise any other cereal crop at the expense of others leads to the extraordinary situation that we have a surplus of one crop and a deficit of others, and that, at a time when wheat is produced in very large quantities, this country has to go outside its own shores in order to obtain its necessary supplies of oats and barley.  The policy in the 1930's of encouraging all cereal crops at least prevented that extraordinary paradoxical situation.</P>
    <P>In the commission in 1928, the question of employment was very seriously considered because one of the arguments in favour of subsidies was the employment it gave.  If Senators, in the light of what I said earlier, could bring themselves to read this discussion which Deputy Allen seemed to think would make any decent Irishman blush, they would find interesting figures showing that the labour content <Col N="587" /> of wheat is lower than that of any other crop.  Therefore, from the point of view of giving employment, if that is to be the end of economic policy which, of course, is extremely doubtful, it is a bad crop.  If a crop has to be subsidised for that purpose, almost any other crop would give more employment than wheat.  Wheat is essentially a crop which can successfully be produced nowadays by mechanisation &mdash; and mechanisation requires imported fuel.  In order to make the country independent of the outside world, what you would gain on wheat you would lose on fuel for tractors and other machines for the crop. That is an aspect of this question that must be borne in mind&mdash;that if there is likely to be an interruption in our supplies of imported wheat there is likely to be an interruption in our supplies of imported fuel.</P>
    <P>The mover of the motion stated, at the end of his speech, that one of the objects of the Government in reducing the wheat subsidy is to save the expenditure of some public money.  That does not seem to me to be a bad thing in itself: for a Government to try to save some expenditure is a very good thing.  However, I should like to point out again to Senators that, if they could bear to read this document which had such a very bad effect on Deputy Allen, they would find there calculations regarding the expenditure of the same amount of money on agriculture in other directions.</P>
    <P>The objection to spending money on wheat subsidy is not that it goes into the farmers' pockets but that it goes into the farmers' pockets for a purpose which is not nationally beneficial.  The argument of that committee&mdash;the Economic Committee of 1928&mdash;was that the same amount of money spent on agriculture in a different way would bring about productive and lasting results; that the same amount of money spent on drainage, research, education, subsidies for credits, lime and other similar things, would build up productive activity in the country and would pay for itself in the long run.  They pointed out that, by subsidising one particular crop, the subsidy has to be <Col N="588" /> repeated year after year, and that if the subsidy is withdrawn the acreage automatically goes down.  They thought, and I still think, that that is an unsatisfactory situation.  As somebody said at the time, in what I consider a good metaphor, the difference between spending a certain amount of public money on agricultural research and on wheat subsidy is the difference between spending money on a perambulator and on a bath chair.</P>
    <P>There is some hope that, some day, the occupant of the perambulator will be able to walk around by himself whereas we know that the person in the bath chair will have to be wheeled around to the end of his life.  I suggest that the wheat subsidy is rather like the bath chair.  The same amount of money spent on agriculture itself-not spent on other sections of the community&mdash;could bring about a rapidly-growing child which would soon be able to dispense with the artificial assistance.  I want to make that point in particular because I know what will be said later in the course of this debate, that is, that I am a spokesman for urban interests; that I object to money being spent on agriculture and that, as the mover of the motion said, we all object to money going into the pockets of the farmers whereas we do not object to its going into the pockets of the civil servants or the pockets of other sections of the community.</P>
    <P>That is why I want to emphasise that the Economic Committee of 1928 did not advocate not spending money on agriculture but, instead, advocated spending money on agriculture in a reproductive fashion&mdash;not in a mere deflective fashion&mdash;spending money not merely as a crutch but as an investment. Therefore, I do not base my objection to wheat on the ground that money is being spent on agriculture, but that it is being spent in a fashion that I, for one, would certainly consider rather wasteful.</P>
    <P>I shall end this speech as I began it. I consider that the Minister has inherited a legacy from his predecessors and, indeed, from the election speeches of his own Party.  He has promised a guaranteed price for wheat for some years, although the amount <Col N="589" /> of the guarantee was never stated at the time of the election.  The Government cannot be convicted of any breach of promise in this matter because a promise of a guarantee is not the same thing as a promise to continue a guarantee at any particular level.  All they did was to promise to continue the guarantee.  I hope that the Minister&mdash;with his courage, his vision, his foresight, his knowledge of agriculture and his inheritance of the great agricultural policy of the first Cumann na nGaedheal Government&mdash; will proceed as rapidly as he can, subject to legitimate expectations, to let agriculture go back to its natural line of development with the minimum cost to the Exchequer and the minimum damage to the soil of the country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Seanad is greatly indebted to Senator Cogan for elucidating from Senator O'Brien the speech which he has just made. Personally, I am deeply indebted to Senator Cogan for providing the occasion on which Senator O'Brien saw fit to quote me at some length with approbation&mdash;for to be so quoted is fame indeed.</P>
      <P>Now, I am obliged to say that I feel constrained to offer the Seanad an apology for being forced to rehash a debate that took place at some length in Dáil Éireann on the 2nd of this month.  It is with a guilty conscience that I must tender to the Seanad substantially what I said in the Dáil, for I have heard no new issue raised, no new point made.  However, the fact that the Seanad have invited me here to speak to them imposes on me the obligation of addressing to them virtually what I think, with great respect, they could much more conveniently have read at their leisure in the columns of the Official Report of Dáil Éireann, Volume 147, No. 10. However, since it is the pleasure of the Seanad that I should reiterate this debate to them, we have one and a half hours and I shall consume my modest portion of that period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator O'Brien has referred to the labour content of wheat as a crop which, as he rightly said, was often advanced as a justification for the <Col N="590" /> promotion of this crop.  Yet when Deputy Moher was speaking in Dáil Éireann, as reported at column 1508 of the Official Report of the 2nd December last, he wished to be put on record as saying: &ldquo;What I did say was that the combine was the solution to a very acute labour problem&mdash;a very acute labour problem&mdash;in the grain-growing areas.&rdquo;  To that I replied:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;It is the old story of whether the hen comes before the egg or the egg comes before the hen.  I think what Deputy Moher, in any case, says is that when there are very few labourers on the land the combine is a great blessing for the farmer who is without labourers on his land. Is not that so?  I remember the time when I used to be told that the wheat policy was designed to multiply the number of agricultural workers employed on the land.  You pays your money and you takes your choice.  I hope I do Deputy Moher no injustice, but it seems that when it suits Deputy Moher to say at the cross-roads that he is urging the employment of more and more men on the land and that the policy he advocates of 82/6 a barrel for wheat is designed to employ men on the land, that is scarcely consistent with the proposition so resonantly put forward by him to-day, that the combine is the most valuable instrument available to a farmer who has the fewest labourers on the land.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The next point that was raised was how did the Fianna Fáil Government &mdash;who, it is now universally agreed, proposed to limit the acreage of wheat to an acreage that would produce approximately 300,000 tons of dried wheat on the mill floor&mdash;propose to do it.</P>
    <P>How did they propose to do it?  All are agreed that they were wrong in doing it.  How did they propose to do it?  I cannot get any supporter of the Fianna Fáil Government to answer that question to me.  There are only two ways in which they could have done it.  One was to ration the acreage. Now, I ask Fianna Fáil Senators here to tell the Seanad before the debate is over did they propose to recruit <Col N="591" /> again what was so poetically described by their own Minister for Agriculture as five fields of inspectors and the Civic Guards to go out and inspect every farm in Ireland and to point out to each farmer: &ldquo;You will be allowed to grow a rood of wheat; you will be allowed to grow an acre of wheat; and you will be allowed to grow 100 acres of wheat&rdquo;?  If it was not their intention to measure up the land of every farm in Ireland, how did they propose to keep the acreage down?</P>
    <P>It is suggested that the adverse weather this season would have deterred a great many farmers from growing it next season, but surely the argument that is made here is that it is a cruel hardship not to give the men who suffered under the adverse harvest this year a chance to get their money back next year, and I can assure the Seanad that, when I have read to them a list of acreages set in wheat in a variety of farms not far from this city by optimists this year, they will realise that, if the present price of 82/6 was maintained for wheat, the number of persons engaged in that type of agriculture would have doubled, trebled and quadrupled next year.</P>
    <P>I cannot dismiss from my mind the belief that the case being made by members of the Fianna Fáil Party in the Dáil and now in the Seanad is that the men who did not get away with the swag this year ought to be given a chance to get it back next year and that it is a most cruel thing to rob them of that chance after they have suffered from adverse weather conditions in 1954.</P>
    <P>I should like to give the Seanad&mdash;it is my duty to give the Seanad&mdash;certain statistics relating to the speculation that went on in wheat this year, but I want to give them in this context: I want to suggest to the Seanad that the right test of a policy is its results and that is the only legitimate test of a policy.  Now, what did the policy of paying 82/6 a barrel for wheat result in for all of us to see?  We are now in the month of December and we have in store a very large quantity of very poor quality wheat.  We have no oats and we <Col N="592" /> have no barley, and I am obliged to license the import of oats from Scotland and I am obliged to license the import of barley from Iraq.  Is that a desirable result of policy?  Does that result commend the policy that evoked that result to the Seanad?</P>
    <P>I want also to demonstrate the type of wheat culture that evolved as a result of the price fixed for wheat, and, remember, this emerged&mdash;what I am about to describe&mdash;in a year in which we have no oats and no barley in the month of December.  In County Dublin, three individuals harvested 1,000 acres of wheat each and of that at least 60 per cent. was conacre land. Senators might remember that, with a fixed price of 82/6 per barrel for wheat, that represents a subsidy of approximately £8 per acre, so that these three gentlemen got away with £24,000 of subsidy on their 3,000 acres of wheat. In the same County of Dublin, three other individuals had each between 500 and 1,000 acres under wheat.  In addition, there were 16 persons in the County Dublin with between 100 and 500 acres of wheat.  In the County Kildare, we had one grower with between 500 and 1,000 acres; and we had 24 individuals in County Kildare with between 100 and 500 acres of wheat.  In Meath, we had one combine who had between 500 and 1,000 acres and we had 11 with between 100 and 500 acres.  In Kilkenny, we had 23 individuals with between 100 and 500 acres of wheat; in Tipperary, five; and in Carlow, eight.  Does anyone consider that that kind of farming is a contribution to prosperity or to anything else that is desirable?  I do not think it is.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanHayes1927" hpid="Mr. S. Hayes Mr. S. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister give us the townlands and the names of those people in Tipperary or in the other counties?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I have them all here, Senator, but I question the propriety of reading out the names of persons who did what was perfectly legitimate and what they were, in fact, encouraged by the Government of the day to do.  I am not indicting the individuals who did this; I am indicting the Government who urged them to do it; <Col N="593" /> but if a Government urges people to do something which, in the judgment of the community is monstrous, you blame the Government and not the individual, and I do not think it would be a fair thing to hold up to public odium, for that is what would fall upon them, the names of individuals who sought guidance from the Fianna Fáil Government and who, having got that guidance and direction, acted upon it. Am I not right in saying that, if there be odium to bear, let the Government that persuaded these individuals to do this thing bear the odium and do not visit it on those who carried out the advice tendered to them by their own Government of the day?  I do not think the Seanad will think me unfair in adopting that attitude, though, God knows, there are few in this category to whom I am indebted, in any sense of the word.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanHayes1927" hpid="Mr. S. Hayes Mr. S. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not surprising that the Minister for Lands would not indict them or try to get after them in respect of this land they are abusing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>To-morrow is a new day, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is conacre land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>It is conacre, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Sixty per cent. of it was conacre, but we do not like landlords in this country&mdash;we never have&mdash;and I have not any doubt that the Irish Land Commission will wish to know who is it sets his land perennially and will inquire into whether such land may not profitably be placed in the hands of those who are prepared to labour it themselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I put, in competition with the policy which has evoked these surprising results, the policy on which I hope to proceed.  But, before doing that, I want to turn to a matter which was mentioned by Senator O'Brien.  The plain fact is that I find myself in entire agreement with all that Senator O'Brien has said, and if anyone does not like that they can lump it.  I think the Senator will sympathise with me in this: that while certain economic <Col N="594" /> facts are inescapable, it is the duty of a democratic Government to have regard, in its administration of public affairs, to considerations other than those strictly economic.  I have ventured the proposition before, that the true test of democratic Government is not the size of its majority but that its title deeds to the description &ldquo;democratic&rdquo; are its solicitude and honest care for the rights of the minority which it is called to govern.</P>
    <P>Now, it is an inescapable fact, as Senator O'Brien has said, that there is an element amongst our people with a sort of mystic devotion to the wheat crop, who would feel it a grievous imposition upon them if a new Government, coming into office, suddenly created a situation in which it was economically impossible for them to continue the cultivation of that crop. It was for that reason that in 1948, when the inter-Party Government came in, that we not only guaranteed the price but we increased the price, then guaranteed for wheat, from 57/6 to 62/6, and we did that avowedly for the purpose&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>The increase was made in the November before the inter-Party Government came into power, and the Minister knows that better than I do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I understood that this body was the very citadel of civility. I understand that Senator Hawkins will have abundant opportunities of speaking after me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Eamon Ó Ciosáin Eamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Eamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nothing uncivil about that remark.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, an interruption is a liberty which should be rarely taken as the Senator and I well know from our long experience in another place. Suffice it for me to say now that it was for that very reason in 1948 when we came into office that we did guarantee the price of 57/6 and increased it to 62/6 so as to carry reassurance to those, then in the minority, that we would respect and protect their legitimate prejudices to wheat, to which, in a free community, they were entitled as free men.  In the campaign which led to their recent defeat, again <Col N="595" /> it was our duty and pleasure, in deference to their legitimate prejudices as free men in a free society, to ensure that they would receive from the inter-Party Government precisely the same forbearance and solicitude for their feelings as they had found in 1948. They might rest assured that for a period of five years there would be a guaranteed price for wheat, and that when it became prudent and necessary to fix a new price for wheat which represented a reduction on the price then ruling, it would go so far as to provide a new guarantee for a period of two years at a fixed rate.</P>
      <P>The purpose of that was to carry conviction to the minority in this country that it was the desire of the Government to give them a larger measure of security in the enjoyment of their particular preference in this matter than they had ever enjoyed heretofore.  Possibly on the strict ruling of economics, it would be hard to defend that position, but I have no doubt that by the criterion of sound democratic procedure it was the right course to adopt.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to come now to the price. We would not have done our part as democrats in an Irish Government if we had proposed to our people, who had this burning zeal to grow this particular crop, a price which would have made it economically impossible for them to grow it.  I want to say to the Seanad with the fullest possible deliberation, that the price of 70/- per barrel for wheat bushelling over 63 lb. is a fair price.  I want to point out to the Seanad that that price represents a bonus of from 12/6 to 20/- per barrel over the world price obtaining for wheat.  The Government, with their eyes wide open, deliberately provided that bonus for Irish wheat in favour of those who desired to grow it.  I see that to-day the old absurdity of pretending that the price offered for Irish wheat is the lowest price offered in Europe has been abandoned.  There has been no reference, I take it, to Turkey, Portugal and elsewhere in the Seanad.  There was the ardent argument made that the price offered for wheat in Ireland was lower than that <Col N="596" /> offered by any other nation in Europe. If Senators wish to see that particular thesis torn to pieces and revealed to be the fallacious argument that it truly is, I would refer them to column 1522, Volume 147, No. 10 of the Dáil Debates.</P>
    <P>I want now to put in competition with the policy as declared by Fianna Fáil of 82/6 per barrel for wheat, and no barley and no oats, the policy which it is the intention of our Government to place before the people, and I gladly invite any challenge on that at the people's tribunal.  Our object is to bring the three cereal crops into some rational relationship with a view to securing that there will be adequate supplies of all, and, accordingly, we offer to farmers who want to grow wheat the assurance that for two years they will have a guaranteed price of 70/- a barrel for the wheat they grow.</P>
    <P>We are in the process of arranging that the oatmeal millers of this country will make contracts with the farmers of this country to grow all the oats that they require in the coming season at prices which the farmers will be prepared to accept.  We are in negotiation with the compound feeding manufacturers and shall shortly discuss the matter with the maize meal manufacturers, and we will reinforce such agreements as we may make with both these bodies with the full resources of the Government to ensure that those who grow feeding barley in the country will be guaranteed access to a minimum price of 40/- per barrel for green barley delivered at a suitable number of delivery points throughout the country.  Now, it will be quite free to any farmer who wishes and who is in a position to sell his barley for more than 40/- a barrel to go and sell it for more if he can get it, but he has the certain knowledge that if he can find no buyer a buyer will be provided for good quality feeding barley without limit as to the quantity for 40/- a barrel next year.</P>
    <P>By this method we hope to secure an adequate supply of barley and oats for our domestic needs and such proportion of our wheat needs as farmers may think fit to produce.  And we have the comforting belief that, <Col N="597" /> whereas it is absolutely or virtually impossible to find a foreign market for surplus wheat in questionable condition, there is relatively little difficulty in securing a ready market for any coarse grain, such as oats and barley, that we might have for sale surplus to our own domestic requirements.  I should add that I should think it highly unlikely that in any early future we would grow in our circumstances quantities of coarse grain in excess of our domestic requirements, but I have the virtual certainty that if we do there would be relatively little difficulty in disposing of it in the markets of the world.</P>
    <P>I put that policy of a balanced sane type of cereals from the agricultural land of this country, plus an adequate acreage of barley and potatoes, fodder beet and such other crops as the farmers think it prudent to produce as the raw material of our live-stock industry, against a policy which produces wheat which is extremely difficult to use, with a steadily diminishing acreage of oats, barley and potatoes; and I invite the Seanad to judge which policy is the better.</P>
    <P>I do not think the Seanad can legitimately dismiss from its recollection that the present Government of this country stands bound by the International Wheat Agreement signed by our predecessors, to take delivery of 270,000 tons of wheat this year and next year if it is tendered to us by any member of the International Wheat Agreement at the minimum price of $1.55 cents, f.o.b. Port Arthur.  I think it must be remembered that the present guaranteed price continues for the entire period in which that obligation devolves upon us in the agreement entered into by my predecessor.</P>
    <P>It may be relevant for me to remind the Seanad that our policy can be crystallised into the aphorism: &ldquo;One more cow, one more sow and one more acre under the plough.&rdquo;  Our objective, then, is to secure not only a growing acreage of cereal crops, prudently diversified, but also to keep constantly pressing into the minds of our farmers the vital value of grass, grown as a crop and recognised by the farmers as <Col N="598" /> such, to be used as the most valuable raw material of the live-stock industry that we can extract from the land of Ireland.  I glory in the fact that part of my duty, in addition to promoting the extensive production of tillage crops, is to keep for ever before the minds of the farmers who live upon and work our 12,000,000 acres of arable land, that every acre of it should in its due rotation carry a crop of grass, as carefully sown, tended, fertilised and saved as any other crop that is sown upon that land.  I think it is my duty to keep for ever before the eyes of our people the fact that one of the illusions, one of the delusions, that has cost us as a people dear, has been the delusion that grass was not a crop but simply an accident that happened to the land.  The fact is that those who believe that some providential accident will sow their land in grass without thought or care are being deluded into believing that grass grown where in fact there was a luxurious crop of weeds, is wasting land.</P>
    <P>All these fundamental truths of agriculture it is my duty to keep constantly before the minds of the farmers.  But I must do more than that, if the duties of the office I hold are to be faced with a discharge.  I must bring within their reach the means effectively to use each acre of land, and there, I should submit to the Seanad, my duty stops.  It is true that an excess of zeal has persuaded some of my predecessors to believe that in certain circumstances they had a duty to line the ditches of the farmers with Civic Guards and to recruit five fields of inspectors to break down their gates and burst open their fences, in order to make them do what they considered it right for them to do. I do not accept from this Legislature or anyone else any such duty or obligation. My duty is to bring within the knowledge, within the reach of the farmer and to take my stand where, by the grace of God, the Land League put every man except the man who owns his land&mdash;standing on the farmer's threshold until he was invited in.  It is to me a privilege that I am a servant of the farmers of this country; and should the Oireachtas ever thrust upon me the rôle of being their master, I would reject it contemptuously to <Col N="599" /> the hands which sought to give it to me.</P>
    <P>To return to more mundane affairs, I admit that the price of £1 a barrel for transferring green wheat dried to the mill floor is a charge that causes me some concern.  It was a charge not absent from my mind when I spoke of the wheat racket being instituted to serve the profits of the Rank interests in this country.  It is true that the Fianna Fáil Government prescribed that the miller who handled the wheat of the farmers of Ireland would be paid £1 a barrel for his trouble and his profit as a miller superimposed thereupon. Who fixed that margin?  Come now, let as come down to tin tacks.  There is £1 a barrel for transferring green wheat from the farmer's sack to the miller's floor.  Who fixed that margin? I hear no angry denials from the Fianna Fáil Benches.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Who is retaining it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>You ask me who is retaining it.  They do not deny the paternity of the baby.  I do not deny I have their foundling in my house and I must deal with it.  To legitimise it is quite beyond my capacity, but I will do my best to make it look respectable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A Senator A Senator">
      <NameTxt>A Senator</NameTxt>
      <P>Give it a good foster-father.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to put a question to the Minister.  Is it not true that in 1948, a particular inquiry was set up, presided over by no less a person than Senator, now Judge, Lavery? I must ask the Minister is his report available to him, and if these matters referred to had taken place, why did not the Government of which Senator Lavery was Minister, and which afterwards appointed him judge, take action to eliminate these irregularities?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Because in 1951, our people asserted the sovereign right denied them by the Senator's leader to do wrong.  We have always believed on this side of the House that the Irish people have the right to do wrong, and <Col N="600" /> by heavens, they exercised that right in June, 1951.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>And in 1918.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>And if they exercised it, at least they vindicated the freedom they enjoyed.  More power to their elbow, and mind you there was a time when they wanted a good deal of power from their elbow to retain it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>And they exercised that power in the interests of the Irish nation.  But the Minister is getting away from answering the question. Here is a report presented at the expense of the State, by Senator Lavery, making certain recommendations, why did not the then Government take action?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Because in the month of June, 1951, the people of Ireland exercised their often challenged right to do wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>As they will on the next occasion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Time will tell.  In the interim, they have exercised their sovereign right to do right, and we are here.  If Senator Hawkins feels that my observations in relation to the 20/-bargain are fair and just, his Government had the findings of that commission in their hands for three years and they did not do anything about it.  Am I to assume that that particular charge of £1 a barrel for transferring grain from the farmer's stack to the mill floor is a fair and legitimate charge? I gave way to the Senator to answer his question and now I want him to answer me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>When the Minister answers my question I will answer his.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>So we will leave it veiled in obscurity.  I do not think that I have anything further to say on this particular issue.  I think the case is so coercive, that it is hard to reinforce it much further than I have done.  I would refer Senators, if they wish to read a more stringent statement in this case, to Volume 147, No. 10, of the Dáil Debates, particularly to columns 157 to 1525.  Of course, if they wish to <Col N="601" /> spend their time reading the rest of it, they are quite welcome to do so.</P>
      <P>Perhaps, in conclusion I should say, so certain am I that the policy of the Government in this matter is the right policy, and so certain am I that this policy will secure the approval of the vast majority of the decent farmers of this country, that I have caused copies of that debate, including all the speeches made by the Opposition, my speech and every other speech, to be sent to every member of every county committee of agriculture in Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister do the same in regard to this debate?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, God forbid!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, might I suggest to the Minister that it is a grave discourtesy to this House, if he is to differentiate between this House and the other?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A Senator A Senator">
      <NameTxt>A Senator</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not a point of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I mentioned this matter in order to assure the Senators that, on the merits of the case, as stated by both sides, I am anxious on behalf of the Government to take the judgment of the representatives of the farmers in every county in Ireland.  I wanted to bring together all the facts, as stated by the best protagonists of each side, for their consideration, so that we might abide by their judgment.  I have not the slightest doubt what that judgment is going to be.  I would urge upon the Seanad, whose opinion in these matters is highly valued by the Government, to speak as emphatically on behalf of the agricultural community in this matter, as the Dáil did ten days ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I observe that the debate cannot conclude to-night, and that, therefore, the House might adjourn at 10 o'clock to-night?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps there will be a consultation between both sides on this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I have listened with great interest to the debate, and I have read the Dáil debate <Col N="602" /> to which the Minister has referred us.  I notice that on both sides of the House and in the other House there was a hope expressed, fairly universally, that Party politics would be left out.  I get the impression, nevertheless, as an Independent here to-day, that Party politics are very much to the fore.  I think it would be a regrettable fact if it should appear to be implied that the Minister acted as he did simply in order to thwart Fianna Fáil policy, or alternatively, if it were to be said that it was simply because the Minister was &ldquo;hostile to wheat&rdquo; that he acted as he did.</P>
      <P>I should like, therefore, at this juncture to try and express something like a middle view, an independent view I hope.  I suffer from the disability, of course, of being a town-dweller, and urban speaker, and I am fully aware of the fact that the farmer has a tendency to be suspicious, not without cause, of those who live in cities and who tell him how to run his farm.  Sometimes, however, I get the impression that the farmer's view of the town-dweller is carried to extremes. One sometimes gets the impression, in fact, that the farmers would be happier if there was nobody there at all to consume their products&mdash;if the consumer could be wiped out altogether. I think that the equivalent and opposite attitude is sometimes displayed by the miller in relation to the farmer.  I get the impression that the miller sometimes tends to disregard the farmer as a human being, and treats the farmer&mdash;who is his customer&mdash;as a person of no importance at all.</P>
      <P>One would feel happier, if in this farmers' union which, we are told, is to come about, there were to be some investigation of the possibility of having public relations officers to act as go-betweens between miller and farmer and farmer and consumer. This might lead to smoother relations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I see it, on this motion, the general principle of the Minister's price-reduction is right and justified. In my opinion, the price of 82/6, which obtained this year for the best quality wheat, is too high.  It is quite clear, of course, that the fixed price of wheat in this country will necessarily be <Col N="603" /> artificial, just as the prices of many things in this country are artificial. We have just passed through the Seanad at lightning speed some measures whose purpose was to maintain tariffs ranging up to 75 per cent. on industrial articles which might otherwise be cheaply imported, and in order to give the local producers of similar articles the right to place an artificial price upon them.  Therefore, I am not quite so afraid as Senator O'Brien is of artificial subsidised prices because I think that in certain circumstances they can be justified.  I believe that to some extent they can be justified with wheat, as they have been justified, I think, with beet, and with at least some of the industrial products to which I referred.</P>
    <P>The &ldquo;bath chair&rdquo; to which Senator O'Brien referred is apparently considered necessary for large numbers also of the industrial community in this country.  Apparently production is to continue indefinitely for that rather odd vehicle for the benefit of the Irish industrialist.  These protective duties do not gradually disappear and the increasing health and strength of the industrial patient does not apparently allow us ultimately to abolish them.  I think, therefore, that an artificial price is necessary, but that this artificial price of 82/6 is, as far as one can judge, too high. Therefore, a reduction in price was necessary, and the Minister was justified in reaching a decision to that effect.  I would say, however, that both the timing of that decision and the amount of the reduction were ill-judged.</P>
    <P>Why is such a reduction right in principle?  Why do I say that the price was too high?  I would suggest that the price of wheat, as fixed by any Irish Government, should be high enough to justify growing wheat efficiently in this country, but not so high as to ensure over-concentration on wheat.  I will not repeat what the Minister and Senator O'Brien said on that point in relation to oats and barley, but it seemed to me eminently sound.  How can we defend a position in which we have so much concentration upon wheat that we have to import <Col N="604" /> quantities of oats and barley?  I am a little disturbed, nevertheless, by the fact that in relation to these other crops, to which the Minister wants to give encouragement, so far all he can say is that he is in process of negotiation for the purpose of seeing to it that the farmers will get a decent price.  I would prefer if, as in the case of wheat, the facts were recognised and the price decided and told to the public now, at the same time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I interrupt the Senator?  Perhaps, I did not make myself clear.  There will be a minimum price of 40/- per barrel guaranteed for green barley of suitable milling quality.  The minimum price for oats will be negotiated between the millers and the actual farmers they contract with in the same way as the beet price is arranged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, Sir.  I should like to turn now to the question of efficiency.  One of the most insulting things that townspeople can say about Irish farmers is to suggest in any way that they are lacking in efficiency.  I would like just to say something about this word &ldquo;efficiency&rdquo; along these lines: I should like to suggest that it is quite possible for a small farmer to be, technically speaking, &ldquo;inefficient&rdquo; through no fault of his own, through lack of capital, lack of machinery, lack of land and lack of arable acreage.  No amount of hard work&mdash;and all these farmers, almost without exception, work hard&mdash;they work considerably harder than we are obliged to do in the towns&mdash;no amount of hard work will make up for these lacks.  Consequently, from the economic point of view, if it is said in relation to certain small farmers that they are inefficient, it is not because the farmers are not doing their job, but simply because the farmers are under-capitalised and have not got the machinery, the equipment, or sufficient arable acreage.  The methods that are forced on such a farmer, by conditions beyond his control, are inefficient from the point of view of the economy of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It would be departing too far, to go into the question of how in the future you might eliminate, or hope to eliminate <Col N="605" /> such inefficiencies.  Suffice it to say that the State, the community, could help to increase the availability of machines and equipment and facilitate capitalisation for the farmer, and that the State could actively help the farmers to farm co-operatively.  Inevitably, I think, that will have to be done in the future, and I hope in the not too distant future.</P>
    <P>I submit, consequently, that if the wheat price is to be kept sufficiently high to enable this type of small farmer to make a reasonable profit to-day, in spite of the technical inefficiency of method which is not their fault, then the more fortunate and the more highly capitalised farmers will make too much, and some of them will make a packet.  That is one of the dilemmas with which any Minister for Agriculture in this country is faced.  One meets with the same experience in many spheres.  You get the example of a grocers' union trying to see to it that the prices of certain commodities are kept sufficiently high for the small and relatively &ldquo;inefficient&rdquo; grocers to be kept in business, when those same high prices would be bringing in too great a profit to grocers or shopkeepers working on a much bigger scale.</P>
    <P>I would say that the same thing occurs in milling, that the smaller mills are in a sense kept ticking over and kept &ldquo;efficient&rdquo; by prices and profit margins&mdash;such as those referred to by the Minister&mdash;which give to the bigger millers far more profit than can be justified either in private or in public.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>The price of the bag of flour is based on the most uneconomic mill in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Exactly.  In general, I agree with James Connolly when he wrote before the turn of the century, as far back as 1897, that &ldquo;the days of the small farmers, as of the small capitalists are gone, and that wherever they are still found they find it impossible to compete with the mammoth farms of America and Australia.&rdquo;  However, whatever may be the evolution in this country of the small farmer in the future, our concern <Col N="606" /> now is to fix a price which will be something in the nature of a compromise&mdash;a price which will not be so high as to mean too fat a profit to the large-scale mechanised farmer and a price which will not be so low as to drive the small and medium farmer out of wheat, or, worse still, out of farming, for want of a vital cash crop. To make such a decision and to fix a price in that way, is not an easy task. It is further complicated by the fact that a price which would be theoretically right for this purpose could be made to seem far too high or far too low by freak weather conditions&mdash;and, as we all know, freak conditions appear to be the only kind of weather conditions we ever get in this country.</P>
      <P>Now, I believe the Minister is right in thinking that the price of 82/6 per barrel has revealed itself to be too high, and I believe that, secretly, the main Opposition Party agree with him; because the Fianna Fáil aim, as has been stated several times, was that we should be able to produce roughly two-thirds of our requirements of wheat here, calculated at about 300,000 tons of wheat.  For that, it was regarded as being necessary to have an acreage of something like 450,000 acres of wheat.  In the Dáil, referring to Fianna Fáil policy, Deputy Aiken said: &ldquo;Our policy and price were aimed at getting that acreage&rdquo;&mdash;450,000 acres of wheat.  But, in fact, they got far more.  They got 490,000 acres in 1954.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>Under very exceptional circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>They overshot their mark by nearly 10 per cent. Why?  Because the price was too high at 82/6 a barrel.  Therefore, I feel that the Minister is justified in asking the proposers of this motion: &ldquo;How else, except by a cut in the price, would you have reduced the wheat acreage by about 10 per cent. next year, and in future years?&rdquo;  I suggest, therefore, that the Minister is right in principle &mdash;the principle involved in the price cut.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>However, with regard to the timing and the amount, I would have some reservations.  I would say, in regard to timing: at any time, in relation to a crop or in relation to farming the <Col N="607" /> farmers are entitled to a longer warning of any intention radically to alter the price.  They have a right to that at any time, but just this year, when not only have harvesting conditions been appalling, but also, later, after the Minister's decision, there have been flood conditions on many farms, it seems to me that the decision in relation to the individual farmer has been too abrupt.  Why was it so abrupt? Why did the Minister feel it had to be done in what appears to me so swift and hasty a manner?  I suggest that it was, at least in part, due to the fact that the Minister was greatly exasperated by the people whom he calls &ldquo;speculators.&rdquo;  I would express my surprise here, because I am frequently told that when in industry there are to be found people who are prepared to risk their capital in the hope of getting a whacking big dividend, that dividend is justified by the measure of the risk they take&mdash;that these people are rugged individualists, taking advantage of the great system of free enterprise, and raking in a perfectly legitmate return for their money.</P>
    <P>The Minister has said, quite rightly, that these &ldquo;speculators&rdquo; have, in fact, not broken the law.  The whole idea of conacre may be bad: I think almost certainly it is; it may even be ruinous to the land.  However, the law has not dealt with that problem.  Why should we ask these people personally to stand back?  Furthermore, these people produce as good wheat as anybody else, and we are committed to the proposition that we want a certain proportion of our wheat to be Irish-produced. These people produce it. They take us at our word.  If they had not produced good wheat they would not have been paid.  Moreover, I think the Minister, in suggesting that the entire subsidy went to them, is not quite accurate, because at least a proportion of that subsidy went to the owners of the land, in the form of rent for conacre, frequently an inflated rent.  It went into the pocket, in other words, of the landowner who was prepared to let this land&mdash;to whom I think the Minister rightly referred in terms not altogether approving.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="608" /> But what about this landowner and what exactly are we going to do with this type of person, who sits back and reaps this entirely unearned increment from high conacre prices?  What action is intended against him?  The Minister himself in the Dáil&mdash;away back in 1937&mdash;said rightly, and I am sure he will still take this view here: &ldquo;Conacre is a most objectionable form of landlordism, and I should like to know if this is part of the Government's policy&rdquo;.  I also should like to know now if it is part of this Government's policy to let conacre continue, or to tackle it, as I think was implied in the Minister's speech this evening.  I think we should be wrong, however, to allow our sense of exasperation with these people, who have used our wheat policy to their own advantage, make us slash the price so quickly that the worst sufferers will be our own small and medium farmers.  So much for the question of the timing of this cut. Now to the question of the amount.</P>
    <P>I think the amount of the cut has been too big for the farmers to have to adapt themselves to all at once.  I agree that the system of staggered pricing, introduced by the Minister, modifies that a bit, but, in fact, it will hit mainly the combine harvester, because his wheat will not be dry enough, unless he is able to get it dried to store in order to wait for a better price.  I suggest that the attitude underlying the Minister's scheme is an attitude of wanting, to some extent, either to turn back the clock or to hold it back.  I think, in relation to this country and to modern conditions both on the land and in industry, that that attitude is wrong. As I see it, the future of Irish farming lies with the highly-capitalised farm. Will that displace labour?  I very much doubt it.  I submit that the method of farming with the combine team, while it may not, in fact, give all the employment upon the farm, will give employment to the combine team themselves, to the lorry drivers, to the millers, and to the workers in the mills. Furthermore, for these men, I suggest it is a better type of work, and better paid, than the work of the farm labourer on the farm twenty or thirty <Col N="609" /> years ago.  Most of these men are young, independent-minded men, and they are serving the country well.  These teams of combine workers, tractor drivers, lorry drivers, mill workers, and so forth, who represent highly-capitalised mechanised Irish agriculture, could be the making of Irish industry as well as of Irish agriculture.  In a country like Denmark&mdash;which, inevitably, one mentions in relation to farming&mdash;I would mention only this: that in Denmark a smaller percentage of the working population is one the land than in Ireland.  They have more mechanisation; and that has resulted in a big home market for agricultural implements and machines and, in turn, that home market has resulted in a big export trade for such things as agricultural implements, tools, machines, churns, and so forth.</P>
    <P>I regard it as the duty of the State and, consequently, of the Department of Agriculture, to see to it that the advantage to be derived from mechanised agriculture will be spread to the benefit of the whole community &mdash;not just of the few people who work it for their own advantage now.  Let us not, however, on that account be led to act against the combine, against mechanisation.  Let us not be led to discourage, even inadvertently, the great capitalisation of Irish farms, most of which are so grossly under-capitalised to-day.  For all these reasons, I would urge the Minister to reconsider the question of the wheat price for this coming year.</P>
    <P>We have been told that Party politics are not entering into this, but that is clearly nonsense.  Certainly, a great deal of Party political capital would be made out of the fact that the Minister had changed his mind or modified his view, if he did so.  If the Minister changed his mind and modified somewhat the price cut now, inevitably those opposing him would claim very loudly throughout the country the entire credit for it.</P>
    <Col N="610" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask the Senator does he advert to the fact that the price already fixed is for two years?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, I realise that, but I want now to recognise the fact that, if the Minister were to be led to reconsider his view, the credit for that change of mind would be claimed by his political opponents. However, I would further suggest that the Minister is not generally regarded as the most supine of men; he is not notorious for the alacrity with which he yields to appeals, to criticism, to abuse or pressure from political apponents and, consequently, were he to change his mind, to reconsider and to review the situation, in view of the very critical position in many farms to-day, the motives, I suggest, of the Minister could not be misinterpreted. In other words&mdash;and I say this in conclusion&mdash;I believe in all sincerity that he is a big enough man to reconsider the matter on its merits, and to announce, first of all, his intention for next year and subsequent years to make a substantial cut in the guaranteed price of wheat, and, secondly, to make a token cut this year as an earnest of that intention, but to make no more than such a token cut.</P>
      <P>I might say, in conclusion, that I intend to abstain from voting on the motion, for the reason that the wording of the motion suggests that we want to stick quite slavishly to this year's price, whereas I regard it as necessary to make a certain cut.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is understood that there is agreement for the Seanad to meet to-morrow at 3 o'clock?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Eamon Ó Ciosáin Eamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Eamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the adjournment of the debate.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 10.5 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Thursday, 16th December.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>