<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="4" Month="Mar" Year="1954" Vol="43" No="7" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 4 Márta 1954" DateEnglish="Thursday, 4 March 1954" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="595">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="595" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take business as on the Order Paper, down to and including item No. 6.  Item No. 7 is not being taken for the same reason that it was not taken the last time.  It was suggested that we might take motion No. 10 and the Clerk of the Seanad is trying to arrange at approximately what time it will be taken.</P>
      <P>It is suggested that if we look like getting finished with the other business at 6 o'clock, we could take the motion which was postponed the last day at 7 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Workmen's Compensation&mdash;Message" RHead="from Dáil">
    <Title>Workmen's Compensation&mdash;Message from Dáil</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has made the following Order:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That a Select Committee consisting of 15 members be appointed to be joined with a Select Committee to be appointed by Seanad Éireann to inquire into the present system of workmen's compensation for injuries due to employment and to consider and report as to what changes are necessary or desirable and, in particular, whether a nationalised scheme of social insurance should be substituted for the existing system, or, if no such change is recommended, whether insurance by employers should be made compulsory;</P>
      <P>That the Committee have power to send for persons, papers and records;</P>
      <P>That the quorum be five;</P>
      <P>That the Committee be nominated by the Committee of Selection.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Workmen's Compensation&mdash;Motion" RHead="to appoint Select Committee">
    <Title>Workmen's Compensation&mdash;Motion to appoint Select Committee.</Title>
    <Col N="596" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That a Select Committee consisting of six members be appointed to be joined with a Select Committee to be appointed by Dáil Éireann to inquire into the present system of workmen's compensation for injuries due to employment and to consider and report as to what changes are necessary or desirable and, in particular, whether a nationalised scheme of social insurance should be substituted for the existing system, or, if no such change is recommended, whether insurance by employers should be made compulsory;</P>
      <P>That the Committee have power to send for persons, papers and records;</P>
      <P>That the quorum be two;</P>
      <P>That the Committee be nominated by the Committee of Selection.</P>
      <P>Motion put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="National Development Fund Bill," RHead="1953&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>National Development Fund Bill, 1953&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 to 3, inclusive, put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 4.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 4 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraigOSiochfhradha" hpid="Pádraig Ó Siocfhradha Pádraig Ó Siocfhradha">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Ó Siocfhradha</NameTxt>
      <P>Molaim an aguisín seo do chur leis:&mdash;</P>
      <P>At the end of the section to add the following words:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Provided that a fixed sum shall be set aside each year to be spent for the benefit of Irish speakers in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht; that the spending of this sum shall be supervised by an administrative unit responsible to the Minister which shall be charged with the duty of preserving and extending the use of the Irish language in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht in addition to improving the economic lot of this the people and which shall have no functions in relation to non-speakers of Irish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="597" /> An lá deireannach nuair do bhí an tAire ag léiriú téarmaí an Bhille seo ba chúis áthais domsa ná raibh dearmad déanta aige ar an gceist thábhachtach seo i dtaobh na Fíor-Ghaeltachta agus go raibh beartaithe aige faoin mBille um Chiste Forbartha Náisiúnta go dtabharfaí £250,000 le haghaidh na Gaeltachta.  Insan alt de na holibreacha sin is ea atá suim agam féin.  Molaim an soláthar atá déanta ag an Aire i gcomhair na gceantar sin. Is mór an t-ábhar dóchais gur chuimhnigh sé féin air gan daoine eile bheith ag brú air.  Molaim an Rialtas mar gheall air.  Maidir leis na hoibreacha atá beartaithe ag an Rialtas faoin gCiste Forbartha Náisiúnta tá ceist nó dhó agam ina thaobh.  Measaim gur luadh £250,000 Níl fhios agam an mbeidh sé i dtaobh leis an £250,000 sin gan aon bhreis a chur ins an gCiste an dara, an treas nó an cheathrú bliain. Níor innis an tAire é sin dúinn.  Is dócha go bhfágfaí gach bliain dó féin agus ná fuil fhios cad a thitfidh amach.  Faoin mBille féin cuirtear £20,000,000 ar fáil.  Le haghaidh na Gaeltachta £250,000 as an £20,000,000 sin agus measain gur beag agus gur ró-bheag é sin.</P>
    <P>Ba mhaith liom daingniú éigin a bheith agam go mbeadh suim éigin sa chiste.  Ní raibh aon léiriú ag an Aire faoi caidé ciall a bhí leis an ainm &ldquo;Gaeltacht.&rdquo;  Ba mhaith liom féin beagán a rá faoin gceist sin.  Níl ionannas coinníoll ná ionannas Gaelachais i ngach cuid den Ghaeltacht fé mar aithnítear anois é.  De ghnáith sambhlaímid dúinn féin trí chinéal Gaeltachta a bheith ann, ag tosnú leis an mbreac-Ghaeltacht mar a bhfuil Gaeilge ag roinnt bheag daoine fásta agus fíor-bheagán ag na daoine óga agus cleachtadh agus conbharsáid Béarla is mó a bhíonn ar siúl acu ionas gur beag leanbh in so' chor a tógtar le Gaeilge.  Tá Gaeltacht eile idir é sin agus an Fhíir-Gaeltacht.  Tugtar an Ghaeltacht air.  Ins an gceantar sin bíonn cuid mhór daoine a bhfuil Gaeilge acu.  Bíionn cuid mhór Gaeilge ag cuid mhór de na daoine agus bíonn tigh fánach thall is i bhfus mar a tógtar leanbh le Gaeilge.  Tugtar an Ghaeltacht air sin agus is cainteoirí Gaelige ó triocha faoin gcéad go dtí bhféidir <Col N="598" /> seachtó nó ochtó faoin gcéad de na daoine.  Ach san gceantar sin tá an Béarla greamaithe go maith sna daoine óga.</P>
    <P>Is é áit ar cóir dúinn an imní is mó a bheith orainn faoi ná an áit a dtugaimid an Fhíor-Ghaeltacht air, áit a bhfuil Gaeilg ag gach duine, áit a dtógtar leanaí le Gaeilg sna tithe, sa bhaile agus ar scoil.  Is í an Fhíor-Ghaeltacht atá i gceist san moladh seo atáimíd a chur ós comhair an Aire agus is air sin atá m'aigne dírithe anios.</P>
    <P>Tá an Fhíor-Ghaeltacht ann fós d'ainneion a bhfuair sí d'fhaillí, d'ainneoin a bhfuair sí de chroch-mheas go rí-mhinic, d'ainneoin Eibhlíse agus Chromaill, d'ainneoin an bhriseadh a tugadh ar lucht na Gaelige lena linn siúd, d'ainneoin na faillí oifigiúla a tugadh inti riamh ó shoin, d'ainneoin an tréigin mhóir a deineadh ins an naoú céad déag nuair do thréig formhór na tíre úsáid na teangan. D'ainneoin na nithe sin tá an Ghaeltacht fós ann, cé gur Gaeltacht bheag chúng atá anois ann tar éis na rudaí a tharla.  Tá an teanga in uachtar go fóill agus tá sí ar an dtinteán sa bhaile agus leanaí á dtógaint inti.  Is inontach an scéal gur mhair aon Ghaeltacht in Éirinn agus is iontaí fós an scéal go bhfuil sí chomh beo, chomh cinnte tugtha do Ghaeilge agus a bhí caoga nó céad bliain ó shoin.</P>
    <P>Is ábhar dóchais dúinn agus is cabhair don náisiún agus do smaoineamh an náisiúnachais in Éirinn go bhfuil an iarsma fós againn chun feidhm do bhaint as, chun bheith maíteach as agus chun úsáid a bhaint aisti, chun an obair a thabhairt chun críche i dtaobh an Ghaeilge a thabhairt thar n-ais.  Mar sin sé mo mholadhsa go gcuirfí cuid de chiste na Gaeltachta ar leith don Fhíor-Ghaeltacht, go gcuirfí airgead i leith an cheantair sin agus go gcaithfí é sin ar fad ar mhaithe le Gaeilge agus lucht labhartha Gaeilge ins an bhFíor-Ghaeltacht.  Nílim á mholadh go ndéanfaí aon éagóir ar an mBreac-Ghaeltacht nó an Ghaeltacht imeallach atá idir an dá shaghas. Gheobhfaidh said sin a gcuid féin ach ba mhaith liom a dhaingniú nach bhfaighdís airgead atá ag teastáil don bhFíor-Ghaeltacht agus go mbronnfaí <Col N="599" /> an t-airgead go cinnte don obair speisialta atá le déanamh sa bhFíor-Ghaeltacht. Obair an-speisialta ar fad atá i gceist agus ní hiononn in aon chor an obair sa bhFíor-Ghaeltacht agus an modh oibre a caithfear a chleachtadh ins na náiteanna sin.</P>
    <P>I suggest to the Minister that of the money provided already he should take part, earmark it for use in the Gaeltacht and in the Gaeltacht only, and see that it is expended for the benefit of Irish speakers and the more firm establishment of the language in the place we for call the Fíor-Ghaeltacht. With a fund like that, many things that have not yet been attempted can be attended to.</P>
    <P>I am concerned with two things in connection with the Fíor-Ghaeltacht; the first is to assist them economically, but before that and above that and receiving greater consideration I wish the fund to be expended in such a manner as will encourage the people to remain in the status of Fíor-Ghaeltacht people, and encourage them to use, as they are doing at present, the Irish language only in connection with all their activities and any new activities that might be provided for under the Bill.</P>
    <P>I want the Fíor-Ghaeltacht to receive public and official recognition and to be dealt with as a special problem, more complex than even the Breac-Ghaeltacht itself.  I want moneys made available by the State to be directed possibly more towards the linguistic advantage of the area than in any other manner.  For that purpose, I suggest the Minister should set up an administrative unit, a committee or board&mdash;call it what you like&mdash;responsible to the Minister himself.  It would be charged with the wise expenditure of this money, or the advice to the given for its wise expenditure, in that very restricted area.</P>
    <P>It is said to have to admit that there is now so restricted an area of Fíor-Ghaeltacht. It consists of ten or 12 parishes only, or parts of parishes. These comprise the Fíor-Ghaeltacht, scattered from Ring to Kerry and from Connemara to Donegal.  That is the area I am concerned about and which I should like the Minister and <Col N="600" /> the Government to be particularly concerned about when they come to apply the funds for the betterment of the people in it and the language they speak.  I am particularly concerned about the expenditure of the money&mdash; it is a considerable amount and it would be disastrous if it were spend to little effect.  In order to ensure its wise expenditure, a body of the kind I mentioned should be set up.  Their function would be to do whatever is given to them by the Minister to deal with, as the Minister is in sole charge and may erect any kind of machinery he wishes.  For a long time we have been looking for such a body to deal with the Fíor-Ghaeltacht.  This is an opportunity to bring it into being.  We have not had as good an opportunity before, when funds could be made available and work laid out for such a body to do.</P>
    <P>I should like that committee or unit to be concerned only with the Fíor-Ghaeltacht and its activities should not be scattered or disintegrated by other duties which verge on that.  The Fíor-Ghaeltacht is so precious a heritage, it is so valuable to the national movement, it is the stamp of our historical nationhood, that I think it deserves at least that this step be taken.  The problem is a very complex one.  It includes the economic welfare of the people of the Fíor-Ghaeltacht, the linguistic character of the purpose we have in mind, cultural instruction and teaching, social and other services. I would like to see a body getting authority to co-ordinate these things in relation to the Irish language and in relation to the beneficial treatment of the people who speak that language.</P>
    <P>I do not intend to refer to the importance of the Gaeltacht.  It is realised by everyone.  We have failed so far to create some body to which the people of the Gaeltacht would look for direct assistance, direct instruction, direct interest, a body which they could take as fathering them and leading them to success and to a more satisfying life in their own area.  That would include many of the things.  I have mentioned.</P>
    <P>There is also need for co-ordination of all the State services in order to aim <Col N="601" /> at a common end and common purpose as well as carrying out their ordinary functions.  These are many.  In the Gaeltacht, like the rest of the country, you have the State services in full operation all the time.  Possibly the most active one is the Department of Education.  In passing, I should like to pay a compliment to those working under the Department of Education for their work in the Gaeltacht schools. They are doing the thing we want done and we wish them success.  You have the social services, old age pensions, unemployment insurance, national health benefits&mdash;for all of which there are very active units in every Gaeltacht in the country.</P>
    <P>Under the Department of Justice we have the policy, the courts, the issue of licences and permits, and so on.  We have the customs and excise people. We have transport, buses, goods deliveries and the rest.  We have the Post Office.  We have possibly the greatest of the whole lot, the activities of the local public bodies and councils.</P>
    <P>One of our principal grievances in the national movement for a long time has been that there is no evidence of co-ordinated purpose among all these. Each works on its own for the carrying out of its own duties, irrespective very often of questions of language or the effect on the practice of the Irish language in these areas.  I should like a body to be set up that would be permitted to take part in certain phases of the work of these Departments. I should like if there was a common purpose in regard to Irish in all the Departments and that advice and instruction would be available to the Departments and their officers from time to time as to particular circumstances in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht.</P>
    <P>If the Government set up the body that I speak of, I should like that they should be endowed with the right of interview with those people and of instruction and that the whole machine of the State, plus the machinery that would be set up under this Bill, would be directed to the betterment of the status of Irish in these areas and that there would not be stultifying carelessness or want of thought on the part of one Department to the detriment of the greater use of the Irish <Col N="602" /> language and more determined propaganda in regard to the Irish language.</P>
    <P>These are the matters on which I should like the Minister to cogitate. After hearing us, he might be inclined to make some arrangement whereby that body could be brought into being. That is my proposal.</P>
    <P>Go gcuirfí airgead cinnte i leith na Fíor-Ghaeltachta, cuid den airgead atá ag dul dóibh ó cheart, faoin mBille seo; go mbeach dream éigin le chomhairle agus le eolas do thabhairt don Aire mar is é a bheas i gceannas an ruda ar fad; go mbeadh an cineál sin coiste nó bord riaracháin ann agus go mbeadh, ina theannta sin, liaison éigin idir iad sin agus na seirbhísí poiblí eile ar fad. Tá riachtanas leis sin.  Tá gach duine againn a bhfuil staidéir déanta aige ar an nGaeltacht ar an tuairim gur gá na nithe seo.  Anois, ó tá an t-airgead seo á chus ar fáil agus coiste á bhunú, tá súil agam go dtiocfaidh as sin institiud nó coiste nó dream éigin a thógfaidh cúram na Fíor-Ghaeltachta orthu féin agus a bheadh ullamh chun chomhairle agus eolas do fhreastal don Aire.  Molaimse go gcuirfimis an aguisín seo le alt a 4.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOgMcFadden" hpid="Mícheál Óg Mac Pháidín Mícheál Óg Mac Pháidín">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál Óg Mac Pháidín</NameTxt>
      <P>Is maith liom beagán a rá ar an mholadh seo atá anois roimh an tSeanaid.  Tá a fhios againn ón Aire cheana féin go bhfuil sé socraithe ag an Rialtas ceathrú milliún punt a chur i leataoibh as an Bhille seo d'fhorbairt na Gaeltachta.</P>
      <P>Mall agus eile mar tá an tarrtháil seo, fá fáilte agam roimhe agus bheirim mo bheannacht dó.  Ach is é an eagla atá orm féin go bhfuilimid lán-mhall anois leis an chuidiú seo; tá sé mar bheimis ag cur glas ar an chomhra nuair atá an seod imithe agus an chreach déanta.  Deir an sean-fhocal &ldquo;Nach dtuigeann an sáthach an seang&rdquo; agus má thuigeann nach i n-am.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Níl amhras ar bith nach dearnadh neamhairt agus faillí sa Ghaeltacht ó cuireadh an Stáit seo ar bun.  Is náireach an scéal é don ghlúin seo agus beidh coigchís trom orthu ag an staraí a thiocfas ina ndiaidh.  Ní rabhamid ach ag úthairt agus ag útamáil le scéimeanna beaga gan tairbhe sa Ghaeltacht, ranganna fíod. <Col N="603" /> óireachta agus cniotála a bhí ar bun cheana féin ag sean-Bhord na gCeanntar gCung.  Leanamuid lorg Seáin Bhuidhe d'fhéach le muintir na Gaeltachta a choinneáil modhamhail sásta le hoibreacha fóirthine mar chineal déirce.  Níor leor sin ar ndóigh.</P>
    <P>Bhí muintir na tíre seo ag dréim go mbeadh saol níos fearr ag an Ghaeltacht faoi Rialtas Gael ach bhí siad meallta go mór.  Anois le fiche bliain chonaicimid an Ghaeltacht ag imeacht agus ag críonadh roimh ár súile. Chonaicimid í ag cúladh siar go himeall chladaigh an iarthair, go dtí nach bhfuil fágtha anois ann ach an cumhanglach beag deireannach de fhírthreibh Gael.  Chonaicimid aos óg na Gaeltachta ag tógáil a n-eiteog mar na Géanna Fiáine agus ag imeacht uainn thar sáile.  Ach níor bhacmuid leo thar tionscail beag a chur ar bun thall is abhus sa Ghaeltacht, obair nár riar do dheichniúr as an chéad.  Nuair a bhí monarchain mhóra á gcur ar bun i mBaile Átha Cliath agus i gCorcaigh, i Luimneach agus i geathracha eile, ní raibh mórán iomrá ar an Ghaeltacht.  Fágadh muintir na Gaeltachta lom folamh ar &ldquo;shop an t-séite&rdquo; i muinín oibreacha fóirthine ar na bealaigh móra nó ag triomú na gcurrach.  Ní raibh obair sheasmhach ag an fhear óg ní an cailín óg a bhí ar intinn pósadh sa Ghaeltacht agus clann a thógáil ann.  Sin bun agus barr agus lár an scéil.  B'éigin don lánúin óg sin a n-aghaidh a thabhairt ar an choigríoch agus is iomadh lánúin mar iad d'imigh uainn agus nár phill ó shoin.  Chuir an t-ocras agus ditheamhail oibre an tóir orthu ón Ghaeltacht agus leis an leatrom a d'fhulaing siad ina gcuimhne.  Is fíor-bheagáin a philleas arís ar an mbaile dhúchais.</P>
    <P>Bhí an Ghaeltacht ariamh bocht agus ní raibh an cúltaca poilitíochta féin aici mar bhí ag an chuid eile den tír le intinn an phobail a choinneáil dírithe ar an droch-chaoi a bhí uirthi. Mheas siad féin gur den bhoichteanacht an Ghaeltacht agus nach raibh modh ná meas orthu nuair nach raibh an Béarla acu.  Chonaic siad lucht an Bhéarla i bpostanna céimiúla fríd an tír.  An dochtúir, an fear gnaithe, an fear dlí: tóiceannaí na tíre ag labhairt <Col N="604" /> an Bhéarla agus dímheas acu ar theanga a sinsir.  Chonaic siad an Dáil agus an Seanad ag cíoradh gnaithe na tíire i mBéarla na nGall.  Thugmuid cúl do chomhairle an Phiarsaigh i dtaca le náisiun Gaelach.  Ní thug an chuid eile den tír an sompla ceart, an treoir agus an teagase, do mhuintir na Gaeltachta sa chruth go mbeadh meas agus grá acu ar theangaidh agus tréithe ár sinsir.  Ní thugmuid an tslí bheatha dhóibh ba chóir dóibh a fháil má bhímid dáiriribh fan taisce luachmhar náisiúnta a choinnigh muintir na Gaeltachta dúinn fríd anró agus géarleanúint na gcéadta bliain.  Ní bhfuair siad an buíochas ná an t-ómós a bhí tuillte acu.</P>
    <P>Fuair siad moladh agus béal bán go leór ár ndóigh ach ní chuireann sin bia ná deoch ar an tábla don mhuirín bhocht sa Ghaeltacht atá beo ar an ghann-chuid ag strachailt leis an tsaol ó cheann go ceann na bliana.</P>
    <P>Is maith liom go bhfuil suim fiúntach airgid as Bhille seo don Ghaeltacht agus tá súil agam go gcaithfear é go tairbheach ar oibreacha oiriúnacha a bhéaras slí bheatha seasmhach do na daoine bochta seo.  Déanfaidh sé maith don fhuílleach beag Gael atá fágtha agus a sheas an fód go dtí seo. Níor chóir go gcaithfí an t-airgead seo ag crúthú postannaí úrá do dhaoine ar thuarastail mhóra le dul i gcionn sin go hoibre seo.  Bheinn in aghaidh sin go láidir nó slugfaí an chuid is mó den airgead seo i gcostas riaracháin.</P>
    <P>Is feasach dom go bhfuil fir mhaithe san Stát-Sheirbhís agus i Seirbhísí na Gaeltachta, fir atá oilte go maith agus a bhfuil a gcroí san obair seo agus atá eolach ar shaol mhuintir na Gaeltachta. Go dtí seo féin, bhí siad creapaillte de dhítheamhail airgid agus ní thiocfadh leo a dhul 'un chinn mar ba mhian leo.  Measaim go mbeadh sé mar chúram ar na fir seo mar Fho-Roinn den Rialtas forbairt na Gaeltachta a chur 'un chinn agus a stiúradh.  Tá súil agam nach mbeidh an Roinn Airgid cumhang nó ceachardha leo.  Beimid uilig ag dréim go gcuirfidh siad snas agus bláith agus feabhas ar shaol na Gaeltachta ach go h-áithrid ar shaol geilleagrach na ndaoine.  Beimid ag dréim fosta go dtabharfaidh siad aire speisialta do <Col N="605" /> shaol cultúrdha na Gaeltachta agus do shean-sibhialtacht na nGael a mhair ariamh anall i measc mhuintir na Gaeltachta go dtí an lá inniu féin.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Is maith liom go móor cuidiú leis an moladh seo atá os comhair an Tí innin ar son na Gaeltachta mar is í ceist na Gaeltachta an cheist náisiúnta is mó atá le réiteach againn sna blianta atá le réiteach. Tá mór-dhóchas agam go dtiocfaidh maitheas as an díospóireacht seo nuair a chím go bhfuil daoine ag cur spéise sa cheist seo ar gach taobh den Tigh. Ach ní hé iné ná inniu a thuit sé sin amach agus admhaím, fé mar admhaigh an Seabhac, go bhfuil mórán déanta cheanna féin ar son na Gaeltachta, ach b'fhéidir nach bhfuil an oiread san déanta agus ba mhaith linn a bheith.</P>
      <P>Nuair a chualas ar dtús go raibh an sórt seo de mholadh le cur síos níróchinnte a bhíos i dtaobh conas cur chun na hoibre seo i gceart.  Do cheapas ar dtús go mb'fhéidir náir chóir ceist na Gaeltachta nó na Fíor-Ghaeltachta a bheith fite fuaite leis an rud atá insan ceist atá sa mBille, sé sin Bille Forbarta Náisiúnta a chur ar bun anseo ar son an Náisiúin uile agus go mb'fhéidir go mba chóir ciste ar leith, lasmuigh den chiste seo, a chur ar bun do'n bhFíor-Ghaeltacht. Acht is dócha a nach mbeadh mórán difríochta ann sa deireadh thiar thall.</P>
      <P>Tá fhios agam go maith, ó thaithí, go bhfuil an Rialtas seo i bhfábhar ceist na Gaeltachta do réiteach chomh mór le haon duine eile anseo.  Ach nuair a aontaím le cainteoirí eile&mdash;agus go háirithe leis an Senabhacgo mba chóir suim áirithe airgid a chaitheamh insan nGaeltacht, deirim nach leor é sin a rá agus go mba chóir dhúinn suí síos agus machtnamh a dhéanamh ar conas mar ba cheart dúinn an t-airgead a chaitheamh.  Do b'fhéidir linn milliún punt sa bhliain do chur ar leataoibh le haghaidh na Gaeltachta&mdash;ach níor leor é sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Ní mór dúinn déantúisí oiriúnacha do chur ar bun ann agus muna ndéanfaimíd é sin is beag maitheas dúinn a bheith ag caint faoi chúrsaí airgeadais. Tá fhios agam go bhfuilim ag insint na fírinne nuair adeirim nach <Col N="606" /> cúrsaí airgeadais atá sa tslí maidir le réiteach na Gaeltachta ach scéim mhaith, chiallmhar sheasmhach a thiubharfadh obair lán-aimsearach do mhuintir na Fíor-Ghaeltachta, a choimeádfadh ag baile iad, agus a thiubharfadh dóchas agus misneach dóibh san am atá le teacht.</P>
    <P>Nuair a dheinimíd tagairt do aonad anseo, aonad a bheadh freagarthach don Aire agus don Rialtas i dtaobh conas a caithfí an t-airgead san bhFíor-Ghaeltacht, ní ró-léir ar fad atáim féin faoi cén sórt aonaid ba chóir dúinn a chur ar bun.  An machtnamh dom ar an scéal, b'fhéidir nárbh b'olc an cuimhneamh é feidhm do bhaint as comhairlí paróistí.  Dá mb'fhéidir linn comhairle pharóste a chur ar bun i ngach cuid den bhfíor-Ghaeltacht ar dtús sé mo thuairim gur céim mhór ar aghaidh a bheadh ann. Nuair adeirim go mba chóir comhairle pharóiste a chur ar buningach cuid den Ghaeltacht sé tá in aigne agam ná go mb'fhéidir nach iad na fadhbanna céadna a bheadh le réiteach, mar shampla, i gCiarraighe is a bheadh i nDún na nGall, agus mar sin de.</P>
    <P>Ach sin rud gur féidir machtnamh a dhéanamh air fós nuair tá fhios againn cheana&mdash;lesmuigh den Moladh seo ar fad&mdash;go bhfuil an Rialtas toilteannach cabhair airgid a thabhairt, uatha chun ceist seo na Fíor-Ghaeltachta do réiteach, más féidir é a réiteach in aon chor&mdash;agus má chuirimíd le chéile chun a dhéanta is dóigh liom go dtiocfaidh linn beart d'réir ár mbriathar a dhéanamh.</P>
    <P>B'fhéidir go bhfuil aonad againn cheana i seirbhísí na Gaeltachta.  Tá Seirbhísí na Gaeltachta anseo cheana le cuid mhaith blianta agus tá mórán déanta acu chun cuidiú le tionscailiú na Gaeltachta.  Óm thaithí-se ar na Seirbhísí sin tá fhios agam go bhfuil iarrachtaí na seirbhísí sin ag dul i méid agus i dtreise ó bhliain go bliain.</P>
    <P>Bhí mé ag cuimhneamh leis, nuair adúirt an Senabhac go bhfuil baint ag beagnach gach Roinn den Rialtais le ceist seo na Gaeltachta gurab é sin díreach an cúram atá ar an aonad, seirbhísí na Gaeltachta, agus tuigtear dom anois go bhfuiltear ag dul ar aghaidh níos dúrachtaí agus í níos <Col N="607" /> dícheallaí anois leis an obair agus gurab é cúram Rúnaí Pharlaiminte don Rialtas aire do thabhairt do seirbhísí na Gaeltachta agus féachaint chuige chun tionscail oiriúnacha do chur ar bun insan Fíor-Ghaeltacht agus san mBreac-Ghaeltacht chomh maith.</P>
    <P>Mar a dúirt na cainnteoirí eile, limistéar ana bheag is ea an Fhíor-Ghaeltacht anois agus sí an cheist í cad is Fíor-Ghaeltacht in aonchura ann, mar an limistéar atá in a Fhíor-Ghaeltacht anois nímar sin a bhí sé nuair cuireadh Comisiúin na Gaeltachta ar bun 28 bliana ó shoin, is dóigh liom.  Tá an Fhíor-Ghaeltacht ag dul i laghadh ó shoin agus is mór an trua é, ach ní fheadar cé go bhfuilmíd go léir annseo duthrachtach agus anduthrachtach sa rud seo, agus go mbeimís toilteannach ár ndícheall a dhéanamh chun deire a chur le meath na Fíor-Ghaeltachta atá ar siúl, tá an cheist ann an eireoidh linn an beart a dhéanamh gan cabhair mhór d'fháil ó mhuinntir na Gaeltachta féin leis.  Is mar gheall ar sin gur dóigh liom gur cheart comhairle pharóiste a chur ar bun ins gach áit&mdash;comhairle a bheadh ar chomh-chomhairle de Seirbhísí na Gaeltachta&mdash;agus mas féidir tionscail oiriínacha do chur ar bun ins na háiteanna san chun na daoine a choimeád sa bhaile is mór mar raghaidh sé chun tairbhe na tíre seo.</P>
    <P>Mar a dúirt Seanadóirí eile, is oidhreacht luachmhar an Fhíor-Ghaeltacht agus an Ghaeltacht agus mar gheall ar sin, níor cheart dúinn sinn féin a spáráil chun teacht i gcabhair ar na daoine atá in a gcónaí ins na háiteanna san agus bfhéidir nuair a bheadh rud déanta againn ansan chun cúrasa eacnamúil na Fíor-Ghaeltachta do chur chun críche, go bhféadfaimís ansan ár n-aire do dhíriú ar an mBreac-Ghaeltacht, mar is dóigh liom gur rud tábhachtach é sin leis.</P>
    <P>I am very glad that this recommendation has been tabled in connection with this Bill.  At first I was more or less inclined to think that it might be better to approach the question of the Fíor-Ghaeltacht on an entirely independent basis, on a basis independent altogether of the considerations that would arise in connection with the Bill <Col N="608" /> in its general form, but, so far as the money question is concerned, it is entirely a matter of providing the funds which would be sufficient to alleviate the bad economic conditions that obtain in that part of the country known as the Fíor-Ghaeltacht.</P>
    <P>While the vast majority of us may be quite willing to lend our support to the expenditure of money in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht, we must consider also the practicability of whatever measures we may take to improve conditions in the Gaeltacht, because it is not sufficient for us to say here or elsewhere that we should put such a sum aside for the betterment of the conditions in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht.  We must also think our a constructive plan for the econoomic rehabilitation of the people in the Gaeltacht.  One could spend £1,000,000 or £2,000,000, and throw it away in the Gaeltacht, without bringing any tangible results, and indeed I am aware of a few times when money spent in the Gaeltacht did not bring the results we anticipated and it is because of that that I think a long term practical plan is necessary as well as the expenditure of money.</P>
    <P>I am sure the vast majority of us here would be willing to give our support to practical proposals for the Fíor-Ghaeltacht, or, for that matter, for the Breac-Ghaeltacht, and I know very well that the members of the Government are only too anxious to come to the assistance of the Fíor-Ghaeltacht for the improvement of the economic conditions there and the advancement of the Irish language, if the way can be found by which it can be done with beneficial results.  The Government organisation knowns as Seirbhísí na Gaeltachta was set up some years ago&mdash;its activities have been growing from year to year&mdash;for the purpose of paying attention to the problems of the Gaeltacht, and, in the matter of the co-ordination of whatever plans would be prepared for the solution of the Gaeltacht problems, the Parliamentary Secretary in charge of Seirbhísí na Gaeltachta is in a better position than anybody to organise the necessary contacts with the various Departments of State for the sake of the Gaeltacht.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="609" /> Nearly all the Departments of State are concerned in this and a lot of good work has already been done, especially, as Senator Ó Siocfhradha has said, by the Department of Education and, indeed, I do not agree with anybody who says that we have neglected the Gaeltacht.</P>
    <P>I do not think it is right for me to detail the things that we did for the Gaeltacht, but under the aegis of the Department of Education things have been done for the people of the Gaeltacht over and above what the people of the country generally are entitled to.  One example, of course, is the £5 grant under the Department of Education for Irish-speaking children.  As far as I know that is not confined to the Fíor-Ghaeltacht.  It also extends to the Breac-Ghaeltacht.  I do not know whether it is advisable to draw a distinction at this stage between what might be termed the Gaeltacht and the Breac-Ghaeltacht.  I think it would be nearly as well to let the term &ldquo;Breac-Ghaeltacht&rdquo; cover the areas adjacent to the Fíor-Ghaeltacht where Irish is still spoken but not exclusively.</P>
    <P>Mar focal scoir, tá áthas orm go ghfuil an ocáid seo againn chun ceist mhór thábhachach na Gaeltachta do chur ós cóir an phobail arís mar gurb í sin díreach an cheist is mó atá le réiteach againn, fé mar adubhairt mé i dtosach mo chuid cainte, ins na blianta rómhainn amach.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I find this a peculiarly depressing discussion.  I listened to the speech of the mover of the amendment which has, by the way, a rather peculiar history.  He made no proposal.  He spoke about administrative units but he made no contribution of any kind as to what he meant by an administrative unit, not, indeed, did the Senator who has just sat down.  Senator Mac Pháidín thought that civil servants should be used and, perhaps, there is a great deal to be said for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is just over 60 years since the Gaelic League was founded in 1893 and it is more than 30 years since an Irish State was founded and yet we have a discussion here to-day on the weakness <Col N="610" /> of the Irish language in its own areas &mdash;a discussion which is completely barren with regard to any definite suggestion to the Minister or the House as to what should be done.  There is a peculiar form of self-deception among people that if they succeed in getting a great many people to put their names to a motion they have accomplished something.  That, of course, is not so.</P>
    <P>This particular amendment was put down in the form of a motion in the names of certain people, including An Seabhac.  I was asked if I would put my name to it and I refused because I said it was out of order.  It was anticipating a discussion on the Bill which we are just discussion now.  I suggested that it should be put it down, if they wanted to put it down at all, as an amendment to the Bill because it is not a proposal to increase the charge upon the people but a proposal to spend part of the money the Minister is looking for in a particular way.</P>
    <P>Peculiarly enough, that proposal was adopted but not acknowledged, although last week, when the Bill had reached its Second Stages and when the Second Stage had been carried, but for the efforts of Senator Douglas on this side of the House the Committee Stage would then have been taken and this amendment could not have been moved at all.  Senator Douglas&mdash;I was presiding at a Joint Library Committee&mdash; fought very hard to have the Bill postponed a week.  Nobody said a word in support of the idea that the Bill should be postponed for a week.  Neither Senators Ó Siocfhradha, Kissane or anybody else on the Government side of the House urged the Minister to give them an opportunity of moving their own amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraigOSiochfhradha" hpid="Pádraig Ó Siocfhradha Pádraig Ó Siocfhradha">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Ó Siocfhradha</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Senator is quite right.  I did.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not in the book.  There is nothing in the book about it.  The only person who urged that was Senator Douglas, who was endeavouring to preserve for An Seabhac rights which apparently he has not the courage to endeavour to preserve for himself.  The amendment is one which asks for a certain sum of money to be set aside for certain purposes. <Col N="611" /> I would agree entirely with the last Senator who, I think, said that it was not entirely a question of money. Perhaps, I would be allowed to say this.  It is now over 60 years since the Gaelic League was founded, and the only success of a major nature achieved as far as the Irish language is concerned surely was to make it an object of State policy, to put the revival of the Irish language into what you might call the canon of Irish nationalism.  On the establishment of an Irish State the Irish language got into the schools and became essential for posts in the public service, but in regard to the all-important matter of preserving the living Irish language as a natural language, of preserving the areas in which Irish would be a naturally spoken language, continuing the tradition of at least 2,000 years, there has been, I am afraid, complete failure.</P>
      <P>In the Gaeltacht the difference is that Irish is spoken not as it was spoken here to-day as a demonstration, and not for a national object, but because it comes easiest to the speakers.  It is their vernacular, the normal means of intercourse, and it comes natural.  The case for this amendment, if a case has got to be made for it at all, is that that kind of Irish, preserved by people whose natural language it is, is the well and spring from which all other kinds of Irish must derive.  If that well dries up, then in the words of a great Irish scholar &ldquo;the rest is silence&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>When that ever happens, if it does happen, no money, no Acts of the Oireachtas, no political speeches in Irish or English, no books, nothing can avail to accomplish the objects that so many people have at heart and for which so many people made such sacrifices. When that happens, we shall have lost a link with our past which is all-important.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I support the substance of this amendment on the ground that we should endeavour to preserve the Irish language in the Gaeltacht, not because of its antiquity, beauty or flexibility, but simply because it is Irish.  For historical reasons the language is spoken on remote areas, often in bad or barren <Col N="612" /> lands or on uneconomic holdings.  I should like to put it to the Minister that apart altogether from the Irish language the State has an obligation towards citizens in those parts of the country to make a living possible for them or to take them out of it.</P>
    <P>The Gaeltacht has a special claim for the reasons I have stated.  Taking the people out of the Gaeltacht by wholesale migration is not, I think, a remedy. It would have the inevitable effect of making the next generation English and not Irish speakers.  But nobody has suggested what can be done. Before we could offer any opinion, we ought to discuss what the problem is. I am sure the Minister and people like him are familiar with the problem he has to face.  The problem is how can we preserve Irish-speaking communities in their present situation.  We must provide the young people with a living which will not induce them to forget, despise or abandon Irish.  That is a very great difficulty.  The problem cannot be considered purely on an economic basis.  It cannot be considered, as I think Senator Ó Cíosáin said, on the basis of what particular tangible, visible value you get for money.  If you accept the thesis about Irish which we all have accepted, you must necessarily accept the notion that these areas must be preserved.</P>
    <P>They have decayed very steadily since just before the Famine.  I suppose Senators are aware that in the 18th century the population of Ireland was more than quardrupled&mdash;of course, largely the rural population and so almost entirely the Irish-speaking population.  In the year that Thomas Davis died, 1845, there were 8,500,000 people in the Ireland of whom at least 3,500,000, probably considerably more, were normally Irish speakers.  The Famine changed all that.  It is interesting when we as an Irish Parliament consider that as late as 1881, when Parnell was agitating for Home Rule, there were more than 1,000,000 Irish speakers in Ireland.  The census gave the figure as very nearly 1,000,000 and the census presentation of the position was probably an understatement.</P>
    <P>There has been decay ever since then and the wide, homogeneous <Col N="613" /> linguistic areas of Irish speakers have been disappearing.  Decay has continued since 1893 since the Gaelic League was founded and has continued over the last 30 or more years under Irish government.  It may have slackened the pace of the decay but it certainly did not stop it.  The present Government has been nearly 20 years in office and there can be no doubt that in spite of any profession of interest in Irish they have not succeeded in accomplishing anything in this particular line. When I say that I would like to add that it is a very difficult problem and it is by no means entirely an economic one.  It does not matter very much in the beginning what sum is set aside. The mover of the motion wanted to know what sum would be set aside after the first year.  I think the Minister's answer&mdash;and a very sound answer &mdash;would be that a certain sum would be set aside in the first years and, according to the results achieved, the same amount or more would be provided later on.</P>
    <P>There are many things against Irish apart altogether from economics&mdash; fashion, all the modern trends, all the new equipment, radio, screen, television, aeroplanes; they all enter in. There is also the immense additional strength of English from the rise of the United States of America, to which we are now so near and to which, incidentally, the Gaeltacht is nearer than any of us.  However, in this Bill we must confine ourselves to the economic consideration.  On that I agree that, if it were possible, there ought to be unified direction.  The reason there ought to be unified direction is that the problem is to get a combination of hard-headed business people who know what will do good in the economic sense, to get as well competent administrators and at the same time to have people who will endeavour to preserve and will succeed in preserving the national and the spiritual values which we associate with the Irish language, which make this amendment important, and which would impel any proposal of any kind to provide particular sums of money in these particular areas.  You need a combination of different kinds of <Col N="614" /> people for these rather different ends and sometimes the two interests conflict one with another, the economic and the linguistic or spiritual.</P>
    <P>I feel that the only unity you can achieve is unity under a particular officer of a particular Minister assisted by the appointment from outside the Civil Service of an advisory committee. There is a very genuine difficulty in allowing somebody who is not a civil servant and who is not directly responsible to a Minister, firstly, to spend public money and, secondly, to interfere in more than one Department. The Department of Education has been mentioned and has been praised but the Department of Education would certainly not be enthusiastic&mdash; the Department of Education, I think it may be said, are not enthusiastic about the Department of Finance but that is natural&mdash;about a position in which somebody outside themselves could direct them as well as directing officers of Industry and Commerce and also directing officers of the Department of Agriculture.</P>
    <P>Under the last Government there was a suggestion made about a particular area.  Deputy Dillon, who was Minister for Agriculture, submitted a memorandum to the Government suggesting that as regards Connemara a particular scheme should be put into operation, and that a great many suggestions should be investigated.  It was also suggested that the money should be found from the land project moneys and that the direction should be under Irish-speaking officers of his own Department.  That would give you an experiment in the part of the Gaeltacht which is to-day the most important of all, Connemara.  My friend, Senator Mac Pháidín, might protest at that but Connemara has the advantage over Donegal of being a homogeneous whole&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>It has no advantage over Donegal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;whereas Donegal is unfortunately divided into two parts, so that you could work best in Connemara if you started there.  The suggestion was to take that area in Connemara because it has the most <Col N="615" /> concentrated number of Irish speakers and is closely knit.  It is not the most numerous by counting heads, but, as I say, Donegal is split into two parts.</P>
      <P>It may be worth while to see what that particular plan was and how far it had got.  It had got so far in 1950 that a particular officer had been appointed and had taken up headquarters in Galway, that various people had been communicated with including some very eminent scientists, some people in University College, Galway, who had always been interested in scientific problems connected with the development of the Gaeltacht and certain English experts who were investigating mineral resources.  In any event, by the end of 1950 the memorandum was written by the then Minister for Agriculture for the Government and his proposal was this.  He pointed out that the principle would have to be accepted that in certain areas like Connemara people would have to be provided with the means of making a living for themselves.  His own words were:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;If this principle is accepted, when the Government finds itself confronted with an area such as Connemara, they must accept the fact that there is an obligation upon them either to evacuate the population to some other area where hard work will produce an income, or create in Connemara conditions which will permit of those families who reside there to earn their living by hard work.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That is the core of the problem which this amendment sets out to meet.  He continues:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;If we accept the view that evacuation of and the population is not a practicable solution of the social problem here envisaged, we must acknowledge the duty to do all that can be done to create the necessary conditions whereunder the residents of the area can earn their own living.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That has been dealt with up to the present by methods of relief, by spasmodic schemes.  The Minister at that particular moment was not <Col N="616" /> optimistic&mdash;and perhaps that is the best mood in which to approach this. He continued:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;To repair the damage done to the morale of the people in Connemara by 15 years of such a policy is a formidable undertaking, and I cannot represent to the Government that there is more than a 30 per cent. chance of success. Nevertheless, so long as there is this slender hope, I feel certain that it is the duty of the Government to make their best endeavour to restore the earning capacity and morale of the Connemara people.  To that end, therefore, I have a programme to recommend which is of an exhaustive nature and will involve the collaboration of several Departments of State and the effective co-ordination of these several activities.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I think that is what the amendment asks for.  He continues:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The great danger in an undertaking of this kind is that one may be tempted to undertake the work piecemeal, with the inevitable consequence that the whole and project will peter out in futility, and it is for this reason&mdash;&rdquo;</P>
    <P>and this meets exactly the point of the amendment&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;that I recommend to the Government that all the necessary measures should be simultaneously undertaken under the direction of a competent and experienced administrator, authorised to call on every Department of State for its assistance within the scope of the plan laid down, and having at his disposal finance on the lines laid down in Section 35 of the Purchase of Land (Ireland) Act, 1891.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this memorand available to the members of the House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I have think it could be put in the Library.  I would be prepared to do that.  I do not think it is a confidential document.  It that what the Cathaoirleach would like done?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="617" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The memorandum continues:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;I, therefore, ask approval for the appointment of an administrator and deputy and administrator for a Connemara development board (the names of these two officers I shall submit verbally to the Government) and suggest that the administrator will be of the rank of an agricultural inspector of this Department (Agriculture) and his deputy of the rank of an assistant principal officer.</P>
      <P>It is intended that one or both of these officers shall be at least the equivalent of a native speaker of the Irish language.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Added to that, the Minister intended to have a board of not less than five nor more than nine persons, acting in an honorary capacity and comprising people interested in the language and skilled in the particular problems which present themselves in those areas.  Now, the Minister was told on that occasion to go ahead with the money at his own disposal and see what could be done about it.  He made a number of suggestions and explored a number of possibilities and interested a number of people who were undoubted authorities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think that was a practical method of beginning.  If you begin in one particular place, other places will at once say they need immediate attention.  I know the problem is urgent, but if one succeeded in Connemara one could make an effort then in Donegal, and in Mayo, where there is a small area with some Irish left.  One could also start west of Dingle&mdash;a place in which Deputy Dillon as Minister was also very interested.  It is not possible to find a sound solution without appointing some group of people to give their special attention to it from day to day, and without appointing an officer or officers whose duty it would be to report upon it.  I am sure the Minister has some experience of the difficulties. The kernel of the problem is how to bring about and economic development without doing injury to the Irish language as a living tongue.  Economic and industrial development is a modern thing, and the Irish language <Col N="618" /> is not in that sense a modern thing at all and the two things do not seem to come together.  The scheme that was adumbrated then by the Minister for Agriculture, Deputy Dillon, involved fishing, as follows.  The Sea Fisheries Association would operate three large boats with Scottish skippers and crews 50 per cent.  Scottish and 50 per cent. Connemara, to train Irish skippers and maximise fish landings at Cashla. It involved special attention to the area by the veterinary staff of the Department, the improvement of sheep and the bringing in of Kerry cattle. All of these plans are necessarily open to argument.</P>
    <P>There is in that an excellent idea, that there should be a development board of not less than five nor more than nine, all honorary, to advise and to be subject to the Minister.  The Minister for Agriculture is a better person than the Minister for Finance &mdash;I do not mean personally, of course&mdash; as the Department of Agriculture is a better Department than the Department of Finance of the Department of Education for this purpose.  The scope of the Department of Education is necessarily narrow.  You need interested people, people experienced in the congested areas and people who also have an interest in the Irish language. All that needs money.  I hold that the need for money is less than the need for expert knowledge, for intelligence and enthusiasm and for direction which is sympathetic and which while in favour of the Irish language is not foolish from the point of view of spending money to no purpose.</P>
    <P>Considerable assistance might be given, for example, in certain areas in the equipment of and houses to receive visitors.  Again if&mdash;as is true, of course &mdash;certain members of families must leave the Gaeltacht, it seems to me they could be equipped to make a better living than they make as unskilled workers when they do leave it.</P>
    <P>The real difficulty in the amendment and in dealing with this problem of the Gaeltacht is the trend of world events.  When the Department of Education made certain proposals&mdash;in 1922, I think&mdash;with regard to schools, someone wrote a leading article in the <Col N="619" /> Gaelic League paper at the time, <i>Fáinne an Lac,</i> saying: &ldquo;Tá gach rud ar ár dtaobh anois; níl in ár gcoinne ach an saol,&rdquo; meaning, &ldquo;everything is in our favour and nothing is against us but the world&rdquo;&mdash;the trend of events and the general trend of fashions and new developments.  Since the Gaelie League was founded and even since the State was founded 30 years ago, the world has become considerably smaller and the difficulties of a weak language have become considerably greater.</P>
    <P>To put this amendment into operation&mdash;not necessarily in its present form, but in any form&mdash;requires a combination of very different kinds of people, working towards two objects&mdash; economic development and cultural development&mdash;which it is not always easy to reconcile.  I agree that an effort should be made in that direction and should be made soon and should get a chance.  I would be satisfied with even partial success.  I feel that nothing can be accomplished for the Irish language in any sphere if the place where it is spoken as an ordinary national language is allowed to decay &mdash;and that is happening.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraigAghas" hpid="Pádraig Ághas Pádraig Ághas">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Ághas</NameTxt>
      <P>Is mian liom labhairt i bhfábhar an aguisín atá molta anso.  Is áthas liom caoi d'fháil ar sin a dhéanamh mar and is dóigh liom go bhfuil an t-am tagtha ina gcaithfimíd cúnamh cinnte a thabhairt don bhFíor-Ghaeltacht más mian linn í choimeád beo.</P>
      <P>Bhí súil againn, nuair a bhí Bille eile cosúil leis seo ós ár gcomhair, go ndéanfaí éacht ar son na Gaeltachta; ach ní mór a deineadh, don bhfíor-Ghaeltacht go háirithe.  Bhí díomá orainn, ach is féidir an scéal a leigheas anois; agus leigheasfar é, im thuairimse, má cuirtear ar bun an rannóg mar atá molta anso chun an Fhíor-Ghaeltacht a chaomhnadh agus a chosaint.</P>
      <P>Anois, is doigh liom gur gá iarracht éigin speisialta a dhéanamh chun an Fíor-Ghaeltacht do chaomhnú agus do chosaint.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>'Sí an Fhíor-Ghaeltacht tobar na Gaeilge.  Is ar an Fhíor-Ghaeltacht a thugaimid aghaidh nuair is mian linn feabhas a chur ar ár gcuid Gaeilge <Col N="620" /> agus má théann an tobar sin i ndísc, crapfar an teanga Gaeilge.  Ní bheidh an saidhbhreas ins an teanga.  Is dóigh liom féin gur mór is fiú dhúinn an Fhíor-Ghaeltacht a chosaint agus a choimeád beo.  Caithfidh gach éinne sin d'admháil, mar is cuspóir linne Éire Gaelach a bheith againn.  Is deacair an cuspóir sin a bhaint amach má cailltear an Fhíor-Ghaeltacht.</P>
    <P>Anois tá a lán daoine a rá go bhfuil an iomaraca peataíreachta á dhéanamh ar an nGaeltacht.  Ní dóigh liom féin gur fíor é sin.  Tá muintir na Gaeltachta ag díol cánacha chomh maith le h-aon dream eile.  Is beag a bhíonn le fáil ag muintir na Gaeltachta de thoradh na gcánacha sin i gcompráid leis an méid a bhíonn ar fáil ag an nGallthacht agus liomatáistí saidhbhre. Baintear úsáid as an airgead sin chun cúrsaí tionscail do chothú agus neartú le cúrsaí feirmeoireachta ins na ceantair is saibhre ins an tír.  Is beag den airgid sin a thagann thar n-ais do mhuintir na á Gaeltachta agus dá ainneoin sin, táimid ag síor-chlos go bhfuil an iomarca peataireachta á dhéanamh ar an nGaeltacht.  Ní dóigh liom gur fíor é sin.</P>
    <P>Má deintear an rud a moltar ins an leasú seo, is dóigh liom gur mór an chabhair é chun an Ghaeltacht do shábháil, sé sin, coiste de shaghas éigin do chur ar bun a bheidh ag obair ago díreach fé'n Aire.  Beidh ar an gcoisde sin daoine a thuigeann an Gaeltacht, daoine a chaitheas a saoghal le cúrsaí na Gaeltachta agus le cúrsaí na Gaeilge.  Beidh cabhair le fáil acu san ó na daoine is cliste ins an Stáit. Ní haon mhaitheas daoine a chur i mbun na n-oibre nach bhach bhfuil tuiscint aca ar an Ghaeltacht, nach bhfuil dúil aca sa Ghaeilge agus nach bhfuil muinín acu as cúis na Gaeilge.  Ní h-aon mhaitheas daoine a chur i mbun na hoibre gur priosuin leo gach blian a chaitheann siad sa Ghaeltacht.  Caithfí daoine fháil a bhfuil eolas acu ar an nGaeltacht agus ar an obair a bheidh le déanamh.  Tá a leithéid sin le fáil agus tá go leor daoine sa tír a bhfuil tuiscint aca ar an Gaeltacht, agus lán stuidéar déanta aca ar an gceist.</P>
    <P>Deir daoine eile linn nach gnó don Rialtas é obair seo na Gaeilge; go <Col N="621" /> bhfuil Connradh na Gaeilge ann agus go bhfuil Comhdháil Náisiúnta na Gaeilge ann agus gur obair dóibh sin é. 'Sé mo fhreagra ortha siúd ná&mdash;ní le Connradh na Gaeilge and teanga; Ní le Chomhadhail Náisiúnta na Gaeilge an teanga.  Is leis an náisiún an teanga agus 'sí an mhaoin is luachmhaire atá againn í 'mo thuairimse agus dá bhrí sin is obair don Rialtas an mhaoin sin do chothú agus do riarú agus do chosaint.  Dá mba mianach airgid nó guail nó iarainn a bheadh ann, féach an strus a bheadh orainn á shaothrú. Tá maoin na Gaeltachta comh saidhbhir agus chomh tairbheach céanna má's mian linn náisiún neamhspleách Gaelach a bheith againn.  Má's maith linn bheith Gaelach agus náisiún Gaelach a bheith againn, caithfimíd féachaint chuige go mbeidh an Fhíor-Ghaeltacht ann&mdash;é sin nó é chaitheamh suas ar fad go díreach macánta agus aghaidh a thabhairt ar an nGalldachas agus a bheith gallda amach agus amach.</P>
    <P>Maidir le módh oibre, ní dóigh liom gur gá dul isteach ins na cúrsaí sin anseo.  Má cuirtear an bord seo ar bun, sin é an chéad rud a bhéas le déanamh aca.  Sé mo thuairim go mbeidh comh-oibriú le fáil acu má's mian leo dul ar a lorg.  Beidh fonn ar Connradh na Gaeilge agus ar Chomhdhail Náisiúnta na Gaeilge gach cabhair agus cúnamh a thabhairt dóibh agus agach comhairle, ós iad is fearr a thuigeann an scéal, nuair a raghfar i mbun na hoibre.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Twenty Senators have signed their names to this recommendation and, judging by the number of Senators who have spoken, there are many other Senators who agree with the principle outlined in the recommendation. When I was asked to sign the recommendation I did so very willingly, visualising the establishment of a privileged class.  The Gaeltacht Committee which investigated the position of the language in 1925 outlined the Gaeltacht and Breach-Gaeilge tacht areas.  I have seen maps issued by Comhdhail Naisiunta and na Gaeilge recently showing that these areas are becoming more restricted every day and that now the Fíor-Ghaeltacht area is very small.  We have applied the <Col N="622" /> word &ldquo;Fíor-Ghaeltacht&rdquo; to a restricted area which was formerly classified as &ldquo;Gaeltacht&rdquo; as distinct from &ldquo;Breac-Ghaeltacht.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The Breach-Ghaeltacht is gone and the Fíor-Ghaeltacht has become so restricted that I felt it a duty to recommend the amendment to the Seanad and the Government which would mean the establishment of a privileged class in the Community.  We must regard those who use the Irish language as their natural medium as a class that we cannot afford to lose.  If, as a community, the Fíor-Ghaeltacht is lost entirely, it will be a national loss.  I think it would be a European loss if it should go altogether.  If it goes altogether, we have nothing in its place except a hope of reviving the language, spreading from, we might say, Dublin.</P>
      <P>Senator Hayes has just left.  While he was speaking, I thought of the time, over 30 years ago, when, in a prison camp, he was teaching me Irish.  We had a discussion on the different dialects as between the Donegal, Connemara and Munster dialects, and on which would ultimately be the spoken or the dominately one in the language of the Irish nation when we all became Irish-speaking. In the course of that discusson, mention was certainly made of the expression &ldquo;Dublin Irish&rdquo;.  What hope have we, speaking here in Irish, speaking Irish salutations and with our children learning Irish, of reviving the Irish language as the spoken language of the people?  The odds are so terrific against us that I, personally, grasp at the idea of creating what I will call a special privileged class in the present Fíor-Ghaeltacht areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Any machinery we have at present, even that established for Seirbhísí na Gaeltachta agus na gCeanntar gCung, has widened the area envisaged by An Seabhac when addressing the House. I agree that it is the present area, which is not so easy to define, but which we conceive at any rate as the Fíor-Ghaeltacht, and those few districts, those 11 or 12 parishes in which Irish is naturally spoken as the average language of the people.  Someone may say: &ldquo;Well, will we build a <Col N="623" /> wall around them and leave them inside it and see that they are immune to all influences from outside whether they be American influences or anglicising influences or other influences?&rdquo; We cannot do that but, by making them a privileged people, I feel that we would make them proud of their language and proud to maintain and speak that language irrespective of any influences that may be brought to bear upon them.</P>
    <P>I more or less disagree with An Seabhac that that can be done as a literary or as a spiritual mission alone. It must be co-ordinated with economic progress.  Certainly, there is immense room for economic development in those areas to make them more self-supporting and to improve the economic conditions so that the people there will be able to live in comparative comfort and will be glad to maintain the language which the rest of the nation has designated to them as their privilege.  These are the points which impressed me when I consented to put my name to this proposal.  I am sure that practically every member of the Seanad will agree that we must do something specific, something further to ensure that our Fíor-Ghaeltacht does not become still more restricted.</P>
    <P>I would just say to the Minister, knowing that he is probably just as interested as we are, that I am quite satisfied that this nation should vote money to make the residents in these areas, few and all as they are, a privileged community that would be so capable of living in average comfort in their districts and that would be so treated by the rest of the nation that they would feel they have a proud possession.  I should like to see them capable of maintaining themselves and maintaining those areas which ultimately would be a centre from which the Irish language would spread outwards to the rest of the community rather than to dream of the day when we shall be so competent in speaking Irish in, say, the Cities of Dublin, Cork and Galway, that we can resuscitate the language through the medium of English.  I feel that that would be a very difficult job and that all our <Col N="624" /> aspirations and speeches to that effect would be negatived if we could not maintain these small areas and make them such that there would be no chance of the people there ever surrendering their language for the sake of any advantages that might accrue to them through falling in with the ordinary economics of the country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraigOSiochfhradha" hpid="Pádraig Ó Siocfhradha Pádraig Ó Siocfhradha">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Ó Siocfhradha</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like, if I may, to put the Senator who has just spoken right.  I did not intend that economic betterment should not be part of the work of the board.  I suggested economic, linguistic, cultural and social means.  I mentioned these specific things.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Like other Senators, I was invited to put my name to this motion.  If I have not done so, it is not out of any want of sympathy with the idea of the restoration of the national language.  In the first place, I was very interested in and anxious to hear the point of view which was responsible for this motion.  I wanted to know the mind behind this motion, before I expressed an opinion on the whole question.</P>
      <P>I do not think that any more difficult or more complicated problem could be set the Oireachtas to-day than to advise or to determine the line of policy or a plan that we would be satisfied and confident would bring about the restoration of the language.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Hayes has pointed to the fact, in his very admirable speech, that the Gaelic League was established here 60 years ago, and that when the State was founded over 30 years ago there was the belief that the problem with regard to the restoration of the language would be solved easily.  I had the privilege of being one of those who served on the Gaeltacht Commission in 1925.  We saw much of the area then styled &ldquo;Gaeltacht.&rdquo;  To-day it is much narrower.  The confines of the language are now limited indeed to a very much smaller part of the country than was the case in 1925.  I think if anything real or practical is to be done in this whole matter then all those who are interested must themselves be realists. We have not succeeded.  The language is not making progress.  Many people <Col N="625" /> have changed and shifted their point of view in regard to the language and the possibilities of its restoration in the course of the past 25 years.</P>
    <P>Many people are not anything like as optimistic to-day as they were 25 years ago.  What is the degree of failure?  Have we failed absolutely or is there a margin left?  I want to suggest that no concrete proposals can be made that will be of any value until, first, we assess the measure of failure and face up to that.  Next we have to study the causes, the factors, operating against the language and try to think what we can do to counter them.  We have to ask ourselves if we can counter them at all.</P>
    <P>My honest opinion is that the language movement has not been the success it ought to be because there has been an awful lot of claptrap talked about it, and an effort made to elevate people for the sake of the language, mar dheadh, and it has done infinite damage to the policy in regard to the restoration of the language, so that, instead of a mere proposal like what one gathers was in the back of Senator Ó Siocfhradha's mind of spending money or the appointment of a body of people to do something, from what I saw in 1925, what I see now and what we have all experienced as a result of the recommendations of the 1925 commission and the efforts to implement them, we have to do much more hard thinking than has been done on the subject, or we will have to abandon the battle altogether.</P>
    <P>There is a major fundamental consideration.  In the first place, let us ask ourselves: Does the nation really desire the preservation of its language, or does it not?  That is something which it is very difficult to answer.  How many people would vote for that policy with grave doubts about the possibility of its being made a success?  If we really desire to see the language the spoken tongue of the country, why must that be our desire? Is it, as Senator Hayes put it, because it is the Irish nation in essence, a symbol of a separate and distinct people, a link with the past, and, if it be broken, the Irish nation changes and become something else?  Is that <Col N="626" /> the real reason for which we must stand for the restoration of the language?  If that be so, there is much in that that is spiritual.  The people in this small area in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht, we may say, are to-day the custodians of the national heritage, but are they conscious of that?  Are they proud of it and what is the nation doing to make them conscious of the fact that they are the possessors of our national heritage?</P>
    <P>Senator O'Donovan spoke of a privileged class.  I do not know if the interpretation which I would put upon that would be what he had in mind.  I do not think the language can survive as the spoken tongue of a people who themselves, as a people and as a race, do not want to survive. If these people who are the custodians of our heritage to-day are brought up with the point of view that there is nothing here, that Ireland is not a land to be proud of, and especially their part of it, that it is something from which they must get away, they cannot hold on to a language, a heritage or any great national possession.</P>
    <P>If we are to do something in these regions of the country, it must not be designed to make a privileged class in the sense that people will get something very easily.  A race like that will be spoiled; a people like that cannot survive, because it is the people who have to battle for survival who manage to carry on through the stresses and trials of life, and these people will not hold on there, unless they have to make a battle for existence equal to what they would have to make elsewhere.  I think they ought to get a chance and it might be made somewhat easier there than elsewhere in Ireland and definitely easier for them than it would be in Britain or America, but to adopt an approach which means pampering means that we are going to make them weaker, and, in such conditions, I do not think we can be satisfied that the heritage of the language can long be safe.</P>
    <P>It is true that the Fíor-Ghaeltacht includes that region which is the most impoverished portion of the country and one has to make a study of the <Col N="627" /> conditions as they are to-day, with the scientific knowledge in the possession of the world to-day, and see what can be done.  I looked on these areas from the purely economic point of view in 1925, along with my colleague, Senator Ó Siochfhradha, and the other 20 members of the commission, but the knowledge and understanding available to us then was nothing like what is available to the nation to-day.  There is in our possession to-day scientific information, ways that and means of doing many things that did not occur to us in 1925 and it may be that there are possibilities of development there which were undreamed of in 1925.  One could survey these areas again now with the new knowledge we have and see what might be done.</P>
    <P>I feel, however, that the first thing we have to do about this problems of the restoration of the language, and the Fíor-Ghaeltacht in so far as this amendment applies to it, is to inculcate in the minds of these people the belief and the conviction that just as soldiers battled in dark and difficult days in this country and carried on the light, these people are the people whom we are asking to play their part in carrying on the light in the future.  Are they competent to do it?  Have they got that spirit, that pride of race? What are we doing to inculcate that pride?  It is possible to go into an area, and, instead of making the people there proud, conscious of their superiority, of their nobility, to degrade them and to destroy that spirit of independence, that desire for progress, initiative and so on.  That is the one thing we have to be most careful of in any recommendation we make to the Minister.</P>
    <P>It is very valuable that this matter has been raised anew.  I presume that from one angle the Council of Education have been replanning the curriculum in our national schools.  I do not know what they are doing, though I have no doubt that this problem of the language in the schools has been resurveyed; but I think the time has come when we need to make a new survey of the Gaeltacht areas, with the new knowledge available and with minds which, in the past 20 years, have <Col N="628" /> had to adjust themselves to new techniques and to many changes, many of which were unknown and were not anticipated by us when the Gaeltacht Commission originally sat.</P>
    <P>I could not help wondering, when An Seabhac was making his plea, whom he had in mind or what type of man he had in mind to go into these areas to do the kind of things which he wanted done.  This is a major problem.  It is very difficult to get the personnel to implement any plan under this amendment which would be sure to bring the reward justified by the money spent. While I realise that no effort should be spared if the language is to survive, I am equally convinced that no ready-made proposals can be enunciated by any members of the Oireachtas or even by a Minister to-day which will prove they will deliver the goods unless there is a further and much more minute and searching inquiry into all the economic, social and psychological problems confronting the people who desire too see the language restored and made secure in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht so that it may spread in other days to the country as a whole.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>As one of the persons who signed this amendment, I should like to say a word about the reasons why I gave it my support. First of all, as to the place which this amendment occupies in relation to what I might call the major policies that concern the language, I suppose the most ambitious policy of any would be that Ireland should become unilingually Gaelic speaking from Fair Head in Antrim to Mizen Head in Cork.  Undoubtedly, the realisation of that policy is going to present considerable difficulties.  One method used for furthering that policy is the compulsory teaching of the language in the schools.  I am glad to see my grandchildren learning Irish at school.  They frequently converse amongst themselves in the Irish language, especially when they want to conceal their thoughts from their parents or their grandparents, but I doubt very much whether in 20 or 30 years' time they will still be speaking Irish in the daily business of life.  I doubt very much <Col N="629" /> whether that major policy is one which has in it the possibility of success.</P>
      <P>A less ambitious and, I think, a more practical policy is that to which this amendment is a valuabel contribution &mdash;a policy of preserving geographical bilingualism in the country as a whole.  We have bilingualism on a geographical basis in the sense that there are certain small areas where Irish is the only language and a certain large area in which English is the common speech of the people.  But the future of geographical bilingualism is undoubtedly very precarious in view of the extremely rapid rate at which the language is disappearing in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht.</P>
      <P>There are examples of successful geographical bilingualism.  Look at Canada, for example.  It is bilingual, French and English being spoken there.  French is exclusively spoken in Quebec and English is exclusively spoken in the rest of Canada.  Why is it that the French language and culture have survived in Quebec, and why is it that Gaelic speaking is in danger of disappearing in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht? The reason is that the people of Quebec had a tolerable economic basis for their culture and language. Therefore, the problem here is not so much a linguistic problem.  The problem is to give a tolerable economic foundation to the life of the people living in the Irish-speaking communities who constitute the Fíor-Ghaeltacht. That is a difficult procedure but not, I think, a hopeless one.</P>
      <P>It will have to be done in such a way as not to pauperise or demoralise the people in those areas but rather to give them a new sense of pride and hope in the realisation of the valuable part they have played in preserving the national life and the part they may hope to play in developing it in the future.  That, I think, is the reason why it is suggested that some flexible unit should be established under Government auspices as a means of giving effect to a policy of this kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The heavy hand of a State Department and the methods of centralised and departmentalised bureaucracy are not at all appropriate to a very delicate and difficult operation of the <Col N="630" /> kind we have in view.  So far, the use of that kind of administrative system has, on the whole, tended to anglicise rather than gaelicise the people in the Gaeltacht in so far as they are affected by the activities of a central Government. Consequently, I think it would be desirable that some kind of semiofficial or even private agency should be created, organised and subsidised out of moneys provided from these sources.</P>
    <P>I have in mind the kind of work done in other parts of the country by bodies like Muintir na Tíre, the Gaelic League or the Irish Agricultural Organisation Society.  Would it be possible to create from these a new private agency endowed with this special task, give them considerable latitude in the way they would approach this very difficult task and not too closely supervise them with regard to the financial side of their operations?  I think some such body would be more flexible, more adaptable and more able to understand the psychology of the problem they would have to deal with than anything that the State could create by using the agency of its own official civil servants.</P>
    <P>I think it is highly important that every effort should be made to preserve the living speech in those parts of the country where it still exists.  I think that a great many people who are themselves hopelessly anglicised would have a great deal of sympathy with the efforts to preserve the language in those parts of the country where it is still a living language and even with the extension of the areas in which it is still a living language.  This is not merely an Irish interest.  It is not merely a matter of national sentiment but it is also a European interest for the people of the Gaeltacht are the inheritors of a tradition that goes back into the mist of prehistory, before the Christian era and before the Roman Empire.  They are the inheritors of a cultural tradition that is of great interest to archaeologists in European countries as well as at home.  It would be a tragedy from a European point of view as well as from the Irish point of view if we allowed the Gaeltacht to perish and its people to cease to be the <Col N="631" /> living inheritors of a spoken Gaelic language.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanRuane" hpid="Mr. S.T. Ruane Mr. S.T. Ruane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S.T. Ruane</NameTxt>
      <P>As one of the signatories to this recommendation I would like to say a few words and I promise to be very brief.  With Senator Baxter I am in thorough agreement that this is a serious problem, and no direct suggestions have been made as to how it can be handled by the Government.  It cannot be denied that since we established our own Government every encouragement has been given to the spread and development of the language and the preservation of the Gaeltacht. Concessions have been given to people living in the Gaeltacht in so far as admissions to preparatory schools and training colleges are concerned, which many in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht said were not altogether fair and which interfered with the possibility of many Irish speakers who did not happen to come from the Gaeltacht entering these colleges, while candidates lower on the examination of successes entered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is unfortunately true that the enthusiasm that marked the language revival at a time when we were under foreign domination has more or less evaporated since we achieved our own government.  It is a matter of regret to those who were associated with the pioneers in the early days of the Gaelic League that not alone has the language position itself deteriorated but even Irish customs are not patronised as they were 30 or 40 years ago. I had the experience some years ago of visiting England and being taken round some of the halls there by Irish men and women who were in lucrative employment there.  I can assure you that there was more evidence of a love of Irish dancing and Irish customs in those English halls than you would find in many halls on the fringe of the Gaeltacht to-day. That is an unfortunate admission but it must be made and we must face up to the fact that something drastic must be done if we are to save the language for the country.  What can be done, and how to set about doing <Col N="632" /> it, is the problem for which I cannot offer a solution.</P>
    <P>At the present time and for the past ten or 15 years those working for the language have been up against obstructions and distractions that did not manifest themselves in the early years.  You have the radio and films which are certainly not racy of the soil.  The people who have radios installed do not always tune in to the Irish programmes; they look for something lighter and more fetching. This also shows that the enthusiasm for the restoration of the language has declined to a great extent.</P>
    <P>I have no suggestions to make as to what the Government can do, but as regards the setting up of a body to work under the supervision of the Government to devise ways and means by which people can be kept in the Gaeltacht, I sincerely hope that there will be no soft money in relation to these provisions, that the work done will be constantly supervised, and that there will be value given for the money that may be allocated by the Government.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Aire Airgeadais Gniomhathach (Proinsias Mac Aogáin) Aire Airgeadais Gniomhathach (Proinsias Mac Aogáin)">
      <NameTxt>Aire Airgeadais Gniomhathach (Proinsias Mac Aogáin)</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá áthas orm gur cuireadh an méid sin suime ins an rún seo.  Ní dóigh liom go raibh gá leis agus ní dóigh liom fosta go ndéanfaidh sé an obair atá in aigne ag An Seanadóir An Seabhac agus na daoine eile a mhol é.  Mar dúirt mé an lá deireannach sa tSeanaid shocraigh an Rialtas go n-íocfaí suim éigin as an gciste seo, an Ciste Forbartha, gach bliain, agus go gcuirfimis £250,000 ar leataoibh an bhliain seo.  Dúirt mé cheana leis an tSeanaid an méid atá íoctha amach as an gCiste go dtí seo agus an méid atá á chaitheamh ag an Rúnaí Parlaiminte atá i gceannas Oifig na Gaeltachta agus go gCeantar gCúng.  Sílim féin go ndéanfaidh an Rúnaí Parlaiminte aon rud is féidir le Bord a dhéanamh agus go ndéanfaidh sé níos fearr é.  Ó cuireadh an Roinn sin ar bun téann an Rúnaí Parlaiminte i gcomhairle lena lán daoine i Ranna an Rialtais.  Taobh amuigh de sin téann sé go dtí gach ceantar den Ghaeltacht agus tugann gach duine a bhfuil suim aige sa cheist comhairle dhó agus déanfaidh sé a <Col N="633" /> dhícheall an chomhairle sin a chuir i bhfeidhm más maith leis an scéim.</P>
      <P>Tá fhios ag na Seanadóirí go léir ó cuireadh and Roinn sin ar bun an méadú mór atá tar éis teacht ar an méid airgid a chaithimid ins an nGaeltacht. Cúpla bliain ó soin d'ardaíodh an méid a caitheadh ins an nGaeltacht. Sa Roinn Tailte, cuir i gcás, táimid ag caitheamh os cionn £200,000. Anuraidh do thug an Rialtas £400,000 don Roinn Rialtais Áitiúil agus tá an méid sin á chaitheamh ins an bhFíor-Ghaeltacht ar dheisiú na mbóithre atá oiriúnach don chuartaíocht. Sílim féin go bhfuil sé i bhfad níos fearr an dualgas a chur ar an Rialtas Féin gach rud is féidire a dhéanamh chun feabhas a chur ar an tslí bheatha sa Ghaeltacht agus chun cuidiú le hathbheochaint na Gaeilge ins an nGaeltacht agus taobh amuigh den Ghaeltacht.</P>
      <P>Aontaím go mór leans lán daoine anseo adúirt nach féidir le muintire na Gaeltachta an Ghaeilge a chosaint iad féin.  Ní féidir agus ins an saol atá anois ann is mó a bhraitheann an bhua ar an gcúl tac ná ar na fórsaí atá tréineáte agus caithfidh an cúl taca ar fud na hÉireann teacht chun cuidiú leis an muintir atá ag troid ins an dún atá sa bhFíor-Ghaeltacht.</P>
      <P>Tá muintir na hÉireann ag teacht, tá an Ghaeilge ag dul ar aghaidh, tá Gaeilge mhaith ag na daoine óga atá ag fágáil na scoileanna faoi láthair. I ngach bliain beidh sé sin ag dul i méid.  Tá obair mhaith á dhéanamh ins na scoileanna náisiúnta agus ins na meán-scoileanna chomh maith.  Níl mé chomh sásta leis an méid atá á dhéanamh ins na hOllscoileanna.  Sílim nach ceart don tSeanadóir Micheál Ó hAodha bheith ag rá gur &ldquo;demonstration&rdquo; a rinneadh anseo nuair do labhair duine anseo as Gaeilge.  Tá sé deacair gó leor labhairt in aon teanga agus tá sé an deacair dhomsa, cur i gcás, labhairt as Gaeilge.  Ach is maith an rud é an saghas sin &ldquo;demonstration&rdquo; a thabhairt ó am go ham. Tá a fhios agam nach bhfuil Gaeilge mhaith agamsa, tá a fhios agam go bhfuil sé go huafásach, do réir gramadaí agus mar sin de.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Micheál Ó hAodha Micheál Ó hAodha">
      <NameTxt>Micheál Ó hAodha</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní bhfuair mé aon locht ar an nGaeilge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="634" />
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Proinsias Mac Aogáin Proinsias Mac Aogáin">
      <NameTxt>Proinsias Mac Aogáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá a fhios agam, ach bhí an chaint faoi dhaoine anseo a labhair i nGaeilge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Micheál Ó hAodha Micheál Ó hAodha">
      <NameTxt>Micheál Ó hAodha</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá an tAire á rá.  Dúradh go maith é, ach ní dúradh aon rud.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Prionsias Mac Aogáin Prionsias Mac Aogáin">
      <NameTxt>Prionsias Mac Aogáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Dúirt an Seanadóir gur &ldquo;demonstration&rdquo; é. Tá daoine timpeall na tíre go léir, daoine nach bhfuil Gaeilge ró-mhaith acu agus tá siad dúthrachtach agus tá siad deimhnitheach go dtiochfaidh an lá nuair bheidh formhór na ndaoine in ann obair a dhéanamh trí Ghaeilge ar fad.  Tá mé cinnte go bhfuil an lá sin ag teacht agus tá sé ag teacht i bhfad níos sciobtha ná mar atá fhios ag a lean daoine anseo.</P>
      <P>On the question of setting up an administrative body, I think we have enough machinery to do any work that any reasonable man will suggest, either to improve the economic life of the people in the Gaeltacht or to help to spread the language through the country.  It is not really more machinery we want but better implementation of the ideas that are already accepted.  We want more ideas and better ideas if possible as to the means by which we can improve the economic conditions of the Gaeltacht. The unfortunate thing for us is that the whole trend of the economic life in the world is to desert areas and occupations in which there is not a livelihood to be got that is as high a standard as people can get in any other area to which they are free to move. Our people are free to move from the Gaeltacht areas to other parts of the country.  They are free to move to a large number of other countries. Whereas the people would be content to put up with a very hard existence if they had nowhere else to go, nowadays people in the Gaeltacht or in the congested districts would like to get the same sort of livelihood as they could get in practically any other country or in any other part of this country.  That is difficult to give them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have, however, improved their economic conditions very greatly.  I remember when I was young&mdash;and I am not too old yet&mdash; that famine was endemic in the Gaeltacht areas.  I <Col N="635" /> remember reading as a boy of famine in Connemara or famine in one or other of the islands.  We are very far away from that now.  I am not saying that is anything to boast about, but the ordinary person in the Gaeltacht now has a very much higher standard of living and very much greater security of that standard, than he had 50, 40, 20 or even ten years ago.</P>
    <P>They are not going to be content with mere security of that kind.  As Senator Micheál Óg Mac Pháidín and other speakers said, we need to put industries into the Gaeltacht that will stand on their own feet, and in which the workers will be able to earn a reasonable standard of living.  We have made several attempts at that. There are scattered throughout the Gaeltacht small industries which are giving workers there as good a standing as they could get a many other parts and indeed a very much higher standard than in many of the industrial towns in most of Europe.  But our people want a better standard than would satisfy most of the people of Europe&mdash;because most of the people of Europe are not free to move.  Our people can.  We have to provide such a standard as will keep them there of their own free will by their own preference.</P>
    <P>I do not agree with the people who are cynical about the future of Irish or regard it as hopeless.  The people of the Gaeltacht have a pride in Irish. There is nothing else has kept Irish alive in the past, say, 100 years and particularly for the last 20 years.  The opportunities of learning English have been multiplied and now it is very easy indeed for the ordinary person in the Gaeltacht to get a complete knowledge of English.  They are proud of their Irish and that is what is keeping it alive and not what has been done for them to improve their standard of living or to give them jobs in the Gaeltacht.</P>
    <P>One definite scheme for keeping Irish alive in the Gaeltacht&mdash;the best one I think&mdash;is the improvement of housing in the Gaeltacht so that they <Col N="636" /> can take in visitors in the summer months.  It improves the morale of the people in the Gaeltacht when they become teachers and use their Irish not only in their everyday work, but in teaching strangers from Dublin or elsewhere a language that they are anxious to learn.  The experience has been that where there is a Gaelic college the morale of the people in the district is improved and the speaking of Irish receives a new life.  Unfortunately, the Gaelic movement as a whole in the country is not doing enough to establish such colleges.  Comhaltas Uladh have shown the lead in that respect and have done magnificent work, with no resources only what they themselves raise.</P>
    <P>There are a couple of organisations here that are doing a little in that regard, but not anything like what they should be doing.  Rather than establishing a body of any description to advise the Government as to what to do what is necessary is a group of people who will start Gaelic colleges in the various Fíor-Ghaeltacht districts and advise the people how to take advantage of the various Government schemes for the improvement of their economic condition.</P>
    <P>There are schemes for the improvement of houses in the Gaeltacht.  There are only a few areas that have taken up these schemes as energetically as they should.  At the moment further sums are available for adding rooms and putting in water and generally improving houses in the Gaeltacht to a point where they each could take an extra couple of people in the summer months.  I would recommend to the people who are interested that they should try to get further colleges established in the Gaeltacht and to secure an improvement of the homes in the areas of the colleges so that they could take extra visitors.</P>
    <P>We should do more than has been done in getting electricity into the Gaeltacht areas.  Senator Kissane suggested parish councils.  If there were parish councils in the area, or committees, who would make it their business to canvass the people of the district to accept electricity very much more rapid progress could be made in <Col N="637" /> getting electricity into every house in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht.  I do not know of anything that would raise the morale of the people more or bring them more closely in touch with modern developments than electricity in their homes.</P>
    <P>If all county councils did what the Donegal Council did in Ranafast, where they put in a piped water supply, great good would be done.  If there were active local public opinion in regard to the provision of piped water in the houses in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht I do not see any reason why such schemes could not be put into operation at once.  Anybody who is interested would spend his time very much better and to much greater advantage for the cause he has at heart if he could organise and promote these schemes and bring them to fruition.  There is plenty of goodwill on the part of the Government.  The funds are available to support it.  It requires not a further centralised committee in Dublin but active work on the spot to get these things going.</P>
    <P>There is a great number of organisations in existence that have an interest in the Gaeltacht.  It is wiser for me not to say how they should come together but I hope they will come together, or else act separately, to promote some of the ideas that I have mentioned.  The money is available for pushing them ahead.</P>
    <P>If we had in some of the universities a group of people who wanted to modernise Irish or to use Irish for all the modern subjects that are taught in the universities, if they took an interest in that sort of work they might learn that they could discuss all the modern subjects through the medium of Irish and be able to steer the people of the Gaeltacht in developing a more modern life.</P>
    <P>One scheme that is available to the people in the Gaeltacht that would do most widespread good and through which they could make most rapid progress is the scheme for fertilising the land.  Recently, the Government announced a scheme whereby anyone who fails to get lime and fertilisers in the ordinary way, by means of his own money or his own local credit, can get <Col N="638" /> credit here through the Agricultural Credit Corporation.  I do not say that it would not be a good thing if some giant could throw all the rocks in Connemara into the sea but I am certain that if it required £200 an acre to do it, that £200 would be much better spent on improving 50 acres to a point where it could produce many times what it is producing to-day.  That is not a wild calculation.  Even on the most acid soils in the Gaeltacht, if they are drained to any extent, an expenditure of £5 on lime, phosphate, potash, etc., would bring it into maximum production for that type of land.  That is more than it would cost on the average. I am certain that if the land of the Gaeltacht around the rocks, without removing them at all, got a treatment costing on an average about £5 an acre, production would be more than doubled.  At the moment production on most of it is very low.  It wants not only lime.  It is short of phosphates, potash and some of the trace elements like cobalt.</P>
    <P>As a scheme and as an activity for people who are interested in getting the maximum number of persons to live in the Gaeltacht, and to give them that chance in the shortest possible time, I would commend some system, whether by way of parish councils, local committees or whatever way it is done, whereby people in the Gaeltacht could be enthused to the point where they would take advantage of the present system to lime and fertilise their land to the maximum desirable extent.  There is no obstacle in the way and if it could be done by some magic or some method overnight I am sure that, within the next 12 months, the capacity of the land in the Gaeltacht areas to produce would be doubled&mdash;and that, at least, would be a step in the right direction.</P>
    <P>I want to say to An Seabhac and to the other Senators who put their names to this motion that it is not pure cussedness on the part of the Government that is responsible for their refusal to accept the suggestions that have been made from time to time that a special board should be set up to deal with the Gaeltacht.  Some of the people who made that proposal went on to suggest that complete and <Col N="639" /> absolute power should be give to this board to spend either a fixed annual sum or some lump capital sum on any work that they thought would do good in improving the economic life of the people in the Gaeltacht and in helping to promote the Irish language.  It would be politically impossible for that system to work at the present time. Fifty or 60 years ago it was possible for the Congested Districts Board to work with great liberty of action simply because they were a long way away from London and the parliamentary question had not been developed to the stage which it has reached to-day.  Any Government organisation&mdash;whether the Government takes direct responsibility for it or whether it is a special board&mdash; if it belongs to the State or is under the State, must give equal treatment to everybody.  If one person gets a five pound note for doing a certain type of work then every other person in the same category must get the £5 also&mdash; and that is very difficult to reconcile with the liberty of action that most people think a board should have and the liberty of action which the old Congested Districts Board had 50 years ago.</P>
    <P>One thing that anybody going through the Gaeltacht from Donegal to South Kerry or West Cork will notice is the patchy work that was done by the Congested Districts Board even though it existed over a great number of years.  The signs of its activities are very infrequent throughout the whole of the Gaeltacht and the congested areas.  In odd little patches of districts here and there you will see the type of house that was built by the Congested Districts Board: you will see the type of little footbridge that they put over rivers, and so forth.  But their activities by no means affected every farm in the congested areas or in every district. Any board that would be established by the Government to help the Gaeltacht would nowadays be expected to do as much for every household as might be done in any single case&mdash; and that is something which it is very difficult to arrange.</P>
    <P>One of the objections that there are to, for instance, the rock scheme of <Col N="640" /> Connemara is that it would take so long to carry out.  It takes a couple of hundred pounds to do an acre. There are tens of thousands of acres in Connemara, Donegal, Kerry and Mayo, and nobody can say that you can do many of those acres, even if you could spend a great number of tens of millions of pounds in doing so. However, one scheme that can be done quickly and in which there are no obstacles of any kind is the raising of the standard of agricultural production in the Gaeltacht by more than double within the next 12 months. I think everybody interested in the economic life of the people in the Gaeltacht, and in preserving the Irish language, should put their shoulders to the wheel and see that as many families as possible in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht and the Breac-Ghaeltacht will take advantage of the scheme that is there to lime and fertilise not only their arable lands but also the grass and the grass around the rocks until we get round to shifting them.</P>
    <P>I think I have dealt broadly with the points that have been put forward by the various speakers.  I can promise this Seanad that the Government fully intend to pursue with all possible vigour the schemes that have already been inaugurated for the Gaeltacht over the years and that they will adopt and put into action any scheme that is calculated to do the work which An Seabhac and the other speakers have in mind.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraigOSiochfhradha" hpid="Pádraig Ó Siocfhradha Pádraig Ó Siocfhradha">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Ó Siocfhradha</NameTxt>
      <P>Is trua liom a thuiscint ón Aire nach bhfuil fonn air na moltaí a chuireamar roimhe a ghlacadh.  Na tagairtí a rinne sé do na nithe is féidir a dhéanamh faoin ngléas atá ann cheana, tá sé sin ceart go leor ach is é an locht atá agamsa ar na gléasanna atá ann cheana ag obair sa Ghaeltacht ná nach bhfuil siad dlúth go leor chun a chur ina luí ar mhuintir na Gaeltachta go bhfuil siad i gceantair a moltar dóibh leanúint leis an nGaeilge atá acu.  Tá rud éigin níos dlúithe, níos muinteartha, níos comhgaraí dóibh fhéin ag teastáil.  Ní mór ná go dteastaíonn a chur ina luí ar an líon daoine atá sa Ghaeltacht go bhfuil oidhreacht uasal le cosaint acu.  Ní mór iad a <Col N="641" /> spreagadh chun an oidhreacht sin a chosaint agus ní mór, freisin, tuiscint a thabhairt dóib ar conas é sin a dhéanamh agus tuiscint ina theannta san ar conas é a dhéanamh.  Sin é an chúis go mba mhaith liom go mbeadh an coiste sin nó an bord sin ann &mdash;daoine a rachadh ag caint leo agus daoine nach mbeadh acu an aigne fhuar a bhíonn ag oifigigh phoiblí. Nílim gan dochas fós ná déanfaidh an tAire an rud sin nuair a thiocfaidh sé chun é a thuiscint, mar tá riachtanas leis.  Ní féidir an obair a dhéanamh gan é, agus is trua liom a rá, ach is fíor é, ná hoireann rialacha ná modh oibre na Stát-Sheirbhíse chun an cheist atá sa Ghaeltacht a fhreagairt agus a réiteach.  Tá an Stát-Sheirbhís ina rud fuar agus caithfear rud éigin a chur ina háit.  Ba mhaith liom go mbeadh dúthracht agus spioraid laistiar de na comhairlí a ndearna mé tagairt dóibh agus go ndéanfadh siad scrúdú ar cad iad na rudaí fónta agus eile a molfaí dhóibh agus rogha a dhéanamh. Tá dóchas agam as an Aire atá ós ár gcómhair go dtiocfaidh sé ar an aigne sin agus go gcuirfidh sé gléas éigin ann a thabharfadh do thuiscint mhuintir na Gaeltachta go bhfuiltear chun beart caidrimh a dhéanamh leo, go bhfuiltear ar aon aigne agus in aon pháirt leo agus go bhfuil Rialtas na hÉireann agus náisiún na hÉireann ag iaraidh orthu-san a ndualgas féin a dhéanamh chun an oidreacht sin atá acu fós a chosaint agus a choimeád. Sin é ba mhaith liomsa a thiocfadh de thairbhe as pé rud a dhéanfadh an Rialtas.  Níl muinín agam as bheith ag caitheamh airgid dóibh&mdash;caithfear rud éigin eile a dhéanamh ina theannta agus seo caoi chun é sin a chur ar bun. Ba mhaith liom a iarraidh ar an Aire tuilleadh machnaimh a dhéanamh ar an gceist agus teacht ar aon chomhairle linne.  Ní haon mhaith bheith ag tathaint an mholta seo ar Aire nach bhfuil fonn air glacadh leis&mdash;ní bheadh aon éifeacht dhúinn ann&mdash;agus le do chead, a Chathaoirligh, tarraingim siar é.</P>
      <P>Recommendation, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 4 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="642" /> Sections 5 to 9, inclusive, and Title, agreed to.</P>
    <P>Bill reported without recommendation, received for final consideration and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Business suspended at 6 p.m. until 7 p.m.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Report of the Committee" RHead="of Selection">
    <Title>Report of the Committee of Selection.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee of Selection has nominated the following six Senators to serve on the Joint Committee on Workmen's Compensation:&mdash;Senators Hawkins, Hearne, McCrea, McGuire, P.F. O'Reilly and Yeats.</P>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the Report do lie upon the Table.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="State Guarantees Bill," RHead="1952&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>State Guarantees Bill, 1952&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Bill passed through Committee without amendment.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take the remaining stages to-day.</P>
    <P>Bill reported without recommendations, received for final consideration, and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Consular Conventions Bill," RHead="1953&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Consular Conventions Bill, 1953&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (4) to delete &ldquo;21&rdquo; and to substitute &ldquo;31.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is an amendment the purpose of which is to give to the Houses of the Oireachtas more time than the Minister prescribes in the sub-section.  By sub-section (4) of the Bill, every Order must be laid before each House of the Oireachtas as soon as may be after it is made, and if a resolution annulling such Order is passed by either House within the next 21 days following, it <Col N="643" /> shall be annulled.  I suggest that we should have more than 21 days, and I think 31 days would be merely adequate.  I think that 21 days would be altogether too short and that an Order of this importance, conferring certain rights, should be given due notice, and a due opportunity should be available to a member of the Oireachtas to make an effort to have it annulled.  In saying 31 days, I think I am being quite reasonable.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Minister for External Affairs (Mr. Aiken) Frank Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Minister for External Affairs (Mr. Aiken)</NameTxt>
      <P>Senators will have noticed that Senator O'Reilly quoted no precedent at all for this amendment. There has been a great number of Bills passed by the Oireachtas and in not one of them has a longer period than 21 sittings days been given to annul any Order made under them.  The period of 21 days does not represent 21 calendar days; it means 21 sitting days and that period covers a great deal of a calendar year as far as the Seanad is concerned.  I feel that the Seanad should within the year make up its mind as to whether it is going to annul an Order or not.  Twenty-one days might be only a couple of calendar months as far as the Dáil is concerned, but it would be most of the year in the case of the Seanad.  Whenever an agreement is made with another Government to give these powers, privileges and immunities on a reciprocal basis, we should know within a reasonable time that the convention under which they are given is not going to be annulled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret I cannot accept the Minister's reasons as a valid excuse for failure to accept my amendment. Frequently Ministers tell us: &ldquo;There is no precedent for what you are proposing.&rdquo;  The precedent in this case is 21 days.  It is simply nonsense to put forward that kind of argument. There is no reason whatever why if 21 days were in every Bill that had a provision of this kind, we should henceforward tie ourselves to 21 days.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I quite appreciate that 21 days means more than 21 calendar days; nevertheless, it is no excuse to say we must have 21 days in this section because 21 <Col N="644" /> days is what is in every similar section. The Minister has mentioned also that indication of approval is given to other Governments on matters of this kind. That is so but, of course, it is made clear to the other Governments that the approval is given subject to the Parliament passing or approving what has been provisionally done by the Government or by a Government Minister.  It is not fair to expect the House to accept as a reason for not accepting my amendment the fact that in similar acts of Parliament only 21 days has been provided for.  I believe the Minister should accept the amendment.  I do not see how it can cause any inconvenience, great or small.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree to a large extent with Senator P.F. O'Reilly that simply because a thing has been done before it is not absolutely necessary that it should be done again.  However, in an amendment like this I think the onus of proof is on the mover of the amendment to show cause why 31 days is preferable to 21.  I entirely agree with the Minister when he says that 21 sitting days could cover the best part of a year as far as the Seanad is concerned.  First of all, if it is agreed that time should be given for the consideration of any Order that may be tabled here, we are faced then with this question: How long should that time be?  We will rule out, for instance, a week&mdash;seven sitting days would be altogether too short; on the other hand we will rule out two years as being preposterously long.  It will be seen, therefore, that you must decide on some reasonable time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The question as to the time that should be given was discussed quite a number of years ago and it has been generally accepted that 21 days is a reasonable period to allow for consideration of such an Order.  If it is to be changed in any way the onus of proof is on the person who wants to change what has been the practice; in other words to show that the practice has given rise to inconvenience on the part of members of the House, that the time was inadequate for consideration. My experience in this connection has been that on no single occasion <Col N="645" /> has an Order not been considered in this House because the 21 days have elapsed.  In this case the mover of the amendment has made no substantial case for increasing from 21 days to 31 days the time within which an Order can be considered.</P>
    <P>Amendment put and negatived.</P>
    <P>Section 2 put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 3 to 5, inclusive, put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete the section.</P>
      <P>My reason for moving this amendment is to see that a class is not further extended.  As the law stands, Ambassadors, Ministers and persons having ambassadorial rank have complete privilege and are immune from the laws of the country to which they are attached.  That is well founded and perhaps the law is there for a very good reason.  If it were sought to pass that law to-day, some persons would oppose it while others would take the strong view that it should be passed, that Ambassadors and persons of high rank representing their king or president should have immunity from proceedings against them in the courts of the country to which they are accredited.</P>
      <P>I do not quarrel with the position, but I see no reason why we should extend that privilege to consular officers in regard to entry into consular offices.  There is no reason why there should be any restriction on the entry of the Garda Síochána, or of any person seeking to execute a legal process against a consul, into the consulate.  The position to-day is that such a process can be executed in a consulate and the premises can be entered for that purpose.  Why are we seeking now to say that the law will no longer be allowed to operate?  What reason can the Minister give for saying that the law hitherto enforced must be changed and that we must now provide that a consulate must not be entered for the purpose of executing a legal process?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not know why the immunity that <Col N="646" /> a Minister or an Ambassador enjoys should be extended to a consular officer or his place of business.  The Minister may say that some years ago, in 1950, the Government of the day signed a convention with another country, the United States of America, and that we should give effect to that convention by this Bill.  Again let us be clear.  In signing the convention subject to legislation, our Government does not definitely bind us, but makes it clear, as does the other country, that the convention is signed subject to the Government being successful in negotiating legislation to give it legislative effect.  Therefore, we need not be in the least bit concerned.  The Minister seemed to be a good deal worried about this.  The convention was entered into on the distinct understanding that it would come to an end if the Oireachtas did not give effect to it by the necessary Act.</P>
    <P>This particular section is entirely revolutionary.  At the moment there is no restriction on entry into consular offices.  Now the Government thinks we should give them a particular immunity.  It must be borne in mind that an under-sheriff or county registrar seeking to recover the amount of a judgment obtained against a consul, which the consul would have been bound to pay in the case provided at sub-section (4) of Section 7&mdash;that is, in a case in which a consul had entered into an agreement not expressly on behalf of his Government and was thereby made amenable to the law&mdash; would be met by sub-section (6), which provides that he may not enter the consulate premises with a view to levying the amount of that judgment unless the officer gave his permission or the Minister gave his permission. I am quite sure that if a consul allowed a judgment to be obtained against him he would not be very anxious to allow the county registrar in to levy the amount of the judgment.  It may be said then that the Minister would give his consent.  Why should anyone, having obtained a judgment of the court, have to go to the Minister, when there is an officer of the court there, the county registrar or under-sheriff? At present that officer can act, but if <Col N="647" /> this section is passed, he will not be able to act.  This section gives immunity to a consul which in my opinion is not deserved and for which the Minister has not made a case.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Senator has not addressed himself properly to this matter.  Every word he said would be in order if this were a one-sided arrangement.  The Senator will see that the definition section, Section 1 of the Bill, says that a consulate means &ldquo;any building or part of a building which is exclusively occupied for the purposes of the official business of a consular officer&rdquo;.  That is a very clear definition.  The provisions in the section which the Senator wants deleted will not apply under Section 2 &ldquo;save to such extent as they are so applied by Order under this section for the time being in force&rdquo;.  The Minister makes an Order.  Section 2 (2) says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Whenever the Government are satisfied that, in a consular convention country, powers, privileges and immunities similar to those conferred by any of the provisions of Sections 3 to 11 are conceded in respect of the State, the Government may by Order apply all or any of these provisions in respect of that country.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>To take an example, the Government of France decides not to give certain privileges; then this country follows suit and denies those privileges to consuls of France here, as they are denied to our consuls in France.</P>
      <P>There is a further provision in sub-section (3) of Section 2 that, even after such privileges are given to a consulate, if the Government concerned withdraws some of the immunities or privileges the Government here will have the right to revoke the Order granting privileges and immunities.  I submit that the section should stand. It is an enabling section.  It enables the Government here to accord immunities and privileges to a consulate here that will be accorded to our consulates in any country with which we have diplomatic relations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="648" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a matter on which personally I do not agree with Senator O'Reilly.  I take a rather different attitude.  It is perfectly proper and a good thing that public attention should be drawn to these provisions by a discussion.  Senator O'Reilly generally takes the view that we ought not to extend what might be called consular privileges.  I take a different view.  I think it is a good thing that they should be extended provided they are extended mutually, as is provided for in the Bill.  I find difficulty in seeing any serious danger, particularly in this case where, if there was any abuse, the Minister has power to authorise a Guard to go into the consulate.  I imagine the number of consulates that come under this definition will be comparatively small.</P>
      <P>I suppose it is because I am a manufacturer and trader&mdash;not, certainly, because I in any way want to lessen the value of having diplomats here&mdash;but I rather feel in the case of a small country that it may be to our advantage to strengthen the position of consuls, particularly, as is provided in this case, when they are our nationals.  I, therefore, would be very unwilling to vote down any provision which would enable us to strengthen the position of our consuls abroad.</P>
      <P>Although Senator O'Reilly is perfectly right in saying that we are not in any way bound by an agreement made, it is equally true that one must think twice before voting for something which would make an agreement made with another country invalid.  I would not for a moment vote for something that was wrong simply because it was an agreement, but one must be careful because what may seem perfectly reasonable to us might be interpreted abroad as something which was directed against a country and the reasons which are behind Deputy O'Reilly in this matter might not be appreciated.  I am not able to support the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to what Senator Hearne has said, I quite appreciate the nature of the buildings and premises covered by the word <Col N="649" />&ldquo;consulate&rdquo;.  It could be that a consul might remove to a consulate the only assets which a sheriff or under-sheriff could recover and then we would be thrown back, if this section goes through, on the consul's consent or on the Minister's consent.  I do not think that anybody with an order of a court of competent jurisdiction should have to go to a Minister to seek enforcement of that court order.</P>
      <P>Again, Senator Hearne has made the position quite clear that this section will affect only consuls, consular officers and consulates of countries which accord us similar treatment.  I have never heard of any claim from any Government Department or any consul of ours that he was in difficulty or had been in difficulty because there was not legislation of this kind to assist him in getting the privileges that will flow to our consuls abroad if we pass this legislation.  I do not know that our consuls have been in any great difficulty as the law stands at the moment. As far as I know, no Minister for External Affairs has made the case that, because of the lack of legislation of this kind, our consuls in other countries were in difficulty, that they could not do this and could not do that because this legislation was not in existence.  I do not think that what Senator Hearne has said affects the position.  We are now extending rights and privileges for which there is no reason, for which no claim has been made, for which certainly no claim has been made publicly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Reilly is wrong when he says that no claim has been made publicly for the matters which are covered in this section.  In Article 10 and Article 11 of the Consular Convention, which was signed in the United States of America, provision is made that American consuls here will get certain privileges and immunities in the performance of their functions.  The Government here at the time agreed to grant them these immunities and privileges in the performance of their consular duties.  I think they were right in doing it because it means that our consuls in the United States of America get the same and equal rights and privileges in the <Col N="650" /> United States of America in the performance of their consular duties.</P>
      <P>Almost every solicitor in the country and a great number of families, particularly in the western parts of the country, are interested in the activities of our consuls in the United States of America.  We cannot ratify this convention, according to the accepted practice, until we are in a position legally to fulfil the terms of the agreement. If we were not to ratify the convention there would be grave disappointment and great trouble would be caused to many of our citizens who want our consuls to fight their cases in the American courts.</P>
      <P>We are not extending the same immunities to consuls as we extend to full diplomatic representatives.  We only grant to consuls the immunities and privileges set out here in regard to the premises which they use as a consulate.  The Senator will see in the definition clause of the Bill that &ldquo;consulate&rdquo; means any building or part of a building which is exclusively occupied for the purposes of the official business of a consular officer.  In the case of a diplomat, the immunities and privileges cover him in all his acts and all the premises which he uses or occupies.  In the case of a consul, the privileges and immunities cover the building which he uses as a consulate and cover him only when he is carrying out the functions of a consul. There is the provision here, which has been agreed to, that in certain cases a member of the Garda Síochána, or other person, acting in the execution of any warrant may enter the premises if he gets the consent of the Minister &mdash;that is, the Minister for External Affairs&mdash;but in no other case.</P>
      <P>To be brief&mdash;I think we discussed this matter before&mdash;if we are going to ratify the American Convention, this clause is necessary.  I believe we should put ourselves into the position that we can ratify the Convention and carry out its terms.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>May I draw the attention of the Senator to a matter of procedure?  The question which I have put on the section is: &ldquo;That the section, or the section as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;  The Senator <Col N="651" /> shall, therefore, proceed with amendment No. 3 on which the question will be: &ldquo;That the amendment be agreed to&rdquo;.  That, of course, will be followed then by the general question, on the section which I have indicated. Perhaps the Senator will now proceed with the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order. In the event of amendment No. 3 being carried, the question then will be: &ldquo;That the section, as amended, stand.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>To make matters easier, I will not press amendment No. 2.  I move amendment No. 3:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (2) to add a new paragraph as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(d) An under-sheriff or county registrar for the purpose of levying execution for moneys payable by a consular officer or consular employee, under an order, judgment or decree of the courts of justice made in a civil action arising out of a contract concluded by such officer or employee in which he did not expressly contract as agent for his Government.</P>
      <P>The Minister, before he sat down, told us that everything would be all right in the long run because the Minister had the power to give his consent to the entry and that, therefore, that should end the matter.  I suggest now that the Minister, in his own interest and in the interests of his Department, should not come into this at all.  Where a judgment of a court is obtained against a consul, the county registrar or the under-sheriff&mdash;the person authorised by statute to execute that judgment against the consul&mdash;should have power to enter anywhere&mdash;the consulate, within the meaning of the Act, or any premises where the consul is at business or resides, in order to give effect to the judgment of the courts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Once a decree has been obtained against such a person the whole position alters.  He is the subject of <Col N="652" /> a court order and there should be no question of his endeavouring to evade payment of the amount due on foot of that order.  It might be that a person in the position of a consul might feel tempted&mdash;with a view to claiming privilege for his goods&mdash;to remove his goods from his residence, say, to the consulate where he would be protected against seizure by this section.  I do not say that that is very likely to happen but I think there is the risk that a person with the rank of consul, against whom proceedings were instituted and against whom a judgment was made, might be tempted to remove his goods from his residence to the consulate and, once they were in the consulate, under the section as it is here, the consulate would be privileged from entry and the under-sheriff or the county registrar would be unable to levy the amount of the judgment.</P>
    <P>The Minister will say: &ldquo;That is quite all right.  I can step in and give my consent.&rdquo;  Why should we have to go to a Minister if we have got an order of a competent court?  Why should we again have to go through proceedings with a view to having the judgment enforced?  I think the amendment is reasonable and it has been drafted with a view to meeting what might be objectionable to the Minister.  Therefore, I think it should be accepted.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelHartnett" hpid="Mr. Hartnett Mr. Hartnett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hartnett</NameTxt>
      <P>If a consular officer were to do what Senator P.F. O'Reilly has described, if he were to remove his private goods into the premises of the consulate, surely the Minister would, in a case like that, bring the matter to the notice of his Government?  I think this matter is being discussed as if consular officers were not the employees of foreign Governments.  They are, and, in the light of common sense, it must be looked at in this way.  If a consular officer proceeds to behave in a manner which is flagrantly dishonest, and if he tries to evade his responsibilities, the citizens who suffer as a result of his actions could, I think, rely on the Minister to take appropriate action.  To suggest that a county registrar or an under-sheriff should have the right to enter consular <Col N="653" /> premises to levy on foot of an execution order is going very far.  If we were to enact such a provision, it could be regarded as an insult to persons appointed by foreign Governments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that the answer which has just been given is the correct one to Senator P.F. O'Reilly and I have very little to add to it. Senator Hartnett pointed out that if a consul were to behave in this fashion he would be behaving dishonestly and would not be a fit and proper person to represent his country here.</P>
      <P>The question of diplomatic immunity &mdash;and we are talking now about what is the normal diplomatic immunity in relation to consuls in the course of their activities as consuls&mdash;has a very long background.  I think that, even without any Act of the Oireachtas on our part, we would be bound, in accordance with the terms of the Constitution, to extend to diplomats their full immunities and privileges and to consular officers their limited protection.  It is laid down there that we will act in these matters in accordance with international law.  This Bill is merely spelling out what is the ordinary accepted international law and practice in regard to officers coming from other countries such as the type of officer in the consular offices we are discussing here to-night.</P>
      <P>Perhaps Senator P.F. O'Reilly would look up a reference that I have got here in the British Year Book of International Law, 1929.  There is a report on an English case&mdash;Engelke v. Musmann&mdash;which was decided by the House of Lords in 1928.  This case was reported on by Sir Cecil Hurst and he had this to say:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;The question of the right of a particular individual to diplomatic status is thus now to be included among those on which the decision rests with the Executive Government and not with the courts, just as it does on the question whether a particular Government is to be recognised as the Government of the country where it is established.  A moment's consideration will show that there are advantages in allowing <Col N="654" /> the decision on the point to rest with the executive authorities.  The existence of diplomatic privileges may always lead to abuse.  With the growth in the numbers of the <i>corps diplomatique</i> in a capital such as London or Paris, questions must arise from time to time requiring tactful handling, if trouble is to be avoided.  On the one side there is the representative of a foreign State, jealous of any encroachment on the liberty of himself and his colleagues to carry out their mission.  On the other, a Government responsible for seeing that its nationals are not prejudiced by any abuse of these privileges. It is clearly better that the discussions which may be necessary before the question at issue in connection with some particular diplomatist can be adjusted should take place in the tranquillity of a Government office rather than in the publicity of a law court.  If this is so, however, it is necessary that the solution which is reached between the foreign representative concerned and the official with whom the case is discussed should prevail.  The head of the foreign mission could scarcely be expected to discuss the question with a representative of the Executive Government, if the solution arrived at were liable to be reopened in the courts.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That may cover slightly more than the point raised by Senator O'Reilly, but it does emphasise that the method of approach to the settlement of difficulties with diplomats or with consular officers who have a limited protection is different from that which the State adopts in the case of its citizens, or of ordinary individuals coming from other countries who have not got diplomatic immunity or privilege.</P>
    <P>It has been recognised in all countries that, when a diplomat is accredited from abroad to another country, that country must protect him in his immunities and privileges.  If he abuses them in regard to his treatment of a member of the community among whom he goes to reside, the remedy is not to the courts, or even to Parliament, but to the Minister for External Affairs, who is in charge of <Col N="655" /> the Department in contact with these officers.  In some countries &mdash; indeed, in most countries &mdash; they go so far as even to prevent discussion of such matters in either House of Parliament.  We here will have to recognise that if we want our consuls to get the immunities and privileges abroad that will enable them to work effectively on behalf of our people, we will have to give reciprocal rights and privileges to the representatives of these countries while they live amongst us.  It is necessary that we should have our consuls abroad, and it is necessary that other countries should have consuls here, in order that they may develop trade and give assistance to their nationals in promoting the purchase and sale of goods in this part of the country.  Senator O'Reilly may rest assured that, if this section is left alone, there will be no reasonable cause of complaint.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to know what the Minister would do if he were informed, this section being law, that a consul against whom there was a judgement had removed his goods to the consulate and thereby obtained protection from the sheriff.  Would he give consent to the entry?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I would consider the case very carefully.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>That would not give very much satisfaction.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 6 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 7.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We will deal with amendment No. 4 when amendment No. 5 has been disposed of.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 5: &mdash;</P>
      <P>To add a new sub-section as follows : &mdash;</P>
      <P>(5)  This section shall not exempt a consular officer or consular employee from any liability for any claim for damages for negligence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>By virtue of this section, neither a consular officer nor a consular employee will be liable in proceedings of any kind to any person in respect of <Col N="656" /> acts performed by him in his official capacity, these acts falling within the functions of a consular official in international law unless his Government requests or assents to the proceedings. One of the effects of the section, in my submission, would be that, if a consular officer, driving from his office in the course of his official business to meet the Minister for External Affairs, were involved in an accident and injured a person, that person could not successfully institute proceedings against the consular officer.  The same would apply in the case of a chauffeur, if a chauffeur, instead of a consular officer, were driving the car.  If I am right in that, and I think I am, a serious position will have been created.  You will then have the position that a person who suffered injury as a result of the negligent driving of a motor car by a consular officer or consular employee, driving in the course of his business, will be penalised to the extent that he will be unable to recover any damages from the employee or the official, unless the appropriate Government requests or assents to the proceedings. The latter, I should say, is extremely unlikely.</P>
    <P>We were told by Senator Hartnett a moment ago that we did not seem to know what we were talking about, that we should know that Governments see that their consular employees and their consuls act properly.  I do not know whether they do or not, but, no matter how well intentioned Governments may be, a consular employee or a consul may perhaps do something that would not meet with the approval of a Government.</P>
    <P>These things having been done, I do not know if Governments would give their consents to proceedings against the consuls.  Many years ago in this country a person in a higher post than that of consul pleaded, in respect of a road traffic accident, his diplomatic immunity.  By virtue of that plea the person who was injured in the motor accident was unable to take any proceedings against that person. His Government, despite what Senator Hartnett told us, did not seem unduly concerned about the plight of our <Col N="657" /> citizen.  It was only when that person left the country in the ordinary way and his immunity lifted in so far as his insurance company was concerned that the person who was injured was able to take any steps to contest the claim.</P>
    <P>Even when the gentleman had left and when the person injured brought the proceedings the insurance company which then contested the proceedings sought, if you please, to continue to establish that the immunity of the person concerned continued.  However, the courts held otherwise and the person's claim was met.  I mention that to show to the House that instead of what Senator Hartnett suggested being the case it would appear that Governments, Ministers or consuls would not be unduly alarmed or concerned over a case of that kind.</P>
    <P>I would say, of course, that in the case of gross misconduct a Government might be very worried and would take steps to deal with it but I am not satisfied that the position is, as Senator Hartnett indicated, that we should not have any worry whatever, that immediately a consular employee or a consul does anything that is not quite right his Government will step in and assist us in every way possible. I think that is just plain unadulterated baloney.</P>
    <P>There is no reason whatever why we should give to consuls and, if you please, consular employees, the privilege that an Ambassador has.  I must be quite clear &mdash; the privilege whilst they are engaged on consular work.  I do not see why we should give them the privilege which would enable them to say, despite their recklessness, they should not be made amenable for any act which they did in the course of their duty.</P>
    <P>I have no doubt that the Minister will tell us that really there is not very much reason to worry for the reason Senator Hartnett gave us and also for the reason that we have a Road Traffic Act, 1933, which obliges most motorists &mdash; I think, perhaps, that diplomats would be outside the Act and that they would not be obliged to insure &mdash; to insure and that, therefore, third parties would be covered against accidents such as I mention.  Then, we <Col N="658" /> may be told that all these people will explain quite clearly to us that they are going to insure their motor vehicles and, therefore, we should have no difficulty.  Very well, but suppose an insurance company says: &ldquo;If the consul does not rely on his privilege I think we will do it,&rdquo; it may then mean that we will have to have another Act to see that other people do not plead privilege of this kind. No.  Let the immunity that obtains for Ministers and people of that status by all means prevail, but why in a case of this kind should we extend it to consuls?</P>
    <P>Certainly let us preserve the archives of the consuls as we have provided already but I do not see why we should go out of our way merely, apparently, to give our own consuls the same rights abroad, to give this privilege to consuls in this country, and I should be amazed to learn that consuls here have asked for this privilege.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps, I might shorten the discussion if I pointed out that the consular convention between Ireland and the United States, signed in Dublin on 1st May, 1950, provides in Article 11, sub-section 5 that all motor vehicles owned by the sending State or used by the consul or owned by the consular officer or employee must be adequately insured by policies against third party risks.  Therefore, a large part of the speech which Senator O'Reilly has just delivered has no relevance to this particular Bill.  Under this Bill, we are giving not full diplomatic immunities and privileges to consular officers but certain immunities and privileges covering them in the course of their official duties.  One of the things excluded from the ordinary run of diplomatic privileges is this right to insist that they will be covered by third party insurance, that they will insure against third party risks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>Supposing somebody forgot to renew his insurance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Suppose an ordinary Irish citizen who was not worth anything except the old car he was driving forgot to renew his insurance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="659" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a real possibility. It has happened.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I know.  The provision in the agreement between ourselves and the United States, which we propose to ratify and which we are placing ourselves in a position to ratify and carry out our undertakings, is that any United States consul or consular employee here will insure himself against third party risks.  We are granting him the right to stay here and perform his functions on that basis.  The same thing will apply to an Irish consul operating in America.  He must insure against third party risks.</P>
      <P>A lot of what the Senator said, even in regard to full diplomats, is out-of-date. The Senator was talking about some case, as far as I can identify it, which occurred, perhaps, 14 years ago. I am informed that the difficulty arose not on the part of the diplomat but on the part of the insurance company. The insurance company, although it had undertaken to insure the gentleman against third party risks, wanted to slide out of its commitments because he could plead diplomatic immunity. Nine years ago, the Department of External Affairs, on the instructions of the then Minister for External Affairs, had conversations with all these insurance companies.</P>
      <P>I have a long list here of insurance companies which agreed to write into the certificate of insurance with the insured diplomat that they would not compel him to raise his diplomatic immunity in the case of an accident involving an injury to a third party.  The insurance companies have agreed that all diplomats here will have the right to have this clause inserted in their policy: &ldquo;Notwithstanding that the insured is or may be entitled under the privileges accorded to the Diplomatic Corps to refuse to submit to the jurisdiction of the courts in connection with any claim against him, it is hereby declared and agreed that the company will not call on the insured so to refuse.&rdquo;  I understand that the difficulty in the case referred to by Senator O'Reilly arose because the insurance company insisted that the diplomat concerned should raise this difficulty, but that case is about 14 years old.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="660" /> In relation to the section as a whole, I want to point out that it is needed in order to enable us to carry out clause 11 of the consular agreement we made with the United States.  We do not propose to give any foreign officials here any more immunity than our officials get in the country from which they come.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>I fully agree with the idea of implementing the terms of this consular agreement, but I think what is worrying Senator O'Reilly is that there should be some safeguard for citizens when they suffer damage or loss.  It has not been made clear at any stage by the Minister, nor is it made clear in this Bill, what happens in the case of a citizen who suffers loss, perhaps very great loss, as a result of this consular immunity we are giving.</P>
      <P>I understand &mdash; and I would like the Minister to tell us whether it is right or not &mdash; that the Minister, in fact, has some powers to compensate citizens if they suffer loss or damage through any consular or diplomatic personnel claiming immunity.  I think that is what is worrying us.  If there was some existing way whereby a citizen could be compensated for loss sustained, then there would not be any need for any of these amendments, and this measure would be accepted quite freely by everybody.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to ask the Minister if the convention to which he refers as being agreed upon between America and Ireland has been implemented by any other Government.  We are not speaking here about American consuls alone; we are speaking about consuls generally, and the reason we desire some clarification of the position is that consular or diplomatic immunity has been claimed and Irish people have suffered as a result.  We think there should be some provision in order to ensure that no Irish citizen would suffer because a foreign consul failed to face up to his responsibilities. Would the Minister tell us if Section 11 has been implemented by any other Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid in following Senator O'Reilly into the broader question of diplomatic privilege, I <Col N="661" /> failed to impress on the Seanad sufficiently that in this particular case we are dealing with consuls.  This Bill refers only to consuls and in that connection all motor vehicles, marine vessels and aircraft owned by the sending State and used by the consul or by a consular officer or employee will be adequately insured by policies against third party risks.  Therefore, apart altogether from the general question of what immunities and privileges consular officers will have here, they will not have the privilege of not insuring their motor vehicle, marine vessel or aircraft against third party risks, and so, citizens will be fully covered.  I feel that consular officers coming here will live up to the instructions which they will receive from the United States Government, that is, to act within the powers and functions which are conferred upon them by the United States and that they will act in accordance with the agreement which the United States has made with this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.F. O'Reilly Mr. P.F. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.F. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask the Minister what can be done supposing, through inadvertence, a vehicle has not been insured?  That is more than a mere possibility and I would ask the Minister to tell us what course he could advise a citizen to take in the case of a consul who did not observe the terms of that convention.  I would also ask him if he is perfectly satisfied that the proviso inserted by the insurance company in the third party policy would be valid to prevent the company from raising in a court of law the point that the insured person was entitled to privilege and therefore could not be sued.  I am not satisfied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to follow the Senator into the general question again.  When the clause which I read out was written into the policy and agreed to by an insurance company of standing, I do not think it would be departed from.  I believe the insurance company would live up to it and the diplomat concerned having insured himself against third party risks, would not be likely to raise a plea of diplomatic immunity and the insurance company could not force him to <Col N="662" /> do it.  He is covered by the terms of that clause written into the policy.</P>
      <P>On the question as to what will be done in relation to consuls &mdash; and it is consuls we are speaking about in this Bill &mdash; I would point out that the agreement between ourselves and the United States Government is that consuls will insure all their vehicles, boats and aircraft against third party risk.  If a consul did not take steps so to insure, he would be breaking the agreement and he would be committing an offence for which he would be held accountable by his own Government.  I am certain it was not for fun that the United States or that we in this country asked that this should be written into the convention.  I am sure that both sides will live up to it. The consuls employed by both sides will have it in their book of instructions that immediately they open up an office they are to insure their vehicles and any other type of craft that they use.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the position of other countries?  In this Bill the Unites States is not mentioned specifically.  Are there other countries with which we have consular conventions? If not, what effect has this Bill upon them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>The whole Bill gives the Government power to conclude a consular convention with any country provided that country gives us reciprocal immunities and privileges. The American agreement is the only one outstanding at the moment.  As soon as this Bill is through, the convention will be brought forward in the usual way for ratification.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>In the few words I said, I asked the Minister if any powers exist under which he may pay compensation to people suffering loss through negligence other than by boats, cars and aeroplanes, which are specifically dealt with.  Are there not other forms of negligence?  Has the Minister power to give compensation to a citizen in such cases?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="663" />
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>That was one of the things which would come in on this section, even on the amendment.  I feel there should be some provision in the Bill for the Minister to do such a thing.  Unfortunately, this House has not the power to frame amendments which are of a money nature, but I would like to get the point in on this stage.  Perhaps it can be arranged by the Minister himself to provide for that contingency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already made it clear that I am in favour of the Bill, that I do not want to alter it, and particularly that I do not want to do anything that would prevent the ratification of a convention.  I have been asked by several people outside &mdash; it may be due to the discussions here or elsewhere &mdash; exactly what would happen in certain imaginary cases.  I am sure that if I were Minister I would decline to answer as to what I would do in a set of circumstances which did not immediately arise. However, there are certain principles which apply to any Minister for External Affairs.  I take it that the present Government policy would be in any new convention to insist on similar provisions with regard to motor-cars, and so on.  That is quite clear from his speech and we must assume that that is so.  On the assumption that the Government of the day will act in good faith in matters of this kind we have to give them these powers, and I am sure there is no way out of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is one matter on which the Minister was not as clear as I think desirable.  Apart altogether from strict legal powers which the Minister may have, it seems to me that when we as a State give certain privileges to diplomatic or consular representatives which could under conceivable circumstances injure our own citizens&mdash;now-adays it is a very rare occurrence indeed &mdash; it is a specific duty of the Minister for External Affairs to do everything in his power to reduce the loss to the Irish citizen and to give every assistance which he may be able to give, having regard to the circumstances at the time.  I would go further <Col N="664" /> and say that if there were a case in which the amount involved was serious it would be the duty of the Oireachtas to step in, because of the privilege we have given.  However, that is no reason why we should not give the privilege and make consular conventions. It should go out that we would expect the Government of the day to take that particular citizen under its wing because of the circumstances and because State action had deprived him of certain rights.  The State should do everything in its power to see that if the rights could not be given the person concerned would get some compensation or assistance.  That was not quite clear from the Minister's speech. I think it should be his policy and the policy of the Government.</P>
    <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    <P>Amendment No. 4 not moved.</P>
    <P>Section 7 agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 8 to 13, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I should have informed the House earlier that amendments Nos. 6 and 7 in the names of Senators O'Donnell and McQuire, respectively, have been ruled out of order.  Intimation to that effect was conveyed earlier to the Senators concerned.</P>
      <P>Sections 14 and 15 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take the remaining stages now.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Local Government (Temporary Reduction of Valuation)" RHead="Bill, 1953&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Local Government (Temporary Reduction of Valuation) Bill, 1953&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 and 2 put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 3</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>When the Bill was before us on Second Stage Senator Stanford asked a question which, completely out of order, he put to me. <Col N="665" /> I ventured to answer it by giving what I thought was the position, namely, that all private houses came within the scope of the Bill unless they were already receiving similar privileges and the Minister said that was correct. In general terms I still think that is correct but I have been asked several questions outside the House to which I was not able to give specific answers. I take this opportunity of asking the Minister for some explanation of the provisions of this section.</P>
      <P>There is one matter which puzzles me.  It is paragraph (e) of sub-section (3).  It provides that this part of the Act shall be deemed not to apply in the case of the enlargement or improvement of a building ... where the enlargement or improvement results from carrying out a work of trivial nature of alteration, extension, repair or renewal.  That puzzles me because, if it is so trivial, the value should not be increased and, if the value is increased, it cannot be trivial. That requires some explanation because it would be quite absurd that persons who decide to give employment&mdash;that is the object of the Bill&mdash; by extending their private houses should run the risk of its being declared to be trivial.  There is an appeal on the question of triviality but, as it stands, at the risk of making a pun, it seems to me that the paragraph is trivial.  There is something that requires an explanation or possibly something that might be amended.</P>
      <P>I have been asked another question to which I do not know the answer.  It is pretty clear to me that if a house has been built and is under the period of reduction of rates, and it is then extended, it will not get the benefit of this Bill, although I am not quite sure whether it will or not as far as the extension is concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Minister for Local Government (Mr. Smith) Patrick Smith">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government (Mr. Smith)</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not get the second point the Senator made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Assuming a private house has been built, and it is within the seven years' period in which the rates payable are on one-third of the valuation, and if that house has been in existence some three or four years <Col N="666" /> and the owner now has a larger family and wants to add a room or two, and the valuation is increased: will that house get a reduction on the increased valuation although it has already got the benefit of a reduction on the original valuation?  I am sorry if I am not making myself perfectly clear but it is not very simple.  This question has been put to me.  I am not criticising the Bill.  I am merely trying to help people who may have to operate under it</P>
      <P>I was asked another question.  If a house is of what we call the grant type and was built two or three years ago and received a State grant because it was within the requisite size, etc., and if that house is enlarged now by the addition of a couple of rooms, is there anything in the reference in paragraph (c) to prevent that house from getting the benefit of this Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be from the previous limitation of 1,250 square feet to 1,400 square feet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Whichever the exemption was.  If, for the sake of argument, I went out to-morrow and bought a house which had been a grant house, I would not get any benefit; I would pay the value of the house.  If I felt I wanted a larger house, and wanted to extend, would I get the benefit under this Bill?  It seems to me that it is desirable that in that case there should be a benefit because, as far as private houses are concerned, it is most likely that the kind of additional building which, in present circumstances, you will persuade the private individual to do is the extension of a house which has become too small for his family.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The whole object of this Bill is to increase building during the next two or three years.  I am not sure of what happens in the cases which I have mentioned but I would suggest that almost the only way in which the private individual, as distinct from a businessman, is likely to spend money is in putting a couple of rooms on to his house that has grown too small for his family.  It would be a serious mistake if that is not included.  I am not saying that it is not included.  I have looked up some of the Acts and <Col N="667" /> it is by no means clear.  I thought it best to ask the Minister to make the matter clearer than it is to me.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I dealt with the first point made by the Senator in the short speech which I made here on Second Reading.  I may not have dealt with that point as clearly as I should have, but it was not raised as clearly as it has been raised now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I was replying to Senator McCrea who seemed to misunderstand this particular provision. I explained the position where reasonably substantial improvements have been effected.  Senator Douglas has referred to the term &ldquo;trivial.&rdquo;  The reason for that is it is recognised that a good deal of improvements have been carried out over the years, say, for the last 20 years, of which the Valuation Office had no notice.  One of the difficulties that people experienced recently was that if they carried out improvements, not only would the improvements that they carried out recently be taken into account, but they would bring to the notice of the Valuation Office work that had been done over an extended period.  If the owner of those premises were to get relief only in respect of the improvements which he had carried out recently he would be discouraged from doing such work for fear the wider field would be covered in the event of a visit being paid to him from the Valuation Office.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It was thought desirable that such people should be encouraged to carry out work now and that they should be given some assurance that if they did so, any work they had done over a period would also be included, provided the work they do now is not trivial.  In other words, if, say, I had been extending my premises for a period of 20 years and it so happened, as it often does, that the Valuation Office had not been aware of these extensions and improvements, and suppose I carried out a minor alteration, that I took advantage of a measure of this kind to get <Col N="668" /> seven years' relief and to get coverage for all that I had done and which had escaped attention for the last 20 years, the term &ldquo;trivial&rdquo; is inserted to ensure that there will be no escape in that manner.  The Commissioner of Valuation will have to be satisfied that the improvements are not trivial.  If he decides that they are trivial, and the owner thinks they are not trivial, then, of course, the owner has the right of appeal in the ordinary way.  The intention in framing the sub-section in this way was to ensure that the considerable advantage here would be given to the type of person I have described and would not be abused by people who would carry out very little improvement in fact.</P>
    <P>The next point made by the Senator was in relation to a house which was already erected, which had obtained rate relief, and which was in the middle of the period, say, of seven years.  His query was whether, when the period was about half way through, if the owner proceeded to provide an extension, he would be entitled&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>And within the time required in this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  The question was whether such a person would be entitled to the relief here.  The owner of a premises &mdash; whether they were premises erected with the assistance of a State grant or otherwise &mdash; would be entitled to relief under this Bill unless relief was already provided under the Housing Acts themselves.  I think that covers the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>The Housing Acts may be quite simple to the Minister but, frankly, I have not that intimate knowledge of them and likewise most of the public.  On the trivial question: the Minister virtually admits that a valuation increase may take place by virtue of the fact that a person now does something of a trivial nature.  I am quite well aware of the fact that if you lodge plans and do not do anything you may find that your valuation is increased.  I know cases in point.  I know of a lady residing in Dublin who wanted to add a <Col N="669" /> garage to her house.  She got an estimate.  Plans were lodged, although she did not know anything about it. Then she found that she could not afford to have the work carried out. Nevertheless, although no work was carried out, the house was revalued up to £40.  I am told that that is within the valuation laws, as they stand, and I am not blaming the Minister for it but obviously it is a matter which requires changing though I realise that it cannot be done under this Bill.  There seems to be the suggestion that somebody can go to the Valuation Office now and say: &ldquo;I carried out a lot of improvements before and you never spotted them.  I never told you about them and I never got an increase.  Put on the increase now so that I can get the benefit&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>If that is not the case then I cannot see the trivial point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not easy to explain this.  I have seen cases myself in recent years where, say, a businessman carried out certain improvements to his premises.  He might have changed the whole front of the premises, put in a new window, made it much more modern than it had been and altered the whole structure internally.  The Valuation Office came to know of these alterations &mdash; surely without any effort on his part.  A duty is imposed upon the rate collector to keep the Valuation Office, and his authorities, informed of these matters if he gets to know about them.  Whatever way the Valuation Office came to know of these improvements, they came to have a look at them.  In the course of their investigation they not only vetted the immediate improvements that the man had carried out but they also vetted his whole premises.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>They often do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I am citing a case of which I have personal knowledge. They went into the back yard and they found that he had erected new stores there and that the whole place was completely transformed from the hereditament that had been valued at <Col N="670" /> the time the original valuation was imposed.  The law entitled them to have regard to all the improvements that had been effected on that place since it was originally valued.  It was a terrific shock to the owner, who would probably understand if his recent effort was the subject of their attention, to have them go over this whole field that he thought was past and done with.</P>
      <P>Now, we were aware of this and, in framing this Bill, we said to ourselves that there are probably thousands of such cases in this country &mdash; cases of people who had carried out a considerable amount of improvement to their premises and who would say: &ldquo;Where is the use in introducing proposals that would give us partial relief of rates for seven years on any building that we may decide to erect, or the erection of which we may start after the 27th of July, because even if we get relief in respect of that building or improvement the valuer will look at what we have done in the past 20 years?  He will include that and then we will have to pay the full amount on these extensions.&rdquo; We were conscious that if the Bill, when it became an Act, were to leave a position like that it would result in such people saying: &ldquo;It is all right as far as it goes but it would not be worth taking a chance on.&rdquo; Therefore, we provided that if the owner of the premises carries out reasonable improvements he will get this advantage &mdash; if he carries out a reasonable extension, if it is not trivial, if it is not a matter of painting a door or putting in a few new windows and painting them and saying: &ldquo;I will do this simple work in order to get relief in respect of work which I have done in the course of the past 20 years.&rdquo;  He might say: &ldquo;I have escaped their attention for a long time and I may be caught.&rdquo;  As the Senator said, the valuation officers can arrive at his premises, or mine, and if you left the door open it would be a temptation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Suppose I had a premises that had been extended over 20 or 25 years ago, and that I knew that the valuation was <Col N="671" /> an old valuation, and that I saw a Bill like this being introduced and becoming an Act whereby, if I carried out any minor improvements, I could get relief for seven years on work which was done over 20 years ago, I might do that minor work and get the relief. Therefore, we stipulated that the person who is to get an advantage must carry out what is regarded by the Commissioners of Valuation as a reasonably substantial alteration or improvement, and in that event, he will get relief in respect of work that has escaped attention for a very long period.  It is not easy to bring that home as clearly as one would like to, but I think it is sensible enough.</P>
    <P>As to the Housing Acts, I would not expect the Senator or any member of this House, or of the other House, or even myself, to know all the provisions of these Acts.  There are limitations in the Housing Acts&mdash;valuation limitations, floor space limitations and a number of other limitations which affect the issue whether or not a grant will be paid and which, if a grant is not paid, will affect the issue as to whether rate relief as provided in the Housing Acts will be given &mdash; and is it not fair enough for me to say that, so far as this Bill, when it becomes an Act, is concerned, any case of the kind cited by the Senator will be entitled to rate relief as provided for in this Bill unless it is provided already in the Housing Acts?  In other words, if the extension, or extensions, which the Senator has cited do not come within any of the Housing Acts for grant purposes, be it a reconstruction grant or a new house grant, they will not get the rate relief provided in those Acts, but they will get relief under this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it be possible for the ordinary person with a small sized house to find out authoritatively in some office or place, by submitting plans, whether or not he came within the Act and was entitled to rate relief? I am particularly anxious to encourage what I call small building and it could be encouraged very considerably, because people have spoken to me about their position if they add a couple of rooms to their houses and I have had <Col N="672" /> to say that I could not tell them as I did not know all the circumstances. My whole object is to encourage building and I think it would be a good thing if there was some official who was prepared to deal with it and could deal with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>He does not require that information in this sense, that he must get rate relief under some head.  He does not have to submit plans to any official or department to find out whether he is entitled to rate relief or not.  He must get it one way or the other.  If he does not get it under the Housing Acts, he must get it under this Bill when it becomes an Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>That is exactly what I wanted and I think it is rather important.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps I could give an example which might help the Senator.  A house to which a room may be added under certain provisions of the 1946 Act in relation to the prevention of T.B. is already covered, whether the room was built within the period prescribed in the Bill or not, but, in the case of a similar house next door, the owner of which decides to build exactly the same addition, but not under the 1946 Act, it will benefit under this legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister's last statement is exactly what I wanted.  I think it should be given publicity and I hope it will get it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I can put it in a few words to make it clearer.  This Bill is designed to gather up every extension and improvement and to give rate relief in respect of it which is not covered by any existing law.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 4.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 4 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Sub-section (1) refers to &ldquo;where the erection, enlargement or improvement of a building is begun and completed during the prescribed <Col N="673" /> period.&rdquo;  Might I ask if he would see his way to extend the period, because people who improved their premises during the past five or six years, or even ten years, and who will now come under the notice of the Valuation Office will be rated on the 1954 valuation, although they built the addition in 1944, which will be a very much higher figure than it would have been ten years ago.  These people will have to pay a very heavy fine for their initiative in improving their premises.  I believe that the commissioners are bound, when valuing, to have regard to the general level of valuations in the area, but my own experience is that that is not interpreted in favour of the person whose premises are valued.  The benefit of it is given to the Commissioners of Valuation rather than to the person whose premises are valued or revised.</P>
      <P>I did contemplate putting down an amendment asking that the commissioners should have regard to the general level of valuations, when valuing, and I was told that it was covered in the Valuation Act.  My own experience as a member of a public body is that, where a revision takes place, the benefits of that section in the Valuation Acts are not given in the way they ought to be to the person whose premises are valued or revised. This whole matter of valuations is of great public importance and the Bill is an effort to deal with the situation as it arises at the moment.  I should be glad if the Minister could give me some information on the point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not very clear as to what the Senator means.  Is it his suggestion that a man who has from time to time over a period of 25 years made alterations to his premises&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Not even as long as that &mdash; ten years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us say ten years. Assuming he made some of these improvements ten years ago, if they had been valued at the time, the valuation would be lower.  Is it the suggestion that some provision should be made now to ensure that, in bringing them into the net, the valuation to be placed <Col N="674" /> on them now should be the valuation that would have been placed on them then?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>No, but maybe he could be given the same consideration as is being given to anyone else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>Provided he pays the arrears.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>In that regard, the Senator is setting a problem.  Is the whole difficulty of this Bill not the question of extensions carried out over a period?  Would it not be impossible to determine just when these extensions were carried out and would the time at which they were carried out not have a tremendous bearing on the point made by the Senator?  Briefly, I think the Senator's suggestion is looking for too much perfection.  If I have extended my premises over a period of 20 years and have escaped the attention of the Valuation Office, it means that I have had ten, 15 or 20 years of freedom. If all that has now been legalised and I am going to get complete security in respect of two-thirds of any increase now being placed on me for seven years, I think I am not doing too badly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>If a person comes under the notice of the Valuation Office for some improvement done before the 27th June, 1953, he gets no immunity and will be valued at a 1954 valuation, and he will not get any immunity under the Act.  I think this whole valuation business is so complex and difficult that it might be better if I did not go further with this point.  I was going to ask the Minister on the Final Stage of the Bill if he would have the whole situation examined.</P>
      <P>The Minister is covering building during a certain period, and in that way he is giving certain reliefs and doing justice to people where anomalies and injustices would arise.  I do not want to press the point because, by doing so, I might make the debate too wide and come under the notice of the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>The reason I was interested in the point was because that case was not made at all in the <Col N="675" /> other House.  I found difficulty in understanding it, because my own approach would be along different lines from the case made by the Senator. My own approach would be like this. In the case of owners of premises who had escaped the view of the Valuation Office for so long, irrespective of when they carried out these improvements, and even if they took no advantage of this measure which we are now discussing, the Valuation Office could, at any time, arrive down on their premises and increase the valuation in respect of these improvements.</P>
      <P>They would have to pay on the full valuation while, in this measure, we are providing that if they add a reasonable addition to their premises they can have a further relief in respect of the valuation over all the improvement for a period of seven years.  I think, myself, that such an owner of property could regard himself as doing very well &mdash;in fact, doing excellently.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope people will not get the idea that all sorts of people have been escaping the Valuation Office in Dublin.  I should like to meet them. Country people seem to talk in a different language.  I think, possibly, the position is not the same somewhere else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator wants to ward off this from the city.  I can tell the Senator that, in my limited experience, it happens both in town and country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly it is not as extensive as far as Dublin is concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnJosephMeighan" hpid="Mr. Meighan Mr. Meighan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meighan</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask the Minister what is the position in regard to people who carried out improvements during the last nine or ten years and who were brought within the net immediately after the improvements were made and rated, and who now propose to carry out further improvements? Will they get relief on what they have done during the past number of years?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="676" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanRuane" hpid="Mr. S.T. Ruane Mr. S.T. Ruane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S.T. Ruane</NameTxt>
      <P>So far as licensed premises are concerned, and where improvements have been done within the specified period which would warrant a reduction in the valuation, would that valuation operate so far as a reduction in the spirit licence is concerned?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Only on the rates.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 5 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 6 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not in the House on the last occasion when the Bill was before it.  I happen to be associated with Buncrana industrially, the town to which this particular section applies.  I know that the inhabitants of that town are very grateful to the Minister for the inclusion of this section in the Bill.  There was near chaos in Buncrana some time ago when the new valuations were disclosed.</P>
      <P>This is probably the most promising industrial town in Ireland.  It is situated near Inishowen in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht itself.  The work done there is of great importance and any action that might adversely affect industrial development there would have very serious reactions on the language movement.  I should like to take the opportunity of thanking the Minister on behalf of all those interested in industry in Buncrana for the inclusion of this important section in the Bill. I should be very glad if the Minister would explain the reason for the ten years' period before the new valuation is imposed.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 7 and 8, the Title, and Schedule agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take the remaining stages now.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="677" />
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like briefly to ask the Minister if he could tell us when he proposes to bring in a comprehensive measure to deal with the Valuation Acts.  The Valuation Acts under which we are working in this country are the old&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that that has nothing to do with the Bill before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>The Valuation Acts are now over 100 years old.  They were based on the value of commodities at that time.  The valuations in rural Ireland particularly in regard to land are static.  The valuations in towns and cities and even those in regard to improvements on farms are not static and are allowed to increase.  With the general devaluation of money over the years, we will arrive at a situation where you will have virtual derating in one section and a whole new system of valuations being done in a piecemeal way in the towns.  Whatever we are going to value we will have to have some standard to go on.  Mr. McGilligan, when he was Minister for Finance, said to me in this House about six months before he went out of office that there were problems involved and that he was having them examined.  I presume they are still being examined.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>He is probably examining them still.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask the Minister before he concludes on this Bill to tell us if he does propose to deal with this very important question in a more comprehensive way at some future date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know if the Senator is inviting me to resurrect a revaluation proposal that was presented to the Dáil about 1938 or 1939. That proposal was, I remember, very badly received on all sides at the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I should say it would be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Defended by Fine Gael and the <i>Irish Independent.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="678" />
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no shares in that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I remember listening to all the criticism that was offered to that proposal.  I think it was in the other House that mention was made of this same thing, the desirability of having a re-examination of the whole valuation system.  As I said there, I do not know what Deputies or Senators mean when they refer to an examination of the system unless they suggest that there is an obvious need for an approach to the revaluation of the whole country.  With the experience of how the proposal was received at the time I mentioned, I said I did not think it would be any great encouragement to an individual or a Department to take up the same strings again.  I admit that various people inside this House and outside it would be able to show the tremendous changes that have taken place in the business life and the business activity of the whole countryside and how the passage of time has affected places and premises that were highly valued long ago on the strength of that business.  Nevertheless, having regard to the reception that was given to the proposal on that occasion, I do not think you would be likely to have a similar approach now.</P>
      <P>The Senator mentioned Buncrana. The proposal so far as Buncrana is concerned was an effort on our part to take the town out of a very awkward situation that they themselves, their representatives or members of the council speaking for them had brought them into.  When certain amendments to what was provided here were suggested in the other House I said it was not intended to relieve them for all time because the valuation of every town is increasing progressively.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would be able to show, if it were necessary, how the valuation of Buncrana, Letterkenny, and the other urban centre in Donegal whose name I cannot remember, has been increasing over the years.  It would not, of course, be fair or reasonable that we should clamp down on Buncrana on the basis of the valuation that existed, say, in 1950 when this review took place <Col N="679" /> which increased the valuation from £7,000 odd to £11,000 odd.  Therefore, we had to have regard to what the movement was, to what the annual increase had been in the past and we arrived at a basis of calculation that I think is entirely fair to the town and will result in the valuation of Buncrana reaching the point at which it would have remained if it were not for the provision which is contained here. I can understand how anxious the people of Buncrana were in this regard and I was very glad to have been able to provide some solution for that situation.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Industrial Research and Standards (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1953&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Industrial Research and Standards (Amendment) Bill, 1953&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Bill passed through Committee, reported without amendment, and received for final consideration.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not wish to keep the House very long at this stage, but it is important in a Bill like this to deal with one or two points arising out of what is in the Bill itself and the objects of the Bill.  This measure was welcomed from all sides of the House and any criticisms that were made or any points that arose in debate had no Party flavour of any kind.  Any criticisms that arose were intended to be constructive to enable the Bill to work and to make it a success.  I feel the Minister, when he was replying on the Second Stage of the Bill, gave expression to some ideas which, if they are not answered, might result in this Bill not having the desired effect.  The Minister made it clear that he was very much behind this Bill and said that he would like to see standard marks in much greater use than they are at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A very important factor in the attainment of that object was dismissed very lightly by the Minister. We are supposed to be a vocational House, and I think we are, to a degree, vocational, as most of us have some specialised knowledge in some <Col N="680" /> particular vocation.  It is a little irritating from time to time when a Minister comes in and will not listen to people who have expert knowledge, from dealing with certain things every day, and who know more about them than the Minister does.  I must pay a tribute to the Minister.  He has himself an astonishing general knowledge and shows that knowledge on an astonishing number of occasions and on quite an astonishing number of Bills, but at the same time there are many points in particular vocations with which he is not really expertly conversant.</P>
    <P>If standard marks are to be the success we would like them to be the atmosphere in which these goods are going to be sold is very important. When the Minister was speaking he showed a confusion of thought as between price maintenance and price rings.  I feel that an understanding of this is absolutely essential if this Bill is to be properly carried out.  Too much Government control or the wrong kind of Government control can completely stifle this and prevent people applying for marks.  I would like briefly to explain the difference between price maintenance and price control.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, this is a tolerant House, but the Bill which we are passing has nothing to do with price&mdash;good, bad or indifferent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not saying that. I am showing what price has to do with the Bill, which is a different thing. This Bill is a Standard Marks Bill which we want to work.  It is surely relevant at least to suggest the kind of atmosphere that should prevail if the Bill is to work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>A discussion of that atmosphere would arise more appropriately on the Second Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>May I be permitted to show that what I am saying is relevant and that I am in order in saying it? If there is to be confusion as between price maintenance and price rings, and if people are going to be <Col N="681" /> prevented from having price maintenance agreements in connection with standard marks, this Bill will not work.  Surely that is relevant.  I will be very brief.  The difference between price maintenance and price rings is that in price maintenance you do not eliminate competition.  There is still competition between all the people selling the same goods but having a standard mark; there is competition also between people who have not a standard mark but are still selling the same type of goods.  A price ring is price maintenance in some commodity where there is complete monopoly. That is the difference.  If this Bill we have before us here is going to work the Government must, in its trade regulations, have regard to the difference between price maintenance and price rings.  If that is done I feel that the Bill may have some chance of achieving the success which the Minister said he would like it to achieve.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Circumstances beyond my control prevented my being present for the Second Stage.  I would like to take this opportunity, which I believe is fully in order, to say how much I and others in industry appreciate the work of the institute.  I read through the debates and there were one or two references to the need to make the institute better known to manufacturers. I would like it to go out that there is no need to make it known to manufacturers.  Any manufacturer who has a problem will write to the institute and will get a courteous reply.  He will almost certainly get an examination of the problem and a discussion as to whether it is within the function of the institute to give assistance.  Many manufacturers have already got assistance by way of research in some of their problems. The main object of this Bill is to provide more money for that research and to that extent I think it must be supported by everybody.  We all feel that not only should we maintain industry here but that industry should have a very considerable degree of independence and should endeavour to go out on its own lines, having regard to circumstances and particularly <Col N="682" /> having regard to the use of the natural resources of the country.</P>
      <P>I have given a fair amount of consideration also to the question of standards, which are dealt with in the Bill.  It is hoped that one of the effects of the Bill and the provision of more money will be greater use of standard marks.  I would very much like to see it made pretty clear that, as regards Irish industry generally, the main object of our industrialists is to provide a standard of which we can be universally proud.  That is not obtained solely or even mainly by standard marks.  It will be achieved, I think, by standards set up by manufacturers themselves on which they put their own brands and their own names and which they will stand over, so that if errors occur they will take the goods back and replace them by new goods. Close co-operation between the institute and manufacturers who wish to have their own branded marks, whether or not they coincide with the standards, is a matter which will be of considerable value.</P>
      <P>There has been a good deal of discussion recently on this and the Minister frequently makes references to the need for improving the standard of industry.  I have no faith in improvement of the standard of industry by means of petty interference. I have great faith in it by means of the methods set out in this Bill, which is the exact opposite to that being carried out in other respects of Government policy.  I am not going into the details.  This Bill is essentially based on co-operation between the institute and manufacturers, whether collectively or as individuals. On that standard I see great hopes.  If that is coupled with attempts to make it impossible&mdash;either by means of price or other regulations &mdash;for firms to have their own standards in consultation with the institute, then I see great danger. The principle on which this Bill stands is one which we can unanimously support and we can look forward to it with considerable promise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am very uneasy regarding the other tendency at the moment&mdash;it is <Col N="683" /> not solely a matter of Government, but it is one which we meet in our business&mdash;the tendency to ask for the lowest conceivable price, with hardly any regard to standard.  Certain manufacturers are being pressed to say what is the cheapest thing they can manage to make.  I do not see a future for Irish industry on that basis.  I do see a future on the basis of a high standard. If a small country is ever to make purely price competition the standard of its goods, it is liable to be beaten by big countries where you get big production and where very cheap articles can be produced.  A small country which is proud of its own standard will have a certain number of manufacturers who will be definite about it, that they will not produce anything below a certain standard and that if they are beaten for price for the time being they will submit to that and let someone produce something cheaper.  They will eventually find that they have held on to their reputation.  On those lines I see a future for industry at home and, within certain limits, in the export market. For that reason, particularly on the lines of this Bill, I am in complete sympathy with its policy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish this Bill god-speed and I commend it to industrialists in Ireland.  I commend it particularly to those who manufacture products that are used in the building industry.  As a result of the application of a standard mark to materials like flue liners, glazed sewer pipes, and so on, they can be easily and readily specified as being up to a certain standard.  The whole building trade has at heart the provision of a good article, be it in the form of a house or an extension.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>No one is compelled to produce all his goods at that particular standard. I hope I did not seem too brusque with Senator McGuire in drawing his attention to the fact that price has nothing good, bad or indifferent, to do with the provisions of this Bill.  The standard specifications may have a certain impact on price.  I will quote one example.  Glazed sewer pipes are <Col N="684" /> normally sold to the trade in three qualities&mdash;first, second and third.  The standard mark will now be applied, in accordance with the specification, to what are commonly known as &ldquo;firsts&rdquo; but, in the ordinary course of manufacture, it is utterly impossible to produce 100 per cent. &ldquo;firsts&rdquo; in the case of glazed sewer pipes.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>And most other things.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator anticipated me.  The same applies to most other things.  I quite agree with what the Minister said that no one is compelled to accept this as being the standard, but let it be hoped that the object of manufacturers will be to have as large a proportion as possible of their goods up to the standard that will qualify for the standard mark.  If it was generally accepted that a manufacturer would make use of the facilities given by the institute to have all his goods up to that standard then, undoubtedly, Senator McGuire would be right in stating that there may be a financial impact because of that.  I do not think it could be so to a very great extent.</P>
      <P>Normally, on building work, the architect has the right to have materials tested at the expense of the contractor.  That, naturally, goes on to the price of the completed job.  The position now is that the institute can test these materials on payment of a fee.  Alternatively, they may test without payment of a fee.  The net result should be no increase or a comparatively small increase in the cost of the finished article.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am entirely in agreement with Senator Douglas that the public as a whole should be encouraged to buy the article that has on it the standard mark because they would then be certain that they are getting a first-class article.  I want to make it clear that the standards of which I have particular knowledge are very high standards. The second advantage would be that, if there is a demand for the article that has the standard mark, manufacturers will be encouraged to put their whole endeavour into producing as large a percentage as possible of standard mark articles.  I welcome <Col N="685" /> the Bill and wish it god-speed.  I commend it particularly to the building industry.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>When this Bill was before us on a previous occasion I asked the Minister if any research of importance had taken place recently and the Minister referred me to the report of the institute.  Would it be wrong of me to ask the Parliamentary Secretary if he is aware if any research of importance has taken place recently, particularly in regard to commodities based on native raw materials, and if any results of importance have been achieved?</P>
      <P>We are voting in this Bill a certain sum of money.  I do not think it is enough.  The sum should be greater.</P>
      <P>A particular commodity that was up to a standard was given a standard mark.  In this ever-changing world, values change constantly.  Are there corresponding changes in the qualifications for a standard mark?  To-day a manufacturer may produce an excellent article which is worthy of the standard mark because of its quality. To-morrow new methods of production may be discovered.  Can the Parliamentary Secretary tell us if the institute are on the <i>qui vive</i> in regard to new production methods?</P>
      <P>I deplore the niggardliness of the sum that we are voting for this important aspect of industrial life.  It is necessary to publicise the standard mark so as to create confidence in Irish goods.  Irish manufacturers generally welcome the standard mark.  They have not used it to the extent that I would like it to be used, but they do welcome it because it will give the public a guarantee of excellence and may, to some extent, give a guarantee of price, where price maintenance is associated with a particular article.  The amount of money provided is far too small. Greater expenditure on projects of this nature would be justified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraigAghas" hpid="Pádraig Ághas Pádraig Ághas">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Ághas</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom ceist a chur ar an Rúnaí Parlaiminte. An bhfuil comhartha ceirde ag dul leis n gcaighdeán?  Is tuigthe dhom go <Col N="686" /> bhfuil earraí á ndéanamh ins an tSeapáin agus go bhfuil siad á ndíol i Meiriceá mar bhréidín Dhún na nGall. Deirtear liom nach bhfuil aon ghléas againn chun stop a chur leis sin. Sa chéad dul síos ba cheart comhartha ceirde a bheith ann agus ní dóigh liom gur leor sin.  Ba cheart fógraíocht a dhéanamh, go mór mhór i Meiriceá, agus an scéal a mhíniú do na daoine ansin. Má deintear é sin, cuirfear stop leis an stuif ón tSeapáin atá ag lot an mhargaidh i Meiriceá le haghaidh bréidín Dhún na nGall.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnchadhOBriain" hpid="Rúnaí Parlaiminte an Taoisigh (Donnchadh Ó Briain) Rúnaí Parlaiminte an Taoisigh (Donnchadh Ó Briain)">
      <NameTxt>Rúnaí Parlaiminte an Taoisigh (Donnchadh Ó Briain)</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl ionamsa ach sop in ionad scuaibe.  Is oth liom nach féidir leis an dTánaiste bheith anso chun freagra a thabhairt ar na pointí a luaigh na Seanadóirí ins an díospóireacht agus an chaint a rinneadar ar an 5ú Céim.</P>
      <P>Tógfaidh mé an cheist go ndearna An Senadóir Pádraig Ághas tagairt di.  Tuigim go bhfuil comhartha ceirde ag dul leis an gcaighdeán.  Má tá bréidín breige aca ghá dhíol i Meiriceá níl fhios agam conas stop a chur leis sin. Tá sé deacair stop do chur le mimhacántacht den tsórt sin in aon áit ina ndeintear é.  Fiú amháin má tá sé ar súil ins an tír seo, tá sé deacair teacht suas leis, uaireannta.  Is dócha nach bhfuil an Roinn Tionscail agus Tráchtála ná an tAire dall ar an droch-obair sin atá ag déanamh dochair don bhréidín sin as Dun na nGall go bhfuil clú air ar fud an domhain.  Cuirfear an tagairt a rinne an Seanadóir Ághas don cheist seo fé bhráid an Aire Tionscail agus Tráchtála.</P>
      <P>Senator McGuire raised a question that he had already ventilated in his speech on the Second Reading.  I can do no better than refer him to the reply which the Minister gave in concluding the debate on the Second Reading.  He suggested then that the question of price maintenance and price rings, to which Senator McGuire again referred this evening, were not relevant to any discussion on any part of this Bill.  That would apply, I think, generally to the point that Senator McGuire was so insistent on developing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="687" /> With regard to the points mentioned by Senator Douglas, both the parent Act of 1946 and the changes that will be brought about by the enactment of the present measure are all intended to benefit our industries, our industrialists and our manufacturers and to induce them to make more use of the machinery that is made available to them under this Industrial Research and Standards legislation.  One would hope that, as a result of this legislation, there will be complete co-operation between the manufacturers and the institute.</P>
    <P>Senator Douglas paid a tribute in his remarks to the work of the institute so far, and referred to the courtesy and consideration always given by the institute in its contacts with manufacturers.</P>
    <P>Senator Hearne referred to certain aspects of this legislation and he gave the specific example of the building industry.  Again, that is only one of the industries that can with advantage be helped by contact with the institute set up under the 1946 Act.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Donnell asked again whether any special research was being carried out in regard to the more extended use of native raw materials&mdash; at least, that is what I understood him to refer to.  The only reply I can give to him is the reply given by the Minister on the Second Reading when he said that information on the results of the work being done every year is made available in the annual report of the institute.  I am sure that any research of that nature that takes place will be made known to the public through that report when the time comes.  One would naturally expect that any opportunities for research of that kind that offer would be gladly availed of and carried out by the institute.  I can also assure him that the institute is always on the <i>qui vive</i> in regard to new methods to be recommended to manufacturers, and so forth.</P>
    <P>The attitude of the Seanad generally and of all the speakers gave an indication that this Bill is welcomed and that the changes that have been made in <Col N="688" /> the parent Act will be of much assistance in the work of the institute.</P>
    <P>I should like to express gratitude on behalf of the Minister for Industry and Commerce&mdash;who cannot be here, as I explained&mdash;for the way in which the Seanad has received this Bill.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Arrangement" RHead="of Business">
    <Title>Arrangement of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask Senator Hartnett what is the position with regard to No. 10?  I understand that the Minister cannot be here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps I may be able to help.  I am afraid I miscalculated the times.  Originally, I told the Minister that the Bills would probably be finished by 6 o'clock and that we could take the motion at 7 p.m.  The Minister told me that he would be available until 8.30 p.m. but that he could not come after that.  For that reason, the Minister is not available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelHartnett" hpid="Mr. Hartnett Mr. Hartnett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hartnett</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to have some indication as to when it will be possible for the House to resume discussion on my motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>After the general election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelHartnett" hpid="Mr. Hartnett Mr. Hartnett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hartnett</NameTxt>
      <P>The expert opinion of Senator O'Higgins, who has just returned from nursing a constituency, should be useful on the matter of health services.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to Bills in progress and business ordered, the Seanad will notice that the 10th March has been fixed for the Committee Stage of the Intestates' Estates Bill.  I suggest that the House discharge that order and that the Bill be taken on the next sitting day.</P>
      <P>Agreed and ordered accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The motions, when we arrive at them, will be taken on that date too.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 9.50 p.m. <i>sine die.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>