<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="8" Month="Nov" Year="2007" Vol="187" No="15" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 8 Samhain 2007" DateEnglish="Thursday, 8 November 2007" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1097">
    <Col N="1097"/><HtmlBk SectId="1" />
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title></Title>
        <P>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar<?oasys _jy ?>10.30 a.m.</P>
        <Line />
        <P Just="Center"><i>Paidir.</i><br /><i>Prayer.</i></P><Line />
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad"> 
    <Title>Business of Seanad. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I have received notice from Senator Donohoe that, on the adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Transport to provide an update on the progress made towards delivering integrated ticketing for public transport.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Fitzgerald of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Education and Science to recognise the urgent need for a secondary school for south Lucan in light of the growing population in the area and the figures available to her Department of primary school children in the area who will require a second level plan and the need to engage with the South Lucan School Action Group to address this need.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I regard the matters raised as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business"> 
    <Title>Order of Business. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>The Order of Business today is No. 1, statements on Government policy on food safety, to be taken at the conclusion of the Order of Business.  It is proposed that spokespersons may speak for 12 minutes and all other Senators for eight minutes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>That is agreed.  Will the Deputy Leader indicate if the Minister for Health and Children has agreed to come into the House to discuss cancer care services, particularly breast cancer care services, as we asked for yesterday?  We have just come from a meeting with Professor Drumm.  I did not get an opportunity to ask any questions, nor did many of my colleagues, but I make the point that having Professor Drumm address us in this setting indicates confusion in governance and administration.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1098"/>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>One of the issues I want the Minister to address when she comes to the House is that question of governance and responsibility for health policy and administration, which are two different aspects.  Part of the confusion about the health service arises because nobody is answering the question, namely, who is responsible?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>What is the role of Professor Drumm and the Health Service Executive in respect of policy or is it service provision?  We need an answer on that from the Minister for Health and Children.  I would be grateful if the Deputy Leader could indicate whether the Minister is coming into the House to address those concerns.</P>
        <P>On a separate matter, I hear there is interest in promoting some of the long-promised D&aacute;il reforms in a real way in the next few weeks.  A report on Seanad reform was published and it contained many detailed recommendations which I understand were accepted cross-party.  Will the Deputy Leader come back to the House with plans to progress in some way the recommendations&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Sorry for laughing.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>Was that a cynical laugh?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>It was a totally cynical laugh.  I put their own recommendations to them&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Fitzgerald, without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>If we are to have D&aacute;il reform and we have a full report on Seanad reform but no action on the issue, it will lead this House into disrepute.  I ask the Deputy Leader to ask the Government about the action that will be taken on Seanad reform in this term.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Nothing.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>I agree with what Senator Fitzgerald has just said.  I remind the House that not only was the matter accepted by all parties in the House, it was then sent to a committee under the chair of the previous Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government and of which our distinguished colleague, Senator Boyle, was a member as well as myself.  We had organised a structure under which some of the issues could have been brought into play immediately.  We examined step by step the changes in Standing Orders, legislation and constitutional changes that would be required.  We <Col N="1099"/>did not put in place a timeframe but we set priorities.  We should take the matter from there.  I support Senator Fitzgerald on this point.</P>
        <P>On a personal note, in a recent contribution on this issue the Leader, who is not present, made a remark to the effect that Senators on the Opposition side are not as committed to Seanad reform as they appear to be.  My core vote consists of primary school teachers but since 1996 not one qualified primary school teacher can vote for me on my panel.  I am fully committed to Seanad reform, although it has the potential to reduce my vote by 10,000.  No Senator stands to lose more than me if we proceed with reform of the university panel.  I also want all the other reforms to proceed.</P>
        <P>I agree with Senator Fitzgerald that the House should discuss the health service.  We should start by examining the legislation which established the Health Service Executive.  While I may not agree with her conclusion, Senator Fitzgerald is correct to call on the House to examine the question of accountability.  We should also examine the issue of responsibility.  It would make for a more serious debate if Senators knew who is responsible and who is accountable and what is the difference between responsibility and accountability.  Unfortunately, as I have observed over the past 20 years, attitudes quickly change depending on which side of the House Senators sit.  We must be able to understand the structure in place and identify who is responsible for what.  As I indicated yesterday, the Health Service Executive was established because we did not want political interference in the health service.  However, once political interference is removed, we are inclined to demand political responsibility.  We cannot have it every way.  We must decide what we want in this regard.  Let us re-examine the legislation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AlexWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Alex White</NameTxt>
	<P>I agree with Senator Fitzgerald that Senators should examine how the House does its business.  If the other House holds a debate on its role, the Seanad should certainly have such a debate on how it orders its business and addresses issues of concern.</P>
        <P>I also agree with the Senator&rsquo;s views on a point I raised in the House yesterday regarding public and political accountability.  The meeting we had this morning, while most useful to people in terms of issues being raised, was an extraordinary spectacle in a modern democracy.  In a crucial public service with a massive public budget voted from taxpayers&rsquo; money &mdash; the health service &mdash; we saw a lack of fit between political representatives and the service providers.  Political accountability has been deliberately removed from the health service to provide an alibi for the Government on issues of concern and to allow the Taoiseach, Ministers and others to argue that the health service is not their problem.  It is the Government&rsquo;s problem and one from which it cannot <Col N="1100"/>walk away.  What we saw this morning was an extraordinary spectacle.  I do not say this to criticise anybody but it is strange in a modern democracy to have politicians raising their hands, as it were, to ask questions of the chief executive of a State agency.  This matter must be addressed.</P>
        <P>On another issue, there was a rare outbreak of all-party agreement in the other House during a recent debate on undocumented Irish people living in the United States.  I am sure Senators support the resolution agreed in the D&aacute;il calling for action to be taken to regularise the status of thousands of undocumented Irish people living in the United States and noting the precarious position in which these people find themselves.</P>
        <P>While I am aware, through experiences in my family, that undocumented Irish people often live in a legal limbo in the US for many years, we cannot forever ignore the fact that we do not have to walk too far from this building to see very similar circumstances.  Thousands of undocumented illegal immigrants face precisely the same sort of precarious life, isolation and exploitation.  We cannot, on the one hand, state that we are actively committed to a certain course of action in the United States, one which I support, while forever ignoring the situation on our own doorstep.  Perhaps the Deputy Leader would request the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform to come to the House to explain the reason he is so quick to reject proposals, such as that made by the Migrants Rights Centre Ireland yesterday, to provide a bridging visa for people in Ireland who face the same precarious, isolating and, in many cases, sad human dilemma that Irish people have faced overseas.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>The issue I raise relates to an issue which featured in the newspapers in recent weeks, namely, the large number of people who send their children for maths grinds before the junior certificate examination.  I ask the Deputy Leader to arrange a debate on the role of the arts, specifically music, in early education. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>We should debate class sizes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>There is a proven link between music and left hemisphere development in the brain, which is the side on which the reasoning function is located.  It is important, therefore, that children are exposed to appropriate influences when the brain is developing.  The House should have a discussion on the fundamental value of music to early education.  The greater use of music in early education could result in parents no longer resorting to sending their children to grinds, a practice which has been shown not to work by a recent report.  In addition, we would have more rounded students who would have social outlets other than spending an <Col N="1101"/>increasing amount of time on the so-called three Rs.  This is a pertinent issue.</P>
        <P>If the Senators who are laughing are so misguided about the role of music and brain development that they find the issue amusing, I suggest they start researching the subject.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Mary M. White</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>The relationship between music and brain development was proven in the 1980s.  MRI scans carried out on professional musicians demonstrate that their brain development, including the shape of the left hemisphere, differs greatly from that of non-musicians.  This is linked to mathematical skills.  Rather than jesting, I ask Senators to inform themselves. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Deputy Leader convene a debate on Irish Aid and development programmes, specifically on the need to mainstream disability rights in development programmes?  I have just come from a seminar on disability and development being run by the Centre for Global Health at Trinity College Dublin in conjunction with D&oacute;chas and Irish Aid.  In the year in which Ireland signed the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities &mdash; it has still not been ratified &mdash; it would be timely for the House to debate the importance of placing the rights of people with disabilities centre stage in our development programmes.  Irish Aid had done a good deal of work on this issue but Ireland is required, under Article 32 of the convention, to promote disability awareness in our international co-operation programmes.</P>
        <P>It is very important we meet this requirement, especially in light of the report published yesterday by the Disability Equality Specialist Support Agency which found that almost half of child care providers in Dublin do not include disabled children in their services.  Even at home, we are falling short of providing for the rights of children with disabiities.  On an international stage, it has been estimated that only 2% of disabled children in developing countries receive any education.  It is critical, therefore, that we address disability issues in development aid and Irish Aid programmes.  I echo the call made by Senator Ormonde yesterday that the House debate Irish Aid and ask that such a debate include the issue of disability.</P>
        <P>I support Senator Alex White&rsquo;s comments on the rights of undocumented persons living here and those who have experienced difficulties in the area of family reunification.  I raised this issue last week.  The Refugee Information Service produced a report showing the difficulty experienced by those with refugee status who seek to bring family members, dependants and children to Ireland from their home countries.  We treat these people, who have secured refugee status and been through persecution in their home countries, <Col N="1102"/>appallingly badly by preventing them from bringing their families to Ireland.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGerardHanafin"><NameTxt>Senator John Hanafin</NameTxt>
	<P>I support calls for Seanad reform, an issue on which Senators have often spoken.  While many of the reform proposals are reasonable, implementing some of them is not a realistic option.  For example, proposals to have 50% of Senators elected and 50% appointed or to hold Seanad elections on the same day as the general election are unrealistic.  It is difficult to meet my constituents between general elections.  It would be virtually impossible to meet them if there was an election.</P>
        <P>The current structure of the Seanad has served the State well.  For this reason, I repeat my proposal to increase the number of Members of the Seanad.  I support reform when it is necessary to change some simple matters.  Senator O&rsquo;Toole, for example, noted that 10,000 members of his constituency cannot vote for him.  By and large, however, I support increasing the number of Senators and leaving the structure as it is.  The Seanad should assume a greater role through its representation on Oireachtas committees.  The Seanad has served the country well and can continue to do so.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Minister for Health and Children attend the House, given the seriousness of the crisis in the health service?  This morning, when we were treated to Professor Drumm&rsquo;s charade, it was like being in spin city.  We need accountability.  Senator O&rsquo;Toole referred to political interference.  As Members, we are worthy of answers and deserving of information, none of which we are getting.  There is no accountability in the provision of health services.  It is high time for political accountability on the part of a Government that has abdicated responsibility.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaudieCoffey"><NameTxt>Senator Paudie Coffey</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>In saying that I am not being political.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator would never be political.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P><i>(Interruptions).</i></P>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Yesterday, we were accused of being political.  When everything goes wrong, it is our fault and when everything goes well, it is the Government&rsquo;s doing.  We need political answers and leadership.</P>
        <P>Given that the Minister will allow Cork Airport&rsquo;s debt, I raised an issue on the Order of Business regarding the elimination of its debt free status.  Has the Deputy Leader information regarding the elimination of the debt and the separation of Cork Airport from the Dublin Airport Authority?</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1103"/>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Mary M. White</NameTxt>
	<P>Deputy M&aacute;ire Hoctor is the dedicated Minister of State with responsibility for older people.  Will the Acting Leader invite her to the House to discuss my document, A New Approach to Ageing and Ageism, and to outline her agenda?  I am not referring to important health issues alone.  For example, there is an age cap of 64 years in respect of free breast cancer screening and a cap of 70 years is only an aspiration.  I want a broader debate on the elderly.  The new Minister of State has been proactive and a debate would be interesting and helpful to everyone.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaudieCoffey"><NameTxt>Senator Paudie Coffey</NameTxt>
	<P>We should spare a thought for the salvage operation under way off the south-east coast at Dunmore East in County Waterford.  It is a difficult and emotional time for the families of those on the stricken vessel, <i>P&egrave;re Charles</i>.  As we are an island nation and similar events could affect any part of our country, there should be a protocol or system in place for when vessels sink.  At the time, there was controversy regarding how difficult it was to have the <i>P&egrave;re Charles</i> raised.  The Minister of the day stepped in and addressed the situation.  Will the current Minister attend the House to discuss protocols and systems for when vessels get into difficulty?</P>
        <P>I acknowledge the role of the emergency services in those tragic circumstances.  I refer to the Irish Coast Guard, the Navy divers involved in the salvage operation and the salvage company.  We hope the difficult operation reaches a satisfactory conclusion for all concerned.  We should consider the families and communities bereaved by tragedies along our coastlines.  Will the Deputy Leader facilitate my request for the Minister to attend the House?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>This is the 20th anniversary of the outrage at Enniskillen, which led to pressure being placed on the Provisional IRA to cease its actions.  I was newly elected at the time and I remember how Mr. John Robb went to the desk of the then Cathaoirleach, Mr. Charles McDonald, and gave him the poppy he was wearing, which the Cathaoirleach then wore for the day.  It was a moving gesture.  We remember the horror of the day and welcome the fact that the situation has ended.</P>
        <P>I welcome the calls for Seanad reform.  I laughed cynically because I have heard such calls for the 20 years in which I have been a Member.  I made many calls and suggestions, but they disappeared into thin air.  Let us not hear about rotten boroughs because none of the nominating bodies have influence.  The majority of Senators are nominated by the Taoiseach or put in by a handful of councillors and parliamentarians.  That is fine, but there is a constant diversionary attack on the only constituencies with real constituents.  We are described as rotten boroughs, but I will not accept that.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1104"/>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>Councillors are&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We can discuss this matter later.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>We will return such attacks four fold.  If one wishes to know how enthusiastic Members are for reform, one should examine the record of some weeks ago when a report I tabled was voted against by Government Senators.  We have a role to play in these matters and we can use our powers, such as they are.</P>
        <P>Yesterday, I raised the matter of former Senator Maurice Manning&rsquo;s statement to the effect that the Government attempted to interfere with his report on rendition and to put him under pressure, angering him.  Will the House exercise its facility to invite Dr. Manning to present the report and to allow Members to question him?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Mary M. White</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Our inquiry was set up, but it was crippled and destroyed at the instigation of the Government.  Let us have the matter out in the open and let us use our facilities to bring Dr. Manning before the House.</P>
        <P>I am proud that Trinity College is one of the 60 top universities in the world and I congratulate Dublin City University on getting into the top 200 for the first time.  As an almost brand new university, this is a wonderful tribute to Ireland&rsquo;s third level system.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator has made his point.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator believed it was the best in the world.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>It is only dawning on me.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Donohoe without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalDonohoe"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Donohoe</NameTxt>
	<P>I will refer to my colleagues&rsquo; comments on the need for a discussion on immigration matters.  A number of weeks ago, I requested that the Minister of State with responsibility for integration policy to attend the House to debate those matters.  I repeat my request.</P>
        <P>One of Ireland&rsquo;s most shameful issues is the number of people who come here to seek refuge and must spend six, seven or eight years awaiting an answer from the State as to whether they are worthy of refugee status.  Consequently, they live in an appalling, grey world on the margins of society.  They cannot work and are not entitled to empathy or support.  Our treatment of them ill behoves us.  Will the Deputy Leader invite the Minister of State to the House?</P><Col N="1105"/>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">11 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>Yesterday, a discussion on the M50 roundabout was requested, but Fingal County Council or its traffic strategic policy group would be the appropriate chamber for the debate.  We should focus on the changes being made to Transport 21.  They appear significant in that the construction and operation of the Dublin interconnector will occur earlier than planned.  It was planned to dig up half of Dublin to put new Luas and metro lines in place, to cover it up afterwards and to dig up other parts of Dublin to join the lines.  Now, this work will occur simultaneously.  That this commonsensical suggestion is lauded as evidence of strategic thinking shows how low the Government&rsquo;s expectations are for joined up and strategic delivery.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AlexWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Alex White</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalDonohoe"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Donohoe</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Minister debate Transport 21 in the House to ensure the nearly &euro;10 million of taxpayers&rsquo; money to be spent on public transport every day for the next ten years will be properly and transparently spent?</P>
      
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>Senator Denis O&rsquo;Donovan</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Deputy Leader ask the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform, when we deal with the Defamation Bill, to consider the sequence of events whereby the courts awarded Ms Julia Kushnir, the woman from the Ukraine, substantial damages regarding the unfortunate and tragic death of our late colleague former Deputy Liam Lawlor.  Ms Kushnir deserved the money she got, but it disturbs me that the National Union of Journalists, NUJ, and the newspapers concerned did not acknowledge the great hurt, opprobrium and shame that fell on Mrs. Lawlor and her family.  We talk about setting up an ombudsman for the press, and in such a situation the ombudsman could take the lead.  It was tragic enough for Mrs. Lawlor to receive the news from Russia that her husband had died, but to read in the Sunday newspapers the allegation that he had been with a prostitute was shameful and damaging.  Nobody in the media, especially the newspapers concerned, some of which are powerful, conveyed a sincere apology.  Under the existing libel laws the dead cannot prosecute or be compensated, but we should at least let them rest.  I urge the newspapers concerned to have the courtesy and dignity to apologise to the widow and family of the late Mr. Lawlor for the severe hurt she must have felt.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I heartily concur with Senator O&rsquo;Donovan&rsquo;s remarks.  It was shocking journalism, as everyone in the House will agree.  I agree with Senator Fitzgerald&rsquo;s remarks, and those of other colleagues, on the health services.  I, too, attended that meeting this morning.  Given the success of our country, I cannot understand <Col N="1106"/>why we use mammography machines that are 15 years old or more, ten years past their expiry date.  This is crazy.  The machines can give false positives or negatives.  We know about the resulting tragedy and how it has damaged women&rsquo;s lives.  I cannot fathom it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is Senator Coghlan calling for a debate?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I do.  As Senator Fitzgerald and others said, the buck must stop somewhere.  I support the call to invite the Minister for Health and Children to explain matters further.</P>
        <P>Perhaps we should hasten slowly on Seanad reform.  Much could be done, but let us see how the D&aacute;il is reformed.  Much of what the sub-committee on D&aacute;il reform deals with relates to procedural matters and how it can improve its use of time.  We can take some actions immediately, particularly to deal with topical matters.  I am sure our Committee on Procedure and Privileges, CPP, has this in mind and will take it up.  Let us wait and see.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>Press freedom is, rightly, a cherished principle in any civilised society.  In light of Senator O&rsquo;Donovan&rsquo;s comments, with which I heartily concur, there is a need for this House to appraise the balance we must strike between press freedom and the need to bring about a greater culture of responsibility among media practitioners.  There is the provision for the award of aggravated damages in certain cases, for example, where parties are shown to have acted in an especially culpable way, either in events leading to the proceedings or in the conduct of the proceedings.  I am concerned about the uncertain status of the proposed privacy legislation and whether the media&rsquo;s influence causes politicians to stay their hands on bringing about the necessary debate on how to foster a culture of responsibility. There is only one way to bring about responsibility in this area and that is to target people&rsquo;s pockets when they are culpable.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Mary M. White</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>Perhaps it is time to consider compensatory mechanisms when the press steps out of line and hurts innocent parties.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Senator Jim Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>I subscribe to the opinions expressed by the previous three Senators.  I regret that the Defamation Bill is coming back on the Order Paper.  Before it does so, it might be opportune for the Leader to arrange to debate the responsibilities and freedom of the press.  It is alarming that the press seeks to impose a veto on the introduction of the Privacy Bill.  That is a significant factor on which we could give our views and consideration.</P><Col N="1107"/>
        <P>I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Transport to attend this House soon to discuss the appropriateness of speed limits.  Speed cameras operated by private firms are to be introduced and this will have consequences.  It behoves the State to ensure realistic speed limits are in place.  I refer in particular to the N11, which has been upgraded to exceptionally good dual carriageway standard but still has a limit of 100 km/h although traffic travels on it comfortably and safely at 120 km/h.  Such matters must be examined.  We are investing significantly in roads to facilitate the travelling public and the economy.  We should benefit from it but we are not.  We should invite the Minister to debate this.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>I second Senator Walsh&rsquo;s call.  We have a similar situation on the Ashbourne bypass in County Meath which could easily cater for 120 km/h but is limited to 100 km/h.  I would like the Minister to come and tell Members if he would consider reviewing speed limits.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>It is up to the county councils.  The Minister has no responsibility.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Hannigan without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>The county councils deal with local and secondary roads.  The National Roads Authority deals with bypasses.  I apologise to the Cathaoirleach.  The county councils have no responsibility for our national roads.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>That is what the Minister told me when I raised the matter in this House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>Somebody is wrong.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>If people continue interrupting those who want to make contributions, I will ask them to leave the House.  I will not tolerate people who interrupt Senators who want to make points on the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I also want to raise the proposed development outside Balbriggan and Gormanstown of the Bremore Port.  This morning Drogheda Port Company announced it had entered an agreement to build a &euro;300 million development on the Meath-Fingal border.  The proposed port is four kilometres from the M1 motorway, which is the responsibility of the NRA, and close to the Dublin-Dundalk rail line.  It is proposed that the port will take up to 10 million tonnes of traffic every year, three times the current volume of traffic going through Drogheda Port.  It will take some traffic from Dublin Port and complement it.  It is important <Col N="1108"/>we ensure a project of this size is carefully planned in terms of its impact on land use planning, the environment, pollution, transport and local housing needs.</P>
        <P>Will the Deputy Leader ask the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government to consider establishing a task force comprising members of the relevant local authorities such as Meath, Fingal and Louth county councils, Dublin City Council, CIE, the NRA, the Health Service Executive and others to set criteria for how this should be planned and managed?  It is vital a development of this size is well thought out and well implemented.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="GeraldineFeeney"><NameTxt>Senator Geraldine Feeney</NameTxt>
	<P>I support Senators O&rsquo;Donovan and Mullen&rsquo;s calls for a debate on the press.  Perhaps we should examine regulating the press in the same way we regulate the medical and legal professions.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Feeney should read the Defamation Bill.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="GeraldineFeeney"><NameTxt>Senator Geraldine Feeney</NameTxt>
	<P>They do as much damage to people&rsquo;s lives as some of those in the medical and legal professions.  At least the medical and legal people have a fitness to practice and a code of conduct to which they must adhere.  If they continue to offend, they are suspended or removed from their register.  I agree with Senator Mullen that newspapers should pay high compensation when they offend and ruin lives, as they do.  Newspapers are wealthy and I do not know how significant an impact fines would have.  If a journalist or a newspaper continued to offend, we should  be talking about sanctions, such as three strikes, then out, cutting off their livelihood.  We would then see how the media would write about people.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Feeney addressed the issue that we tried to struggle with in the last session, the delicate balance between the freedom of the press and the privacy of the individual.  Both points of view have a very strong case, and we certainly have not resolved it.  It is important that we state that we abhor the intrusion on one&rsquo;s privacy by the press, for the obvious reason that we are all public figures.  If we are talking about regulation, we should make absolutely certain that we are not talking about control, which is offensive to the freedom of the press.</P>
        <P>I did not rise to speak on that issue, but on an issue of interest to the Leader where we can set the example.  Much has been said recently about the Oireachtas setting a bad example on pay and expenses, when we are asking the general public to restrict themselves in the weeks and months to come.  We might take this a little further.  I drove into Leinster House, just as I suppose everybody else did.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I walked.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1109"/>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>That is exactly what the Senator ought to continue doing.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I walked.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>I saw the Senator&rsquo;s car there on Monday.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>No, the Senator did not.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>A Senator</NameTxt>
	<P>A gas guzzler. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>A big black Jaguar.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Ross without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>He is asking for it.  I am being provoked.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">The Senator is like a child at the back of the classroom.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I will decide that.  Let Senator Ross speak.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>Leinster lawn was once a lovely park, a green space, which was temporarily made into a car park some years ago.  We are all at fault because we all drive and the car park is chock a block every single day.  We could give an example to the public if we were to put restrictions on ourselves and on the staff of this House.  We look after the internal fabric of Leinster House magnificently.  The staff and the OPW have done phenomenally good work, but the outside is a desecration of the past.  We are not looking after the heritage of the house.  It is a disgrace that there are hundreds of cars there everyday.  The Oireachtas Members and staff should be prepared to make some sort of sacrifice to restore it to its former glory as a green area, of which people of Dublin could be proud.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn"><NameTxt>Senator Camillus Glynn</NameTxt>
	<P>I support the remarks made by Senator Denis O&rsquo;Donovan and others on the press.  The former Senator Willie Farrell called <i>ad nauseam </i>for a press council.  I am sure that few members in this Chamber have not felt the weight of the pen in an adverse way at one time or another.  In most cases, the central focus is the story and if the truth gets in the way, the story wins every time. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Mary M. White</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn"><NameTxt>Senator Camillus Glynn</NameTxt>
	<P>I hate to say &ldquo;I told you so&rdquo;, but now that the ashes have settled, the reports of what happened at Hallowe&rsquo;en make very dismal reading in the Westmeath local newspapers.  The county council workers were stoned.  This is being reflected in reports right around the country.  I spoke on this issue down through the years.  Other Members have spoken on what has now become an annual event.  It is high time the <Col N="1110"/>matter was addressed, as not only have valuable trees and tracts of play areas been destroyed but old people and animals have suffered.  There must be a meeting of minds between the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government and possibly the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform.  If we are to have bonfires and fireworks, let them be organised and co-ordinated under the auspices possibly of the local authority.  The current <i>ad hoc </i>arrangements serve no purpose.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PearseDoherty"><NameTxt>Senator Pearse Doherty</NameTxt>
	<P>I have sought information from the Leader on a number of occasions, but perhaps the Deputy Leader may be able to inform me on when the student support Bill will come before this House.  Is it expected before the end of the year or at the start of the next term?  A commitment was given to students that the Bill would be taken in early 2007 but the end of the year is now approaching.  </P>
        <P Just="Left">Will the Deputy Leader facilitate the taking of an all-party motion, similar to what was agreed in the D&aacute;il last night, that we support 100% the call for the plight of the undocumented Irish to be resolved?  Will those who are not members of the main political parties be given an opportunity to add their voices and send a clear message to the families of the undocumented that not only Deputies but Senators agree that the issue needs to be resolved and are calling on the Government to do everything in its power to resolve it and to send a clear signal to the US Government that both Houses of the Oireachtas are in full support of it?  Will the Deputy Leader agree to consult the leaders of the groups on a motion, similar to the way we dealt with the issue of Burma, that could be debated as early as possible?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MariaCorrigan"><NameTxt>Senator Maria Corrigan</NameTxt>
	<P>I support the point made by Senator Glynn on the Hallowe&rsquo;en season.  The more vulnerable members of the community suffer hardship and distress at that time.  It is ironic that we outlaw burning in the open, yet we see evidence of an ever-increasing number of enormous bonfires.</P>
        <P>I have come from a briefing with the HSE this morning where it was stated that those with an intellectual disability in institutional or in State residential care, who had money deducted for such care, similar to what happed to old people in nursing homes, are not eligible to have that money returned to them.  I would like the Deputy Leader to clarify this matter.  I believe it could be a misunderstanding on the part of the HSE representatives.  The families of people with intellectual disabilities were encouraged to apply for the return of money deducted by those in charge of the institutions.</P>
        <P>Will the Deputy Leader also take the opportunity to ask the Minister what steps are being taken to ensure accountability for the standardised rate paid by those with intellectual disabilities for residential care?</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1111"/>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, Deputy Gormley, should attend the House to discuss water quality monitoring and safety.  Yet again the water crisis has revisited us in Galway with a new outbreak in Clarenbridge.  It was national news in Galway city and the hinterlands, including Knocknacarragh, but the issue has not yet been resolved.  The latest outbreak of water pollution is likely to have a far wider national impact than it did in Galway.  The HSE tests are proving to be so sensitive in Galway that contamination is being picked up, but the same level of testing may not be happening elsewhere in the country.  I would appreciate if that issue could be addressed by the Minister and I ask the Deputy Leader to invite him to the House.</P>
        <P>Senator Norris referred to the issue of Seanad reform.  As a former councillor, I wish to state that councillors are a very real electorate.  In the first instance, they are elected by upwards of 2,000 people which may be up to half the electorate that some people have to achieve in this House.  They are in touch with people on the ground, which is local democracy in action.  It is important to state that some Senators who have chosen to be elected through the Oireachtas route or via nominating bodies, could have chosen the university route.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>They would be very welcome.  I hope they do.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu"><NameTxt>Senator Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</NameTxt>
	<P>I find it encouraging to hear so many Senators calling for greater responsibility and accountability on the part of certain sections of the media.  In the past, there was a tendency to remain silent lest we might suffer the media&rsquo;s ire by criticising them.  I have had a couple of such instances in this House.  On a few occasions I called on the National Union of Journalists to see if the ethics of that profession were being upheld.  However, the union wrote to the CPP complaining about me.  That letter was circulated to every Senator at that time.  Luckily, when I checked the official record I found that they had erred with regard to the case they had cited.  Eventually they offered me an apology and asked me if I wanted a public apology.</P>
        <P>At the time of the Liam Lawlor case, I made the point that if a public representative had done what a particular Sunday newspaper did, they would call immediately for our heads.  Three weeks later, the newspaper ran a story about another issue on which I had spoken, which was totally at variance with the record.  I checked the Official Report and the paper was wrong in that case.  It even went as far as publishing a cartoon with the article.  I wrote privately to the editor furnishing him with a copy of the record of the House and the report from the <i>Sunday Independent</i>, asking whether this was ethical and fair comment.  I heard nothing for three weeks and then got a telephone call.  It was evident they had <Col N="1112"/>decided they were going to do a good news story for me and gave me a half a page.  That is not the way to run this business.  If we can be criticised daily and rightly held to account, likewise, the media must accept criticism.  By showing a stubborn streak in complaining, writing and trying subsequently to misrepresent someone, they are doing harm to their own profession, credibility and the great record which so many journalists have had in the past.  At this stage, we should take off the gloves.  It should not be dealt with on the Order of Business but in a real debate on the issue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Why is the Senator&rsquo;s Government introducing the Defamation Bill on Committee Stage?  There is no Second Stage debate. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu"><NameTxt>Senator Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</NameTxt>
	<P>In fairness, when the previous Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform, Michael McDowell, attended the House, many of us spoke courageously at that time.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Absolutely.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu"><NameTxt>Senator Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</NameTxt>
	<P>We should revisit the matter now and not let the media off the hook on this occasion. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>We were cut off because the Government is introducing this legislation on Committee Stage.  I have asked about this matter. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Norris has already spoken on the Order of Business.  </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes but we were cut off without a proper Second Stage debate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I call Senator O&rsquo;Sullivan before the Deputy Leader replies.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NedOSullivan"><NameTxt>Senator Ned O&rsquo;Sullivan</NameTxt>
	<P>I have one or two brief points.  I welcome the proposed debate sought by Senator O&rsquo;Donovan and would like to participate in it.  Like everyone in public life at any level, I have also received a few belts from editorials.  At the same time we must be cautious and remember the words of Benjamin Disraeli who said &ldquo;Never complain and never explain&rdquo;.  That maxim goes a long way for me.</P>
        <P>I ask the Deputy Leader to convey my thanks and the thanks of the House to the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, Deputy Gormley, for the efficient way in which he resolved the issue I raised here two weeks ago concerning expense remunerations for members of regional river basin committees.  He moved with great speed on an issue that had been dragging along for quite a while.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1113"/>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>That is ten votes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NedOSullivan"><NameTxt>Senator Ned O&rsquo;Sullivan</NameTxt>
	<P>I also ask the Deputy Leader to raise an issue with the Minister for Education and Science concerning the establishment of a payment regime for chairpersons of vocational education committees.  Senators will be aware that chairpersons of almost everything are salaried, including county and town councils and strategic policy committees.  Chairpersons of vocational education committees do tremendous work and have a large workload.  Many of them are well known to us as public representatives.  The Deputy Leader might raise that matter with the Minister for Education and Science.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>Today we have had a more varied assembly of requests from Members but some were also carried over from yesterday&rsquo;s Order of Business.  I regret that I have not been able to announce the availability of the Minister for Health and Children to attend the House.  I am confident, however, that we will have confirmation of her intention to come here by the time we meet again next Tuesday.  Several Members raised the question of the governance of the health services on top of yesterday&rsquo;s concerns about cancer care, and whether it is possible to have combined statements on both matters.  I think that can be facilitated.  It is accepted that today&rsquo;s briefing session, following the first such session last year, is not the most satisfactory for informing Members of the Oireachtas, allowing Members to voice their ongoing concerns or discuss the development of health policy.  Perhaps collectively we can come up with better ways of approaching these maters when the HSE next offers such a facility.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senators Frances Fitzgerald, O&rsquo;Toole, Alex White and others broached the question of Seanad reform.  The Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government has responsibility at Cabinet level for progressing this matter.  I understand he is in the process of writing to the Leaders of political groupings in both Houses seeking a reconvening of the committee that was established during the last D&aacute;il and Seanad.  Once established, I would like the committee to have a time commitment, perhaps even as narrow as six months, in which to undertake its work.  We have an agreement from the last D&aacute;il and Seanad, which is the 11th such report.  There have not been any legislative or constitutional changes in the make-up or workings of this Chamber since it was established under the 1937 Constitution.  We have a responsibility to ensure such changes can come about in the lifetime of the 23rd Seanad.  I can certainly give my personal commitment on that.</P>
        <P>The question of an agreed motion on Irish emigrants has been debated in the Lower House.  It was raised here by Senators Alex White and Doherty.  I cannot see any difficulty in having such a debate and I think the House will speak <Col N="1114"/>with one mind on that issue.  As someone who was born in the United States, the son of Irish immigrants, I can readily identify with the matter.</P>
        <P>Senator Keaveney raised the question of early schooling and the development of music in the curriculum.  I am convinced that I became the Green Party&rsquo;s finance spokesperson because I was seen strumming a guitar at a party convention.  It is obviously true, as Senator Keaveney said, that the development of mathematical and musical skills are on a par and our primary school curriculum should reflect that.</P>
        <P>Senator Bacik sought a debate on development aid which can be easily arranged.  In light of recent statements, we should also focus of the disability programme in such a debate.  She also referred to access to child care for children with disabilities.  Initially, the implementation of the Disability Act is concentrating on the 0-5 years age range.  In implementing personal development plans for this age group, it is hoped that many of these continuing difficulties can be overcome.  However, if a debate is needed to show progress on that, we can arrange it.</P>
        <P>Senator Bacik also called for a debate on family reunification, as did Senator Donohoe.  The immigration Bill will come before the House early next year and we hope that will provide the forum.  Most Members are frustrated with the current system and the need to make it more humane and more efficient.  I realise that Senator Bacik is speaking at a conference on this next week.</P>
        <P>Senator Buttimer asked about the current Cork Airport debt.  As I understand it, the airport will stay under the auspices of the Dublin Airport Authority until an agreement is reached.  Everybody in the Cork area thinks that this is unsatisfactory.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>We were given a commitment in this House that it would be debt free.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>I am trying to explain the current situation.  A consultant report has referred to a debt of &euro;50 million being carried over, but that is disputed by the interim committee for the Cork Airport Authority.  That is where the matter lies at the moment and I do not believe any firm decision has been made on it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>How long must we wait?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>I will try to find that out.  Senator Coffey spoke about the raising of the <i>P&egrave;re Charles</i>, which is the second vessel to be raised this week.  The Minister is to be commended on trying to meet the concerns of the family involved.  It is subject to ongoing policy review as to whether this could be done in every circumstance.  It does not seem to be standard practice in other countries, but the information gained from the raising of these two vessels will <Col N="1115"/>bring a degree of certainty for the families involved.  The Minister may be given an opportunity in the House to talk about policy in that area.</P>
        <P>Senator Norris asked about the Irish Human Rights Commission&rsquo;s report on rendition and whether Dr. Manning could come before the House.  I am not aware of precedent in this matter, but if it can be arranged there might be a value in it.  Senator Donohoe spoke about the interconnector and Transport 21.  I am not too sure of the point he was making, but the House should acknowledge a policy that gives precedence to public transport and tries to build public transport links in Dublin city, even if it is a reversal of what has happened before.</P>
        <P>Senator O&rsquo;Donovan brought up the issue of an award to a Ukrainian citizen, following the reporting of a story a few years ago that represented a huge stain on journalism in this country.  He was supported by other Members.  We await the introduction of the Defamation Bill 2006 and we should acknowledge the informal arrangement that currently exists, following the appointment of a press ombudsman working through the press council.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Bill be brought before the House on Second Stage?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AlexWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Alex White</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of order, will we all be permitted to have supplementary questions when the Deputy Leader is responding to the Order of Business?  This has happened three or four times in the last few minutes and it is not fair to other Members.  I would like to come back in with supplementary questions as well.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader should not be interrupted in any shape or form, so that he could be given an opportunity to answer questions raised.  I hope people respect that and if they cannot do so, there is room outside for them.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>I hope that every question can be answered eventually, even if not within the scope of this reply.  I am trying to get through all the submissions that have been made this morning.  We should acknowledge the appointment of a press ombudsman operating through the informal press council that the media organisations have established themselves.  The fact that the ombudsman is a former Member of the House and a distinguished commentator on media affairs will help to avoid reoccurrences of situations like this.  If such situations do occur, he can make sure that there is a better response for all those who are affected by such defamation.</P>
        <P>Several Members, beginning with Senator Walsh, spoke about the re-establishment of speed limits on various roads, particularly redeveloped roads.  I am sure the Minister would be pleased to respond to such a debate.  There were contri<Col N="1116"/>butions yesterday from Senator Quinn and Keaveney asking for restrictions on speeding.  The debate must be held within the context that there are many problems with speed on our roads.  Whatever speed limits are set, there are people in our society who will drive even faster.  Perhaps we should adopt the Japanese technology that restricts cars from going faster than the legal limit.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of order&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator, without interruption please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I was misrepresented.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Ross spoke about Leinster Lawn and I know that the Minister for Environment, Heritage and Local Government has expressed his unhappiness about it in the past.  There have been proposals for an underground parking facility to restore the lawn to its former glory, but these have not been funded.  It is a matter for the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission and perhaps Members of the House on that commission can express our concerns.  I agree with the sentiments of Senator Ross.</P>
        <P>Some Senators spoke about the effects of Halloween.  I am not sure if this is a matter for debate or new legislation, which is already in place.  It is difficult for the various agencies to enforce it.  We could do with an audit of the cost of policing and the fire services at this time.  A factory unit was burned down in Ballincollig, yet Cork does not even have the tradition of bonfires on Halloween night.  These problems are becoming manifest all over the country.</P>
        <P>Senator Healy Eames spoke about the continuing difficulties with water quality in the Galway area.  I will bring those to the attention of the Minister, but the water services funding programme has been recently announced and it is the highest ever in the history of the State.  It is hoped that we can start to tackle the problems that exist.</P>
        <P>Senator Doherty spoke about the student support Bill, which is in section A of the legislative programme of the Oireachtas.  There is a promise that the Bill will be published before the start of the next session.  By the latest, it will be published by the middle of January.   The Senator can keep reminding us of that if he feels there is a need to do so.</P>
        <P>Senator White called for a debate on the care of the elderly.  There was a similar request yesterday for the Minister of State, Deputy Hoctor, to come before the House and this debate can be easily facilitated.  There are particular references in the programme for Government that would help such a debate.</P>
        <P>Following the Order of Business on 25 October, the House divided on the ministerial <Col N="1117"/>order for Cockles (Fishing Management Conservation) (Waterford Estuary) Regulations 2007.  On foot of the concerns expressed that day and following further investigation, I am pleased to announce that the order is to be rescinded next week.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Well done.  Bravo.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
 <HtmlBk SectId="2" />
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Food Safety:" RHead="Statements"> 
    <Title>Food Safety: Statements. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome to the House the Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children, Deputy Pat the Cope Gallagher.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatTheCope"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Pat The Cope Gallagher</NameTxt>
	<P>In my role as Minister of State with responsibility for health promotion and food safety, I welcome this opportunity to discuss these issues in the House.  We live in a society in which the availability of fresh, wholesome, varied and, above all, safe food is taken for granted.  Undoubtedly, standards of production and distribution of food have improved significantly and one can now walk into shops in almost any part of the country and buy foodstuffs, the existence of which one would have been unaware only a generation ago.  Moreover, while I am conscious that I am showing my age in this respect, foods such as oranges and bananas, which were once infrequent treats, are now a completely unremarked-on part of our daily diet.  However, such welcome developments have given rise to their own challenges and I will address this issue in the course of my contribution.</P>
        <P>In this new period of prosperity, previously exotic foods are consumed routinely and increased affluence has led to more foreign travel and greater attendances at restaurants.  Our palates have become more sophisticated and our tastes more varied.  Consequently, the food industry has expanded significantly.  According to Bord Bia, the total turnover of food and drink for 2006 was almost &euro;20 billion.  The agriculture and food industry is now the largest indigenous sector and agriculture alone employs 109,000 people.  It accounts for more than half of indigenous exports, contributes significantly to rural development and represents almost one tenth of the economy.</P>
        <P>Against this background, the need to assure the consumer of the safety of Irish food, thereby helping to safeguard public health and the interests of this industry, has reached a new level of importance.  It has also reached a new level of complexity.  It is necessary to meet this challenge with a proactive, long-term approach, including the provision of a robust legislative framework and through the provision and efficient use of resources within this framework.  This approach must be guided by science while being informed <Col N="1118"/>by the needs of the food industry&rsquo;s key stakeholders, namely, producers, processors, caterers, retailers and, most importantly, consumers.</P>
        <P>Members will recall that in the late 1980s and early 1990s, in the wake of various crises that besieged the European food industry, Ireland was one of the first EU member states to restructure and modernise its food safety regime.  The establishment of the Food Safety Authority of Ireland, in which the power to implement national food policy was vested, freed the Department of Health and Children and what is now the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food to concentrate on the formulation of national policy and to represent Ireland&rsquo;s interests at international level.  While one should never become complacent, I believe this arrangement has worked well.</P>
        <P>Some of the major achievements since this restructuring include a dramatic decline in the numbers of BSE cases in the national herd, which is due largely to the strict enforcement of food safety controls throughout the food chain.  There has been an increase in the number of food premises that have put in place food safety management systems based on the principles of the hazard analysis and critical control point, HACCP, system.  Moreover, there has been a reduction of salt levels in processed foods in partnership with industry and a reduction in the incidence of salmonella in poultry flocks and in eggs produced in Ireland.</P>
        <P>There are two key areas in food safety, namely, guaranteeing to the greatest possible extent that food is safe and the provision of clear and accurate information to consumers regarding what they are eating.  Almost all food legislation now originates at EU level and a key change being faced at present by all stakeholders in the food chain concerns the implementation of the new hygiene regulations, which represent the single biggest change in food legislation in recent years.  The new legal obligations will have an impact on all food operations in Ireland, of which there are now approximately 44,000.</P>
        <P>The cornerstone of the new regulations is the requirement for traceability in the food chain.  The need for this has been widely discussed in the media and many different sectors of industry.  In particular, traceability helps to facilitate the withdrawal of food and enables consumers to be provided with targeted and accurate information concerning implicated products.  Current regulations require food business operators to have a so-called one-up and one-down system for traceability.  In others words, they must keep records of those from whom they purchase products and to whom they sell such products.</P>
        <P>Well-developed traceability systems provide food business operators with more than the simple ability to withdraw or recall food effectively, if required.  The ability to ensure the provenance of food and to satisfy consumers who need to know where their food comes from is also much <Col N="1119"/>easier.  While traceability is a legal requirement, it also makes good business sense.  There are few things worse for a food business operator than to be obliged to recall its product in the full glare of the media and the associated public attention that goes with such events.  It is at the time of such crises that advance planning is of major benefit and those companies that have crisis management plans in place usually will be able to limit reputation damage and economic loss.</P>
        <P>In regard to the provision of information, food labelling should provide sufficient information to help the consumer make an informed purchasing decision.  Proper labelling should encourage healthier food choice and may provide industry with incentive to reformulate foods that are less healthy such as, for example, those containing large quantities of trans fatty acids.</P>
        <P>The Government recognises the need for well-regulated labelling of foodstuffs.  The Department of Health and Children and the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food have produced a significant body of work in this area.  In the past two years, four pieces of EU labelling legislation have been transposed.  At national level, 2006 saw the enactment of primary legislation under which the beef labelling requirements on country of origin were extended to the catering sector.  This year saw the implementation of a consultation programme on country of origin labelling that culminated in draft national legislation.  This legislation is intended to extend mandatory country of origin food labelling to sheep, pig and poultry meats.  The two Departments are working closely together to make progress on the proposed legislation.  It will be necessary to notify the draft legislation to the European Commission to allow it and other member states an opportunity to comment.</P>
        <P>While much work has been done in the area of labelling by Departments, it must be recognised that industry also has a responsibility in this regard.  With this in mind, the Food Safety Authority of Ireland recently produced a new report on food labelling in Ireland and implemented a national campaign to highlight the importance of correct food product labelling.  The report, The Labelling of Food in Ireland 2007, aims to dispel confusion as to what a food label should contain.  This will ultimately assist food businesses in ensuring correct labelling and will benefit consumers by enabling them to make informed purchasing decisions based on clear and accurate labelling information.</P>
        <P>The 140-page report brings together in detail all Irish and European law governing the labelling of food.  It provides specific information and guidelines on labelling with regard to ingredients, additives, storage instructions, nutrition, novel foods and genetically modified foods.  In addition, there are special sections covering organic food labelling and specific requirements for commodi<Col N="1120"/>ties such as beef, chocolate, fruit juices and milk and sugar products.</P>
        <P>As with all areas of food safety, there is an international dimension to this work.  At present, EU food labelling legislation is harmonised by Council Directive 2000/13/EC, which was transposed into national legislation in 2002.  To date, there have been seven amendments to the transposing regulations which apply to the labelling of pre-packaged foodstuffs for sale to the ultimate consumer or for supply to mass caterers.  These regulations are based on the principle that food labelling should not mislead consumers.  While labelling should be clear, consistent and understandable, the current diversity of legislation, coupled with the range of regulations and directives in force, presents a complex and potentially confusing matrix.  It has therefore been recommended that the provisions currently spread across a number of texts be recast into a single simplified text.  A working group has been set up at EU level to consider changes to legislation in this area as part of the Commission&rsquo;s overall review of food labelling legislation.  As part of this process, Ireland submitted its particular concerns on food labelling to the Commission.  It is intended that the Commission will present the outcome of the working group&rsquo;s deliberations to the European Parliament in December.  Both the Department of Health and Children and the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food will be working closely with the European Commission on this important issue.</P>
        <P>I referred earlier to the increased complexity of the food safety area.  This is exemplified by the advent of foodstuffs containing genetically modified organisms, GMOs.  Although Ireland has traditionally adopted a precautionary but positive approach, the Irish public appears to be divided on this issue.  Government policy in this area is currently being re-evaluated to ensure that as far as possible the views of supporters and opponents of the use of GMOs are taken into account.</P>
        <P>I also mentioned that there were some areas of concern with regard to health promotion.  In general, there is much crossover between food safety and health promotion.  The importance of making an informed choice regarding food is emphasised by current research which suggests that just under 30% of cancer deaths are potentially avoidable by diet modification.  This makes diet second only to tobacco as a preventable cause of cancer.  To help the consumer to modify his or her diet for the better, the health promotion unit of the Department of Health and Children has, since the early 1990s, co-ordinated an annual national healthy eating campaign which aims to promote awareness of specific healthy eating messages and to provide practical information to the general public.  These campaigns have enhanced public awareness on healthy eating guidelines in terms of increasing fruit and vegetable and fibre intake, reducing fat <Col N="1121"/>intake and maintaining a healthy weight.  In addition, the Department is currently developing a national nutritional strategy.</P>
        <P>Healthy eating is just one component of health promotion.  The World Health Organisation has stated that regular physical activity is a significant element in the prevention and control of cancer.  There is consistent evidence that regular physical activity in some form is associated with a reduction in the risk of colon cancer.  The protective effect of physical activity improves with increasing levels of activity.  Twelve physical activity co-ordinators have been appointed in the HSE and structures have been put in place to provide advice and support in a number of settings, including schools, workplaces and communities, particularly targeting younger and older people.</P>
        <P>The Irish food environment has changed much in recent years and will change further in years to come.  The robustness of our food safety system has been severely tested and has so far passed.  I am confident it will also pass any future tests.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and wish him well in his new portfolio.  He has served with distinction in a number of Government Departments over the years and he now faces a new and important challenge in the area of food safety and preventative medicine.</P>
        <P>The question of food safety is of interest to every family and person in this country.  Fine Gael has a certain number of priorities in terms of marketing of Irish food, consumer issues and food imports.  As the Minister of State has heard over the last few years from my colleagues in the other House and from our spokespersons, we believe there should be a single food label for all Irish food products &mdash; a &ldquo;Green Ireland&rdquo; type of label which would be simple and easily recognisable and could be used in both the domestic and international market.  A label of this type would emphasise the ability of the Irish farmer to supply healthy, environmentally friendly and safe foods.  We are also adamant that the consumer must be fully protected.  This can only be achieved by ensuring supplies of safe, traceable and clearly labelled products which provide good value for money.  In addition, there will always be imported food, and we must seek and secure new regulations at EU level to ensure that all foodstuffs, particularly meat products, imported from outside the EU will be clearly labelled as such and that they will meet the same strict and exacting standards that apply to products produced by EU farmers.</P>
        <P>Over the past 20 or 30 years the focus of the food budget has changed and the proportion of family income spent on food has decreased.  When we joined the EEC in 1973, people were spending 30% to 35% of their weekly incomes on food, whereas now they spend a significantly <Col N="1122"/>lower percentage of their incomes, perhaps 8% to 10%.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">12 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P>We must question whether cheap food can be quality food.  This issue was addressed some time ago by Professor Patrick Wall who warned consumers of the quality of cheap imported foods.  It is not possible to produce quality, safe, premium food at knock-down prices.  We must send out to the Irish consumer the message that the production of quality, safe, wholesome food comes at a price.  We must be concerned about some of the food imported from outside the European Union and placed on the shelves of big chain stores.</P>
        <P>Meat products imported from Asia and Third World countries are often reprocessed by way of the addition of breadcrumbs, as in the case of chicken, and deemed to have been produced in Ireland.  We must be careful to ensure that type of labelling is not permitted in the future and that only meat produced within the European Union, and in Ireland in particular, is labelled as such.  Fine Gael is adamant that the green Ireland labelling system be put in place as soon as possible.  The consumer is king and he or she will decide what price is appropriate.  We must ensure that when consumers make a choice in respect of quality, price and value for money, they know exactly what they are paying for and what they are obtaining.  I am concerned that some of the cheaper foodstuffs which sometimes masquerade as foodstuffs produced in the European Union are not so produced and may be of a quality with which we would not be comfortable.</P>
        <P>I readily concede that the Food Safety Authority of Ireland has done a great deal of work in terms of building up a national system of health and safety regulation for producers and retailers.  I understand it is involved in various media campaigns informing consumers and producers about clear and accurate food labelling.  However, as I stated earlier, an issue arises in respect of misleading labelling of foodstuffs imported from outside the European Union.  This type of misleading labelling is worse than no labelling at all.  The voluntary controls and inspections, which we hoped would resolve this problem, have not resulted in change.  For this reason and to ensure the consumer is aware of where products are produced, we must introduce the green labelling system.  The loopholes in our existing legislation are allowing products produced outside of Ireland, such as chicken from Asia or beef from Brazil, to be passed off as Irish products following minimal processing here.  This is not acceptable.  I hope the Minister of State and his Department will tackle this issue.</P>
        <P>I mentioned earlier the good work being done by the Food Safety Authority of Ireland.  Part of its work and research has identified the false labelling of products, something which must be of concern to us.  The European Union, European Commission and European political system are obviously to the fore in trying to promote food <Col N="1123"/>safety and health.  However, some of the inspections carried out by the European Union in respect of foodstuffs produced outside Europe and imported into Europe have identified inferior hygiene and quality standards yet these foodstuffs continue to be appear on supermarket shelves and, in some case, on the restaurant table.  The lack of labelling in this regard denies the consumer the right to make an informed choice.</P>
        <P>An issue about which people are now speaking in terms of quality food is that of food miles and how far food has to travel from the farm gate to the table.  Most meat consumed in Ireland 40 or 50 years ago, pre-European Union accession, was produced on local farms.  This has changed and we are now advised that the average distance travelled by the average food product can be approximately 3,000 miles, making food less nutritious than local produce and more at risk of damage through transportation and handling.  The absence of a clear guaranteed Irish label makes choosing Irish produce a trial.  There is a much greater willingness on the part of Irish consumers nowadays, as a result of our increased wealth, to seek out better quality food and to pay the slightly higher price that such food costs.  It is often not possible for the consumer to make that choice given the lack of a clear guaranteed Irish labelling system.  It is important we try to rectify this situation.</P>
        <P>My colleagues in Fine Gael have done a great deal of work during the past three or four years in respect of the rip-off, in terms of the cost of food, being endured by the Irish consumer.  One of our most recent surveys indicated that shoppers are often ripped-off by mark-ups of more than 200% on basic food items by supermarkets.  We must be concerned about this and try to tackle the problem.  Consumers must be guaranteed quality, safe food and they must be permitted to make healthy choices.</P>
        <P>Experience in the United Kingdom has shown that shoppers want to purchase healthy food and that following the introduction there of a proper labelling system, sales of unhealthy food decreased by 40%.  The Minister of State referred to the role of food in health promotion, disease prevention, cancer prevention and in tackling obesity levels.  We have a long way to go in this debate.  The debate on obesity and the role of quality food in health promotion and disease prevention has only begun.  It is important the Minister of State leads this debate.</P>
        <P>Again, perhaps because of our increased wealth and increased disposable income, people are consuming greater volumes of foodstuffs that can lead to obesity and an increased risk of heart disease and cancer.  We must continue to promote the consumption of healthy, quality, nutritious, natural food not only in terms of it being better for one&rsquo;s diet and the most satisfying, but also in terms of it being the best food from a disease prevention point of view.  The Minister of State&rsquo;s <Col N="1124"/>comments in respect of disease prevention and his work in that regard are important.  I wish him well in that regard.</P>
        <P>The importation of Brazilian beef is causing serious concern for Irish farmers.  I accept the importation of Brazilian beef perhaps relates more to the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food than to the Department of Health and Children.  However, the Irish beef industry is in crisis and Irish farmers see Brazilian beef being imported at will into the European Union and being placed on supermarket shelves in Ireland and Europe.  This is a source of great distress to the Irish agriculture sector and it should be of concern to consumers because of the clear lack of health and quality checks on Brazilian beef.</P>
        <P>The Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Deputy Coughlan, has been remiss at European Union level in not tackling this problem in a more serious fashion, and in not seeking a full ban on the importation of Brazilian beef.  The standards we have in Ireland and the standards that are demanded throughout the European Union are much higher than the standards being imposed on Brazilian and other South American farmers.  It is not good enough that one set of standards apply at home, yet Brazilian and other South American beef can be imported and placed on Irish supermarket shelves and tables without strict controls applying.</P>
        <P>I urge the Minister of State, Deputy Gallagher, to raise the issue of the importation of Brazilian beef with the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food because in the long run it will not just be the income of Irish farmers that will suffer but the health of consumers.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NedOSullivan"><NameTxt>Senator Ned O&rsquo;Sullivan</NameTxt>
	<P>Ba mhaith liom ar dt&uacute;s f&aacute;ilte a chuir roimh an Aire.  T&aacute;imse an-bhu&iacute;och d&oacute; as ucht an l&eacute;ar&aacute;id suimi&uacute;il a thug s&eacute; d&uacute;inn ar maidin.  I welcome the Minister of State and thank him for a most interesting presentation.  I wish him well in this challenging portfolio.  I also welcome the thoughtful contribution made by Senator Bradford.  I agree with the many interesting points he made.</P>
        <P>It is a sign of a forward-thinking Government that we now have a dedicated Minister of State with responsibility for health promotion and food safety and that a section of the Department of Health and Children is now dedicated to dealing with this important issue, which is becoming more important in today&rsquo;s health conscious society.</P>
        <P>We are fortunate to live in a country where the quality rather than the quantity of food is at issue.  My generation is probably the first generation that lived free from the shadow of the &ldquo;great hunger&rdquo;.  We have come to expect full and plenty on a year round basis.  We witness shocking scenes on television of famine and horror in Third World countries and when we commiserate with those unfortunate individuals we realise how lucky we are to be able to have three square meals a day.  It is not so much the availability of <Col N="1125"/>food but the quality of it that is important.  It is vital for the Government to ensure, in so far as it is possible, that the food we eat is free of inferior ingredients, shoddy practices and poor hygiene.</P>
        <P>I acknowledge and welcome the invaluable work being done by the Food Safety Authority and the Food Safety Promotion Board.  The image of a clean, green Ireland, which is so important to our economy, is being safeguarded by these agencies and their subsidiaries, along with their partners in Bord Bia and the overlapping work done by the Departments of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food and Health and Children.  Of the 4,500 staff in the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, approximately 2,000 people are employed in the area of food safety and quality assurance.</P>
        <P>I welcome the interest in this matter of the Minister of State, Deputy Gallagher, and his counterpart in the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Deputy Sargent.  In fairness to the Green Party, it has taken a lead in many of the issues we are discussing.  The Minister of State, Deputy Sargent, will be in my home town of Listowel tonight to open the annual food fair which was organised by Deputy Deenihan.  I know the Minister of State will get a warm welcome.</P>
        <P>I see Senator O&rsquo;Toole is present in the Chamber.  He recently raised in the House the issue of the disappearance of mutton.  He will be delighted to hear one of the competitions in the Listowel food fair this year is the making of mutton pies, which were a staple diet for people attending the Listowel races.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>In the rest of the county they are called Dingle pies.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NedOSullivan"><NameTxt>Senator Ned O&rsquo;Sullivan</NameTxt>
	<P>In Listowel we call them mutton pies.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State referred to the issue of traceability, which is a key element in guaranteeing customer satisfaction.  Progressive restaurateurs and hoteliers have turned regulation into an opportunity.  They have cottoned on to the fact that if one advertises Limerick ham, Wicklow lamb or Clonakilty black pudding on a menu that it is attractive to the customer and it also ensures people know from where the product is coming.  Many restaurateurs now cite the individual farmer who is the source of the beef, lamb or other product, which is a good practice and is good for business.</P>
        <P>Even though we have regulations in this regard, they are more often honoured in the breach than the observance by restaurateurs who are not all at the bottom end of the market.  One often wonders about the source of last night&rsquo;s beef lasagna or chicken curry.  I am indebted to my colleague, Senator Corrigan, for pointing out that in certain retail establishments where a dish like lasagna is prepared in-house, there is no onus on the proprietor to indicate the country of origin of the <Col N="1126"/>beef used in it.  I urge the Minister of State to examine this anomaly to establish whether this is the case.  If so, the system is very open to abuse and could lead to a serious health hazard.</P>
        <P>Senator Bradford referred to Irish farmers.  There is no doubt they are keen and proud to comply with the most stringent of regulation.  The Minister of State said almost all of our food regulation comes directly from Europe.  It is galling for farmers to see that food products that would not have been subjected to the same hygiene regime experienced by Irish farmers are being imported here and sold at knock-down prices in competition with Irish farm produce.  It is difficult for Irish farmers to put up with that.</P>
        <P>We were briefed recently by the IFA in the Mansion House on the issue of labelling.  It was pointed out that non-Irish bacon is imported here in bulk and is then dressed, packaged, vacuum-packed or sliced and sold on as an Irish product, which is misleading.  The suspicion is that this may be going on in other sectors also and this sharp practice should be stopped.  In a D&aacute;il debate on 24 October 2007, the Minister emphasised the importance of good food information.  We need clear, unambiguous data to be readily available to customers.</P>
        <P>I take issue with Senator Bradford on one matter.  He referred to the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Deputy Coughlan, as being in some way deficient in terms of ensuring the highest standards in regard to the importation of Brazilian beef.  I commend the Minister for the hard work she has done to initiate European Union regulations, quite a number of which have already been put in place following her efforts.</P>
        <P>I received a report by e-mail from a veterinary mission which travelled to Brazil.  I look forward to reading the full results, which I expect will make for interesting reading.  The Minister, Deputy Coughlan, stated that Commissioner Kyprianou will not hesitate to take whatever action is required if there is any risk to Irish livestock, consumers or plants.</P>
        <P>I wish to digress briefly and refer to vegetables.  It is a matter of ongoing concern that so many of the vegetables sold here are imported.  Even the potato, which was historically our staple diet, is likely to be Dutch nowadays.  It seems the only product in the vegetable sector in which we have a strong export balance is the mushroom, although I am not sure what this tells us.</P>
        <P>I do not want to turn us back to the day when every cottier had his couple of acres and grew his potatoes and root crops.  There is enormous potential in this area from a health, nourishment and economic perspective.  If there were a new emphasis on home tillage and vegetable production, we would not have the same reliance on imports and the Irish consumer would prefer to have the choice of Irish products.  The Minister of State, Deputy Gallagher, should consult his colleagues in the Department of Agriculture to find <Col N="1127"/>out how we might redress the economic and nutrition balance.</P>
        <P>The public has come to expect the highest standards.  To paraphrase Senator Quinn, who used the expression &ldquo;crowning the customer&rdquo; in his book, it is now a matter of crowning the consumer.  Consumers must be prioritised because they are no longer prepared to accept standards lower than premium or first class.  We must work harder to involve producers and the agribusiness sector in developing and working towards healthy practices.  Those sectors have not been slow in this regard.  I am proud of a Kerry-based organisation, Kerry Group plc, which has been a leader in this area and is represented on the boards of the Food Safety Authority of Ireland and Bord Bia.  However, there is room for further improvement nationally.</P>
        <P>We have come a long way from the hygiene standards which obtained when the following joke was coined.  A small shopkeeper &mdash; I think he was a Donegal man &mdash; had some American visitors.  There was a big side of bacon on the counter with a couple of bluebottles buzzing around it.  The shopkeeper rolled up his newspaper and flattened the bluebottles onto the bacon, and said: &ldquo;I&rsquo;m very strict on the hygiene, you know.&rdquo;  We have moved on from that time.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PhilPrendergast"><NameTxt>Senator Phil Prendergast</NameTxt>
	<P>Was he from Donegal?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>It would not happen in Kerry.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NedOSullivan"><NameTxt>Senator Ned O&rsquo;Sullivan</NameTxt>
	<P>We must be ever more vigilant.  Change will not happen overnight.  As Bob Dylan said, we have to keep on keeping on.</P>
        <P>Another issue that might be examined is the question of food provision at major events, which is a bugbear of mine.  People believe they can drop their standards with regard to sporting occasions, rock festivals and the like, where shoddy practices are in evidence.  I am amazed there are not more reports of food poisoning and ill health as a result.  My particular hobby-horse for years was the quality of catering at racecourses, which was a scandal, although the prices were straight from Maxim&rsquo;s.  The predecessor of the Horse Racing Authority, the Irish Racing Board, tackled this issue with great success and one is now assured of clean, safe food at racecourses.  The prices are still Parisian but that is another matter.</P>
        <P>No reference was made to drinks.  I am concerned with health and safety issues in this area owing to the proliferation of available spirits, especially vodka.  There are now many themed vodka bars and specialist hostelries where customers do not know exactly what is being consumed.  There are also vodka-laced alcopops which are quite lethal.  While we must depend on <Col N="1128"/>the maturity of adults, there is a health issue due to the lack of knowledge in this area.</P>
        <P>Scotch whisky seems to be accepted as the premium whiskey throughout the world, when any judge of whiskey knows the best Scotch only comes close to the purity and maturity of an Irish whiskey.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Well said.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NedOSullivan"><NameTxt>Senator Ned O&rsquo;Sullivan</NameTxt>
	<P>Despite this, one can visit the best international chains in the world and there will be 20 Scotch whiskies, ten American whiskeys and ten Canadian whiskies but no Irish whiskey.  While this is not a health issue, it is one that can be considered from an economic perspective.</P>
        <P>If one walks through any city of the world, one will see South American steak restaurants,<?oasys _jy ?>Pampas themed restaurants, Latin American<?oasys _jy ?>restaurants and so on.  Where are the Irish<?oasys _jy ?>steakhouses?  We have ubiquitous Irish pubs, which are about as Irish as chicken chop suey, but there are no Irish steakhouses although we are supposed to be the best producers of beef in the world.  Somebody is falling down in this regard.</P>
        <P>I have moved from addressing health issues to marketing issues, so I will conclude.  I commend the Minister of State on the great work he is doing.  I look forward to working with him and his Department in the years ahead.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to share time with Senator Norris.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Roche, to the House.  I found the contribution of Senator O&rsquo;Sullivan most interesting.  I recently asked for two debates on food issues, one on food quality and the other on food safety, and this is the first of the two.  We need to consider these issues.</P>
        <P>I remind the Minister of State, Deputy Roche, of an issue on which he and I were slightly culpable as Members of this House in the late 1980s, namely, the passing of the Abattoirs Act 1988, which was the biggest legislative mistake we have made for many years on food issues.  Like many Members, I grew up in a town where, when one ordered meat from the local butcher, it most likely came from his own or a neighbour&rsquo;s farm and traceability was a very simple issue.  Now, even the best organised butcher&rsquo;s shop might have difficulty telling a customer from where the meat it is selling came because it is buying from a central abattoir in vacuum-packed trays.  We are spending billions to improve traceability although it was not an issue in the past.  As the question of the provenance of food is so important, we must examine this issue.</P><Col N="1129"/>
        <P>I agree with a point made by Senator O&rsquo;Sullivan.  I recently went to what is probably the best food shop in Dublin at present, Fallon and Byrne in Wicklow Street.  It had a fantastic selection of mushrooms, such as chantelles and many other types one does not see in shops any longer.  We have destroyed the taste of mushrooms.  There is no comparison between the taste of wild mushrooms, which people picked and put on the fire with a knob of butter, and the tasteless stuff that comes from dark, covered growing areas nowadays.  This is because we have not trained growers in the area of taste and related aspects.</P>
        <P>I agree with Senator Bradford and the IFA on the issue of Brazilian meat.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>Irish farmers have made an argument that is convincing to any interested person.  I have not heard an answer to this simple question: why, if foot and mouth disease is found in this country, does the whole country close down, whereas if it happens in another country, that country can still export to us?  It does not make sense.  I do not add to this a criticism of the Minister, Deputy Coughlan.  As Senator O&rsquo;Sullivan noted, she has made every attempt to move Europe&rsquo;s position on this issue.  The Government should state clearly that this is wrong.  If necessary, we should pass legislation to protect our farmers.</P>
        <P>The issue of food labelling is related to that of food safety.  I would like to conduct a survey of Oireachtas Members to find whether they know the difference between Irish smoked salmon and smoked Irish salmon.  I suspect most would not.  Most would simply read the word &ldquo;Irish&rdquo; and would not know that Irish smoked salmon is more than likely imported salmon which has been smoked in Ireland.  Also, the distinction between wild and other salmon has not been properly made.</P>
        <P>An area related to food safety in which Ireland is badly lacking is how we develop new products in a safe way.  The Minister of State, Deputy Gallagher, has just left the House.  I intended to remind him that not long ago air-dried venison from Donegal was available in good food shops in Senator Keaveney&rsquo;s constituency.  It was a beautiful product, pure black, well presented and very unusual, yet the company producing it has gone out of business.  As far as I know, it came from the place famous for its connection with Tabasco sauce, and the venison was raised and air-dried on the McElhinny farm.  This country does not produce air-dried bacon, venison or beef.  We import Serrano ham and we pay big money for it.  We could produce this ourselves.</P>
        <P>In terms of the issue of drink which was touched on by Senator O&rsquo;Sullivan, we should give some recognition and more support to local breweries.  I was in the west recently and saw a very <Col N="1130"/>unusual and cloudy beer, which one does not see in Ireland.  It is usually a continental commodity.  It was named &ldquo;Galway Hooker&rdquo;.  I inquired about it.  It is made in Roscommon and it is available in certain hostelries in Galway city and also in other parts of Connacht and down as far as Limerick.  This is something that needs to be encouraged.</P>
        <P>Many years ago the Government attempted to develop a new product, one-calf heifers, and failed.  I mentioned mutton in the House previously.  That is a product one can buy all over France.  I am glad Senator O&rsquo;Sullivan mentioned it.  Mutton is available in some restaurants in Dublin.  Roly&rsquo;s Bistro sells Kerry pies as one of its signature dishes, and it is a mutton pie.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Senator Paddy Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>Do they have mutton in Kate Kearney&rsquo;s Cottage?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>That is a good question.  They probably do.  The reason it is important is that it is mountain mutton with a small bone in it and it has a different taste to lowland mutton.  That is what people should look for.  In France, where people value the taste of food, they still maintain a taste in chickens.  They sell hens, <i>chapons</i>, which are year-old chickens, usually corn fed.  Each one is numbered.  They are expensive.  They cost &euro;12 in the supermarket but they are available.  Beside them in continental supermarkets &mdash; and this is an issue on which I have never received an answer &mdash; is Irish lamb, <i>agneau Irlandais</i>, and Irish lamb is cheaper in continental Europe, especially in France, than it is in Ireland.  I often bring this to the attention of my colleague, Senator Quinn.  I do not understand why it is the case.  It has something to do with regulation.</P>
        <P>I live, at the moment, in north County Dublin, which used to be the centre of the Irish vegetable industry.  People go to France and to continental Europe and take photographs of vegetable displays.  They want to know why we cannot have these lovely shiny large vegetables in Ireland.  The answer is very simple.  We apply the regulations here and that is not done in any other European country.  I can walk into a food market in Provence in France and see cucumbers, root vegetables, tomatoes in particular, which would not get through the sorting system to get into the Dublin vegetable market.  They would be dumped here.  More good food is dumped here than is sold in other countries.  We need to examine the regulation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I hesitate to interrupt the Senator&rsquo;s flow but as he wishes to share his time with Senator Norris, I should issue a gentle reminder at this stage.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>Other issues are the regulations relating to cottage industry, farmers&rsquo; markets and farmer outlets.  Does the Minister of State know that there are farmers doing quite <Col N="1131"/>well selling vegetables to local people at the farm gate but they cannot include in the sale anything which has not been grown on the farm?  One can buy a variety of vegetables but one might also want to buy ginger which would not have been grown on the farm and, because of ridiculous legislation, farmers are not allowed to sell that.</P>
        <P>Somebody who wants to set up a sandwich business in Ireland to cater for four schools and a small factory, which would be a small operation, must fulfil the same regulations that would apply to the establishment of an Irish version of Freshways to cater for the whole country.  There is a lack of balance in the regulations.  We are overly enthusiastic about some of these.  I have tried to be practical.  I could say much more on these issues.  The Department is doing a reasonable job in moving this forward, but there are many more practical, simple things it could do.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I am grateful to my colleague for sharing his time.  I welcome the Minister of State.  I wish to raise a small number of concerns.  The first is the question of labelling which was raised by my colleague, Senator O&rsquo;Toole, who is very interested in this area.  I am concerned, as he is, because people, including shopkeepers, do not appear to appreciate the difference between &ldquo;use by&rdquo; and &ldquo;best before&rdquo; dates.  This has been drawn to our attention by Dr. John O&rsquo;Brien, Chief Executive of the Food Safety Authority of Ireland.  He says:</P>
        <P LI="1">It is alarming that some businesses are ignorant about this most basic, but critical labelling requirement &mdash; the shelflife of the product.  Our campaign simply explains that a &lsquo;Use By&rsquo; date is used on products that are highly perishable and if they are consumed after their &lsquo;Use By&rsquo; date they could cause illness.  &lsquo;Best Before&rsquo; dates refer to a period that a product remains at its best condition and whilst people can eat products after the &lsquo;Best Before&rsquo; date has passed, they may disappoint in terms of quality but they should not pose a food safety risk.</P>
        <P FLI="0">This is a very significant point if there is misunderstanding not just by shoppers but also by shopkeepers.  The authority also examined breakfast cereal that was labelled as gluten free and yet was found to contain high levels of gluten.  That is very dangerous for people who suffer from coeliac disease.  Labelling is clearly an important and significant element.  There is also the question of items labelled as Irish when they are of foreign origin.  A study of 55 different kinds of noodles for irradiation found that approximately 25% of products had irradiated ingredients.  There is a legal requirement that this be stated on the label but it was not.</P>
        <P>This leads me to the question of genetically modified foods.  I would like the Minister of State to take this very seriously, as the Minister of State, Deputy Trevor Sargent, does.  I draw the <Col N="1132"/>attention of the Minister of State to a very interesting book, entitled <i>Genetic Roulette</i>, by Jeffrey M. Smith.  The information contained in it is very worrying.  It is compiled by scientists and it demonstrates clearly that in terms of genetically modified crops, frequently the pollen from those crops can adversely affect the health of people living in the area.  We have noticed, even in this country, an increase in allergies.  This situation will only be made worse if we do not retain our status as a GM free country.  I note the Minister of State, Deputy Sargent, is committed to this position and I applaud him for it.</P>
        <P>It is important we would remain committed to this position even if there were not scientific worries.  From a marketing and labelling point of view, it would very advantageous for us to be able to indicate that our food products were free of this material.  However, it is a position that is very difficult to maintain.  Tesco, for example, has a GM free policy but this has been vitiated because their own brand American long grain rice was recently contaminated with Bayer CropScience&rsquo;s genetically modified American long-grain GM rice variety LL601.  It was discovered in two packs of Tesco dried American long grain rice.  This is illegal in the EU and the USA, yet it managed to get into the shops in Ireland.  That is how penetrative it is.</P>
        <P>Monsanto is behind most of this.  Monsanto claims, through Mr. Robert Shapiro, the chief executive officer, to be interested in all kinds of ideals of feeding the world and so on.  In the introduction to the book <i>Genetic Roulette</i> it is recounted that somebody who was idealistically motivated by the speeches, words and writings of Mr. Shapiro took a job there and was told by senior management that what Robert Shapiro says is one thing but what they do is something else.  They are there to make money.  He is the front man who tells a story.  They do not even understand what he is saying.  That is what we are dealing with.  A scientific committee which was established in the United Kingdom made certain quite worrying findings.  Subsequently it was disbanded.  It is time we looked at the question of genetically modified food, the idea of patenting life forms and the questions raised about whether there can be pollution of neighbouring areas from genetically modified crops.  There have been court cases about that where neighbouring farmers found their crops were contaminated but were then sued by Monsanto.  The judgment of the Canadian court was that regardless of whether the farmer was responsible, and it was found he had not stolen the material, he was responsible.  He owed money to Monsanto precisely because it had patented the life form and was entitled to a return on it, regardless of whether he had taken it from elsewhere or planted it.  It was due to the fact that it crept in&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
	<P>Your time is up, Senator. </P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1133"/>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>This is an extraordinary takeover of our food resources and the Government would be right to resist it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DeirdredeBurca"><NameTxt>Senator D&eacute;irdre de B&uacute;rca</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and the opportunity to speak about the Government policy on food safety and health promotion.  </P>
        <P>The point has been made already that the food sector is an important sector in the Irish economy.  It is estimated that it directly employs approximately 300,000 people and that in 2006, the sectors of food retailing and tourism, respectively, contributed &euro;12 billion and &euro;5.9 billion to the economy, almost &euro;20 billion between them.  It is clearly a very important sector and our national policy on food safety is central to protecting the reputation of our food sector and improving the image of Irish food exports abroad.</P>
        <P>I am delighted that my Green Party colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Sargent, is now the Minister of State with responsibility for food and horticulture at the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food.  He has a major interest in the issue of food and food safety and the promotion of Irish food internationally as a quality product.</P>
        <P>I look forward to many of the initiatives my colleague will support and promote during his term of office.  In the programme for Government, some of the goals that have been agreed will make a positive contribution towards general food safety and food promotion here, one of them being the agreement to convert a minimum of 5% of national acreage to organic farmland by 2012.  That will be no small feat because currently less than 1% of our farmland nationally is dedicated to organic farming and as we are aware, organic produce offers significant health benefits to consumers because it is produced without the use of chemical herbicides, pesticides and fertilisers.</P>
        <P>I recently attended, with the Minister of State, Deputy Sargent, a meeting of the Irish Organic Trust in the Brook Lodge Hotel in my constituency of Wicklow, which has put itself on the map as the leading Irish hotel with the only fully certified organic restaurant.  Some frustration was expressed by those involved in organic farming about the difficulties they are experiencing in trying to access organic produce.  The chief executive of Flahavan&rsquo;s spoke at the AGM and told us he has to import 90% of organic oatlets for the organic porridge he sells because it is impossible to source organic oats here.  We must provide many incentives to encourage conventional farmers to be part of the move to dedicating a greater percentage of our national acreage to organic farming.  The more organic produce we can produce here, the more it will enhance the reputation of the food we are producing because there is a growing consumer demand for organic produce which Ireland would be foolish not to exploit.  We have a strong green image and given <Col N="1134"/>the growing public concerns about genetically modified foods, which other speakers mentioned also, it is important that Ireland would capitalise on its clean, green image and the opportunity to develop this island as a GM-free island.  I was delighted to see that objective in the current programme for Government and the decisions recently made in Brussels by the Government reflected that change in emphasis.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Other European countries have clearly placed restrictions on GM organisms and produce ranging from Austria, which has a strong ban, to other countries, in particular regions in France, Italy and so on, which have strong organic markets and restrictions on the growing and cultivation of GM produce.  It is important to point out, however, that there are difficulties because of WTO rules which are placing great pressure on the European Union to open its markets fully to GM produce, often coming from very large producers such as the United States, Australia, Canada and so on.  We must have an enlightened policy at EU level.  I hope that the fact that many individual member states already have these restrictions in place, and Ireland will join them in having a very proactive policy on becoming a GM-free island, will be reflected in the kinds of decisions that are made within the Council of Ministers in the coming years.</P>
        <P>Another issue close to this one is the issue of GM feed and the current dependence of Irish farmers on imported GM feed.  Unfortunately, Irish consumers are not aware that in terms of much of the meat they are eating, the animals have been fed GM feed because it is the most affordable feed available to the majority of farmers.  Those who have expressed an interest and sought to source non-GM feed find it prohibitively expensive.  There is an onus on the Government, given the commitment we have made in the programme for Government, to work towards making Ireland GM-free.  We must help farmers and the farming sector to access affordable GM-free feed to ensure that Irish consumers can be confident that the meat they are eating is genuinely GM-free.</P>
        <P>That leads on to the issue of labelling.  Currently, food must be labelled as GM if it contains above 0.9% of GM ingredients.  An EU wide survey of food products was carried out in 2006 &mdash; it was carried out here by the State Laboratory.  Unfortunately, low levels of GM rice that had been illegally imported from the US were found in five out of the 19 food products it examined.  That obliged food retailers like Tesco and Marks &amp; Spencer to withdraw those products from their shelves.  The correct labelling of food is essential to a healthy food sector and is something consumers are increasingly demanding.  It is important that if there are GM ingredients in the food we are eating, they should be clearly labelled as such.  There should be proper implementation of the requirement that any foods contain<Col N="1135"/>ing over 0.9% of GM ingredients would be so labelled.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">1 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>On a related issue, I am delighted that the Minister of State, Deputy Roche, is present because in his brief he would probably be aware that an EU directive on food supplements was adopted in 2002 but it is being implemented in different phases.  Currently, maximum permitted levels of food supplements are being set by the EU Commission, and the Irish health food sector is extremely concerned about that.  When we talk about healthy food we must also recognise that many natural food supplements would come under this heading.  It is of concern to the health food sector here that maximum limits are being set that appear to be unduly precautionary, extremely prohibitive and that will have a negative impact on the health food sector and on the growing discipline of nutritional therapists.  They are currently lobbying the Government for a slightly more flexible approach to the setting of these limits by the EU Commission.  I hope the Minister of State, Deputy Roche, will be able to use his position to advocate for the interests of the Irish health food sector in the discussions that take place with the EU Commission.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PhilPrendergast"><NameTxt>Senator Phil Prendergast</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to share my time with Senator Buttimer.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
	<P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PhilPrendergast"><NameTxt>Senator Phil Prendergast</NameTxt>
	<P>I am delighted to be part of this debate and welcome the Minister of State to the House.  Many of the issues have been raised already and I will not go into them again.  The other day, a baker informed me that while he is obliged to list all ingredients on a product label, there is no obligation to list the products used in wrappers, many of which are sprayed with chemicals.  I had never considered this issue before but it is a matter of concern.  He also pointed out that preservatives and chemicals are used to keep food fresh, a word I use advisedly.  Is legislation planned to oblige manufacturers to inform consumers that chemicals have been added to keep products fresh?</P>
      
        <P>I am concerned at the frequency with which environmental health officers visit fast food outlets, particularly those which operate late at night.  The temperature at which foods are stored and the condition of other facilities in such outlets is a matter of concern.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State noted the increased complexity of food safety in the area of genetically modified organisms.  I also acknowledge Senator de B&uacute;rca&rsquo;s contribution on this issue.  The Minister of State noted:</P>
        <P LI="1">Although Ireland has traditionally adopted a precautionary but positive approach, the Irish public appears to be divided on this issue.  Government policy in this area is currently <Col N="1136"/>being re-evaluated to ensure that as far as possible the views of supporters and opponents of the use of GMOs are taken into account.</P>
        <P FLI="0">When will this re-evaluation be completed?  Who is contributing to the debate?  In what forum is information on GMO foods being collated?</P>
        <P>It was interesting to learn that when animals fed GMO foods are sold on, there is no obligation to label the resulting food products as GM modified.  It is a serious error to allow members of the public to be denied the full facts.</P>
        <P>Recently, I had occasion, as a former employee in the health service, to visit a boys&rsquo; school to speak to a group of young transition year students on diet, healthy living and exercise.  We had great fun during a debate on childhood obesity and the students made a knowledgeable and substantial contribution to the discussion.  We talked about the importance of having breakfast and drinking water and I asked them to take part in an experiment.  Instead of having breakfast rolls for lunch, they were told to eat the home cooked ham for lunch.  I was aware that this product was supplied to the outlet they visited to buy lunch.  Later that day, the shopkeeper in question contacted me to tell me I had not done him any favours as he had been left with many unsold sausages, rashers and eggs because the children had chosen a healthier option.  This small experiment had an effect because the students tried an alternative and some of the them changed their lunchtime choices.</P>
        <P>It takes five hours to burn off 300 calories &mdash; the equivalent of three digestive biscuits &mdash; if one is sitting and one hour if one engages in moderate walking.  Awareness is lacking about the extent of over-eating.  A survey on portion size indicated that a regular lunch consisting of a 250 ml soft drink, a 25g packet of crisps, two slices of bread with a slice of cooked meat and a chocolate bar contains 702 calories, which would make a substantial contribution to a person&rsquo;s daily calorie intake.  It has now become normal to sell lunches consisting of a 500 ml soft drink, a 40g packet of crisps, three slices of bread with two slices of cooked meat and a chocolate bar.  Such a lunch contains 1,294 calories but because it is not labelled, people are not aware that it makes a major contribution to obesity.  The large increase in the incidence of childhood obesity has major economic and health implications.  Childhood obesity has caused a large increase in the incidence of diabetes.  At any given time, 70% of those who have diabetes are not aware they suffer from the condition.  It is easy to diagnose the disease by performing a simple blood test.  The absence of proper labelling and the practice of labelling sugar in a variety of different guises means we are not aware of what exactly we are eating.</P>
        <P>I am concerned to learn that it is possible to add breadcrumbs to food sourced in other countries and then label it as manufactured in Ireland.  This is dishonest and dangerous practice.  We <Col N="1137"/>need to have a proper analysis of the contents of food items to allow us to make informed and safe choices.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>It was Socrates who said that we should eat to live and not live to eat.  Herein lies our predicament.  The food industry is worth almost &euro;20 billion per annum.  At minimum, we must have safe food.  The role of the Food Safety Authority and the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food is to pursue this objective.  An unpublished Food Safety Authority report suggests the organisation has turned a blind eye &mdash; perhaps &ldquo;averted its gaze&rdquo; is a more appropriate description &mdash; to the issue of food labelling and traceability. </P>
        <P>Ordinary people, whether they have dinner at 1 p.m. or 6 p.m., eat a home-cooked meal or purchase food in a restaurant or on their way from work, must have confidence that the food they eat is safe.  Senators on all sides of the political divide agree on the need to protect consumers and address the misinformation in food labelling and food safety.  In a fine contribution, Senator O&rsquo;Sullivan discussed in detail the whole issue of food.</P>
        <P>The Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Deputy Mary Coughlan, must take a strong stance on Brazilian beef.  Irish farmers and consumers should be told that the European Union, particularly Ireland, will not become a haven for Brazilian beef.  For how much longer can we tolerate the current position?  I attended an IFA briefing on Brazilian beef imports.  The association is not scare-mongering and it is clear we have reached the point at which we can go no further.  I ask the Minister of State, Deputy Pat The Cope Gallagher, to vigorously pursue this matter with the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food.  We must have confidence in food.</P>
        <P>The Fine Gael Party proposed the establishment of a single food label for all Irish products which, I understand, would be known as &ldquo;Green Ireland&rdquo;.   Such an initiative would increase brand recognition of Irish products abroad.  Senator<b> </b>Ned O&rsquo;Sullivan referred to Irish beef being sold in restaurants here.  We should be proud to market Irish food on international markets.  Senator Bradford referred to food miles.  The global market has become a global village.  We need to have a single, simple recognisable brand for all Irish foods.  I accept, however, that considerable efforts are being made in this area.</P>
      
        <P>European Union regulations do not always take cognisance of local conditions pertaining to food.  I concur with Senators O&rsquo;Toole and O&rsquo;Sullivan on the issue of vegetables.  Some years ago, Dinny and his free range eggs in the television programme, &ldquo;Glenroe&rdquo;, highlighted the fact that we must examine how to produce good food and offer choice in the home market.  Many large retail outlets do not use Irish vegetables or meat.</P><Col N="1138"/>
        <P>I concur with the Minister of State regarding health promotion.  The food pyramid idea should be used in schools in educating young people, but we are being disingenuous at one level.  The Department does considerable marketing work in respect of fresh food and healthy options, but the national healthy eating campaign is diluted by a lack of adequate physical education facilities and inadequate PE teacher staffing levels in many instances.  Recently, I met a PE teacher in my constituency who has been qualified for four years or five years and cannot get a full-time job.  Despite being serious about the campaign, we are taking away from the good work of the Department.  In this respect, will the Minister of State discuss the provision of PE facilities with the Minister for Education and Science?</P>
        <P>Will the Minister of State consider traceability?  We must address the imbalance.  If we are to promote nutritional food, we must ensure adequate traceability.  A host of regulations on the clear labelling of meat and other foodstuffs imported from outside Europe are being introduced at EU level.  These comprise a minimum prerequisite.</P>
        <P>On the hazardous analysis and critical control points system in operation in every chain of supply, be it regarding fast food outlets or restaurants, I agree with Senator O&rsquo;Sullivan concerning the provision of fast food at certain events.  How adequately are these outlets policed by environmental health officers?  Sometimes, we read court reports in newspapers telling of how some restaurants have been closed because they do not adhere to the structures, etc.  In tandem with the Food Safety Authority, these closures inspire confidence, which Ireland needs.  Our nation used to produce marvellous food.  I do not comprehend why the clean, nutritious and healthy food produced in Ireland, as compared with other types of food, is not used in Irish restaurants in cities and towns everywhere.</P>
        <P>I thank the Minister of State for attending the House and I commend him on his work.  Much is being done, but there is more to be done.  We are turning a blind eye in many respects.  I look forward to the Minister of State&rsquo;s reply.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancisOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Francis O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Gallagher, to the House.  I will take my first opportunity in the House to congratulate him on his position and re-election to D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.  It was a wonderful victory.  I disagree with Senator Buttimer&rsquo;s statement to the effect that we used to produce good food.  He should rephrase his statement, as we are still producing excellent food.</P>
        <P>Good food information is important.  The public wants good regulation and labelling of foodstuffs, the need for which has never been greater.  The Government recognises the importance of labelling.  The Departments of Health and Children and Agriculture, Fisheries and Food have produced a significant body of work in this regard.  In the past year, a programme of consul<Col N="1139"/>tation resulted in draft national legislation on country of origin labelling.  The legislation is intended to extend mandatory country of origin food labelling to sheep, pig and poultry meats.  I urge the Departments to move quickly because they will need to show the draft legislation to the European Commission to allow it and other member states an opportunity to comment.</P>
        <P>It is intended that the term &ldquo;country of origin&rdquo; will be defined as the country where the animal, bird or meat contained in a product spent most of its life.  If this differs from the country of slaughter, both countries must be indicated.  The proposed regulations will apply to meat and to products comprised of at least 70% meat in weight.  The Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Deputy Coughlan, has pressed this issue at EU level to ensure consumers are provided with full information on the origins of food products.  It is important to note that the industry has a responsibility as well.</P>
        <P>The Food Safety Authority report, entitled The Labelling of Food in Ireland 2007, aims to clarify any confusion as to what food labels should contain.  It will benefit consumers by enabling them to make informed decisions based on accurate and clear food labelling information.  All food labelling should provide sufficient information to help consumers make informed purchasing decisions.  Given that label space is limited, it is accepted that it may be necessary to distinguish between the information that must and should be provided.  It is good that proper labelling should encourage healthier food choice.  Food labelling should never mislead consumers and I will always speak out against bad labelling.</P>
        <P>As food labelling should be clear, consistent and understandable, we need a simplified text.  Many changes are imminent in food control activity, most of which will come from Brussels.  The EU has been and will continue to be the main driver of change in terms of food safety.  It is important that Ireland continues to be an active participant in the decision-making process.  I do not disagree with Senator Buttimer but he made a slight error&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of information, I meant we should continue to produce good quality food in the vast quantities we did previously.  I take Senator O&rsquo;Brien&rsquo;s remarks.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PearseDoherty"><NameTxt>Senator Pearse Doherty</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Leas Aire.  Food safety is a major issue and has been underlined this week by the report of the EU Food and Veterinary Office, FVO, on Brazilian beef production and the confirmation that foot and mouth disease has been discovered in Cyprus.  The FVO report proves that serious irregularities and shortcomings exist on Brazilian farms and in processing plants.  It also confirms the allegations that have been made by farmers&rsquo; groups here in regard to the import of beef from <Col N="1140"/>Brazil and the findings of an IFA investigation into Brazilian production methods.</P>
        <P>The FVO report shows irregularities in animal registration, identification, vaccination and breaches of EU residency requirements.  Most seriously it discovered that meat that ought to be deemed ineligible for export to the EU was being falsely certified in order to be avoid import controls.  It was also found that foot and mouth disease is still present in the Mato Grosso region from where most EU imported Brazilian beef originates.</P>
        <P>The report puts beyond doubt the need for the EU to impose a ban on Brazilian imports until producers there can prove that they comply with the stringent regulations that are applied to EU producers and processors.  It also underlines the need for the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Deputy Coughlan, to change her stance on this issue and support a ban, in line with the demands of Irish farming organisations and consumers.</P>
        <P>The discovery of foot and mouth disease in Cyprus is also a cause for concern.  It is the same strain that was responsible for the last outbreak in Britain and the one that is most common in Brazil.  That raises the question of where the strain originated and how it infected EU herds.  That was never satisfactorily explained and emphasises the importance of strict controls on imports.</P>
        <P>This country has a good record on animal diseases and was able to limit the effects of the last outbreak of foot and mouth disease and ensure recent outbreaks of animal disease in Britain were not transmitted here.  That was due to the effectiveness of controls in both parts of the island and in which my party colleague Ms Michelle Gildernew, Minister for Agriculture in the Northern Ireland Executive, played a full part.</P>
        <P>To ensure that this country retains and strengthens its high standards in food safety it is vital we have an all-Ireland approach in which the two Departments co-operate fully.  Sinn F&eacute;in will be doing its part in both parts of the island to ensure that this is the case.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatTheCope"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Pat The Cope Gallagher</NameTxt>
	<P>Ba mhaith liom mo bhu&iacute;ochas a chur in i&uacute;il dos na Seanad&oacute;ir&iacute; a ghlac pairt sa d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht f&iacute;or-th&aacute;bhachtach seo.  Beidh m&eacute; ag cur san &aacute;ireamh na point&iacute; &eacute;ags&uacute;la a chur siad os comhair an tSeanaid inniu.</P>
        <P>I thank Senators from all sides for their contributions to this important debate on food safety and health promotion, for which I have responsibility.  There is considerable consensus on the issues discussed, particularly on ensuring the consumer is fully protected and informed.  One of the most important issues raised was food labelling and the potential for misleading labelling.  Central to the issue of labelling is that the consumer should not be misled and that labels should <Col N="1141"/>provide clear, understandable information that will inform consumers and allow them to make appropriate choices.  There should be no question of labelling deceiving the public.  I will immediately investigate such suggestions if they are brought to the attention of my Department.  Misleading information is unacceptable and, in the context of the recast of EU labelling regulations which I mentioned earlier, Ireland will be pressing to ensure the issue of misleading, or potentially misleading, labelling is addressed.  We should not, however, adopt a siege mentality.  We should not lose sight of the fact that Ireland is a major food exporter and we have no national interest in undermining the concept of international trade in foodstuffs.</P>
        <P>Many speakers raised the importation of beef, in particular Brazilian beef, and the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Deputy Coughlan, has a particular interest in this issue.  She has actively pursued the matter with the EU Commission and will continue to do so.  Senators referred to the FVO report, as a result of the March mission to Brazil, which was made available yesterday.  I look forward to reading this report, which is welcomed by the Government, Deputy Coughlan and me.  Deputy Coughlan said it would be helpful in the overall process of ensuring equivalence.</P>
        <P>Senators raised a number of points that do not fall within my remit but I will ensure that the Minister is fully briefed on these.  The gluten-free issue was raised and this is significant, given the high level of coeliac disease in this country.  This issue will be discussed at next week&rsquo;s Codex meeting and Irish officials will be putting proposals to address the problem of potentially misleading information being given to those who have this condition.</P>
        <P>GMOs were mentioned in the House and in my speech.  Government policy is being re-evaluated and I suggest we await the outcome of this process.  This re-evaluation will be completed soon.  It is being co-ordinated by the Department of the Taoiseach through a senior officials group of EU affairs.  It will then be considered by the relevant Ministers.  The question of food contact materials falls in the remit of the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment and I will ensure the concerns expressed will be brought to his attention.</P>
        <P>I concur with the points on obesity and diabetes.  These are emerging health issues with significant potential consequences for many people.  One of the key issues is exercise and physical activity, and we are fortunate that throughout this country we have a wide network of voluntary clubs in which people give their time and commitment to ensuring that children and young people have ready access to sport.  I do not have to convince Members of this House of the tremendous investment by the Department of Arts, Sports and Tourism over recent years.  Even more important is the investment of resources, time and effort by many voluntary organisations <Col N="1142"/>throughout the country.  If that were to be converted into euro it would total many millions.  It complements the investment by the State.  I commend the positive contribution of those voluntary organisations to our society and to the health and welfare of our children.  Long may we continue to benefit from this voluntary aspect of our society.  Various issues were raised, particularly the availability of sports facilities in schools, as requested.  I will bring that to the attention of the Minister for Education and Science.</P>
    <HtmlBk SectId="3" />
        <P>I do not have to outline for the House the major capital investment that has been made in education in recent years.  Integral to all these developments is the necessity to provide sports facilities in all schools.  Reference was also made to the importation of vegetables to Ireland.  Of course, we would prefer import substitution, however, this does not lie with the Government alone but with the private sector.  We would like to think we could substitute for many items that are imported.</P>
        <P>Senators referred to the food pyramid.  I was very impressed by the food pyramid and the suggestions made by the Department.  We should familiarise ourselves with the pyramid and try to prevail on others, particularly our young people, to eat the type of food that is best for them and thus ensure they may not suffer from obesity and its effects.</P>
        <P>We are victims of the success of our economy.  While the Government, the Department and State agencies can advise, each is responsible for his or her health and parents have a major responsibility to ensure healthy food is provided for children.</P>
        <P>In conclusion, I am pleased to have the opportunity to address the House on the important topic of food safety and health promotion.  Members can be assured that while I was out of the House, I listened attentively to the contributions.  I thank Members for their contributions and I look forward to further debate in the future.</P>
    </Speaker><!--Fix-->
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>That concludes the statements.  When is it proposed to sit again? </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>At 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 13 November 2007.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment" RHead="Matters"> 
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. </Title>
  </MainHeading><Line />
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public" RHead="Transport"> 
    <Title>Public Transport. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalDonohoe"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Donohoe</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Cathaoirleach for giving me the opportunity to raise this issue on the adjournment.  I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Pat The Cope Gallagher for standing in for the Minister.  I am seeking to find out where we stand on the delivery of integrated ticketing for public transport in Dublin and across the country.</P><Col N="1143"/>
        <?oasys _cl11.7- ?><P>This proposal has a long history, spanning 15 years and I am not aware of the timetable for its delivery.  I believe the Dublin Transport Authority made proposals in the early 1990&rsquo;s and then handed the baton to the Rail Procurement Agency in 2005.  I understand the Rail Procurement Agency initiated a procurement process which was ultimately inconclusive and ended sometime in 2006.</P>
        <P>The benefits of integrated ticketing for public transport are very clear both to the providers and the people who use public transport.  The idea is simple and means that one can go on a journey where one can go from the train to Luas and or to the bus with a single ticket.  The reason that is important for those who use public transport is that it makes it easier to take journeys involving different forms of public transport and it would encourage people to use different forms of public transport on the same journey.  This would be very important because what makes public transport successful is the number of people who use it.  The more people use public transport, the more revenue will be generated, which enables further investment and public transport to flourish.  When integrated ticketing is not available, the providers of public transport lose out on a significant opportunity to attract more people to use the forms of transport available.  For those who want to use public transport for many different journeys, the process is complicated and as a result people decide not to use it.  I recently made a journey from the northside to the southside of Dublin, where I had to use the bus, and then the DART.  I had to purchase two tickets at two different stages.  Obviously, the provision of a single ticket for the entire journey would make it cheaper and simpler and thus encourage more people to use it.</P>
        <P>An announcement has just been made about the provision on an interconnector under Transport 21.  What an interconnector will do is allow the different forms of public transport to link up between the heavy rail system and the Luas.  The thinking behind it is so clear that if we allow these forms of public transport to link up, more people will use it.  That capital project will run into billions but for a fraction of that amount, which could be measured in the single tens of millions, we would make it more attractive and simpler for the public to use the different forms of transport that are available.  Given the significant environment benefit of greater use of public transport, and ensuring that capital infrastructure is better used and the money is spent more efficiently, this seems to be the most obvious thing to do in the Dublin region.  I am disappointed that integrated ticketing for public transport is not available and I would appreciate if the Minister would give us up-to-date information on what will happen next.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1144"/>
      <Speaker pid="PatTheCope"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Pat The Cope Gallagher</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senator Paschal Donohoe for raising the matter as it affords me the opportunity to update the House on progress towards delivering integrated ticketing.</P>
        <P>Good progress is being made on the provision of integrated tickets in the greater Dublin area.  Using magnetic strip technology, integrated tickets are available which allow transfer between bus and commuter rail, bus and Luas, and Luas and commuter rail and these tickets are enjoying increased consumer support.</P>
        <P>The next significant development will be a wider integrated ticketing scheme in and around the greater Dublin area, based on smartcard technology, as part of Transport 21.</P>
        <P>Smartcard technology will offer passengers simpler, more convenient and consistent access to, and payment for, participating public transport services.  In addition to conventional ticket products, the smartcard based integrated ticketing system will include a pay-as-you-go electronic purse for payment of fares which is similar to prepaid mobile phones.  An independent back office clearing system will ensure that the relevant transport operator will be paid for use of the electronic purse in order that passengers will not have to worry about what particular ticket type is valid on which particular transport service prior to undertaking their journey.  An integrated ticketing project board was established last year to bring forward this project, pending the establishment of the Dublin Transportation Authority, which will ultimately have responsibility for integrated ticketing.</P>
        <P>The board comprises the chief executive officers of the Railway Procurement Agency, Bus &Aacute;tha Cliath, Bus &Eacute;ireann, larnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann, a representative of the private bus operators, and a senior official from the Department of Transport under an independent chairperson.  A senior official from the Department of Social and Family Affairs also attends, as required.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The project board has been given the responsibility for delivering this smartcard technology required for an integrated smartcard ticketing system within an agreed specification, timeline and budget.  The board is working through all the elements required to deliver the system including commercial, operational, legal, competition and state aid issues.</P>
        <P>The board submitted a comprehensive proposal for the delivery of the project to the Department of Transport.  The proposal puts the expected capital cost of the integrated ticketing system at &euro;49.6 million.  This figure is the best estimate before tenders are received.  On 1 June, the Department wrote to the chairman of the project board authorising him to proceed with the <Col N="1145"/>implementation of the project along the lines proposed.</P>
        <P>The chairman has since informed the Department that the procurement process to secure a supplier for the back office systems is under way.  The procurement notice was placed in the <i>EU Journal</i> in June this year.</P>
        <P>Smartcard ticketing systems are in place on the Luas and Mortons services.  The board has also given approval for both larnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann and Bus &Aacute;tha Cliath to introduce their own interim smartcard systems in the near term.  These will enable both users and operators to familiarise themselves with the use and flexibilities of smartcard systems in the lead-up to the fully integrated system.</P>
        <P>The next stage will be to roll out the proposed integrated ticketing system within the greater Dublin area, also including long-distance daily commuting into and out of that area.  All of the current smartcard schemes are designed to migrate to this integrated smartcard system at the appropriate time.</P>
        <P>The board has informed the Department that the roll-out will commence by the end of August 2009 on the services of Bus &Aacute;tha Cliath, Luas and Mortons.  It will be extended to larnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann, Dart and commuter rail services within the following year.  Bus &Eacute;ireann has agreed to commence a trial project on one of its commuter routes.  Full roll-out will be completed within four years.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Schools Building" RHead="Projects"> 
    <Title>Schools Building Projects. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>I am glad of the opportunity to discuss the need for the Minister for Education and Science to recognise the urgent need for a secondary school in south Lucan in light of the growing population in the area, and the figures available to her Department of primary school children in the area who will require a second level place.  The Minister and her departmental officials should meet the south Lucan secondary school action group to address this need.</P>
        <P>Earlier this week, I met representatives of the south Lucan secondary school action group which was formed to highlight the overwhelming need for a secondary school in south Lucan.  I wish to bring some startling statistics to the Minister of State&rsquo;s attention.  In 1996, the total population of the Lucan-Esker electoral division was 7,451.  As of 2006, the number of children aged up to 14 years in the same electoral division amounted to 7,547.  According to the census, the population in the Lucan-Esker electoral division increased by 347% between 1991 and 2006.  It is one of the fastest growing areas in the country.  Based on these figures, if the Department of Education and Science does not act urgently to meet the need for a second level school in south Lucan, we will <Col N="1146"/>see there the first crisis in the country in terms of secondary schools places.</P>
        <P>This year, the Minister and her Department saw the results of inaction in school planning to meet demographic demands concerning primary schools in rapidly growing communities.  Should the Minister fail to act on the need for a secondary school for south Lucan she will see a similar problem emerging in that area.  There are a number of primary schools in the locality, including Archbishop Ryan&rsquo;s national school, Lucan Educate Together school and Griffeen Valley Educate Together school.  Where does the Minister propose these children should go when they complete their primary schooling?  Does she believe it is fair there is no second level school based in this large community?</P>
        <P>The county council&rsquo;s view on meeting this requirement can only be described as piecemeal and disappointing.  It is based on the idea of sending a portion of the students to one school, while sending others to another and so on.  A large amount of travelling is involved, although the area&rsquo;s transport problems are well known.  At present, young people must travel all over Dublin city to secondary schools, with the resulting destruction of a sense of community among south Lucan students and their parents.  I have met the teachers involved in placing these children in secondary schools and they are upset by the complete disruption to the sense of community that has already developed in those primary schools.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Furthermore, there is no assurance that the existing secondary schools can cope with such an increase in enrolment.  The departmental officials should examine the figures that have been put together by the south Lucan secondary school action group.  The figures are thorough and based on the numbers of children currently in primary schools there.  The major increase in pupil numbers warrants another secondary school for south Lucan.  The idea of sending young people to secondary schools all over the place is not a solution; it is a cop-out.  It represents a failure by the Minister and her Department to provide for the second level educational needs of this rapidly expanding community.</P>
        <P>Will the Minister arrange for her Department to work with the south Lucan secondary school action group and all interested parties to examine this matter?  They should not do so with eyes closed, stating that enough places are already available.  They should re-examine the issue because their figures are inaccurate.  Such co-operation and liaison should take place as soon as possible.  I hope to see the Minister in my constituency to turn the sod on the grounds of this much needed second level school in the near future.  I am grateful for the opportunity to have raised this important matter on the Adjournment.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="1147"/>
      <Speaker pid="PatTheCope"><NameTxt>Deputy Pat The Cope Gallagher</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Senator for raising this matter as it provides me, on behalf of the Minister for Education and Science, with an opportunity to outline to the House the Department&rsquo;s position regarding the demand for post-primary places in the Lucan area and how this demand is being met.</P>
        <P>The four post-primary providers in the immediate Lucan area have a combined capacity of 3,000 places.  The combined enrolment of the schools in September 2007 was 2,531 pupils.  Therefore, there is current surplus capacity of some 470 pupil places.  In addition, two other schools adjacent to the south Lucan area, namely, St. Kevin&rsquo;s community college and Collinstown Park community college, have considerable spare capacity which can be availed of.  Apart from this, the Department has plans to increase capacity at two of the schools in Lucan: Lucan community college and St. Joseph&rsquo;s college.</P>
        <P>Taking the demand for post-primary pupil places in Lucan against the places available and the interventions recently made or planned, the Department is satisfied that the immediate post-primary needs of the Lucan area can be met.  Having said that, the Department has asked South Dublin County Council to identify a site for further post-primary provision and it is the Department&rsquo;s intention to develop this site, when acquired, commensurate with any additional demand for pupil places.</P>
        <P>The Senator will be also be aware that Adamstown, which is adjacent to Lucan, is the subject of a strategic development zone, SDZ.  The planning scheme for the SDZ, which is endorsed by An <Col N="1148"/>Bord Plean&aacute;la, requires that housing and supporting infrastructure, including schools, be provided in a phased manner.  It is a condition of the SDZ that at completion of phase 2, that is, a maximum of 1,800 housing units, a primary school of eight classrooms or a post-primary school of 12 classrooms must be in place.  Subsequent phases require the provision of further school accommodation.</P>
        <P>In compliance with the requirements of the SDZ, the development of a multi-school campus is well under way.  The plans for this campus comprise two 16-classroom primary schools and a 1,000 pupil post-primary school.  The first of the primary school buildings opened in September 2007 and the second primary school will open shortly.  The timing and extent of this development means that primary provision for the area is ahead of demand.  Now that the primary school provision is in place, the emphasis has shifted to the delivery of the post-primary school, which the Department intends to provide commensurate with the phasing arrangements under the SDZ scheme.  This new post-primary school may be of assistance to the Lucan area pending further provision if the need arises.</P>
        <P>Through increased investment under the national development plan and the improved planning and delivery processes we have put in place in recent years, the Government will ensure the need for extra school places is met wherever it arises.  Areas such a Lucan are kept under continual review for this purpose.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <adjournment>The Seanad adjourned at 1.45 p.m. until<?oasys _jy ?>2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 13 November 2007.</adjournment><Col N="1147"/>
    <HtmlBk SectId="0" />
  </MainHeading><?oasys _te ?><!--Fix-->
</Debate><!--Fix-->
