<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Wed" Date="8" Month="Jul" Year="1936" Vol="63" No="9" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 8 Iúil 1936" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 8 July 1936" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1069">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1069" /> Do chuaidh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Great Southern Railways and Bus Passes">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Great Southern Railways and Bus Passes.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce whether his attention has been drawn to the refusal by the Great Southern Railways Company to accept railway passes issued to members of the Irish Live Stock Exporters' and Traders' Association on buses operating between the points covered by the passes where train services have been discontinued or are not at the time operating, and whether he will introduce proposals for legislation to compel the railway company to issue traders' passes available on rail or road transport operated by the company.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Minister for Education (Mr. Derrig) (for the Minister for Industry and Commerce) Minister for Education (Mr. Derrig) (for the Minister for Industry and Commerce)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Education (Mr. Derrig) (for the Minister for Industry and Commerce)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am informed by the Great Southern Railways Company that they are in communication with the Irish Live Stock Exporters' and Traders' Association relative to the availability of traders' season tickets on road services operated by the company where train services have been discontinued and in other cases.  The issue of traders' season tickets is subject to the regulations of the railway company applicable thereto, which are not governed by any statutory requirements. The company state that such tickets can be obtained to include road services operated in substitution for a closed section of their railway system so long as such services form part only of the journeys to be provided for in the ticket.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1070" /> I do not propose to introduce legislation in the matter.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Workmen's Compensation Act">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Workmen's Compensation Act.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCurran" hpid="Mr. Curran Mr. Curran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Curran</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he is aware that the procedure under Sections 26 and 34 of the Workmen's Compensation Act, 1934, is proving burdensome to the workman, and is causing grievous delay, hardship and expense by postponing his right to a hearing in open court (as was formerly the practice) until the cumbersome procedure laid down by these sections has been complied with; and, if so, if he will introduce proposals for legislation to provide that the procedure referred to will be speeded up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig (for the Minister for Industry and Commerce) Mr. Derrig (for the Minister for Industry and Commerce)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig (for the Minister for Industry and Commerce)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware that the procedure under Sections 26 and 34 of the Workmen's Compensation Act, 1934, is proving burdensome to the workman or that it is causing him grievous delay, hardship or expense.  If the Deputy will forward to my Department particulars of any case in which such delay, hardship or expense is alleged, I will have the allegation investigated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCurran" hpid="Mr. Curran Mr. Curran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Curran</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to state that this question is prompted by my own personal experience.  The Minister will agree with me that six weeks is too long for workmen to be kept out of benefit.  I am informed by people who know more about the sections to which I have referred in the question than I do, that the delay is caused principally by these sections.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Unemployment in Emly">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Unemployment in Emly.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarSeanDoyle" hpid="Mr. Doyle (for Mr. Séumas A. Bourke) Mr. Doyle (for Mr. Séumas A. Bourke)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Doyle (for Mr. Séumas A. Bourke)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if, in view of the widespread unemployment in and surrounding Emly, he will expedite the drainage of the Camogue and Ballyvistea Rivers inspected last year and also the provision of a sanitary sewerage system for the town, the present one having been condemned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee) Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>Preliminary reports on the drainage works referred to have been received <Col N="1071" /> and will be considered on their merits in connection with the employment programme, in so far as may be consistent with the provisions of existing drainage legislation.  The sanitary sewerage scheme for the town of Emly is a matter for the Minister for Local Government and Public Health.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Afforestation in Ballingeary District">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Afforestation in Ballingeary District.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnONeill" hpid="Mr. O'Neill Mr. O'Neill">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Neill</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands if he will state (1) how much land has been offered for afforestation purposes in the district of Ballingeary; (2) how much has actually been acquired; (3) to what extent has afforestation been started on the lands acquired; and (4) if the work on the schemes now in hand will be completed before any new areas are acquired in that district.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands whether he has received a resolution, passed at a meeting composed of representatives of all political Parties held at Ballingeary on the 15th June, regretting the delay of his Department in promoting afforestation in the district, and urging that work of this nature should be begun forthwith in Coomroe so as to relieve a portion of the unemployment in the area, and if he can state what, if any, land has been acquired or is in course of acquisition for the purpose of afforestation in the Ballingeary area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMichaelBurke" hpid="Mr. James M. Burke Mr. James M. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. James M. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands if he has received a copy of a resolution adopted unanimously by a meeting of representatives of Fianna Fáil, Fine Gael and Labour, held at Ballingeary, regarding the lack of progress in dealing with the question of afforestation in this district, and the delay of three or four years required to complete negotiations, and urging that instead of seeking to purchase new areas, negotiations in connection with existing schemes be definitely concluded and work be forthwith begun on Coomroe, which, in itself, constitutes an economic area, and to ask what action the Minister proposes to take relative to this resolution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOGrady" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Lands (Mr. O'Grady) Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Lands (Mr. O'Grady)">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Lands (Mr. O'Grady)</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose <Col N="1072" /> to take together, as relating to the same matter, the questions asked respectively by Deputies Eamonn O'Neill, Daniel O'Leary and James M. Burke, in regard to afforestation work in the Ballingeary district.  Approximately 2,000 acres have been offered to the Department for forestry purposes in the Ballingeary district.  Of this area, one holding containing about 450 acres is not suitable for afforestation, and of the remaining 1,550 acres, a considerable portion has been found to be unplantable.  As regards the lands at Coomroe referred to by Deputies, the owners have refused to accept the prices offered.  It is anticipated, however, that it will be possible at an early date to issue revised offers in these particular cases, and to make at the same time offers for other lands in the district.  The proceedings in the matter have been protracted owing to the fact that so large a proportion of the lands mentioned to the Department as being for sale is unplantable, and it has, therefore, been necessary to have wider investigation made in the hope of obtaining sufficient plantable land to justify the formation of a new forestry centre in the district.  The representations to which the Deputies refer have been received, and steps will be taken to complete negotiations as early as possible.  Forestry operations cannot be commenced until the lands have been acquired.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Parliamentary Secretary aware that negotiations have been going on for three or four years in connection with these lands?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOGrady" hpid="Mr. O'Grady Mr. O'Grady">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Grady</NameTxt>
      <P>As I have already indicated in my reply, I am aware of the fact that negotiations have been going on for some considerable time. Ex-Senator Keyes has been endeavouring to bring about a settlement in the matter.  Of course, there is an inspector in the district this week, and it is hoped that there will be no further delay in the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. -" RHead="Issues out of Central Fund">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Issues out of Central Fund.</Title>
    <P>Resolved:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Chun slánú do dhéanamh ar an soláthar a deonadh i gcóir seirbhísí <Col N="1073" /> na bliana dar chríoch an 31adh lá de Mhárta, 1934, go ndeontar suim £10 amach as an bPrímh-Chiste.</P>
    <P>That, towards making good the supply granted for the service of the year ended 31st March, 1934, the sum of £10 be granted out of the Central Fund.</P>
    <P>Chun slánú do dhéanamh ar an soláthar a deonadh i gcóir seirbhísí na bliana dar chríoch an 31adh lá de Mhárta, 1935, go ndeontar suim £10 amach as an bPrímh-Chiste.</P>
    <P>That, towards making good the supply granted for the service of the year ended 31st March, 1935, the sum of £10 be granted out of the Central Fund.</P>
    <P>Chun slánú do dhéanamh ar an soláthar a deonadh i gcóir seirbhísí na bliana dar chríoch an 31adh lá de Mhárta, 1937, go ndeontar suim £19,233,707 amach as an bPrímh-Chiste.</P>
    <P>That, towards making good the supply granted for the services of the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1937, the sum of £19,233,707 be granted out of the Central Fund. &mdash;(Minister for Finance.)</P>
    <P>Resolutions reported and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Appropriation" RHead="Bill, 1936&mdash;First Stage">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Appropriation Bill, 1936&mdash;First Stage.</Title>
    <P>Leave granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to apply certain sums out of the Central Fund to the service of the years ended on the thirty-first day of March, one thousand nine hundred and thirty-four and one thousand nine hundred and thirty-five and the year ending on the thirty-first day of March, one thousand nine hundred and thirty-seven and to appropriate the supplies granted in this Session of the Oireachtas.&mdash;(Minister for Finance.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the Second Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand we are to get all stages of this Bill to-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>In so far as the Opposition are in a position to give any undertaking, yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1074" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I regard the undertaking of Deputy Dillon as very valuable in this case.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Land" RHead="Bill, 1936&mdash;First Stage">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Land Bill, 1936&mdash;First Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Minister for Lands (Mr. Aiken) Minister for Lands (Mr. Aiken)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Lands (Mr. Aiken)</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask leave to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to amend and extend the Land Purchase Acts in divers respects.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the forecasts which appeared of the nature of this legislation, we consider it our duty to oppose the introduction of this Bill. My experience of a great deal of the land legislation, for which the Minister for Defence made himself responsible in this House, has been that it seriously interferes with the fixity of tenure which the tenant farmers fought for, and secured, from another Government at another time.  Owing to the exertion of Deputies in this House great abuses that were threatened under, I believe, the direct inspiration of the Minister himself, were averted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The House will recollect that an attempt was made to evict a number of tenant farmers in the County Wexford under the powers conferred upon the Government by the 1923 Land Act. Owing to the exertions of the members of the Opposition the Minister for Agriculture, who had made himself responsible for this attempted evic tion, was brought down to his con stituency in sack-cloth and ashes, to apologise to his constituents and to assure them that he had learned his lesson, and would use his influence to persuade the Land Commission to stay their hand.  And he used his influence to such good effect that these tenant purchasers, threatened with eviction were left in their holdings and then security of tenure vindicated.  We objected that any provision should make it possible, for any Minister, to shake the fixity of tenure of any tenant, when the Bill was before the House.  Such provisions were carried in spite of us by a cabal formed by the Fianna Fáil and Labour Parties. We are not in a position, at this juncture, to know the exact contents of the Bill which is now proposed to be introduced; but seeing that the kept Press of the Government has forecasted <Col N="1075" /> that the purpose the Minister for Defence has in mind is to extend his absolute jurisdiction to disturb tenant purchasers in this country, we find it necessary to oppose the introduction of the Bill with a view to eliciting from him now the general grounds upon which the Bill is drafted.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Dillon, of course, opposes the Bill before he knows what is in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, the procedure in this House lays it down that the only method, and the only way, in which a Minister who asks leave to introduce a Bill can indicate what the contents of the Bill is if the Opposition oppose it.  Then the Minister has an opportunity of explaining what is in the Bill.  There is no other way, on such a stage, that the Minister's lips can be unsealed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>The fact that Deputy Dillon does not know what is in the Bill is not sufficient to keep him quiet in entering a protest against its introduction. I hope at a later stage, after the Bill is introduced, to be able to show the Deputy that what is in his mind is a figment of his imagination.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1076" />
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. Morrissey Mr. Morrissey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Morrissey</NameTxt>
      <P>The imagination of the <i>Irish Press.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill is intended to amend and extend the Land Purchase Acts in divers ways.  Briefly, the purpose of the Bill is to ensure that what was intended to be done under the 1933 Act will, in fact, be the law of the country.  The principle of the 1933 Act was the subject of actions in the courts, and the effect of the courts' decision was to say that what the Government really intended to do under the 1933 Act was not, in fact, the law.  This is an amending Bill. It consists largely of drafting amendments. There is nothing very new introduced by it into the Act of 1933.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it the only purpose of the Bill is to upset the decisions of the courts even under the 1933 Land Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the Bill is not to upset decisions, it is to enforce the views of the people as represented here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I oppose and challenge a division.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That leave be given to introduce the Bill&rdquo;&mdash;put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The House divided: Tá, 44; Níl, 23.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Aiken, Frank.<br />Bartley, Gerald.<br />Beegan, Patrick.<br />Boland, Gerald.<br />Brady, Brian.<br />Briscoe, Robert.<br />Concannon, Helena.<br />Crowley, Timothy.<br />Daly, Denis.<br />Derrig, Thomas.<br />Dowdall, Thomas P.<br />Everett, James.<br />Flynn, John.<br />Flynn, Stephen.<br />Fogarty, Andrew.<br />Gibbons, Seán.<br />Goulding, John.<br />Hales, Thomas.<br />Harris, Thomas.<br />Hogan, Patrick (Clare).<br />Jordan, Stephen.<br />Keely, Séamus P.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kelly, James Patrick.<br />Keyes, Michael.<br />Killilea, Mark.<br />McEllistrim, Thomas.<br />MacEntee, Seán.<br />Maguire, Conor Alexander.<br />Moore, Séamus.<br />Moylan, Seán.<br />Murphy, Patrick Stephen.<br />Murphy, Timothy Joseph.<br />O Briain, Donnchadh.<br />O Ceallaigh, Seán T.<br />O'Grady, Seán.<br />O'Reilly, Matthew.<br />Rice, Edward.<br />Ryan, James.<br />Ryan, Robert.<br />Sheridan, Michael.<br />Smith, Patrick.<br />Traynor, Oscar.<br />Victory, James.<br />Walsh, Richard.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="1077" />Alton, Ernest Henry.<br />Beckett, James Walter.<br />Bennett, George Cecil.<br />Bourke, Séamus.<br />Broderick, William Joseph.<br />Burke, James Michael.<br />Cosgrave, William T.<br />Curran, Richard.<br />Daly, Patrick.<br />Dillon, James M.<br />Dockrell, Henry Morgan.<br />Doyle, Peadar S.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="1078" />Good, John.<br />Keating, John.<br />McMenamin, Daniel.<br />Morrisroe, James.<br />Morrissey, Daniel.<br />Mulcahy, Richard.<br />Nally, Martin.<br />O'Donovan, Timothy Joseph.<br />O'Leary, Daniel.<br />Redmond, Bridget Mary.<br />Wall, Nicholas.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers:&mdash;Tá: Deputies Smith and Beegan; Níl: Deputies Doyle and Bennett.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <P>Leave granted to introduce the Bill.</P>
    <P>Second Stage fixed for Wednesday, 15th July.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Night Work" RHead="(Bakeries) Bill, 1936&mdash;First Stage">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Night Work (Bakeries) Bill, 1936&mdash;First Stage.</Title>
    <P>Leave granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to carry out and give effect to the Night Work (Bakeries) Convention, 1925.&mdash;(The Vice-President.)</P>
    <P>Second Stage fixed for Wednesday, 15th July.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Vice-President want to get these two Bills through before the Recess?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>When will this Bill be circulated?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>Immediately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Vice-President arrange that a number of copies of the Convention will be available to Deputies who may wish to see them in the Library?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume that will be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Aran Islands" RHead="(Transport) Bill, 1936&mdash;First Stage">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Aran Islands (Transport) Bill, 1936&mdash;First Stage.</Title>
    <P>Leave granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to make provision for promoting the maintenance of an efficient steamship service between the City of Galway and the Aran Islands, and to authorise the payment of subsidies to persons carrying on such service.&mdash;(The Vice-President.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the Second Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>This day week.  The Bill will be circulated immediately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>In case we are sitting on Tuesday, would the Minister find it convenient to put the Second Stage down for that day?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>I am hoping that it will not be necessary to meet on Tuesday of next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>Shall we meet on Friday of this week?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot say at the moment.  That will depend on the course of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Finance" RHead="Bill, 1936&mdash;Fifth Stage">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Finance Bill, 1936&mdash;Fifth Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee) Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Bill do now pass.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Final Stage of the Finance Bill, one matter of immediate importance arises, and certain matters, arising out of the attitude adopted by the Minister for Finance on the earlier stages of the Bill, may be properly referred to.  The Finance Bill affords an opportunity for reviewing the general policy of the Executive Council.  In view of proceedings reported in the <i>Irish Press</i> and other newspapers on last Monday, July 6, the Minister for Finance should hold himself ready to answer for the policy of his Department, in particular, and that of the Executive Council, generally, in regard to the activities of a certain <Col N="1079" /> member of the Civil Service.  We deliberately abstained from any comment on the quite unprecedented procedure of transferring an active politician into the ranks of the Civil Service on the occasion of ex-Senator Connolly's appointment to the office of chairman of the Commissioners of Public Works.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The debate on the Fifth Stage of a Bill is confined to what is contained in the measure.  The matter to which the Deputy refers might have been raised on the Vote for the Office of the Minister for Finance. I fail to see how it can be made relevant on the Fifth Stage of the Finance Bill.  The Minister, as Head of the Civil Service, may not on this Bill be held accountable for the administration of the Civil Service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Your ruling, Sir, must be closely observed, and if this matter does not arise now, it will arise to-morrow on the Appropriation Bill.  I should have preferred to dispose of it now, as a matter of general policy.  If it must be raised on the Appropriation Bill, raised it will be in another form, subject to your approval.  I would submit, Sir, that the questions of policy dealt with on the earlier stages of the Bill might be further commented on at this stage. Surely the general question of whether members of the Civil Service of this State ought to take an active part in politics or not is a matter proper for discussion on the general policy of the Executive Council, or do you hold, Sir, that that is a matter that cannot be raised?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that an opportunity will arise on the Appropriation Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a matter for future consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I do want to ask the Minister for Finance, in view of the attitude which he adopted on the Financial Resolutions and on the Finance Bill, on its Second Stage, of <Col N="1080" /> deliberately avoiding all the arguments put to him, whether he is prepared now to deal fully with the problems that were raised by the Opposition in the course of those debates?  I want to refer again to a signed article which was written by the Minister for Finance, in the Fianna Fáil Bulletin, that unfortunate manifesto which put the national policy an issue in the Municipal Elections in the City of Dublin and in the course of doing so put the national policy an issue with the disastrous results which ensued for the Government.  The Minister for Finance in that article used the following words:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;It would be a very cruel deception indeed of the needy and the destitute to provide, say, widows' and orphans' pensions, for only a year or two, or unemployment assistance for a similar period, out of borrowed moneys, and then, at the end of that time to turn round and say to the people:&mdash;&lsquo;The Government cannot borrow any more money and the national financial resources are so disorganised that we shall have to deprive you of the help and assistance which your destitute condition demands.  We shall have, in fact, to do as has had to be done in other countries where the Governments have borrowed what ought to have been raised by taxation, that is, to cut down or, perhaps, entirely abolish social services.&rsquo;&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Let me say again that I adopt every line of that statement.  I consider it an excellently phrased, coolly considered and a most necessary and timely statement of policy on the part of the Minister for Finance.  On the Second Stage of this Bill the discussion ranged largely about our visible balance of trade.  On the Financial Resolutions I ventured to deal at some length with the question of our invisible trade balance and I directed the attention of the Minister to the fact that the favourable balance on invisible trade which this country enjoyed was dwindling and dwindling in such a way that no Government could arrest its diminution and that, therefore, a peculiar responsibility rests upon the Government <Col N="1081" /> to remove the causes of that diminution and so arrest that growing adverse balance of trade, that has been increasing since the present Government came into office.  Unless we do that, the very disasters which the Minister for Finance envisages in the statement which I have just read are bound to result in taxation in this country rising to dizzy heights.</P>
    <P>There are optimists, some of whom contribute to the columns of the British newspapers, who are beginning to reconsider their whole attitude towards the economic conditions of this country who ask themselves whether they did not make a mistake in considering that the people were not too heavily taxed in the past.  Perhaps that was not true and that the truth was they were never sufficiently taxed until Fianna Fáil came into office.  There are sober newspapers like the <i>Irish Times</i> who in the past few years, having been taken into the bosom of the Minister for Finance, have discovered a new financial gospel. They have begun to discover that an adverse balance of £20,000,000 in a total export and import trade of £59,000,000 is not so injurious to the country as an adverse trade balance of £12,000,000 in a total trade of £101,000,000.  In fact, there are many sober-minded people in this country who still protest that they are not members of the Fianna Fáil Party, and that they do not join in the characteristic orgies of adoration at the shrine of President de Valera, but they still manage to echo in the most extraordinary way the gentle accents of the Minister for Finance.</P>
    <P>Some of us are beginning to ask ourselves whether it is not the pleasant social contact with the Minister, whether his charming personality is not dazzling these economists and bewildering these sober, prudent newspapers. Some of us expect the <i>Irish Times</i> to emerge one of these days in very small print describing itself as the <i>Irish Times</i> or &ldquo;Small Truth in the News.&rdquo; I need hardly say that if they did that there would be found no one to suggest that the <i>Irish Press</i>, in describing itself as &ldquo;Truth in the News,&rdquo; likened itself to the President, while the <i>Irish Times,</i> in describing itself as &ldquo;Little Truth in the News,&rdquo; intended to cast <Col N="1082" /> no reflection on the Minister for Finance.  Whether they did or not, I think a good many of us observe his prophetic voice sounding in the columns of that particular newspaper.  Nevertheless, there are some of us who cannot be consoled by such startling conversions, and who still prefer to look up the figures as they appear in the undramatic official returns of the Minister for Industry and Commerce and the Minister for Finance, who feel good ground for the apprehension that was clearly visible in the warning that was uttered in the &ldquo;Fianna Fáil Bulletin&rdquo; by the Minister for Finance.</P>
    <P>Either we are going to husband our resources, or else our social services are going to fail to be abolished.  I say the only way in which our resources can be effectively husbanded is by improving our external trade.  In that connection I direct the attention of the Minister for Finance to a development which has recently taken place in Great Britain.  When Fianna Fáil first came into office, they told us that the British market was of no account.  They told us that they were to find alternative markets.  They were two or three years in office and spent thousands, even millions of money in trying to find these alternative markets.  Then President de Valera came to the House and told us that, having sought to find those markets, he found that they did not exist.  Shortly after that confession was made, the then Minister for Lands, a member of the Executive Council, boasted that he rejoiced to think that he could in 100 days destroy the cattle trade which it had taken 100 years to build up.  The Minister for Agriculture had to come in here two years afterwards to explain that that was never meant, that it was only a joke, and that it was quite contrary to what the then Minister for Lands had in mind. Some of us were sufficiently irreverent to ask what was it that the Minister for Lands had in mind.  Some of us went further and suggested that, while we did not know what the Minister for Lands had in mind, it was clear that he did not know himself either.</P>
    <P>Now I want to suggest to the Minister for Finance that, while Great Britain is making up its mind to make adequate provision for the <Col N="1083" /> food supply which would be available to them in times of war or in times when it would be extremely difficult to carry such foodstuffs over a wide expanse of ocean, part of that general scheme provides that the British fat-stock industry is going to receive a very substantial subsidy from the British Government.  I suggest to the Minister for Agriculture and the Minister for Finance that a very large part of that subsidy, which the British Government intends for the fat-stock industry in Great Britain, can be diverted into the pockets of the Irish farmer, and as it is diverted into his pockets, my submission is that the Irish farmer will give very good value for every £ he gets if the Government of Saorstát Eireann will only co-operate with him and make it possible for him to do so.</P>
    <P>I ask the Minister for Finance is he now prepared to induce his colleagues to open negotiations with the British Government to make an end of the penal duties on Irish cattle, so that we may co-operate with the farmers of Great Britain in building up the supply of foodstuffs for which the British people are prepared to pay an enhanced price.  I apprehend that, unless steps of that kind are taken immediately, we may lose an opportunity that will never recur.  The British farmer has found for years that the Irish store cattle do better in Great Britain than store cattle from any part of the world.  The Irish farmer, particularly the small tenant purchaser, has found that there is no economy more suitable to the small holding in this country than mixed farming founded on the production of live stock.  I now assert, and I challenge President de Valera to deny it, that President de Valera received in his office a deputation from a public body in this country who came to discuss with him rural development in Ireland and, in the course of that interview, President de Valera said to that deputation that, in his opinion, the best factory that could be provided for the rural population in this country was the bullock.  I may say that I entirely endorse that statement.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1084" /> The most economic and the most valuable factory that operates in this country to-day is the small farm, which is supporting the farmer and his wife and family, who are growing on the land of that farm the raw materials of their industry and who, on that farm, are converting those raw materials into the finished products of the agricultural industry. Those are the factories of inestimable value to the community in this country.  There are 200,000 or 250,000 such factories in the country at present, and I say that the duty devolves upon the Government to ensure, by agreement with Great Britain, that permanent prosperity will be secured for these factories and, through them, for the people who work in them.</P>
    <P>I make this last point to the Minister: that, bearing in mind the note of apprehension he so properly sounded in the &ldquo;Fianna Fáil Bulletin,&rdquo; I suggest to him that ultimately the resources of this State depend upon the prosperity of agriculture; that we can neither maintain social services, and such other services as we wish to maintain; nor hope to maintain industries in our cities, or any other form of commercial activity, unless the prosperity of agriculture is first secured.  I put it to him that the best insurance he can get against the catastrophes which he appears to apprehend in his statement to the &ldquo;Fianna Fáil Bulletin&rdquo; is the prosperity of the tenant purchasers of the country.  I submit to him that all the experience he has had in office during the past five years and all the intelligent advice that is available to him at the present time, must lead him to the conclusion that the only system of agriculture which can bring prosperity to the small farmers and, through them, to the community as a whole, is that form of agriculture founded on the live-stock industry and requiring mixed farming&mdash;that form of agricultural industry which induces the farmer to produce on his own land all the raw materials and to convert those raw materials on his own holding into a finished product.  That is the one industry in Ireland all the raw <Col N="1085" /> materials of which this country can produce.</P>
    <P>I do urge on Deputies most strongly to remember that there is one industry only in this country all the raw materials of which are available in Ireland, and that is the agricultural industry.  It is the one industry <i>par excellence</i> which can make a contribution to the people directly employed in it and to every section of the community where it is functioning.  I press upon the Minister that, with the considerations he has to bear in mind as to the ultimate financial solvency of this country, he should use all his influence with the Minister for Agriculture, the Minister for Industry and Commerce, and the Executive Council as a whole to ensure that energetic steps will be taken immediately to dispose of the economic war and to substitute for it such a trade agreement as will secure for us a substantial share of what is going to be the most valuable market in the world for agricultural produce.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know that there is very much for me to say in reply to the speech we have just listened to from Deputy Dillon.  As you, Sir, very pertinently remarked, the purpose of the Fifth Stage of the Bill is to review what is in the Bill and, upon such merits or demerits as that review discloses, to take that action which seems to serve the country best in regard to the Bill. The Deputy has not addressed himself to the general proposals of the Bill. He has chosen instead to discuss matters of wide general policy, particularly those dealing with our external relations.  The House, a week or two <Col N="1086" /> ago, had an opportunity to go over the whole field in that regard, and I do not think that it would be advisable, in view of the very heavy programme of work which we hope to get through this evening, to reopen that discussion and to resurvey that field afresh.  I do not propose therefore to deal with the speech of the Deputy in regard to that matter.</P>
      <P>As to the other matter which he raised, the necessity for securing that our farmers will have a fair opportunity to share in the British market, I think we have already had indications of the zeal with which the Government have served the interests of the Irish farmers in that connection, and I have no reason to believe that the agricultural interest is in any way dissatisfied with what we have done.  If it were not that I feel myself confined by your ruling, Sir, I should like very much to discuss the aspects of the Dublin elections to which Deputy Dillon referred.  I can only say that we do not regard them as unsatisfactory. In any event, both in the county and in the city they have marked an advance for the Fianna Fáil programme and the Fianna Fáil Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>What have&mdash;the Dublin municipal elections?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>It was the rain that kept them in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister turned round.  That is how they advanced&mdash; backwards.</P>
      <P>Question put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Dáil divided: Tá, 46; Níl, 26.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Aiken, Frank.<br />Beegan, Patrick.<br />Boland, Gerald.<br />Brady, Brian.<br />Briscoe, Robert.<br />Concannon, Helena.<br />Corbett, Edmond.<br />Crowley, Timothy.<br />Daly, Denis.<br />Derrig, Thomas.<br />Dowdall, Thomas P.<br />Everett, James.<br />Flynn, John.
<Col N="1087" />Maguire, Ben.<br />Maguire, Conor Alexander.<br />Moore, Séamus.<br />Moylan, Seán.<br />Murphy, Patrick Stephen.<br />Murphy, Timothy Joseph.<br />Norton, William.<br />O Briain, Donnchadh.<br />O Ceallaigh, Seán T.<br />O'Grady, Seán.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Flynn, Stephen.<br />Fogarty, Andrew.<br />Gibbons, Seán.<br />Goulding, John.<br />Hales, Thomas.<br />Harris, Thomas.<br />Hogan, Patrick (Clare).<br />Keely, Séamus P.<br />Kelly, James Patrick.<br />Kelly, Thomas.<br />Killilea, Mark.<br />McEllistrim, Thomas.<br />MacEntee, Seán.
<Col N="1088" />O'Reilly, Matthew.<br />Pearse, Margaret Mary.<br />Rice, Edward.<br />Ryan, James.<br />Ryan, Robert.<br />Sheridan, Michael.<br />Smith, Patrick.<br />Traynor, Oscar.<br />Victory, James.<br />Walsh, Richard.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Alton, Ernest Henry.<br />Beckett, James Walter.<br />Bennett. George Cecil.<br />Bourke, Séamus.<br />Broderick, William Joseph.<br />Burke, James Michael.<br />Cosgrave, William T.<br />Curran, Richard.<br />Daly, Patrick.<br />Dillon, James M.<br />Dockrell, Henry Morgan.<br />Doyle, Peadar S.<br />Esmonde, Osmond Grattan.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Fagan, Charles.<br />Good, John.<br />Keating, John.<br />McMenamin, Daniel.<br />Morrisroe, James.<br />Morrissey, Daniel.<br />Mulcahy, Richard.<br />Nally, Martin.<br />O'Donovan, Timothy Joseph.<br />O'Leary, Daniel.<br />Redmond, Bridget Mary.<br />Rowlette, Robert James.<br />Wall, Nicholas.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers:&mdash;Tá: Deputies Smith and Moylan; Níl: Deputies P.S. Doyle and Bennett.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Agricultural Produce" RHead="(Cereals) Bill, 1936&mdash;Fifth Stage">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Agricultural Produce (Cereals) Bill, 1936&mdash;Fifth Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan) Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I simply want to repeat a question that I asked the Minister for Agriculture on a previous occasion. It was this: would any rational man in this country tell me why the Government want the people to grow wheat? I put that question to the Minister for Agriculture before, and he said that he could not tell me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not.  I answered any rational man, but I did not answer the Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I have the Minister's answer here in my hand.  It was so futile that I marked it on the cover of the Dáil debates.  In column 904, volume 63, the Minister for Agriculture is reported:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Deputy Dillon wanted the big reason we have for burdening the community with extra cost in order to induce farmers to grow wheat. It is part of our protective policy.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That is the entire explanation afforded to me and to the House by the Minister for a burden of £1,500,000 per annum in order to induce the farmers to grow wheat.  &ldquo;It is part of our protective policy.&rdquo;  Does that make sense to anybody outside Grangegorman? I do not think it does.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy ought to know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Protecting what?  My submission is that it is not protecting anything.  Protecting what?  Is it protecting the farmers from disaster?  Go and ask the farmers what their position is.  Ask the farmer supporters of the Minister what their experience has been in connection with the growing of wheat last year and in the present cereal year.  Ask our supporters what has been their experience.  Many of them have been forced by circumstances to grow wheat.  I have no quarrel with them in their attempt to make some money because their other means of livelihood have been taken from them by reason of the Government's policy.  What is being protected and what advantage is the community getting out of paying <Col N="1089" /> £1,500,000 in order to induce farmers to grow wheat?  Is there any rational man on the benches of Fianna Fáil who can answer that question?  I do not believe there is.  I believe they are all so bewildered and bemused with this business of growing more wheat that they have absolutely lost all power to approach the question rationally.</P>
      <P>I ask the Minister for Agriculture can he elaborate that observation any further&mdash;&ldquo;it is part of our protective policy&rdquo;?  Whom are you trying to protect?  Is it the wire worms who eat the wheat or the blight that comes on the wheat, or what is it?  Surely it is not the community who have to pay £1,500,000 extra for their loaves. The House is entitled to a fuller explanation than the bald statement that &ldquo;it is part of our protective policy.&rdquo; When the scheme was first introduced its purpose was to provide more labour on the land.  Deputy Victory said that his experience was that in many places increased tillage had provided no extra labour on the land because more efficient methods of carrying out tillage had, in fact, in some places diminished employment.  That excuse for the wheat policy is gone and Deputy Victory has slain it.  Will the Minister dig up some other reason to explain the expenditure of £1,500,000 per annum on the production of wheat? What has the Minister for Finance to say to this expenditure?  Precipitate flight is the answer, and I do not blame him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Finance got rid of it by putting it on the consumer of flour and bread.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Finance has fled the House.  I ask the Minister for Agriculture, who is now alone and unprotected, why it is that he wants the people of this country to grow wheat?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask the Minister, now that he is getting this Bill, whether he anticipates that it will do anything to improve the condition of the agricultural labourers.  Deputy Dillon has indicated that the farmer does not get <Col N="1090" /> very much in the way of results from the policy pursued in this matter, and repeatedly we have had to discuss not only the reduction in the number of permanent agricultural labourers but also the fall in agricultural labourers' wages.  Take Wexford as an example. It is one of the principal counties getting advantage from these subsidised crops.  It might easily be the most subsidised county in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OsmondGrattanEsmonde" hpid="Sir Osmond Esmonde Sir Osmond Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Sir Osmond Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I would like to hear what county is and I would like to hear some person, who thinks some other county is more subsidised than Wexford, discussing the condition of agricultural labourers in that county in relation to this Bill.  Going back to County Wexford, the facts have been brought before the House several times and put before the Government. In this highly-subsidised county, the county committee of agriculture have three times running in the beginning of last year pointed out that married agricultural labourers had to exist on 8/- a week and procure their own food. They even went to the extent of appealing that free beef be given to them, and they wound up by asking the Government to introduce a subsidy scheme for agricultural labourers' wages so that with the Government subsidy the agricultural labourers' wages there could be raised to the enormous sum of 14/- a week.  The Minister is quite aware of that.  He has the statistics in regard to agricultural employment and I would like him, just as he is taking this third, fourth or fifth Bill amending cereal legislation with a view to the further production of cereals here and their further subsidisation, whether he anticipates now that this fourth or fifth Bill will do anything to improve the condition of agricultural labourers, particularly as regards their pay, but also as regards the number that he expects will be employed on the land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely it would be a mere waste of time to go once more into the reasons for growing wheat?  Since we came here, nine years ago, this Party has been in favour of extended wheat-growing and many a time we <Col N="1091" /> have given our reasons here.  The Party opposite have published as part of their political programme that they are going to keep the wheat scheme in operation.  Surely they are not doing that in order to get votes.  They surely have some good reason for doing it.  Deputy Dillon, perhaps, does not altogether agree with them He said here the last day, in answer to Deputy MacDermot, that if his Party got power they would gradually cut that policy out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister be good enough to quote me?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>If I am not quoting the Deputy properly, I am sorry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>Beidh lá eile againn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Beidh, beidh lá eile ag an Teachta, pé scéal é.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Béidir go mbeadh sé fliuch.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Béidir go mbeadh.  We have two big Parties here who have stood over and over again for the wheat policy.  The Labour Party have supported legislation in regard to cereals, generally speaking, all through.  Surely the three Parties here can scarcely be in agreement that the wheat-growing should be extended unless they all have very good reasons. Why should we go into any arguments for the growing of wheat in the circumstances? It would be an unnecessary waste of time, I think.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister will not tell us why he wants wheat?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Why should I tell you? I consider it would be a mere waste of time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I venture to express the opinion that there is not a single member of the Minister's Party who knows why he wants wheat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Why is it made part of the Fine Gael programme?  Surely it is not for the purpose of getting votes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not in the programme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1092" />
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg the Minister's pardon, it is not there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I must look up the latest Fine Gael programme to see if the scheme for the growing of wheat is going to be continued under the people opposite.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely, when you go out of office next year, you do not expect us to burn all the wheat in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not expect you to lose one vote that you think you could get by adopting any policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Come back to wheat, and tell us what you are going to do about wheat.  Why do you want to grow wheat?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is absolutely ludicrous for Deputy Dillon to talk about the farmers not wanting to grow wheat because the extended growing of wheat in this country exceeded everybody's expectations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>All I want to know is why do you want people to grow wheat?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy, when speaking on the Finance Bill&mdash;those are the words he used; I jotted them down because I thought them rather strange &mdash;said in reference to agriculture: &ldquo;It is the one industry all the raw materials of which can be produced in this country.&rdquo; Why was the Deputy lauding the agricultural industry for that reason?  He said it was the one industry on which to depend because it was the one industry all the raw materials of which could be produced in this country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>May I take it from that that the Deputy thinks we ought to produce raw materials in this country &mdash;that it is desirable that we should do so?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes&mdash;that we should develop our natural resources.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy wants to make one speech on the Finance Bill and another on the Cereals Bill.  On the <Col N="1093" /> Finance Bill he said it was a desirable thing to produce all our raw materials, because he wanted to make some point against the Minister for Finance about coming to a settlement with England and exporting some of our stuff to England. But on the Cereals Bill, because we want to grow more oats and barley, according to him we should not produce all our raw materials.  It is a different Bill, so the Deputy changes his argument, and we ought not to produce all our raw materials! That is the reason why I think it is useless going into the arguments for the growing of wheat with the Deputy or the Deputy's Party.  If the Deputy were in any way addicted to sticking to the same arguments on Bills one could understand it, but he gets up and makes those debating points, and God knows he takes long enough to make them too.  He holds up the business of this House in order to hear himself talk and make those little points which do not matter in the least to the country.  I think it would be much more important to get on with our business, and let Deputy Dillon ask his own Party what are their reasons for wanting to grow more wheat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>And let the people have some more experience of your policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1094" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The people intend to have plenty of experience of our policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>God help them!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Mulcahy talked about agricultural wages.  Of course, we have heard that speech about agricultural wages repeated a good many times in this House.  It will be possible, I hope, to pay better wages under this Bill, and it will make it easier to put into operation the provisions of the new Bill that is being drafted with regard to agricultural wages.  I hope the Deputy and the Party opposite who are so very much concerned about agricultural wages will be as enthusiastic as they are now when this Bill with regard to agricultural wages comes before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>To get blood out of a turnip?  Is that it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have often heard that term applied to a man who has not very much in his head, but not in regard to a case like this.  Those are the only points that were raised against the Bill, as far as I know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>That was a very eloquent speech.</P>
      <P>Question put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Dail divided: Tá, 46; Níl, 26.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Aiken, Frank.<br />Beegan, Patrick.<br />Boland, Gerald.<br />Brady, Brian.<br />Briscoe, Robert.<br />Concannon, Helena.<br />Corbett, Edmond.<br />Corish, Richard.<br />Crowley, Timothy.<br />Daly, Denis.<br />Derrig, Thomas.<br />Dowdall, Thomas P.<br />Flynn, John.<br />Flynn, Stephen.<br />Fogarty, Andrew.<br />Gibbons, Seán.<br />Goulding, John.<br />Hales, Thomas.<br />Harris, Thomas.<br />Hogan, Patrick (Clare).<br />Keely, Séamus P.<br />Kehoe, Patrick.<br />Kelly, James Patrick.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kelly, Thomas.<br />Killilea, Mark.<br />McEllistrim, Thomas.<br />MacEntee, Seán.<br />Maguire, Ben.<br />Maguire, Conor Alexander.<br />Moore, Séamus.<br />Moylan, Seán.<br />Murphy, Patrick Stephen.<br />Murphy, Timothy Joseph.<br />O Briain, Donnchadh.<br />O Ceallaigh, Seán T.<br />O'Grady, Seán.<br />O'Reilly, Matthew.<br />Pearse, Margaret Mary.<br />Rice, Edward.<br />Ryan, James.<br />Ryan, Robert.<br />Sheridan, Michael.<br />Smith, Patrick.<br />Traynor, Oscar.<br />Victory, James.<br />Walsh, Richard.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="1095" />Alton, Ernest Henry.<br />Beckett, James Walter.<br />Bennett, George Cecil.<br />Broderick, William Joseph.<br />Burke, James Michael.<br />Cosgrave, William T.<br />Curran, Richard.<br />Daly, Patrick.<br />Dillon, James M.<br />Dockrell, Henry Morgan.<br />Dolan, James Nicholas.<br />Doyle, Peadar S.<br />Esmonde, Osmond Grattan.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="1096" />Fagan, Charles.<br />Good, John.<br />Keating, John.<br />McMenamin, Daniel.<br />Morrisroe, James.<br />Morrissey, Daniel.<br />Mulcahy, Richard.<br />Nally, Martin.<br />O'Donovan, Timothy Joseph.<br />O'Leary, Daniel.<br />Redmond, Bridget Mary.<br />Rowlette, Robert James.<br />Wall, Nicholas.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers:&mdash;Tá: Deputies Smith and Moylan; Níl: Deputies Doyle and Bennett.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Air Navigation and" RHead="Transport Bill, 1936&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Air Navigation and Transport Bill, 1936&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Acting-Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Derrig) Acting-Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Derrig)">
      <NameTxt>Acting-Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Derrig)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: That the Air Navigation and Transport Bill, 1936, be now read a Second Time. It would be well, I think, at the beginning, to outline briefly the international position of the control of air navigation and the present position in the Saorstát.  Aviation, as Deputies know, has provided us with a form of transport, the outstanding characteristic of which is speed.  It is over the greatest distances that this feature of speed provides the most advantage, and the limits set by political frontiers to surface transport cannot be applied in the same way to transport in the air.  It seems clear, therefore, that for the development of international air transport uniform facilities for the passage of aircraft into and over States are required.  As might be expected, therefore, even in the early stages of air transport development, the subject was one for international consideration with a view to its regulation.</P>
      <P>A first attempt to effect international regulation of air navigation was made in 1910, but it was found impossible to reach a unanimous agreement on a draft convention.  The idea was taken up again at the opening of the Peace Conference in 1919.  It became clear that, owing to the war, very considerable advances had been made in aerial transport, and the result was that in October, 1919, there was signed at Paris a Convention relating to the regulation of aerial navigation.  The Saorstát is a party to this Convention which laid down principles to serve as a basis for uniform national regulations for the control of international flying.  These principles, I think, might be briefly summarised as follows: that every Power has complete and exclusive sovereignty over the air space above its territory; that each contracting State undertakes, in time of peace, to give free air passage to the aircraft of other contracting States; that each contracting State may prohibit flight by aircraft over certain areas of its territory, and that each contracting State may conclude special conventions, not contradictory to the general principles of the International Convention, with non-contracting States.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Air Navigation Act of 1920 implemented the International Convention and, in addition, provided for certain consequential and supplemental matters not covered by the Convention. This Act is the existing statutory authority for the regulation of flying in the Saorstát, and under it various orders and regulations have been made from time to time.  For a considerable time the Government has been closely examining the question of air transport and, in connection therewith, the reconsideration of legislation applying to air navigation came up for consideration. It was considered advisable, having regard to all the circumstances, to introduce the present Bill.  I think Deputies will fully appreciate that, if only on account of the passage of time and the general progress of civil aviation which has taken place in the meantime, modifications and amendments <Col N="1097" /> will have to be made in the 1920 Act. But there is also the further important consideration that the steps which are now definitely about to be taken for aviation development in this country, to which I shall refer later, make it even more necessary that new legislative provisions should be made for the regulation of air navigation and transport. The Air Navigation and Transport Bill, 1936, contains no startling innovations. The House has already had experience of the application of the principle of public control and regulation of other forms of transport, as, for example, the road and railway measures which it has passed during recent years. This control which has been found desirable from experience in other forms of transport is now being adapted and modified to suit aerial transport, and is being applied to aviation in the present Bill.</P>
    <P>Other matters dealt with in the Bill arise from the International Conventions of Paris, Warsaw, and Rome in connection with air transport.  Provisions are outlined in the Bill, by which the contents of these conventions, and the principles laid down in them, may be specifically applied to aerial transport in Saorstát Eireann. Furthermore, co-ordination and economy of air transport development will be secured by centralising such development in one principal company.</P>
    <P>There are ten Parts in the Bill, and I think the best course would be if I dealt briefly with each one of these. Part I is preliminary and general, and contains the usual sections covering definitions, fees, orders and expenses. It provides in Section 8 for the repeal of the Air Navigation Act, 1920.  It has been decided to repeal that Act because it is thought better to incorporate the whole law in a single statute of the Oireachtas, and in so far as the provisions of the Act of 1920 are still found to be required, they will be re-enacted in this Bill.</P>
    <P>Part II deals with the international convention signed in Paris in 1919 and re-enacts a section of the Air Navigation Act, 1920, which empowers the Executive Council to give effect, by Order, to the convention. The section gives power to compel <Col N="1098" /> compliance when an aircraft disobeys signals, and to pay the annual contribution towards expenses of an international commission which was set up under the convention of 1919, which is also re-enacted.  Provision is made for the continuance in force of existing certificates, licences, orders and regulations, made under the earlier Act.</P>
    <P>Part III provides for the implementation of the international convention for the unification of certain rules relating to international carriage by air which was signed at Warsaw in 1929.  The convention was acceded to by the Government of Saorstát Eireann by a formal notification to the Government of the Polish Republic, made on 20th September, 1935, and was presented as a White Paper to the Oireachtas by the Minister for External Affairs.  This convention is limited in its application to the international carriage by air of persons, luggage or goods, performed by aircraft for reward.  It lays down amongst other matters certain conditions as to the contract of carriage both for passengers and goods.  It sets a limit to the carrier's liability in respect of death or injury to passengers, and in case of loss, damage or delay to goods.  In Section 18 of the present Bill, the liability imposed on the carrier by the convention is substituted for any liability of the carrier in respect of the death of a passenger under any statute or at common law, and the benefit of such liability is made available for such members of the passenger's family as sustain damage by reason of his death.  Power is taken in the Bill to apply the provisions of the Convention of Warsaw by Order of the Executive Council with any necessary modification to carriage by air which is not international.</P>
    <P>Part IV makes provision in respect of damage by aircraft to persons on land or water.  Liability for surface damage is at present governed by Section 9 of the Air Navigation Act under which absolute liability, subject to the defence of contributory negligence, is imposed on the owner of the aircraft or in certain circumstances on the hirer.  This section, which makes proof of negligence or intention on the <Col N="1099" /> part of the owner unnecessary, is re-enacted in the Bill.  Under this Part also we come to the important new feature by which provision is made for a system of compulsory insurance by the owner of the aircraft against the liability imposed, and for the limitation of such liability, or, in other words, for compulsory insurance against certain third party risks.  The Government has already thought it desirable in the case of motor vehicles to make compulsory a policy of insurance or alternative security for the protection of third parties.  In the general interests of the community it is considered that similar provision should be made in respect of aviation and that the third party on the ground should be guaranteed reasonable compensation in the event of damage to person or property from the flying of aircraft.  The necessary steps will be taken, before this chapter of the Bill is brought into operation, to ensure that as far as possible reasonable rates of insurance will be made available and that the protection of the injured third party from the adverse effects of omissions or misrepresentations on the part of the insured or the action of the insurer will be secured. I should point out with reference to this question of compulsory insurance against third party risk that an international convention dealing with the question of compulsory insurance and the limitation of liability for damage to a third party on the surface in the case of aircraft engaged in international air transport was signed at Rome in May, 1933, but has not yet come into force.  Power is taken in this Part of the Bill to give effect to that convention by order of the Executive Council when it is considered necessary and expedient to do so.</P>
    <P>Part V is concerned with the establishment and maintenance of aerodromes by the Minister for Industry and Commerce and by local authorities, and the acquisition of land and water rights, etc., for this purpose. The Minister has already power to establish and maintain aerodromes and to acquire land for that purpose <Col N="1100" /> either by consent or compulsorily.  The repeal of the 1920 Act, to which I have referred, makes the re-enactment of this provision necessary.  Some minor defects found in the provisions of the 1920 Act have been removed or remedied and advantage is taken of the present opportunity to replace the existing method of the compulsory acquisition of land, which involved the Military Lands Acts, 1892 to 1903, by the more direct and more expeditious procedure of acquisition by order, subject, if considered expedient, to a prior public inquiry, and to the incorporation in such order of the Acquisition of Land (Assessment of Compensation) Act, 1919, and the Land Clauses Acts.  It is considered desirable, also, that the efforts of local authorities to establish and maintain aerodromes should be facilitated by extending their present powers of acquisition to cover acquisition by compulsion, subject to the consent of the Minister for Industry and Commerce. The provision of aerodromes and landing-grounds is essential to the development of aviation, and the acquisition of sites therefor should not be held up by the unreasonable demands of property owners.  The Bill accordingly provides, in Section 41, for the application of the powers now held by local authorities under the Public Health (Ireland) Acts of 1878 and 1896, and the Local Government Act, 1925, to the acquisition of land for the purposes of this Part of the Act. In order also to encourage co-operation between local authorities in providing aerodromes, provision is included in the Bill for the making of a contribution by a local authority or a harbour authority to the expenses of construction of an aerodrome undertaken by another local authority and for the setting up of a joint committee of management with representatives of the different contributing bodies.  Provision is also made to extend the borrowing powers of local authorities to meet expenses incurred in the establishment of aerodromes.</P>
    <P>Part VI of the Bill is made up of provisions similar to those in the Air Navigation Act, 1920.  It excepts aircraft from action for trespass or nuisance by reason only of flight over <Col N="1101" /> property at a reasonable height and in compliance with air regulations.  It also specifies the liability and penalty for unnecessary dangerous flying.</P>
    <P>Part VII contains a number of administrative and miscellaneous provisions. The sections in the Act of 1920 dealing with wreek and salvage, investigation of accidents, infringement of patents, and jurisdiction, have been brought up to date without involving changes in principle, and the amended provisions are included in this Part.  In addition, the powers at present held under the Merchant Shipping Acts relating to ships in respect of collisions, signals of distress and urgency, and the making of regulatory bye-laws by harbour authorities have been extended to cover their application to sea-planes.  Provision is also made in this Part for the detention of aircraft to secure compliance with any of the requirements of the Bill, and to prevent aircraft from flying when unfit to fly.  The procedure for the detention of aircraft is on the lines of that applied to vessels by the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894.  The Minister for Industry and Commerce is also empowered in Part VII to collect statistics and such other information as he may specify by order from air transport concerns and the holders of licences for customs aerodromes.  Finally, air transport undertakings are placed in the same position as regards the carriage of mails as railway, tramway and omnibus undertakings.  That is to say that the General Post Office may require them to carry mails.</P>
    <P>I now come to the Parts of the Bill which will, I think prove of greatest interest at this stage.  They are Parts VIII and IX which provide for the formation of a principal national air transport company and subsidiaries and for the restriction, with a minor exception, of internal air services to those carried on by the company and its subsidiaries.  The House, I think, will fully realise the great importance of air transport in our time.  In fact, aerial transport might be described as the special expression of the spirit of the age, the spirit of scientific achievement. It has gripped the imagination <Col N="1102" /> of the people of our time in a way that few other things have.  This wonderful success, which riders of the air have achieved, in subduing the elements and utilising the powers of nature for the benefit of humanity, has awakened sympathy and interest everywhere.  Furthermore, aerial transport has provided a most important link which has brought the nations of the world nearer to one another and has done a great deal to cultivate better international understanding and better feelings amongst the peoples.  But apart from these considerations, which are considerations of importance, there are also very practical and economic considerations which Governments of the present day must have regard to, in considering the development of air transport within their territories.  Although transport by air is, comparatively speaking, in an early stage of development, wonderful progress has been achieved.  What is certain is that Governments everywhere are attaching more and more importance to the development of aviation within their own territories. They are fully alive to the tremendous possibilities of air transport development. In fact, even in the internal transport systems of many countries, air transport has become a serious rival to other forms of transport.</P>
    <P>In the international sphere, it is undoubtedly becoming a matter of first-class importance particularly to the larger countries, both from the point of view of their own prestige and of their commercial and political influence in the world, to give more and more attention to the development of the air arm.  Very many of them have taken practical steps to encourage aerial development within their own territories and internationally.  So far as we here in Saorstát Eireann are concerned, I think we have reached a very important stage in connection with air transport development.  In fact, having regard to the international developments that are going on, the position is that this stage is a very significant one for us and one to which we ought to advert in the most complete manner.  The routes along which international traffic will pass are now <Col N="1103" /> being determined and it is of importance that the Saorstát should be in a position to utilise such advantage as is afforded by its geographical position on the fringe of the Continent of Europe, to establish its claim to inclusion on these routes in which it is interested.</P>
    <P>The Government, I think I may say, have taken, and are taking steps under the present measure, to ensure that, as far as we are concerned, we shall do our utmost to utilise whatever position we may have, and whatever opportunities may offer, to secure our appropriate place in future developments and to participate in the economic and other benefits which may follow for our people and our State. So far as internal air services are concerned, it is of the first importance that there should be sufficient traffic available for the maintenance of such services once they are established. When they are established and working, I think it is clear to everybody that they provide for the acceleration of the carriage of passengers, mails, and urgent freight, and for connections with the main international services.  It is clear, therefore, that whilst having regard to international developments in air transport, we must also have regard to domestic developments and make our arrangements accordingly, so that both internal and external developments in so far as we can regulate them or influence them, will proceed hand in hand.</P>
    <P>A problem now arises in connection with the whole question of the future policy of Saorstát Eireann with regard to the development of air transport. That is, having made up our minds to follow a certain policy, what steps should the Government take to implement that policy, and what manner of organisation should it set up.  What has been the experience in other countries, and what are the best lines for us to follow?  The Minister for Industry and Commerce and his Department have been giving a good deal of attention to this matter for a considerable time past, and they have been influenced by the fact that the <Col N="1104" /> tendency in Europe has been towards the formation of large-scale companies to operate all domestic and foreign air transport under close Governmental supervision.  In France, for example, the company Air France was formed by a decree of the Minister for Air, in 1933, by an amalgamation of four companies and by taking over the assets of a fifth in liquidation.  In Germany a very similar development occurred.  After the European War, several air transport companies came into existence.  These early companies underwent a process of grouping and regrouping until in 1924 German air transport was in the hands of two rival concerns.  Following a period of very rapid development, the rivalry between those two companies developed into harmful competition and duplication, and eventually, as a result of Government intervention, a single combine, the present Deutsche Lufthansa, came into being in April, 1926.  In Holland the Government hold a large share of the capital of the principal company, the Royal Dutch Air Lines (K.L.M.).</P>
    <P>The tendency, therefore, is for modern Governments, in some form or other, to induce or require restriction of competition in air transport services. I think we may attribute this tendency on the part of modern Governments to a desire to eliminate utterly wasteful competition and to see that as far as possible the highest standards of safety will be observed.  In June of last year the Minister told the House that aviation development in the Saorstát would be organised on sound lines with proper equipment and under Irish control. The Government have decided that development on these lines can best be secured by the establishment of a national company which will control directly or through subsidiaries all internal services in the Saorstát and all participation in international services from the Saorstát.  We have come to this conclusion, after carefully considering the merits of the case for a long period.  We believe that all the advantages are on the side of creating a national transport company in which will be unified and centralised all the air transport activities with which we have to <Col N="1105" /> deal in the Saorstát.  We consider that that is the most economical and most effective way and, having regard to all the circumstances of this State, by far the most suitable method of organisation we could set up.  Provision for the formation of such a company is made in Part VIII of the Bill, and Part IX restricts the operation of all internal services to this company and its subsidiaries.</P>
    <P>The control of any regular services between Saorstát Eireann and any other country is effectively secured by the Air Navigation (International Lines) Order, 1935, which makes it necessary for the authority of the Minister for Industry and Commerce to be obtained before such service may be established by either a Saorstát Eireann or a foreign company.  It is proposed to exercise this restrictive power in favour of the national company and to give it the support of the Government in its relations with foreign Governments and competitors. Among other advantages, it is hoped, in this way, to secure for the company reciprocal treatment in the countries concerned.</P>
    <P>If we are to have any air development in Saorstát Eireann and if the Government are embarking on a large policy, I think there can be no doubt whatever that we are entitled to see that any efforts we make, and any expenditure we may commit the country to, will be utilised in such a way as to make the future commercial development of the country as economical and effective as possible.</P>
    <P>I come now to the finance clauses of the Bill.  Part VIII provides for the formation of the company and empowers the Minister for Finance to take up by subscription shares of the company and to underwrite any public issue.  The Government is satisfied that if there is to be any development of aviation in this country, on the reasonable scale contemplated, the State will have to take the initiative, and, at least in the early stages, will have to provide the necessary capital. One million pounds has been fixed as the nominal share capital of the principal company.  I should explain, with <Col N="1106" /> reference to this, that the share capital will be only called up as and when required.</P>
    <P>In Section 72 the Minister for Finance is empowered to guarantee, if he thinks fit, any issue of debentures by the company.  It is not possible at this stage to indicate what liability the State may incur under this section, but I should like to call attention to the fact that it is provided in the Second Schedule that so long as the Minister for Finance holds not less than one-tenth of the share capital, the company's right to issue debentures is subject to his consent.</P>
    <P>There are two other matters in this financial Part of the Bill which require special mention.  One is the provision for the payment of subsidies in Section 76 and the other for the loan by the principal company to Aer Lingus, Teoranta, in Section 77. With regard to the matter of subsidies, Deputies will appreciate that the principle of the subsidy, where it is working, has been accepted by certain other countries because they have considered it essential for the proper development of certain types of air lines.  Some such provision may have to be made by Saorstát Eireann for the development of certain routes.  Section 76 provides that the House will have an opportunity of examining any proposal to pay subsidies for the development of air service in Saorstát Eireann wherever the Government think such to be suitable and necessary. The procedure will be that under this section of the Bill the Minister for Finance may from time to time by Order authorise the payment of subsidies to the company on such terms and conditions as may be specified in such Order laid before the House. These Orders may be annulled or ratified and provision is made accordingly in the measure now outlined.  The section limits the aggregate amount which may be authorised to be paid to the company by way of subsidy to £500,000, and no such Order may be made after the expiration of five years from the date of the passing of this Act.</P>
    <P>I should say here, with regard to this financial proposal, that it is impossible at the moment to give details of the expenditure which has to be investigated. <Col N="1107" /> A definite figure&mdash;which is at present under consideration &mdash; is not available and it is not possible to give the House all the details we would like to give it at the present moment.  I hope it will be satisfactory if I point out at the moment that any proposal in connection with the granting of a subsidy will have to come before the House, and to come before it specifically in the way of an Order laid upon the Table and which can be discussed.</P>
    <P>There is one other provision of a financial nature and that is in Section 77 of the Bill.  It is provided that as soon as may be after the registration of the company, the company may, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, lend to Aer Lingus Teoranta, a sum sufficient to discharge any liabilities of that company.  This provision is necessary in order to regularise the position created by the formation of a subsidiary company prior to the formation of the parent company itself, which is to finance it.  It is entirely a legal matter and the present procedure has been adopted as a result of legal advice.</P>
    <P>When moving a Supplementary Estimate in November last, the Minister gave the House an indication of the Government's plans for the initiation, at the earliest possible date, of air transport services between Saorstát Eireann and Great Britain.  The arrangements he then outlined for the setting up of a Saorstát company to operate these services, on a basis of joint working with a British company, have since been completed.  Services were inaugurated on the 27th of May on the routes Dublin to Bristol, Dublin to Isle of Man, and Dublin to Liverpool via the Isle of Man.  In furtherance of the policy to operate strictly on commercial lines, these services link up with express trains on the other side of the Channel.  Further schemes for the development of services from the ports of Cork and Galway are under consideration, but I again stress the fact to which the Department has already called public attention, that the provision of suitable aerodromes is an essential preliminary <Col N="1108" /> to the operation of regular air lines. The provision of direct services to Liverpool and London from Dublin is also being considered.</P>
    <P>I should say, in connection with this international service, that reciprocity is required by all countries and the grant of landing rights in Great Britain involves the grant of corresponding rights here to a British company.  The knowledge and experience of the British company, which is one of high standing, is now made available for the joint committee of management of Irish Sea Airways, and in making the arrangement for a joint working Aer Lingus, Teoranta, has not limited its independence to any greater extent than any ordinary business agreement for joint working limits the independence of both parties to the agreement. As I have already stated, both companies have equal representation on the joint committee of management, and expenses and receipts will be pooled.</P>
    <P>The remaining sections of Part VIII deal with the relations of the principal company with the Minister for Finance, and provide for the exemption of the company and its subsidiaries from the application of the Control of Manufactures Acts, as was done in the case of Comhlucht Siuicre Eireann, Teo.</P>
    <P>Part X deals with the control and regulation of certain classes of aviation business and is in furtherance of the policy I have already outlined for the restriction of commercial flying to the principal company and its subsidiaries.  The interests of the company would be adversely affected by unrestricted operation of the private chartering of aircraft and it is, consequently, proposed as from a day to be appointed to permit such operation only under licence.  Persons who were on the 1st of January of this year engaged in the provision of charter services will be entitled, as of right, to a licence to continue to operate.  The same restriction is proposed for pleasure flights or, as they are usually called, &ldquo;joy rides,&rdquo; and for instructional flying.  I should, perhaps, <Col N="1109" /> mention, with reference to this matter of licences, that the Minister will have power to attach conditions to any licence which he may grant.  He will have power to refuse an application for renewal of a licence, and he will also have complete discretion to revoke a licence, under Section 95.  It is not considered feasible to extend the licensing provision to journeys under charter originating in another country but aircraft engaged in such flights will not be allowed to take up passengers for hire or reward within the Saorstát without a licence.  The remaining provisions of this Part of the Bill cover the grant, renewal, transfer and revocation of licences and do not call for any special comment at this stage.</P>
    <P>These are the main principles of the Air Navigation and Transport Bill. Although the Bill looks rather formidable, the principles of control, as I have already mentioned, have already been applied to other classes of transport and are well known to and appreciated by the House.  The Bill is easy to understand and will not provide any great difficulty in its later stages.  Amendment may be necessary on points of detail but, generally speaking, I think it will be conceded, that under the terms of the Bill, the Government are making definite and adequate provision to enable the Saorstát to take its due part in the development of aviation.  With the financial aid which the State will provide and the control which it will exercise through the provisions of this Bill when it becomes law, I have no doubt we shall be able to ensure that future development will be carried out by and for the benefit of Saorstát nationals as far as possible.  Finally, I think I am safe in prophesying that with the interest, financial and otherwise, which the State will in future have in the development of commercial aviation in and through Saorstát Eireann and with the direction which it will be able to give policy, that development will proceed on lines which will make certain the economic working of commercial services and the highest standards of operation in commercial and private flying.</P>
    <Col N="1110" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Minister any information to give as to the personnel of the company which it is proposed to form?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>The company has not yet been formed.  As I explained in my speech, we are not in a position to state definitely what the personnel of the company will be or, indeed, what the programme will be.  The Government is considering the programme.  I am hopeful that, within a comparatively short time, we shall be in a position to make a statement on the position.  I regret I cannot give the Deputy the information he asks.  In fact, we are only in the preliminary stages of the enterprise and the company has not yet been set up.  I am sure the Minister for Industry and Commerce will take the first opportunity to give the House the fullest information in his possession.  The information I can give at the moment is rather limited for the reason I have stated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister can scarcely be congratulated on the attendance of his Party on the Second Reading of this remarkable Bill.  For the better part of 40 minutes, two members of his Party listened to what he had to say and, for five more minutes, the number was increased to three.  The Minister, in the course of his observations, laid stress on the importance of aerial navigation.  In fact, he emphasised its importance.  I presume the information at his disposal is exhaustive.  His sources of information are, at any rate, much more numerous than those at our disposal.  May I state shortly my own experience in this connection?  I went by air from Croydon to Paris and there were approximately 20 passengers on board the vessel.  If aerial transport is of the importance which the Minister thinks, one would expect that there would be a larger number of passengers.  I went from Barcelona to Madrid by air and there were ten or 12 passengers on board.  In the light of these circumstances, we are asked to give the Minister a blank check for £1,000,000.  We are asked <Col N="1111" /> to do more than that.  We are asked, in the absence of information as to the personnel of the directorate, to give our sanction to this measure, which might be divided into three parts&mdash;the ratification of certain international agreements or protocols arrived at over a great number of years; the regulation of payment of compensation to persons or their representatives for damage done to them in the course of any flying across this country, and, thirdly, provision for the setting up of a company, the names of the directors not yet having been disclosed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have a right to complain of the manner in which this measure has been treated by the Government, in the first instance, and by the Party which supports the Government, in the second instance.  Two members of the Government Party, out of a total of 76, were present here this evening during the Minister's speech.  That is not very creditable to the Government Party.  It is all the more remarkable because the Government newspaper states that, on account of lack of opposition yesterday, the Dáil adjourned at 6 o'clock.  Apparently, we are becoming very humorous in this country when that sort of information is dished up to the public.  This Bill was first introduced to the Dáil about 12 months ago, when the Minister for Industry and Commerce announced that he had such a measure in mind.  It was formally introduced on the 1st July and it was published on Saturday last.  Some of the members of the Dáil go to the country on Saturday.  They had an opportunity of reading the Bill on Saturday or Sunday.  Some of us had not that opportunity.  We have only had this Bill in the last couple of days, and at the end of the session at the very last moment we are asked to consider this Bill to regulate air transport, to make provision for it, and to set up a company with a capital of £1,000,000.  The Minister whose duty it is to substitute for the Minister for Industry and Commerce neglected to tell us these matters that I have <Col N="1112" /> referred to in connection with the financial proposals.  There is provision in some section previous to Section 77 for an expenditure of £5,000 preliminary expenses in connection with the company.</P>
    <P>In the course of his remarks, the Minister told us that in most other countries they had come to the point where they were reducing the number of persons engaged in air transport down to one.  Obviously, if it were a profitable concern in those countries it might not be necessary to reduce the number to one, but it would appear, on the face of it at any rate, as if the Government were not particularly in earnest in regard to this matter. Having 12 months ago given notice to the Dáil that they had an Air Navigation and Transport Bill, they produced this Bill on the 1st July, and the Dáil is to adjourn, presumably, before the 1st August.  I expect the Minister wants all the stages of this Bill before the Recess.  While he takes 12 months to produce the baby he expects us to baptise and confirm it in the short space of three or four weeks.</P>
    <P>There are provisions in this measure which, a few years ago, would have shocked anybody with any democratic feelings.  There is power given to the Minister to make Orders, to revoke Orders, to amend Orders, and to alter them almost at will.  Is there any measure in transport or otherwise, apart from a measure introduced during the course of a war, that gives greater power to an Executive Minister or to the Executive Council than are given in this Bill?  I suggest to the Minister the advisability of withdrawing the measure and giving it to us in three parts, first its international side if it is an international measure.  We would then arrive at the other part after due consideration, and, if it was necessary for us to implement the first part, to pass it.  Surely we ought to have had a single measure dealing with that side of the question.  The next question is air navigation.  Does it matter to the individual whether he is killed by a foreigner or by a member of our Army?  Is there provision in this Bill for compensation for any damage done <Col N="1113" /> by an Army officer in the course of manæuvres?</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, I suppose that means that there is to be no compensation in respect of a person killed by an Army plane.  He has such honour done to him that it is worth while for him to go out in a blaze of glory.  Is that the idea?  I think no matter who does the damage the citizen ought to be compensated.  Presumably we are to have Army aeroplanes.  Aeroplanes come over my house occasionally, and it would be all the same to me whether it was one of these crashed or one of the new company.</P>
      <P>I am glad the Minister has referred to the fact that we are not reducing our political status by this measure, that we are to give and take, and that we are not in this impossible position of isolation, of solitary and absolute independence. We have in the question of air to come down to earth at some time or other.  The Minister realises that we have to do business on earth with other people whether we agree with them or not.  But all the time we can wrap the green flag round us and say that everybody else must come down to earth, too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>From the point of view that we are to put £1,000,000 into an Irish company we ought to have before us the names of the directorate.  That is not an unreasonable request.  We ought to know all about the firm and what it is to do. The Government ought not to take the line that in regard to the powers that are embodied in this Bill to the extent that if subsidies are given or if debentures are going to be given the Dáil is the last place where any information about the company is going to be furnished.  This measure in all its compilation makes a mockery of democracy. I noticed that in the 40 or 45 minutes that the Minister was speaking there were present only three members of his Party.  That is not creditable to his Party.  My own Party was better represented; there was one Independent who lasted out for some time; one solitary member who has resigned from the Fianna Fáil Party, <Col N="1114" /> and one member of the Labour Party. In the ordinary course of events this measure should be a matter that ought to concern all Parties in this State.  It ought to be dealt with in a non-Party manner and in the way I have said&mdash; that is that the international arrangements should be in one Bill, compensation in the second, and the other matters dealt with in the third Bill, or alternatively that the Bill should be divided into two compartments and the new company with regulations should be set out in the second part of it.  I object very strongly to the form in which this Bill is presented.  If we are to put £1,000,000 into a concern, the Dáil should know the names of the persons who are to be directors.  As the measure stands, it is open to the Minister to select whom he likes after the Bill passes this House.  The House has no control and it cannot utter any criticisms.  It is not advisable that criticism should be uttered once we are committed to the Bill.  But there is no reason why if this is a serious effort towards improving transport in this country that the Minister should not have provided us with the names of the directors and informed us of the other provisions.  It is strange that there should be such a provision in the Bill as to embody the principle that subsidies should be paid when the Minister desires.</P>
    <P>There is the other proposition about debentures.  Debentures may be issued in very sound companies for very good reasons.  The ordinary conception of a debenture is that it means a mortgage.  That the Government is going to back the flotation of an air navigation company is the fact before us and information is furnished that there may be debentures subsequently issued.  The ordinary man who is an investor is very likely to be frightened by the idea of debentures.  Is his money that is going to be put into this concern in its earlier stages to be the speculative part, and if there are losses or if the company does not pay, are the debentures then to be brought in to make what we call the solid or stable portion of the company? I suppose the Minister is in a hurry with this measure.  However, I <Col N="1115" /> cannot congratulate him on the haste with which it has been introduced nor on the attendance of his Party to listen to his speech in the House.  I am quite sure the Minister who is acting as substitute for the Minister for Industry and Commerce has done his best in the circumstances.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OsmondGrattanEsmonde" hpid="Sir Osmond Esmonde Sir Osmond Esmonde">
      <NameTxt>Sir Osmond Esmonde</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Industry and Commerce has been absent from the House for some time now.  Some time ago he promised to introduce this Bill and pass it through the House in all its stages before the Recess.  These promises are being carried out in spite of his illness.  I think a great deal of the detail in the early stages of the Bill is of a routine character.  Regulations are being brought up to date to fit in with the corresponding regulations in other countries.  Certainly this Bill has been long delayed.  I think it is three years now since the Bill was promised by the Minister.  Two Bills have recently been passed in the British House of Commons embodying many suggestions and the regulations which are to be found in this measure.  I carefully read through the debates in the British House of Commons on these Bills, and I must say there was nothing very enlightening to be had from the contributions made on these occasions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Bill is more in the nature of an enabling Bill to enable the Government to do certain things in future, but even when the Bill becomes an Act everything will remain to be done for the development of commercial air transport in this country.  The full responsibility will devolve on the Executive Council and the Minister. As Deputy Cosgrave pointed out, they are given great latitude in making such regulations as they choose.  It is to be hoped that they will show care and foresight, which they have not shown on other occasions in connection with other matters, because to make mistakes at the starting of a national air transport service would be a very serious matter and might be irrevocable. There are many amendments and adjustments which can be brought into this measure on the Committee <Col N="1116" /> Stage.  It will be found on looking through the Bill that there are a considerable number of contradictions from one section to another.  That need not concern us to-day, however. The main matter which the public are interested in will be whether there is any danger of foreign influences getting a monopoly of our air communications. We have had sad experience in the past of monopoly, or more or less monopoly, with regard to shipping, which resulted in great losses over a large number of years to the agricultural community owing to the rates being higher than they would have been if that monopoly had not existed.  We have now an internal monopoly, more or less, with regard to land transport.  We heard accusations bandied about during the last year that national possessions in our territorial waters or in the subsoil of the country are being gradually surrendered to foreign interests.  There is no doubt that the country must insist that in this question of the initiation of air transport there must be a clear acceptance of co-equality between the State and its neighbours.  In no other matter is insistence on co-equality more important than in this matter. Some people are alarmed that the Government may not be sufficiently alive to the vital importance of that at the very beginning&mdash;that air transport should not be mortgaged or put in such a position that within a certain number of years it will be mortgaged to outside interests.</P>
    <P>There are certain sections in the Bill which at first sight might appear to be rather alarming.  I notice that under Section 80 the Control of Manufactures Act does not apply in respect of any act or thing done by the company or any subsidiary company.  I do not know if such a provision in a Bill of this kind is not of too far-reaching a nature.  As I have not got these Acts before me, I do not know exactly how they will apply, but that is a matter which the Minister might look into before the Committee Stage.  In any case, the Bill will be quite useless unless it is followed up by active measures on the part of the Government for the development of commercial aviation.  In the first place this <Col N="1117" /> Bill will be absolutely useless from the point of view of our international air communications until we make that convention with Great Britain provided for in the final section of the Schedule to the Treaty of 1921.  The very final section of that Schedule says that a convention must be arrived at between Great Britain and the Saorstát to regulate air navigation. Until we have that in black and white, we are very much in a vacuum as to what the prospects of air development are.  Secondly, I think there will be very little use in this Bill being operated by the Government unless they insist from the very beginning that, as far as this country is concerned, our mutual relations by air with other countries should be on a fifty-fifty basis&mdash;that we should have 50 per cent. of the air-borne traffic from the very beginning.</P>
    <P>Apart from the Department of Industry and Commerce, this Bill will not be of very much use unless it has the active co-operation of other Departments of State; unless the Post Office authorities go out of their way perhaps to lose some money on their Vote in order to help in establishing this venture.  Likewise, the Department of Defence will have to give its co-operation and, perhaps most important of all, the Minister who is in charge of the Bill will have to give the active and financial support of his Department, the Department of Education, in order to provide for the future personnel of this line which is about to be started.</P>
    <P>During the last 15 years practically nothing has been done in this country to provide personnel for an eventual national air service of this kind.  A few individuals have, out of very meagre resources, endeavoured to give opportunities to the younger generation to learn the art of air navigation, but from the point of view of the Government nothing has been done, whereas in other parts of the world Governments have set aside vast sums to provide their own young people with opportunities of instruction in these highly-technical matters. In this country we have the advantage or disadvantage, according to the political <Col N="1118" /> opinions of people, of being a member of the Commonwealth and so great numbers of young men have been able to learn the elements of aviation in the British service and in the service of other members of the Commonwealth.  But that is only a very temporary employment and after five years they cease to find any outlet for the profession which they took up more out of curiosity than otherwise. So that if this is to be a permanent national institution the Minister for Education, in conjunction with the other Departments, must be prepared to take the necessary steps and to provide the necessary money to equip the Irish air line with Irishmen and women to run it efficiently, just as in the case with other national lines in other parts of the world.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Esmonde remarked that nothing had been done to develop, in any kind of a satisfactory or effective way, air services in the State during the last 15 years. The introduction of this measure recalls, however, the fact that it was not from lack of appreciation of the importance of air services that this neglected development arose.  One of the first things that was done during the time of the Provisional Government in April or May of 1922 was to set up, in connection with the Department of Defence, a Military Air Council and a Civil Air Council, one being under Commandant MacSwiney and the other under Colonel Russell.  In 1922 we had a situation which brought the services of both these officers and of the personnel associated with them into the military side of aviation. The losses and the distractions of 1922 and 1923 prevented, during these years and the years immediately following, the kind of development that we so readily set out to bring about in the earlier years of the State. They emphasise, too, how many of the Sibylline Books have been burned during these last 15 years.  When we see the amount of money that is involved in this Bill&mdash;when we see that some of the Sibylline Books are still burning&mdash;and find that the Minister is setting up this company at a time when there is not so much <Col N="1119" /> money available as there might have been two or three years ago; that there will not be as much money available next year as there is this year, it all shows the way things are going.</P>
      <P>That leads me on to direct attention to Sections 39 and 40 in connection with the acquisition of land. Two questions arise in connection with the acquisition of land by this company or, for the setting up of an aerodrome, by the Minister or a local authority.  In the first place, we have no information as to what the terms of the capitalisation of this company are going to be.  We have no idea of the rate of interest which people who invest their money in the company may expect to get.  In connection with the powers taken in the Bill for the compulsory acquisition of land, I would like to ask whether the promoters of this new company&mdash;the capitalisers of it I imagine will expect to draw 6 per cent. or some rate like that on their money&mdash;are going to be assisted to set it up at the expense of a few farmers in the country who may have their land taken from them at the miserable price that, say, the Land Commission is paying for land at the present time.  I do not think that, in setting up a company of this particular kind, the Minister either on his own behalf or on behalf of the company should vest himself with power that will enable him to select any land in the country that he thinks he wants, and then take it from the present owners at a price other than the market price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want also to have a very clear statement from the Minister on a question that has already been raised here regarding the taking of some part of the Phænix Park and setting up there an air port.  I think it was an officer of Aer Lingus, Teoranta, who, in correspondence in the Press, disclosed that communications had taken place, or were taking place, between ourselves, or somebody interested in them, and the Minister for Finance, urging the taking of a substantial part of the Phænix Park, and turning it into an air port.  Now, the financial stringency in which the Minister and this company <Col N="1120" /> may find themselves may induce the Ministry to consider doing that.  I want to say that it would be a disgrace and an outrage, apart altogether from the injury it would do to the capital to have any part of the Phænix Park taken away as an amenity from general use by the people.  It would be a disgrace to have that amenity taken away from them, but it would be much worse to have it taken away and turned into an air port, and at a point of the city, too, in which, in my opinion, it would be most unsuitable to have an air port established.  That question was raised here on the Estimate for the Board of Works.  The Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance would not commit himself to any statement on the matter then beyond saying that no communication had been addressed to him.  But it is explicit in the statements that have been made in the correspondence appearing in the Press that the matter has been raised as between the representatives of or the persons interested in Aer Lingus, Teoranta, and the Minister for Finance.</P>
    <P>I want the Acting Minister for Industry and Commerce to address himself to the matter when replying, and to assure us, in the first place, that no section of the Phænix Park is going to be taken from the people to be used for this purpose, and that, if an air port is going to be established in the neighbourhood of the City of Dublin, the Minister for Industry and Commerce will consult with the Minister for Local Government and Public Health, who is the Governmental expert on town planning, to see that it will not be in the wrong place, either from the point of view of its own particular requirements as an airport, or of the city as a whole.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister to reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is rather strange that both Deputy Esmonde and Deputy Cosgrave should complain that this Bill is being rushed through. There is no attempt to rush the Bill through.  Deputies will have ample time to consider the Bill fully, and to move whatever amendments they wish <Col N="1121" /> on the Committee Stage.  Deputy Cosgrave seemed to find fault with the Minister for Industry and Commerce because the Minister had indicated 12 months ago that this Bill was forthcoming. Deputy Esmonde suggested that the Bill was promised so far back as three years ago, and now both Deputies tell us that it is being rushed through.  I cannot see that the Bill is being rushed through.  There is very little other business on the Clár, and if the attendance in the House is disappointing in view of the importance of the measure, I think I can say that the nature of the criticisms which have been levelled against the measure is still more disappointing.  They would seem to indicate that if the heat has kept a large number of Deputies away from the House, it has also had some effect on those who remained, and prevented them from giving of their best to the consideration of an important measure of this kind.  This is a measure which, obviously, is not merely a matter for this Government or even for the next Government.  It is a matter in which all future Governments will have to be interested.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One point that Deputy Cosgrave raised was the question of the directorate. I must say that, at first glance, I thought his demand for the names of the directorate of the new company was reasonable, but on reflection I do not think it is convincing. Even if we had reached the stage when we had actually established the company and had the names available, I do not think that we could bring them here to have a discussion on them. I do not think that has been the practice in connection with the appointment of directors to any public corporation of this kind.  I think it has never been suggested on any previous occasion when Governments were taking steps to set up big corporations such as the Electricity Supply Board, the Agricultural Credit Corporation, the Industrial Credit Corporation or Comhlucht Siúicre Eireann Teoranta, that the names of the directors should be brought up here and that we should have a discussion on them.  The practice has been, I think, that before the Government <Col N="1122" /> can appoint the directors in a company of this nature the Bill which provides for the establishment of the company must first be passed into law. Even when it has passed into law, there would obviously be a difficulty in discussing the personnel here in the House.  I think we have to assume that the Government, when the Bill has passed into law, and when they have received the decision of the House in favour of going ahead with their proposals, will select the best personnel they can possibly secure for this important work.  We all know the difficulties that attend the procuring of suitable personnel for a highly technical undertaking of this nature. There is the difficulty of securing Irish nationals with the necessary high technical qualifications, training and experience, and there may be other difficulties.</P>
    <P>I think Deputies should at least be thankful to the Minister and the Department of Industry and Commerce for having brought us so far that we now, at any rate, have definite proposals laid before the House.  If the actual concrete programme of work which is envisaged by these proposals has not advanced as far as we would like, possibly the explanation is that it is a matter of the greatest difficulty and the greatest complexity.  Obviously the Government have to walk warily and examine cautiously every step they take.  Any step we take at the present juncture is likely to be considered a precedent in the future.  We cannot always say, as has been the experience in connection with the setting up of those other big public companies, what the reactions or the results of the steps we are taking will be in all cases.  We have to try to envisage what the ultimate consequences will be and I think Deputies will appreciate that any delay that has arisen is due to the fact that the Government are going into the matter most carefully and are using the most expert opinion they can secure to give them advice in regard to the flotation of the company and the development of commercial aviation in the Saorstát.</P>
    <P>I do not think Deputy Cosgrave was in earnest when he suggested that this was an antidemocratic measure.  It <Col N="1123" /> has not been the proud privilege of this Government, it has not been their special prerogative, to come to the Dáil with Bills which give Ministers power to make Orders.  That has been a feature of all modern legislation and, while jurists may quibble at the extended authority that that brings to Ministers and Departmental officials, I think it will have to be recognised, on the other hand, that it would be impossible for a modern Government to deal with all the complex matters that come up for consideration unless Ministers were granted this power of making Orders and Regulations.  When an Order is made by a Minister the Dáil always has the opportunity for discussion, by a Deputy putting down a motion calling for its annulment; any member of the Dáil can always secure a discussion on any particular Order if he so wishes.  Deputy Cosgrave has not submitted a single point against the Bill except that with regard to the board of the company, and even there I doubt if he is in earnest.  He has not put forward a single argument to show that he takes exception to anything in the Bill.  His general attitude seems to be to make any points against it that may come into his head and then let it go through with the least possible delay.</P>
    <P>This Bill has been in process of preparation for several years.  Again and again it has come before the Executive Council and has been sent back to the Department of Industry and Commerce.  A special committee has been working on this question of air transport.  Discussions and conferences have been going on continuously for the past two and even three years. This Bill is the fruit of all that labour. If Deputy Cosgrave had a grievance because there is not sufficient criticism or because the House is not more interested in the measure, I can only assume, having regard to the policy which the Government are embarking upon, that the House considers the Bill is in a satisfactory state, that it represents national policy fairly well and that on the whole it should get general national support.  That is undoubtedly very welcome to me as representing the Minister for Industry <Col N="1124" /> and Commerce.  I am glad to see that all Parties, in so far as we have had a discussion, seem united in desiring that aerial transport and all matters connected with aerial navigation should be taken up by the Government and that an energetic policy should be pursued.</P>
    <P>Deputy Cosgrave and also Deputy Mulcahy raised a question with regard to cost.  Of course air transport, the development of commercial aviation, is a most expensive business.  The Government have considered that fully and there are two alternatives, either to do nothing, to allow the state of affairs we have had in the country for many years past to continue&mdash;a policy which Deputy Esmonde certainly is not satisfied with, and even Deputy Mulcahy is not satisfied with&mdash;or to take our courage in our hands and go forward, making the fullest use of whatever opportunities now offer. That is our position.  Undoubtedly these services are uneconomic; undoubtedly they are extremely costly to maintain.  Our country is not in a very fortunate position as regards wealth.  We have not a long tradition of industry behind us.  At the same time, I think there is a spirit of enterprise in the Ireland of the present day and a desire to take advantage of any opportunities that may present themselves to extend our influence, to put ourselves on the map, and to show that we are prepared to take our place amongst the States of the world. If, in order to do so, we have to face certain responsibilities, make certain sacrifices, spend certain sums of money, then we have to be prepared to make those sacrifices.  We have to carry out our responsibilities and to put our country on the map, and that is the attitude of the Government.</P>
    <P>Deputy Esmonde referred to the question of co-equality.  I think I can assure him that since the moment when the Government first undertook the consideration of this whole question of air transport, and how best it might be developed, they have had in the very forefront the idea of establishing equality with any other country with which we may have to enter on business relations. <Col N="1125" /> That is what the Government have been striving for.  As regards the convention in the Treaty of 1921, I do not think it is necessary for me to enter into that question.  At the present moment there are cross-Channel services in operation.  There has been agreement and friendly co-operation between the British Government and ourselves in the running of those services, and we can only hope that in the future, if there is to be further development in which the British Government and ourselves will participate, or any other Government for that matter, there will be this agreement.  So long as you have cordial working agreements of that character I do not think we need worry very much about the Appendix to the 1921 Treaty.</P>
    <P>As regards Section 80 of the Bill, to which the Deputy referred, regarding the Control of Manufactures Act, I am advised that the Control of Manufactures Act does not apply in this instance, because the Minister for Finance is a corporation sole, and as such is not a Saorstát national.  His holding of a majority of shares in the company would possibly necessitate the issue of a licence by the Minister for Industry and Commerce under the Control of Manufactures Act.  I presume that it is in order to eliminate the necessity for the issue of a licence by the Minister for Industry and Commerce to the Minister for Finance that this section has been put into the Bill.</P>
    <P>With regard to the question of the training of personnel for the development of air services, we are somewhat handicapped in this country.  I think I should take the opportunity to say that the Government and anybody who is interested in this question must pay a tribute&mdash;and I gladly do&mdash;to Deputy Esmonde, to the Army officers and to those private citizens who have been interested in the development of air transport, who have tried to focus public attention on the possibilities of developing that service in An Saorstát, and who have been for a considerable time past, at their own expense, on their own volition and without any Government assistance, carrying on a campaign to arouse more public interest in this whole question.  We <Col N="1126" /> are thankful to them for what they have done.  I hope that in the future they will continue that work and that we shall have voluntary organisations co-operating with the Government in creating an air feeling amongst the people and in getting them to realise that it is absolutely necessary that the population generally should endeavour to co-operate with private persons or voluntary organisations in spreading the idea of flying and in making flying more popular here.</P>
    <P>We have to depend very largely on the Army for the training of our personnel, and I think that recently the Army have been taking apprentices in their engineering shops and training them.  I think they have taken quite a large number from the technical schools.  That is a very good instance of what can be done, and I hope it will continue and expand.  The technical schools in themselves would find it very difficult to provide technical training. They would not have the necessary finances to provide machinery and so on, but a good foundation can be laid in the ordinary motor engineering classes which are carried on in most of the technical schools throughout the country.  Boys can get a very good foundation there if they continue the motor engineering classes for a period of years.  If at the end of the course they get a motor engineering certificate, I am sure that if commercial aviation is to develop in this country, and if the Army are to develop this course of training which they have initiated, the possession of such a certificate would be a passport to further training, enabling a boy to get higher qualifications, and probably to get employment.  If he could not get employment in this country, at least anywhere he might go he would be amply equipped to take up employment.</P>
    <P>We would require, therefore, the co-operation of the Army and the co-operation of the new company with the Department of Education before we could do very much in the way of training personnel.  I hope that in the same way as Comhlucht Siúicre Eireann has set up a scheme for the training of apprentices, one of the first things the new company will turn its hand to will be the training of personnel.  By training <Col N="1127" /> the ordinary rank and file we are doing the surest and best thing to ensure that finally the control of the industry will be in the hands of purely Irish technicians.  If at the present moment, and for some years to come, we have any difficulty in getting Irish technicians of the most highly-trained character, and with the highest qualifications, we will, at any rate, be able to look forward to the time when any foreigners we may have to employ&mdash;and I hope we will not have to employ a great number&mdash;will be replaced by Irish nationals.  Deputy Esmonde knows that the Minister for Industry and Commerce has been particularly keen on that aspect of national policy in regard to those ventures in which he has had some share of responsibility, and I feel quite certain that the overwhelming importance of the air transport service will demand that very special attention indeed will have to be given to the training of personnel, and to the provision of facilities to enable Irish nationals to get the fullest possible training in all processes relating to air transport.</P>
    <P>I do not, A Leas-Chinn Comhairle, think that there are any further points with which I have to deal.  I do not agree with Deputy Cosgrave that amalgamations in foreign countries are a proof that air transport is not profitable. Undoubtedly, as I say, there are losses attaching to it, particularly in the preliminary stages.  We have scarcely passed out of the preliminary stages yet.  In some of the most important international routes we are only entering on the preliminary and experimental stages.  It is obvious that there must be certain financial losses for some years, but eventually there can be no doubt that air transport will be firmly established, and will be a competitor, as I have already said, with other forms of transport in every sphere, and in every international line of communication.</P>
    <P>The point which Deputy Cosgrave raised with regard to Army plane accidents is rather a trivial one.  As a matter of fact I think the present Minister for Industry and Commerce introduced a clause in one of his Transport Acts providing that compensation <Col N="1128" /> for accidents caused by Army or other Government motor vehicles should be available in the same way as in the case of ordinary private vehicles.  If it is necessary, I am sure it can be arranged that persons who suffer in life or property from accidents in which Army planes are concerned will be entitled to seek compensation, but I think the number of such accidents up to the present has been very small.  As far as I know, it is the Army personnel who have suffered in any accidents which have occurred.  I do not think the point is of importance, or indeed that it should have been raised here.  It is really a matter for either the Minister for Defence or the Minister for Finance if Deputy Cosgrave is seriously concerned.</P>
    <P>Deputy Mulcahy has raised the question of the possible occupation of the Phænix Park as an air port or aerodrome.  I cannot say definitely that the Phænix Park will not be chosen.  A Departmental Committee has been working on the question.  I cannot at the moment say any more than that in coming to a decision as to what site in the vicinity of Dublin will be most suitable, I am sure the committee will have due regard to the fact that the Phænix Park constitutes a very important amenity for the people of Dublin.  I am sure that the committee, unless it is absolutely necessary, will scarcely advise that that particular site should be taken over as an aerodrome.  I cannot give the Deputy any further information at the moment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister say if the inter-Departmental Committee to which he referred had actualy been considering the Phænix Park?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume the committee have considered all the sites in the neighbourhood of Dublin, but I have nothing to show that, when it comes to making a decision, they are going to go out of their way to suggest the Phænix Park as against other sites unless there is something which induces the belief in them that <Col N="1129" /> the Phænix Park is really the only suitable site.  However, I have no information at the moment, but the Deputy can put down a question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister tell us when the committee was set up, to whom the committee will report, and whether its report will be published?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the committee will report almost immediately to the Minister for Industry and Commerce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>And will that report be published?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>No. The Deputy can put down a question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good.  Can the Minister give a reply to the point with regard to the purchase price of land under Section 39?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>The same procedure has been followed as under the Assessment of Compensation Act&mdash;I think that is the name of the Act&mdash;and the Minister may, if he considers it expedient, hold a public inquiry.  I think the desire of the Minister for Industry and Commerce is not to do anything that could be regarded as unjust to the owners of land, but simply to have powers, in cases of urgency, and, in his anxiety to get the work going at the earliest possible moment, to afford him sufficient powers, in case of failure to agree, to compel the owners, if they were making unreasonable demands as they do sometimes when they feel that the Government is interested, to give up possession.  I think the matter might be gone into more fully on the Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be read a Second Time&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the Committee Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest next Wednesday, Sir, if the House is agreeable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Sir, the Minister <Col N="1130" /> has already pointed out that this is a matter that has been under consideration by the Government for a number of years.  The Dáil was only asked to have the Bill printed on the 1st July, and the Bill was not circulated until a few days ago.  The fact that the Bill has not had a very adequate discussion on the Second Stage, I think, is all the greater reason for reasonable time to be given for further consideration of the Bill and for the insertion of amendments that may be found to be necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>May I point out to the Deputy that his Party have agreed to take the Committee Stage of the Land Bill on Wednesday next although they divided on the First Reading?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not here when that arrangement was made.  As far as I know, the arrangement was to take the Appropriation Bill.  However, whatever may be said about the Land Bill, the Minister, in introducing the Land Bill, minimised the provisions of that Bill as matters of very minor importance and as matters that had already been fully discussed in the House before, only indicating that the fully-discussed intention of the Government before had not materialised in the actual drafting.  Accordingly, I think it is quite unreasonable to ask for the Committee Stage of this Bill to be taken so soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, if we put it in for the following week, I presume that, in case the Dáil would be adjourning for the Recess shortly, the Deputy would facilitate us in getting the Bill through?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister could be much more easily facilitated after the Committee Stage than between the Second Stage and the Committee Stage, in view of the short time that has elapsed since this Bill was put in Deputies' hands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>Very well.  Let us say Tuesday week, then.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 21st July.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Bread (Regulation" RHead="of Prices) Bill, 1936&mdash;Final Stages">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Bread (Regulation of Prices) Bill, 1936&mdash;Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1131" /> Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Acting Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Derrig) Acting Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Derrig)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Derrig)</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the House agree to take the remaining stage now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Minister anything to say to the criticisms that were put forward on the Committee Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>There were two criticisms put forward.  The first was the contention by Deputy McGilligan that owing to the lack of a definition of the word &ldquo;bread&rdquo; in the Bill it would be difficult, according to the Deputy, to operate the Bill.  He considered it necessary to have a definition of bread.  The Minister explained at considerable length that he considered such a definition was not necessary, and that the best way to proceed was by making Orders fixing the price or prices for different kinds of bread, and the Minister informed the House on that occasion that he had gone fully into the matter in the Department.  I do not agree with Deputy McGilligan that it will be possible for the Minister to define some other commodity, such as confectionery and so on, as bread in any Order which he may make.</P>
      <P>The other point was raised by Deputies O'Neill and McGilligan, and was to the effect that under a strict interpretation of Section 4, sub-section (1), a trader would commit an offence if he sold bread in units which were not exact multiples of a pound.  The sub-section says:</P>
      <P>The Minister may by any Bread (Price) Order prohibit the sale or offering for sale in the area to which such Order applies of bread of any kind to which such Order applies, unless such bread is sold or offered for sale either (1) in units of less than eight ounces in weight or (2) in units of one pound or multiples of one pound in weight.  ...</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The contention was that a trader would commit an offence if he sold <Col N="1132" /> bread in units which were not exact multiples of a pound, and it was actually stated that probably it would be regarded as an offence against the section if a trader gave a few ounces more in a loaf of bread, which would be offered for sale, we will say, as a 2-lb. loaf.  The Minister promised to look into the matter.  Since that we have consulted the draftsman and legal adviser in the Department, and their opinion is that a seller would comply with an Order made by the Minister under sub-section (1) of Section 4 if he purported to sell in units of a pound, even though the weight was not an exact multiple of a pound, and they are of opinion, as I would be, that we have to assume, in connection with the administration of this Act, that reasonable foresight and reasonable intelligence and common sense will be exercised to ensure that equity is maintained and that ridiculous prosecutions are not made.  I do not think there would be any doubt whatever but that there would be no prosecution in a case where the loaf was a few ounces over the weight which it was purported to contain. These two points are not of very great importance, and in the opinion of the expert advisers in the Department the method laid down in the Bill is the best way in which to proceed.  Accordingly, I think we should take the Bill as it stands.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>A very important point was raised in the earlier discussions on this measure concerning the price of bread, and it is a remarkable thing that in a Bill introduced by the Minister, because he thinks the price of bread should be controlled, he has not been brought to earth at any stage as to what the price of bread should be.  It was pointed out that people who are buying bread and flour, and that means almost every member of the community, as a result of the wheat policy alone, are paying £1,500,000 each year more for the stuff they consume than they would be paying if the Government's policy was not being pursued.  In addition to that, the Commission that reported on the price of bread stated that the <Col N="1133" /> millers during the first quarter of the year 1934 made an unreasonable profit, that is, a profit beyond what would have been thought to be a reasonable profit&mdash;£32,000&mdash;in that quarter.  When the Commission was reporting, the price of the 4-lb. loaf in Cork and Waterford was 10d., in Dublin 8½d., and in Limerick 8d.  Since then the price of the 4-lb. loaf has gone up by 1½d., and in Cork by 1d.  As a matter of fact, when the Commission was reporting, the price of bread in Cork was excessively high, but the bakers in Cork were then raising the price of bread.  We want to know under these circumstances what the Minister for Industry and Commerce has in mind for the price of the 4-lb. loaf in Dublin, Cork, Waterford and Limerick.  The Minister indicated that it had to be made by formula.  On June 25th he was asked whether he had not time enough between then and the Committee Stage to figure out what the price of the 4-lb. loaf in Dublin should be, with the particulars available to him that went to make up the formula.</P>
      <P>We are now asked to let the Bill go through, and to hand over these powers to the Minister.  He rather indicated that he hoped he would not have to use them, that is that this was a piece of legislation to be applied <i>in terrorum</i> but he has given no indication in the House, to the public or to the bakers what he considers the price of bread should be in the City of Dublin.  However, in the City of Dublin we have the fact that when the millers were making that unreasonable profit of £32,000 in a quarter, on top of the cost to the people of the Government's wheat policy, the price of bread was 8½d. for the 4-lb. loaf but it has now gone up to 10d.  It is in these circumstances that I say it is utter nonsense and really degrading to the intelligence of the House that the Minister should ask us to pass this Bill without telling either the public or the bakers what the price of the 4-lb loaf should be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Mr. Derrig Mr. Derrig">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Derrig</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Minister would be in a position to state definitely what the price of bread should be in Dublin.  The Deputy <Col N="1134" /> knows that under the Bill the Minister has to consult the Millers' Advisory Committee and has probably to make further inquiries.  The Bill is based on the recommendations of the report of the Prices Commission on bread and, according to that, it was stated the wholesale and retail prices charged for batch bread were unreasonably high in a number of cases.  A formula was laid down in the report, and all I can promise the Deputy is that when the order is being made regard will be had to that formula.  Of course, the Minister will have to make further inquiries, and to consult with the millers, so that it would be quite impossible for me here and now to say what the actual figure will be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>There you are. We had a long examination into this business and we had a report in existence for a long time, then discussions, and consideration of the whole question by the Department of Industry and Commerce, after which an elaborate Bill was brought in.  Although the price of the 4-lb. loaf in Dublin was 8½d. when the Commission considered the price of bread too high, it is now 10d.  The whole machinery of the Department of Industry and Commerce is not able to tell the unfortunate purchaser of bread what ought to be reasonably asked for the 4-lb. loaf.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Superannuation" RHead="Bill, 1936&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Superannuation Bill, 1936&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee) Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is confined exclusively to questions of Civil Service Superannuation and one of its aims is to secure that a number of civil servants who by reason of interruption of service due to association with the events of 1916 to 1923 will be in no worse position as regards the application to them of the Superannuation Code than they would have been in if there had been no such interruption in their service.  In applying this principle an endeavour is being made <Col N="1135" /> as far as possible to adhere to the practice followed in connection with the Superannuation and Pensions Act, 1923.  In that Act, recognition for pensions' purposes was given to service in the Civil Service of Dáil Eireann, but this recognition was subject to certain limitations and qualifications. Of these the most important was that all civil servants proposed for benefit should have been employed in the Dáil Civil Service before the date of the Truce, that is before the 11th July, 1921.  No provision was made for what are known as post-Truce Dáil civil servants and in actual practice such officers were assimilated with the general body of the temporary staff of Saorstát Eireann, and subsequently given an opportunity by means of a limited competitive examination to acquire permanency.  The main examination at which a number did secure pensionable posts was a limited examination held in June-July, 1925.  Successful competitors at that examination were in due course assigned to permanent pensionable posts as clerical officers, the majority of such assignments taking place about February, 1926. Under the present Bill, this distinction as between pre-Truce and post-Truce service is being retained, that is, the pre-Truce people are being treated as pensionable, with the exception of one peculiar type of case in which the officer originally entered the service in circumstances which clearly indicated that his appointment was to be on a permanent and, presumably, when the circumstances permitted, on a pensionable basis.  With this exception post-Truce entrants are regarded as non-pensionable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have already indicated that the post-Truce officers assimilated prior to 1926 were afforded an opportunity of securing establishment which enabled those officers who availed themselves of that opportunity to commence pensionable service from February, 1926. It is proposed, as far as possible, to equate post-Truce Dáil civil servants, dealt with under the present Bill, to their former colleagues, in the matter of pensionability.  Where, <Col N="1136" /> therefore, they have acquired establishment, for instance by means of successful competition at limited examinations, they have been treated as if they never had an interruption of service and had competed successfully at the limited examination held in June-July of 1925.  Accordingly, under this Bill, their pensionable service is, on that basis, being allowed to reckon as from the 1st of February, 1926.  In relation to civil servants, other than those who came over from the Dáil staff, and whose service was interrupted for the same reasons, the same principle is being followed which governed the treatment of similar cases under the Superannuation and Pensions Act, 1923.  Pensionable officers have been reinstated in pensionable posts and the period of their absence is being allowed to reckon for pension purposes.  Non-pensionable persons have been reinstated in non-pensionable posts and their period of absence is also being included in the calculation of any award that may fall to be made under the Superannuation Acts.</P>
    <P>Service for the purposes of these Acts will, in both cases, fall into three divisions&mdash;(a) service before forfeiture of office for political reasons, (b) the period of absence which will be deemed to be service, and (c) the actual service which they render subsequent to reinstatement. Where unestablished officers reinstated in unestablished or temporary posts have, since reinstatement, secured establishment, regard has been had to the possibilities of establishment which would have been open to them in common with the post-Truce Dáil civil servants had they remained in the Service.  They have, therefore, whether they have been established or acquired establishment, been allowed to reckon their pensionable service as from a date not earlier than the 1st February, 1926.  Where the application of that date would, by reference to normal superannuation practice, involve the grant to a reinstatee of a lesser benefit than would have been accorded to him, if he had never ceased to serve, power is being taken to grant to such reinstatee the benefits appropriate under the normal superannuation practice.  This concession <Col N="1137" /> will apply principally to Departmental classes, such as postmen and technical assistants in the Ordnance Survey who, by long established custom, are allowed to reckon unestablished service or a proportion thereof for pension purposes.  Where suitable posts are not available for offer to certain pensionable ex-civil servants, by reasons of considerations of age or ill-health, power is being taken to pay them a special pension, based on a period from a date not earlier than that at which they entered the Service to the date of attaining the age of 65 or the date of the passing of the Act, whichever is the earlier.</P>
    <P>Certain pensionable civil servants have not on reinstatement been able to acquire pensionable posts in the Civil Service on account of ill-health.  They have, however, been admitted to unestablished posts.  Power is being taken to allow their service in such unestablished posts to reckon for pension in their particular cases.  The following distinction is to be noted between the two types of ill-health cases.  Pension is payable as from the date of the passing of the Act to the person whose ill-health precluded his admission to the Civil Service in any capacity.  Naturally in that case the chief medical officer of health of the Civil Service will have to be satisfied in regard to the officer's health.  In cases other than the ill-health cases to which I have referred, where they formerly served in the British Civil Service, particularly in established posts, they had already secured a certificate of health.  Since then, their health may have deteriorated though they are still regarded as being fit to serve.  But while they will have been admitted to the Civil Service, nevertheless they will have been rejected by the Civil Service Commissioners for the certificate of qualification which is a condition precedent to admission to the permanent Civil Service of Saorstát Eireann. Naturally this question of their recertifying on health grounds would not have arisen if they had been simply transferred in 1922 with the general body of civil servants.  It is to remove this disqualification which otherwise they would carry in regard to superannuation <Col N="1138" /> and pensionable service, that we are taking special power in this Bill.  That briefly deals with those civil servants who have had association with the events from 1916 to 1923, and who by reason of that association have had an interrupted service in the Civil Service.</P>
    <P>Apart altogether from those who fall into that category, the Bill deals with a number of technical difficulties which have cropped up in administering the Superannuation Acts since the establishment of the Saorstát.  These are mainly difficulties of interpretation and adaptation.  They arise largely from the circumstances of the transfer of services from the former régime and from delays and uncompleted negotiations incidental thereto.  For instance, a number of persons were voluntarily transferred to the Civil Service of Saorstát Eireann on the understanding that when their pensions came to be computed, these pensions would be awarded on the basis of their aggregate service in the British and Saorstát Civil Services.  The Superannuation and Pensions Acts, 1923, contemplated that we should declare the revenues of the United Kingdom and Northern Ireland to be public funds for the purpose of our Superannuation Acts; and that they would declare our revenues a public fund for the purpose of their Superannuation Acts.  Agreement, however, could not be reached on some of the details inherent in such an arrangement, in particular as to who should bear the charge for the gratuity payable to the legal personal representatives of deceased male permanent civil servants.  Accordingly since a number of these officers have died, or have retired, a difficulty has arisen as to the charging of the moneys payable to or in respect of them.</P>
    <P>Statutorily the Saorstát is liable only in respect of service rendered to it, but public faith is pledged in all these cases, and the officers were definitely promised that their superannuation awards would be based on their total service.  Payment in full has, therefore, been made in each case.  British rules governing apportionment of superannuation liability in respect of aggregate service, however, prescribe that the payment of <Col N="1139" /> death gratuities shall be borne by the last employing body.  With a view to putting the undertaking given to each of these officers permanently on an unchallengeable basis, power is being taken in this Bill to treat all their services as service in the Civil Service of Saorstát Eireann. Recovery will, of course, be effected of portion of the award if and when possible.</P>
    <P>The other sections not dealing with reinstated civil servants are for the most part concerned with technical difficulties&mdash;for example, the superannuation position of the Quit Rent Office staff during three years when payment of salary was not made directly from voted moneys; or, as another instance, the reckoning of service for pension purposes of certain Intermediate Education inspectors, whose names had not been added to the scheme relating to pensionable officers in the service of the Intermediate Education Commissioners; or, again, the reckoning of service with the late Congested Districts Board in certain cases, and the taking of power to charge superannuation liabilities against voted moneys which would, prior to the dissolution of the Congested Districts Board, have been a proper charge on the funds of that Department.</P>
    <P>Again, arising out of the Ministers and Secretaries Act, 1924, and the Civil Service Regulation Acts, 1924 to 1926, certain doubts have been felt as to the valid application of the Superannuation Acts to certain permanent officials in the service of the State; for instance, heads of Departments appointed by the Executive Council on the recommendation of the Minister in charge of each such Department.  The British Superannuation Acts provide that pensions may be granted to persons admitted to the permanent Civil Service with a certificate of qualification from the Civil Service Commissioners or on appointment by the Crown.  It has been thought desirable to extend the provisions of these Acts as adapted to Saorstát requirements, so as to include appointments to the <Col N="1140" /> permanent Civil Service made by the Executive Council.</P>
    <P>Furthermore, in the case of certain statutory boards and bodies, certain jurisdictions, powers, etc., have been reserved to these bodies, and these powers include in some instances the power of appointment which is not exercised by the Minister in charge of the Department to which these bodies are assigned, but by the bodies or boards themselves.  As power of appointment to the Civil Service really vests in the Executive Council and in the Ministers in charge of each of the Departments, subject in the latter case to the application of the Civil Service Regulation Acts, it has been felt desirable, from the standpoint of superannuation, to remove any ambiguities as to the superannuation position of the civil servants appointed by these boards or bodies and in their service.  The provision has been extended to cover employment as an officer or member of the staff of the Oireachtas and as a member of the staff of the Comptroller and Auditor-General, as these two offices are not included in any of the Departments of State.</P>
    <P>As from the 15th day of October, 1932, persons concerned in the Post Office strike of 1922 are having their period of absence from duty restored to them for the purposes of the application of the Superannuation Acts.  It has also been found necessary to make provision for the rectification of certain certificates granted under the Superannuation and Pensions Act, 1923, the validity of which was open to question inasmuch as they contained mistakes as to facts.  For instance, one former pre-Truce Dáil civil servant was described in the relevant certificate as having commenced to serve from a date anterior to the setting up of the Dáil Civil Service, viz., 21st January, 1919.  The time-limit prescribed by that Act has been extended to admit of the grant of fresh certificates to the individuals concerned and of new certificates to certain individuals who were inadvertently excluded from the application of the benefits conferred <Col N="1141" /> by that Act.  Any rectifications will have the effect of securing to each individual the maximum benefits designed for his case by the relevant Act.</P>
    <P>The Bill contains the normal provisions against double reckoning of any period for purposes of pension, and limits the application of the rule of average prescribed by the Superannuation Acts, where the enforcement of that rule would, in the cases of reinstatees, entail hardship.  Special authority is taken to make a grant of £300 to each of the several persons whose names are specified in the Schedule to the Bill who are precluded from securing pensionable posts in the Civil Service by reason of the Civil Service regulations applying to marriage. All of these persons rendered pre-Truce service in the old Dáil Civil Service.  If they had been transferred to the Civil Service of Saorstát Eireann, they would, in the ordinary course, have been entitled to a gratuity on retiring on marriage.  The award which is being made to them now is in substitution therefor.  They would naturally have a claim to reinstatement, but it is thought that this is a better way of dealing with the matter than by making a breach in what is now the invariable practice&mdash;to require women to retire from the Civil Service on marriage.  The expense of carrying the Bill into effect will be met by moneys to be provided by the Oireachtas.  On account of the number of individuals affected and the varying incidence of charge, it is not possible to give even an approximate estimate of the expenditure which will arise.  Finally, ou account of the complexities and number of cases involved, the time limit for certification has been extended to two years to afford ample time for considering each case prior to certification and to ensure that no admissible case will be overlooked.  I do not think that it is necessary for me to say more except that we hope by this Bill to close a regrettable chapter in the history of our country&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>A regrettable chapter?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>In one sense, yes. <Col N="1142" /> We hope to allow all these people who served together prior to 1921 to continue to serve together in our present Civil Service.  No special privileges have been given to any person. We endeavoured to treat them all as they would have been treated if they had joined the Civil Service of Saorstát Eireann in 1922.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate the Minister on introducing this Bill, and I agree with him that it will help to close a chapter which was brimful of unhappy memories for many people.  I hope the enactment of the Bill will help to extinguish some of the still-smouldering embers which have come to us from the unhappy period associated with the civil war, and that it will restore to certain persons, who were prominent in the activities of that period, some of the rights which they lost largely through being guided by the dictates of their own conscience in the events of that period.  I am particularly glad that the Minister has included Section 23 in the Bill, because the object of the section is to restore their superannuation rights to Post Office employees who participated in the strike of 1922.  By his action in including this section in the Bill, the Minister has removed an injustice which operated very inequitably against some persons.  The insertion of this section will help to close a wound which has been suppurating in indignation since 1922.  I am glad that the Minister has seen fit, by including this section, to do something which his predecessor, though appealed to for ten long years, had stubbornly and unreasonably refused to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On some sections of the Bill, I should like information from the Minister.  In Section 21 provision is made for the reckoning of service as a teacher in the case of persons who subsequently passed into the Civil Service as inspectors or organisers in the Department of Education.  I observe that the Minister takes power to prescribe the nature of the teaching service and the amount thereof which may be reckoned for such superannuation and the extent to <Col N="1143" /> which and the manner in which such teaching service shall be so reckoned. Having drawn the section in that careful way, I imagine the Minister has some idea as to the manner in which he proposes to allow those persons in the employment of the Department of Education who were formerly teachers to reckon their service.  I would like if the Minister would give us some general idea as to what he intends to do in that connection.  This is an important matter and it may have to be adverted to on the Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>The Minister made reference in the course of his speech which I took as relating to Section 26.  This section refers to certificates under the Superannuation and Pensions Act of 1923. It would appear from the section as if it were necessary to clear up certain difficulties and errors.  I should like if the Minister would tell us the precise difficulties which necessitated the introduction of a section of this kind. Under Section 28 power is taken by the Minister to add years of service in the case of the superannuation of certain persons.  I should like the Minister to say whether that is intended to be a general provision, applicable in all cases, or whether it is intended to be limited to the special cases in which a certificate is given for the purposes for which certificates are given under the other portions of this Bill.  In Section 30, the Minister treats us to what, I think, is an innovation. This section requires the Post Office Savings Bank to pay annually to the Minister a certain sum in respect of superannuation allowances, gratuities or other benefits which become payable under the Superannuation Acts in respect of persons employed in the Post Office Savings Department.  I should like to ascertain from the Minister whether that provision has been common to the Superannuation Acts in existence prior to the establishment of the Saorstat, whether there is complementary legislation on this matter in Great Britain and what set of circumstances operated to require a provision of this kind in a Superannuation Bill.  It seems a novel provision, <Col N="1144" /> but then the Post Office Savings Department was not a feature of the administration here in pre-Treaty days. This provision may be complementary to similar legislation in Great Britain. I gather from the section that payments have been made from the funds of the Savings Bank Department into the Exchequer in respect of the liability of the Exchequer to pay certain superannuation allowances and gratuities.  I should like to know from the Minister what the justification is for this seemingly unusual method of requiring one branch of the State service to hand over to the central Exchequer a certain sum annually&mdash;a thing which is not, apparently, required in so specific a way in the case of other branches of the State service.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJMurphy" hpid="Mr. T. Murphy Mr. T. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>The section Deputy Norton has referred to, dealing with the recognition of teaching service for certain purposes, prompts the thought that a number of people gave long and faithful service in the teaching profession, which service is unrecognised so far and is not provided for in this Bill.  I refer to the small number of lay convent teachers and junior assistant mistresses whose cases have been long and persistently brought to public notice by reason of the hardship that the position of these teachers entails.  I understand that, when the matter was fully gone into some time ago, it was estimated that the total number of persons so affected would not exceed 60.  The most recent inquiries go to show that the number of such people entirely unprovided for would not exceed 30.  I seem to remember that when the measure dealing with the settlement of the teachers' pensions was going through the House, and when this matter was brought to the notice of the Minister for Finance, he said if there were cases of hardship they would be inquired into and considered. I want to assure the Minister that there is a number of such cases of hardship, even amongst the small number of outstanding cases.  I want to ask him on a subsequent Stage of this measure or at some other early opportunity to endeavour to do justice to such people.  The total number involved <Col N="1145" /> is very small.  Having regard to the fact that the whole aim of this measure is to remove cases of hardship, to remove a feeling of grievance and a feeling of victimisation from the minds of public servants, I think the Minister would be only doing the barest act of justice in including within the terms of this or a similar measure which he might devise at an early date the small number of persons to whom I have referred.</P>
      <P>On the question of hardship, I want to assure the Minister that there is no exaggeration whatever in the statement that there is hardship in some of the cases to which I have called attention.  I have in mind one case of which I know the details very well. That was the case of a person who had close on 50 years' service in a convent school.  She was a trained teacher, amply qualified in every sense of the word, and I might add that she had qualifications that in her time were not generally possessed by teachers as a whole.  I think it is a very serious hardship that such a person after that service should be compelled to exist on the old age pension.  I think this is the most suitable opportunity that has arisen for a considerable time for bringing this matter to the Minister's notice.  He might well give the matter some consideration before the further stages of this Bill are taken up or else at the earliest possible opportunity.  To allow this hardship to continue will be perpetuating an injustice in the case of a small number of people of whom I speak.  These are people who have been left entirely unprovided for.  I urge the Minister to face up to this matter at the earliest possible moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like an assurance from the Minister that this is the last pension Bill we are to have.  To how many more such Bills are we to look forward, or have we as yet reached the final Bill?  I have no objection to Ministers or to members of the Labour Party protesting that these Bills are to staunch a wound.  I always notice that these wounds have <Col N="1146" /> to be staunched with gold.  I was brought up in quite a different tradition. In the old days men went out to work for their country.  Many of them lost a great deal but they felt that that was their contribution to service of the country.  I know many of the veterans of the fight for freedom in this country, which fight, strangely enough, was going on long before 1916, who are hard put to it to survive. They never asked for anything for their services and they never expected anything.  I have known some of those old veterans to be hungry.  I have known them to be in need of clothes and quite destitute until friends came to their aid.  They never asked for a pension and they never seemed to think that they had a claim on the State for compensation for the losses they had sustained in the fight for freedom.  They considered that they were merely doing their duty by the country.  But, unfortunately, that spirit seems to have departed from amongst us.  Anyone who since 1916 kept a dog to bark at the Black and Tans wants compensation for keeping that dog and wants to be paid for the food he gave it.  Have we come to an end of the list of people who have claims on this State for the services they did in the cause of freedom?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I must say I had much more sympathy with the type of person to whom Deputy Murphy has referred, people who laboured at the job of the type they had to do and felt all the time that the terms of their employment were not equitable, that there were others working beside them doing similar work who were receiving preferential treatment.  A case of that kind is more deserving of consideration than the case of a person who comes along and says: &ldquo;I fought for Ireland.&rdquo;  There is little credit in fighting for Ireland if we get paid for it.  My conception of a patriot is a man who fought for and worked for his country without any consideration and no hope of getting reward except the feeling and the inspiration he had that the nation as a whole would be better off by reason of his work.  That was the old conception of patriotism. We cannot expect those old-fashioned <Col N="1147" /> ideas to prevail now and in this atmosphere of largesse one might be tempted to make a suggestion.  But I would do so without authority, because I do not believe that the men I have in mind would permit me to mention them. I would not mention them without asking their leave but I cannot help speaking of the services rendered the country by a number of old veterans in the fight.  These people are now finding it hard to keep body and soul together.  Their names are never heard of and they never dreamt of asking anybody for anything.  I know they would not permit me to ask this House or anybody else to give them a reward for the work they did for their country.  Nevertheless if they are not to have any monetary reward, let them at least have this tribute from a Deputy of this House that they are the one section of the people who fought for this country and lost thereby who have never asked one penny from this State by way of compensation for the sufferings they have undergone.</P>
    <P>I want to mention another very restricted class of person slightly analogous to those mentioned by Deputy Murphy.  I am not sure that their cases have been disposed of. The Minister may remember that when the Department of Agriculture was first set on foot most of the instruction was of an advisory character and most of the modern marketing methods that we have in this country were built up by the work done by a small band of enthusiastic instructresses, who went around this country teaching the people how best to produce eggs and fowl, how to pack eggs and how to carry on the agricultural industry in accordance with modern methods.  On their work was built up the entire sum of modern agricultural instruction and regulations that now exist.  Do Deputies here know that not one of these instructors and instructresses on whom this whole gigantic structure of agricultural education now rests ever received one penny by way of pension?  They were unestablished officers.  Many of them <Col N="1148" /> spent long periods at this work.  To the work of some of them is due the entire machinery that is now operated by certain divisions of the Department of Agriculture.  Some of these left the service at 70 years of age.  At that age they had to look for a job and to start afresh.  I know one case myself where peculiarly onerous family responsibilities had forced the civil servant in question to spend every penny of the earnings while service in the Department of Agriculture continued.  That person, on account of having a delicate family, left the Civil Service without any savings, and with great gallantry set up a little business of her own, managed to keep the wolf from the door, and was doing fairly well until the economic war hit it and smashed it. That does not arise immediately now. They are a very small group of people and they have had a very raw deal.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not spoil it by dragging in the economic war.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I may have been guilty of an error of judgment in that matter, and let us eliminate it again. These people are deserving of consideration. Their numbers are very few.  They make no claim on the ground of lofty patriotism or having suffered for the State.  All they claim is that they worked honestly and well at the jobs they undertook to do, and those who are acquainted with the machinery of the Department of Agriculture know that their work was not in vain.  It was very valuable work from the point of view of the State. I did make the strongest representations in an ordinary Departmental way to secure the establishment of these officers and I think it was found impossible within the framework of the law, as it stood, to establish them.  I take it the general principles of this Bill will permit of an amendment to provide for their case, and, if it would, I think if the Minister inquires he will find that a very deserving case exists.  I believe he would have the unanimous support of the House if he brought forward an <Col N="1149" /> amendment on the Committee Stage giving him power to provide for the cases to which I refer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>With reference, first of all, to the points raised by Deputy Norton in regard to Sections 21, 26 and 30 of the Bill, I should like to say with regard to Section 21 that the regulations have not yet been threshed out between the Department of Education and the Department of Finance, but in the anticipation that suitable regulations may be devised, we are taking power under this section to make these regulations and to give effect to an undertaking which I believe was given some considerable time ago, before my period of office, in regard to those who will come within the terms of the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>The teachers' pensions will not be threshed out as well as the regulations?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>We have to remember that it takes money to do these things, and that, after all, it is the public interest we have to serve and not the private interests of any individual. With regard to Section 26, I could not give the Deputy all the cases, but I have a couple of cases.  Two former established pensionable civil servants under the British Government failed to get Civil Service certificates on being reinstated, due to some flaw in the procedure. The purpose is to re-certify in some cases and to remove doubts as to the validity in others.  If the certificate contains on its face a statement which is not in accordance with the ascertainable facts, the certificate might be declared to be invalid.  There is also the case which I mentioned in my opening statement of a Dáil civil servant who was described on the relevant certificate as having commenced to serve from a date anterior to the setting up of the Dáil Civil Service, whereas, of course, it only came into existence on the 21st January, 1919. There is yet another officer who was described on the certificate granted to him under the 1923 Act as an established <Col N="1150" /> officer, whereas he was, in fact, an unestablished officer.  The whole purpose of the section is, as I have said, to rectify certificates in order to secure to each individual the maximum benefits designed for his case by the Act.</P>
      <P>With regard to the question that the Deputy put under Section 30, as to giving us power to charge the Post Office Savings Bank with its proper superannuation liability, I think I can tell the Deputy that that is done in Great Britain.  We had some legal difficulty in doing it in this country heretofore, but this provision has been inserted in the Bill to give effect to an undertaking given to the Public Accounts Committee that the question would be dealt with by legislation at the first available opportunity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the plea made by Deputy Murphy, I am afraid that these cases could not possibly come within this Bill, for it relates purely to the superannuation of civil servants, and these cases are those of junior assistant mistresses.  The Deputy mentioned that the matter had been discussed when the regulations governing the Teachers' Pensions Fund were before the House. In that connection I think I ought to mention that we did grant in that settlement pensionability to a large class of junior assistant mistresses who were formerly denied it.  It may be that some people were left outside the scope of that arrangement, but it is very difficult for me to reopen it.  The Deputy said that he thought I promised to look into this matter when it was debated in the House, and I think his recollection is correct, because I do remember we did look into it to see whether it would be possible to do something in regard to it, and regretfully I had to turn it down, because if I opened one door, another, which is closed, might have to be opened, too. It is not as if one were dealing with this matter as a private individual. When an arrangement has been made naturally I am very diffident and very dilatory about reopening it.  As I say, I do not think the case could come within the terms of the Bill.  I understand the Deputy is to have a word <Col N="1151" /> with the Minister for Education in the matter, and beyond that I cannot go at the moment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>They will be all dead before anything is done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That is all very well, but, unfortunately, in my Department we come up against many hard cases and you simply have to say that the law and regulations are there.  We cannot deal with public moneys as if we were private individuals, spending from our private purse.  We have to be tighter than we might be in that case if we could afford to do it, for there must be some safeguard for the taxpayers of the country, and the taxpayers are the poor as well as the rich.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a true word.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I have never taken up any other attitude in this House in regard to the question of taxation than that.</P>
      <P>On the point raised by Deputy Dillon, I think the Deputy was under a misapprehension in regard to the terms of the Bill.  This Bill really proposes to put, for pensionable purposes, individuals who were in the Civil Service, and who were driven out of the Civil Service, because for patriotic reasons they took part in a certain campaign on one side or the other, in the same position as individuals who were, I am not going to say, less patriotic, but who were possibly more fortunate.  And that is all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Bill is merely to redress what you might call penalisation.  I will not say it was victimisation, but certainly it was penalisation.  The persons affected by it had to leave the service because of certain things which they did, certain things which the majority of the people, in the last four or five years, have said were done from patriotic motives and in the general interests of the country.  We are only making that good to them.  There is no doubt that if these men who were driven out of the Civil Service in 1916, and subsequently, had remained in it <Col N="1152" /> they would have had the full period of their service reckoned for pensionable purposes.  They would have had everything that we are going to give them under this measure, and I do say that we are not doing anything more than making restitution to them for loss of pensionable service. They are not getting any monetary reward immediately.  It only means that, when they come to retire, the service which they gave to the country in one form will be counted in the same way as if they had rendered that service in the Civil Service in which they were originally engaged.  That is all we are doing.</P>
    <P>There is no question here of men fighting and bleeding for Ireland and being paid for it.  Deputy Dillon, of course, is in a very independent position, but I say as regards the men and women who have been brought back into the Civil Service, and who are being restored to their former rights under this measure, that there are many among them who have suffered starvation, who have been hungry and have been scantily clothed, that there are some who have seen their children suffer in that way, and all because they would not subscribe to a certain formula.  We are simply putting them in the position in which they would have been if they had subscribed to it.</P>
    <P>It is all very well to talk and to say that the country is not in a position to do its duty in regard to those individuals. It is now, and I do not feel that acceptance of the position and of the rights which this Bill will confer on them will carry with it an iota of discredit for any persons concerned. It is very easy for the Deputy and others who are in independent circumstances to talk about men having fought and bled for Ireland in the days gone by without being paid for it.  I know what some people have gone through from 1916 up to now, of men who have seen their whole careers gone and a very uncertain future waiting for them.  I do not think that it is right for the Deputy, whose age absolved him from the responsibilities which other people had to shoulder, to get up here and sneer at the <Col N="1153" /> sufferings and efforts which those men made on behalf of their country and by virtue of which the Deputy is sitting in this House.  The Deputy is Deputy-Leader of the Opposition, and, should fortunes change, may sit eventually where I am now.  He ought to remember, whether he sits on that side of the House or on this side at some time as a member of the Government, that he owes his position very largely to the sacrifices which these men made.  I think it is unworthy of the name which the Deputy bears.  The name of Dillon had a repute for chivalry and for good taste in Irish politics, and I am sorry that the Deputy made the speech which he made here this evening, because I think it does not do us any good.  Irishmen who have gone into political life on the side of their country have never had anything to gain.  They have lost a great deal, and if the country is at any time able to put them in a position in which they will not have penury staring them and their families in the face until they go down to the grave, I think it ought to be the common endeavour of every one of us to bring home to the people that they do owe these obligations to the men who made possible what we enjoy to-day.  That applies also to what the Deputy said in regard to the old veterans in the fight.  I have never decried the services which the men who won the land war, and engaged in the Parliamentary movement, rendered to this country.  If any of them should be in want, I certainly would be sorry to see them in that position, and if it would meet with public approval I would like to do what I could for them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister did not deal with the small section of civil servants to whom I referred.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I will look into the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I just want to ask the Minister one question on Section 23, line 58.  The phrase is used that a certain period of service &ldquo;may, if the <Col N="1154" /> Minister so directs, be reckoned in the said service of such person,&rdquo; etc.  The word &ldquo;may&rdquo; there may be used to govern the general decision of the Minister in respect to superannuations. If it is, well and good.  I would like to ascertain from the Minister whether that is a kind of discretion which he intends to apply in each separate case, or whether, having done it in one case, the precedent thus established will govern others.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy understands that the granting of all pensions is permissive and that no person has an exact title to a pension.  The Deputy may be certain that I am not going to use any powers conferred on me to discriminate against any person.  It is a matter of like case, like rule.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>And one decision will govern the others?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Exactly.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the Committee Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked the Deputy's colleague that I might have the Committee Stage on Wednesday next. He was anxious to have it the week following.  If the Committee Stage is now fixed for Wednesday next, I am prepared to give the House an undertaking that I will not take it on Wednesday unless it is clear that there are not likely to be any amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>On that undertaking I cannot resist the Minister's request. I take it that if we make reasonable representations to the Minister on Wednesday that the Committee Stage ought to be postponed on that day, the Minister will agree?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1155" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Subject to that, we have no objection to the Committee Stage being set down for Wednesday next.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1156" /> Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 15th July.</P>
    <P>The Dáil adjourned at 7.20 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Thursday, 9th July.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>