<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="8" Month="Sep" Year="1943" Vol="28" No="1" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 8 Mean Fómhair 1943" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 8 September 1943" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="5" />
      <Col N="6" />
      <i>Agricultural Panel.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">(a)  Nominating Bodies Sub-Panel.</P>
    <P>PATRICK FRANCES BAXTER,</P>
    <P>JOHN JOSEPH COUNIHAN,</P>
    <P>DOMINICK McCABE,</P>
    <P>WILLIAM QUIRKE,</P>
    <P>THOMAS WALSH.</P>
    <P Just="Center">(b)  Dáil Sub-Panel.</P>
    <P>MICHAEL B. COLBERT,</P>
    <P>SEÁN GIBBONS,</P>
    <P>DANIEL HOGAN,</P>
    <P>PATRICK KEHOE,</P>
    <P>PETER TIMOTHY LYNCH.</P>
    <P>GERARD SWEETMAN.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Labour Panel.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">(a)  Nominating Bodies Sub-Panel.</P>
    <P>MICHAEL COLGAN,</P>
    <P>THOMAS HAYDEN,</P>
    <P>THOMAS KENNEDY,</P>
    <P>SAM KYLE,</P>
    <P>MICHAEL SMYTH.</P>
    <P Just="Center">(b)  Dáil Sub-Panel.</P>
    <P>JOHN BUTLER,</P>
    <P>THOMAS FORAN,</P>
    <P>FREDERICK JOSEPH H. HAWKINS,</P>
    <P>SÉAMUS JOHNSTON,</P>
    <P>RICHARD MULCAHY,</P>
    <P>SEÁN THOMAS RUANE.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Industrial and Commercial Panel.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">(a)  Nominating Bodies Sub-Panel.</P>
    <P>JOSEPH BRENNAN,</P>
    <P>DAVID JOHN MADDEN,</P>
    <P>JOHN MAGUIRE,</P>
    <P>FRANCIS HUGH O'DONNELL.</P>
    <P Just="Center">(b)  Dáil Sub-Panel.</P>
    <P>DANIEL CORKERY,</P>
    <P>JAMES CROSBIE,</P>
    <P>SEÁN GOULDING,</P>
    <P>PETER TRAINOR KELLY,</P>
    <P>FRANK O'BEIRNE.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="7" />
      <Col N="8" />
      <i>Administrative Panel.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">(a)  Nominating Bodies Sub-Panel.</P>
    <P>DENIS D. HEALY,</P>
    <P>MICHAEL HEARNE,</P>
    <P>JAMES THOMAS MCGEE.</P>
    <P Just="Center">(b)  Dáil Sub-Panel.</P>
    <P>JOSEPH HANNIGAN,</P>
    <P>MICHAEL HAYES,</P>
    <P>EDWARD MONAHAN,</P>
    <P>RICHARD WALSH.</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">I gcólíonadh Buan-Ordú Uimhir a trí, de na Buan-Orduithe i dtaobh Gnótha Phuiblí, táim tar éis cóipeanna de na deimhnithe ar thorthaí na vótaíocht do chomhaltaí toghtha do leagadh ar an mBord.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">In compliance with Standing Order No. 3, of the Standing Orders relative to Public Business, I have laid upon the Table copies of the certificates of the results of the polls for elected members.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Election of" RHead="Cathaoirleach">
    <Title>Election of Cathaoirleach.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Seán MacGiobúin Seán MacGiobúin">
      <NameTxt>Seán MacGiobúin</NameTxt>
      <P>Molaim don tSeanad:</P>
      <P>Go dtoghfar an Seanadóir Seán O Guilidhe mar Chathaoirleach agus go racha sé i gceannas an tSeanaid anois.</P>
      <P>Ní gádh dhom a ráadh cad tá déanta aige arson tíre agus teangan, go mór mhór ar son na teangan.  Bhí sé ina Theachta Dála ar feadh roinnt mhaith bhlianta.  Tá sé ina chomhalta de Chomhairle Chonntae Phortláirge le fada.</P>
      <P>Tá sé ina Sheanadóir ó cuireadh an Seanad so ar bun, agus, mar is eól don chuid is mó dhíbh anso, duine anoiriúnach mar Chathaoirleach iseadh an Seanadóir O Guilidhe i ngach slighe.</P>
      <P>After consideration, I have decided, for personal reasons, not to seek re-election to the Chair and I have asked my friends, on vácating the office of Cathaoirleach, to permit me to have the privilege of proposing the name of Senator Seán Goulding as my successor.</P>
      <P>Senator Goulding, who has been a member of the Seanad since 1938, had previously served in the Dáil for a number of years, and has also been a member of the Waterford County Council and of other local bodies.  He has, therefore, had long experience of public administration&mdash;an experience which, I think I can say, fits him in an especial manner for the Chair of this House.  During the past five years he has, on occasion, presided over the deliberations of the House in relief periods to the Chair.  There is no need, I think, to mention to the House his splendid record of service in the Irish-Ireland movement, as that service is already well known to his fellow-Senators. I, therefore, recommend the motion nominating Senator Seán Goulding as Cathaoirleach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Before resuming my seat, I should like to take the opportunity&mdash;the first I have had of addressing the House on other than official matters&mdash;of expressing to those Senators with whom I have had the honour of working for the past five years my gratitude for the co-operation and kindness I have received from all members of the House during my occupancy of the Chair.  That co-operation and kindness which I shall treasure in my remembrance has made my task a pleasant one indeed.  May I also be permitted to express my thanks to the staff for their efficient and loyal service during my period of <Col N="9" /> office.  They did much to lighten the work which must at all times devolve upon the Chair.</P>
    <P>I now formally propose that Senator Seán Goulding be elected and do take the Chair of the Seanad as Cathaoirleach.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HelenaConcannon" hpid="Bean Ui Choncheannainn Bean Ui Choncheannainn">
      <NameTxt>Bean Ui Choncheannainn</NameTxt>
      <P>Cuidím leis an rún agus cuidím leis go fonnmhar agus go croidhiúil.  Aontuím le gach rud atá ráidhte ag an Seanadóir MacGiobúin faoi'n Seanadóir O Guilidhe.  Ní gá dhom mórán a rá faoi'n Seanadóir.  Tá eolas ag an saol le fada ar an obair atá déanta aige.  Tá sean-ráidhte ann adeir go molann an obair an fear; agus an obair atá déanta ag an Seanadóir O Guilidhe, molann sí go hárd é.  Ní raibh aon ghluaiseacht sa tír chun saoirseacht, chun an teanga nó chun an tír do chur ar bhealach a leasa nach raibh baint ag an Seanadóir O Guilidhe léi.  Dá bhrí sin, is mór an onóir dom a ainm do chur os bhur gcóir.</P>
      <P>It is with mixed feelings that I stand up to-day to second the nomination of Senator Seán Goulding as Cathaoirleach. When I came into this Chamber to-day, I thought I would have the honour of proposing for the third time the honoured name of Senator Seán Gibbons for that distinction, and no one could feel more poignantly than I&mdash; I am still under the stress of the emotion caused by it&mdash;the announcement that, for personal reasons, he does not feel able to accept the honour which I feel it would be the unanimous wish of the House to confer on him of election for the third time as Cathaoirleach. During the 5½ years in which he presided over our deliberations, with his courtesy, his tact, his quiet efficiency and his impartiality, he won not only the esteem and respect of every side of the House, but, I venture to say, their affection.  I think that the good tone of the House which made itself felt was taken largely from our Cathaoirleach and I believe the effectiveness of the House&mdash;and we did very effective work, thank God&mdash;was due to that spirit which emanated from the Cathaoirleach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="10" /> If I were to look for a personification or model of that term, &ldquo;a true Irish gentleman,&rdquo; I do not think it would be necessary for me to go outside the House to seek it.  For courtesy, kindliness, noble bearing, noble outlook and unselfishness, I would signal out two people who were in the last House.  One was our Cathaoirleach, Senator Seán Gibbons, and the other, our late-lamented comrade and dear friend, Senator David Robinson. These two were an ornament and a credit to any House, and we all felt the better for their presence.  I, therefore, feel great sorrow that it has not been my privilege for the third time to propose the name of Senator Seán Gibbons as Cathaoirleach, but there is some compensation in that I have the honour to second his nomination of Senator Seán Goulding.  I have known Senator Goulding for a great number of years&mdash;I shall not say how many&mdash;and the only fault I have to find with him is that he is not married.  I hope he will improve on that situation soon and that we shall have the honour of complimenting him on his choice.  That is the only fault I can find with him.  For everything that deserves the name of Irishman, for his service to his country, to the language and to the national advance in every direction, there is no one bears a more honoured name than Senator Seán Goulding, and I have great pleasure in seconding his nomination.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Micheál Ó hAodha Micheál Ó hAodha">
      <NameTxt>Micheál Ó hAodha</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní raibh a fhios agam go dtí gur tháinig mé isteach annso cé hé an duine cuirfí os ár gcóir chun bheith ina Chathaoirleach, ach is dóigh liom go bhfuil rogha maith déanta ins an Seanadóir O Guilidhe. Tá aithne agam air le fada, agus tá a fhios agam gur duine díreach macánta é, gur duine é a thuigeann an gnó agus a dhéanfaidh a dhícheall chun obair an Chathaoirligh a dhéanamh mar is ceart. Ar an abhar san, molaim an Seanadóir O Guilidhe mar Chathaoirleach ar an Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I had no knowledge until a moment ago that Senator Goulding would be nominated for the Chair and I should like to say that I think Senator Goulding <Col N="11" /> is a good nomination.  I have known him in the other House and in this House for a considerable number of years.  I think he has the qualities that go to make a good Chairman.  He is honest, competent and good tempered and, with these three qualities, I think one can go a fair distance in the Chair, particularly with the courtesy which has been extended to the Chair and which has become a tradition in this House.  I agree entirely with Senator Gibbons that the most harmonious relations have obtained between all members of the House, between members of different Parties, if one may breathe a word like &ldquo;Party&rdquo; in this non-Party Assembly, members of no Party and the Chair.  They succeeded in getting along very well together and I certainly agree that some of the credit for that is due to Senator Gibbons himself.</P>
    <P>On my own behalf, and, I think, on behalf of many others in the House, I would like to support the nomination of Senator Goulding for the Chair.  So far as I am concerned, I and those for whom I can speak will give him the same assistance as we gave his predecessor to carry cut the difficult duties that fall to the Cathaoirleach.  Whatever faults this House may have, and many faults have been ascribed to it, we cannot do any work at all unless we can succced in having order, and unless we ourselves combine to help the Cathaoirleach to preserve that order.  I should like to approve the choice of Senator Goulding and to promise him every support.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>Before extolling the virtues of the new Cathaoirleach, I want to pay a tribute to the outgoing Cathaoirleach.  He was very tolerant to our people, which is not usual, and we appreciate that.  He was very courteous and very efficient in the Chair, and he kept up what, in my opinion, was a great tradition.  We had some other people, very competent and very good chairmen in this House, and Senator Gibbons during his occupancy of the Chair maintained that position and I believe that the new Cathaoirleach will uphold that <Col N="12" /> tradition.  I hope that he will be guided by the example of the former Cathaoirleach and be tolerant with our people, who are generally regarded as being somewhat more turbulent than the general run of Senators.  I am sure we will get sympathy and support from him.  I think the Government Party have made a very wise selection in nominating Senator Goulding for the position of Cathaoirleach and that the business will be carried on, as it was formerly, with respect for the Chair.  I believe that Senator Goulding will maintain the high standard set by former Cathaoirligh and, so far as I am concerned, I will give him every support.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonalOSullivan" hpid="Mr. O'Sullivan Mr. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>As a newcomer to this Assembly&mdash;since 1938&mdash;may I say that I have watched its proceedings with a not unfriendly eye and hence I am aware that, during that period, Senator Gibbons presided over its deliberations with commendable ability, tact and impartiality.  Therefore, I regret that, on purely personal grounds, he did not feel able to go forward for re-election.  Speaking as an Independent, I wish his successor similar good fortune and I am very glad to gather from what Senator Hayes and Senator Foran have said that his election is likely to be unanimous and that he will uphold the best traditions of the Chair in this House since it began its existence in 1922.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Senators rose in their places and remained standing while the Cathaoirleach proceeded to the Dais.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Standing beside the Chair, the</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>said:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Is mór an onóir dom, a Sheanadóirí, mé thogha mar Chathaoirleach ar an Seanad.  Gabhaim fíor-bhaochas libh ar a shon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Geallaim díbh go ndéanfad mo dhícheall chun na hoibhre a bhaineann leis an bpost do stiúrú chó maith agus atá im chumas, agus tá súil agam go bhfuighead cabhair o gach taobh den tigh chuige sin, i slí go mbeidh, mar <Col N="13" /> a déarfadh na Seana-Ghaedhilgeoirí, cothrom na Féinne le fáil ag gach éinne.</P>
    <P>Má dheinim an obair chó maith agus do dhein mo chara Seán MacGiobúin romham í beidh mé sásta.</P>
    <P>I deeply appreciate the high honour of having been elected Chairman of the Seanad and I trust&mdash;in fact I feel assured&mdash;that I shall receive every help and co-operation from every member of the Seanad.</P>
    <P>I deeply regret that my friend, Senator Seán Gibbons, was unable to accept nomination for the Chair, and I hope that I shall deal as ably and as impartially as he did with all matters which arise for decision by the Chair.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Promulgation of" RHead="Tillage Orders">
    <Title>Promulgation of Tillage Orders.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The following notice has been received from Senator McGee:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;On the motion for the Adjournment this evening, I propose to raise the matter of the promulgation of Tillage Orders for next year.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I am accepting that notice and the matter will be taken on the conclusion of to-day's business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Date for Election of" RHead="Leas-Chathaoirleach">
    <Title>Date for Election of Leas-Chathaoirleach.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the next day of sitting be fixed as the date for the election of Leas-Chathaoirleach.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Debate&mdash;Promulgation" RHead="of Tillage Orders">
    <Title>Adjournment Debate&mdash;Promulgation of Tillage Orders.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMcGee" hpid="Mr. McGee Mr. McGee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGee</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the adjournment of the Seanad.  When I came into the House this morning and found that six weeks will probably elapse before we meet again, I thought it advisable to hand in the notice which you, Sir, have graciously accepted.  On previous occasions I had mentioned to the Minister for Agriculture that, in my opinion, the Orders regulating the tillage for the coming season should be before the <Col N="14" /> farmers certainly in the month of September. It has been customary heretofore since the emergency arose to announce these Orders in the early spring, and afterwards Ministers visited each committee of agriculture in February, March and April.  Experience has prompted me, and I doubt if it has not prompted the Minister, that that period was too late.  Therefore, I suggest in all seriousness to the Government that all these Orders, essential during the emergency as they are, should be announced almost immediately. If the Administration are not in a position to come to a conclusion now, the opinion of this House should help them to do so.  From the agricultural point of view I think nothing further need be said, except that in this emergency every effort should be made to produce every item of food that it is possible for the land to give us.  In examining the position of our farms and farmers, it is obvious that the plans must be made sometime, and I hold that that time is now.  Already some fields are in a position to be utilised for the coming season, and in the branch of farming that relates to tillage it is in my opinion essential that that course should be adopted. Accordingly, I am grateful to the Chair for permitting me to raise this matter and to the Minister for attending.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to say just a word or two in support of what Senator McGee has stated.  One would like to believe that the Minister was about to tell the country what his plans were and what he expected the country, meaning the farmers, to do with regard to tillage for 1943-44.  No doubt there are a great many farmers who have their plans made in such a way that their scheme of tillage for 1944 will work automatically, but that is not the case throughout the country generally.  I was very impressed this morning by the point of view which I heard Senator McGee advance, and that is that, from his experience in his business as an auctioneer, he finds himself faced with the problem of letting very considerable areas of land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Many people are in this position, that they just do not know what the <Col N="15" /> Minister expects them to do for next year; they do not know what crops the Minister expects them to grow, or what price will be paid for these crops.  On my way to Dublin yesterday I saw stubble cleared and I saw farmyard manure being put out.  There are men who are prepared to plough now for next year's root crop, but there must be thousands of acres of stubble land yet to be cleared.  Perhaps many of the men who own that land do not know what they are going to do with the stubble when it is cleared.</P>
    <P>Our problem with relation to the provision of food for people and for animals is becoming much more difficult; the situation is becoming more grave one year after another.  I am not going to go into this matter at any great length now.  The Minister, I am sure, must have a growing appreciation of the difficulties which confront him as Minister in endeavouring to ensure that there will be sufficient food provided for our people.  I have dealt with certain aspects of this matter in the past and I may have an opportunity of discussing it again under different circumstances here.  The Minister has the responsibility of giving the country a lead, of telling the farmers of the country what he wants them to do.  He also has the responsibility of encouraging the farmers to do their job fully. The important point at the moment is that the farmers ought to know what is in the Minister's mind.</P>
    <P>The Minister, and his colleagues in the Cabinet, feel themselves obliged to go around among our county committees of agriculture and to talk to groups of farmers in the spring of the year.  I should like to point out that spring is not the best time of the year to sow wheat; it is much better to sow it before December, if that is at all possible. We would like to know what the Minister has in mind with regard to getting the fields tilled and the right sort of crops grown for the next harvest.</P>
    <P>Senator McGee mentioned that the Minister ought to indicate to the country what his plans are and if, in the execution of these plans, it is found necessary for the Minister and his <Col N="16" /> colleagues to mobilise the civic sense of the nation to get a proper job done on the land, he ought to do it long before Christmas rather than leave it over until spring.  It may be difficult for the Minister at this moment to say all that we would like him to say, through this House, to the farmers.  We would like to tell him, however, that the farmers ought to be given a chance of looking ahead and planning their tillage schemes in such a way as to ensure that the right sort of tillage will be done in the most efficient way possible. In order to achieve this the Minister ought to give them some directions as early as possible.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>There was one thing mentioned by Senator Baxter which, as one who has a slight interest in industry, concerns me to some extent, and that is the price of crops.  It strikes me that the solution of our farming difficulties and of the problem of food production generally lies in our making it possible for the farmer to live economically.  I know everybody here is anxious that the farmers should be enabled to live economically. Purely as an industrialist, I want the farmer to live because he is my customer.  Unless the farmer is in a position to consume our industrial products, we are going to have a very bad time both in industry and agriculture. When I was outside this House I could not quite understand why we should import wheat at 84/- a barrel and pay our own farmers only 40/- a barrel. Even still I cannot make out why that should be so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I hope there will be a little more imagination used in the direction of financing agricultural production.  It is very important to us in the industrial sphere, at any rate, that those who are, in the main, our best customers should have the wherewithal to buy what we produce.  I think the time has arrived when a little more courage should be displayed, when there might be a little bit less of the <i>laissez faire</i> attitude, and a little bit more of imagination and daring in the direction of the financing of agricultural production. An improvement in agricultural prices might result, with benefit to <Col N="17" /> people like myself, who are engaged in the industrial arena, and to farmers generally.  I trust that the Minister will give serious consideration to the matter of the prices of agricultural produce.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan) James Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad that an opportunity has been afforded me of saying a few words on this question.  I agree with the Senators who have described it as a very important question.  Usually towards the end of September in each year an announcement is made with regard to the tillage requirements for the coming year; that is, the minimum percentage that farmers will be required to till and the prices that will be given for certain crops.  As regards the minimum percentage, that, as it happens, has been announced very much earlier for the coming year than was previously the case.  This time last year, when the Order was announced for the 1943 tillage programme, it was indicated that it was intended to increase the percentage for 1944.  The percentage will be increased for 1944 to 33? per cent. instead of 25 per cent., the idea being that first-crop meadows will be counted in the tillage.</P>
      <P>That has been done, as Senators are aware, for a specific purpose.  We found from experience that farmers who were traditionally opposed to tillage intended, so far as we could see from inspections, to till a certain portion of the land and go on tilling that certain portion until the war is over and, to use their own words, not to spoil the rest of their lands.  We thought it might be a good idea to encourage those farmers to put some of that tillage land down to grass and till new land instead, and, in order to encourage them to do so, it was announced that in the 1944 programme first-crop meadow would be allowed in the tillage.  But first-crop meadow cannot occupy more than one-fourth of the total tillage under the minimum percentage rule&mdash;I think that point ought to be fairly clear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is some delay, naturally, about announcing prices, because we have to wait to form some opinion on the yield of the 1943 harvest.  We will not have <Col N="18" /> that information for another week or two.  That is absolutely necessary, not only from the point of view of fixing a price, but also in order to consider the various propositions that have been put up for the growing of wheat.  Senators know that it is held by some people that we should have a minimum percentage of wheat on each holding; that we should have an attractive price, as mentioned by Senator O'Donnell, or there might be other ways of getting the wheat that we require.  It is most essential that we should get enough wheat, as it is a most important crop, and human food must come before animal feeding stuffs.</P>
    <P>The position is, therefore, that the percentage is known to farmers.  The prices of the guaranteed crops cannot, I am afraid, be considered or announced for another couple of weeks, but it will be made known, I hope, by the end of this month.</P>
    <P>Another point raised by Senators McGee and Baxter was that when other Ministers and I go to various county committees of agriculture in the springtime, it is then getting rather late to sow crops.  That may be, but my experience has been that it is not easy to arouse any great interest in the tillage programme before Christmas.  It is well that the farmer should know how much he should till and that he should know what the prices of the various crops will be, so that he may make up his mind what crop to sow, but I do not think that, if we were to make that final appeal which is usually made in spring&mdash;the appeal to farmers to till a few extra acres&mdash;before Christmas, it would have much effect.  However, I am quite prepared to consider the points raised by the Senators.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Donnell said that he failed to understand why any Government should import wheat at 84/- a barrel while paying its own growers only 40/- a barrel.  It may be difficult to understand that position without knowing the full facts.  We can only hope that the Senator will learn those fine points of economics as a result of taking his seat in this House.  I should like to inform Senator O'Donnell that, <Col N="19" /> since 1933, we have paid the farmer for home-grown wheat what we thought was a fair price.  We paid no attention whatever to the price of imported wheat.  Senator O'Donnell may remember that in 1933, 1934 and 1935, we were paying from 27/- to 30/- a barrel to the Irish grower, although we could import wheat then at 14/- a barrel.  In the past few years, we have been paying the grower 50/- a barrel.  We had to pay more than that for imported wheat. When this war is over, I hope that we shall be able to continue to pay the <Col N="20" /> grower of wheat a fair price, whatever it may cost us to bring wheat from Canada or the Argentine or anywhere else.  That was the consideration with us and it is, probably, a better way of looking at the question, so far as the Irish grower is concerned, than the old Manchester rule of buying the cheapest article in the cheapest market.</P>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Seanad do now adjourn <i>sine die</i>&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 3.45 p.m. <i>sine die.</i></P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>