<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="27" Month="Oct" Year="1943" Vol="28" No="2" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 27 Deireadh Fómhair 1943" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 27 October 1943" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="21">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="21" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Election of" RHead="Leas-Chathaoirleach">
    <Title>Election of Leas-Chathaoirleach.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The first matter on the Order Paper is the election of the Leas-Chathaoirleach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. O'Connell Mr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the Motion standing in my name and that of Senator Barniville: that Senator Michael Tierney be elected Leas-Chathaoirleach. It requires very few words of mine to commend this motion to the House.  Senator Tierney acted as Leas-Chathaoirleach in the previous Seanad for a period of, I think, some five years, and during that time he discharged the duties of his office efficiently, courteously, and fairly, and, I think it can be said, with satisfaction to all concerned.  I have no doubt that if this motion be agreed to, he will fill the office of Leas-Chathaoirleach as satisfactorily in the future as he has in the past.  I have no doubt, also, Sir, that his relations with you, as Cathaoirleach, will be as cordial and happy as they were with your predecessor in the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I need hardly say that we do not all agree with the views which Senator Tierney puts forward so vigorously, when speaking from the floor of the <Col N="22" /> House here, or, perhaps, when speaking in other places, and the fact that I am proposing the Senator for this position does not necessarily mean that I agree with all the views he puts forward.  That, however, does not concern us here.  What does concern us is his fitness for the office of Leas-Chathaoirleach, and I think it will be agreed that Senator Tierney has all the qualifications for that office, and, in addition, he has the experience that he has gained during his occupancy of the Chair, as Leas-Chathaoirleach, during the last five years.  I do not think it is necessary for me to detain the House any longer in connection with this matter, except to say that I wish to express the hope that this proposal will meet with the unanimous approval of the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HenryBarniville" hpid="Dr. Barniville Dr. Barniville">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Barniville</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad, Sir, to know that the motion on the Order Paper, in the names of Senator O'Connell and myself, is such that it almost automatically precludes me from making a speech.  However, in seconding the motion proposed by Senator O'Connell, I simply wish to say that I feel and know that the House agrees that, in his capacity as second-in-command of the control of this House, Senator Tierney has exhibited a very efficient personality.  He has been efficient and loyal to this House while acting under the last very popular Cathaoirleach, and I therefore feel, and I am sure the House will agree with me, that Senator Tierney will show the same loyalty and efficiency under the present very efficient and happily-chosen Cathaoirleach, as he did under the former Cathaoirleach. I beg, formally, to second the motion proposed by Senator O'Connell.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="Pádraig Ó Máille Pádraig Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Ó Máille</NameTxt>
      <P>Ar ócáid den tsórd seo is gnáthach an té atá ainmnithe don onóiremhór seo a mholadh go hárd agus, chó fada agus is féidir, féachfa mé le claoi leis an nós sin. Aontuím leis an té a mhol an rún agus leis an té a chuidigh leis, gur cumasach an duine an Seanadóir Ó Tighearnaigh, <Col N="23" /> agus go bhfuil go leor eolais ar an nGaedhilg aige chun gnó an tSeanaid a stiúradh sa teangain sin nuair is gá sin.</P>
      <P>San am chéadna, ámthach, ba mhaith liom go dtuigfí go soiléir go bhfuilim go tréan in aghaidh na dtuairimí a nocht an Seanadóir Ó Tighearnaigh faoi mhúineadh agus aithbheóchaint na Gaedhilge; agus go bhfuil cáirde na teangan ina aghaidh mar an gcéadna. Ní ceart a thuigbheáil, toisc gur toghadh an Seanadóir Ó Tighearnaigh mar Leas-Chathaoirleach, go bhfuil na Seanadóirí ar aon aigne leis faoi'n Gaedhilge.</P>
      <P>Tá súil agam go bhfuil an méid sin sáthach soiléir anois uaim.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On occasions like the present it is a usual thing, and a well-established practice to shower praises on the recipient of a prospective honour, such as you, Sir, are about to confer to-day on Senator Tierney.  I am one who admires the great ability of Senator Tierney, and I also recognise that he has a good knowledge of the Irish language, but, at the same time, I thoroughly disagree, as the majority of the nationally-minded people in this country disagree, with the public views with regard to the teaching of the Irish language that have been frequently given expression to by Senator Tierney, and I wish to make it clear that we, as members of the Seanad, are in no way responsible for Senator Tierney's public opinions as regards the Irish language.  I wish Senator Tierney well.  He and I are natives of the same county.  He comes from the English-speaking part of Galway, and I come from the western portion of the county.  Although brought up in an English-speaking district, he has acquired a good knowledge of the Irish language, but it does damage to the language movement to see a man who has gone to considerable trouble to acquire a knowledge of Irish expressing unpopular views in regard to it. I feel that I have made my position clear on this question.  I suppose that <Col N="24" /> my views will be held by a great many members of this House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Brathaimse, go háithrid, dualgas a bheith orm, dualgas mí-thaithneamhach go deimhin, maidir leis an tairgsint atá os ár gcomháir.</P>
      <P>Aithním agus admhuím an ceart atá tugtha, de bharr nóis, do dhreamanna aithride, an leas-chathaoirleacht a bheith aca.  Ag an am céanna, ní féidir liom an ócáid seo a leigean thart gan a chur in iúl don tSeanad go bhfuil mé mí-shásta leis an Seanadóir Ó Tighearnaigh mar gheall ar an gcaoi inar chuir sé i gcoinne ceisteanna áithride a bhaineas le teagasg agus le foirleathnú na Gaedhilge sa tír. Aithním gur duine an-fheiliúnach an Seanadóir Ó Tighearnaigh ina lán slite le haghaidh na honóra atámaid ar tí a bhronnadh air agus ba mhaith liom a rá arís leis an Seanad agus leis an Seanadóir Ó Tighearnaigh gur mar gheall ar cheist na Gaedhilge amháin atá mé mí-shásta leis.  Níl fúm cur i gcoinne toghcháin an tSeanadóra agus ba mhaith liom go luaifí mo mhí-shástacht ar thuarascbhála an tSeanaid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisHealy" hpid="Donnchadh Ó hÉaluighthe Donnchadh Ó hÉaluighthe">
      <NameTxt>Donnchadh Ó hÉaluighthe</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom a rá go n-aontuím leis na tuairimí atá ag an Seanadóir Ó Máille agus ag an Seanadóir Ó Buachalla.  Ba mhaith an rud é duine eile bheith molta mar Leas-Chathaoirleach. Cad chuige an gáire?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Risteárd Ó Maolchatha Risteárd Ó Maolchatha">
      <NameTxt>Risteárd Ó Maolchatha</NameTxt>
      <P>Cad chuige ná beadh?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisHealy" hpid="Donnchadh Ó hÉaluighthe Donnchadh Ó hÉaluighthe">
      <NameTxt>Donnchadh Ó hÉaluighthe</NameTxt>
      <P>Bhí mise ag obair ar feadh níos mó ná cúig bliana is dachad ar mhaithe leis an nGaedhilge, agus ní aontuím le cuid de na tuairimí do léigh mé ins na nuachtáin, tuairimí an tSeanadóra Uí Thighearnaigh, agus siné an príomh-fháth go bhfuilim i gcoinnibh an rúin seo.</P>
      <P>Like the previous speakers, I would prefer some other name to be put before the House for the position of Leas-chathaoirleach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="25" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Why did you not put in the other name?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisHealy" hpid="Mr. Healy Mr. Healy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Healy</NameTxt>
      <P>For 45 years, we have been endeavouring to advance the language of our country, and I am not at all pleased with the pronóuncements of Senator Tierney recently in relation to it.  I would prefer to have some other name before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HelenaConcannon" hpid="Mrs. Concannon Mrs. Concannon">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Concannon</NameTxt>
      <P>The question before the House is whether Senator Tierney is suitable for this high post. I am of opinion that he is, and, therefore, I am going to vote for him.  He has shown his ability, his impartiality and his knowledge of procedure, and he has proved it during the last five years.  Therefore, when his name is proposed, extraneous considerations should not be introduced.</P>
      <P>I do not think that Senator Tierney's opinions on outside things&mdash;his opinions about the war, for instance&mdash;should influence us.  They are not of immediate importance.  I do not agree with those who hold that if Senator Tierney criticises the method of teaching Irish that he is necessarily against it.</P>
      <P>Although I do not agree with his opinions&mdash;I think they are founded on insufficient knowledge and experience&mdash;when a man honestly expresses his opinions, there should not be any attempt to penalise him.  I believe that the question before us is whether Senator Tierney is a fit man to help you, A Cathaoirligh, in the very important duty of guiding this House.  His record for the last five years gives an emphatic &ldquo;yes&rdquo;, and that is the question for us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mícheál Ó hAodha Mícheál Ó hAodha">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál Ó hAodha</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní rabhas chun éirghe in aon chor mara mbeadh an méid adubhairt an triúr Seanadóirí a labhair mar gheall ar thuairimí an tSeanadóra Uí Thighearnaigh ar an nGaodhluinn.  Níl aon bhaint dá laghad ag tuairimí an tSeanadóra leis an dtairgsint atá os ár gcómhair anois.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Tá mise ar aon aigne ar fad leis an <Col N="26" /> Seanadóir Bean Uí Choinceannain nár cheart cúrsaí mar seo do tharraing isteach sa díospóireacht iniu.  An chainnt do dhein an bhean uasal atá tar éis suidhe síos, chuir sí áthas orm, ach is mór an náire go ndéanfadh aon triúr Seanadóiri cainnt chó hamadánta leis an gcainnt a dubhairt an triúr eile do labhair.  Ní fheadar an mbeidh ciall go deo ag na daoine seo a bhíonn ag síor-chainnt mar gheall ar an nGaodhluinn.</P>
    <P>Nuair a bhí an Cathaoirleach dá thogha dubhairt mise go raibh mé sásta go mbéadh sé go maith sa Cathaoir. Is duine le Fianna Fáil an Cathaoirleach; cá bhfuil an páiste do cheapfadh go raibh mise ag iompódh le muinntir Fianna Fáil nuair a mhol mé Seán Ó Guilidhe mar Chathaoirleach ar an Seanad?  Agus nach é an scéal céanna anois é?</P>
    <P>Nílim ag cur síos ar thuairimí an tSeanadóra Uí Thighearnaigh.  Táimíd d'iarraidh a fháil amach an mbeidh sé go maith sa Chathaoir, ag tabhairt congnaimh duitse, a Chathaoirligh.  Is dóigh liomsa go raibh, agus go mbeidh arís; agus ní thuigim cad é an saghas díth céille ná cad é an sórt leanbhaíochta atá ag baint leis na daoine a labhair annseo agus ná tuigeann an scéal san.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Lest there might be any misunderstanding arising out of the speeches which the House has just heard, I should like to say that I entirely support the proposition of Senator O'Connell.  After all, Senator Tierney has his point of view as to the methods of teaching Irish and he is quite entitled to hold them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>And they are quite irrelevant, Sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senator Mrs. Concannon has pointed out, what we are doing is electing a Senator to the post of Leas-Chathaoirleach who, we think, is qualified to fill the position for which he is proposed.  Having known Senator Tierney in his personal <Col N="27" /> and in his professorial capacity, I think it is an honour to have a man of his mental attainments to assist you, Sir, in the deliberations of this House.  I very much deprecate that a man's private personal opinions should be made the subject of an attack upon him.  Lest there might be any misunderstanding in the matter I wish to say that I do not at all approve of the methods employed on this occasion.</P>
      <P>Question put and declared carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfMichaelTierney" hpid="Micheál Ó Tighearanigh Micheál Ó Tighearanigh">
      <NameTxt>Micheál Ó Tighearanigh</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom mo bhaochas a ghabháil leis an Seanad.  Tá bród mór orm go measann na Seanadóirí gur ceart an post árd seo do thabhairt dom an dara huair agus nach ceart mé do chaitheamh amach.  Geallaimse go ndéanfa mé mo dhícheall le dualgaisí an phosta seo do chólíonadh chó maith is atá i mo chomhacht.  Ní hí seo an ócáid, is dóigh liom, le díospóireacht do chur ar bun ar na tuairimí atá agamsa ar cheist áirithe.  Ach ba mhaith liom a chur in iúl don Seanadóir Ó Buachalla nach námha don Ghaedhilg mise, nár nocht mé aríamh tuairim ar bith i gcoinne na Gaedhilge, agus go ndéanfa mé mo dhícheall i gcómhnaí le cúis na Gaedhilge, mar a thuigimse í, do chur ar aghaidh.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Appointment of Committee" RHead="of Selection&mdash;Motion">
    <Title>Appointment of Committee of Selection&mdash;Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>D'ainneoin éinní contrárdha dho san atá i mBuan-Ordú a 58 de na Buan-Orduithe i dtaobh Gnótha Phuiblí, gur ocht Seanadóirí bheidh ar an gCoiste Roghnathóireachta ceapfar fén mBuan-Ordú san; agus go gceapfar na Seanadoirí seo leanas chun fónaimh ar an gCoiste sin:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in Standing Order No. 58 of the Standing Orders relative to Public Business, the Committee of Selection appointed under that Standing Order do consist of eight Senators; and that the following <Col N="28" /> Senators be appointed to serve on the said Committee:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Joseph Brennan, Seán P. Campbell, John J. Counihan, Frederick J.H. Hawkins, Denis Healy, Margaret L. Kennedy, Robert J. Rowlette and Gerard Sweetman.</P>
    <P>Motion put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Ordered accordingly.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Procedure and" RHead="Privileges&mdash;Motion">
    <Title>Committee on Procedure and Privileges&mdash;Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Go ndéanfar do réir BhuanOrdú 59, Coiste um Nós Imeachta agus Príbhléidí do cheapadh; agus go n-ainmneoidh an Coiste Roghnathóireachta na Seanadóirí chun fónaimh ar an gCoiste sin.</P>
      <P>That, in accordance with Standing Order No. 59, a Committee on Procedure and Privileges be appointed; and that the Senators to serve on the said Committee be nominated by the Committee of Selection.</P>
      <P>Motion put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Ordered accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Oireachtas Restaurant" RHead="Committee&mdash;Messages from the Dáil">
    <Title>Oireachtas Restaurant Committee&mdash;Messages from the Dáil.</Title>
    <P>The following Message was received from Dáil Eireann:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Tá Dáil Eireann tar éis an Rún so leanas do rith agus is mian leo aontú Sheanad Eireann leis:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Go bhfuil sé oiriúnach Có-Choiste ar a mbeidh seachtar ball ball den Dáil agus seachtar ball den tSeanad do bhunú chun congnamh agus comhairle do thabhairt don Cheann Comhairle i dtreoradh agus i stiúradh Seomra Bhidh an Oireachtais.</P>
    <P>Dáil Eireann has passed the following Resolution in which the concurrence of Seanad Eireann is desired:&mdash;</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="29" /> That it is expedient that a Joint Committee consisting of seven members of the Dáil and seven members of the Seanad be set up to assist and advise the Ceann Comhairle in the direction and control of the Oireachtas Restaurant.&rdquo;</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Restaurant" RHead="Committee&mdash;Motion">
    <Title>Restaurant Committee&mdash;Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Go n-aontóidh an Seanad leis an Dáil ina Rún a cuireadh in úil don tSeanad an 22adh lá de Dheire Fómhair, 1943, go bhfuil sé oiriúnach Có-Choiste ar a mbeidh seachtar ball den Dáil agus seachtar ball den tSeanad do bhunú chun congnamh agus comhairle do thabhairt don Cheann Comhairle i dtreoradh agus i stiúradh Seomra Bhidh an Oireachtais.</P>
      <P>That the Seanad concur with the Dáil in their Resolution communicated to the Seanad the 22nd day of October, 1943, that it is expedient that a Joint Committee consisting of seven members of the Dáil and seven members of the Seanad be set up to assist and advise the Ceann Comhairle in the direction and control of the Oireachtas Restaurant.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Oireachtas Library Joint" RHead="Committee Message from the Dáil">
    <Title>Oireachtas Library Joint Committee Message from the Dáil.</Title>
    <P>The following Message was received from Dáil Eireann&mdash;</P>
    <P>Tá Dáil Eireann tar éis an Rún so leanas do rith agus is mian leo aontú Sheanad Eireann leis:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Go bhfuil sé oiriúnach Có-Choiste ar a mbeidh cúigear ball den Dáil agus cúigear ball den tSeanad do bhunú chun congnamh agus comhairle do thabhairt don Cheann Comhairle agus don Chathaoirleach i dtreoradh agus i stiúradh Leabharlainne an Oireachtais.</P>
    <P>Dáil Eireann has passed the following Resolution in which the concurrence of the Seanad is desired:&mdash;</P>
    <P>That it is expedient that a Joint <Col N="30" /> Committee consisting of five members of the Dáil and five members of the Seanad be set up to assist and advise the Ceann Comhairle and the Cathaoirleach in the direction and control of the Oireachtas Library.&rdquo;</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Oireachtas Library Joint" RHead="Committee&mdash;Motion">
    <Title>Oireachtas Library Joint Committee&mdash;Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Go n-aontóidh an Seanad leis an Dáil ina Rún a cuireadh in úil don tSeanad an 22adh lá de Deire Fómhair, 1943, go bhfuil sé oiriúnach Có-Choiste ar a mbeidh cúigear ball den Dáil agus cúigear ball den tSeanad do bhunú chun congnamh agus comhairle do thabhairt don Cheann Comhairle agus don Chathaoirleach i dtreoradh agus i stiúradh Leabharlainne an Oireachtais.</P>
      <P>That the Seanad concur with the Dáil in their Resolution communicated to the Seanad the 22nd day of October, 1943, that it is expedient that a Joint Committee consisting of five members of the Dáil and five members of the Seanad be set up to assist and advise the Ceann Comhairle and the Cathaoirleach in the direction and control of the Oireachtas Library.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Seanad Election&mdash;Motion" RHead="for Judicial Investigation">
    <Title>Seanad Election&mdash;Motion for Judicial Investigation.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>This House requests the Government to take such steps as may be necessary to institute a judicial investigation into the operations of the Seanad Electoral (Panel Members) Act, with particular reference to allegations concerning unlawful and corrupt practices arising out of the recent Seanad Election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I need not dwell very long on the importance of this motion.  The fact that the Taoiseach is here indicates his interest in the matter, and certainly I think every member of this House attaches considerable importance to this motion.  I may say, in passing, that <Col N="31" /> the motion has not been put down with any idea of gaining any political advantage whatever and it is not the intention of the Party to which I belong to exploit it in that direction, nor shall we indulge in personalities, though it is very hard to keep away from them in dealing with a motion of this kind.  We regard this motion as one of fundamental importance, fundamental in the interest of democratic government.  We know that democracy is severely challenged throughout the world and that attempts have been made to discredit democratic Parliaments in other countries.  Undoubtedly anyone living here and moving around this country about the time of the Seanad election, unless he were living in a cloister&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>And he would not be safe even there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;must have heard the allegations of bribery and corruption that were rampant.  Unfortunately or fortunately that is some little time ago and it may be that it has been forgotten by a fair number of the people. Still, the impression remains that this House is in bad repute with the general bulk of the community and, because of that we believe that an opportunity should be given to every person who has any allegation or charge of corruption or bribery to make in the recent election to come forward.  It is for that reason that we put down the motion.  We hope that the Government will give it every assistance and, if the charges are proved, the people concerned should be dealt with and dealt with very drastically.  If, on the other hand, these charges are ill-founded they should be withdrawn and the public mind cleared as regards this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As is known, a comparatively small electorate elects this House.  I think the great bulk of the electors are from the county councils.  Let us see how the county councils are regarded by the Government.  In almost every county and borough council, a manager has been appointed.  One asks oneself <Col N="32" /> why?  It must be for one of two reasons&mdash;incompetence or corruption, either one or the other.  Therefore the Government themselves must be satisfied that these county councils are not competent to conduct the ordinary functions.  Yet these very same bodies can come together and elect people to the Seanad.  In that atmosphere is it any wonder that suspicion and doubt exist and that allegations of corruption and bribery are made?  Everyone will agree that a county council that is not considered competent to run the ordinary affairs of a county should not have the right to elect members to this House.  The figures are fairly astonishing.  The county council voters comprise in or about 253 votes. Remember that these people are considered incompetent or corrupt according to the action of the Government. The Dáil has only a voting power numbering 138.  It is small wonder that suspicion and doubt exist in the minds of the people.  I could quote numerous instances where allegations of bribery were made.  I will not mention names but this much I will say: one lady in this House bears a name that will be honoured by generations of Irishmen to come and she only secured two votes in the Seanad election.  Yet people who are unknown outside their own borough could head the poll.  How is it done?  I will leave it at that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a very remarkable statement for the Senator to make in a House of Parliament.  I think it is clear that the Senator is now making specific allegations but he is not giving evidence to support them. They do not concern me.  I did not head the poll.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad I succeeded in exciting Senator Hayes.  It may give me an opportunity of coming to what I wanted to say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I might intervene at this point.  In my opinion it would be advisable that references should not be made to any person or to persons by name or otherwise.  This motion proposes the setting up of a <Col N="33" /> judicial inquiry into happenings which, it is alleged, occurred during the recent Seanad election for panel members.  It seems to me, therefore, that the House should not pre-judge the matter, and if the House decides that these alleged happenings are to be the subject of investigation by an external body, obviously the investigation should not be prejudiced by references here.  I, therefore, cannot allow any reference to particular cases, and I ask Senators who wish to take part in the debate to bear that in mind.  As there have been references also to the present system of electing panel members of the House, I think it well to let the House know that while incidental reference to the system may be permissible, the present motion cannot be made use of to turn the debate into one on the system itself.  If the House wishes to discuss that matter it will have to do so on a separate motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that that is a wise ruling, and as far as I can I will obey.  If I slip it will not be intentionally, but I must refer to the recent Fianna Fáil Árd-Fheis, where the rank and file generally were very loud in disparaging both the methods of election and the procedure in connection with the election.  The Taoiseach's attitude on that occasion was that every honest-minded citizen should come forward and inform the Government. Assuming that that attitude were adopted towards the black-marketeers, what would happen&mdash;if it were just left to individuals and to the person who received the bribe? Bribery is comparable with hoarding and using the black-market or overcharging for necessary commodities. The Government do not wait on people to come forward and make charges. They send people out to investigate, and rightly so.  That is our answer to the attitude of the Taoiseach at the recent Fianna Fáil Árd-Fheis.  We want a judicial inquiry, so that evidence can be taken on oath, and we want the co-operation of the Government, through the Ministry of Justice, to bring the people concerned before this tribunal and have the matter <Col N="34" /> thoroughly investigated.  Surely, this is a matter of fundamental importance to the House.  We all know the charges that have been bruited about. I have heard it argued that, instead of private sales, a public auction should have been called for the Seanad votes and the proceeds given to reduce the National Debt.  That is, perhaps, an exaggeration.  Yet, these allegations have been made and, until they are thoroughly probed, and proved or disproved, this House will be under a cloud of suspicion and will not occupy the position it ought to occupy in the public estimation.  Therefore, it is our duty to provide facilities to have these matters thoroughly investigated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelColgan" hpid="Micheál Ó Colgáin Micheál Ó Colgáin">
      <NameTxt>Micheál Ó Colgáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom cuidiú leis an tairgsint seo.  Mar is eol do gach aon duine san Tigh seo, tá ráflaí ag dul thart maidir leis an gceist seo ar fud na tíre.  Bhí na ráflaí céadna ag dul thart mar gheall ar an togha a bhí ann roimhe sin agus is dóigh liom gur mithid don Riaghaltas fiosrúchán do chur ar bun chun na ráflaí seo do cruthú no stop do chur leo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The motion before the House is of considerable importance to every member. It is well known that suggestions regarding corrupt practices in connection with the Seanad election are widespread.  Similar allegations were made in connection with the previous election.  The first Seanad was elected in March, 1938, and lasted for a period of five months.  The second Seanad was elected in August, 1938.  People throughout the country have been asking why people who, at the previous election, secured no votes, or very few votes, topped the poll at the second election in some cases and, in other cases, secured a sufficiency of first preference votes to be returned on the first count.  The explanation that, in the intervening five months, these people had become so popular that they obtained extra votes is not acceptable to the country.  The suspicion of the general public was not allayed by the conduct of the election we are now considering. Members of county councils have publicly alleged that they were approached by candidates and offered <Col N="35" /> bribes for their votes.  Candidates have alleged that, when they approached electors, they were promised support on condition that some consideration would be given for their votes.  None of us asserts that the allegations are true.  But because these things have been alleged both in public and in private, we are asking the House to agree that the Government should take whatever steps it thinks necessary to have the fullest inquiry made to ascertain if there is any foundation, in fact, for these assertions.  The honour of public men is gravely affected and the fabric of democracy, on which our institutions rest, is threatened by the allegations which have been made. Nobody will have any respect for the Seanad if the people are suspicious that the strength of a man's or woman's purse is a sure passport to election to this House.  If it is believed that public men are prepared to sell their votes to the highest bidder in the market-place, the days of this and other democratic institutions are numbered.</P>
    <P>The motion is not a Party motion. Senator Foran made that perfectly clear.  The allegations to which I have referred have been made against members of every Party.  We feel that the motion should be considered in a non-Party spirit.  There is no question of making Party capital out of the motion.  As a matter of fact, it was with some reluctance that the motion was tabled, but we felt that every Party should be anxious to inquire as to whether these abuses occurred.  If they did occur, every effort should be made to prevent their recurrence.  The Cathaoirleach has ruled that reference cannot be made to individuals.  I am not sure whether that ruling covers specific cases.  We have evidence that a certain gentleman, who will be nameless, stated in County Kilkenny that he was offered £50 for his vote. We have also evidence that, at a meeting of Longford County Council, certain allegations were made.  People, who shall be nameless, stated that votes were bought in the town of Longford. Allegations are also made that <Col N="36" /> votes were bought and sold in the County Tipperary, and that this can be proved.  Responsible people are quite agreeable to come forward before any judicial tribunal which may be set up to give evidence that these things have occurred.</P>
    <P>Senator Foran made reference to the attitude of the Taoiseach at the Árd-Fheis.  I think that, by a slip, he referred to the Cathaoirleach when he intended to refer to the Taoiseach.  The position which the Taoiseach took up was a peculiar one, to say the least of it.  All over the country these allegations have been made.  Since they were made, as we know they were, it was the duty of the Government to get after the people who made the allegations and compel them to prove them.  The Taoiseach stated at the Árd-Fheis that the Department of Justice had communicated with one of two persons concerned.  My information is that the person communicated with was not a voter at all.  I understand that he wrote to the papers to the effect that he had been communicated with and that, as he had not a vote, he was not concerned in the matter and could not give any evidence.  There will be plenty of material for inquiry by a tribunal such as we suggest and I think that, in fairness to the House&mdash; every member of it&mdash;the Government should agree to the motion we have submitted.</P>
    <P>We have been told that we are not going to touch on the system of electing a Seanad.  The panel system is enshrined in the Constitution and it would be a difficult thing to touch it; but I do not think that we are tied to the present method of electing on the panel system.  We are satisfied that there are organisations on the Nominating Bodies' Panel whose credentials to be on these panels are open to question.  We also know that people are proposed on the Dáil Panel who have no connection with it.  I have seen candidates selected for the Labour Panel-men who during their lives have never done a day's labour in the accepted sense of the word&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Col N="37" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator will permit me, I am afraid he is now dealing with the system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelColgan" hpid="Mr. Colgan Mr. Colgan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colgan</NameTxt>
      <P>You will have to be patient with me.  I am a stranger to procedure and I hope I am not departing from rule and regulation.  At any rate, we are satisfied that if the system cannot be changed, some alteration should be made in the procedure adopted for selecting candidates for the Seanad.  We feel&mdash;and I would be surprised indeed if it were&mdash;that this motion will not be resisted.  It is in the interests of every one of us that these allegations should be probed. We agree that they have been made all over the country, and that if we are going to ignore them, we would be doing a very bad day's work for the House.  I hope the Government will agree to set up the inquiry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps I will be allowed, before I enter into this matter of the motion, to congratulate Senator Colgan, whom I have known for a great many years, upon his maiden speech in the House, delivered with great clarity and force, and upon his success in coming out not too badly in a brush with the Chair.  When I saw this motion for the first time, I was not quite clear what it meant, and I must confess that I am still in the dark as to what it aims at accomplishing.  In the first place, I recognise, in accordance with your ruling, Sir, that we must not discuss the system.  But I hope you will allow me to say that I did not devise it, and that I have no admiration for it.  I think it is a thoroughly bad system myself, and consequently I am not concerned with defending it.  I did not top any poll&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>You were at the bottom.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes; I was rather at the bottom, so my withers are entirely unwrung no matter how we look at the problems here.  Considering the future, one might devise a better system of election, and considering the past, if there have been any flaws, it would be right that we should devise a system to bring the culprits to book <Col N="38" />&mdash;if there are any.  I think that when Senator Foran put down this motion he did not really advert to the exact meaning of the words &ldquo;judicial investigation.&rdquo; Apparently Senator Foran suggests that the Government should take steps to set up a special tribunal which would in some way carry out an investigation.  That is entirely contrary to the meaning of &ldquo;judicial investigation&rdquo;, which conveys the idea of the functions of a judge sitting and hearing evidence, or such matters as he deems to be legal evidence, and who, having heard the evidence, declares his view of the law or of the facts or of both.  If Senator Foran thinks that you could appoint a particular judge to carry out an inquiry and to go out and look for information, that is surely contrary to our system of law, and could not be done.  If he does not mean that, then I wonder what does he mean.  The judge is to decide upon the facts presented to him, not to collect the facts or the evidence.  It seems to me that if there is any evidence available, or anything that would be regarded as evidence&mdash;and a newspaper report could not be regarded as such&mdash;it should be offered to the proper quarter, the Attorney-General or the Minister for Justice, and taken before the ordinary courts.  If there is no evidence available, then a judicial inquiry will not in any way help us. That is to say, if the Government here set up some particular court, the only way they could do it would be under the Tribunals of Evidence Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We speak here as members of the Houses of Parliament under privilege, and we should be very careful indeed not to use our privilege so as to reflect upon individuals, either by naming them or otherwise indicating them. Senator Foran will agree with me, because he is an experienced Parliamentarian, that whatever our private opinions may be we should certainly not pillory individuals where they have no opportunity of defending themselves, and even if they had, this House is not a tribunal sitting to weigh evidence and give a judicial decision.  It seems to me to be no use to set up a special court to hear evidence if there be any.  Surely one <Col N="39" /> must regard the ordinary courts as impartial.  I do, and I am not a supporter of this Government&mdash;very far from it.  There were people here to-day explaining what their opinions were about the Irish language, but I suggest there is no need for me to explain that I am not a supporter of the Government.</P>
    <P>I take it that this Government, and any other Government, would be anxious to discover whether there has been corruption in this matter&mdash; whether candidates have offered, or electors have accepted, bribes.  I take it that whatever investigation can be made has been made, and if there are people who can give information which has not been put at the disposal of the authorities, then they should come forward and have the matter investigated before the appropriate ordinary court which, I take it, would be generally regarded as being as impartial as any special tribunal set up by the Government for the particular purpose.  I think Senator Foran's statement that the House is under a cloud was not quite correct.  The House would be, of course, under a cloud if it made a fool of itself in transacting its business. We will be judged, not by rumour, but by what we do ourselves, and this kind of motion, put, as it has been, without any great clarity, is in the end going to do us more harm than any idle rumour.  There is a complete misunderstanding of the word &ldquo;investigation&rdquo;. That seems to me to be the whole kernel of the matter.  What the Senator is asking for is a judge to weigh evidence; but he has not suggested that there is any evidence for a judge to weigh, or that anybody has come forward to make allegations capable of investigation.  I know there are rumours; but these are quite different things from evidence&mdash;even in this country.</P>
    <P>The system is one which naturally leads to all kinds of allegations.  The elector is regional, representing a particular local area, whether a member of the Dáil or of the county council, and he has to deal with the candidates <Col N="40" /> nominated on a vocational or pseudo-vocational basis.  About many of them he knows nothing whatever, and I think that the system was intended to produce a particular political result while maintaining an outside veneer of vocationalism.  Naturally the small number of voters led to charges of corruption and difficulties concerning panel returns.  But these difficulties are quite different from any suggestion of evidence leading to proof that money has passed or that any form of bribe has been offered or accepted.  If these things are to be dealt with at all, it should be by the ordinary courts and not by a special tribunal in which I can see no virtue whatever.</P>
    <P>If Senator Foran means the setting up of a special investigation system, then he is really suggesting some particular police body.  If he is suggesting a special judge to try this particular matter, then I think that we have sufficient judges in this country already to deal with such matters, and I am sure that we could find a court suitable to try such a thing according to the ordinary procedure.  It seems to me that the terms of his motion do not allow us to discuss certain things that have happened in the past&mdash;about which I have very strong opinions&mdash;and it does not make any provision for the future. Since, as it seems to me, the motion makes no provision for the future, and also makes no provision for the past, it would appear to me that this motion, put forward, undoubtedly, by Senator Foran in a non-Party spirit, is of no value, unless, in the course of this debate, some clarity can be thrown upon it.  Unless some further clarity can be shown with regard to the motion before the House, I do not see how anybody in the House could support the motion at all.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill-Moore Mr. Kingsmill-Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill-Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I rise, Sir, to oppose this motion, with some diffidence and very considerable hesitation: with diffidence, because this is the first occasion on which I have had the privilege of addressing this House, and, with hesitation, because if the <Col N="41" /> motion had been framed somewhat differently&mdash;if, for instance, it had called for investigation by a joint committee of both Houses, to make suggestions how the method of electing panel members to the Seanad could be improved, then I would find myself speaking on the other side.  But we have to deal with the terms in which this motion is framed and also with the words used by the proposers of the motion.  The motion calls for a judicial investigation into the operations of the Seanad Electoral (Panel Members) Act.  But that differs in at least three important ways from a suggestion of setting up a joint committee of both Houses of the Oireachtas to deal with the system. First of all, the motion calls for a judicial inquiry, as opposed to an inquiry by a joint committee of both Houses.  Then, it refers to things that are supposed to have happened in the past, and it does not look to what may happen in the future.  Lastly, by reason of the reference to allegations of bribery and corrupt practices, such an inquiry would result inevitably in an investigation into the conduct of individuals, as opposed to an inquiry into anything that could improve the system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A judicial investigation is asked for here in this motion.  Now, I confess that when I came in here, I was rather at a loss to understand the meaning of that phrase.  So far, the only enlightenment I have got was from what Senator Foran said, to the effect that there was to be an opportunity for anybody to come in and give evidence; and from his later statement, that the reason for having a judicial inquiry was that evidence could be taken on oath.  Of course, it is not necessary to have a judicial inquiry in order to have evidence taken on oath.  I presume that a judicial inquiry means an inquiry that would be presided over by a judicial person, or an inquiry in which the usual methods of judicial investigations would be followed; and I do not think there is very much difference as to which of these meanings you attach to the phrase, because I think that any judge would adopt the methods which all systems <Col N="42" /> of law regard as necessary before you can have any fair investigation whatever.</P>
    <P>As I understand it, before you could have a fair investigation, it would be necessary to be satisfied of three things.  First, if there are any charges to be made against any individuals, those charges would have to be clearly and precisely formulated before the investigation started, and you would have to have all the evidence confined to those and precisely formulated charges.  Secondly, you would have to give to anybody implicated in those charges an opportunity of being present when the evidence was being given, on which the charges were being made; and, thirdly, the person or persons implicated would have to be given an opportunity of preparing and presenting a defence against the charges.  But if you look at the terms of this motion, you will see that it is suggesting a kind of a rambling inquiry; and, again, in the words of Senator Foran, an opportunity is to be given to any person who can come along before that body and make any allegation he wishes to make &mdash;the result of which would be that you might have a witness, or a number of witnesses, who could come along and make any allegation they liked to make against any one of the 43 panel Senators in this House or against any one of the odd 350 electors to the House.  An inquiry of that nature would not, and could not, be a judicial inquiry.  Any inquiry could not be a judicial inquiry if a number of people, who had had no opportunity of hearing the charges against them, were to be condemned on the evidence of witnesses whom they did not know.  Let us say, for instance, that one of the members of this House were to be implicated in such a charge, as a result of evidence given by such witnesses, even if he were able to clear himself of the charge on a subsequent occasion: still, the mischief would be done.  The first reason for which I ask the House to oppose this motion is that any inquiry, such as is proposed in this motion, would be grossly unfair, not alone to every Panel Senator in this House, but to every member of the electorate.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="43" /> Let us take it a step further, however. How could such a committee or judicial body report?  It could only make one of two reports.  It could say either that it had found evidence against A or B amongst the Senators, or the electorate&mdash;that certain things had happened; or it could say that there was no evidence of any corruption. There is one thing that such a body could not report under any circumstances, and that is to report that there had been no corruption.  Not only would it be unfair to the individuals concerned, but it would also be unfair to all the other Senators and electors.  In my opinion, any finding of that kind would be tantamount to showing that there was an infinitely greater amount of corruption or malpractice than could be ascertained by any such inquiry.  If certain individuals were found guilty of such mal-practices, the whole body could be accused of such mal-practices.  I think it will be admitted that in the case of corruption, bribery, or mal-practices of that kind, it is a characteristic that those who are the most guilty are the least likely to be found out, whereas the tyro or the apprentice in such crimes will be found out and held up to the obloquy of the nation.  Supposing, however, that the report was that there had been no evidence against any persons, and that, therefore, no case was made out; will that convince any single person in Ireland, except a lawyer who is accustomed to take into account only that which is actual evidence?</P>
    <P>But the ordinary man in the street whom I hear so much about, and who is referred to as Seán Citizen, is not so particular.  He is a little cynical. He has a shrewd knowledge of human nature and he knows that corruption is a weed which is a comparatively common object of the political countryside. It is as old as time and as wide as geography: and unless you are continually on the lookout to pull it up or to produce conditions in which it cannot grow, you are likely to get it rampant. If men can obtain advantages for themselves by doing a thing which costs them nothing in a matter in <Col N="44" /> which neither their personal interests are very closely concerned, nor have they any strong political or other feelings, the ordinary man in the street is going to assume that a certain proportion will yield to temptation; and a mere whitewashing report that there was no evidence of corruption would not affect the opinion of a single person in Ireland.</P>
    <P>The truth of it is that there are only three ways that I know of to avoid corruption.  You can, first of all, have straightforward nomination.  That avoids corruption because the person who nominates has to take responsibility. You may think that the persons nominated are good or bad, but you cannot get away from the fact that the nominator has to take the responsibility and I do not think that anyone has suggested that in respect of the nominated members of the House there could have been any corruption. The second method is to ensure that before a person can get elected he must obtain a large number of votes, counted if not by thousands, at least by hundreds; because to corrupt successfully hundreds of people would require not only a long purse but considerable time to do it, and it would involve the risk that in the getting of hundreds or thousands of votes the candidate would be likely to make mistakes and run into danger.  I have not heard that in respect of those members of the House elected by a considerable number of votes, there has been any accusation of corruption.  I may be wrong.</P>
    <P>Lastly, the third and only other safeguard against corruption is to get a system of election by a body of people whose reputation stands so high that the slightest suggestion of corruption would do them more harm than they could possibly get advantage by the successful exercise of corruption.  That is the method which the majority of the joint committee recommended for the selection of panel members, and which was turned down.  Now the ordinary member of the public sees that there are none of these safeguards.  A maximum of ten and a minimum of two or three votes is sufficient to get a <Col N="45" /> person in, and Seán Citizen is not willing to accept a finding that out of the whole electorate there are not two or three people who are willing to vote for other than purely political reasons.</P>
    <P>I would say that this suggested investigation stands condemned not only as one which would be unfair, but as one which would be useless. We could take the objection one stage further.  It would be unfair, useless, and I think it would be unnecessary.  Everybody in this House knows perfectly well what is being said in tram and 'bus and train, and snug and street corner and parlour.  It does not matter whether what is being said is true or not.  The important thing is that it is believed.  If people have lost confidence in a certain method, it does not matter on what grounds.</P>
    <P>There is no doubt that if there ever was confidence, it has been forfeited and therefore I say that it is unnecessary as well as being unfair and useless to have this inquiry.  If there is to be an inquiry I hope that the Senators who proposed the motion may on some other occasion produce a motion which looks forward and not back, which aims at improving the system and which does not aim at pillorying individuals.  It is admittedly true, as has been often pointed out, that it is impossible to achieve an ideal system; but that does not mean that we cannot make the system better if only for the reason that it would defeat human ingenuity to devise anything worse.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>We have had an assurance from the Taoiseach in the Press that if there was any evidence of corruption brought to the Attorney-General proceedings would be initiated at once before the appropriate court.  That assurance would assist very greatly in improving the dignity of this House, if it went further, if it went to the length that any person who made such a public statement as that reported from Longford, that he had been approached and offered a bribe, and who when approached by <Col N="46" /> the Attorney-General went back on his statement, was prosecuted for a public mischief, and for bringing this House into contempt.  In other words, if a man makes a statement, he has to stand over his charge of bribery against the man he attacks, or suffer for making irresponsible, untrue and mischievous suggestions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>When I saw the motion I was inclined to support it but, after listening to the encircling movements of the lawyers, I have come to the conclusion that much as I agree with the spirit of it I must oppose it. It seems to me that it does not secure the objective the proposer desired. There is not a single member of this House who does not agree that an investigation of some sort into the allegations which have been made should be approved, but, until some <i>modus operandi</i> can be discovered, it does not seem to be possible to carry out the terms of the motion.</P>
      <P>It seems to me to be like playing Hamlet without the ghost to try to discuss the defects arising from a system without discussing the system itself. We are discussing the effects without examining the causes, and while I accept the ruling of the Chair, I never liked Hamlet without the ghost anyhow.  One of the reasons why I should like to see some inquiry is that I am a raw, untutored member of the House, and up to this point when anyone approached me and said: &ldquo;Congratulations, Frank Hugh.&rdquo;  I felt that at the back of his mind he was asking: &ldquo;I wonder how much does it cost.&rdquo;  Being of that super-sensitive nature, I entirely support any investigations that would eradicate such horrors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would be sorry for the Seanad to be proven guilty of the methods ascribed to it, because there was a gentleman called Ollamh Fodhla in 1277 B.C., and I think that the mentality of the Irish people should be preserved as clean as it was in the time of our progenitors.  But the slur that is existing in the public mind, created to a very goodly extent by <Col N="47" /> rumours and by publication in the Press of rumours, is a thing we should, if possible, eradicate.  We should find out exactly the sources from which these rumours emanate, why certain newspapers have commented on them, and why an attempt should be made to lower the dignity of this House, which is portion of the Oireachtas.  All these things should be open to investigation, to my mind, because it seems there is a certain attempt by people outside this House to cast a slur on the whole Legislative Assembly of this country.  As an ordinary member of the Seanad I resent that.  I resent the insinuation that has been made by certain people that I, or some of my fellow Senators, bought or sold votes. I resent the insinuation that the ordinary members of the county councils are people who would sell votes.  That whole question is something which should be inquired into as exhaustively as possible and the greatest penalties should be imposed on the originators of such rumours.  Senator Foran referred to the fitness as electors of county councillors.  My retort is: in what way are they less fit than members of the Dáil?  Surely they are as good a cross-section of the national life as any other representatives?  I think there should not be any thought behind his mind&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, although the Senator is a new member, he should be fair.  I said that that was the mentality of the Government towards county councillors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course, if Senator Foran sits down to analyse the psychological factors of the Government attitude towards members of county councils, that is something that even a new member could not dare to attempt, but I would imagine that that is what he had in his mind, and I leave that to be dealt with by other people.  Although we have gone so far in discussing this motion, we cannot, I understand, refer to the system itself, and on that point I would only re-echo Yeats: &ldquo;The wrong of <Col N="48" /> unshapely things is a wrong too great to be told.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>When I saw this motion on the Order Paper, I had a feeling that the Labour Party were going to produce something definite beyond mere allegations and rumours, but the mover of the motion, I must say, made a very poor and feeble attempt to secure any support whatever for it in the House.  The seconder did not go very much further.  On asking myself the question, what prompted the Labour Party to put this motion on the Order Paper, I could come to only one conclusion, that it might help them very considerably if they could get an investigation to find out where the votes they expected for the candidates they put up went to.  If some of the county councillors elected on the Labour ticket at the local elections felt that the candidates put forward by the Labour Party for the Seanad were not people they could vote for, and voted for other candidates in preference to those people, I think it is grossly unjust to accuse such county councillors of corruption, because I am sure the Labour Party will agree with me that their foremost thought is the advancement of their Party and their policy.  Therefore, it is only natural that they would be anxious to secure the greatest representation they could in this House.  They expected to control about 50 votes, but they secured something in the neighbourhood of 17 or 18 votes, and they think it quite right now to set up some machinery to find out where these votes went.  It is certainly very poor coming from the Labour Party to accuse those representatives on the county council of corruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelColgan" hpid="Mr. Colgan Mr. Colgan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colgan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Labour Party accused no one of corruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor Magennis Professor Magennis">
      <NameTxt>Professor Magennis</NameTxt>
      <P>They accused the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>They most certainly did.  They lost these votes and in putting <Col N="49" /> down this motion they are accusing certain people.  They cannot segregate these voters from other people.  They cannot say that the Labour representatives that had votes were the only honest people because if they were honest in the view of the Labour Party they would have voted for the Labour Party.  Now Labour Senators attack members of their own Party because, in their view, they were not honest.  I think that is a very poor line to take.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I felt rather sorry for Senator Foran having seen the way his motion was received by the House.  It is quite obvious that he thought it was the most important motion that came before the House for years.  I am sure he was so much taken up with the motion, he missed seeing the wave of satisfaction that passed over the House when the Senator announced that this was not a Party motion. When I read the motion, the first thing that struck me in my innocence was that it was a Party motion and that as Senator Hawkins has suggested, Senator Foran and his Party were really anxious to find out where their votes went.  However, I feel like most other speakers, that no case whatever has been made for the motion.  I can see no reason at all why anybody who is really serious about locating any faults there may be in the present system or tracing any corruption that may have existed, cannot do so under the law as it stands already.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Foran, if I mistake not, said that he could use names.  If Senator Foran could use names, has he already used them?  Has he given the names to the Department of Justice?  If not, why has he not given the names to the Department of Justice?  I know that there have been considerable talk and many wild statements about corruption here, there and everywhere else.  I know also that in many cases where this talk was loudest, on thorough investigation nothing has been found, and no proof whatever has been forthcoming to support this talk.  It is a very easy matter for anybody to shout <Col N="50" /> about corruption and to accuse other people, but when it comes to a question of proof, the very people who make the accusations are the last people to come forward with any kind of proof. I am not one of those who believe that we are an island of saints, not by any means; but I have gone into this matter; I have examined it very thoroughly; I have done considerable thinking over it, and I came to the conclusion that there are two types of people who talk loudest about bribery and corruption.  One type is the people who lost votes, and the other is the people who found the votes.  That may be a rather drastic statement to make, but I am quite satisfied that a good deal of the talk of bribery and corruption is due to the fact that Mr. So-and-so did not get the vote of somebody whom he expected to vote for him.  Because he did not get it, he cannot think of any other possible explanation except that the voter sold his vote to somebody else.  There are good reasons why voters do not vote for people who expect their votes, besides bribery and corruption.  Perhaps it is a sign of the weakening of certain political Parties that they selected certain candidates or that they selected wrong candidates.</P>
    <P>It strikes me that it is like the little boy who whistles passing a graveyard so that he will not hear his heart beat. A lot of this talk has been shouted around the country by people who are themselves very much under suspicion. I feel at any rate that the setting up of this judicial commission could not serve any useful purpose.  I believe that if we are really serious about this matter and any Senator has any information which would lead to the conviction of any person, it is his duty to give that information to the Department of Justice.  I think that an assurance has already been given that if any such information is given to the Department of Justice it will be thoroughly investigated.  Any Senator who talks about bribery and who has not done that has neglected his duty as a public representative.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Sé an chéad rud <Col N="51" /> a gcuimhneódh duine air maidir leis an rún nó an tairisgint seo, go bhfuil sé ar Chlár an tSeanaid le tamall fada. Cuimhneófar freisin go raibh, ar feadh tamaill sul má cuireadh an rún isteach, campaign tréan ar bun i gcoinne an tSeanaid i gcuid de na páipéir nuaíochta nach bhfuil cáil ró-mhór ortha i dtaobh a ndílseachta don tír nó i dtaobh an mheasa atá aca ar institiúidí áithride sa tír.  Ag cuimhniú domhsa ar an méid sin, ní fhéadfainn gan an tuairim a bheith agam gur thuit moltóirí an rúin faoi anáil na bpáipéar seo gan fhios a bheith aca céard a bhí siad a dhéanamh.</P>
      <P>Tá aithne mhaith ag cuid againn ar an Seanadóir Ó Fuaráin, agus de bharr na haithne sin tá meas againn air agus muinghin againn as.  Ós mar sin atá an scéal, is léir gur cuireadh an rún síos gan machtnamh ceart iomlán a dhéanamh air.</P>
      <P>Maidir leis an rún féin, tá dhá chuid ann.  Phléidh an Seanadóir Kingsmill Ó Mórdha an chéad chuid de go beacht soiléir, agus theasbáin na lochta móra a bhaineann léi.  Na lochta a nocht sé chonnaic a lán againn ó thosach iad, ach ó phléidh seisean chó cruinn iomlán iad, ní call domhsa iad a phlé a thuille.</P>
      <P>Maidir leis an dara cuid den rún, shíleas i dtosach go mb'fhiú iarracht a dhéanamh leis an bpobal a chur ar a suaimhneas i dtaobh na rudaí a bhí á rá agus i gcoinne na ráflaí a bhí á sgaipeadh.</P>
      <P>Ach annsin, shíleas go mb'aisteach an rud é, má bhí eolas ag an Seanadóir Ó Fuaráin ar imeachta mí-dhlisteanacha, nár chuir sé an t-eolas sin os comhair an Aire Dlighidh agus Cirt nó an t-eolas a chur isteach chuig an Rialtas.  Má tá a leithéid sin d'eolas ag na Seanadóirí a mhol an rún, tá cliste ortha ina ndualgas mar shaoránaigh. Tá fhios aca go bhfuil dlí ann cheana i gcoinne caimiléarachta a bhaineas le toghcháin.  Bainidís feidhm as an dlí sin má tá eolas aca ar an gcaimiléaracht má tá siad dáiríribh.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="52" /> Is truagh nach bhfuil dlí ann le teacht ar dhaoine agus ar pháipéir nuaíochta a sgaipeas ráflaí den tsórt a bhí i gceist annseo iniu.  Déanann na páipéir seo dochar do dhaoine agus deanann siad dochar d'institiúidí an Stáit, institiúidí an daonfhlaithis. Níl fhios agam cé na cáilíochta atá ag cuid aca seo labhairt ar an gcaoi a labhruíonn siad ar a lán neithe, ach tá mé sásta go bhfuil an t-am tagtha le cose a chur leis an saoirse atá aca le ráflaí éagcóra dainséaracha a scaipeadh i dtaobh daoine, i dtaobh institiúidí an Stáit agus i dtaobh gluaiseachtaí.</P>
    <P>Tá súil agam nach nglacfaidh an Seanad leis an tairisgint seo.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. O'Connell Mr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>It strikes me that we are inclined to pay too much attention to mere rumours.  It is characteristic, not alone of this country but any other, that anybody who occupies a public position or aspires to do so leaves himself open to criticism, suggestions and allegations of all kinds. Anybody who is thin-skinned enough to pay attention to these rumours should not be in public life.  That is how I feel about it.  Many of the rumours that are going about are in the nature of humorous sallies, if I may put it that way, of the <i>Dublin Opinion</i> type rather than something that is seriously meant.  It will not help us or add to our dignity in any way if we attach to these rumours an importance which they do not deserve.  A famous statesman once said that if a person is turned aside by every dog that barks he will never get to the end of his journey.  These rumours should not be taken seriously, they are humorous or semi-humorous, and I think that was the case when Senator O'Donnell was congratulated on his election and was asked how much it cost him.  Nobody seriously believes that there was any charge being made against him.  The Senator took it in the humorous or semi-humorous way it was put to him.  I do not think we should take these rumours as if they were meant seriously, and it would not be worth investigating <Col N="53" /> something in which there is no substance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankOBeirne" hpid="Mr. O'Beirne Mr. O'Beirne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Beirne</NameTxt>
      <P>I have listened to this debate so far as it has gone and I have read articles&mdash;leading articles and other articles&mdash;in certain daily newspapers on this subject.  I am happy to be able to state that I still have faith in my fellowmen, and I have not lost faith in myself.  Listening to the moves of this motion and reading those articles in certain daily newspapers, one would think that this country was reeking with corrupt politics and that, somehow, a number of corrupt politicians had found their way into this House.  When I look around, I see that this House is composed of people drawn from various walks of life&mdash;from the professions, the trades, education, industry and agriculture. Before our names became eligible to appear on the ballot paper, we had to be selected.  We were selected by our various groups and organisations. Our names, records and qualification were carefully scrutinised before we were selected.  It is very serious for anybody to suggest that the elector had at the time of this election with drawn the trust which they reposed in members of the Dáil elected a few months previously.  Similarly, in the case of the county councillors.  These people had been elected just a year previously, and it is not fair for anybody to suggest that they betrayed their trust.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I see on the benches on this side and on the other side of the House men and women who, twenty years ago, worked and fought for the liberty of this country.  I am happy to boast that I number myself amongst those who so fought and worked.  We worked and fought for an ideal.  We saw our comrades die for that ideal. I think that it was the sacrifices of those days that made possible the free Constitution to which this House and other national institutions owe their very existence.  It is a very serious matter for the editor of any newspaper to pretend that he constitutes the people.  I agree with Senator Foran that membership of this House <Col N="54" /> carries with it very important duties and obligations.  The most important duty it carries with it is the protection of the good name of this House and of its members.  I regret very much that Senator Foran's motion is not in different terms.  I cannot support it because it pillories every member of this House as well as those who failed to be elected.  I hope that the House will not pass the motion in its present form.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephHannigan" hpid="Dr. Hannigan Dr. Hannigan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Hannigan</NameTxt>
      <P>There seems to be a good deal of misunderstanding with regard to the intention and purpose of the mover and seconder of this motion. One point made clear both by the mover and seconder was that the reason this motion was tabled was not because either of them had first-hand knowledge that bribery and corruption had occurred in the recent Seanad election but because allegations had been made in responsible quarters, such as local authorities, that such practices had occurred.  The point was, furthermore, made clear that responsible organs of the Press had also referred in very clear terms to the fact that there were known cases of bribery and corruption so far as that election was concerned.  There is a good deal of adverse criticism so far as the method of election is concerned but I should like to hear a little constructive criticism.  It is easy to find fault with the system of election but it is a different matter to improve that system.  It must be well known that each political Party has its chosen candidates for this election and that, in so far as the machinery these respective Parties permits, it is used to secure the election of these candidates. I think that the Act might be amended in some way in that regard because it does not appear to me&mdash;whatever my humble opinion may be worth&mdash; that the action taken by the major political Parties, so far as this election is concerned, is strictly in accordance with the Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>A rather well-known southern bishop tells a story of how he was passing through a town one day and saw two young boys <Col N="55" /> messing around in the mud.  He asked them &ldquo;What are you doing?&rdquo; and they replied: &ldquo;We are making a priest.&rdquo; The bishop said, &ldquo;Why don't you make a bishop?&rdquo;  and they replied, &ldquo;We have not enough mud to make a bishop.&rdquo;  The position in which we, happily, find ourselves is that neither of the Senators who tabled this motion has sufficient material to make a charge or allegation.  We may appreciate the spirit in which they brought forward the motion, but I think, nevertheless, that they have spread a little more mud.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Hannigan wanted to make it clear that neither of the Senators responsible for the motion desired to make any allegation.  I am glad to have that assurance, because it did seem to me that one of the Senators had suggested that there were some people here who ought not to be here, because they bought votes, and that the other suggested that there were some people who got here under false pretences.  I hope that examination of the charges against the Seanad will not occupy our minds to a very large extent.  The system of election is complicated, but I hope the Seanad is not going immediately to devote any great part of its energies to trying to draft another system.  We are spending millions of pounds on an Army to protect us in the difficulties which exist in the world at present.  Any Senator going through the country, whether city Senator or rural Senator, must realise that there are certain difficulties which must be tackled in a serious way.  Senator Foran said that this House was under a cloud of suspicion, and that unless it clears it away, it will not occupy the position that it ought in the public mind.  However, we came together here&mdash;60 of us closely associated with the life of the country&mdash;and if we manage to find differences among ourselves because of some cloud concerning the way some of us came here, then we certainly are not going to occupy the position that we ought to occupy as a group of experienced people in one of the greatest emergencies our economic life has ever known.  Having brought <Col N="56" /> forward a motion, and having, in my opinion, confused the situation and dragged suggestions, alleged against the House, wider, I hope that it is realised by the Senators who put forward the motion that it could not possibly be implemented, and that we see here the last of it.  Instead, we ought to see how we can find work upon which we can act together as a complete body, bearing on urgent economic circumstances before we start to remodel this institution.  I do not believe that this body here could remodel the institution and at the same time pay attention to the important business that it ought to be paying attention to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanRuane" hpid="Mr. Ruané Mr. Ruané">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ruané</NameTxt>
      <P>In common with many who have been elected to this Assembly, I would like, in considering all the rumours that were made about bribery and corruption so far as the last Seanad was concerned, that some investigation would be set up that would allay these rumours.  But the more I thought about the difficulty of setting up such an investigation, and the difficulty of its character, the harder I found it to satisfy myself as to what could be done.  As far as rumours and insinuations are concerned, any man in public life for a considerable time will always find himself food for that sort of thing, and, as a matter of fact, the longer he is in public life the more he will have to develop a hide as thick as an elephant's, or he will wilt under it.  I fail to see how any judicial inquiry would separate these rumours that have got publicity in the Press and by the public&mdash;how it would set these rumours at rest in the absence of something in the nature of direct evidence, which has not been forthcoming so far.  In my estimation, the Government has already gone as far as any Government could go in responding to the need to keep the election of public bodies pure and above any insinuation of corruption by inviting evidence from the one county in Ireland where publicity was given to the fact that allegations of bribery were made.  As far as I know, no response to the invitation to supply evidence has been forthcoming, <Col N="57" /> and in the absence of that evidence what would be the use setting up an inquiry to investigate rumours in connection with which there is no practical evidence?  If any inquiry could be established that would definitely do away with such rumours for all time, I would be happy to vote for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonalOSullivan" hpid="Mr. D. O'Sullivan Mr. D. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>Having listened to the debate so far, I have come to the conclusion that the commission demanded by Senator Foran's motion is not a proposal that I could stand over from the legal point of view.  It would only result in a fishing inquiry.  The actual statute law on this whole subject is perfectly adequate provided that you have a virile public opinion behind the law.  If you do not have that in this country, then this country is heading for disaster.</P>
      <P>The Electoral (Prevention of Abuses) Act, 1923, takes the gravest view of bribery and corrupt practices.  These are defined in a very long section&mdash; Section 2.  The punishment for a person tried in due form of law and found guilty of a corrupt practice is, on summary conviction, imprisonment with or without hard labour for a term not exceeding one year.  There is power to set up an election court, and it is defined in Section 56 as a &ldquo;court or tribunal constituted and having jurisdiction to inquire into, hear, determine or report upon allegations, charges, disputes or differences in respect of elections generally or any particular election or class of elections.&rdquo;  That procedure covers what we here are discussing, provided that the Government is in a position to move.  I have no doubt whatever that if the Government were in a position to move, then the Government would move.  Of these widely prevalent rumours one might say, as in Bardell v. Pickwick: &ldquo;What the soldier said is not evidence.&rdquo;  Hearsay evidence is not evidence in a legal sense, and it may be extremely dangerous to the individual who cannot defend himself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="58" /> The dilemma here is in connection with people who retail hearsay evidence and cannot, or will not, go any further.  If a man possesses direct evidence, if he has been offered a bribe, then it is his duty to inform the Attorney-General.  Under Section 44, &ldquo;where information is given to the Attorney-General that any corrupt or illegal practices have prevailed in reference to any election it shall be the duty of the Attorney-General to make such inquiries and institute such prosecutions as the circumstances of the case appear to him to require.&rdquo;  I have no doubt that has been done in so far as the Attorney-General can do it.  But he cannot have any regard for rumour, and it seems to me that the tribunal envisaged by Senator Foran might do great moral damage to innocent individuals, and being a fishing inquiry would not result in any redress.  Unless there is a virile public opinion behind the law and unless the individual acts in accordance with the law, then we shall get nowhere.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know that there is any need really for me to say anything in addition to what has been said against this motion.  I do not think that the proposer and seconder really gave any thought as to how it would operate if it were approved. Naturally, anybody who is interested in the institutions of the State, or in any democratic institutions at all, is anxious that these institutions should be kept pure, and, of course, any suggestions of corrupt practices are damaging.  Now, sometimes it occurs to me that a lot of the rumours that are spread are spread deliberately, with a view to damaging these democratic institutions, and that those who spread such rumours know very well what they are doing.  It would appear to me that such people know that there is no way in which the community or the State can adequately defend itself against such attacks.  If there were any procedure by which one could get after these rumours and examine them home, then, of course, that method would not be so frequently resorted to as means of damaging the <Col N="59" /> State.  Now, there is not the slightest doubt that, with regard to the previous election and this recent election, suggestions of corruption, bribery, and the purchase of votes were bandied about.  We, in the Government, having regard for the democratic institutions of the State, naturally, are very anxious to have these rumours or allegations examined home, but we find ourselves in the difficult position that there is no adequate way in which such rumours can be pursued home, as has been pointed out by Senators who have spoken on this matter, unless the people who make such allegations are prepared to come forward and give direct evidence.</P>
      <P>For instance, certain statements were made in the public Press with regard to this matter.  The moment these statements appeared, the Minister for Justice wrote to the people who had made these allegations, and asked them to come forward, either to the Attorney-General or to himself, and make available any evidence that they had in their possession that would lead to the proving of the allegations that had been made.  None of these requests bore any fruit.  For instance, I have here an account of two or three of the cases.  One of the first of these has reference to a statement made at a meeting of the Association of Municipal Authorities.  Perhaps I should not mention names, but since the names were mentioned in the newspapers already, any Senator can find them out for himself, but I think, Sir, that it would be better for me to avoid mentioning the names here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, I think it would be better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good, Sir; although the names are mentioned in the Press, I shall avoid giving them here now, and if any Senator wishes to follow the matter up, he can find out the names in the newspapers, because I think it would be better not to mention here the names of the particular individuals concerned.  At any rate, in the report it was mentioned <Col N="60" /> that a certain man said that he had been offered a substantial sum in cash for his vote.  This matter was investigated by the Gárda Síochána in the district, and the person concerned had to admit to the member of the Gárda Síochána who called upon him in connection with the matter that he had not been offered anything for his vote in the recent election but stated that, in the 1938 election, he had been approached by a certain man, whom he named, and who, he alleged, offered him £50 on condition that he voted for a certain party.  It then appeared, however, that the person whom he mentioned was two years dead!</P>
      <P>The second report referred to a meeting of the Longford County Council. I think it was reported that three members of the Longford County Council had indicated that they had information to the effect that money had been offered for votes for candidates for the Seanad.  The three members in question were communicated with&mdash;I have a copy here of the letter that was sent to them&mdash;and the first person to whom one of these letters was sent denied that he had been offered any money for his vote, and said that the report of his remarks at the county council meeting was false and misleading.  The second person who was communicated with stated that that was what he had been told, and that he was not going to inform on anybody.  The third person referred the matter back to the first person. Now, that is where you get in a case of this kind.  Here you have the case of three people in the Longford County Council who are alleged to have made these remarks with regard to the offering of bribes.  The first man denies that he was ever offered any money. The second man says that he was told that such a thing had happened, but that he was not going to inform on anybody; and the third person refers back to the first person, who denies being offered any money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The next case that I have here is concerned with a meeting of the Kilkenny County Council, at which the following statement was made.  One <Col N="61" /> man&mdash;talking about bribery and corruption&mdash;stated:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I was offered £50 for my vote. In my 30 years of public life I was never bought for any money or for anything else.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>A letter, along similar lines, was sent by the Department of Justice to the person who spoke in that manner, but, so far, no reply has been received. Now, that is the result of examination by the Department of Justice in their attempt to follow up these cases.  I do not know whether there is anything further that the Department of Justice can do.  Actually, I am rather sorry that there is no way of punishing people who make statements of that kind, and who are not prepared to stand over them afterwards, or who are not prepared, at least, to show that such statements, even though they may be proved afterwards to be false, were made in good faith.  According to my information, there is no way of getting after such people.  I understand that there is some law to deal with people who are causing public mischief or damage, but I am afraid that that law is too narrow in its implications to deal with the type of people that I have in mind here.</P>
    <P>Some Senators have pointed out that there might be a way of dealing with that kind of thing if a tribunal of some sort were set up, before which public-spirited people would come forward to give evidence; but why will they not come forward and give evidence now in the ordinary way, if they have such evidence?  There is an ordinary way to deal with such matters.  Such people can say: &ldquo;Very well, I have evidence to give, and I am prepared to give it now.&rdquo;  I think that I need not assure the House that if the Attorney-General and the Government can get such evidence, they will be only too glad to avail of it.  But we find ourselves in the position in which these rumours are spread, and, as I said on another occasion, with regard to the old saying that where there is smoke there is fire, neither I nor the Government can say, with regard to rumours of this kind, <Col N="62" /> whether there is any fire behind the smoke.  Perhaps there is, but I cannot tell.</P>
    <P>But we have no means, unless we get evidence, of finding out, and we have got, therefore, into the position that this tribunal which it is proposed should be set up, could not do any effective work.  It is something unknown to our present method of procedure. Are we then, for instance, to set up this tribunal which will bring before it these men who have made statements and examine them on oath?  What are we to do with them? If they say, as they have said, that it is a false and misleading report, what are we to do with them?  I do not know if there is any way in which we can prove an offence if they simply tell the tribunal what they have said, that the report is misleading, that they did not say that, and have no evidence of any kind.  I do not know how we are going to prosecute, or if there is any punishment.  You cannot force them, particularly if it is a statement which would implicate themselves.  I do not know what cautions we would have to give them beforehand if there was inquiry of this sort.  If it came to a point which showed very definitely that the Attorney-General should be informed, I do not know whether the tribunal should suspend its operations while criminal proceedings were being taken, because all these acts or corrupt practices are criminal offences. But, I am afraid, anxious as I would be to have this probed open, that I have to say, like every Senator after the proposer and seconder, that there is no way open in which we can do it. It is not a judicial investigation&mdash;it is a probing investigation&mdash;and the Department of Justice, in so far as they can probe, are the only people who can do it.  But, they cannot do it until they have some particular type of evidence on which they can take action.</P>
    <P>Therefore, I must agree with Senators who have spoken against this motion on the grounds of its uselessness. It would serve no good purpose, and I have to recommend the <Col N="63" /> Seanad not to accept it, but I do that with reluctance from one point of view, because I think it would be of great value if we were able to do away with those things and to find somebody who is guilty and have him punished properly, or else be able to clear the House, if possible, of the insinuations made.  I do not think that is possible. It was pointed out that if we set up a tribunal, everybody would take his own view as to the personnel of the tribunal&mdash;what were the leanings of the people appointed, and so on.</P>
    <P>I am not saying that is a major difficulty.  We could get over it, but there are certain things we cannot do, and no matter what the findings of an inquiry were, you would not satisfy people who would believe rumours.  If a tribunal were set up to investigate the matter and said: &ldquo;We have not been able to find anything,&rdquo; people would say: &ldquo;It is there all the time.&rdquo; It has been suggested: &ldquo;Why do you not get after it as you get after the black marketeers?&rdquo;  That reminds me of accusations against the Government in other directions.  Some people think that methods used in one direction can also be applied in others. In the case of a black market, some inspector goes in and the people engaged in it do not recognise him.  He gets overcharged, or obtains something which should not be available.  You cannot do that in the case of an election which is over and gone.</P>
    <P>Is it suggested that in the case of future elections we should send people around who would try to get people to bribe them or to accept bribes?  I do not see how this black-market method of investigation can be applied to the thing at all.  I think it is quite a different sort of offence you have got to get after.  In the case of black market offences you have something concrete and definite to point out.  In this particular matter you can be sure that if money passes, it is not likely to be passed by cheque. You have the difficulty of laying your hand on anything concrete that would satisfy any impartial court as being really evidence.  I do not think that I <Col N="64" /> should delay the House any longer. My only point is that I do not think that the proposer and seconder have given the matter any serious thought. If they did, I think they would have to come to the same conclusion as every other member who spoke after them. Certainly, it was the conclusion forced on us.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to ask the Taoiseach if he would inquire from his law officers whether these people who have gone back on their word can be prosecuted for public mischief, and if the answer is in the affirmative?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, I have already thought of that.  I inquired the moment the suggestion was made, and the answer was given to me quickly and I have given the answer as given to me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>That they cannot be prosecuted?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>They cannot.  At least the procedure suggested is intended for different purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Foran to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>After hearing the Taoiseach we may throw up our hands altogether.  If corrupt practices existed heretofore, the parties know now that they are immune, because the State has no machinery whatever to deal with them.  They are free now and for all time.  That, in effect, is what they have been told by the Taoiseach. We have no machinery of State to destroy corruption.  I suggest to him that these rumours are very closely allied to sedition and he knows he has machinery for dealing with sedition.  I regard the allegations and rumours as disruptive as those for which other organisations are very severely pursued.  If we are to allow people to weaken confidence in Parliamentary institutions, well, we are heading, without doubt, towards ruin for democracy, yet we are told by the <Col N="65" /> Taoiseach that there is no machinery in the State to deal with any people who wish to engage in corruption or bribery in regard to the Seanad election.  If it occurs in the Seanad election, it is quite possible that it can occur in every election in the State, and, therefore, we are on the brink of a very dangerous period, and the sooner the Taoiseach realises that and sets up machinery, however difficult it may be to set it up, to check this rot before it destroys the constitutional body of this country the better.  I say that in all earnestness.  The time has arrived for the machinery to be set up.  It is said that there are no means of bringing these people to justice, but there are other means of dealing with people in other directions, and I suggest there he will find machinery to deal with these people because they are equally destructive, with other forces against constitutional Government, in this country.</P>
      <P>These rumours are not confined to ordinary street talk.  Responsible newspapers have made the allegations and reports have been published in rural papers, all tending to show how the recent Seanad election stands in the minds of the people.  From that point of view, we were perfectly justified in putting down this motion and if it stimulates the Government to organise machinery to deal with these corrupters, we will have done a very good day's work.  I would like to make passing remarks on some of the comments we heard during the discussions. Senator Kingsmill Moore started the Seanad after a herring that was not there at all.  As I said to him outside the House: &ldquo;Never trust a lawyer's opinion when you get it free.&rdquo; He certainly succeeded in drawing the Seanad away from the real issue in the motion.  I shall say no more about that just now.</P>
      <P>I was very amused to hear Senator Hawkins accusing the Labour Party of being malicious in this matter and stating that because they had lost certain votes they put down this motion. I am reliably informed that Fianna Fáil had a private inquiry of their own as to where certain votes went.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="66" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>That was a rumour also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I have very good evidence, so you see, let it be the Labour Party, Fianna Fáil, Fine Gael or any other Party in this House, Party allegiance is weakened when it is a question of money and, because of other influences, Party influence is not sufficient to ensure allegiance in a Seanad election.  All this is a pointer; it shows what is happening.  We certainly lost votes in the election and so did every other Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Who got them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Senator should be allowed to go ahead.  He is obviously speaking from experience.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>And knowledge. Another Senator asked us to look around and see the men who were elected.  I should like to take a picture of the people who were not elected.  Men of outstanding ability, men who would be a credit to any assembly, men who would be capable of maintaining the prestige of this or any other institution of the State, did not get a solitary vote and they represented very influential organisations in the country.  I do not know that there is very much more I want to say on the matter.  Apparently the House is not with us.  When we put down the motion we had the feeling that we would have the unanimous support of the House because we assumed that every Party was as anxious as we were to have the matter cleared up.  We are jealous of the credit and prestige of the Parliamentary institutions of this State.  We want to remove any possibility or suggestion of corruption and we thought the means here suggested were the best that could be adopted but after hearing the Taoiseach, we must, I fear, withdraw the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do wish to impress on the Taoiseach that as long as the present system of election to this Seanad exists, we must have some such machinery adopted. <Col N="67" /> Whether he in his wisdom or his advisers are able to create that machinery, some such machinery must be devised before any further election to this Seanad arises because at present, as I have said, the Seanad stands low in the estimation of the people of this country.  When allegations and rumours of corruption are bandied about, machinery must be devised to deal with them if democratic institutions are to continue in this State.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>How would the Senator say it can be done?  Any two or three irresponsible people may circulate rumours.  How can you defend yourself against that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a tribunal in existence before which people are made to account for certain things.  I suggest that something like that should be applied in this case.</P>
      <P>Motion, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="First Report of the" RHead="Committee of Selection">
    <Title>First Report of the Committee of Selection.</Title>
    <Col N="68" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The following report has been received from the Committee of Selection:&mdash;</P>
      <P>The Committee of Selection has nominated the following Senators to serve on the Committee on Procedure and Privileges:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Senators P.F. Baxter, T. Foran, F. J. H. Hawkins, M. Hayes, M. Hearne, W. Magennis, T. C. Kingsmill-Moore, R. Mulcahy, S. O'Donovan and P. J. O'Loghlen.</P>
      <P>Ordered: That the Report do lie upon the Table.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned <i>sine die</i> at 5.30 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>