<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Tue" Date="2" Month="Dec" Year="1969" Vol="67" No="3" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 2 Nollaig 1969" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 2 December 1969" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="127">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="127" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Panel of" RHead="Chairmen">
    <Title>Panel of Chairmen.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose, if the House agrees, to nominate five members to the Panel of Chairmen.  This is two in addition to the three provided for in the Standing Orders.  The Members are: Charles B. McDonald, John J. Nash, George E. Russell, Eoin Ryan, and W. A. W. Sheldon.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - The Dublin Cemeteries" RHead="Committee Bill, 1969: Second Stage">
    <Title>Private Business. - The Dublin Cemeteries Committee Bill, 1969: Second Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - The Dublin Cemeteries" RHead="Committee Bill, 1969: Joint Committee">
    <Title>Private Business. - The Dublin Cemeteries Committee Bill, 1969: Joint Committee.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Tairgim:</P>
      <P>Go bhfuil sé oiriunach Comhchoiste den dá Theach a cheapadh chun an Bille um Choiste Reiligí Bhaile Átha Cliath, 1969, a bhreithniú, eadhon, Bille dá ngairtear Acht do bhunú comhlacht corpraithe chun na feidhmeanna a ghabháil de láimh agus a chur i gcrích atá gafa de láimh agus á gcur i gcrích faoi láthair ag an <i>Dublin Cemeteries Committee</i> agus do mhéadú agus do leathnú na bhfeidhmeanna sin.</P>
      <P>I move:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That it is expedient that a Joint Committee of both Houses be appointed to consider the Dublin Cemeteries Committee Bill, 1969, being a Bill entitled an Act to establish a body corporate to undertake and carry out the functions at present undertaken and carried out by the &ldquo;Dublin Cemeteries Committee&rdquo;<Col N="128" /> and to enlarge and extend such functions.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>A message will be sent to the Dáil accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. -" RHead="Order of Business">
    <Title>Private Business. - Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 2, 3, 6 and 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to put a point of view to the Leader of the House. The business ordered for today is, to a large extent, financial business and I wonder if the Leader of the House and if the Minister who is present consider it appropriate that financial business might be discussed during the period when the present national loan is open? It seems to me that it might have an unnecessary inhibiting effect on Senators in dealing with financial business in those circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot see any validity in that point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>That is fair enough. I simply wished to put the point to the Leader of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Oireachtas" RHead="Library Joint Committee">
    <Title>Private Business. - Oireachtas Library Joint Committee.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has made the following Order:</P>
      <P>That a Select Committee consisting of seven members be appointed to be joined with a Select Committee to be appointed by Seanad Éireann to assist and advise the Ceann Comhairle and the Cathaoirleach in the direction and control of the Oireachtas Library, and</P>
      <P>That the quorum of the Committee be two.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That a Select Committee consisting of seven members be appointed to be joined with the Select Committee appointed by Dáil Éireann to assist and advise the Ceann Comhairle and the Cathaoirleach in the direction and control of the Oireachtas Library;</P>
      <P>That the quorum of the Committee be two.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Immature Spirits" RHead="(Restriction) Bill, 1969: Second Stage">
    <Title>Private Business. - Immature Spirits (Restriction) Bill, 1969: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="129" /> Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. Haughey) Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. Haughey)</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the Immature Spirits (Restriction) Act, 1947, potable spirits, with certain exceptions, must be warehoused for at least five years before being cleared for home consumption. The main exceptions are gin and liqueurs.</P>
      <P>The Irish distilling industry indicated recently that they would like to have this minimum warehousing period shortened.  As it stands, it is longer than that applicable in the United Kingdom &mdash;three years&mdash;and it affects our export trade to the United States in that spirits cannot be put on the market there unless they are eligible for sale in the exporting country.  This means that Irish whiskey may not be sold in the US until it is five years old while whiskey produced in Northern Ireland and Scotch whisky may be sold when three years old.</P>
      <P>Apart from export considerations, there is the desirability of keeping in line with developments in Europe.  The Council of Europe has prepared a draft Convention relating to spirits in which a minimum age of three years is proposed for whiskey and of one year for rum.  These limits may well be adopted in the EEC.  Thus, the Bill now before you brings our law into line with thinking abroad on the subject.</P>
      <P>The repute and characteristics of Irish whiskey will not be affected by this Bill.  The Irish distillers have taken care always to ensure that their products are of the highest quality. At present, the industry is gearing itself for the seventies and is developing its outlets and can be relied on to safeguard the valuable reputation of Irish whiskey.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There will be no loss of revenue as a result of this amendment but a minor alteration in the additional duty charged on immature spirits becomes necessary as a consequence.  At present, spirits warehoused for less than five years are liable to a small additional duty of 2s. 6d. a proof gallon.  In line with the reduced warehousing requirement <Col N="130" /> this charge will for the future be applied only to spirits warehoused for less than three years.  It is proposed to give effect to this change by means of an order under the Imposition of Duties Act, 1957.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of the Fine Gael Party I should like to welcome this measure and to make three points about it.  Firstly, it is the sort of measure which particularly recommends itself to us in that although it is small in apparent effect its totality of good achievements can make something enduring and remarkable. This is a technical change recommended to the Department of Finance by the industry concerned and it is from all the information one has, likely to facilitate the increased exportation of the product of this very great and ancient Irish industry.</P>
      <P>The second point I should like to make about this, which in a way leads on to the third, is just to mention to the House, if the House or any Member of it are not aware already, that the background to this type of legislation is to be found in the events of 1915 when Britain at war found its munition industry being damaged by excessive alcoholism.  The then Minister for Munitions, Lloyd George, as Chancellor of the Exchequer, introduced a very savage new duty on spirits in which he actually doubled the duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There was a great outcry which had one not unexpected effect&mdash;every Irishman in the House voted against it The second even more remarkable effect is that the predecessor to Senator Owen Sheehy Skeffington and his colleague, the representative of Dublin University, Sir Edward Carson for the first time did not vote in favour of a measure proposed by the Government; he abstained from voting in fact and said he was opposing it in speech but he did not in fact vote against it. As a result of this outcry the extraordinary situation emerged that for ten days the duty was on and then had to be withdrawn.  They settled for a restriction of immature spirits.  As I say, this was opposed by Sir Edward Carson the representative of Dublin University, his particular interests, the distilleries in Belfast, had not in fact <Col N="131" /> stocks on hand to meet the demand. The people in the south had stocks and they were prepared to meet the three year period.  There was a great objection taken to the consumption of raw potable spirits.  As one who was mature enough to have consumed during the war what was called &ldquo;lovely two-year old&rdquo;, and almost perished as a result of it, I have great sympathy with the criticisms made.</P>
    <P>This leads me to my third point. There is some evidence at any rate that there are certainly in some spirits, and in minute quantities in potable triple distilled whiskey, certain higher forms of alcohol which have become degraded. However, I am sure the industry here, in the interests of its own reputation, always ensures that the toxic effects are eliminated.  It occurs to me to be an important point to make &mdash;and one to which I draw the Minister's attention&mdash;that the effect of this Bill will be to reduce the restrictive period of five years to three years not merely in respect of Irish whiskey, but in respect of whiskey wherever it may be produced.  There may be countries which have not the same concern our distillers have in regard to these toxic elements.  Therefore, it seems appropriate that I should, in welcoming this Bill, draw the Minister's attention to the desirability of having this question, in relation to other types of whiskey, referred to Comhairle na Nimheanna, which is concerned with such matters and will be aware of the possible toxic effects of immature whiskey, which may be not matured after three years in uncivilised places.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. Haughey) Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. Haughey)</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator FitzGerald that it is very important indeed that we should protect the Irish palate from the incursion of uncivilised whiskey from abroad.  Whatever action may be necessary from time to time in that regard will, of course, be taken by me. I am grateful to the House for the expeditious way in which they have dealt with this Bill.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="132" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Can we have the remaining Stages of this Bill now?</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Immature Spirits (Restriction)" RHead="Bill, 1969: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Private Business. - Immature Spirits (Restriction) Bill, 1969: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 1 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>On section 1 (1) I should like to ask the Minister what is the position in regard to vodka.  The Minister mentioned whiskey, gin and liqueurs but he did not mention vodka. I understand that the distilling industry are not happy about the present arrangements with regard to vodka.  As this is a growing industry in the country with export potential, I should like the Minister to deal with it for the benefit of the distillers of vodka in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Home-made vodka is not affected.  Imported vodka cannot be sold unless it is three years in warehouse. The export prospects are not really affected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>Do I understand the Minister to say that it must be in warehouse for three years?  I understand that the distilling industry want to reduce that to one year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Home-made vodka is not affected at all.  Imported vodka must be three years in warehouse.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>That does not apply to home-made vodka?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>With respect, I should like some authority from the Minister for this proposition because &ldquo;spirits&rdquo; is given a particular definition in the basic Act.  I understand vodka is outside that definition and that is why it is not required to be matured for three years.  Whether it is home-made or foreign-made, it would be outside this restriction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I am advised that home-made vodka is described as a home-made compound and therefore is <Col N="133" /> not subject to a warehousing restriction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It is purely a question of proof.  If the imported vodka is a compound, it is outside the restriction also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a question of the definition of &ldquo;spirits&rdquo;.  May I ask the Minister for authority for this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I am fortified by the authority of no less a body than the Revenue Commissioners.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>With great respect, and retaining my particular respect for the Revenue Commissioners, I am unable to accept that as final authority for the satisfaction of my question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>It remains the situation until the Senator proves it to be otherwise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has made an assertion that on all matters we must accept a statement from the Revenue Commissioners as to what the law is.  I do not think if the Minister were practising as he once practised that he would be satisfied with that himself.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 2 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Trustee (Authorised" RHead="Investments) Order: Motion of Approval">
    <Title>Private Business. - Trustee (Authorised Investments) Order: Motion of Approval.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann approves the following Order in draft:</P>
      <P>Trustee (Authorised Investments) Order, 1969.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. Haughey) Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. Haughey)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the order before the House for approval is to give trustee status to the shares of Allied Irish <Col N="134" /> Banks Limited.  It is being made in response to a request from that bank.</P>
      <P>The investments in which trustees may invest trust funds, unless prohibited by the instrument creating the trust, are set out in the Trustee (Authorised Investments) Act, 1958. Subject to the approval of the Oireachtas, the Minister for Finance may vary the list of investments by order.  The main qualifications for trustee investments are that they should be secure and give a reasonable income to the beneficiary.  The shares of Allied Irish Banks fulfil these criteria and they are a suitable security for inclusion in the list of authorised investments.</P>
      <P>Allied Irish Banks Limited was set up as a public company in 1966.  It is the parent company of a number of well-known banks, namely, the Munster and Leinster Bank, the Provincial Bank of Ireland and the Royal Bank of Ireland.  Its authorised share capital consists of 12 million shares of £1 each, of which 7,700,000 have been issued and are fully paid-up.  The shares are quoted on the Belfast and London Stock Exchanges as well as on the Dublin and Cork Exchanges. Total assets of the company on 31st December, 1968, amounted to £386 million.</P>
      <P>The stocks and shares of the two principal banking groups in this country&mdash;that is, the Bank of Ireland and Allied Irish Banks' groups&mdash;are the only Irish bank stocks and shares which can be purchased by the public. The Bank of Ireland's capital stock has been a trustee security since 1889 and a loan stock issued by that bank in 1966 was accorded trustee status by means of an order similar to that which I now propose to make.  There are no good grounds for differentiating between the two banking groups in this matter and I am satisfied that the request of Allied Irish Banks to have trustee status given to its shares is reasonable and should be acceded to. I would be reluctant, however, to make further additions to the list of authorised investments pending completion of a comprehensive review of the existing legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Under the 1958 Act, the Minister for Finance is obliged to consult the following <Col N="135" /> persons on the terms of any order he wishes to make varying the list of authorised investments&mdash;a judge of the High Court nominated by the Chief Justice, the Governor of the Central Bank, the Public Trustee, the Chairman of the Irish Banks' Standing Committee, the President of the Incorporated Law Society of Ireland and the Presidents of the Dublin and Cork Stock Exchanges.  I have consulted all these persons and they have no objection to the proposed order.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of the Fine Gael Party I want to welcome this but must make the following comments on it.</P>
      <P>First of all, it is quite evident that the Minister's statement is absolutely correct that there is no reason why if the Bank of Ireland stock is a trustee security the Allied Irish Banks' stock should not be a trustee security too. The most recent market capitalisation for these stocks I had made was that the Bank of Ireland Stock stood at £44 million on the Irish market and the Allied Irish Banks at £36 million. It is perhaps pertinent to observe that the Bank of Ireland stock is the only equity which is within the narrow range of authorised security in both Britain and Ireland.  However, I do not think that the Minister has been fully and thoroughly briefed on this.  He says that the main qualifications for trustee investments are that they should be secure and give a reasonable income to the beneficiary but at the same time he says he would be reluctant to make further additions to the list of authorised investments pending completion of a comprehensive review of existing legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I agree and certainly welcome the news that such a comprehensive review is under contemplation; but if the main qualifications for trustee investments are that they should be secure it certainly does not take sufficient note of the fact that the whole trustee code was introduced at a time when giltedged securities were secure.  We are now living in an age when this can no longer be true, certainly in relation to undated stocks.  I must emphasise that the short-dated type of security which <Col N="136" /> is now on offer is an entirely secure one.  However, take the case of an unfortunate trustee who, without the proper authorisation of his trust, 20 years ago invested in trustee securities and bought an undated security. According to the information given in a publication I have before me, The Investment Review of the <i>Financial Times</i> Investment Bureau, his investment would now be 30 times worse off than if it had been put into equity securities, from which the unfortunate beneficiaries of trusts are now excluded. When one considers the type of people they are, this is very serious. They are people who are dependent on the provisions that have been made for them because they were afflicted citizens of one kind or another.  Their moneys are locked up in courts of justice.  This is a very serious matter. It is not correct to say that the main qualification of a trustee security is to give a reasonable income to the beneficiary.  This is a wholly inadequate statement of what the position is.  The duty of a trustee is to consider as well the tenant for life, if it be a trust of that kind, and also the remainder man. This may mean that he should take a lower income in the circumstances of the tenant for life.  In case the House should think I merely think of the well-off people, may I draw the House's attention to the fact that there are two formidable types of body who make their investments in trustee securities and can only make their investments in trustee securities and in certain other limited types of investments.</P>
    <P>I shall take one of the two, friendly societies.</P>
    <P>Friendly societies, for example, who hold the investments of very modest savers&mdash;of institutions such as trade unions, for instance&mdash;are permitted to invest only in the investments specified in section 44 of the Friendly Societies Act, 1896, which depends on the provisions of the Trustee (Authorised Investments) Act and certain other authorisations, for example, the purchase of land or the erection and alteration of offices and other buildings.  It is of some interest to note that the Minister has created the situation in which intelligently guided trade unions <Col N="137" /> may look beyond the building of office blocks to investment in the Irish banking system.  However, this does not seem to be a sufficient extension of the powers that should be given to trustees, particularly when in the neighbouring country there is provision for full investment in equities if there is good advice given to the trustees to do so and a proper proportion of the portfolio is invested in narrow-range securities which would be equivalent to the only type of security in which one may invest in Ireland if one does one's duty as a member of the committee of a friendly society or as a trustee concerned with the public welfare.</P>
    <P>It has also a restricting effect on a type of institution we ought to be concerned to attract into business here &mdash;merchant banks&mdash;who have the job very often of administering portfolios and who have got this great limitation on their ability to take over trustee investment because they must comply with the local trust law, where they cannot get sufficient indemnities to go beyond it, and where the trustee has not got the right under the law to simply leave the matter to the advice of the bank in question.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Alexis FitzGerald has commented on the Minister's statement that the main qualification for trustee investments is that they should be secure and give a reasonable income to the beneficiary. As regards the particular matter being dealt with under this order I do not think anybody has any doubts about it&mdash;I think the Minister is doing the right thing in making it a trustee investment. However, it is right to say that &mdash;and I imagine any Senator in the position of Senators FitzGerald and Nash and myself will appreciate this&mdash; the time has come when the Minister and the Government must try to do something in a serious way in regard to the fall in the value of trustee securities. I am thinking now only in terms of investments in trustee securities arising on the application of funds in court&mdash;settlements made or awards given in court proceedings&mdash;where the plaintiff is a minor and where the money is lodged in court and invested in trustee securities.  We all have had <Col N="138" /> the experience from time to time, and I am sure the Minister is not unaware of the problem, that investments were made in what at the time of investment was a trustee security of good standing and value but after a period of years, consequent upon further issues of Government loans and stock, the value of the investment is reduced.</P>
      <P>I have just consulted the Dublin Stock Exchange news in one of the daily papers today and my eye fell on one in particular&mdash;6 per cent Exchequer Stock 1980-85&mdash;which according to this morning's <i>Irish Times</i> is quoted on the Dublin Stock Exchange at 71. Take the case of a court settlement which was made say eight or nine years ago; at the time the money was invested that stock was standing at about the 99 or 100 mark.  If that is being paid out today the beneficiary is suffering a very heavy capital loss.  This may not possibly be the Minister's direct concern in relation to this particular order but it is a matter of general concern in which I think the Minister and the Government must interest themselves and endeavour to do something about it.  I could make some suggestions to the Minister with regard to this but all I wish to say to him now is that this is a question to which he should devote his attention in the coming years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say a few words on the same lines as Senator O'Higgins.  The Minister has indicated in his statement that before he adds any further stocks to the trustee list he would want to have another careful look at existing lists.  I would suggest to the Minister that this offers a good opportunity to have another look at the Trustee (Authorised Investments) Act, 1958, which Act will be 12 years old very shortly, and I suggest to the Minister that the time is now opportune to consider what constitutes a trustee investment.  As Senators FitzGerald and O'Higgins have pointed out, in the last ten or 12 years the rate of depreciation in the value of all types of stock, trustee stock not excluded, has been more rapid than in any other time in recent history.  If this rate of depreciation&mdash;which is of course the <Col N="139" /> result of an increasing depreciation in the value of money&mdash;goes on, it is obvious that trustee stocks, even in their own right, will not be regarded as a safe investment compared with property and land.</P>
      <P>I wonder if the time has not come when the list of trustee stocks could not be expanded to include investments in certain types of property or land.  We all know that over the years, if one was to invest in property as against investment in trustee stock, one would be far better off and wealthier in terms of capital assets today than one would have been ten or 12 years ago.  I would suggest that the time has come for us to look at that again in the light of current conditions.  I do not know what the Minister or what any Government can do about the value of trustee stock which has been depreciating over many years.  British War Loan, which is now quoted at less than 40 as against the original 100 many years ago, is regarded in England as the classic example of the depreciation in value of money and the continued inflation going on for almost a century.  Very serious consideration must be given to the continued depletion in the value of money if all stocks are not to be regarded as of very doubtful value in the years ahead.</P>
      <P>The Minister might perhaps be inclined to reply that, from the point of view of estates, the purchase of trustee stock at its declared value is acceptable at its face value, and from that point of view it is a very good investment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Senator should wander on to that particular matter.  The scope of the motion is relatively narrow.  The Chair has allowed some latitude as regards the general position of trustee stock, but this should not be taken advantage of.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask the Minister to confirm that the stock of three banks which now constitute the Allied Irish Banks group was previously trustee stock in its own right and whether this Order is regularising the position and putting the shares of Allied Banks in the list of trustee stocks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="140" />
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. Haughey) Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. Haughey)</NameTxt>
      <P>Taking the last point first, the answer is no.  As Senator FitzGerald pointed out, the Bank of Ireland was the only bank stock which was a trustee security.  In reply to the point raised by Deputy O'Higgins&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know whether the Minister is looking to the past or to the future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Higgins.  I would say to Senator Russell that the situation is that we are making a very comprehensive and detailed review of the whole position of trustee securities and what should or should not be authorised as a legitimate outlet for trustee funds.  I agree that this review is necessary and that there is need for considerable changes.  I am certain that the review will confirm the need for changes in the existing position.</P>
      <P>On the question of the funds which are lodged in court losing their value, I also recognise that this has been a source of considerable discontent for some years.  I would point out that in recent times we have been doing a fair amount to improve matters generally in this regard.  The existing National Loan which is on offer at the moment &mdash;and I cordially invite all Senators to subscribe handsomely to it&mdash;has its own built-in arrangements whereby it will maintain its value over a considerable period.  We have had the same safeguards incorporated in recent issues.  Furthermore, we can help, and have been helping, by making a greater variety of securities available to the market and to trustees in general and we intend to continue doing that.  The hoped for extension of the money market here in Dublin will also be of assistance in this regard.  Trustees will have available to them a greater range within which to select, and they will not have to put their money into something for which they may have to wait a long, long time for redemption.  They will have available to them a variety of stocks from which they can pick and choose as suits their purpose.  In any event this comprehensive and detailed review is underway at the moment and we hope that as a result the situation will be very considerably improved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="141" /> I did not think that my opening words about the security necessary for trustee investment would be taken so literally, and I can only regret in that connection that I used the word &ldquo;secure&rdquo;.  I did so in its widest sense, and I do not think that it was restricted to simply meaning something that was safer in so far as it was not going to disappear overnight.  I meant security in all its aspects.  Security in holding its value would, of course, be one of these.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Appropriation Bill," RHead="1969 (Certified Money Bill): Second Stage">
    <Title>Private Business. - Appropriation Bill, 1969 (Certified Money Bill): Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. Haughey) Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. Haughey)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Appropriation Bill is an annual measure which is taken in the Dáil after the passage of the Estimates for the Supply Services for the financial year.  Its purpose is to appropriate formally the amounts voted by the Dáil for these services.  The Seanad customarily uses the Bill as a vehicle for a debate on the broad spectrum of Government activity as comprehended in the Supply Services Estimates.</P>
      <P>This year's Bill follows the general pattern of previous Appropriation Acts.  A section has, however, been added to clarify certain aspects of the foreign borrowing powers of the Minister for Finance.</P>
      <P>Section 1 appropriates to the specific services set out in the Schedule to the Bill the sum of £363,498,080 which comprises the 1968/69 Supplementary Estimates which were not included in last year's Appropriation Act, the Estimates for 1969/70 and the Supplementary Estimates already voted for this year.  The section also authorises the use of certain departmental receipts amounting to £24,252,112 as appropriations-in-aid. These are also detailed in the Schedule to the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 2 relates to the external borrowing powers of the Minister for Finance.  As Senators are aware, the Government successfully negotiated a loan of 100 million Deutschemarks in September last.  At the time, however, <Col N="142" /> the international monetary climate was uncertain and there were very strong grounds for expecting an upward revision of the parity of the Deutschemark. Against this background, I felt that it would be most imprudent to arrange for immediate conversion of the proceeds of the loan into Irish currency.  Rather, the course of reason seemed to be to ensure that the Exchequer would benefit to the fullest extent from revaluation.  I arranged, therefore, that the loan proceeds would be placed on deposits abroad until the realignment of parties was settled. Events have borne out the wisdom of this course.</P>
    <P>The Comptroller and Auditor General was of the opinion, however, that I was not entitled to do this and advised that I should arrange for immediate conversion into Irish currency.  This section, which amends section 4 of the Appropriation Act, 1965, is designed to clarify the position.  It provides that the Minister for Finance may exercise his reasonable judgment as to when, in the interest of the Exchequer, it is appropriate that the proceeds of any external borrowing should be converted into Irish currency and paid into the Exchequer.</P>
    <P>I now commend the Bill to the House for a Second Reading.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the Bill which gives the Seanad an opportunity of expressing views generally with regard to Government administration and Government policy.  Most of us would regard the present position generally as the start of a new term.  There has been a general election; that general election has been won and lost, and the present Government are now in a position where they are back in Government, and back in Government with sufficient support behind them in terms of numbers to carry out any policy they may choose.  So far as I am concerned, I am prepared not to look on the past record of the present Government party but to judge them on their performance in the future.  They are there, as I say, with an overall majority, and I think it is fair comment to say that, so far, in <Col N="143" /> the comparatively short time since they achieved that position their start in their term of office has not been very promising.</P>
      <P>It seems to me that there is evidence, to put it no stronger than that, of stresses and strains within the Government which require clarification. Within the last few days we have had a situation arising where there seems to be a very definite and clear-cut conflict between the Government, as represented in this instance by the Minister for Justice, and the Radio Telefís Éireann Authority.  I should like to make it clear at the outset that I am accepting without question, and I do quite sincerely accept, that both parties believe in their own cases and believe the facts to be as they have stated them.  But it seems to me that there is no possibility of reconciling the points of view expressed by the Minister for Justice on the one hand and the RTE Authority on the other.  For that reason I want to commence my remarks by referring to this particular topic, which I believe to be of urgent and public importance, and to add my voice in support of the pleas that have been made that there should be an inquiry into the entire position.  I think the House should be told where exactly the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs stands in this matter.  Senators will be aware of the contents and the nature of the statements made by the Minister for Justice.  They will equally be aware of the fact that the Radio Telefís Éireann Authority have issued a statement which reads as follows:</P>
      <P>The RTE Authority met the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs at the Authority's request.  The Authority informed the Minister that they have reviewed the &ldquo;Seven Days&rdquo; programme on illegal money-lending transmitted on November 11th.  The Authority told the Minister that the content of the programme was authentic and that the people shown in it as money-lenders or borrowers were not fictitious.  The Authority maintained the view that the programme did not present a distorted or exaggerated picture of the social problem of illegal money-lending in Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="144" /> That statement was issued by this Authority in the face of the statements made by the Minister for Justice and by the Taoiseach and contributed to to a lesser extent by other Ministers. I think that the clear purport of the arguments advanced by the Minister for Justice, by the Taoiseach and the other Ministers to whom I referred, was that this programme was grossly exaggerated and largely fictitious.</P>
    <P>I accept that there was sincerity as regards the statements issued and that each believed the stand they were taking to be correct.  But we have the situation now in which there is such a gulf between the two that it is quite impossible for the ordinary person to even attempt a reconciliation of these points of view.  I am speaking now from memory but, as far as I know, the only relevant comment made by the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs on this matter was that he hoped all would be cleared up one way or another.  I may not be quoting the Minister's precise remarks but I wish to say that it is not good enough for the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs to adopt the attitude &ldquo;this, too, will pass&rdquo; in relation to a problem that is so urgent and is of such public importance. I do not wish to labour the subject but it is for these reasons that I consider it necessary for whichever is the correct authority in the Government to clarify the whole situation, and it seems to me that the appropriate way of doing that would be to accede to the request that has been made for a sworn public inquiry.</P>
    <P>As I see it&mdash;possibly I am wrong in this&mdash;an unhappy atmosphere has developed in relation to this matter within the Government.  On the one hand, there is the point of view portrayed by the Minister for Justice&mdash; and apparently supported by the Taoiseach&mdash;while, on the other hand, there is the Telefís Éireann Authority and the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs who has overall responsibility for the authority.  Either the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs must support the statements issued by the authority&mdash;issued I presume with his knowledge because it followed a meeting with him&mdash;or he must repudiate it and take his stand beside his colleagues in the Cabinet.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="145" /> In recent weeks we have had also the situation of the apparent conflict between the Minister for Justice and the Minister for Lands in relation to the future of the Department of Lands. I do not wish to pinprick on this and I recognise the right of anyone to express his own opinion with regard to any matter of public importance or any matter of Government policy.  However, it was announced Government policy that there was to be this step towards decentralisation in the removal of the Department of Lands from Dublin to Castlebar.  At the time that was announced as Government policy I do not think there was any grave objection from people with regard to the principle involved.  The objection taken at the time was an objection which I also took and that was that from evidence there did not appear to have been proper consultation between the Government and those who will be affected by the change in policy.</P>
    <P>We now have a situation that has altered radically.  One Minister expressed the viewpoint as I understood it&mdash;I have not got his remarks before me and I am speaking from memory and subject to correction&mdash;that instead of moving the Department of Lands to Mayo, the correct policy would be that it should be merged with another Ministry, the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries.</P>
    <P>The Minister may speak as an individual.  He may express his own private views&mdash;possibly that is what he was doing&mdash;but he cannot shake off the fact that he is a member of the Cabinet and that in this country we have the principle of collective responsibility in the Cabinet.  If we are to have a situation in which one Minister can express a personal view on a matter of vital public importance and Government policy and is repudiated, in effect, by another Minister who says there is no change in Government policy and that they are going ahead with their proposal to transfer the Department of Lands to Castlebar, there is glaring evidence of stress and strain between different members of a Cabinet who should be exercising collective responsibility, at least in matters of major Government policy, and this is a matter of major <Col N="146" /> Government policy.  The whole situation has become so beclouded by the statements of the Minister for Lands and those of the Minister for Justice that some clear-cut definitive statement of what the intentions of the Government are in relation to this matter of policy is required urgently.</P>
    <P>There are some other matters on which I should like to get information before this debate concludes.  I have been talking about the proposal of the Minister for Lands&mdash;apparently a nonstarter&mdash;that there should be a merger between his Department and the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries. Recently, we have had a statement by the Minister for Justice with regard to another merger and here again it is necessary that we get some clear-cut information.  We should be told if this is Government policy, to what extent it is Government policy and to what extent consultation is taking place with regard to it.  I am referring to the recent statement made by the Minister for Justice regarding the legal profession. I am quoting now from my own notes of a statement which I think appeared in the <i>Irish Press</i> of 10th November where the Minister for Justice was reported as stating that the Government were considering plans for a unified legal profession which would eliminate the present distinction between solicitors and barristers, empower solicitors to plead before every court in the country and make them eligible for appointment as circuit court judges.  The statement was a lot longer than that.  I have merely given an extract. The first thing which is notable about this is that the Minister referred to plans, not merely proposals for discussion, not merely something which was somewhere near the rim of the horizon.  He referred to plans which were actually being considered by the Government, plans being considered at Government level.</P>
    <P>Surely we are entitled to ask what are those plans?  Who formulated them?  From what source did they spring?  Is it a Ministerial plan brought direct by the Minister to the Government, or is this a plan which was produced somewhere in the Minister's <Col N="147" /> Department?  What consultation has taken place between the Minister or his Department and the two branches of the profession concerned, the Law Society and the Council of the Bar? What consultation or examination has taken place to ascertain the views of members of the public with regard to this plan?</P>
    <P>I accept the Minister's word at its face value, that this is not merely a proposal, but that it is an actual concrete plan.  Surely that is what the Minister's words mean?  Surely it is a plan which is being considered at Government level?  It occurs to me, if the Minister's plan contemplates the complete elimination of the distinction between solicitors and barristers, why does it also make provision that solicitors will be eligible only for appointment to the circuit court bench?</P>
    <P>It seems to me that, if there was to be an elimination of the distinction between the two branches of the profession, it should go right across the board and that a person who has been trained, has practised and qualified as a solicitor should under the Minister's plan be eligible for appointment to the High Court and Supreme Court benches as well.  I should like to know what kind of merger is envisaged by the Minister and the Government when the Minister speaks of a unified legal profession? Again, I am subject to correction in this because I have not got the report before me, but my recollection is that the governing body of the solicitors' profession, the Incorporated Law Society, have not committed themselves as a body in favour of this proposal.  I think it is equally fair to say they have not committed themselves as a body against this proposal.  I think that is probably a reasonable position for it to adopt.</P>
    <P>Individual members of the solicitors' profession will probably have different points of view, but surely they are entitled to be consulted?  Surely they are entitled to know what the plan is? Generally speaking, I should imagine that possibly a majority of the profession to which I belong, the solicitors' profession, might in principle favour the idea of a unified legal profession, <Col N="148" /> possibly on the grounds that many of them would feel that the solicitors' profession have nothing to lose in a proposal of this sort.</P>
    <P>That is one of the matters which would need to be examined, and to my mind it should be examined in joint consultation between the Minister's Department and the solicitors' profession.  The present position, as I see it&mdash;there are other members of the solicitors' profession who are also members of this House&mdash;is that, no matter how remote or how small a solicitor's practice may be, any solicitor's office anywhere in the country can on payment of a reasonably modest fee secure the services, the advice and the opinion of specialists for their clients.  The smallest office is in a position now to provide the same service for their clients so far as legal advice is concerned as the largest solicitor's office in the country.  It has got to be considered and examined and that should be done in consultation with the profession.  I want to make it clear that I am not in the slightest degree opposed to the rationalisation, in so far as it requires to be rationalised, of the legal profession in this country. I am not in the slightest degree opposed to the carrying out of any reforms that may be seen to be necessary in either or both branches of the legal profession.  Rationalisation and reform are all to the good but to my mind the test should be efficiency and the common good, the interest of the clients rather than the interest of individual members of the profession. I do not think anybody will contradict me when I say that the whole tradition of the legal profession in this country has been one of putting the interest of the public&mdash;I am using &ldquo;public&rdquo; in the sense of the client&mdash;first, regarding it as being of paramount importance. I do not think anybody would claim that our present system is perfect but, again, it would be hard to make the case that it has not been adequate because it has been adequate and it has stood the test of time.  It is true that there is in many countries today, particularly in the United States of America and in Canada, complete fusion of the two branches <Col N="149" /> of the profession.  On the other hand, in this country, in England and in South Africa, to mention a few, there is still the distinction.  There are arguments for and arguments against fusion.  I shall not enter into them here but I want to emphasise that the announcement made by the Minister disclosing the fact that the Government are considering a plan is to my mind not good enough unless there is proper consultation and discussion between the Department and the two branches of the profession and the views of the public should also be taken into account.</P>
    <P>I should like to get some information on another matter which affects the legal profession and affects some members of the public also, I hope not too many.  That is the question of free legal aid.  I should like to find out how the free legal aid scheme which became law following the adoption of the Criminal Justice (Legal Aid) Act, 1962 is faring.  I felt at the time that that Act was being enacted by the Dáil and by the Seanad that it had certain limitations.  Those limitations, of course, are still there but the step was worth taking.</P>
    <P>I suppose it took some time for the scheme to be put in order so that it could be operated but it has now been in operation for five or six years.  I should like some information as to how it is working and whether or not there are any proposals to extend it to the civil side.  The House will be aware that under the Act of 1962 free legal aid can be given in certain cases. There are certain conditions which have to be fulfilled before a certificate of free legal aid will be available.  These are that the means of the person charged with an offence are insufficient to enable him to obtain legal aid, that by reason of the gravity of the charge or of exceptional circumstances it is essential, in the interests of justice, that he should have legal aid in preparation or conduct of his defence. Therefore, there are three prerequisites to the grant of free legal aid at the moment&mdash;that the person should have insufficient means, that there should be a grave charge or exceptional circumstances and that it should be essential in the interests of justice that <Col N="150" /> free legal aid be granted.  Those are fairly severe restrictions; I think possibly too severe.  I should have thought that it would be better that our approach to this matter should be that it assisted the ends of justice that free legal aid should be given rather than that the requirement should be that it was essential in the interests of justice before legal and was granted.  However, the scheme has now been in operation for a number of years and I should like to have some information as to how it is working.  I should like to know what is the cost of this scheme and to what extent has it been taken advantage of and how many certificates were granted under it.</P>
    <P>Another matter I should like to raise for the purpose of urging the Government to give it some consideration in the reasonably near future is the question of the Emergency Powers resolutions. The House will be aware that on the 3rd September 1939, more than 30 years ago, a resolution was passed by the Oireachtas declaring a state of national emergency.  The House will also be aware that the effect of the resolution is that the courts cannot declare invalid any Act expressed to be for the purpose of securing the public safety and the preservation of the State so long as that resolution continues in force.  There is a volume of opinion in this country which feels, I think not unreasonably, that after the passage of 30 years a resolution which was passed on the outbreak of the last great war should no longer be allowed to continue in force.</P>
    <P>I do not have here the actual terms of the resolution&mdash;I am speaking from memory&mdash;but I think the resolution was expressed in terms that because of the state of war which then existed between Germany on the one hand and the allies on the other, it was necessary in the interests of public safety and the preservation of the State to pass the resolution.  That was more than 30 years ago.  Surely it is not unreasonable to ask now that the Oireachtas should consider the question of rescinding this resolution?  I think the position is that it requires a motion to rescind both in the Dáil and in the Seanad.  It is clear that without the co-operation of the Government <Col N="151" /> those motions will not be passed.  I would urge on the Government to give favourable consideration to putting down rescinding motions themselves.  If they are not prepared to do that, if they are not prepared to say that they will do it, so far as I am concerned I propose to consider putting down such a motion for consideration by this House so as to enable Senators to give their views as to whether or not it is appropriate after the passage of 30 years or more, after the lapse of many years since the ending of the war which occasioned the passing of the resolution in the first place that the resolution should still remain in force, carrying with it, as it does, the side effect that prevents the courts declaring invalid under our Constitution any Act which might be passed by the Oireachtas and which is expressed to be for the purpose of securing public safety or the preservation of the State.</P>
    <P>Another matter I should like to deal with is the question of the policy publicly pursued in relation to Irish people who have emigrated, and in particular who have emigrated to England.  Our party have adopted and stood by a particular policy of emigrant welfare.  I am aware that some months ago the Government made some announcements which indicated that they were, to some extent at any rate, thinking on the same lines.</P>
    <P>I would suggest the following principles which we might adopt. First, the Irish Government should accept responsibility for assisting in the provision of welfare centres in England.  Secondly, they should be prepared to give financial assistance to existing organisations to expand hostel accommodation and community centres.  Thirdly, it should be agreed that an advisory council be established from the various voluntary organisations in England dealing with emigrant welfare work.  Fourthly, we should actively endeavour to negotiate with the British authorities with a view to seconding to the British probationary services some of our Irish probationary officers.  Finally, some steps should be <Col N="152" /> taken to try to ensure that young people under the age of 18 years do not emigrate to England without their parents' consent.</P>
    <P>For a number of years there have been many excellent voluntary organisations doing particularly good work in England so far as Irish emigrants are concerned.  I do not wish to be controversial or critical about this but they have had to depend entirely on their own efforts to furnish the services they have provided.  As a nation we cannot afford to shelve responsibility for Irishmen who are forced by economic circumstances to emigrate to the neighbouring island.  I am concerned here with what one might call the short-term emigration that takes place between Ireland and England; I am not speaking of persons who emigrate for the sake of adventure, even of persons who emigrate across the Atlantic, because by and large, those persons are able to make adequate arrangements for themselves and their families if they go to Canada or the United States.  The possibility there is that the people concerned have jobs already lined up, but as between this country and England there is the ebb and flow of emigration all the time.  When the economic pinch comes here, and it seems to me it is coming at the moment, people become disemployed; if they want to maintain themselves and their families they are very often forced to go to England to seek employment and we have the tragedy of young people, very often under 18 years, going to England to secure work in an effort to keep the fires burning.</P>
    <P>They are the people with whom I am concerned and I think we should have a Government policy here beamed on those people with the object of keeping in touch with them, encouraging them while they are away and by providing an information service ensuring that they have knowledge of any jobs which might become available. I should like to know the Government's views and policy regarding this question of emigrant welfare in the next few years.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to point out to the Senator that he should be careful to confine his remarks to <Col N="153" /> existing Government policy in practice and not to look so far to the future that he is advocating legislation of a particular type.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course, I accept the Chair's ruling on this point.  In fairness to the Government and to the relevance of my remarks, it should be noted, as I did state, that the Government announced some months ago certain policies in this area which they proposed implementing.  However, I have stated my views on that subject and, to the extent that they are not being actively pursued by the Government at the moment, I can only express the hope that my remarks will not fall on deaf ears.</P>
      <P>I should like also to get some information from the Government as to how they stand at present on the question of the proposed merger between the universities.  It will be remembered that this aspect of the Government's educational policy was announced, and as I recall it there were pronouncements, or a particular pronouncement at any event, by one of the Ministers for Education.  The reason I say one is that I think there have been two or three changes in that Cabinet post since the announcement was originally made. As I recall it, one of the Ministers went so far as to adopt the attitude that there could be no further debate on the question of whether or not the merger was going to take place.  There has been a resounding silence on this topic for some time past.  I do not want to be putting any niggers into the woodpile but I want to know, and we are entitled to know, what is happening.  Again, it seems to me that this aspect of Government policy was one that was announced without what I would regard as the essential consultations taking place between the particular interests concerned, and it does seem to me that there was a very sharp reaction from many in the academic field with regard to the proposal.  I think that it is a matter of general interest and a matter on which we should hear whether or not the proposal is still regarded as a live one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If it is still regarded as a live one what kind of timetable has been established by the Government in connection <Col N="154" /> with it?  And this is the final comment I want to make.  I have expressed the view that the kind of consultation which I would have thought was necessary and desirable before the initial pronouncement was made did not take place in relation to this aspect of policy.  I want to urge very strongly on the Government that even at this stage if the proposal is still regarded as a live and viable one they should ensure that the type of consultation which I regard as absolutely vital should take place, and that the full expression of the views not merely of the students but of the academic staffs in both universities should be allowed to be expressed, and that there should not be any question of ruling out further debate or further discussion on the topic.</P>
    <P>I hope that some information on these matters which I have raised will be given to the House in the course of this debate.  It is not often that this House will have the opportunity of raising matters affecting Government policy and Government administration in a general way such as this.  I know from my own experience previously as a Member of this House and from views that are expressed from time to time or have been expressed from time to time with regard to this House that the feeling is abroad occasionally in any event that this House, as one of the Houses of the Oireachtas, is not treated seriously, and that there are times when members of the public feel that unless this House is treated seriously by the Government there is no point in having a Seanad.  This is one of the occasions when the Government spokesmen will have an opportunity of treating this House seriously and through this House giving their views with regard to the Government administration covered by the Estimates and with regard to those matters of current Government policy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHorgan1977" hpid="Mr. Horgan Mr. Horgan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Horgan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Higgins spoke about our discussion now as if we were at the beginning of a new term, a description which I would certainly endorse as a very new boy in this assembly.  I should like to make one very brief point, if I may, at the beginning, that it is the convention <Col N="155" /> in this particular debate&mdash;indeed, it is more than a convention&mdash;that the affairs of the Government should come under general review.  I propose to do this in a comparatively brief kind of way.  I should like to observe that I do not exempt people from this side of the House, either, from some of the more general remarks I may have to make. I do not wish on this account to give Members of the Government party the impression that they may select the criticisms which they think apply to them and those which they think do not.  I should simply like to make a general remark to the effect that I do not think that people on this side of the House should feel immune from criticism either, certainly so far as they go along with or fail to object to Government policy.</P>
      <P>The first point I should like to make is rather a general one and it comes from the experience I have had both before and in this House on the few days it has been sitting.  I am concerned at what seems to me to be a lack of vision on the part of the Government in the expression of its policies about the future, about the way in which this country is going to set about creating a fully human community.  I think this is very important.  I choose one or two very brief quotations to emphasise, if I may, the wide spread of opinion that touches man and the future.  The Second Vatican Council said: &ldquo;The future of humanity lies in the hands of those who are strong enough to provide coming generations with reasons for living and hoping.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>A gentleman called Lenin said that &ldquo;without a revolutionary theory there can be no revolutionary movement,&rdquo; and another man whose name I do not remember said: &ldquo;Without a vision the people perish.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I see no evidence of this vision in any long-term sense in the kind of planning and legislation that the Government are bringing in at the moment.  I see an unwillingness to face up to the future.  I see a desire, even an almost constant desire, to keep the future at arm's length.  Indeed, in some areas I would almost go so far as to say that there are people who would like to see <Col N="156" /> the future, or a goodly portion of it, behind bars where it could do no harm or damage to anybody.  In the place of this open and positive dynamic attitude to the future we are offered something which I can only describe as the politico of reassurance, the idea that somehow we will muddle through.  I do not think that this is good enough and I do not think that this is the kind of thing that people respond to.</P>
    <P>We are expected also to acquiesce in a kind of tolerance which I think is a very dangerous thing.  We have been describing ourselves as a very tolerant society, and in many ways we are, but the kind of tolerance we are proud of, the tolerance of different opinions making for a genuinely open society&mdash;this kind of tolerance in Ireland is too often qualified by another kind which is not at all as helpful.  This is a passive tolerance, a tolerance of things which are in themselves radically evil because they help or at best do not get in the way of the progress of the country toward some kind of affluence.  This kind of tolerance simply implies that whatever the means, they are justified by the end, whatever produces the end result is worth it.  One of the things we need and one of the things I do not see so much of in the Government is a sense of anger and indignation in the face of injustice.  We need to rediscover these things, to rediscover how right and how holy a thing like anger can be instead of always attempting to justify the <i>status quo.</i></P>
    <P>In these kinds of situations there is a great deal of danger of the Government&mdash;and I am not accusing it of bad faith in this&mdash;falling slowly but inevitably into a kind of conservative authoritarianism with very deleterious effects on the community as a whole. This is something which exists on the side of the Government.</P>
    <P>There is also a tendency in an area for which the Government are directly responsible and which is equally serious.  I am talking about the Public Service.</P>
    <P>Karl Mannheim said that &ldquo;The fundamental tendency of all bureaucratic thought is to turn all problems of politics into problems of administration.&rdquo;<Col N="157" /> I see this happening today in a number of Government Departments. We can see evidence of the attitude that a thing is &ldquo;good for the people &mdash;We know what is good for you&rdquo;&mdash; and the kind of tidiness which can only develop into something rather dangerous. An administrative tidiness is necessary and must be brought about in society, but there are people whose genius for administrative tidiness can, I am afraid, lead them to believe that they ought to extend it to tidying up people's minds.  This is not the kind of attitude which does the public service in this part of the country as a whole any good.</P>
    <P>I see this especially in the Department of Justice; I see it also to some extent in the Department of Education and I am pointing to it simply as a way of saying to the Government that the people are aware of this attitude, that they resent it and that it must not be allowed to develop and that, above all, there is the greatest need for attracting the very best kind of person into the public service to ensure that this kind of thing does not happen.</P>
    <P>The position here is not the same as in Britain where the public service tends to be dominated by a particular class of persons.  Our public service, on the whole, is a very democratically constituted one and this is something for which we should be grateful, but we must be perpetually on our guard against this kind of tendency in the public service.  I ask the various Ministers involved to keep this very much in their thoughts.</P>
    <P>I should like to comment briefly on the Department of External Affairs and, in particular, on the campaign of publicity which was inaugurated following the disturbances in the north. I do not wish to comment on the effectiveness of the campaign as such except to say that I have reasonably good information to the effect that it was not at all as biased or as, if you like, anti-British or anti-north or as propagandist as we have been frequently led to believe.  From my personal knowledge of some of the people involved and from my knowledge of their calibre, it is only what I would expect.  However, there <Col N="158" /> is a much deeper moral to be drawn from this and it goes back to this question of the public service.</P>
    <P>If it is part of Government policy to ensure that news and information about what is happening in this country should be made available in countries other than ours, why have they not made appropriate arrangements within our foreign service as a whole?  As I have said, the particular campaign was not as bad or as black as it had been painted but it showed up the extraordinary lack of foresight and the lack of flexibility of any kind of approach to the problems of the twentieth century which seem to have existed until now in the Department of External Affairs.</P>
    <P>I suppose the functions of the Department abroad could be enumerated briefly as representation, consular activities and, thirdly, though not necessarily, in order of precedence, news and information.  This must be done and I ask the responsible Minister to see that there is a complete change of attitude in his Department and to ensure that this very necessary work be done abroad.</P>
    <P>I shall deal very briefly with the Department of Education.  Education is a subject in which I have a particular interest.  There are one or two brief points about present Government policy and, possibly, future Government policy that I should like to comment on.  We had much discussion recently about the managerial system in primary schools.  There seems to be a kind of conspiracy of silence about this.</P>
    <P>If the Department of Education is happy with the managerial system simply because it is administratively convenient, this is far from being an adequate justification for the absence of any serious inquiry or research into the way it is working and, in the absence of this kind of research, we are faced with all kinds of subjective assessments of it.  I know many people and many primary school managers, Catholic and Protestant, who are deeply involved in the whole education process and who see themselves in a genuine sense as representatives of the parents.  On the other hand, the <Col N="159" /> INTO apparently know many managers of another persuasion entirely.  The lack of public discussion on this issue and how the system is really working may be seriously damaging to the educational prospects of many of our schoolchildren.  I should like to see this debate inaugurated in a much more public way.</P>
    <P>At the secondary level, we have the quite extraordinary position of considerable resistance to the very necessary forms of co-operation which must be brought into action and which, I am glad to say, the Department are trying to bring into action to achieve something like full educational participation by our young children.  I would go so far as to support the Government in what they are doing and I urge them not to be namby-pamby about it.  There is general public feeling that the measures they are introducing are genuinely necessary to ensure adequate educational opportunities for all.</P>
    <P>We have also been told, almost <i>ad nauseam</i>, about the free education system, that is, free post-primary education. I ask the official reporter to put the word &ldquo;free&rdquo; in quotation marks because I find it difficult to convey what I mean phonetically.  This education is not free in any sense of the word, in the sense that the taxpayer is paying for it.  As a taxpayer, I have no objection to paying for it and I will gladly pay more if the Government should consider it necessary, but there is another sense in which it is not free and this is the sense in which schools have entered the scheme for free post-primary education on condition&mdash;it is more or less a self-made condition&mdash;that the various debts which they have, mainly capital debts, will be reduced by the parents themselves in the form of voluntary contributions. From my very brief research, mostly in Dublin, it has become obvious that the nature of these contributions is decreasingly voluntary. One school has gone so far as to threaten to publish a list, not of the parents who have not paid&mdash;that would be rather dangerous&mdash;but of those who have paid.  This shows, in a sense, how inadequate was the original idea <Col N="160" /> of post-primary education although it was an improvement on the previous position.  Another objectionable factor of this is that it transfers from the management of the schools to the parents and to parents committees, the odium of collecting money.  It is not a responsibility that should have been on the managers of the schools in the first place.</P>
    <P>There is a case for a continuing increase in the involvement of the State in the educational process but I am horrified at a development which means that when Irish parents for the first time are being directly involved in the educational process, that it is only by way of asking for money from other parents for sending their children to the same school.</P>
    <P>There is one fundamental question about the free post-primary education scheme which I should like to see being discussed and examined, preferably by the Minister for Education.  The Minister and, indeed, his predecessor, have made considerable play of the increase in the number of children who are now attending secondary schools as a result of this scheme.  I am not going to decry the fact that more children are going to school.  This is marvellous.  A large part of the benefit of the free post-primary scheme came from the degree of public awareness of education which it helped to spread throughout the country.  I do not know if anybody on either side of this House knows, and I would not be surprised if the Minister did not know it, but I should like to know to what extent those new thousands of children who are coming into the post-primary schools are children who would be coming in anyway.</P>
    <P>This is something which is very difficult to evaluate but some kind of an attempt to evaluate it can be made if we look at the school going population in various sociological categories. I tend to suspect that a lot of the new participation in education at post-primary level may be by children whose parents would have sent them there in any case, and that there is a danger even of a new division in our educational system between the children with some kind of educational <Col N="161" /> tradition behind them and children who have little or none.  A recent book by an Irish sociologist, Miss Kathleen Cullen, has indicated that the gap between those two classes of children has if anything widened, that the educational expectations of the children who have no educational tradition behind them&mdash;in the sense that their parents were not particularly well educated&mdash;are not as high, that those children are in fact in a very serious position indeed, and they are the most difficult children in the community to reach.  I should like to know how the Department of Education are planning to reach those children.</P>
    <P>There is one final matter on the question of post-primary education to which I should like to advert.  Even if there is increased participation in post-primary education this does not necessarily mean that things are very much better, because there is a sense in which all that it will ensure is that the upper ranks of society, and especially the growing middle class, will from time to time be given a transfusion of new blood from underneath, which indeed it needs.  The system itself will be basically unaffected and the whole discussion about the social consequences of education and the role of education in the social and political society of the country should be gone into more thoroughly.  On this whole question of participation, its effects on the problems and its effect on the society in which it has taken place, there should be much more research going on in the Department of Education, and especially in the development branch, from which we have seen comparatively little recently.</P>
    <P>I would agree, to move on to another point, with Senator O'Higgins when he spoke about this House itself.  I did some reading recently and discovered that as far back as 1930, just 39 years ago, a Deputy, a member of Mr. de Valera's party, and subsequently a Minister in Mr. de Valera's Government, said that &ldquo;Last year&rdquo;&mdash;it would be 1929&mdash;&ldquo;the Seanad met for only 40 hours and then it was merely to watch the clerk stamping Government Bills and to discuss the advisability of adjournment for tea.&rdquo;  That was 39 <Col N="162" /> years ago.  The more things change, the more they remain the same.  I gathered that last year the Seanad sat for only 33 days.  One is bound to ask whether we are taking the thing seriously at all. Certainly the lack of time available for Private Members' Motions, the lack of consultation with Members who might be described as Independents on the Order of Business and the general air of desuetude which seems to surround the Seanad seems to make people in this country think that it is a symbol of the way in which our parliamentary institutions are slowly seizing up.</P>
    <P>I should not like to see this happen. I should like to see the Seanad meet much more often&mdash;whatever the unfortunate Official Reporters might think &mdash;and I should like to see it devoting much more time to Private Business. As Senator O'Higgins said, basically the only alternative is to abolish it.</P>
    <P>This process of calcification which a lot of people discern in our parliamentary institutions has, I think, been shown up most clearly by the events arising out of the controversy which involved the Radio Telefís Éireann and various members of the Government.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the Senator proceeds further on this line perhaps I might mention that the Dáil have this afternoon decided to set up a commission to investigate this matter and that being so the Senator should not continue further.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHorgan1977" hpid="Mr. Horgan Mr. Horgan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Horgan</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept the ruling of the Chair on this matter.  If I may make a few general remarks about the broadcasting service and leave the matter of &ldquo;Seven Days&rdquo; aside, as it is clearly <i>sub judice</i>, I should like to make two very brief points.  The first is on the concept of impartiality in general, as it is applied by the Authority under the terms of the Broadcasting Act.  We will have to radically revise our concept of impartiality.  At the moment it is a very limited concept indeed and tends to mean, in the way in which it is actually practised, impartiality as between Fianna Fáil, Fine Gael and Labour.  When we say this we ignore the fact that there are divisions in the country other than those between the three major political <Col N="163" /> parties and that a one-sided stress on impartiality in this way can often act to keep out of the public limelight people and issues which are in any way directly counter to the <i>status quo</i> as expressed in the common ground agreed by the three political parties.  If we are to be honest we will have to rework our definition of impartiality beyond the party political system, as we know it at the moment, to the wider area of Irish society as a whole.  In this connection we should be giving much more time on television and radio to issues and even groups to a greater or lesser extent, outside this consensus.</P>
      <P>My second point is a very minor one and refers to the question of schools broadcasting and adult education.  We are frequently told there is not enough money for building this particular school or that particular school or for providing the physical resources which are needed in a decent educational system.  It is well known that broadcasting, and especially radio, is one of the cheapest forms of education, both at the juvenile level and at the level of adult education, which becomes increasingly important in a world which is rapidly changing.  I would commend to the attention of the various Ministers this possibility.  I would also express some concern about reports which I have heard that one of the reasons why there is very little of this kind of broadcasting, especially on radio, is that the Department of Posts and Telegraphs and the Department of Education have been unable to make up their minds as to who should pay for it and who should have control over it.  Difficulties like this should not be allowed to stand in the way of any genuine approach to educational broadcasting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>May I look very briefly at one matter which is connected with the remarks by the Taoiseach and by other speakers in connection with the Constitution.  I shall not attempt to suggest anything concrete on this.  I am sure I would be out of order if I were to do so, but I should like to commend just one or two general criteria to the attention of the Taoiseach as he has stated that this <Col N="164" /> matter is under examination and I take it, therefore, that this is part of Government policy.</P>
    <P>It is frequently said that our Constitution should be revised in terms of rights.  It is sometimes said that we should discuss what are the rights of Irish Catholics and what are the rights of Irish Protestants.  I do not think the Constitution can be revised along those lines, not least because of the absolute impossibility of defining Catholic rights and Protestant rights in any way that would be acceptable to the majority of people.</P>
    <P>It has also been said, with an eye on the north, that we should discuss the revision of the Constitution in terms of the rights of the north and the rights of the south.  I consider this equally unhealthy as a manner of proceeding in this situation, again because of the total impossibility of agreeing on anything remotely like a decent and recognisable picture of the rights involved. The simple thought that I would commend to the Taoiseach and to those members of the Government party who are considering this problem is that if we decide to revise the Constitution we should do so not as Catholics, not as Protestants, not as northerners nor as southerners but basically as Irishmen, because only constitutional revision on these grounds will have the opportunity of attracting any wide measure of support.</P>
    <P>I would draw the Taoiseach's attention to the existence, and indeed the fact that this Government have signed the European Convention on Human Rights.  This is a very different kind of instrument from the United Nations Declaration on Human Rights in that it was intended to be, and in many respects still is, a legislative instrument for countries who have signed it.  I would draw the Taoiseach's attention to this and to its possibilities in terms of constitutional revision.  I feel the only true and sure criteria for constitutional revision is that it should be done not to appease anybody.  Above all, there must be an end to the kind of squalid, bargaining approach which has characterised discussion on this in recent months.</P>
    <P>My final word is to welcome the <Col N="165" /> Taoiseach's action in setting up a commission on the status of women.  I looked up the heading &ldquo;Woman&rdquo; in my copy of the Constitution and found &ldquo;See Family, Sex&rdquo;.  From this subheading alone we can see what a limited view of womanhood and what a very dated view of womanhood finds expression in our Constitution.  I welcome the Taoiseach's proposal to set up this commission and I would urge him very strongly that it should have the widest possible terms of reference, that it should have a majority of women members and that it should be encouraged to report as soon as possible.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Miss Bourke Miss Bourke">
      <NameTxt>Miss Bourke</NameTxt>
      <P>As someone new to the House, like the previous speaker, I should like to comment on some selected areas of Government policy rather than to generalise too much.  Like the previous speaker, I think there is a lack of an overall idea of where the country is attempting to go.  The legislation which is coming before us is very piecemeal and very pragmatic.  I would also agree with him that the Seanad is grossly underused.  In our brief tenure of a couple of months in the Seanad we have met only three or four times.  Any body which meets so infrequently could never contribute to the public opinion of the country or play its part vigorously in that country. One of the reasons the Seanad is not used to the extent to which it might be as a forum for public discussion is because of the tendency in Government policy to make policy decisions without reference to specific bodies; to announce these as a sort of <i>fait accompli</i> and afterwards to refer the working out of these policies to the particular bodies concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On this question I should like to mention a matter which has been referred to by Senator O'Higgins&mdash;the question of the university merger.  This was an area where a statement of Government policy was made without consultation with the bodies concerned, with the idea: &ldquo;There is going to be a merger, let us have your views&rdquo;. Then the two academic institutions in Dublin and other institutions of higher learning in the country got down and tried to work out the detailed implementation <Col N="166" /> of this stated Government policy.  I think this is a reason there has been a failure to carry out this policy because the people concerned were presented with an idea which they were expected to implement in detail, which was not necessarily their own. The forming of the Higher Education Authority is similar to the tactics used by any particular body that is in trouble, which in order to get out of trouble forms a sub-committee.  The formation of the Higher Education Authority was an attempt to dilute the problem, to put it out of the public mind.  I think it has done that; but what many of the people concerned are asking is: What is the Higher Education Authority doing about this?  What sources of information has it?  What links of communication has it with the people who would be required to implement the proposals?  These people are, of course, the staff and students of the universities concerned.</P>
    <P>This is one example of by-passing the proper bodies from which such proposals should come.  A more recent example, which again was just a statement and yet could have the same implications and could have the same resulting failure, was the statement by the Minister for Justice in Galway, following upon references to some good reforms in court practice and procedure, in which he stated that he would favour a merger of the legal professions and that he was considering referring this matter to the Higher Education Authority.  Is the Minister not aware that the two sides of the legal professions concerned are studying the problem, that they understand the problem and that they are not all people with such vested interests that they will not have the long-term ideals both of better education and the provision of an improved administration of justice in mind?  For the Minister to make a statement that he favours a merger of the professions and that this matter would be referred to the Higher Education Authority is to by-pass the particular bodies concerned who in the long-term have to implement those policies.  This type of approach is no compliment to the integrity or the intelligence of the particular professions and only leads to an attitude of wrangling  <Col N="167" /> between the Government body or organisation and the professions, who do not like to be by-passed in this way.</P>
    <P>A better approach would be to begin by consultations with the professions as to what they are doing in regard to reform of their professions and on the proposals which they would themselves see as providing better justice for the country.  In this respect I refer particularly to the subject of legal education. There has been a great deal of study recently by the Incorporated Law Society, the Bar Council and the students on the subject of legal education. Proposals have been made and submitted; and yet the Minister seems to speak in a vacuum and says that the matter is to be referred to the Higher Education Authority.  I deplore this attitude of lack of reference to the particular bodies concerned.</P>
    <P>I should like to speak about the use of the Seanad itself.  In reading back on Reports of the Seanad, particularly prior to 1935, the role it seemed to play then was a role of informing public opinion, of people advocating proposals they would like to see discussed.  One of the areas where this body, as a vocational body and hence a slightly less political body than the Dáil, could play a part is in the area of civil liberties in southern Ireland.  I have been very disappointed at the attitude of the Government. I think Senator Horgan was kind when he noted that constitutional revision is under way.  What seems to have happened is that there was a report of the Committee on the Constitution in 1967, that this report has died, and nothing concrete has happened since then&mdash;a very considerable length of time in view of the urgency of the proposals in that report.  None of these reforms was very radical, the vast majority were fairly easy to implement, and yet the whole matter has been put on the long finger.</P>
    <P>I was disappointed with the attitude of the Taoiseach when he said that, as far as he was concerned, the topical points in the northern controversv&mdash;the special position of the Catholic Church in Ireland and other matters relating to possible religious discrimination <Col N="168" /> existing in this part of the country&mdash; were matters into which the Government did not intend to look immediately, but that they would be looked at in the context of a general reform of the Constitution.  Since this matter of general reform has been postponed indefinitely it will be a substantial time before any concrete proposals in relation to civil liberties are put forward. The Seanad is a place where there could be discussions in this area on a less political plane&mdash;to use Senator Horgan's words &ldquo;More as Irishmen rather than Catholics and Protestants&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>We can look to the example of other countries in this area.  We can look to the fact that we are in an unusual position in relation to our policy of excluding the facility for obtaining a divorce in Ireland by a special provision to that effect in the Constitution. In the Seanad we could advert to the fact that this is possibly the only example in the world where there is a constitutional prohibition on divorce. It is possible that our courts do recognise a divorce granted to domiciliaries of other States, but otherwise there is no recognition of divorce.  The Seanad can play a vital role in anticipating public opinion in the area of divorce; the same may be said of the area relating to the law on contraceptives. There is too much double-thinking on these points; too little willingness to voice points of view which at the moment may be of a minority appeal and may not be acceptable to the majority; but which in the long run, because of the type of world in which we live, because of our closeness to England may inevitably result and must be faced.</P>
    <P>I should like to see the Seanad engaged in that type of activity meeting more frequently, speaking on issues of this nature that are relevant to the young people of this country&mdash;issues which may not necessarily be popular or acceptable in the country but which are aired in a body which is reported in the papers and which does have prestige and importance.  Therefore, I would endorse the views of those who would like to see the Seanad meeting more frequently and performing a more vital and relevant role.  My main criticism to date of Government policy <Col N="169" /> is the lack of prior consultation with the professions or bodies who are going to implement whatever scheme is being proposed, who are by-passed and who are then presented with a <i>fait accompli</i> which must be implemented. This is a denial of the integrity, the intelligence and the independence of these particular professions.  I think that in the long run this attitude could impoverish this country, because we would not continue to have independent academic or professional people left in the country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>In speaking on the Appropriation Bill I am first of all conscious that we are talking about the spending of £363,500,000 for the public services.  It seems to me that this massive expenditure must be regarded as a community investment, and it is very important that this investment should produce value for money in the community.  Value for money in the community is not just a matter for the Government alone or for the individuals involved in the public services. It is a matter in which the whole community can get involved in extracting value from this investment.</P>
      <P>For example, part of this appropriation will go towards the National Gallery. This is an example of fine recent achievement by the Government.  There has been a tremendous advance in display in the National Gallery and in the public services there, but the investment will not represent value for money to the community unless the National Gallery is used to the full by all citizens of the country as they are free to use it.  That is one example of the value for this money we are talking about today which it is open to the public themselves to draw the best from this investment.</P>
      <P>In the same way when we are voting funds for the Post Office, for example, this investment will only be value for money if the individual employees of the Post Office throughout the country act as if they were providing a public service and are seen by the customers on the other side of the counter to be interested in attracting business, and seem to be interested in explaining how these services are used.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It seems to me that we must recognise <Col N="170" /> that all the public servants, those whom we are paying so to speak through this Appropriation Bill, have a part to play in the development of the country, and an extremely important part.  When members are talking critically about these appropriations they must remember that it is not entirely the fault of the Government if some of this money goes astray.  The public who use the services and the public servants are all an essential part of the services in seeing that the community get value for their money.</P>
    <P>Senator Horgan talked about what he saw as a lack of vision for the future from the Government.  I feel myself&mdash;and I would not be a Government supporter if I did not feel this&mdash;that there is some indication of vision in the Government's programmes. I see this vision in the Third Programme for Economic and Social Development, in the Budget, and in the Estimates that we are talking about. The difficulty about these documents and about Budgets is that dull figures are easily cast to one side and, unless somebody begins to talk in the way Senator Horgan has talked, with nice philosophical phrases, nobody is prepared to believe that there is a philosophy in these documents.  I would suggest that anyone reading through the Third Programme for Economic and Social Development will find many ringing phrases in the small print. They will also see many ideas for the future, and see that these ideas are indeed laying down a pattern for future legislation.  There is talk of social objectives, an equitable sharing of economic progress, care of the underprivileged, fostering cultural and artistic values, the preservation and development of our national heritage, the improvement of environment, promoting of community development, and so on.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the Senator quoting from?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quoting from page 16 of the <i>Third Programme for Economic and Social Development.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Progress in these fields is evident from the legislation which is under way or about to get under way.  The overall <Col N="171" /> strategy of the Government&mdash;and again it is unfortunate that the word should be &ldquo;strategy&rdquo; rather than &ldquo;vision&rdquo;&mdash;must be its concern to do a job, as distinct from talking about doing the job, a strategy of social development based on economic development.  I should like to stress this point that, unless first and foremost we see continued and growing economic development in this community, none of the fine ideas which are likely to be lofted through this chamber during this debate is likely to be seen in action.</P>
    <P>Again I would stress that economic development itself is a community mission as much as a Government responsibility.  If I could quote from the review of the Third Programme by Professor Kaim-Caudle in the summer 1969 issue of <i>Administration:</i>&mdash;</P>
    <P>If the Irish people were more nationalistic in the sense of being willing to accept a lower standard of living at home than they could enjoy abroad, it would not merely be possible more rapidly to raise the level of social services, but the rate of economic progress as a whole could be very much faster.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>This is the nub of the matter and it is the job of the Government to draw out this national spirit of the community.</P>
    <P>It has been mentioned that we are talking at the start of a new term.  I hope that we will see in the remainder of this term the drawing out of this national spirit which will lead to continued economic development on which social development can be based.  This type of leadership, of creating a national spirit, is one which depends very much on the climate of opinion in the country.</P>
    <P>There has already been substantial reference to the role of the communications media in the country, and I should like to refer to one area of communication which comes directly under the Government's ken and which appears in the Schedule to this Bill. That is, of course, the Government Information Bureau.  We find in the Estimates&mdash;and I am speaking from memory now&mdash;that the appropriation for the Government Information <Col N="172" /> Bureau is almost doubled this year and the staff has also almost been doubled. This is quite apart from the special additions to the Government Information Bureau which were made at the time of the crisis in the north of the country which will be the subject of a supplementary estimate later in the year.  I would suggest that this increased expenditure on the Government Information Bureau is fully justified, and I would like to urge, indeed, that the Government Information Bureau be even further expanded.  Even at the time of the northern crisis when we saw that there was a need for greater resources those greater resources could well have been aimed entirely at our own people here at home, because it is vital, if the Government are to provide leadership, that news of Government plans and Government views on the situation should be constantly accessible to the Press.  I understand that many journalists have problems in getting information speedily from the Government Information Bureau and that there are other difficulties at times about getting firm answers to questions and so on.  If we had an effective Government Information Bureau it would help to get across to the people news of Government plans and Government progress.  This would help to create the proper climate which I am talking about, the climate of leadership towards economic development.  It would also be a service which could be availed of to a much larger extent by people like ourselves, public representatives, who often find that it takes that little bit too long to get information from a Government Department when one would like to have it immediately for a debate or for a continuing discussion.  That is one suggestion that I would make which might help to create a better climate of understanding for the Government as leader in the community.</P>
    <P>If I could give examples of other areas in which this applies, productivity is one of these.  Again it is so easy for us to say that if we are to have economic development all we need is increased productivity.  But the Government cannot bring about increased productivity.  All they can do is to try to provide an environment in which <Col N="173" /> employers and employees will appreciate the goodwill of the Government in seeking increased productivity and will join in the effort to increase productivity as being, in the long term, nationally good.</P>
    <P>We see in the Estimates this year one effort by the Government to increase productivity.  This is National Productivity Year.  From memory, again, I think that the expenditure on this MOVE operation has been about £90,000.</P>
    <P>I think that nobody would claim that this National Productivity Year had been a very great success.  It has been a fine public relations idea and it was on the right lines, but I am arguing that it was a pity that it came in the year of a general election and that the Government consequently found it very difficult to get across the idea that this was a national promotion and an urgent national requirement.  I am sure that the seminars which have been held to discuss various aspects of productivity throughout the country have been very useful but I do not think that the idea of overall increased national productivity, which is such a high priority, got across to the community at large.</P>
    <P>This type of public relations idea must be very finely balanced.  It would be easy for Government Departments to think that public relations was all and that the job was not so important. I am talking a lot about public relations but it is no substitute for real achievement.</P>
    <P>In the industrial relations field, for example, there is quite a bit that the Government can do in providing leadership, but once the Government have indicated what they see as the lines to be followed it is an entirely free matter for employers and employees to sort out their differences.</P>
    <P>We have all had these statements from the ESB which say that for reasons publicly announced, electricity bills are delayed and inviting us to make a payment in line with the normal payment, including hire purchase instalments, if any.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think this is a matter of Government administration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="174" />
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to me to be a matter of Government administration in that we accept that the Government have some responsibility for leadership in matters of industrial relations.  The ESB is a semi-State body which comes under the aegis of the Department of Transport and Power and in voting funds to the Minister for Transport and Power I should like to underline his responsibility in this sort of thing. There is a problem to be solved and I urge him to make certain recommendations to the board for the solution of the problem.  My point is that there is no shortage of advice available to the ESB in this matter.  They have had the benefits of the commission of inquiry of 1961; they have had the benefits of the interim report from the Committee on Industrial Relations in the ESB, July, 1968, and they have the final report of the committee of April, 1969. I should like to make two quotations from that final report.  The first is that:</P>
      <P>The country has a right to ask of the ESB that its administration in industrial relations and personal matters shall be recognised by professionals in that field, as surpassing normal industrial standards to the degree needed to ensure that breakdowns such as might be tolerable in other industries are avoided.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not wish to interrupt the Senator but there are no moneys for the ESB in this Bill.  Therefore, I suggest that he should not go into any detail on this matter but refer to it in passing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>As I understand it, under the Appropriation Bill we are including certain expenditure for the Minister for Transport and Power and I expect and hope some of that money will be spent on negotiations between the Minister and the ESB.  In the interests of the economy generally we cannot tolerate lengthy trade disputes in a State-sponsored body like the ESB. However, I will bow to your ruling, a Chathaoirleach, and move on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As a newcomer, the Chair will appreciate I am in some difficulty in these matters.  I have looked up what was said on previous Appropriation debates and I have listened to the other <Col N="175" /> contributions but it is very difficult for me to decide what is relevant and what is not.  I will endeavour to explain my relevance, if pressed, on each occasion that it might be challenged.</P>
    <P>I have talked about the role of the Government in industrial relations and about the dependence of the Government on co-operation from employer and employee.</P>
    <P>Another area in which I am interested, and which is a similar type of area, is the National Savings Committee. There is a slight increase this year in the appropriation for the National Savings Committe.  As we are at a stage where we would all like to see increased savings to make possible the further development of the economy, a small adjustment in the grant to the National Savings Committee may not be sufficient at this stage.  When the Government are viewing the development of the economy, it is extremely important that as far as possible trends should be anticipated and that when there is an agency in existence, like the National Savings Committee and when it looks as if money will be tight and that savings should be encouraged, the first thought of the Government should be of the agency who have some responsibility in this role.  There should be signs of immediate and substantial action to prepare for the future trends.</P>
    <P>I may say that I have a vested interest in this, being a member of the National Savings Committee but it is a legitimate point to make.  The National Savings Committee are keen to play a role; they make recommendations from time to time and they could play a very real part at a time when there is such a need for greater saving.</P>
    <P>Another agency which aims to galvanise public interest and support in the same way in another area is the Buy-Irish campaign.  I see that it also has got an increased grant this year but it is a pity that as we approach the Christmas season there is such a remarkable lack of evidence of action and attention by the Buy Irish campaign. The shops seem to be filled with foreign goods.  In this season we should be particularly conscious of the contribution <Col N="176" /> which home industry could make to the national economy and I should like to get in another commercial and urge everyone to buy Irish for Christmas in this spirit of self-help towards national development which I hope will be talked about on both sides of the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>And save at the same time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly, if we can save at the same time, so much the better.</P>
      <P>While I am talking about public relations, some of what I have to say may sound a bit gimmicky, but we must not concentrate all the time on public relations and forget about the real action.  Now that we are entering European Conservation Year, we are entering a year in which there is a great danger that public relations could be all and we would forget about the real action.  It seems to me the public are already sold on conservation and I do not think there is any problem about this.  It is an idea which has got across to the country at large.  The real need is for action as regards conservation.</P>
      <P>I should like to pose a question arising from my look through the Book of Estimates.  Are we well looked after as regard conservation in this country?  It seems to me we are not as well looked after as we might be. There is a need for rationalisation and an avoidance of overlapping responsibilities where conservation is concerned. I would support the view of the Devlin Commission and the committee which produced the national heritage report for An Foras Forbartha that there is a clear need for a body with a primary responsibility for conservation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>To take, for example, the present controversy over Hume Street&mdash;and I want to say that I made my views on this situation known to the Minister for Finance so I am not speaking out of turn.  Whose concern is Hume Street? A number of bodies have an interest in it.  The corporation, the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance and the Department of Local Government have an interest in it. When we had the recent conservation congress in Brussels we saw that two Parliamentary Secretaries, the Parliamentary <Col N="177" /> Secretary to the Minister for Finance and the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government, were present at it.  It seems to me there is room for rationalisation here and for a body whose primary interest would be conservation.</P>
    <P>It seems to me that in the voluntary conservation bodies there is a very real spirit of goodwill and national interest and this interest is a constructive one.  You will always have the wild men who are keen to picket and make noises but every organisation, including political organisations, have wild men of this type and one must at times forget about those wild men and realise that in those volunary conservation bodies there are a lot of hard-headed, creative people basically interested in the good of the community. I would urge on the Ministers concerned, even if at times the fringe activities of some of those bodies appear to get out of hands, for heaven's sake not to break off civilised communications with those bodies because I believe they are voluntary bodies which have something to contribute to the country.  The nation has everything to gain through continuing to tap the efforts of these volunteers.  I believe the decision on the canal sewage scheme and the decision on the new Central Bank building are decisions which will help to win the general support and sympathy of those voluntary bodies.</P>
    <P>I should like to make a point in regard to conservation that we have a tendency when starting something new to think that before we do anything we must start researching and so on and we must get together more and more information before we do anything.  I should like to stress the urgency of the conservation problem and particularly the urgent need for action on water pollution.  If we have another dry summer next year we will have another Blackwater situation. The problem is as urgent as that.  I would like to quote from the leader in <i>The Guardian</i> of November 21st which referred to something Lord Kennet said.  <i>The Guardian</i> stated:</P>
    <P>In other words there are no scientific mysteries to be unravelled in order <Col N="178" /> to cleanse our surroundings.  A better environment is a matter of will and it is useful to have had that so ambiguously stated by a Member of the Government.</P>
    <P>I think the point is quite clear, though the reference there is, of course, to the British Government.  The scientific information is available where conservation is concerned.  The immediate need is for financial investment to tackle the urgent needs of conservation.</P>
    <P>Again, on a general theme, which I hope is not getting too obscure as I move on.  I am trying to stress the need for Government foresight, for coordinated effort and elimination of overlapping, and I urge the Government to constantly keep in mind these considerations.</P>
    <P>I would sympathise with, I think, Senator Horgan when he looked for speed, action, initiative, and so on.  The Government, and, indeed, the Fianna Fáil Party, in this respect are often their worst enemies.  They have plenty of ideas and they have plenty of action in hand but they rarely talk about it in an enthusiastic way and relate it to the general spirit of national advancement. Let us try, in showing initiative ourselves, to bring out the best in our public servants about whom we are talking when we discuss this Appropriation Bill.</P>
    <P>I would urge the Government to give serious and urgent consideration to the report of the Devlin Commission and not rely on the civil servants themselves for views on this report.  It seems to me the Devlin Report provides a framework for real worthwhile Civil Service initiative.  I should like to see that report adopted on a very wide scale. Since this Seanad began meeting it has often been referred to also that there is urgent need to change the system of audit in local government which, as it stands at present, holds back initiative in the local government service.</P>
    <P>In this spirit of initiative and trying to build up, if I can, some feeling of enthusiasm, some feeling of vision for the work of the Government, I should like to remind this House of some of the work in progress at the present time.  We have the Devlin Report <Col N="179" /> before us.  We know there is a white paper to appear shortly on the structure of local government.  We have the Buchanan Report and in the <i>Third Programme for Economic and Social Development</i> we have reference to a complete review of the income tax structure.  We have the commission on women which has been referred to and we have a commission sitting to examine the state of affairs in our reformatories and industrial schools. We have a recent report on the agricultural advisory service.  We have hoards and hoards of documents and reports but none of the documents and reports will be worthwhile unless we see urgent Government action on those reports and unless we see the Government advance on a wide front preaching the message of national development and new thinking in all these areas.</P>
    <P>Goodness knows some of these areas are crying out for attention, particularly the reformatories and industrial schools.  It is a pity we have to wait for a report to decide what is the best way to deal with them.  In the same way, in the survey of the income tax structure there has been much talk recently of the urgent need for a change in the allowances for married women who are working.  I would certainly support that thinking at the present time.</P>
    <P>All this is there as work in hand or work about to be put in hand and I would hope that it would not be left there so that Members on the other side of the House and the public in four years time will come back and say: &ldquo;It was just work in hand.&rdquo;  I would hope that in four years time it will be a job well done and on a massive scale.</P>
    <P>There has been reference by two speakers from the other side to the context in which we must consider constitutional reform and other matters. I should like to stress that when the Government are considering legislation or the Constitution it would be a well worthwhile exercise to look at these matters as if they were matters occurring in a 32 County context and see how they would stand up in that situation. I consider that there is quite a lot to be said for a complete review of the Constitution rather than piecemeal <Col N="180" /> amendment of the Constitution.  I would also suggest that there is a need for legislation to permit birth control and information on birth control.</P>
    <P>We often hear criticism of the Fianna Fáil Party that they never consult people or keep in touch with the community but I was extremely encouraged that in Dún Laoghaire the other day there was a big gathering of members of the Fianna Fáil organisation to consider suggestions on policy which they would put forward in terms of resolutions at the annual Ard-Fheis.</P>
    <P>One resolution which was passed was that legislation prohibiting access to information and means of birth control be repealed.  That was not an assembly of long-haired youths and bearded anarchists.  It was an assembly genuinely representative of the whole community in that area.  This is an example of how much progressive thought there is at large in the community which the Government have only to tap and encourage to create the sort of society which I think they want to see in the 32 Counties.</P>
    <P>When I speak of the Constitution and contraception the Cathaoirleach may raise his eyebrows but in regard to the next matter I want to speak about he would find it hard to raise his eyebrows because it is in the Estimates. This is the sum made available to the Adoption Board.  This sum at the moment is not nearly large enough and there is need for great reform in the area of adoption law.  It should certainly be made possible for persons of mixed religions to adopt a child and legislation on this should be brought in. There should also be funds available to provide social workers to carry out proper visits to homes where children have been adopted.  This is a point I shall be returning to again in this House&mdash;the need for professional social workers in every aspect of our social services.  I am just mentioning it in connection with adoption.</P>
    <P>I hope by now that some of my concern for quality of life has been appearing in these rather rambling remarks.  May I continue to suggest a few more areas of activity which I consider could contribute to quality of life in the community?  Part of this <Col N="181" /> appropriation arises from the announcement of the Minister for Finance that £100,000 would be made available to young people this year for recreation and other purposes. At the time I wrote to the Minister for Finance suggesting that this money could appropriately be used to set up a national Youth Volunteer Corps.  Again, I would recommend this idea to the Minister because a corps of volunteers available for projects both at home and overseas would create a genuine interest in community development and would be of value to those young people and to the nation and would be something which, as a direct result of Government action and initiative, would help to raise the quality of life in the community.</P>
    <P>When there is talk of the activities of the Department of External Affairs emphasis is usually put on topical matters such as the Biafran situation and the situation in Vietnam.  I should like to underline another two areas falling under the Department of External Affairs which I consider worthy of attention and of our continuing interest regardless of whether the spotlight of the world is on them or not. One is our contribution to the freedom from hunger campaign.  The long-term effects of the freedom from hunger campaign are far more important than any brush-fire-war in any part of the world.  The hope of the world lies in the freedom from hunger campaign. I am proud that in the Third Programme for Economic and Social Development the Government state that one of their aims is to make larger and larger contributions to the poorer countries overseas from our increasing national wealth.</P>
    <P>The other matter under External Affairs to which I should like to refer is the question of disarmament.  There was a day when it was very fashionable to talk about CND, about marches to and from Aldermaston, and so on. It is tragic that this seems to be forgotten about now, because I still feel the greatest danger to the world could well be from nuclear annihilation, whether by accident or by war.  I think this Government has a tremendous record in pushing disarmament resolutions <Col N="182" /> at the United Nations.  It is a record which tends to be underplayed, to be swept to one side, because it is dull.  Even in the present negotiations between the Americans and the Russians at Helsinki there is nothing very glamorous about them, they do not hit the headlines.  However, they are extremely important and this Government must constantly keep up their crusade for world disarmament, for nuclear disarmament and for nuclear limitation in particular.</P>
    <P>I fear when I see Senators looking at their watches I am boring them but I should like to continue for a little longer.  However, as I am a newcomer here I do not know whether or not we should suspend business now and resume later?</P>
    <P>
      <i>Business suspended at 6 p.m. and resumed at 7.30 p.m.</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>In contributing to the debate earlier my aim was to continue with the start of term theme which has been common to all the speakers in this debate, and in particular I was talking about the role of Government in providing dynamic leadership for the community, stressing that the success of this leadership required a constructive contribution from all sections of the community.  I tried to indicate that the goals and aims of the Government had been laid out in the Third Programme, in the Budget, and in the Estimates, and indeed it is my view that it was on these goals and aims that the Government were returned to office.  I was also anxious to point out that at this time, as perhaps never before, the Government have in their hands basic information, reports, the results of studies and research on many aspects of the economic, social and agricultural life of this community, and that, with so much information before them, now is the time, at the start of a new session, for the Government to initiate a programme which will change the country even more than their work in the preceding years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In talking about these things my intention was not to talk about them in a party propagandistic way, and if I gave that impression slightly in some <Col N="183" /> of the things I had to say about the Government Information Bureau, for example, I should like to withdraw that inflection in what I have to say, in that I had not anticipated contributing to the debate at quite such an early stage and my inflections may not have been all I would like them to have been.</P>
    <P>The spirit of my approach, I had hoped, would be that all these&mdash;and it is an old-fashioned term now&mdash;are matters which would be considered part of a patriotic approach, if you like, to the problem before us.  I think that this is the issue in our time&mdash;that there is nothing romantic about real patriotism, but it is a matter of increased productivity and hard work and more effort all round.  I tried to take examples from areas of Government in which I felt that community participation was important or where voluntary bodies had a role to play, or in areas where there were matters of attitude or communication which had considerable importance.</P>
    <P>At the adjournment I was about to move on to the topic of education.  Education is, of course, an area in which community involvement and matters of attitude and communication are of vital importance.  I welcome particularly the favourable noises that have been heard both from Government sources and from sources like the Hierarchy regarding the development of parent-teacher relations&mdash;parent-teacher associations and groups&mdash;particularly in primary schools.  This is a very welcome development and it should have considerable effect on our educational system.  I urge the Minister for Education to give all the impetus he can to this development.</P>
    <P>In education, we have had a period of very great development.  Education has been the topic on which all politicians have picked.  It is the subject that has constantly made the headlines.  I suggest that we have now reached a peak and that, perhaps, this is the time for consolidation, the time for looking around to see where these advancements and developments have brought us so that we can stabilise the position before moving on.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="184" /> There have been many developments in primary education.  We have had the new curriculum, the closing down of scattered schools and the amalgamation of schools and so on. The free transport scheme has also made its impact, particularly in post-primary education.  All these developments have had their teething troubles and it must be extremely frustrating for the Minister for Education to find these teething troubles being stressed constantly in view of what has been achieved and in view of the transformation that these changes have brought about in many parts of the country. At this stage, the Minister would be quite entitled to rest on his oars and try to tidy up the defects and not, as many speakers would have him do, go seeking after new horizons.  This is a time for reflection and consolidation.</P>
    <P>Senator Horgan talked about the possible impact and use at all levels of education of radio and television.  It is easy to say this.  We would all like to see this come about but the problem is that we still have schools where there may not be electricity and where they may not have a radio or a television set.  There are many schools where it is still difficult for the teacher to use even a tape recorder, over which he would have direct control and could therefore get a much better pupil reaction than by something more remote such as radio or television.  It is the responsibility of the Government to be sensible and calm and to consider the practicalities and to get down to dealing with these little points of detail in tidying up these matters before trying to make another great advance.</P>
    <P>On higher education, for example, we have had this staggering report from the Higher Education Authority suggesting that £24 million are needed in the next six years.  It is very difficult to know where £24 million can possibly come from.  There are a number of urgent matters and these urgent matters will have to have attention.</P>
    <P>I would suggest a time for consolidation and reflection to see how we can get the best from money invested in higher education.  I suggest that the policy of the Government on this will have to be that technical and scientific <Col N="185" /> education can be of most use to the developing economy at this stage.  For instance, it is difficult to understand how a continuing vast increase in the number of Arts graduates could be justified.  Perhaps the need and yearning for this type of literary and cultural education could be met by adult education and I am sure that many others are waiting, like myself, for the report of the special committee on adult education which was set up by the Minister.</P>
    <P>There are two other things with which I am very concerned and which I would suggest should be kept constantly in view.  One is the continuing training of careers guidance teachers for our schools, to work in conjunction with the developing new placement service in the Department of Labour.  If we have a full guidance structure available to school pupils right up to the time they enter employment, this is one of the best ways in which we can get full value from our investment in education.</P>
    <P>As soon as one talks in these terms he is accused of ignoring the value of art for art's sake, so to speak, and education for its own sake.  It is difficult to attain the balance but it is the responsibility of the Government to strike the balance and I have great confidence that they will try to do so.</P>
    <P>With reference to the university merger to which Senators O'Higgins, Horgan and Bourke referred, their common plea seems to be for greater consultation and dialogue before any moves are made regarding the merger issue.  It seems to me, on reading the report of the Commission on Higher Education, that the very reason why the late Deputy Donogh O'Malley launched this merger idea was because it was quite obvious that there was no communication between Trinity College, Dublin and University College, Dublin.  This would appear to be so from the commission's account of the evidence, as I understood it, and particularly the attitude of Dr. Tierney at the time.  The commission felt they could not do anything about this and Mr. O'Malley seemed to say that he would try to do something about the situation.</P>
    <Col N="186" />
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>The commission recommended against the merger.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>I am suggesting that from the evidence one of the main reasons for recommending against it was that they did not have the courage to deal with this gap in communications between UCD and TCD.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank God we have a sensible Trinity man here at last.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>That was my reaction to that particular passage of the report of the Commission on Higher Education. I suggest that there is every opportunity for developing dialogue between UCD and TCD and, as this dialogue develops and increases, it will be another factor in the continuing situation as long as the merger remains under discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>UCD and TCD have worked very closely together in resisting it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>If this is the reaction it is unfortunate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not mind Senator Sheehy Skeffington.  Nobody pays any attention to what he says.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I dissociate myself from that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>I pay some attention to his views and I am happy to spar with him and derive value from that sparring.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Senator, but not the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator's gratitude is one thing I never expect or desire.  If I did I would examine my conscience.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has not much to examine if he does not mind my saying so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Keery on the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>A reference, which I think was relevant to the Bill, was made by Senator O'Higgins regarding <Col N="187" /> the proposals of the Minister for Justice&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Plans.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;to merge the professions of solicitors and barristers.  If I may refer back again to the points made by Senators Horgan and Bourke, when they were calling for consultation at all times.  Senator Horgan is shaking his head so, in her absence, I will blame Senator Bourke.</P>
      <P>The Government have plans to make a move which will affect this particular area of the community.  Both speakers stressed the need for leadership and vision at this time.  It seems to me that there are many occasions on which it is very difficult to decide how to have both consultation and leadership.  I feel it is most desirable in many ways to bring together the professions of the bar and solicitor just as I feel in many ways it is desirable to bring together University College, Dublin, and Trinity College.  However, as long as the process of consultation continues, and as long as you leave it to the lawyers and academics to settle it themselves, you will not get any result whatever.  It is the position of the Government to provide some leadership.</P>
      <P>Earlier I referred to this matter when talking about the Devlin Report. There is no future in this report if decisions are left to the civil servants whom it affects most.  Of course, they have to be consulted but the Government must lead at all times.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the merger between Lands and Agriculture? Who is leading on that, the Minister for Justice or the Minister for Lands?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>At least the consultations seem to be going on at a high level and I hope the leadership will emerge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A Senator A Senator">
      <NameTxt>A Senator</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is not very edifying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>Some Senator referred to edification.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should ignore interruptions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="188" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. O'Higgins Mr. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>They are helpful sometimes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>This interruption is related to the next point I want to make In talking about leadership and the role of the Government, it seems to me the image of the Government is extremely important.  It is important that the Government should have the confidence of the people and be seen to have the confidence of the people. I hope they will have this confidence in the term of office which lies ahead. Many of the difficulties which have arisen affect not only confidence in the Government but the whole attitude towards politics in the country and this has arisen through disputes between politicians and journalists and the Government and RTE.</P>
      <P>I take the point, a Chathaoirleach, that a commission has been established to look into a particular situation and that matter is <i>sub judice.</i></P>
      <P>I should like to suggest that matters of this kind arise through misunderstanding between politicians and journalists. Lest what I have to say be construed as another attack from this side of the House on journalists, let me say that I am happy to have been a member of the National Union of Journalists at one stage.  It seems to me, particularly here in Ireland, that many of our journalists are sadly equipped to deal with matters of government and politics.  It seems to me that the provincial press does not provide a very good training ground for journalists and yet they move from the provincial press straight on to the national papers in Dublin.  In the same way the graduates of our universities tend to go straight into journalism and they have no experience or training beforehand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The training schemes for journalists in this country are very inadequate. The opportunities for studying the working of government procedure and the working of all government Departments and following up things in any critical way are limited.  I would suggest there is room here for more competition between our newspapers and if each did not tend to carry the same story.  If they acted in a much <Col N="189" /> more crusading manner, we would find the points which cause controversy were not proved or justified when followed up in the same manner as the newspapers in our neighbouring country follow matters up in depth.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A Senator A Senator">
      <NameTxt>A Senator</NameTxt>
      <P>They told us they are phoney.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been talking about the understanding of journalists and the understanding of politicians by journalists.  Politicians must equally well understand journalists and not be at all surprised by cheque book techniques when they appear.  Often the truth can be produced by journalists even though money may change hands at some stage of the matter and that expenditure is quite justified if it brings about&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no expenditure here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>I am about to make a suggestion that some of the funds voted under this Appropriation Bill might well go in the year 1969-70 towards the foundation of a Press Council in this country.  If we had a Press Council which was available to everybody, and for consultations with editors and journalists, this would make a valuable contribution to better relations between the Government and journalists and be a real contribution to the image of politics and the Government generally.</P>
      <P>Another point I would like to suggest would be the setting up in office of an ombudsman.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That would involve legislation and legislation may not be advocated on this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NevilleKeery" hpid="Mr. Keery Mr. Keery">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keery</NameTxt>
      <P>I bow to your ruling, having made that point.  I believe what is relevant to the Bill, as I tried to make clear at the outset, is that expenditure under this Bill will only be of value to the community when the whole community can participate in the profit.  If there was an office of ombudsman to investigate matters of apparent administrative abuse this would help to raise the whole climate <Col N="190" /> of confidence and encourage community participation under this Bill.</P>
      <P>I should like to conclude on a point made by a number of other speakers on the other side of the House who have spoken by saying that if this Seanad can make its contribution to greater productivity during the year and adopt a real constructive patriotic approach to problems and discussions as they arise through the year it will prove to be a really worthwhile session.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDunne" hpid="Mr. Dunne Mr. Dunne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dunne</NameTxt>
      <P>I was told today that in speaking on the Appropriation Bill almost any subject could be discussed. I wish I had known that as I would have spent most of the night preparing a fairly extensive paper.  There are, however, some points I should like to make which, perhaps, apply more to my field as a trade unionist.  I do not know whether I am speaking here on behalf of the Labour Party or the Irish Congress of Trade Unions but I take refuge in the fact that I am a trade unionist.</P>
      <P>I should like to refer, if I may, to the present economic position and to the utterances we have had from the Minister for Finance and, indeed, from the Taoiseach.  With the greatest respect to both the Taoiseach and the Minister, however well framed those exhortations may be, the people I represent regard them as being exhortations to tighten their belts.  Before the working class people tighten their belts there must be clear-cut evidence that similar sacrifices are being made  all levels of the economy and by all sections.  I am afraid there is no great evidence of that in the present situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We are aware that profits and in some cases great profits are being made by industrial concerns.  It must be made plain also that there can be no trade union interference with the present and developing round of wage and salary increases.  That is not to say that the trade unions intend to be irresponsible. It is merely to say that they are being responsible to their own members and, after all, the first duty of trade unions and similar organisations is to better the lot of their members, particularly in a situation in which those members <Col N="191" /> are finding it increasingly difficult to keep to a normal standard of living. I have said and the Minister has been made perfectly aware of it that if we could be satisfied that restraint was needed and restraint would be practised by all the people in the community this would be done but we must have clear cut evidence of this.  Perhaps, it is unfortunate but it is a fact that these appeals are made at periods and it always seems to us that they are directed only towards the working class people.  However regrettable it may be to some people these appeals are bound always to fail or at least fail to be wholly effective.</P>
    <P>I would suggest to the Minister for Finance that it is an essential task of the Government to devise and seek to have implemented a prices and incomes policy rather than embark on courses and procedures which are not acceptable to the trade union movement and to the people it represents. Here is a course which has been asked for by the trade union movement.  They have made it quite clear that they are prepared to co-operate in any fair system even if that system involves control of workers incomes but only when the same or similar controls apply to all forms of income.  In other words, we will not acquiesce in a situation in which only the working class people are asked to make these sacrifices.</P>
    <P>The Government would be well advised also to examine the whole economic system under which this country operates.  I am no economist but it has always seemed to me that, among other things, we took over from England, when we formed our own State, their system of capitalism and after initial shudders and shocks by the people who owned the capital in this country they remained.  We are still a young nation, a small nation but we have many advantages because of this.  We are relatively free from the many divisions which affect and inhibit other countries.  I believe it is possible even yet and perhaps, with growing urgency for this country to embark upon a policy of social experimentation. There is much talk today about the <Col N="192" /> high incidence of trade disputes in our country.  Many experts, so-called and otherwise, offer many reasons and cures for this situation.  There are many contributory factors in this situation not the least of which are insufficient wages, insecure employment, the absence of correct procedures or the presence of wrong procedures, but in all the examinations made of the faults and ills of our system of industrial relations, perhaps, the greatest single factor and cause of our trouble&mdash;it is very seldom if ever adverted to&mdash;may be the very system under which we operate. We see the experiences of other countries which operate similar systems. They are subject to the same stresses and strains as we are here.  These are present everywhere that the system is similar to ours.  Many people refer us to continental examples with particular reference to the number of trade disputes.  This is a very unfair comparison because it ends there.  It does not go on to compare the disparity in the wages paid in those countries and the wages paid here and the social benefits and the security of employment, the great extent of superannuation schemes and other benefits of that kind.  All these are conveniently overlooked. I do not think it is fair to take just this one, however important it may be, relatively narrow sector of industrial relations and compare us unfavourably with other countries.</P>
    <P>I will return to my thesis on social experimentation.  If I may introduce a personal note, when I entered trade unionism 20 years ago I entered in the hope that I would be able to make some contribution towards industrial peace.  To that extent, and in the eyes of some, I was a conservative.  I have slowly and very reluctantly come to the very strong view that we will never put things right here under our present economic circumstances.  We will never change men however much on occasion we might like to do so but we must change the system and structure under which they operate because they are the cause of the trouble not the men.</P>
    <P>I repeat it is a tragedy, and may become an even greater one, if we persist in our present way of doing things without taking sufficient cognisance of <Col N="193" /> what is happening.  Last year it seemed at one stage that a great national debate on industrial democracy was gaining momentum but for some reason it seems to have died.  It may well be it was a pity this concept was seized hold of by political parties; it would not be the first thing political parties took hold of and caused its death but it should not be allowed to die.  We are fortunate in this country in that we have a large area of public ownership of industry; industries officered and manned by our own people; they are the property of all the people. Why should they be merely pale shadows or reflections of similar institutions across the water&mdash;either across the channel or the Atlantic? Have we no room, or readymade fabric as it were, for this adventure in social living and work?  Can we not see how far the concept of industrial democracy may be operated in those particular concerns?  If we are concerned at the large number of strikes in our country we should be even more alarmed that they are a particular feature of industries which we own ourselves or at least are supposed to own.  Just as in another direction we try to put responsibility on management, here in the field of publicly-owned industries the responsibility is ours.</P>
    <P>For this reason I should like to refer to the report of the Commission of inquiry into Industrial Relations in the ESB commissioned by the Minister for Labour.  Among other things&mdash;most of which were desirable&mdash;that report recommended two alternative forms of board structure, both of which would be designed to give representation to the workers in the ESB.  So far as I am aware, though it is many months since the report was issued, no steps have been taken by the Government or the ESB itself to seek to implement those recommendations and yet we have strikes and the threat of more strikes in the ESB.  What is the point of instituting those commissions?  I would be loath to believe they are elected just to meet the clamour of a particular day.  If that were so it would be an insult to the intelligence of those who formed those commissions and committees. In this connection I sincerely <Col N="194" /> hope much more attention will be given to that particular report than apparently has been given to date. Here in this very important sector of industry we could take, perhaps, the first steps towards achieving that degree of worker participation which is so essential if we are to achieve industrial peace in this country.</P>
    <P>There are many who wonder at the unrest of workers at the present time. It has always seemed to me that one cardinal error made by Governments, made, indeed, by political parties and at times by trade unions, is to underestimate the intelligence of average people in this country.  It is a mistake often made by those supposed to be on top that they know more than those who are at the bottom.  I have detected an uneasiness among the working-class people with whom I am privileged to associate and I have often tried to assess the cause of this uneasiness. Very many of those people work in industries which are threatened or they believe are threatened by the gradual implementation of the free trade agreement with Great Britain.</P>
    <P>I would suggest&mdash;and I do not want merely to use a cliché&mdash;that in the matter of communication as to what would be the effects and consequences of that agreement on the working-class people the Government have notably failed to get across what I might describe as their point of view.  The Common Market and membership of the EEC is now resuming the stage from which it departed some years ago. What attempt, if any, has been made to educate our people on the effects and consequences of membership of that community?  At this stage I do not wish &mdash;I imagine I should be out of order&mdash; to debate the merits and demerits of our application to join that community, but even to the most simple-minded man and woman in the country it is obvious that this will, if achieved, be one of the biggest steps ever taken by us.  What do the people know about it in detail?  They have a shadowy knowledge of it and a vague fear and many of the people with whom I am associated are afraid it will affect their employment.</P>
    <P>When we consider trade disputes and <Col N="195" /> industrial relations we have got to take down the textbooks written by experts distinguished for their ignorance and throw them in the wastepaper basket. We have got to get down amongst the people who are the very fabric of industrial relations and if they are receptive&mdash;and they are very receptive at the present time&mdash;we have to examine the root cause of that uneasiness, and I again suggest that no major effort in that connection is being made by the Government.</P>
    <P>In summary of the few points I have made, the idea I would seriously suggest is that the Government, and the Minister for Finance particularly, should give the attainment or implementation of a prices and incomes policy designed to cover all sections of the community first priority.  The Minister for Labour, or whoever may be the appropriate Minister, should seek to have implemented the report of the ESB committee on industrial relations with particular reference to worker participation in the industry and representation on the board.</P>
    <P>I have just a few more comments which I should like to make, one with reference to secondary education. Whether it is free or not, we must be thankful that it is now on offer for the children of our country.  To those of us who did not benefit from it because it was beyond us it is indeed to be welcomed, but again I would suggest that the Government must take further steps along that road.  For very many, and too many, of the parents of our country it is not economically possible for them to allow their children to take advantage of this secondary education, or in cases where there are large families to let perhaps more than one of a family benefit from secondary education.  Certainly an examination should be carried out to see how it would be possible to relieve the family of the burden that it can be for so many of them if they release their children.</P>
    <P>I made a few notes during Senator Keery's excellent speech and I take possibly unfair advantage of him but I hope that he will forgive me.  He was referring to the task of the Government to make it possible for management and labour to tackle their own respective <Col N="196" /> affairs, and he did use the words that after that it was a free matter.  I hope that this will represent the thinking of the Government if and when they reintroduce the Trade Union Bill.  However painfully slow we may travel along the road towards industrial peace it must be said that we will not be harried nor goaded along that road, however advantageous such short-term plans might seem to the Government.  It remains and will remain a free country so far as the Irish trade union movement is concerned.  I have said before in other places that however irksome they may be at times, particularly to Ministers for Finance, strikes will remain a comparatively small price to pay for the privilege of living in a free democracy.</P>
    <P>Productivity some years ago was the equivalent of a dirty word in the trade union movement.  It is not quite so bad now, but I am not aware that the employers of this country have any quarrel with the productivity of their work people; quite the opposite.  Man for man and woman for woman and particularly&mdash;a point sometimes overlooked&mdash;given the same machinery and tools as their continental and other counterparts, our working class people will rank with and indeed go better than the best elsewhere.</P>
    <P>I do not want to be over smart by relating the word &ldquo;productivity&rdquo; to the Seanad, but I share the hope of other Senators, and indeed I hope the wishes of all Senators, that more use will be made of this House than apparently has been the case in the past.  It seems to me that when one reads these articles which attack the Seanad and attack the need for such a House or cast reflections upon its workload this was quite all right when one was not a Senator, but now the implications are personal and I think that we ought to try to make this House work and make a contribution to the life of our people.  If we are not prepared to do that we should wrap it up. I remember on one occasion when I was a soldier in our own army and five or six of us privates were sitting around the fire in the billet and we were bemoaning the fact that the young ladies would have nothing to do with us because we were Free State soldiers, as <Col N="197" /> we were then, one old soldier said to us&mdash;and I shall never forget it&mdash;that &ldquo;the people will only respect you if you learn to respect yourselves&rdquo;.  I think we can apply this thinking to this House, and I do hope that in the future this House will work well and make a valuable contribution to our national life.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a considerable embarrassment to address the House after a speech so impressive in its sincerity as the speech we have just listened to and to express so very well the adherence to the values that I imagine the great majority, if not everyone in this House, adheres to.  I am unable to follow him on many of the points because, though I am testing the capacity of this House to listen to me, there are some topics that Senator Dunne referred to that I do not know about and would find it quite difficult to make up well.</P>
      <P>At the same time, while the speech was impressive in its sincerity, it emphasised rather the problem with which we are all faced.  An aspect of that problem to which I have been giving consideration, particularly since I thought it had some special relationship to the Bill before the House, is the matter of inflation with particular reference to the deficit in the balance of payments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not apologise to the House or through you, a Chathaoirleach, to Senator Dunne for referring to this matter, because there is here a question of fundamental social justice involved in terms of the distribution of income between different members of this society; just as there is at one remove a fundamental question affecting every member of this society, and that is the possibility that, if we do not curb this inflation and get a proper policy of control of deficits in the balance of payments or a clear view of their cause and their ultimate elimination, then every member of this community, including those on whose behalf Senator Dunne so well addressed himself, will suffer and we will all be in trouble.  This is a problem which represents a great social injustice in absolute terms and a great potential danger to economic development <Col N="198" /> and therefore to the well-being of every member of society if it is not coped with.</P>
    <P>May I preface what I have to say with a reminder to everyone that this is a problem that a free economy has to face, whether it be an economy administered by a socialist government, a labour government or a conservative government.  The clearest-minded administrator of the British economy would have been more dedicated on this, or at least as well dedicated, to the values expressed by Senator Dunne tonight.  I refer to the late Sir Stafford Cripps.  He appreciated the necessity for controls and clearly saw that controls imposed on one category of persons alone, people bearing a particular economic relationship to the economy, would not be acceptable and would not work, and that there must be an inspiration given to the whole of society if an incomes policy such as Senator Dunne has recommended was to be acceptable by society; a sense of social justice must permeate society and permeate the leadership given to that society if that society was prepared to accept and truly endorse restrictions and controls by taxation or otherwise.</P>
    <P>I make no apology for dealing with the social injustice of inflation for the particular reason that it is not a popular subject for a member of an opposition party to direct himself to because it leads inevitably to &ldquo;What would you have done or not have done if you had been in power?&rdquo;  I direct myself to this theme because I do not see any point in being a Member of this Seanad or any assembly unless I express my mind and my thinking. I do not think I could be of use to this Assembly if I did not express my mind and thinking as fully as they should be expressed at that moment whether it was politically desirable to express it at that moment or not. Perhaps that may make me a very bad politician.  My attention is directed at the moment to raising this matter through the House to the country because it is the kind of problem which I see existing.  It is a problem that is not being fully faced up to, not being recognised with the clarity with which <Col N="199" /> it should be recognised by the persons in charge of the Government at the moment.</P>
    <P>Inflation consists of overspending in terms of available resources.  Available resources consist of what is provided by the self-restraint of the community coupled with what borrowings they can make for productive development.  The policies which would be required to be designed to please these people who reject the idea of an open economy if spelled out would amount to a pretty stark proposition.  I suggest to the House that we are in a factual situation in which we cannot afford to be in anything other than an open economy.  If we so wished we could have a controlled economy.  We could, as someone recently suggested was required, abandon the policy of free mobility of labour and abandon the policy of free exchange of capital between this country and the rest of the world&mdash;from what Senator Dunne has said, I am sure that would not be acceptable to him and that it would not be acceptable to any other self-respecting citizens of the country&mdash;the policy of the control of labour and capital and accepting only such growth as would be made possible by a policy of compulsory saving where citizens did not by voluntary restraint provide the required capital.</P>
    <P>It is possible to have overspending for a period of time and it may generate economic development that improves the lot of most people.  These people may be in the relationship of providers of capital or they may be in the relationship of being employed by the providers of capital.  If workers are well organised they may get their share of the benefits of that development but there are people whose position may be substantially damaged by economic development to any degree involving inflation, by a growth of affluence in which they do not share: for example, pensioners whose conditions of pension do not give them any chance of getting supplements; pensioners, from the public services, may, after the usual unfortunate delay, get some restoration but who will not share in the gains.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="200" /> There will be those who have nobody to protect them: people not organised in employment, people working in small offices who are unfairly treated and there are people who exploit others in our society as everywhere else in the world.  There are a number of people living in our society who may be badly or otherwise disabled or who are not particularly able to work because of psychological or other difficulties and whose parents recognised this as being something they had to provide for and took that responsibility on themselves. The funds provided by parents for these people have to be very carefully organised and dealt with if the incomes are to be sufficient to look after them. The affluence generated by an economic development policy which gives rise to uncontrolled inflation deprives them of wealth and money is taken from them.</P>
    <P>The thrifty-minded are penalised, particularly the small capitalist&mdash;a small capitalist is any man who has any money saved that he could have spent.  He puts his money in a bank where it erodes in value.  He may put it into savings certificates and, perhaps, these may not erode in value if the rate of inflation is not too excessive but people who take out life policies pay a premium in 1969 £'s but what will be their return in 1989 £'s.</P>
    <P>Savers suffer when their abstaining from expenditure permits a level of consumption by others at the cost of inflation.  Their savings are wasted by others who can borrow their savings.  I am not dealing with inflation in relation to this particular Government but all Governments because we are dealing now with governmental currency throughout the world.</P>
    <P>Borrowers always benefit from inflation. Inflation encourages people to buy now on the basis that it will cost them more in the future and thus divert resources that could be made available for the better development of the country, and generate employment resulting in better rewards for those employed. It is inflation too, generally, which causes high interest rates, and the current rate of interest is a fact of life in the free world.</P>
    <P>All that is by way of describing as <Col N="201" /> best I can some of the consequences of inflation in absolute terms.  If you have a rapid expansion which leads to a serious inflation, it creates a situation in which a monetary and fiscal restraint policy must be applied to restore the balance and to lay the basis for a further expansion.  From that point, if one looks at some of the most successfully managed economies in the world&mdash;I have not been as far away as Tokyo but some people not too far from this House have been there&mdash;Japan, in the past 20 years, has multiplied by ten the real income of her people.  What Keynes said can truly be said to have been followed up by Japan with logic; that is to say that, when restraints are required to be imposed, they were imposed.  In Japan during various years investors in its economy ran into great difficulties because, in fact, their returns were not coming home because the authorities were imposing the restraints which were necessary so that the future development of the economy could go forward on a sound basis.</P>
    <P>It is well, if I may, to summarise a couple of recent accounts of our present situation.  The Central Bank reports are there for anyone to check. In looking at the current Central Bank report we are not looking at the report from the bank of 1948, without mention of persons, but we are looking at the Central Bank report whose Governor is the man who drafted the original development plan for this country.  He signs this report and says in it:</P>
    <P>The inflation instead of being brought under control appears to be getting worse.</P>
    <P>He gives instances of this and says:</P>
    <P>There are signs of a strong upturn in consumption in the June quarter.  The adverse trade gap has widened.  The balance of payments deficit has increased.  There is a fall in the ratio of external reserves to annual import excess from 216 per cent in August of 1968 to 173 per cent in August, 1969.  There has been an upsurge in costs and prices <Col N="202" /> of consumer goods and services in the year of 8.4 per cent.</P>
    <P>I may remark this has been exceeded since the foundation of this State in one year only.  That was in the year following the Korean war and we know what special consequences came from that.  The situation described in the Central Bank report which appeared in September, and we are now in December, is that we had a dangerous inflationary situation.  Our rate of increase in money income was three times the rate of increase of real output.</P>
    <P>This was followed shortly afterwards by a document, the quarterly commentary of the Economic and Social Research Institute.  I pause at this moment to say it being so very popular to speak ill of America in her trials and tribulations that we owe very much to the Economic and Social Research Institute for the degree of enlightenment it has spread with regard to our affairs.  I personally have learned a great deal from its publications.  It was, of course, established by American money.  The Economic and Social Research Institute on the assumption that credit is now more firmly under control and on the assumption that exports rise more rapidly than seems likely this year say we are likely to have a deficit of £70 million. Incidentally, it would appear from adding and subtracting, an operation at which I am not particularly good, that the Central Bank estimated in their autmumn report that the deficit would be £62 million.  The Minister for Finance in volume 241 of the debates of the other House said he believed on the 29th October that the deficit would be £55 million broadly in line with his Budget forecast.  In fact, I believe he has adjusted that figure somewhat upwards.  It does not matter whether it is £60 million to £70 million as the figure is very serious.  The figure is made much more serious, however, by the fact that the Economic and Social Research Institute's report which was written by people who in the past have viewed the trend of the economy not always in a pessimistic way and this may have permitted a degree of inflation to develop, perhaps, by absence of criticism.  In this issue it takes it <Col N="203" /> squarely in although it leaves the policy decisions to the Government that the external deficit for the second consecutive year in 1970 will run at £70 million.</P>
    <P>It made certain assumptions with regard to this figure.  That is to say, assumptions which if not correct, if there was an adversity about them, would make the figure greater and the matter would be that much worse. One of the assumptions was that price rise in the coming year would drop by about 25 per cent.  The price rise would not be over 8 per cent but a rise of 6 per cent.  In a moment I will give the House, if I may, some of the other assumptions which they made and the other assumptions I make that might not be achieved.  Allowing the present trend to continue, it says that this country is running with no safety margin and if the capital inflow which is financing the development were to be reduced we would have a dramatic fall in external assets.</P>
    <P>A number of assumptions were made.  It was assumed the credit situation would be brought under control and remain under control without damaging confidence.  This may be an assumption which will be attained.  It will be a painful one for the economy to experience.  It will be a difficult one to maintain and even if maintained we will have a deficit of £70 million. It assumes there will be a slight slackening in the rate of growth of money earnings.  I am not sure if I inferred from what the wise man&mdash; Senator Dunne&mdash;who spoke before me said he would agree that he sees from his apprehension of the reactions of his colleagues there would be in the coming year a slight slackening in the rate of growth of money earnings.  It assumed there would be no export recession and there has been some optimism in this matter generated by the highly optimistic report of the National Institute for Economic and Social Research in Britain which optimism for me was entirely pricked when I read the <i>Financial Times</i> analysis of it in its issue of November 28th.  It assumed there would be no decline in tourism. It assumed there would be disruptive <Col N="204" /> strikes.  It made an assumption there would be nothing to disturb the size and nature of the capital inflow.</P>
    <P>It also assumed there were no errors in projection.  I hope there are no errors in projection of an adverse kind. It is difficult to make any projection which does not have an error of some kind but I would assume, because those people are really responsible, that they appropriately discounted their various calculations in the correct directions in this situation.  I should like to add a number of other assumptions which seem to me necessary to make.  It must be assumed that there would be no political changes in the United Kingdom, in the USA or anywhere else in the world with an adverse affect on this country.  There has been a great inflow of money into Ireland in the last ten years or so, especially in the last five years, an inflow which has been affected very much by the kind of taxation policy which has been pursued by Britain but what if there is a change in Government and there is an outflow of individuals returning home?  It is worth noticing that according to the most recent figures I saw &mdash;and I only pursued the matter as far as a Senator need pursue it&mdash;there is a relatively slow rate in the growth of interest and dividend payments out of this country to abroad which is interesting but there has been a very considerable increase in the income from investments abroad made by residents of this country.  I suggest that this growth in income from investments abroad may to some degree of significance, which has not been estimated or if estimated the estimates have not been published, due to people taking up residence in Ireland whose considerable incomes are brought home here, taxed and subscribe to the national revenue and also are available to balance the budget or the national economy.  In fact the figure that I have, the one for 1967, shows that the income from investments abroad was £47 million representing one-sixth of the total trade merchandise exported from the country.</P>
    <P>There is another point to be made here.  With regard to this outflow of income from the country because of <Col N="205" /> the kind of industrial development policy we have pursued, perhaps had to pursue in our circumstances, in fact I, for one, would have supported it.  It would have liked to have seen more information about its effects as it went forward, but I suspect one of the consequences certainly I know in relation to one particular country from which much of the investment has come has been to trap in Ireland the profits made from the export enterprises of these companies.  That means that there is locked up in this country money which if it were declared by way of dividend and paid out to the investor would be susceptible to taxation in their own country and therefore he would lose the benefit of the export tax relief which he gets while he traps it here and so he awaits the day when he will break up his company and liquidate it and take it home and pay a lower capital gains taxation.  We have a lot of that kind of money locked up here.  There are a number of these items which could be affected by various events.  For example if, the Lord forbid, we had any extension of the trouble in Northern Ireland it would have a disruptive effect on our income from tourism.  If we have disruptive strikes this will have a serious effect.  On account of the profession into which I was thrown when too foolish to sensibly choose another I do not in fact find everyone as they offer themselves to me.  There are some fishermen and fisherwomen around the place looking for and perhaps finding troubled waters who could have in their ultimate consequences bad effects.  It is possible, for example, if the matter of the administration of justice is not successful, did not maintain the confidence of people, that money would be taken out and it could not be stopped from being taken out, that people would leave with their capital and that the savings made by export companies and retained here would go.  I have been seriously concerned by the burnings and threats to foreigners. This is quite contrary to Irish policy, it is quite contrary to the national tradition, it is quite contrary to Christian living, it is quite contrary to the whole Judaic Christian tradition <Col N="206" /> which tells one to treat the guest within ones city with more respect than one treats one's neighbours.  These people have been badly treated and the people who did it have not been brought to justice.  If that policy is pursued and the culprits not brought to punishment and if the Minister for Justice&mdash;and this is the only reference I will make to him&mdash;is not held in the fullest respect by the whole community the consequences could be bad.</P>
    <P>From these words you may perhaps see that I take the situation to be somewhat worse than the recommendations of the Central Bank and the account given by the Economic and Social Research Institute.  I shall make my first point on that and I am surprised it has not been made in either of the two publications.  It is a point worth making because it concerns matters of communication to everybody concerned&mdash;employees, employers, whoever they may be all are involved in our economy.  When they see this figure of £70 million of a deficit they will say: &ldquo;What about it? Those fellows have plenty of money, can they not do something about it?&rdquo; It is not as simple or easy as that because there is the extraordinarily important matter of confidence.  I take the view that the development of the last 20 years and without wishing to get into controversy with my friends on my right the change took place 20 years ago when our party introduced the capital budget; indeed it took some years to get going.  I agree we had our little local difficulties, which I believe was the expression, they got going at any rate and they only succeeded to the extent that they have succeeded because of confidence. There is no good in my not acknowledging that there has been a degree of success attained in the industrial policy that has been pursued although we may not have measured the adverse consequences that we must in duty face.  It has been successfully pursued because we established confidence in our currency, because we established the confidence of the world in our country's good sense in our ability to be stable and to make the right decisions and not to be irrational. <Col N="207" /> If one looks back to the situation prevailing in the early 1930s when it was not possible to make a borrowing in London without a kind of concession being made by the Government which the Government was not prepared to make and where the Government of South Africa&mdash;at that time it was Herzog, who was not the father of the present Herzog as somebody said he was recently, had to make concessions to the British because he was dependent on the Controllers of Funds in South Africa for his money who were English and not Afrikaaner, at that time.  This matter of confidence is very important.  To come back to those figures, if the deficit in the balance of payments were not £70 million this year but £20 million as it was last year the inflation would be much more this year than it was last year, much more than the eight per cent it has already exceeded.  The inflow of goods which represents this balance of payments deficit has been to some extent mopping up the money supply which if it were not being mopped up would in fact make for higher prices.  This is a fact to look at because it means we are in a more dangerous situation than we realise, a situation demanding much earlier action than has been taken.</P>
    <P>There is another point that arises from a remark of the Governor of the Central Bank in an address he made to the Cork Chamber of Commerce. It develops a theme which is only slightly referred to in the Central Bank Report.  He said that the funds that flow into the economy from nonassociated banks&mdash;the merchant banks, hire purchase companies and so on&mdash; who are drawing in their money on a short-term basis and generally employing it for consumer financing have the same effect, although I would not follow him fully here personally, as external borrowings.  I take it what he means here is external borrowings of a non-development kind but perhaps the report of what he said is not adequate. To the extent that these have financed consumption, these have added to the internal level of demand and made the problem of final financing their return the more difficult.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="208" /> According to my calculations, and I hope I shall not trouble you too much by giving these, the position in 1963 was that we had a deficit of £22 million; we had external assets available to the Government and Departments of £234 million.  The deficit was covered ten times and I prefer the ratio of external assets of the banking system relative to the deficit which takes in the invisibles as well as the visibles to the ratio applied by the Central Bank when it makes a relationship between external assets and trade figures.  The figure based on the same formula for August last at the lower of the two figures that seem likely to emerge&mdash;£65 million deficit&mdash;with the latest figure I have for external assets of £267 million means that at the outcome of this year our external assets, at the end of a period of six years, only covered our deficit four times.  We have financed deficits, taking the 1965 figure, from 1963 a total of £181 million with a large intake of capital and our external reserves have risen during that time by only £30 million.</P>
    <P>I should like to know the composition of the capital inflow.  No doubt the Department of Finance have the best available information but it would be helpful if people could know the position.  If I am shown a man with many assets and he tells me that so much of his own money is in it and when I ask him what are the terms of borrowing and if he replies to me &ldquo;I do not really know; I do not know if I have to pay it back next Tuesday, in two years time or whether it is a 20 or 50 year loan&rdquo;, my attitude to his finances will be remarkably affected.</P>
    <P>We do not know how much of the money in our banking system is hot money, avoiding taxation elsewhere, which would have to be covered.  The Economic and Social Research Institute say we are leading to a situation in which the apparent real standard of living must be reduced, whether through devaluation or severe deflation. I wish to say as emphatically as I can that unless it is a very carefully-planned operation from strength through time &mdash;and I see no argument anywhere yet <Col N="209" /> which would seem to me to justify even such a policy&mdash;devaluation would be absolutely unthinkable for this country in the involvement we have with the world economy, having regard to our size, the forces operative in the world concerned to assist Britain and to help her to maintain a not too severe devaluation could not be relied on to come to our assistance.  In my view all the steps that should be taken must be taken as soon as possible to prevent the unthinkable devaluation.  As St. Paul said, let it not be so much as mentioned among you.</P>
    <P>I recognise in any economy, and this is the first time in my view anything serious has emerged here, the necessity of economic management.  It is very easy to talk about what should be done.  We have a real problem here and I discern in some of the Minister's statements that he is trying to not strike at confidence and at the same time perhaps to prepare the way for measures.  I think he is taking too long about it and I do not understand some of his statements.  I do not see how on the 29th October in response to a Question in the Dáil at column 2043 of the Official Report which I have already quoted, he said it might be necessary to take some action between now and December, and how he could go to the Stock Exchange seven days later and bind himself not to introduce an autumn budget.  I am not harrying anybody for an autumn budget, but I am harrying the Government for a statement of their policy of how and when they intend to apply it, with regard to a reserve situation which only covers four times the current deficit of the balance of payments.  On November 6th the Minister said he could find no comparable need as in 1968 for immediate fiscal measurements, although the deficit on his own Estimate is going to be more than 2½ times what it was in 1968.  There may be special reasons for justifying measures when a deficit is £20 million, which are not justified when the deficit is £65 million, the more probable figure.</P>
    <P>I should like our intelligence to be respected and to be given these reasons.  I would join very much in <Col N="210" /> support of what Senator Dunne said, that political parties and a lot of other people in charge of capital, managers and people in the business of persuasion, insufficiently respect the intelligence of our people.  Much more cooperation would come from them if a full and courageous statement were made to them of all that is implied even if that involved&mdash;and this has been done in the history of this State &mdash;political damage to those who had to make that statement.  It is their plain duty to take whatever political consequence comes.  I do not wish this to be a political speech, but the truth is the truth, even if political benefits may be garnered from it, that only if they are prepared to gather all the political consequences will growth take place.  Let them face the political consequences now and respect the good sense and the patriotism of the Opposition parties and of other people in the country in not taking unfair advantage of what decisions they may have to take.  I think he should have denied himself the satisfaction of talking at this time, as he did on that evening, of the doubling of capital investment over the last ten years.  This is the sort of language which if I did not have some little training earlier in my life in this field would make me say: &ldquo;If they have done that then everything is in order&rdquo; but I do not think that this is the sort of language that should be uttered by a Minister for Finance.</P>
    <P>He went to the bankers' dinner on 15th November.  I heard him myself and he made a very good speech, or rather I was amused by his earlier remarks but possibly confused by my hosts' hospitality, so that I did not take in the full sense of his remark that &ldquo;economic development must not be held back by credit restraints&rdquo; until I read it later.  That is the sort of thing he was saying on that night rather than that we must slow down economic development so that we do not endanger confidence, and take measures to slow it down.</P>
    <P>He went to some other meeting on 19th and again made an amusing speech and again I was there&mdash;I mix in excellent society sometimes.  He said that the increase in the Republic's <Col N="211" /> import excess is only marginally attributable to consumer goods and is in the main accounted for by increased productivity within the country.  If you are trying to tell a lot of people who see no reason why they should not have incomes corresponding to the kind of thing they see lying behind the expenditure, they are witnessing, that they should not at this time seek these increases, if the economy is in a state of affluence but you know that this affluence is delicately balanced and that if this delicate balance is lost there will be a toppling over damaging everyone, it is your duty not to talk in such a way as to suggest that it is only marginally attributable to the fact that you bought a piano last week which you should not have bought at all but should have put away to protect the economy for next year.</P>
    <P>This leads me to the point that I do not think I would be in this House were it not that I was convinced that our ills, such as they are require a commitment to a policy of social justice of a peculiarly definite kind.  Looking back to the earlier years of my life I think that the society here was happier when we were not overall as well off. The moment we all got mad was when we were standing in the bus queues and Ministers passed in their State cars and shortly afterwards there were a few people who had been watching carefully the different ways of putting money into their pockets without paying the proper taxes on it and they began to spend it.  This sense of justice is most important and can only be conveyed by someone who believes in the importance of justice.  It can only be conveyed if you do not just talk about it.  Talk is a kind of action, I suppose, if it is addressed to people who you believe may be in a position of going on and acting and are in a position to act, but it is real action that matters.  In saying as I do that this commitment to social justice must be there, I have to recognise the economic difficulty facing its full and satisfactory realisation.</P>
    <P>As I understand the working of the economy&mdash;and I am ready to be shown otherwise if there is some alternative <Col N="212" /> system&mdash;we are not in the kind of closed situation that the Americans have who might be a little worse off if things could be better distributed and yet that be the right policy to pursue.  We are in a situation that if we pursue without regard to efficiency a policy of social justice we may not have the wealth to distribute that we are so concerned to distribute.  While the ultimate priority is clear that social justice as an objective must come before the actual creation of wealth we must first create the wealth, so that we must be careful that our policy of social justice will not distribute or reduce wealth so much as to lessen what is there to be distributed.  We know that there are certain situations in this country, people living in conditions which are quite unsuitable and unsatisfactory, and even at the present time I would say that such are not tolerable and that irrespective of the effect on economic growth those problems must be solved.</P>
    <P>The first task of any Government at this moment is to justify themselves to the people to win this support and to generate a national spirit such as&mdash;I am using the very language that Senator Keery used because I am afraid this is a job in which the Government are failing&mdash;&ldquo;drawing out the national spirit, which would lead to economic development and provide for the social development depending on that economic development&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>A climate of opinion has got to get convinced about the people in power &mdash;and, mind you, it cannot be ignored that in a democratic society in a certain sense the Opposition parties are always in power too because they help to create the conditions which make possible the policies pursued by a government.  There are certain topics which the Houses of the Oireachtas have with certain minor exceptions over a long period of years not ever dissented from, because they are the most fundamental, matters of law and order.  If it is possible to have unity between parties on this sort of matter without someone throwing out a taunt that these are the two conservative parties getting together, I do not think this is a matter of left or right but a <Col N="213" /> matter of all parties of recognise that in this situation we have to act.  We have very little to spare and very little spare capacity and we must protect our selves, we must preserve stability and secure confidence and we cannot do that without the support of all the people.</P>
    <P>What is required?  I am not in the Government and I do not know all that they know.  It is well-known that those in politics in opposition, Deputies and Senators, think it wiser politics not to say much of what they would do but that line does not attune with what I have been saying, I hope that I am keeping within the limits of the debate in saying that obviously the first thing is the matter of confidence, and second to confidence and necessarily parallel to it is the creation of the prices and incomes policy to which Senator Dunne referred.  This means an urgent high level discussion between people, I would say by all Parties as well as the Government Party, with a view to having a shared policy on this.</P>
    <P>We know that our institutions are defective in this matter of both prices and incomes.  I have expressed it in this Assembly since I came here that the Fair Trade Commission is not value for money.  The Minister replied that it was, and he did it in a very well-mannered way so that I did not want to pursue the matter by reference to my own experience with that body. Industry and Commerce shares with the Fair Trade Commission the administration of the prices and incomes policy.  This is a limited function, and a limited amount of expertise is gathered there as in the Fair Trade Commission.  An Irish manufacturer has to give notice of his intention to increase his prices.  A wholesaler and a manufacturer has to give notice of his intention to increase his wholesale margins, but then we are not given information as to what was asked for or told how justifiable those costs were, how tested they were and what conditions they had to comply with.  To this degree there must inevitably arise suspicion in the minds of people who see prices rising.  The cost to the economy of trying to control retail prices is such <Col N="214" /> that I certainly would concentrate more on the matter of competition and the elimination of monopolistic practices, perhaps laying down a code of rules under the Fair Trade Commission to ensure that where you have monoply retail situations they are not able to extort unnecessary profits from unnecessary and unjustifiable price rises.</P>
    <P>With regard to the Labour Court, I am trying to speak only of things I know something about and I really do not know anything about it, but it would seem that as an institution&mdash; perhaps it is due to the legislation, perhaps to the background economic situation&mdash;it has not succeeded in its function.  Perhaps I could make a point here which may be relevant and should be noted.  The first economic programme was called The First Economic Programme, and the second was called The Second Programme for Economic Expansion.  The third programme was called The Programme for Economic and Social Expansion. That is very significant and there I think lies a fundamental error.</P>
    <P>This programme followed the publication of the policy for a Just Society by this Party on whose behalf I am speaking.  I believe this was an error of judgment rather than of heart and the draftsmen of that first programme were more concerned in pulling the country out of the stagnation that they believed it to be in than in recognising the priorities with regard to social policy.</P>
    <P>The next matter to consider is the effect of conspicuous consumption in a country like this.  It is not bad to have a lot of money but to spend it conspicuously or selfishly is bad.  It can be well spent by backing good projects, by helping one's family or by helping others.  It is not having money that is bad but how it is spent.  There are those who say that if we want to attract people to the country whose presence here yield a substantial benefit to the economy, it is difficult to deal adequately with this but it must be dealt with to some degree.  It is necessary to take a sensible line.  I am not recommending taxation of any kind to the House.  Indeed, I do not know if it would be in order for me to speak about taxation.</P>
    <Col N="215" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not in order to refer to it in detail on this Bill; certain classes of taxation could probably be discussed in general terms.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We had a very interesting analysis recently in respect of motor car owners 3 per cent of whom held a second car.  I would have thought it reasonable to impose a little extra taxation on this group even though it might present problems for people with large families and so on.  However, I think that most people who own a second car would be prepared to pay a little extra.</P>
      <P>We all know that, some years ago, householders were taxed on the basis of the number of windows they had in their houses but why not now tax people who have private swimming pools.  A private swimming pool should be well and truly taxed.  I shall not go into any detail on taxation except to suggest that we look at our whole tax structure which is not revised sufficiently often to eliminate injustices. If I could make a recommendation through the House to the Minister for Finance, I would ask him to take out some of the sections of the Income Tax Code and compare them with the 1801 Act.  He would probably be surprised to find that the language in both sections is more or less the same.  Sections of the Income Tax Code were very often designed to meet particular needs at particular times that have long since passed and it is this sort of thing that gives rise to injustices.</P>
      <P>Someone referred to the position of married women in regard to taxation. It is quite clear that this is unsatisfactory and needs to be changed.  We might at least change the system to the British one where, speaking in gross terms, a married pair pay the taxation which a married man would pay plus what a single woman would pay.  In other words, by marrying, a pair actually have taxation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Another item which should be looked at is in relation to what used be called wages goods.  I wonder if that has been revised.  Has it been considered <Col N="216" /> what sort of goods could be taxed that would not be reflected in a demand for extra wages?</P>
    <P>In the context in which I am speaking, this may not seem particularly relevant but I think it is because of certain experiences I have had recently. It is in relation to the Estate Duty code.  In terms of the income of farmers with family and so on, the rates are now grossly excessive.  I made a calculation a while ago which I did not bring with me, showing the manifest injustices of the lower rates of this code at their present levels.</P>
    <P>I have long favoured the principle put forward by Senator Dunne as to worker participation and I have been surprised at his particular concern in the matter not because I have been told that workers are not interested in participating in the government of companies&mdash;it pleased me to hear that they are&mdash;but I am not certain or yet convinced that the participation should be exercised directly but should be more on the German model where they are represented on a body to which the Directors must report back.  It is not every worker who has the talent or the expertise to direct or administer but what he should have is full information about what is going on and of what everyone is getting.</P>
    <P>There were some other items but I shall not go into these.  One item I shall mention, though, is the role of co-operatives in relation to the development of industry.  These should be considered in the light of the desirability of the expansion of the stock market and there are changes that could be made quite easily along the lines of making the organisations similar to a life insurance company. The particular advantage I see in this is that it would tend to bridge this gap between the country and town which is bad.  Do not forget that a great deal of the investment which is made in any market nowadays is not made by large capitalists.  It is made by institutions such as pension funds, insurance companies of one kind or another, credit unions, friendly societies and so on.  Anything which would, for example, make the city of Dublin <Col N="217" /> more aware of the realities of country life would be for the better and it would justify a change.</P>
    <P>There is one other thing with regard to foreign firms investing here. Most of those foreign firms have guarantees in terms of currency.  This to me seems to be a matter of concern. Most of them have guarantees made that they will get their money back in foreign currency if they want it, so there is a potential claim in foreign currency to be met.  Another point I should like to mention is that it is out of fashion to talk about the Minister for Finance being the watch dog of public expenditure when you rarely hear him saying other than boasting of the amount of expenditure he is involved in being increased with each year.  In this House we could perform a very useful function if we made ourselves and everyone else aware of the fact that every pound which is provided by the taxpayer&mdash;wherever that taxpayer may be, whether he be employed in the most humble job in the country or whether he be the poorest in the country and not paying direct tax but contributing by indirect taxation&mdash;has an alternative use and could perhaps be put to better use.</P>
    <P>This is my final word on this.  It may be a shock to anyone in the Labour Party but, as it is a matter of personal integrity, I have to say there is an important word to be said about the role of profits in our society.  You should have a taxation policy applied to those people who are being personally enriched.  But the kind of profits made after people have paid their proper share in taxation is justified and necessary for the future development of industry and the economy.  Without them there can be no progress.  I adopt a succinct phrase about such protests: &ldquo;Profits are demand for Labour.&rdquo; Those profits must be made whether they are made in Soviet Russia.  I was going to say in Maoist China.  But the real income of 1,500 million people of China and India equals the real income of 100 million in Japan&mdash;a well controlled capitalist economy.  Residual profits, which are properly availed of, will be enjoyed by people in general <Col N="218" /> according to the extent to which they are properly employed.</P>
    <P>We should use every strategy in solving our present difficulties.  We should not allow swag-pooled profits to be made by extortionists.  There has got to be inspiration, courage and a full and honest pooling of our knowledge in order to help overcome our difficulties.  When I criticise the Government I do much more than that.  I criticise the establishment with and behind the Government and I criticise even those very intelligent people who have done so much to make progress in our economy&mdash;the managers and the people who have been doing so well in technical terms for the better organisation of our economy.  I tax them all.  I tax us all here with insufficient concern for all our people; the mere fact that we developed our abilities along particular technical lines is no justification for postponing final judgment.  Our people have got to have a just and proper share if they are going to co-operate in bringing the country forward to the position it should occupy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mícheál Cranitch Mícheál Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>Is mian liom labhairt ar an mBille seo.  Ní bheidh mórán le rá agam mar tá sé beagnach fiche nóiméat chun a deich agus tuigim go n-éiríonn an Teach ag an am sin.</P>
      <P>The Appropriation Bill involves a sum of £363,498,080.  By any standards that is a sizeable amount of money. It is necessary to spend it.  It will be spent and I propose to make some suggestions as to how it could be spent wisely and well and how we can contribute to that wise spending. I am a newcomer here and I have been most heartened by the speeches made this afternoon and tonight.  It is quite clear that everybody here is anxious that the money be spent wisely and well, as I said, and that the country would be geared to further production, that bigger and better targets would be aimed at and that the country would prosper in every way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>From both sides of the House we have got valuable contributions, valuable suggestions, and it is quite clear to me that, whatever differences may exist in what we may euphemistically <Col N="219" /> call this side of the House and that side of the House, the end product everybody has in mind is exactly the same.  We have a wonderful little country and if everybody does his part &mdash;I will indicate presently how he can do that&mdash;then a great future lies before us.  The price of freedom, they say, is eternal vigilance.  We may go a step further and say that, as far as our little country is concerned, the price of existence is eternal vigilance. That is becoming more apparent every day and it will become a reality if and when within the next five, six, seven or eight years we become part and parcel of the European Economic Community.</P>
    <P>Our target must be and will be productivity, reliability, responsibility. These terms were mentioned already. These things will not be achieved unless we have the spirit and the soul to make the thing work.  I am speaking of a national spirit to enable us to overcome all obstacles.  I often think of the example of that little country, Israel, which came up, one might say, from nothing.  What brought them to the peak they have reached?  The extraordinary national spirit in these people and the fact that within a few years, approximately 12 years, they have succeeded in restoring their native language. That is one of the first things I propose to deal with tonight.  If I speak mostly in English it is because I do not want to intrude on anybody's susceptibilities.  There are many of us here tonight who may not be very good at the language through no fault of our own.  Thus I speak mostly in English.  One of the major tasks we have always regarded as before us in this country is the widespread use of the Irish language.  That in itself will lead to a revival of our songs, traditions, dances and will in a big way help to further the economic progress of the country.  I give as an example the Danish folk schools.  They in their own way, even though they did little in the teaching of economic principles, by the very fact that they fostered the growth of nationality in Denmark led to an extraordinary economic achievement in that country.  I hope to see the <Col N="220" /> day when at meetings of the Seanad and Dáil it will be possible for everybody to speak in his own language here and if necessary to have simultaneous translation so that everybody will be understood.  So far that has not been possible but we hope the day will come when it will be.</P>
    <P>Radio Telefís Éireann was mentioned here and the suggestion was made that the type of programme we get from Radio Telefís Éireann could be improved.  I do not think anybody here has any doubts about that.  Serious objection can be taken to certain types of programmes.  We might not go so far as to say that they foster permissiveness, but programmes are shown at an early hour of the evening when children are about which are entirely unsuitable for children.  We have not enough and I speak now for people in rural districts&mdash;of what might be called the lore of the country.  There is not enough of the Irish language&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGeoghegan" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Geoghegan) Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Geoghegan)">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Geoghegan)</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mícheál Cranitch Mícheál Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;Irish songs, dances, <i>et cetera.</i>  I hope I am within the rules of order in referring to this.  It comes within the jurisdiction of the Department of Posts and Telegraphs.</P>
      <P>Speaking of permissiveness, I noticed with a certain amount of disquiet various suggestions in some speeches here today.  One of the greatest curses of the present age is this permissiveness, whereby a person is assumed to have a right to do what he likes, to whom he likes, when he likes.  Somebody suggested, possibly as a palliative to the north, that divorce should be permitted under the Constitution and that contraceptives should be allowed for sale.  These things, I am sure, would not be accepted by the vast majority of our people and such ideas I imagine should be discouraged.  We must go on our own course.  We must work out our own destiny and not be subject to detrimental influences from abroad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Can we go <Col N="221" /> into Europe and avoid influences from abroad?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mícheál Cranitch Mícheál Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>I referred quite distinctly to detrimental influences from abroad.  We are delighted to have good alleviating influences from abroad. This country reached the peak of its fame when we had very intimate contact with Europe during Ireland's golden age.  We have lost a lot since then.</P>
      <P>I wish to say a few words on the question of education&mdash;primary, secondary, vocational and what is called higher education.  Much has been done as far as primary education is concerned. Much has been done in recent years in providing decent buildings. Now there is a change in the curriculum. It will be some years before all schools will be adopted to the new curriculum.  That is all for the good. The suggestion is that education should be child-centred rather than programme centred.  As everybody knows, in every good school that has always been there.  The child was the first concern.  The master teaches John Latin.  He teaches Latin but he also teaches John.  That was there, but it is no harm that it should be seen to be there from now on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Secondary education has posed many problems, especially since what is commonly called free secondary education has come into being.  These problems are being ironed out.  One of the greatest achievements in modern times was the organisation of transport for secondary school pupils.  The position with regard to transport for primary school children has many anomalies but they will be ironed out too.  One of the things we should do, and we can all play out part in this, is that when children come to what is known as the leaving certificate stage &mdash;and this may seem an extraordinary thing for me to say&mdash;as many as possible of these children should be discouraged from going to university unless they have a special bent or a special aptitude or a particular ability to profit by it.  Unfortunately it is true that quite a number of young men and women, having got two honours in their <Col N="222" /> leaving certificate or what is now known as two grade Cs, proceed to the university, just barely manage to get in and a year or so later feel disillusioned, fail their first examination, leave the university and are far worse for their experience.  It would be to these people's advantage if they went to a higher technological college, to a commercial school or into business. That is the point that was mentioned in the recent report on higher education. It was not developed but it would be a partial solution to the present overcrowding in the universities, overcrowding that will be much worse in 1975 if steps are not taken to deal with it.</P>
    <P>Looking through the Department of Defence figures I feel something should be done for the plight of old IRA pensioners.  There is a system working at the moment for old IRA pensioners who may be in distressed circumstances.  There are not many of those men left and it would be a God send for them if something could be done to ease their lot.</P>
    <P>A commission will be set up shortly to inquire into the status of women in this country, and it is time that this was done.  There is a tradition in this country which relegates women to, possibly, the status of second-class citizens.  We do not advert to that fact but the tradition is there.  Women can contribute considerably in all walks of life.  At the moment they are doing wonderful work in the medical and teaching professions and I look forward to the day when women may enter all professions from which up to now they have been debarred.</P>
    <P>An irritation to a small country like ours, emerging from subjection during the past centuries, is the fact that we are very often referred to as being in the British Isles.  This has occurred even in programmes from RTE&mdash;I admit this has been quite inadvertent. It is a term which is repulsive to all of us here and we should put a stop to it. Another irritating point is the fact that the Twenty-six Counties are referred to as Éire which, as we all know here, means in the Irish language 32 counties. These are irritants and I hope <Col N="223" /> that something will be done to put them right.</P>
    <P>We can do wonderful things in this country if everyone is imbued with the spirit to work and do what is best for this nation.  I remember reading a story about three men who were working on the building of a cathedral; two were digging at their work but the third was also whistling.  The first man was asked why he was doing this work and he said he had to earn wages to get enough food for his family; the second man said he was working because he was afraid he would be sacked by his employer if he did not work; but the third man who whistled simply replied &ldquo;I am building a cathedral.&rdquo;  If we could be imbued with the spirit of this man who took such pride in his work, and get rid of a tradition we have of accepting what is not good enough, we could do much good.  Otherwise God help us if and when we get into the Common Market.</P>
    <P>The image of this country abroad depends entirely on ourselves and on those who see us.  We often find fault with foreigners for giving a wrong picture of Ireland abroad.  We found fault recently with British newspapers and the BBC during the recent troubles in the north when they presented a perverted story of what was taking place in Northern Ireland.  There was a film shown on the American network, NBC, recently which was nothing short of character assassination of our teachers&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Senator seen the film?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mícheál Cranitch Mícheál Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Department of External Affairs will be able to do something about this.  We cannot expect foreigners to view us with sympathy&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I am asking the Senator if he has seen the film.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mícheál Cranitch Mícheál Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall ignore interruptions. One other point before I conclude: in dealing with the present <Col N="224" /> state of our economy Senator FitzGerald considered the special point of inflation.  That is something that could possibly upset our economy when we are heading for greater things and I hope something will be done in the near future to put things right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBelton" hpid="Dr. Belton Dr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>My speaking after some of the very excellent, erudite speeches we have heard from many Senators today is tantamount to a TD speaking after a Senator, when I see all the talent that surrounds me on the benches here.  What has struck me forcibly after listening to all the speeches here today is that in this assembly there is as much talent as in any other assembly in the country at the moment. However, it is not my business on the Appropriation Bill to pat anybody on the back.  What we are aiming at to see is that this country is put into proper order.  The main topics have been dealt with; finance by Senator Alexis FitzGerald and by Senator Keery; industrial relations and trade unions by Senator Dunne and other matters by Senators O'Higgins and Horgan and other people.</P>
      <P>I am going to attack this problem on a more mundane basis.  I shall get down slightly from the clouds, or the moon and back to earth.  I am a member of two local authorities and I know there are certain staffing problems with which local authorities find themselves faced at the present time. One is the rapid turnover of technical officers, architects and engineers.  This is due in my view to two main problems; in the first place it is due to the competition for graduates.  This competition comes from private industry and commerce who are in a position to offer salaries higher than those offered by the local authorities.  This is not the fault of the local authorities but of the Department of Local Government which sets the scales.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Another aspect of this turnover of technological staff is the method of examining, marking and assessing the ability of architects and engineers who come before the Local Appointments Commission.  They get higher appreciation if they have widespread experience in different areas which, of course, <Col N="225" /> means that they leave their post in one local authority and take up a post in another.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will permit the Chair to point out that the clock in the chamber has now <Col N="226" /> reached the customary time for adjournment.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 10 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 3rd December, 1969.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>