<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="12" Month="May" Year="1938" Vol="21" No="3" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 12 Bealtaine 1938" DateEnglish="Thursday, 12 May 1938" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="149">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="149" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand an agreement has been arrived at to take item No. 6, Prices Commission (Extension of Functions) Bill, after No. 2, the Finance (Agreement with United Kingdom) Bill, 1938.  This is for the purpose of facilitating the Minister for Industry and Commerce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask how this agreement was arrived at?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>May I suggest that when an agreement is arrived at between different sections in the House in order to facilitate a Minister, the agreement should be unanimously agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFGibbons" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It was through the Clerk that this agreement was made, and he conveyed it in due course to me, so if Senator Douglas's suggestion satisfies Senators, I think we will all be quite happy over it.</P>
      <P>Ordered accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Agreement with United Kingdom (Capital Sum) Bill," RHead="1938 (Certified Money Bill)&mdash;Committee Stage">
    <Title>Agreement with United Kingdom (Capital Sum) Bill, 1938 (Certified Money Bill)&mdash;Committee Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That Section 1 form part of the Bill&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That Section 2 form part of the Bill&rdquo;&mdash;put.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>On this section I want to say that the section provides for the payment of £10,000,000 to the United Kingdom Government, and a later section provides for the issuing of a loan not exceeding £10,000,000 for the purpose of liquidating the dispute with the British; but the amount which we <Col N="150" /> have lost is by no means confined to the £10,000,000.  There has been over £26,000,000 lost, and there has been a considerable loss to the whole population, the farmers and others.  There has been a decrease in production and a decrease in population.  On the other hand, we are glad that the dispute, which reflected no great credit on either of the combatants, should be concluded in this way and for this sum, and we wish the Minister luck in his loan.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 3 and 4 and the title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Final" RHead="Stages">
    <Title>Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be returned to the Dáil&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Message to be sent to the Dáil accordingly.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Motion for Earlier" RHead="Signature">
    <Title>Motion for Earlier Signature.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That, pursuant to sub-section (2º) of Section 2 of Article 25 of the Constitution, Seanad Eireann concurs to the earlier signature by the President of the Agreement with the United Kingdom (Capital Sum) Bill, 1938.</P>
      <P>Question put, and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Finance (Agreement with United Kingdom) Bill, 1938." RHead="(Certified Money Bill) &mdash;Committee Stage">
    <Title>Finance (Agreement with United Kingdom) Bill, 1938.  (Certified Money Bill) &mdash;Committee Stage.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 and 2 agreed to.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to draw the attention of the Minister to a possible difficulty surrounding the operations under Section 3.  The direct effect of the section is that there will be a prohibitive duty on artificial silk which is not of United Kingdom origin.  I do not want to be taken in any way as objecting to that, but the effect will be that the manufacturers and the makers of garments <Col N="151" /> who have been using cheap foreign silks will in future have to use silk which is produced in the United Kingdom. That is part and parcel of this Agreement and it is not an unreasonable provision.  It will make the goods a bit dearer, but my opinion is that it will be a better article and the public will not lose.  But there is this possible danger: that artificial silk can be imported from countries outside the United Kingdom and the duty paid on it; but when that silk is re-exported the duty can be refunded.  It is very important there should be no question that if Japanese silk, which is the cheapest type of artificial silk, is imported into Great Britain and there made into an article of clothing, it will not be possible to call that article an article of British origin.  Because, if that could be done, it would be very serious indeed for certain of the manufacturers here.  I know that in certain certificates of origin which we accepted in the past something varying from 25 per cent. to 75 per cent. of British material and workmanship was admitted as of British origin.  I am connected with a company that is exporting to the Dominions and some of them insist on a certificate of 100 per cent.  British origin.</P>
      <P>I suggest to the Minister&mdash;and I do not think it would be in any way contrary to the Agreement&mdash;that it will be very important that the proof of United Kingdom origin should require a certificate of 100 per cent.  I think if he looks into the matter he will find that, as far as certain British possessions and, I think, certain Dominions are concerned, that is required. I just draw attention to it here, not that I think that the Minister will overlook it, but that it is a thing in which a certain amount of publicity is desirable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the existing law, articles are deemed to be of a particular origin if 25 per cent. of their value results from labour within the particular country concerned; but the Senator will notice that in Section 16 of the measure we are taking power to increase the percentage of labour <Col N="152" /> which must be added in order to qualify an article as coming within the definition of origin.  I think it will be probably found necessary to utilise that power in relation to the class of goods to which the Senator refers.  It would be unfair to the persons engaged in the making of these clothes in this country if British manufacturers of the same class of goods could import Japanese or other cheap cloths and re-export them to this country, getting a draw-back here.  If the existing requirement as to the added percentage of value is not sufficient to exclude goods of that character, these powers in Section 16 will be utilised for that purpose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I would suggest that 25 per cent. is not sufficient to exclude several classes of goods which do not come within that section.  I have proof that under the existing system 25 per cent. is not sufficient.</P>
      <P>Section 3 agreed.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 4 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to secure some elucidation of the point raised yesterday in regard to Article 16 of the Agreement and I think this is the proper section on which to deal with it.  The Minister was not here yesterday and I had, therefore, better re-state, as briefly as I can, the point I want to make.  My reading of Article 16 of this Trade Agreement leads me to the conclusion that it has been imperfectly drafted and that it makes it mandatory on the Government of Eire to charge 3/- per ton on fuel which has its origin in this State.  I know that it is not the intention. I know that, if my impression is accurate, probably it is entirely due to an oversight but we are not competent, as I understand it, to alter a word of these Agreements.  It states that there shall be 3/- per ton charged on fuel the place of origin of which is other than the United Kingdom.  The United Kingdom no longer extends to Eire and I want to be informed whether or not an accurate reading of this Article, as drafted and as printed here, does place upon the Government of Eire <Col N="153" /> the duty of imposing this tax upon fuel of Eire origin.  I do not know whether that has been brought to the Minister's attention or not but I think it is an important point and I think that this section does not clear it. The omission as I see it from the Article is this: that this 3/- per ton should be levied only on imported fuel of other than British origin but it says a duty of 3/- per ton shall be levied on coal, coke and manufactured fuel of other origin than the United Kingdom.  The fuel of this State has an origin other than the United Kingdom.  I hope I have made my point clear on this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Article clearly relates to imported fuel and imported fuel only.  There can be no possible interpretation of it which would oblige us to put a duty of 3/- per ton on fuel of Irish origin.  It certainly was never intended that the Article should have that meaning and there is no intention on the part of the Government to impose such a duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure that it was not intended, but it states specifically that this tax has to be imposed on fuel the origin of which is other than the United Kingdom.  That is as clear as language can be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>In any event it is quite clear that Section 4 of the Bill does not impose a duty on fuel of Irish origin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am dealing with the Article by which this State is bound. It does not specify that this 3/- per ton shall be levied on fuel imported from sources other than the United Kingdom but on fuel of origin other than the United Kingdom.  My contention is that it can be argued, and argued without possibility of its being challenged, that fuel originating in this State is of origin other than the United Kingdom.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not really think, nor do I think now, that the Senator was serious when he brought up that point on the Second Stage of the Bill. I would refer him to line 46 in the <Col N="154" /> section and I would suggest that the word &ldquo;imported&rdquo; which appears in that line covers the whole argument, at least unless the sea washes in at this side of Castlecomer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I would prefer to hear something from the Minister on this matter.  Although Senator Quirke may have a very wide range of knowledge, he is not the competent legislative authority on matters of this kind.  I suggest that there has been an oversight in this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that the Agreement could possibly be interpreted as meaning that there was an obligation upon us to impose a duty upon coal of Irish origin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what it says.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not care what it says.  The Government proposes to act upon its own interpretation of the Article.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>Who is going to interpret it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>We are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>Have you any guarantee that they will agree with your interpretation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that there is much likelihood that they will not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill puts it right. The Government cannot impose such a charge without coming back to us.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 5 and 6 ordered to stand part of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 7 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder would the Minister let us know whether the Second Schedule is intended to impose fresh duties in place of some of the duties that are being removed under Schedule 3?  Under Schedule 3 certain duties are taken off grapes and fruit <Col N="155" /> of other kinds and duties are being put on some of these Articles in Schedule No. 2.  Just take, for instance, one thing, item No. 13 of the Third Schedule, which operates to remove certain duties from grapes completely.  But, item No. 5 of the Second Schedule puts on a duty of 1d. in the pound.  Do I understand the operation of the Third Schedule is to wipe out the duty and the Second Schedule is to impose a varied duty?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The duty imposed by Section 11 of the Finance Act of 1935 is being removed, and this duty upon grapes will operate.  The duty chargeable under Section 5 of the Finance Act of 1937 will operate, as defined in the circumstances set out in the second column of the Second Schedule.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Particularly with regard to the question of fish, the duty is taken off kippered or smoked fish under reference No. 12 of the Third Schedule.  In the Second Schedule a duty is put on fish which is both kippered and smoked.  I wonder if the Minister would let us know what is exactly happening to the fish position? As I understand it, in regard to fish that are the products of the United Kingdom or Canada, a duty of 3d. the pound on filleted fish is being removed and a duty of 1d. the pound is being put on.  Then again, a duty of 1/- the stone is being put on instead of 2/- the stone on fish which are both kippered and smoked.  Does that apply to fish that are smoked only, or fish that are kippered only, and, if not, how do the fish that are simply smoked or the fish that are simply kippered come in?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The existing duty on kippered or smoked fish is to be removed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>One member of the Seanad was raising the question as to the relaxation of duties relating to some particular Waterford industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The duty on kippered or smoked fish that is defined in Section <Col N="156" /> 8 of the Finance Act of 1934 is being removed and this duty of 1/- the stone is being imposed on fish both kippered and smoked.  That will operate in the future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Are kippers unsmoked going to come in as fish with a duty of 1d. the pound?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Unless they come within the definition of fish which are both kippered and smoked, they will not be liable to that duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusOhEochadha" hpid="Séamus O hEochadha Séamus O hEochadha">
      <NameTxt>Séamus O hEochadha</NameTxt>
      <P>One point in connection with this motion is that I have a current issue of the <i>Fishing News</i>, which is issued in England, and it indicates that the fish that are sent over here and that compete with our dry fish are actually imported into England.  Fully 75 per cent. of them are imported, according to this paper. The curers in Ireland, who have established little factories of their own, are very concerned as to whether these fish, which really originated in Iceland or somewhere else may, when properly done up by the English factories, be imported here under this particular Order as English fish.  That is their trouble, and there is the danger that the little factories established during the last four or five years may fall asunder.  It would be a great pity if that should be the case.</P>
      <P>I understand the fish they are curing in Ireland are of a much superior quality to the fish coming in, and, as a result, the demand for our fish has increased considerably.  I hope the officials concerned with the matter will see to it that only fish of English origin, caught by English boats, will be permitted entry.  I do not care if they are caught in English waters or caught outside English waters by English boats, they can be looked upon as English fish, but if they are actually imported into England to the extent of 75 per cent., it would be a great pity that they would be allowed into Ireland practically free of duty, to destroy the factories here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The duty is changed only in respect of fish of British origin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="157" /> So far as fish of non-British origin are concerned, the duties now in operation will continue to operate whether the fish come through Great Britain or not.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister say if fish caught in Iceland and kippered in England will be regarded as of United Kingdom origin?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not answer that straight off.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>Who will have the duty of inquiring into the antecedents of these fish?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Revenue Commissioners will require a certificate of origin to accompany each consignment.</P>
      <P>Section 7 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>In connection with Sections 8 and 9, I should like to know whether a certificate of origin will be required in order to avoid the duty. Will that apply to the parcel post? Manufacturers are not worried about this, but it affects the retailers.  There is some question as to whether a certificate of origin is to apply before the minimum duty can be made applicable. Certain traders may not be so very enthusiastic about sending small packets.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not like to answer that dogmatically.  The remission of the customs entry duty applies in that respect to goods which are shown, to the satisfaction of the Revenue Commissioners, to be grown, produced or manufactured in the United Kingdom.  I presume there is no alternative method of meeting that point than by the production of the certificate of origin.  That is the present practice of the Revenue Commissioners, and it may be presumed it will continue to be their practice.  Possibly the Revenue Commissioners may devise some other method of having their requirements met.  I do not think that is likely, and, therefore, I think the Senator can take it that for a long time to come the requirement <Col N="158" /> of the production of the certificate of origin will remain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>My reason for drawing attention to this matter is that the section sets out &ldquo;solely of British origin.&rdquo;  There is no doubt advantage will not be taken of that for large quantities of goods.  The advantage will assist London stores that advertise and sell their goods here.  I think that is pretty obviously the case.  It is quite probable that a mixed parcel of goods, not solely of British origin, may come in, if this is made too easy, and I think the whole thing wants watching.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Steps which are necessary to ensure that only goods that come within that definition will come in without this customs duty have been taken.</P>
      <P>Sections 8 and 9 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>On Section 10, has an estimate been made of the probable loss to the Revenue of the operations of Sections 8, 9 and 10?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>An estimate of about £35,000 was mentioned at one stage, but whether it is accurate is hard to say.</P>
      <P>Sections 10 and 11 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestHAlton" hpid="Professor Alton Professor Alton">
      <NameTxt>Professor Alton</NameTxt>
      <P>As regards Section 12, which relates to the modification of the rate of motor car duty, will the Minister tell us how many cars are likely to be affected?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It is obviously very difficult to answer that question.  The importation of all assembled motor cars has been prohibited and it is now proposed to limit that prohibition to cars of a value less than £750.  There has been no experience over recent years which would give any indication of what the number of such cars is likely to be, but I should imagine the number will not be very great.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestHAlton" hpid="Professor Alton Professor Alton">
      <NameTxt>Professor Alton</NameTxt>
      <P>About 50?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I hardly think so.</P>
      <P>Section 12 to 18 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="159" /> FIRST SCHEDULE.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the First Schedule stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>On the First Schedule, Sir, I wonder would the Minister give the House a statement as to what exactly the safeguards are likely to be to ensure that certificates will be really confined to articles that are properly to be regarded as of United Kingdom or Canadian origin?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The normal safeguard is a certificate of origin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>By whom?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Generally, by a chamber of commerce, or by whatever body the Revenue Commissioners are prepared to accept as a reputable and responsible body, competent to issue such certificates.  That practice is not a new one.  It has always applied here and also in Great Britain with regard to duties generally, and with regard to any class of goods where there was a differential rate of duty, or, in fact, any class of duty at all, it has generally worked satisfactorily.  Of course, goods exported to Great Britain from this country will also have to have a certificate of origin in the same way, because the British authorities will require to be equally satisfied that these goods are produced in this country and, consequently, liable to free entry.  The practice has been to accept the certificates of chambers of commerce, and I think that that will continue.  The only circumstances under which it would be discontinued, I imagine, would be those in which some chambers of commerce were issuing certificates without proper inquiry or investigation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>With all due respect to the Minister in connection with this matter, I do not think the chamber of commerce has been relied upon generally at all for these certificates. I know that, in the case of goods of British origin, the certificate of origin was signed by the secretary of a manufacturing company and did not have <Col N="160" /> to be verified by a chamber of commerce, but that in the case of foreign goods, or goods from outside Britain, the certificate of the secretary of the manufacturing company had to be countersigned by an official of a chamber of commerce which proved that he was a proper person to sign it, but that did not prove that the chamber of commerce knew anything about the accuracy of the statement. The only thing the chamber of commerce could certify about would be goods which come from a manufacturer. There has always been a very high code in these matters and I have no question that, where the certificate is signed by the secretary of a manufacturing company, it is very rarely wrong.  It is only where the goods are sold retail that there is a danger of abuse&mdash;not always deliberate or intentional abuse&mdash;of the certificates; but I think the Minister will find that it is not necessary to bring your certificate for Great Britain at present before your chambers of commerce, and the only value of the chamber of commerce is in guaranteeing that the person who does sign the certificate is a proper person and competent to sign it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Senator should not draw conclusions from a single experience.  Where a flat rate of duty operated, a certificate of origin was required for certain purposes only, and in such cases no great vigilance was required on the part of the Revenue Commissioners.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I am referring to the matter of getting a preferential duty only.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>In that case, it only means that more vigilance is required on the part of the Revenue Commissioners, and I think they have been more vigilant in connection with such duties.  The same, of course, applies to our goods going out from this country. During the past four or five years they were liable to the higher rate of duty anyway and, consequently, there was not very much <Col N="161" /> necessity for the British authorities to examine them.  The circumstances, however, will be different in the future.  In respect of differential duties, I think the Revenue Commissioners, from time to time, will exercise whatever vigilance is necessary to ensure that only goods entitled to the preferential rates are, in fact, imported under them.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Second and Third Schedules, and the Title of the Bill, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Final" RHead="Stages">
    <Title>Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question: &ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration,&rdquo; put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Question: &ldquo;That the Bill be returned to the Dáil&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Finance (Agreement with the United Kingdom)" RHead="Bill, 1938&mdash;Motion for Earlier Signature">
    <Title>Finance (Agreement with the United Kingdom) Bill, 1938&mdash;Motion for Earlier Signature.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That, pursuant to sub-section (2º) of Section 2 of Article 25 of the Constitution, Seanad Eireann concurs to the earlier signature by the President of the Finance (Agreement with United Kingdom) Bill, 1938.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prices Commission (Extension of Functions)" RHead="Bill, 1938&mdash;Committee Stage">
    <Title>Prices Commission (Extension of Functions) Bill, 1938&mdash;Committee Stage.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>After sub-section (2) to insert a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister may, whenever and so often as he thinks fit, request the Commission to report, as respects any class or kind of goods, on the extent (if any) to which the cost of economical and efficient production is higher than in the United Kingdom and to make recommendations as to the steps necessary to secure for producers and manufacturers <Col N="162" /> full opportunity of reasonable competition in the sale of such goods to Great Britain.</P>
    <P>I thought that somebody was going to raise this matter on the previous sub-section.  My object in putting down this amendment was to raise a point which I was not sure I could raise, strictly speaking, within the Bill itself unless I put down an amendment.  I have felt for some time that, if we were going to get a reduction of prices and a greater variety from our manufacturers, it was of the utmost importance that they, in the course of a reasonable time, should develop some export trade, and that nothing would be better for the majority of our manufacturers&mdash;particularly those who have grown up in the last four or five years&mdash;than if they could get into a market, such as, let us say, Great Britain, and sell some of their products.  Now, assuming that, as I maintain is the case in regard to a very large percentage of Irish manufactured products, the quality is good and that they have reached a reasonable standard of proficiency, the only thing that prevents that export is the price.  In some cases, that price may be due to the manufacturer's own fault; in other cases, it may be due to circumstances which are immediately or substantially beyond his control, and it seems to me that, if you are going to have an enquiry by the Prices Commission and a review of existing tariffs, if that review is to be on the basis set out in Article 8 of the Agreement, with which we are all familiar and which I need not read out now, the Prices Commission, of necessity, under the terms of Article 8, will have to investigate to some extent the causes for increased cost of production here and make allowances for such of those as are consistent with efficient production.  I think that is the phrase used.</P>
    <P>The Minister may say that he has the powers in the Bill to get this report.  If so I am satisfied.  It seems to me desirable that in this report, whether it is made public or not, the Minister should have information in the case of those industries sent directly to him as to what the Prices Commission, which is an impartial <Col N="163" /> body, considers are the differences in the cost of production here as against Great Britain.  In other words, what would have to be made up to put the Irish manufacturer in the same position of &ldquo;reasonable competition&rdquo; in Great Britain which it is intended, except in the case of new industries, to provide for the British manufacturer here.  I think if that were ascertained it might be found wise policy, at any rate for a limited period, for the Government to consider whether some assistance should be given to make up that difference.  There are quite a number of ways in which that assistance might be given, whether by means of licences, a reduction of certain taxes or certain allowances or even a bounty if that were found desirable, though I am not in favour of an ordinary export bounty.  If that were done it could only be done within the spirit and terms of the Agreement, and only to such extent as would enable the Irish manufacturer to compete on even terms. There could be no such question as getting up an export trade by paying for it out of the pockets of the people here.</P>
    <P>If this Agreement should, following an examination by the Prices Commission, result, as I think it must do if it is going to have any effect at all from the British point of view, in an increase of the imports of British manufactured goods, it is not at all impossible that at the lower duty the actual revenue from this may be higher.  My suggestion is that the Government might carefully watch that situation, and might ear-mark such increased duty as they may receive on these particular commodities, and use that sum for the assistance of the commodities that obtain some proportion of an export trade.  It is quite common to find that everybody who complains here of the cost of production begins by speaking of wages.  I think that, in some cases, the wages paid here are proportionately higher when compared with Great Britain, but I doubt if any Irish manufacturer wants to get wages down to the absolute rock bottom.  There are quite a number of other things besides wages.  Paper, for instance, is very much higher, and a number of other things necessary for an export trade.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="164" /> I do not know the position in Great Britain, but I do know that in the case of manufacturers here who are competing directly with Northern Ireland, they are faced by the fact that the factories in Northern Ireland are derated.  I know quite well that our Minister for Finance would be horrified if he heard that I intended to start a campaign, even if I were able to do it, for the derating of factories.  I suggest that it might be possible to provide an allowance to meet that to the extent to which there was export.  I suggest that if this Agreement is to be made work, one way of giving wise and sane protection to our industries would be to help them to get some export trade. It would be good for them also in this way, that if with a concession equal to the proper difference in the cost of efficient production they were not able to build up an export trade, then I am afraid they would have to face the fact that there was something wrong elsewhere, and to that extent it would be good for the community.</P>
    <P>If the Minister thinks that he has this power already, then what I am suggesting is that in the case of industries in which there was a hope of building up an export trade, he should ask for this additional information from the Prices Commission when they are reviewing the tariffs which, in view of the terms of Article 8, means reviewing the industry as a whole.  It is with a view to drawing attention to that as a possibility that I put down the amendment.  If the Minister thinks it is not necessary, then I am not going to press it.  I would not, of course, have put down an amendment to any Bill which was part and parcel of the Agreement.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment introduces something which the Senator, I think, has not provided for.  If accepted, it would mean introducing into the Bill the term &ldquo;United Kingdom&rdquo;.  That, I think, would require an amendment of the definitions. In the two Bills that we have dealt with, the term &ldquo;United Kingdom&rdquo; is in disagreement.  United Kingdom, in one, is defined as &ldquo;Great Britain, Northern Ireland, the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man.&rdquo;  In the <Col N="165" /> other the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man are deleted.  I simply want to call attention to the fact that if the amendment were accepted, it would, in my opinion, involve the moving of a further amendment on the Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know if Senator Douglas wishes to initiate a discussion on the advisability of putting an export bounty on industrial products.  I do not think this is altogether a suitable time to discuss the practicability or advisability of adopting that as a policy.  The question which the Senator wishes to have considered is whether it is desirable by any such means to assist manufacturers to export their products to the United Kingdom.  That is a fairly wide question, and I doubt very much if we would gain wisdom by debating it at length now.  I am clear in my mind that it is not desirable to ask the Prices Commission to deal with that question or to submit recommendations relating to it.  That, of course, is the direct purpose of the Senator's amendment.  I think that the Prices Commission will have a very considerable volume of work to discharge both in consequence of the enactment of this measure and of the Trade Agreement as a whole, and also arising out of its original functions as a Prices Commission, and that it would be unwise to put upon it the further task which the Senator contemplates.</P>
      <P>In any event, I doubt very much if the making of a decision, whether or not to give assistance in the export of industrial products, could be facilitated by an inquiry of the kind which the Prices Commission would ordinarily undertake.  It has been my experience that in matters of that kind it is necessary to meet directly the industrialists concerned, and discuss not merely the measure of assistance which they may require but also the extent to which they are going to take advantage of it, and make detailed arrangements involving a number of different possibilities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That type of investigation, of which <Col N="166" /> we have had some limited experience, is a very different type of business from holding a public inquiry such as the Prices Commission would ordinarily hold, nor do I think that the Prices Commission would get from such an inquiry the really vital information on which a decision would have to be based.  It is extremely improbable that the Government can undertake at an early date, as a general policy, the giving of financial assistance, direct or indirect, to industrial exporters.  If it should decide to proceed upon that line, I think we would not bring the Prices Commission into the picture as an essential part of the machinery which would have to be operated before a decision could be made.  The Prices Commission can only get information as a result of evidence submitted to it, and the information procurable in that particular way is not precisely the type of information necessary for dealing with such matters as the Senator has in mind.</P>
    <P>I suggest that the Senator should not press his amendment, but I think it is necessary to bear in mind that it is desirable to keep upon industrialists themselves certain obligations in the matter of their costs, and that the mere suggestion that all their difficulties might be overcome in the internal market by means of tariffs and, in the export market, by means of bounties, is not going to make it easier for them to meet demands from the trade union representatives of their workers or in other ways deal with circumstances which might occasion an increase in their production costs.  It is much better that the industrialists of the country should understand that there is a direct obligation on them, from which they are not going to be relieved by Government action, to keep their costs at the minimum in the interest of the consumers in this market as well as for the purpose of reaching that degree of efficiency which would permit of an export business being contemplated. Therefore, even though in very exceptional cases the extension of State assistance to the export trade is not ruled out, it is, I think, very undesirable that the idea should go <Col N="167" /> abroad that any general policy of that kind is likely to be adopted.  In fact, I think we have got to move in the other direction and, particularly in relation to those industries which might come within the description &ldquo;fully established&rdquo;&mdash;the description used in the Trade Agreement&mdash;impress upon them the necessity for overhauling their existing costs and effecting whatever reduction is possible without hardship.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to press the amendment, but I want to explain that I did not suggest anything such as the Minister has envisaged.  I made quite clear that there were two types of difference in costs&mdash;one for which the manufacturer might be held responsible and the other for which he could not be held responsible.  I instanced derating in a competitive country.  The manufacturer could not possibly be held responsible for that difference.  I tried to make clear that there were two distinct types of difference in connection with this matter.  I agree with the Minister in principle, but I believe that there are certain things for which the State is responsible. I am not in favour of giving assistance for anything more than that which is attributable to conditions over which the manufacturer has no control.  I do not think that, in the long run, you can build up industries on any other basis.  You cannot build them up on high prices or by bringing them up in cotton-wool.  If the Minister will carefully read what I said, he will find that I did not suggest what he thinks.  The only reason I suggested the Prices Commission in this connection was that it would have a great deal to do with this particular class of work.  I thought that they might be able to do this in the course of their work if the Minister had the details given to them.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>On the section, I mislaid my copy of the Bill and did not come across it until last night, when it was late to table an amendment. If I had had an opportunity, I should <Col N="168" /> have moved to delete certain words from line 45.  Sub-section (4) reads:</P>
      <P>Where a review is being made under this section by the commission in relation to goods of a particular class or kind, and any member of the commission is personally interested in any business selling goods of that class or kind, such member shall inform the Minister of the nature and extent of his interest, and shall not, unless authorised by the Minister so to do, act as a member of the commission for the purposes of such review.</P>
      <P>The words I would propose to delete, had I been able to table an amendment, would be, &ldquo;unless authorised by the Minister so to do&rdquo;.  I cannot visualise any circumstances or any contingency which would justify an interested party sitting on the board and acting as an adjudicator in a review of this kind.  The Minister may be able to indicate some contingency where that might be tolerated or justified. At the moment I cannot see any reason for the provision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Sub-section (4) of Section 2 is taken from the Prices Commission Act.  The same sub-section appears in the relevant section of that Act.  I agree with the Senator that any member of the commission who has an interest in any business selling goods of the class or kind the subject of investigation should not act on the commission when a review in relation to these goods was in progress unless that interest was of such a very slight nature that it could not be held that the member was likely to be biassed or prejudiced in consequence of it.  If the interest of the member in the business was only of a very slight nature, I think circumstances might exist which would make it desirable for him to continue to act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a limited personnel in the Prices Commission.  The members are chosen because of their special qualities. They are likely to gain, in the course of time, experience which will be very useful to them and which newcomers could not easily acquire.  It is obviously desirable that there should not be frequent changes in the personnel <Col N="169" /> of the commission.  It is desirable that the same body of people should deal with all the types of investigation, if possible.  If we were to adopt the amendment the Senator suggests, we should have to face the possibility of some one member, or perhaps more members, of the commission dropping out in respect of every investigation because of some slight interest in a business dealing with the goods concerned.  If the interest is a slight one, I think no danger is involved.  If it is not a slight one, then the Minister will not, in prudence, give the consent the sub-section visualises.</P>
    <P>I think I can assure the Senator that, so far as I am concerned, that authorisation would not be given in any case in which there was the slightest possibility of a member of the commission being influenced in his judgment by personal considerations.  I do not know that any member of the commission would allow himself to be so influenced, but if there is the slightest danger of it, or the slightest possibility of people suspecting that that was the case, the authorisation would not be given.  It is only where the interest is a slight one&mdash;the fact that some distant relative was engaged in the business, or an individual was a very small shareholder in one concern engaged in one business in which there was a large number of other concerns&mdash;that we might allow a person to continue to act because of his personal qualities and experience and the desirability of having them in carrying on the work of the commission.  If, however, the interest were any greater, if it were sufficient to lead people to think that he might be influenced by that personal interest, the authorisation should not, and would not, be given.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a matter entirely for the Minister.  No one questions the good intentions of the present Minister, but he may not be always Minister. We do not know who might follow, and we have no guarantee as to how the term &ldquo;slight interest&rdquo; might be interpreted. I do not see that the argument that changes might be necessary if my suggestion were accepted is very <Col N="170" /> convincing.  I think it would be quite possible to arrange to have a panel of commissioners who would be called on to act in the event of a vacancy being created by some such contingency.  I have not moved an amendment, and I have no opportunity of doing so, and, therefore, I cannot press this, but I think it is very unwise to have a loophole of this kind in a matter which is going vitally to affect trade between two countries.  It opens a loophole from which very great abuses might emerge, and I do not think it is a desirable phrase to have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>There is, of course, no provision in the Bill for a panel, but there is power to add additional members for the purpose of any investigation, under Section 10 of the Control of Prices Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Article 8 says that representatives of British manufacturers will be given an opportunity of appearing before the Prices Commission at any of these examinations in which their firms are interested.  The Prices Commission has certain powers under the Control of Prices Act in dealing with these inquiries.  A series of powers is given to them under Section 17 of the Control of Prices Act, which says that the Commission inquiring under this Act will be given power to enforce the attendance of witnesses, to examine them on oath, and to compel them to produce documents. It provides certain powers such as are vested in the High Court for the punishing of people who either do not attend when summoned or, being present, refuse to take an oath or to produce any documents.  I should like the Minister to say whether it is the intention that these powers will apply to all persons appearing before the Prices Commission, whether they represent English firms or Irish firms.  I take it that persons on behalf of English manufacturers who would be appearing before the Prices Commission at inquiries such as these would be either Irish people representing them here or people resident here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that these powers do not extend to any person <Col N="171" /> residing outside the jurisdiction, but I am not clear that they would even be necessary.  Clearly, in the case of a tariff review undertaken on the suggestion of the British Government, in which British manufacturing or exporting firms were interested, if the representatives of these manufacturers or exporters came before the Prices Commission the extent to which they are going to impress the Commission will depend upon their readiness to produce whatever information and data the Commission may require.  If they were to refuse to supply that information, or to act in such a way as to create doubts as to the truth of their statements, the validity of their position or their own <i>bona fides</i>, the Commission would refuse to hear them or would place no credence in what they said.  The power to compel the production of witnesses and documents would apply only in respect of our own nationals, but there is another power &mdash;not a legal power, but a power equally effective&mdash;to procure a similar service from outsiders coming in the form of plaintiffs before the Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister anticipate that in asking for an investigation of the commodities of any particular industry, the British Government, in forwarding the application, would forward a case prepared by the British manufacturers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so.  We have had no experience as to how this is going to operate.  We undertook that we would have this review of tariffs carried out by the Prices Commission and we undertook to allow British manufacturers to appear before the commission and to give evidence in respect of any investigation in which they were interested.  I do not think that was a very great concession on our part because the Prices Commission, in doing its work, would obviously seek to get all the information it could and would require such information in order to produce a valuable report.  It was then suggested that the review should be undertaken first in respect <Col N="172" /> of those classes of goods for which the British Government desires early consideration. We accepted that because we thought it would prove a convenience to ourselves.  If the British manufacturers had to come direct here, a large number of them would come at once and we would have the difficult, and perhaps invidious, task of choosing the firms which should have priority. We thought it much better if the British Government would, in the first instance, put them, as it were, in a queue, and ask us to deal with particular items.  I did not understand, nor do I contemplate, that the British Government will itself prepare a case for the modification of a duty or the removal of some import restriction. What, in fact, will happen is that the Prices Commission will commence a review of the position and, in pursuance of that review, will get the evidence of British manufacturers as well as that of home producers and others interested, and will then report whether, having regard to the principle enshrined in Article 8 of the Agreement, any alteration of the duty should be effected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the Agreement provides only that the British manufacturers should have a right of audience.  To my mind, that is quite a different thing from giving them the right to send counsel and to produce a case as in a court which, I think, would be highly undesirable. It would be undesirable for various reasons.  It would be a minimum of assistance to the commission and liable also to put Irish manufacturers to expense if they were, as I see it, foolish enough to think of doing the same. The secretary of one group of manufacturers, of which I am not a member, told me that one investigation before the Tariff Commission cost that group £3,000.  It seems hard to believe that, but he is a perfectly reputable person. If you are going to have this as a court of law, in which British manufacturers will be represented by counsel&mdash;and it is well known that the Federation of British Manufacturers is a very wealthy body&mdash;I think you will defeat your purpose. <Col N="173" /> I assume that nothing of the kind was promised or intended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is aware that the Prices Commission, as such, have refused to hear counsel.  Their attitude was quite reasonable.  They did not want to appear before them somebody who knew less about the business than themselves and who was merely speaking from a brief.  They wanted people to give information so that they could cross-examine them and get the information in the form in which they wanted it.  I was pressed in the Dáil to urge on the Commission that they should allow counsel to appear in respect of these tariff applications, but I replied, as I must reply now, that it is a matter for the Commission themselves.  They are entitled by statute to determine their procedure and I propose to leave that position unchanged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GearoidOSullivan" hpid="Mr. O'Sullivan Mr. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is one point I want the Minister to make clear. Is the British manufacturer coming over to make his case before the Prices Commission in a better position than the Irish manufacturer who may have to apply?  In other words, must the Irish manufacturer produce books, documents and witnesses, give evidence on oath and be sent to jail, if necessary, while the Britisher will get off and have no responsibility of that type?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Any person summoned by the Prices Commission to give evidence and refusing to give evidence, or summoned to produce documents and refusing to produce those documents, would be liable to the penalties which the principal Act prescribes.  A British manufacturer could, of course, refuse to come or could refuse to give evidence.  We are not compelling them to do so.  We give the right of audience before the Commission if they choose to exercise it.  But the Prices Commission will be endeavouring to get whatever information they can so as to enable them to discharge their functions.  If they can get that information they will have it and act on it.  If they get information <Col N="174" /> from the Irish manufacturer only then it is on the basis of that information they will make their recommendation or report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GearoidOSullivan" hpid="Mr. O'Sullivan Mr. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill enacts the giving of power to the British manufacturer which the Irish manufacturer has not.  The Irish manufacturer may not refuse to give evidence. The British manufacturer, say of paper, may refuse to give evidence; he may come in but he may refuse to be sworn.  He may refuse to produce his accounts and he cannot be punished as the Irish manufacturer&mdash; say the Clondalkin Paper Mills&mdash;can be punished.  The Minister, I am afraid, has not made the position clear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>But the British manufacturer who with that intention came to the Prices Commission to get them to recommend the reduction in the duty of his goods would be acting foolishly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GearoidOSullivan" hpid="Mr. O'Sullivan Mr. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, I am afraid, is thinking of the effect of such.  I am thinking of the equity. I think both manufacturers, Irish and British, should come in on an equal status.  When I say both manufacturers I mean the representatives of both manufacturers.  As the matter has been raised, may I say that I think the Minister has been unduly indiscreet in his reference to the matter of representation of persons before the Prices Commission by counsel.  I happen to be nominated on the Seanad by the General Council of the Bar of Ireland and I want to take this opportunity of objecting to his remark.  The Minister said counsel would be speaking from a brief and they want someone who knows more about it.  I think the same could be said about the police court and other courts.  The criminal knows much more about the crime than does the counsel.  The police know much more about it than counsel who prosecutes.  The reference by the Minister was rather facetious and casual.  In making that remark he was not judicious and I want to make a protest here and now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="175" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I had no intention of saying anything which in the words of Fluther Good would be derogatory to the Senator's profession.  The Prices Commission are there to get facts.  It will have nothing to do with the law.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That Section 2 stand part of the Bill,&rdquo; put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:&mdash;</P>
      <P>New section.  Before Section 3, to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>3. The power contained in Section 1 of the Emergency Imposition of Duties Act, 1932 (No. 16 of 1932) to vary by order of the Executive Council any Customs Duty in force shall not apply in the case of the variation of any Customs Duty which is recommended by the Commission in a report under the foregoing section.</P>
      <P>Briefly, the effect of the amendment, if passed, would be that where the Prices Commission recommended a variation in the tariff of any particular article or class of goods that variation would take place through means of legislation being presented to the Oireachtas.  At the present time there is power in the Executive Council to issue an order under the Emergency Imposition of Duties Act, 1932, and the variation would take place forthwith. I do not know whether it would ever come before the Seanad.  When the Act was passed it contemplated only the Dáil.  Even before the Dáil that order would not necessarily come for discussion inside a period of four, five or six months.  The limit would be eight months.  Now the Emergency Imposition of Duties Act was passed under certain circumstances.  When introducing the Bill on the 14th July, 1932&mdash;column 1004, Volume 43 of Dáil Debates&mdash;the Minister for Finance said:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The powers which we are seeking are wide; they are sweeping.  I do not want to disguise that fact either from the Oireachtas or from the people of the country.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Earlier in the debate when introducing the measure, the Minister for Finance said:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="176" />&ldquo;First of all, this measure is not introduced in a spirit of retaliation or aggression.  It is brought in primarily as a measure of self-defence.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That is, the Minister says, a measure of self-defence.  It is to defend the Irish manufacturer against penal duties.  In column 1187, Volume 43, of Dáil Debates the Minister said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The purpose of this Bill is not to wage economic war upon them, not to destroy England's industry, but to safeguard our own people against hunger and want, to open up new markets for our goods if the British market is closed to us....&rdquo;</P>
    <P>In the circumstances in which the Minister for Finance found himself compelled to speak in these terms power was given by Executive Council Order to impose tariffs.  The order did not come before the Dáil for a period of eight months.  I am suggesting that we are now reversing the process that has been gone through.  At any rate, I would like to say that while the Emergency Imposition of Duty Act was being passed to deal with an emergency, it has now become the natural machinery for use by the Executive Council for imposing customs duties.  It is the normal thing now; once when it was proposed to put duty on an article legislation was introduced.  The normal thing is to make the order, and when a number of these orders have been collected together they are put into a Bill which is passed through the House.  I do not question the advisability of continuing that.  It would be advisable perhaps that the powers might now be regarded as emergency powers and the Act might be dropped.  I do not go so far as that; but under this Agreement in order to give the British manufacturer a chance of competing on fair terms here, the tariffs are now being lowered.</P>
    <P>The Irish manufacturer thinks that the weapon that was formed to protect him in different circumstances should not now be used to remove whatever protection has been given to him. That protection gave him satisfaction, and having the operation of that tariff discussed by the Oireachtas before the duty was produced gave him some protection. <Col N="177" /> Attention was called in the debate that went on here yesterday to the difference in the phraseology in the section dealing with this part of the Agreement.  There is a difference between our present Agreement and the Agreements with Canada and the Dominions.  There was a definite reference to that matter.  Where these duties are being varied under the present circumstances I think it would ease the position if the Minister did not take powers by order to vary them. If legislation were necessary there would be the Oireachtas with which to deal.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Mulcahy said that he did not propose now to discuss the operations of the Emergency Imposition of Duties Act, 1932. Neither do I.  Experience has shown that the particular method of dealing with new customs impositions for which that Act provides has proved more suitable in practice than the method which preceded it.  However, I do not know that every Senator would agree with that point of view. The old arrangements under which all changes in customs were brought into operation at the time of the Budget and implemented in the Finance Act would not prove satisfactory at all, in the circumstances of the past few years, apart altogether from the dispute with Great Britain.  These years were years of industrial development and many new projects were brought in most of which involved changes in the customs tariffs.  In the circumstances of this country, which is a small country, everybody knows what is happening and it is not possible to prevent information leaking out amongst the business community.  If duty on an article had been sanctioned by the Government and if that leaked out there was the danger of forestalling the tariff by imports of goods which might be very heavy and which might very well nullify or destroy the immediate possibility of getting an industry under way.  For that reason I think there should be power to deal expeditiously and at various times with the imposition of customs duties. The name of this Act may no longer <Col N="178" /> be applicable to the present circumstances. The machinery has proved workable and the consensus of opinion would favour maintaining it.  That however is a very different question from that to which the Senator's amendment is directed.</P>
      <P>I agree that in the ordinary course the recommendations of the Prices Commission should be discussed in the Dáil, and that the motion to give effect to the recommendation should be brought before the Dáil for that purpose.  I agree, because in a number of cases, at any rate, the recommendation of the Prices Commission would involve, not an increase, but a reduction in the existing duties and, because of that fact, urgency would not arise.  In fact, when reducing a duty it is always necessary to give some notice to interested parties so that stocks may be cleared, orders cancelled and other arrangements made to avoid loss.  There may, however, be some cases in which the recommendation of the Prices Commission would involve an increase in duties, such as when a customs duty is being substituted for import restrictions. Certain of these recommendations may then involve an increase in the customs duties.  It may be necessary to move fairly quickly in such matters because, of course, fairly considerable publicity will be given to the proceedings before the Prices Commission and people will be withholding orders or delaying purchasing or in other ways anticipating the position resulting from the recommendation of the Prices Commission.  The Dáil may not be meeting or, for some other reason, it may not be possible to act speedily otherwise than by using the powers in the Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The same would apply in the case of possible reductions of duty during periods of the year in which the Dáil would not be meeting.  If everybody knew that a reduction was coming but that the reduction could not be effected for quite a protracted period until the Dáil had assembled, there might be considerable trade dislocation. It might be desirable to prevent that arising by acting on the recommendation <Col N="179" /> of the Prices Commission. In the circumstances it is desirable that we should retain, in relation to the recommendation of the Prices Commission, the powers of this Act so long as the powers of this Act exist at all.  I think it is unlikely that it will be repealed but that is a matter of policy which may arise in another connection.  So long as these powers are there at all, we should have authority to utilise them in respect of a Prices Commission recommendation. In the ordinary course there will be plenty of time to proceed by the slower procedure&mdash;by way of a Money Resolution followed by a Finance Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Do I understand the Minister to say that he is going to make the fullest use of the Emergency Imposition of Duties Act powers in dealing with these changes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>We propose to use them where expeditious action is required, but, in the ordinary course, where the Prices Commission recommend a modification of a particular duty, I think it would be desirable to proceed by the slower method so that the public would have adequate notice of what was coming.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Sections 3, 4, and the Title ordered to stand part of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Bill reported.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prices Commission (Extension of Functions)" RHead="Bill, 1938. - Motion for Earlier Signature">
    <Title>Prices Commission (Extension of Functions) Bill, 1938. - Motion for Earlier Signature.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That pursuant to sub-section 20 of Section 2 of Article 25 of the Constitution, Seanad Eireann concurs to the earlier signature by the President of the Prices Commission (Extension of Functions) Bill, 1938.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prices Commission (Extension of Functions) Bill, 1938. -" RHead="Agricultural Produce (Cereals) Bill, 1938&mdash;Committee">
    <Title>Prices Commission (Extension of Functions) Bill, 1938. - Agricultural Produce (Cereals) Bill, 1938&mdash;Committee.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="180" /> Sections 1 to 9 ordered to stand part of the Bill.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 10 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to paragraph (b) of this section, I should like a little enlightenment from the Minister as to what exactly that paragraph applies.  Does it mean that farmers or people living close to the Border can go across the Border and take home a baker's loaf, or two and a half baker's loaves, or to what commodities exactly is this paragraph meant to apply?  I think it would be a welcome relief for some of them if that were so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan) James Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I should say, perhaps, that this Bill appears a very long measure to deal with a very simple subject, but that is because it re-enacts a great deal of old legislation on the subject.  Section 10 is a re-enactment of an old provision. It really relates to a traveller coming into the country who might have a cake or a bun, or it could relate to goods which are sent to a person.  It does not relate to a person who shops across the Border.  That would be dealt with more in Section 20.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Baxter raised the question of a person who brought in a couple of 2 lb. loaves. The section says that it shall not be lawful for any person to import any commodity in the preparation of which wheat or any product of wheat is used except he is licensed.  I should like to ask the Minister if, in the Trade Agreement, the question of bread was envisaged at all, because if it was the intention to issue a licence for the import of bread, say, by bakers' vans coming in from the North of Ireland to enable them to distribute that bread in Border counties, I think very serious consideration should have been given to that matter before that was agreed to.  When bread was stopped coming in, particularly over the Border, it was suggested that a large number of new bakeries were being established along the Border.  The fact is that the production <Col N="181" /> of bread has gone down very considerably in the country.  The last information we have is for 1936, when the production of bread had gone down by the equivalent of 6,000,000 2-lb. loaves.  Prior to that there was an import of the equivalent of 12,000,000 2-lb. loaves.  With a reduction of the equivalent of 18,000,000 2-lb. loaves, and with actual production gone down so substantially, it would be a very serious blow to any of the new bakeries operating along the Border if bread imports were allowed to come in in a substantial way.  I should like to ask the Minister if there is any contemplation of that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no contemplation of bread being allowed in at all, except, as pointed out in this section, bread coming in in a passenger's baggage.  The second case is where it comes in as a gift by post.  That does not allow of bread coming into this country in a commercial way across the Border.  Section 20 deals with feeding stuffs, so that bread is not permitted in under this measure.</P>
      <P>Sections 10 to 15 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianORourke" hpid="Mr. O'Rourke Mr. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>On Section 16, I should like to know what is the policy of the Minister in regard to the maize-meal mixture?  The farmers of the country, and particularly the farmers in my county, are very interested in this matter.  We expect that the Minister will do away with the maize-meal mixture altogether.  I am not questioning whether or not it was necessary during the economic war, but I do know that it would be most objectionable to continue it.  My county is a very large pig-producing county, and the people there expect the Minister to arrange so that they will be able to take pigs across the Border and sell them in the Northern Ireland markets. We are satisfied that the farmers in the northern counties are getting better treatment in regard to the purchase of grain and other feeding stuffs and are getting better prices than we are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We hope, for one thing, that the Minister will do away with the maize-meal mixture.  It might have been necessary two or three years ago, but I <Col N="182" /> think it is time now that the farmers should be enabled to get cheaper and better feeding stuffs.  The numbers of fowl and pigs in this country have gone down by a quarter or one-third, and I believe that that reduction in numbers was caused by the imposition of the higher prices for this mixture and its inferior quality.  In the very beginning the Government's policy did a lot of harm.  It turned people off feeding animals altogether.  It is essential that the people of the country should know as soon as possible what the Government intend to do, so that those who are interested can go in again for pig breeding&mdash;pig producing and poultry rearing.  At the present time in County Monaghan hundreds of pigs cannot be sold.  The Pigs Marketing Board have a big advertisement about pig prices and a guaranteed market. As against that there are farmers who tell me that they cannot sell their pigs.</P>
    <P>Presumably the situation will be altered in the course of a few weeks. It certainly is not encouraging for men to breed pigs if the conditions are to be the same as they are at the present time.  If we are to extend our pig production&mdash;and we hope we soon will be able to&mdash;then it is necessary for the Government to act quickly.  We should have twice as many pigs and fowl as we have at the moment.  There is money to be made out of the industry if we have free access to the English markets.  If we could get the pure maize meal the same as the people in Country Armagh, and if we could get the same price as they do, we would go in very largely for pig production and poultry rearing.  Is there to be any change in the policy of the Minister as regards the maize-meal mixture, or is the present position to be allowed to remain?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid Senator O'Rourke has raised a large number of very big questions, any one of which might be usefully debated for a few hours.  I hope, however, that it will not lead to any discord in the Seanad if I answer a few of the points raised. I think Senator O'Rourke has begged the question many times in his speech. <Col N="183" /> He has assumed that the price of our pigs is less than in the North; he has assumed that the price of the maize-meal mixture is higher than in Northern Ireland, and that it is a worse feed than what they have up there.  In every one of these things I will disagree with him.  If the Senator gets the published prices in regard to these matters he will find that our prices are more favourable than those in the North.  If he will look up the price of maize he will find the Mark Lane price is £8 3s. Od. per ton for the whole maize.  Senator O'Rourke is interested in the feeding of pigs.  I know that I can buy feeding stuff in Dublin for almost as low at £8 3s. per ton, and that is certainly not giving the miller very much on his work.</P>
      <P>I saw the millers and I asked them if we were to stop the mixture, to what extent would the price of ground maize go down?  They told me that it would not go down at all; there would be no reduction in price.  At any rate, we could not consider any change in the maize-meal mixture until the end of the cereal year, because a number of maize-meal millers and merchants purchased oats and barley on the understanding that they would be absorbed during the cereal year, so that there could not be any change made until the end of August.  At that time I will be open to consider any proposition, even to go so far as to alter radically the whole maize-meal mixture scheme. I would not encourage the farmers to think that they would have food stuffs cheaper when that occurs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senators interested in the subject know that when a pig is fed it must get something besides the mixture or maize.  It gets bran and pollard and meat meal, and when the mixture is made up I think our ration for a pig is cheaper than in the north.  We have cheaper bran and pollard.  We will now allow bran and pollard in from Great Britain and I will guarantee that it will not come in because it cannot come in at the price.  Our price is too low and therefore it will be proved to farmers and others that what I have been saying is correct&mdash;that our bran and pollard are lower than in England. Our meat meal is lower than in Great <Col N="184" /> Britain or in Northern Ireland.  When the maize-meal mixture was used, our material for pig feeding was lower and at the same time we were getting a better price.  It is not true to say that our pigs went down for that cause.</P>
    <P>Everybody who can go back a period of 50 years knows that there always has been a cycle in the number of pigs. Every three years they are up and for the next three years they are down. The fact of Fianna Fáil coming in did nothing to alter that condition of affairs.  Neither did the advent of the Fine Gael Government alter conditions. Even when the British Government was here, there was no change. Pigs are on the up-grade now, and whether Fianna Fáil remains in office or whether Fine Gael comes into power, you will find that there will be the ordinary cycle, as I said, in which they will go up for a while and then, after a few years, go down again.  Nobody can explain why that is so, but it is a fact nevertheless, and nobody has been able to solve the problem.</P>
    <P>With regard to Senator O'Rourke's complaint, I am afraid that any modification of the maize-meal mixture scheme would not come into force until the end of August, but I do not think any hardship will be created in the meantime and, as I have said, I shall then be open to consider any suggestion that may be put up&mdash;whether to modify the maize-meal mixture scheme or to drop it altogether, I do not know, but I shall be open to consider any scheme that may be put up.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to delay the House or the Minister in a discussion on this matter, because we know our respective points of view with regard to it; but I think the Minister ought to know, just as well as Senator O'Rourke and I know, that the pig population in this country began to drop in or about 1933.  It was lower in 1933, in fact, than it has been for a great number of years&mdash;I think it was actually lower than it was last year, when it was much lower than it has been for five or six years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>But it was up again in 1935.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="185" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>The figure went up for a period, but there is no doubt that the introduction of the maize-meal mixture created a great deal of prejudice in the minds of our farmers.  I am speaking now of our small farmers who were engaged in pork raising by the mixing of maize with home-grown products, such as potatoes and skim milk.  The Minister must remember that when Senator O'Rourke and I are talking of pig raising, we are not talking of it in terms of the man who raises 50 or 100 pigs, but of the small farmer raising six or seven or eight, or even ten pigs, and, in the case of these small farmers in the past, the pigs were raised partly on what the farmer produced on his own farm and partly in conjunction with the imported product.</P>
      <P>I am afraid you will not convince the ordinary farmer in my county or counties such as mine that the introduction of the maize-meal mixture was not to the detriment of speedily finished pork.  As to the actual value of the particular grade of pig when you bring it to the market, that is another matter and I shall not debate it now.  Simultaneously with the introduction of your maize-meal mixture, however, you had also the position when we were shut out from our Northern markets, from Derry and Belfast, where we had been sending a great deal of our pork.  The result is revealed in County Monaghan at the present moment where the farmers are in a kind of panic and cannot get away with their pigs.  The Minister has referred to the rise and drop in pig population going in cycles.  All I can say with regard to that is that it is very strange that, while it was dropping here, it was going up and up in the Six Counties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Not now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>It may not be at the moment, but at the period of which I speak, the figure had considerably decreased here from what it had been in 1931, whereas it had increased, by about 30 per cent., in the Six Counties over what it had been in 1931.  I have not got the exact figures at the moment, but that is approximately <Col N="186" /> correct.  That is something for which the Minister will find it hard to give an explanation when he talks of the pig population going up and down in cycles.</P>
      <P>Then, when the Minister tells us that they have certain commitments to the grain growers that they cannot get out of until the end of August, of course one can understand that, but I hope that the whole position will be reconsidered with regard to the commitments to the grain growers in the future, and that the pig producers will not have to carry the grain growers on their backs.  It should be possible for us to be able to get cheaper feeding stuffs in the future. If we are going to compete with the fellow in the Six Counties, we have got to be able to get our meals and feeding stuffs cheaper.  We know that the relationship between the prices here and the prices in the Six Counties is not what it was for four years, but those of us who have been examining those figures over four years, week after week, know quite well that the prices here were much dearer than in the Six Counties, and that sometimes the materials here were as much as £1 a ton above the price at which the people in the Six Counties could buy their materials.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ChrisMByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to what has been said by the last speakers, Sir, I hope that the Minister will not overlook the interests of a very large number of farmers who are grain growers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>That is another problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ChrisMByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a problem in which we are very interested.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianORourke" hpid="Mr. O'Rourke Mr. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I admit that it is quite reasonable to develop the production of oats and barley, but I question the Minister's statement with regard to the numbers of pigs here and in the Six Counties.  I have been producing pigs myself and, as a matter of fact, I sold some pigs a few weeks ago, and my experience does not bear out what the Minister has said.  Of course, the <Col N="187" /> Minister can tell us that the highest grade of pig here fetches a better price than the highest grade pig in the North, but we do not get the highest price.  I sold pigs, and I did not get the first grade&mdash;some third grade, and some fourth grade.  I attended a meeting of farmers in connection with the Pigs Marketing Board recently, and the whole contention of the farmers was this matter of grading and so on, and they asked the Pigs Marketing Board: &ldquo;Why are you robbing us in this way?&rdquo; Their contention is that they are not being treated fairly.  It is no argument for the Minister to say that our highest price is higher than the highest price in the North.  The average price that the ordinary farmer gets is not nearly as high.  That is our grievance, and that is what we object to very much, and we hope that the Minister will arrange with the British authorities that we can take our pigs across the Border and sell them in Armagh, and so on, if we are not getting a fair deal in the Free State.  We feel that we shall have a grievance if we are not allowed to do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Of course, the Minister is not correct, either, in saying that the price of maize meal here is the same as in the North.  There is no use in the Minister quoting Mark Lane.  I know something of the trade, and I can say that the price in Dundalk is 10/- a ton higher than in Newry&mdash;only a few miles away.  I am quite prepared to agree that it was necessary to do that in the past because we could not sell our grain, but now that we have a market in England, there is no necessity for that.  Of course, in some cases, such as Sligo and Tralee, there is the matter of transport, and sometimes as much as 200 or 300 miles would be involved, but here is a case where only a few miles are involved, but the farmer who is using the meal of these millers must pay all the cost of that transport, and it is not an economic proposition if we have to send our stuff across to England.  We should be able to get the cheapest food that can be got.  At any rate, the Minister should consider the farmers, especially in this matter.  If you do not encourage them to feed pigs, they will go out of the <Col N="188" /> production of pigs altogether.  One man whom I know told the Secretary of the Pigs Marketing Board: &ldquo;You have robbed us with your grades and so on, and we are going to quit feeding pigs altogether.&rdquo;  Now, that is the attitude of the farmers, and that is not a good attitude.  We should say to the farmers: &ldquo;You are going to make money by pigs, and you should go on with the production of pigs because it is one of our chief industries in the Border towns, and we will help you to do so.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Sir, as a member of the Agricultural Panel, I suggest to the Minister for Agriculture that he should be very cautious before taking the advice of any of the people who suggest radical changes as regards the importation of feeding stuffs.  I would also like to say that I disagree with Senator Baxter in the suggestion that he has made about the maize-meal mixture. Anyone listening to him would imagine that, as a result of this mixture regulation, people were going out of the production of pigs.  I got a circular from the Department of Industry and Commerce this morning which I am sure was received by every other member of the House.  It states that the number of pigs six months old and upwards in 1934 was 59,700 and in January, 1938, 62,600.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>And the number of sows.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>In 1934 the number was 99, 100, and in 1938, 92,500.  I have the number of boars, if Senator Mulcahy wants the information.  The number was 2,100 in 1934, and I find the same figure for 1938.  The number of pigs three months old and under six was 348,510 in 1938, and 371,500 in 1934. I claim that these figures give no indication whatever of an inclination on the part of our people to go out of pig breeding as a result of this regulation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephJohnston" hpid="Professor Johnston Professor Johnston">
      <NameTxt>Professor Johnston</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to draw the attention of the House to some figures in regard to the imports of feeding stuffs.  It appears from the official figures that in the years 1927 <Col N="189" /> to 1930 we imported, either in the form of maize or maize meal, an average of over 8,000,000 cwts.  In 1931-32 the imports rose to 12,000,000 cwts.  From 1933 to 1936 the imports fell from 6,000,000 to 4,000,000 cwts.  The figure for 1937 was about 5,000,000 cwts. Obviously we are using less imported raw materials for the production of animal products.  Were we using more home-grown cereals?  On that point the official statistics are also of great interest.  It appears from them that in 1929-30 we fed to live stock 10,000,000 cwts. of our oat crop, but in 1934 we fed only 7,000,000 cwts.  Where was the expanding outlook for home-grown cereals?  To put it in another way, in 1929-30 we used 73.2 per cent. of our home-grown oats products for the feeding of live stock, and in 1934-5 we used only 62 per cent. The point is of importance in connection with the desirability of cheapening the cost of the raw materials of our principal agricultural activities as much as possible.  I would like to advocate that, as soon as our commitments to the millers or others in the matter of wheat and maize mixture have been liquidated, we should get back to a completely free import of feeding stuffs, because in no other way can we put our agriculturists on the footing on which they may compete, on something approximating to their former terms, with their rivals in Northern Ireland and Great Britain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say a few things about pigs that I omitted to deal with when replying to Senator O'Rourke.  I would like to say for the benefit of Senators and others, that the Pigs Marketing Board are very anxious to clear any pigs that may be anywhere in the country.  I have never known of them, even if a telephone message only reached them on the morning of a market, not to clear the pigs that were there.  I think if Senator O'Rourke, or anybody else who is concerned, would get in touch with the Pigs Marketing Board, that they will find it will facilitate them in clearing any pigs that may be there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to grading, I would not like the farmers of the country to get the impression that the grading is very <Col N="190" /> bad because it might discourage them. I know that in the last report I got it showed that 63 per cent. of the pigs were passed as &ldquo;A 1&rdquo; and &ldquo;B 1.&rdquo; In other words, two-thirds of the pigs got top and second top price, and as well as I remember, the average for all pigs over a period was 3/- under the top price.  I think that compares very well with any other areas with which we can make a comparison.  There is, I believe, a lower percentage of pigs going into the top grade in Monaghan and in the northern counties than in the rest of the country, principally due to the breed favoured there.  It is now in process of being changed.  I mention these matters so as to prevent, if possible, any discouragement with regard to farmers going more into pigs.  I am very anxious&mdash;as Senators are&mdash;that we should increase the number of pigs in the country.  I believe that the number of pigs will increase. An indication that an increase will take place is to be found in the fact that the price for small pigs is going up.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Rourke referred to the price of maize meal and the maize-meal mixture in Dundalk and Newry.  I am told that the price of maize meal in the northern counties was always cheaper there than in the southern counties, even when there was free trade between both parts of this country, and free trade between this part and England, so that we might have to go further than to drop the maize-meal mixture to get the same price prevailing in Dundalk and in Newry.  Millers, for some reason or another, have always claimed to have higher costs in the South than in the North.  With regard to the point that was raised by Senator Johnston, there are certain things that have not been taken into account when we compare the figures of imports of feeding stuffs for particular periods.  There is one point to be borne in mind, and it is that we are using a good deal more wheat offals than we used before the restrictions came into effect.  Our flour millers at that time used to import more, but they have now come to the point when they have a bigger output of offals, so that we are now using very much more <Col N="191" /> bran and pollard than we were using in 1931.  The second point is that we have a comparatively high acreage of wheat.  As Senators know, there is a fair percentage of any wheat crop that is unfit for milling.  I should say that it averages two or three cwts. per acre. All that is now used for general feeding, for the feeding of poultry and so on.  We have four times as much beet pulp now as we had in 1931.  In that year we exported a big part of our beet pulp.  Last year we exported only about 3,000 tons, and from this on we do not expect to be exporting any at all.  These three items&mdash;the increased quantity of offals, the small wheat and the beet pulp&mdash;have to be added to the general pool of feeding stuffs that we had not got before.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 17.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 17 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the section that puts a restriction on the importation of hay, oats and straw.  I want to draw the Minister's attention to the fact that farmers living in the Border counties, and having farms on both sides of the Border, are faced with extraordinary difficulties in trying to get their crops from one farm to the other. The experiences that some of them have had to undergo are really grotesque. I do not know what exactly the regulations are, but the Revenue authorities surely should realise that people in their position have to travel from one farm to another, and that if a man goes off with a horse and cart and returns with a load of hay or straw, he should not be regarded as a criminal. In the case of these farmers, there is plenty of scope, I suggest, for the exercise of ordinary commonsense.  I have heard of men being taken to the barracks and kept there all day because they went off with their horses and carts and took a load of potatoes from one farm to the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>He really did not comply with certain regulations, but the regulations are of <Col N="192" /> such a nature as to cause great dissatisfaction and to involve great restraint in the carrying out of a man's ordinary business.  The preventive officers, or whoever is responsible for dealing with these matters, ought to be advised to exercise discretion and to get to know the local circumstances better.  They should interest themselves in local conditions, and see who the men are who, in the course of their ordinary callings, have to cross the Border with crops.  So far as these regulations can be eased, I think it should be done.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not present during the discussion which is now proceeding, and I understand that it has assumed rather a general character. If that be so, I should like to put one question.  It refers to a minor matter, but it is one with which a number of people are concerned.  For many years, many of us have got to believe that our health has very much benefited by the consumption of a proprietary article known as &ldquo;Bemax.&rdquo; Latterly, I tried to obtain &ldquo;Bemax&rdquo; which, I am told, is a preparation of wheat.  I was told that it could not be procured here, but that there was an equally efficient substitute. In these matters, into which faith enters largely, we are inclined to look with suspicion on what is described as an equally efficient substitute. A few days afterwards, I saw a carton of &ldquo;Bemax&rdquo; on a friend's breakfast-table.  I asked him where he got it, and he said: &ldquo;I used my brains.&rdquo;  We can form our own conclusions what sort of brains he used. Perhaps the Minister would say whether, under this Agreement, a person will be able to get &ldquo;Bemax.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That does not arise on the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not know that we were discussing a section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are dealing with Section 16, which has to do with feeding stuffs&mdash;hay and straw.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="193" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>In reply to Deputy Baxter's question, this is an enactment of an old section, and there is no change so far as this section goes. The practice has been, in cases where a man has a farm on each side of the Border, or across the Border, to pro vide him with a permit.  He would have no difficulty in getting a permit to move straw, hay, oats or barley&mdash; there is an exception in the case of potatoes&mdash;across the Border.  That permit is issued through the Revenue Commissioners, and they attach conditions to it.  I do not know what the conditions are.  In some cases, they may be considered vexatious.  If the Senator would let me know, I should be glad to point out anything that I thought was causing difficulty or that was unnecessary in the conditions to the Revenue Commissioners.  I cannot guarantee, of course, that the Revenue Commissioners would agree with my representations.  I should like to make things easier for these people, so far as I can.  So far as the law goes, there is no change in these cases.</P>
      <P>Senator Sir John Keane raised a point to which I may, perhaps, refer, although it might have been dealt with on a former section which was concerned with wheat-preparations.  There is no change so far as that is concerned.  A licence can be issued by the Minister for Industry and Commerce. Any person can bring in under 5 lb. of wheaten preparation as a traveller&mdash;that would be, I suppose, for the purpose of his lunch, or as a present to a person.  It can also, I think, be allowed in for health reasons but only under licence.  I do not think that the Minister for Industry and Commerce would presume to point out to any person that there was a preparation which was just as good from a health point of view as the other preparation.  There must have been some other objection.  It is the Minister for Industry and Commerce who administers the wheaten-preparations part of the Act and I cannot say any more about it.</P>
      <P>Section 17 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 18 and 19 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="194" /> SECTION 20.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 20 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is taking power to permit certain feeding stuffs to be brought in under licence.  Do I take it from this section that all the feeding stuffs mentioned in the Third and Fourth Schedules can be brought in?  Suppose I have got a ton lorry of my own, can I go into the Six Counties and bring back a ton of feeding stuffs for my own use?  Can I take in 16 stone of maize meal, or what exactly am I at liberty to do?  It seems to me that the Minister has a big discretion in this matter.  I do not suggest that he is not going to be just in the administration of the Section, but he is given great liberty to grant a licence to one and to refuse it to another.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It was to prevent that that this section was drafted.  At present, I could give a licence to any farmer on the Border to import any feeding stuffs, but the Department never did issue a licence to a farmer to bring in linseed cake or maize-meal mixture. This section provides for the making of a general order and, in the general order, it will be laid down that linseed cake, for instance, will be allowed in free or, perhaps, maize-meal mixture, though I am not sure that that could be allowed in.  In that case, any farmer bringing in anything named in the order for his own use will be entirely free from any restriction&mdash;so long as the Revenue Commissioner are satisfied that he is bringing it in for his own use.  We must, in the order, lay down certain conditions and try to regulate how it may be brought in&mdash;for example, in his own cart or in certain quantities.  It was pointed out in the Dáil that if we were to say his own cart, it would limit the right to six or seven miles of the Border.  In the county Donegal, I should be anxious that it would extend to more than six or seven miles.  In fact, I should like to take in the whole of County Donegal for any feeding stuffs that might be imported and to provide <Col N="195" /> that a farmer bringing in feeding stuffs for his own use in County Donegal would not be subject to restriction as regards quantity and would not be subject to any tariff.  We are trying to avoid the danger the Senator pointed out.  By making a general order, every farmer will get what he is entitled to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Can I bring these feeding stuffs in without paying any revenue duty?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, if they are in the order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Regardless of what the price may be in the Twenty-Six Counties?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I can actually buy a cheaper commodity in the Six Counties, bring it in here and feed it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>If you can get a cheaper article.</P>
      <P>Section 20 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 21 to 26 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Schedules and Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration, and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prices Commission (Extension of Functions) Bill, 1938. - Agricultural" RHead="Produce (Cereals) Bill, 1938: Motion for Earlier Signature">
    <Title>Prices Commission (Extension of Functions) Bill, 1938. - Agricultural Produce (Cereals) Bill, 1938: Motion for Earlier Signature.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That, pursuant to sub-section (20) of Section 2 of Article 25 of the Constitution, Seanad Eireann concurs to the earlier signature by the President of the Agricultural Produce (Cereals) Bill, 1938.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister tell us when he expects this and the other Bills to be operative?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator mean when this Agreement will come into force?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="196" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>When does he expect the Agreement will come into force, because a great many people in the country are very anxious to know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>So far as we on this side are concerned, when we finish in the Seanad, as we expect we will to-day, we shall be ready, but I am afraid they are not ready on the other side. I think I could say about the middle of next week, but not sooner.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prices Commission (Extension of Functions) Bill, 1938. - Agricultural" RHead="Products (Regulation of Import) Bill, 1938.&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Prices Commission (Extension of Functions) Bill, 1938. - Agricultural Products (Regulation of Import) Bill, 1938.&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Bill passed through Committee without amendments.</P>
    <P>Bill reported.</P>
    <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That, pursuant to sub-section (2º) of Section 2 of Article 25 of the Constitution, Seanad Eireann concurs to the earlier signature by the President of the Agricultural Products (Regulation of Import) Bill, 1938.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prices Commission (Extension of Functions) Bill, 1938. -" RHead="Diseases of Animals Bill, 1938&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Prices Commission (Extension of Functions) Bill, 1938. - Diseases of Animals Bill, 1938&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1, 2 and 3 agreed to.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 4 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRobinson" hpid="Mr. Robinson Mr. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>This section provides for a fine.  I have not read the Principal Act so I speak as a fool speaketh, but I presume that the reason the export order is made is to get rid of something brought in which might render other articles of a similar kind liable to disease.  I presume that the Principal Act includes the destruction of the article in connection with which the Order is made, but in this case, although you might get your £50 fine, the harm would be done if the creature were allowed to remain.  Would the Minister say if the Principal Act includes destruction?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="197" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Customs (Consolidation) Act, 1876, gives the Revenue Commissioners powers either to destroy a prohibited article that comes in at the importer's expense, or to sell it and then recoup themselves of whatever expenses there might have been. They have no power to compel a person to export the article again, and we are adding that power here because, as Senator Robinson has pointed out, we would not like to have diseased eggs or poultry sold, as they would do the damage which we want to prevent.  We might not like to have them destroyed because, although not useful to us, they might be useful to somebody else.  We think the best thing in the circumstances would be for the Revenue Commissioners to have power to compel the person to re-export the goods back to where they came from.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 5 and the Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That, pursuant to sub-section (2º) of Section 2 of Article 25 of the <Col N="198" /> Constitution, Seanad Eireann concurs to the earlier signature by the President of the Diseases of Animals Bill, 1938.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prices Commission (Extension of Functions)" RHead="Bill, 1938. - The Adjournment">
    <Title>Prices Commission (Extension of Functions) Bill, 1938. - The Adjournment.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>When do we expect further business from the Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I expect there will not be any business before the 1st June.  There is a motion on the Order Paper in the names of Senators Baxter and O'Dwyer, but it and the setting up of two committees are the only items to be dealt with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>In the circumstances, I feel it would be unfair to ask the Seanad to come together, if there is no Government business to be dealt with, so that we might agree to allow the motion to stand over until the next day on which Government business would necessitate the Seanad sitting.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 5.20 p.m. until Wednesday, 1st June.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>