<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="12" Month="Jun" Year="1935" Vol="20" No="4" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 12 Meitheamh 1935" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 12 June 1935" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="273">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="273" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Dairy Produce (Price Stabilisation)" RHead="Bill, 1935&mdash;Message from the Dáil">
    <Title>Dairy Produce (Price Stabilisation) Bill, 1935&mdash;Message from the Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The following Message has been received from the Dáil:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Dáil Eireann has agreed to the amendments made by Seanad Eireann to the Dairy Produce (Price Stabilisation) Bill, 1935.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Milk and Dairies Bill," RHead="1934&mdash;Message from the Dáil">
    <Title>Milk and Dairies Bill, 1934&mdash;Message from the Dáil.</Title>
    <P>Dáil Eireann has agreed to amendments 1 to 9 inclusive and 11 to 16 inclusive, made by Seanad Eireann to the Milk and Dairies Bill, 1934; it has disagreed to amendment 10; to which the agreement of Seanad Eireann is desired.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusRobinson" hpid="Mr. S. Robinson Mr. S. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: That Seanad Eireann do not insist on amendment No. 10.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardBigger" hpid="Sir E. Coey Bigger Sir E. Coey Bigger">
      <NameTxt>Sir E. Coey Bigger</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry that the Parliamentary Secretary who was in charge of the Bill in this House on the last occasion is not here to-day.  It is rather a pity that the Government should object to this amendment.  It was in the interests of the public health that this House passed it; I do not know why it should be objected to in the Dáil.  In the last three or four years there was a very serious epidemic of sore throat in Howth.  A very large number of people were affected and there were a number of deaths.  If the same occurred in Dublin the absence of this amendment would mean delay of three or four days in which a number of people might become infected before the source of the infection was discovered. However, as the Parliamentary <Col N="274" /> Secretary is not here to offer an explanation, I do not think it is worth while dividing the Seanad.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Pigs and Bacon Bill," RHead="1934&mdash;Report">
    <Title>Pigs and Bacon Bill, 1934&mdash;Report.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to draw attention to the fact that two amendments which I sent in, for this Stage of the Pig and Bacon Bill, were not accepted. As Monday was a Bank Holiday there was no one in the Clerk's office to receive these amendments, and so they did not reach him until Tuesday.  The Clerk, following the Standing Orders, ruled that the notice was not sufficient and he could not accept them.  I would ask permission, in the special circumstances, to be allowed to move these amendments now.  They are two noncontroversial amendments and I think the Minister could accept them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I have no power to allow the Senator to move his amendments now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>On the last day in reference to the Dairy Produce (Price Stabilisation) Bill, an amendment was allowed to be put forward that only appeared on the Paper that morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There were specific reasons and I said it was not to be taken as a precedent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>There are specific reasons for allowing my amendments to be taken also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot allow them to be moved now.  The House can adjourn the Report Stage of this Bill if it so desires, in order to allow these amendments to be taken later.  But the Minister is very anxious to get the Bill, and that was really the reason for the Seanad meeting to-day.  There were three days allowed for handing in amendments in connection with the Report Stage of this Bill and the Senator did not avail himself of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it possible to know what Senator Counihan's amendments are?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>What good would it do?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="275" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>If they prove to be of consequence there might be a possibility of adjourning the Report Stage to-day.  If they were only trivial there would be no need for anything like that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill has been considerably rushed.  The Committee Stage was only taken a few days ago and a Bank holiday intervened. We had only two days in which to hand in amendments.  We had not even got the Official Reports to consult, and these are very important when preparing amendments.  I am not opposing the taking of the Report Stage but I think the Seanad ought to give me the opportunity of putting in my amendments which if accepted would considerably improve the Bill.  Whether they are accepted or not we should get an opportunity of discussing them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry they cannot be moved now.</P>
      <P>The following Government amendments were agreed to:&mdash;</P>
      <P>1.  Section 15, sub-section (1).  To delete in line 1 the word &ldquo;three&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;seven.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>2.  Section 15, sub-section (2).  To delete in line 15 the word &ldquo;three&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;seven.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>3.  Section 17, sub-section (4).  To delete in line 29 the word &ldquo;of&rdquo;, where it secondly occurs.</P>
      <P>4.  Section 17, sub-section (4).  To delete the word &ldquo;account&rdquo; in line 35 and to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;document.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>5.  Section 33, sub-section (1).  To delete in line 7 the word &ldquo;to&rdquo;, where it first occurs, and to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;shall.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>6.  Section 33, sub-section (4).  To delete in line 52 the word &ldquo;of.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>7.  Section 33, sub-section (4).  To delete the word &ldquo;account&rdquo; in line 58 and to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;document.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>8.  Section 36, sub-section (6).  To delete in lines 28-29 the words <Col N="276" />&ldquo;cleanliness and suitability of&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the words &ldquo;suitability of slaughtering.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Government amendment No. 9:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 39, sub-sections (1) and (2).  To delete the sub-sections and to substitute the following new sub-sections therefor:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1)  Wages payable to a workman employed at licensed premises shall be at a rate not less than the rate generally recognised by trade unions and employers as the rate applicable to workmen employed in a similar kind of work at similar licensed premises.</P>
      <P>(2)  The conditions of employment (other than the rate of wages) of a workman employed at licensed premises shall not be less advantageous than the conditions of employment generally recognised by trade unions and employers as the conditions of employment applicable to workmen employed in a similar kind of work at similar licensed premises.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan) Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>We had a lot of discussion the last day on this matter in reference to wages.  I have put in here the exact words used in the Cereals Act as applying to workers in flour mills. I think Senator Foran will agree that it is better to insert these words than to proceed with his amendment on the Paper.  Personally I do not mind which.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>The Cereals Act will meet the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Minister will remember there are other people concerned besides the Department of Agriculture and Senator Foran in this amendment.  Unless we have definite assurances from the Minister on this matter we will oppose it. Does this amendment mean that a minor curer in Cavan or Ballina will have to pay the same rates and observe the same conditions as similar curers in Dublin?  The Minister <Col N="277" /> argued on the last day that that was out of the question, and that it would be unfair to compel an employer in these country places to pay the same rates and observe the same conditions as prevailed in Dublin.  And he explained that the cost of living in Dublin was very much higher than in the rural districts.  Senator Dillon and other Senators pointed out that many of the minor curers in rural parts of Ireland were at a great disadvantage in comparison with the minor curers in the big cities.  The Minister agreed that both the major and the minor curers in the cities had a big market at their door and that it would be unfair competition if minor curers in the rural parts of the country had to pay similar wages as were paid in the cities.  He pointed out also that the cost of transport from these rural areas and the expenses of commission on sales amounted to a very big item.  He made a strong case which convinced the majority on this side of the House that this amendment would not be the same as the clause in the Cereals Act.  We could not possibly support Senator Foran's amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not think it was necessary, after the long discussion we had on this matter the last day, to go into this question in detail again, but I had no intention of confining the discussion to Senator Foran and myself.  I thought, however, it was only right to ask Senator Foran if he were agreeable to accepting the amendment.  I could not really say what the effect of the amendment is going to be.  Experience is the best test in all these matters.  There is a similar clause in the Cereals Act and there is no doubt that it has given satisfaction.  Area wages have been fixed under it.  I must admit, reading the section, that it does not say that you can fix area wages, but it has been done in the case of other industries and perhaps that is sufficient to go on.  The effect of that would be that a different rate of wages would be paid by factories situated in rural districts to that <Col N="278" /> paid by factories in cities, small and large.  The minor curers do not come under that at all.  They are not affected.  I think that the Senator probably meant small curers when he referred to minor curers.  I think that what the Seanad really wants is a clause that will enable a position to be created under which, in areas such as Cavan and Monaghan, one wage can be fixed and in areas like Limerick and Waterford another wage can be fixed.  That has been the effect under the Cereals Act and I think no harm will be done by inserting a similar clause in this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Senator Foran would be wise to accept the Minister's amendment.  I do not think there is any fundamental difference between his proposal and that of the Minister.  I have given the matter some thought since the last day but I was not aware that under other Bills wages had been fixed for various areas.  It seems to me that the proposed new wage will be really governed by the words &ldquo;generally recognised by trades unions and employers,&rdquo; and until there is a dispute as to the meaning of these words, no one can say what will be the outcome of the clause.  If you have a system which has worked amicably in other industries then there can be no harm in applying it to this industry. I do not think it will have the effect that Senator Counihan thinks.  It seems to me that the whole question hangs on these words, &ldquo;generally recognised by trades unions and employers.&rdquo;  If there is agreement between employers and employees as to the meaning of that phrase there can be no harm in the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Douglas that the amendment is clearer and more definite than sub-section (2) as it appears in the Bill.  I find it very difficult to make up my mind as to how you would construe the last words in sub-section (1) as it appears in the Bill: &ldquo;Workmen employed in a similar kind of work at licensed premises in similar localities.&rdquo;  It would be very hard to find one locality which was similar to <Col N="279" /> another and in the amendment now proposed we have something which gives us a clearer idea:</P>
      <P>Wages payable to a workman employed in licensed premises shall be at a rate not less than the rate generally recognised by trades unions and employers as the rate applicable to workmen employed in a similar kind of work at similar licensed premises.</P>
      <P>I think that is much better than saying: &ldquo;At licensed premises in similar localities.&rdquo;  I take it that in the working out of this sub-section it will be possible to differentiate between licensed premises situated in a district like Cavan or Mayo and licensed premises situated in Dublin, where workmen, in order to be on equal terms with workmen in these rural areas, would require to get a somewhat higher wage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickLynchKC" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Comyn in the view he has put to the House.  Unless the phrasing of the amendment were altered and the wording of the amendment moved by the Minister substituted, I think it would be very difficult to operate it.  The section, as he has very well pointed out, will be governed by the agreement arrived at between employers and employees regarding the wages paid in the district.  That is a matter that is best left to these parties themselves. Again, as Senator Comyn has pointed out, the phrasing, &ldquo;in similar localities,&rdquo; is very awkward wording.  It might mean that a factory situated in a backward part of the State might be treated on the same basis as a factory in a more accessible part.  The court, in construing the section, might say: &ldquo;Well, the words were put in there with some object.&rdquo;  I suggest that the retention of these words would only do harm and that we should leave the section now proposed, to be interpreted by the people affected, the employers and employees, &ldquo;employed in a similar kind of work in similar premises.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that there are certain other factors that should be taken into account in considering this <Col N="280" /> amendment.  The amendment, I agree, is a very important one and I have no objection to the principle of it.  In fact, I always support the best possible wages and conditions for workmen employed in factories or otherwise. But I suggest to the supporters of the amendment that there are certain other factors that should be taken into account, such things say, as the cost of production in the various factories. I think that certainly should not be lost sight of by supporters of the amendment if we are to have a sense of fair play.  We are always very ready to insert such amendments in Bills brought forward here and, as the Minister has pointed out, such a clause is already in operation in the case of the Cereals Act.  That industry, however, is not as centralised as the one now in question.  Another important factor is the cost of transport.  That must be a very serious factor in the economic working of any factory.</P>
      <P>On the last day, I pointed out that another important factor was the method of curing.  The method of curing, I might mention again, carried on on the Continent is wet curing, with the result that Continental producers are able to compete with us and defeat us at every point.  They are able to defeat us to the tune of millions of cwts. of bacon exported.  They are able to supply the British market where the demand has been progressively increasing for a great number of years.  We have got no share or part of that increased demand.  All these factors must be taken into account in considering an amendment like this, and I would suggest that consideration of the amendment should be further deferred for the purpose of giving more thought to these matters. We have also to consider the great body of the unemployed.  Supposing we give what may be considered an excessive wage, thus adding to the cost of production and to the cost of living, we must certainly trespass on the rights of these men to whom no benefit will accrue.  We cannot properly consider an amendment such as this unless all these factors are taken into consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="281" />
      <i>Senator Counihan rose.</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask is not this the Report Stage and how often is a Senator entitled to speak?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Once.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I only just desire to say that I am satisfied with the Minister's definition of the amendment, and that we withdraw our objection to the amendment suggested by the Minister.  The Minister has given us a satisfactory explanation, and we hope that the other people will also accept his definition.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 10, 11 and 12 by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Government amendment No. 13:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 73, sub-section (2).  To delete in line 48 the figures and words &ldquo;1938, the year 1940&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the figures and words &ldquo;1939, the year 1942, the year 1945.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>There are a number of amendments which will be ruled by this amendment.  Amendments Nos. 16, 17, 18, 28, 29, 32 and 36 are all consequential. There are also a number of amendments put forward by Senator Baxter which are certainly connected with this amendment.  Senator Baxter expressed the opinion on the Second Reading that a two years' term of office was hardly sufficient or at least that it was not advisable, that it was too short.  He suggested that a period of three years would be more advisable. I was inclined to agree with him at that time and, on consideration, I think a three years' term of office would be better.  This amendment therefore, provides for a three years' term of office for the members of the board.  Of course, we shall be able to deal with the other board in the same manner when we come to it.  I do not think that there is any great necessity to make any great case for the amendment. It is simply a matter on which Senators must make up their own <Col N="282" /> minds as to whether it is more advisable to have a two years' or three years' term of office for members of the board.  It does take some little time before new members reach their full value, before they understand the position perfectly and give of their very best.  If that takes six or nine months, two years would be a rather short term.  On the other hand, if a member is not doing as he should, perhaps those who elected or appointed him might desire an opportunity of getting rid of him as soon as possible.  On the whole, I am inclined to think that we should change the period to three years rather than the two suggested in the Bill.  The other amendments are more or less consequential on that and I need hardly speak on them.  There are other matters put forward by Senator Baxter which more or less hinge on this amendment, but I think it would be impossible to meet Senator Baxter further than we have met him. It would not, however, be in order to discuss Senator Baxter's amendment until we come to amendment No. 15.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that in this case also it would be better if the Minister were to adhere to the provision in the Bill.  I am speaking from experience.  I think I can claim to have been mainly responsible for getting into the Slaughter of Cattle and Sheep Act an amendment somewhat on the lines of the one that the Minister proposes to insert in this Bill. I think it was most regrettable that I did so.  Certainly, some of those who were selected to advise the Minister on the Slaughter of Cattle and Sheep Act could not, by any stretch of the imagination, be described as suitable. I feel that if the Minister had the appointing of them he would have had to scrap three-fourths of them afterwards. In this case, it is proposed that the members of the Bacon Marketing Board should be appointed permanently for a term of three years.  If some of these people prove to be duds, then I think either the board or the Minister should have the opportunity of dispensing with their services.  There certainly should be power to do that at the end of the first term, at all <Col N="283" /> events.  This, again, seems to me to be a case where second thoughts are best.  My submission to the Minister is that it would be wiser to withdraw the amendment and leave the section stand as it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>May I point out to Senator Counihan that the first people who come on the board will only remain as members until December, 1936.  From that date on, it is proposed that the three year term should commence to operate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Counihan's condemnation of public men who come forward to give their services, either gratuitously or for a consideration, on a board such as we are dealing with here rather surprises me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>These are not public men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Counihan's declaration appears to me to be rather an amazing one: that people in the cattle trade in this country who were called upon by the Minister to come forward and give advice in connection with the Act that has been referred to, did not prove to be as capable as might have been expected.  Apparently, a mistake was made in the original selections.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is responsible for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Apparently, it was a mistake of not knowing the men sufficiently well, whether they were to act for a week or a month or for a term of years.  If Senator Counihan had read this section carefully he would have seen that the members of the Bacon Marketing Board are not to be nominated by the Minister.  They are to be elected by the curers.  I suggest that it would be time enough to make a commentary such as has been made by Senator Counihan after the men selected by the curers to act on the Board had been put to the test.  Some of us hold that the curers are fully qualified to select most competent men to represent them on this Board.  The <Col N="284" /> members of the Bacon Marketing Board will have a very responsible duty to discharge.  It will be their responsibility to manage the bacon curing trade in this country within the powers given to them in this measure.  Obviously, it will take them some time to get hold of the threads of the business.  When this measure comes to be operated it will, I suggest, be found to contain many difficulties and some snags.  It has to be remembered, too, that the representatives of the trade acting on this Board will, in addition to the duties falling upon them as members of the Board, have to give their time and attention also to their own particular business.  It will take them some time to get a good grip of this measure, and even though one or two on the Board may not prove to be as competent as the others, the Board, as a whole, will, I am sure, be composed of a competent body of business men.  Even if one member of it should not prove to be up to the level of the others, it does not necessarily follow that he will be of no value on the Board, or that there will be any desire on the part of the other members to get rid of him.  For various considerations, it may be considered highly advisable to have such a man on the Board.  It is not the man who has most to say on a Board who is always the most valuable member, and it is often desirable that the views expressed by the other members should get his assent.</P>
      <P>It would be a bad thing, in my view, to have the membership of the Board changed every two years.  The members ought to be able to feel that the personnel of the Board is not likely to be changed for a reasonably long period.  That would help to give stability to any policy they may decide on.  If the members felt that they would have to go up for election at the end of two years, then I do not believe they would be able to concentrate on the business of the Board in the way that they should.  I think the Minister is wise in introducing this amendment.  Experience, I think, will prove that, as it has in the case of most successful commercial institutions in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="285" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Baxter that a three-year term is much better than a two-year term.  In fact, I would go so far as to say that if you get sensible men a three-year term is too short, because the thing to be aimed at is to get the independent judgment of sensible men.  No matter how they are elected, if you give them a certain continuity they are more likely to exercise an independent judgment.  I do not say that a man is consciously or directly influenced by the fact that he is up for election in a year, in two years or in three years; but human nature being what it is, he is undoubtedly subconsciously influenced in the judgment which he may give on a particular issue by the fact that in 12 months' time or in two years' time he is eligible for re-election, and that there will be a necessity to re-elect him.  If he wishes to remain on that Board, he cannot avoid, in any period of his office, reflecting on the fact that he has to please the people who elected him, or who will have the choice of electing him or his substitute.  In that way, the longer the term the more independent is likely to be the judgment of an ordinary, sensible, prudent man.  For that reason, I am in favour of the three-year term rather than the two-year term.  Senators cannot forget that their own tenure of office is for nine years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>Six months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Now, we are getting something corresponding to the economic war cropping into every debate that we have here; but, as I was saying, the normal tenure of office for Senators is nine years.  The reason for that is that we expect from Senators, sensible men, an independent, unbiassed, impartial judgment, uninfluenced by the prospect of re-election.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 13 put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Government amendment No. 14:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 77, sub-section (2).  To <Col N="286" /> delete in line 9 the word &ldquo;year&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;order.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 15:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 82.  To delete the section and to substitute the following new section therefor:&mdash;</P>
      <P>82.&mdash;(1)  Except in the case of the first ordinary members the period of office of ordinary members shall be three years.</P>
      <P>(2)  Of the first ordinary members two to be selected by lot as soon as may be after election shall except in case of death, resignation or disqualification hold office for one year from the establishment of the Board and two others similarly selected shall except in case of death, resignation or disqualification hold office for two years from the establishment of the Board and three others to be similarly selected shall except in case of death, resignation or disqualification hold office for three years from the establishment of the Board.</P>
      <P>(3)  Every substitutive member shall hold office for a period of three years.</P>
      <P>(4)  An ordinary member or a substitutive member retiring on the expiration by effluxion of time of his term of office shall be eligible for re-election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister suggested, in the case of a previous amendment, that it indicated the distance that he was prepared to go.  I do not think that the acceptance of that amendment by the House queers the pitch in any way so far as the change that I propose in the section goes.  In fact, I think that my amendment is essential.  I hold very strong views on this.  I stated them to the House last week, and I do not think there is much to be gained by repeating my arguments to-day.  I think that the acceptance of my amendment, the purpose of which is to replace the section in the Bill, would cover the whole case that <Col N="287" /> I want covered, and that there would be no need for the moving of consequential amendments to Section 82. If the sense of the House seems to be against the acceptance of the amendment, then I am not inclined to hold forth on it at any length.</P>
    <P>The Minister has already to his credit quite a number of Acts dealing with the agricultural industry.  I submit that pig production here can be as contentious a matter as any other branch of agricultural productivity. People are sometimes inclined to think that cattle matter most.  Undoubtedly they do, but very close on their heels you have this question of pig productivity, marketing and all the rest. All these matters are dealt with in this Bill.  Therefore, I submit that we ought to consider this question calmly, trying to visualise, as best we can, what the position is going to be when this Bill becomes an Act.  For myself, I feel that we are going to have a contentious atmosphere created between the Pigs Marketing Board and the Bacon Marketing Board, and that possibly the Bacon Marketing Board may be blamed for quite a number of difficulties that may not actually be the outcome of their work at all.  That has been the experience in the Six Counties, and I think that we are likely to be as argumentative here on these matters as they are in the Six Counties.  Therefore, I think that, as far as possible, the work of the Bacon Marketing Board, in so far as it has to do with this particular branch of the business, ought to be smoothed out before this Bill becomes law.  In other words, I think that the foundations in this Bill ought to be laid as broadly, as deeply and as soundly as possible.  I hold strongly to the view that we have greatly improved the Bill by extending the period of office for the members of the Bacon Marketing Board to three years. But we must not forget that at the end of the three years we are leaving the position in this way: that every member of the Bacon Marketing Board can be sent, so-to-speak, into oblivion, and a new Board brought <Col N="288" /> into existence.  I think it is most unfortunate that it will be possible to do that.  It is not improbable either that it may happen.  I stated here on a previous occasion that the curers themselves, on many points, had given no greater display of unanimity than other sections of our people on this particular question.  There are to-day divergent views amongst the curers. They have their own peculiar differences and difficulties and their own problems.  I have no doubt that even on the Board there will be divergent views amongst the curers.  They will be drawn from different panels and will already have been grouped before the Board is brought into existence. The Board will be drawn from three groups of curers.  They will come in with different views and with their own prejudices&mdash;and they have prejudices. If one stands a little bit apart, it is easy to get the atmosphere. It is not at all improbable that, when the Board is operating for a short time, some of these prejudices may become accentuated, making for differences in the business of the Board and amongst the general body of curers.  It is easy to visualise a situation in which a sort of campaign will be worked up to change completely and wipe out the personnel of the Bacon Marketing Board.  Consider the situation that would be created if every member of the Beet Board or the Electricity Supply Board or the Board of the Agricultural Credit Corporation or the Currency Commission were to be removed and the business left in the hands of new groups.  The men who will come on will not, of course, be complete strangers to the work, but certain lines of procedure and certain lines of policy will have been adopted by their predecessors.  They may reverse engines and alter everything their predecessors have done.  We may have change for the sake of change and because the new members feel that something new has got to be done. They may not wait to discover whether what was done by their predecessors was the wise thing or was done in the right way.  They may feel that, being new men, they are bound to do something <Col N="289" /> new, whether it be right or wrong.  The work accomplished by the previous members of the Board will not be given a fair chance because it could be judged properly by new men only if they were sitting side by side with some of the older members who would be able to explain to them why certain lines of policy or procedure were adopted.  Let the new members after some experience decide upon change if they think that change is desirable, but there ought to be no swift and sudden changes in the management of a business like this, dealing, one way or another, with trade amounting to millions of pounds to which there might conceivably be added £2,000,000 per year. These are considerations that, weighed calmly, should, I think, convince members of the Seanad that the proper method of dealing with the constitution of this Board would be to provide that two of the first ordinary members, to be selected by lot, should hold office for one year from the establishment of the Board, two others, selected in the same way, to hold office for two years, and three others, similarly selected, to hold office for three years.  The outgoing members would be eligible for re-election.  If, in their wisdom, the curers did not re-elect them but elected new men, we would not have change of policy unless it was obvious that there were good reasons for such a change.</P>
    <P>I realise that a point can be made against my proposal.  It is conceivable that the new men coming on instead of the retiring members might not come on from the same panel of curers as that which elected the original members. The Bill, as it stands, makes mandatory the selection of representatives in respect of a certain panel.  It is obvious that if a man who has been elected by the curers on a certain panel retires, these curers will be responsible for filling the seat vacated.  These reasons, in my opinion, stand out as good and sufficient reasons why this section should be inserted in the Bill instead of the section contained in it at present.  It seems to me that the wisdom of the House ought to favour such a gradual process of change in <Col N="290" /> the personnel of the Bacon Marketing Board rather than having a swift, steep change because of the method laid down in the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Every argument for continuity and steadiness of work is against this amendment.  Senator Baxter has given the House a great many arguments which seem to me to cut the foundation from his proposal. He said it was undesirable to have election campaigns.  It is very undesirable. But his proposal would mean that there would be an election campaign every 12 months.  This Board has to look to its own constituents, to its own trade, and also to the Pigs Marketing Board and to the Minister. It is desirable that the people who constitute that Board should have an opportunity of knowing one another and working together.  They should have an opportunity of knowing the men on the Pigs Marketing Board and the officials of the Department.  It is desirable that they should also be known, because it is only by being in contact with men that you can work smoothly and harmoniously with them. If Senator Baxter's proposal is accepted, there will be a change of Board every year.  The new men will have some difficulty in understanding the working of the Board.  They will also have the human impulse to try to assert themselves.  If you want steady work, if you want continuity of work, if you want to escape, as far as possible, from campaigning and electioneering, the best thing to do is to appoint the Board for three years or, as I should say, for a longer term. Let the members understand one another.  Let them understand the other Board and let them understand the officials of the Department.  It would be much better to have a system like that than to have the continual excitement that would result from candidates every year seeking a seat on this Board and having their own faction to support them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There will be difficulties in connection with the administration of this Act.  There will be a good many people disappointed and if they have the prospect within 12 months of <Col N="291" /> altering the personnel, that will give them an additional inducement to agitate.  What is wanted in the administration of this Act and of these numerous other statutes is steady continuity of work and a certain unchanging line of policy.  That will be better for the Board, better for the trade, better for the pig producers, who will be to a certain extent in rivalry with the members of this Board, and better for the Department.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am opposed to this amendment for various reasons.  The reason which I shall mention first is not the principal reason.  If this amendment were made, it would necessitate a number of other amendments. I do not know how we could proceed, in that event, because it would be necessary to have another Stage in this House to get the Bill right.  As the Standing Orders of this House are framed, I do not know whether or not that could be done. For that reason, the adoption of the amendment would mean the withdrawal of the Bill.  A great part of it would have to be re-drafted because the machinery for election enters into many sections.  Amendments would have to be moved to these sections to bring them into line with the new procedure. That is not, perhaps, a good reason to give because the Seanad may ask whether, if I were in favour of the proposal, the change could not have been made at the right time.  I am not in favour of the proposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a great deal in what Senator Comyn said, that you would have, under this proposal, a disturbing factor entering into the procedure every year. If the curer members are to be elected every year and if the producer members are to be elected as proposed and if, as Senator Baxter suggests, there is going to be a great deal of interest taken in the proceedings, you will have a certain amount of election fever every year instead of every three years.  I do not think that that would be advisable. However, I do not know that there will be as much interest as Senator Baxter suggests taken in the <Col N="292" /> election of these members.  The number of electors among the curers will be small.  There will be only about 30 altogether and they will be divided into three panels&mdash;a panel of large curers, consisting of two or three; a panel of medium curers, consisting of eight or nine, and a panel of small curers, consisting of 17 or 18.  Where you have only seven or eight businessmen electing two of their number to represent them on the Board, there will not be that electioneering air about the proceedings.  They will probably decide easily amongst themselves who will represent them, and it is quite possible that the two members first elected will remain on the Board for years.  It is more than likely that they will give satisfaction as representatives of the bacon curers.  If we have elected representatives of the producers, there may be a different position. The producers may be dissatisfied with the working of the Board or with the prices.  They may blame their representatives on the Board for not doing more for them.  They may be anxious to change their representatives and elect others.  If that is to be the case, it is better that they should all go out every three years.  If we are to have democratic control by the producers, there is no reason why we should not go the whole way and make the change complete.</P>
    <P>The arguments that Senator Baxter used could be used just as well against this amendment.  It is very difficult to know how these things will work out.  As the boards are being constituted&mdash;election by the curers and nomination in the case of the producers&mdash;no argument can be put up for the amendment.  If we came to the stage where the producers elected their representatives, there might be something to be said for the amendment although, against it, it could be said that you would have the election fever, to which I have referred, every year.  If that change in the method of constituting the board be decided upon, it will have to be done, so far as I can see, by a new Bill.  There is a certain amount of power in the Bill to have it done by the Minister but I do not think it could be satisfactorily <Col N="293" /> done without a new Bill.  At that stage we could discuss whether we would have the system of a certain number retiring each year, or of all retiring at the end of three years.  I ask Senator Baxter to withdraw the amendment, because I do not think that any great argument was put up in its favour and, for the more immediate reason, that I am afraid it would delay the Bill unnecessarily. We would have to postpone further consideration of the Report Stage in order to bring in further amendments if this amendment were adopted.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask leave to withdraw the amendment, not for the reasons mentioned by the Minister, but in order not to complicate the position.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>The following Government amendments were agreed to:&mdash;</P>
      <P>16.  Section 82, sub-section (1).  To delete in line 46 the word &ldquo;two&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;three.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>17.  Section 82, sub-section (2).  To delete in line 56 the word &ldquo;two&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;three.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>18.  Section 91, sub-section (2). To delete in line 44 the word &ldquo;biennial&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;triennial.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Dowdall I move amendment No. 19:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 98, sub-section (2).  To delete the word &ldquo;one&rdquo; in line 26 and to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;three.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRobinson" hpid="Mr. D. Robinson Mr. D. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think anything is to be gained by this amendment. It would compel the Bacon Marketing Board to make an allocation for three weeks instead of for one week.  As the Bill stands, the board may, if they wish, make an order three weeks beforehand.  I think they will, when ever they can, give such notice.  It would be unwise to bind them to give three weeks' notice, because there might be a wrong calculation about <Col N="294" /> the number of pigs in the country or something like that and it might be awkward to delay operations for three weeks.  The principle we adopted in the Dáil and in this House is to give boards the fullest freedom of action. As they are there for the good of the industry, and not there to hurt it in any way, as a Curers' Board naturally they will give as long notice as possible.  But there is no reason for binding them to give three weeks' notice.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Dowdall I move amendment No. 20:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 99, sub-section (2).  To delete the sub-section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the Bill the Minister has power to grant licences to a person who sets up a bacon factory. In doing such a thing the Minister may possibly be &ldquo;up against&rdquo; the curers, because they may resent another factory being started. I mentioned already in this House that I would like very much to see a bacon factory started in County Donegal, as I think it would be a good thing for the people of that county.  Taking that particular instance, the Bacon Board might say that there were sufficient factories in existence.  I might give the licence but if I did so the board might not allot any bacon.  There is no use in giving a licence unless there is power to allot a quota: otherwise the powers to issue the licence would be useless.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Dowdall I move amendment No. 21:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 99, sub-section (3).  Before the word &ldquo;and&rdquo; in line 22 to insert the words and figures &ldquo;and the six months ending on the 30th day of June, 1935.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The board is asked to base its allocations on the 12 months <Col N="295" /> ending on the 31st December, 1934. The 12 months prior to the appointed day was the original date, but, when the Bill was published, a number of curers went out and bought pigs at any price in order to drive up the qualifying amount.  We issued a statement from the Department pointing out that I intended in the Dáil to change the qualifying period to the calendar year 1934.  Of course, that had the desired effect.  On the whole, the year 1934 would be the fairest. The words in the amendment if added now would not do the same amount of damage, because there are only a few weeks to go.  The year 1934 is the qualifying period for every purpose and there is no great reason for changing it.  This only refers to the trade.  It does not make any difference to the producers.  It would be unfair to insert the amendment as between curer and curer, because they were working on the basis of that qualifying period and while some curers may have done more than the average during these six months some may have less.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Dowdall I move amendment No. 22:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 99, sub-section (3).  To add at the end of the sub-section a new paragraph as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(d)  the prices realised for bacon, hams, offals and by-products during the relevant production quota period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment would throw the enormous task on the Board of finding out these figures.  They have to take certain things into consideration when allocating the quota, the output of a particular factory in 1934, and the prices realised for bacon, hams, offals and by-products during the relevant production quota period.  I am afraid that would be an enormous task for any Board.  It would mean a sort of judicial inquiry to get all the relevant figures.  They would have to get a good deal of the evidence practically on <Col N="296" /> oath, as to the price realised.  My objection to the amendment is that that would be an impossible task.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Dowdall I move amendment No. 23:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 99, sub-section (3).  To add at the end of the sub-section a new paragraph as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(d)  the progress in production at each licensed premises for the three years preceding the 31st day of December, 1934.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We took the year 1934. The amendment would have the effect of giving a sort of arithmetical progression.  There are factories that dealt with 400 pigs a week in 1932, 500 in 1933, and 600 in 1934.  Under the amendment that factory should deal with 700 pigs a week in 1935, 800 in 1936, etc., while another factory dealing with 1,200 pigs a week in 1932, 1,100 in 1933, and 1,000 in 1934, might go down to 900 in 1935, 800 in 1936, etc.  I do not think that is what the Senator meant.  The amendment means that the small factories would be able to reach 1,600 pigs a week while a big factory might automatically go out of business on the arithmetical basis.  In practice all that could be gained by the amendment would be a slight change from the 1934 basis.  If there was slight progress upwards one factory would get a little higher, but if the progress was downwards it would go a little lower.  I do not think it is worth while bringing in that principle for what would be achieved.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 24:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 109.  To add at the end of the section a new paragraph as follows:</P>
      <P>(c) subject to conditions approved by the Minister, sell bacon or establish a marketing organisation for the sale of bacon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If the Minister says the Board can do this I presume there is no necessity for <Col N="297" /> the amendment.  But I cannot find that there is power to establish a marketing organisation.  Possibly the Board may do so, and may use the people who come together to allocate the quantity.  They may also discuss prices of bacon on the home or on the English market.  My feeling is that that position should be regularised, and that the Board should have power to undertake advertising and marketing, as well as research work to deal with the utilisation of by-products.  There is very little use in advertising as a Board or as a group unless they are going to sell as a group.  There is just as keen competition between our curers in the British market as there is between creameries.  I see no reason why that should be.  There is the possibility of the general level of prices in the English market being lower, because one factory may have hams or sides to offer at 1/- or 2/- per cwt. less than another factory.  Whatever may be said of the home market undoubtedly there should be a marketing organisation for our bacon in England. In my view that organisation should be constituted under definite regulations to be approved by the Minister.  The Board should have power to establish such an organisation but the Minister should be responsible for saying &ldquo;yes or no&rdquo; to the regulations that will be drafted.  Possibly the curers would welcome the opportunity of bringing such an organisation into existence.  I cannot see how it is going to injure anyone.  Possibly it would raise the general level of prices for Irish curers in the English market and incidentally the prices paid Irish farmers for their pigs.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought this amendment was not necessary; certainly it is not necessary for a voluntary marketing scheme.  I can see Senator Baxter's point.  Nineteen out of 20 might agree to come into the marketing scheme but where you have one holding out you would want some sort of legislative sanction.  When these curers meet in Committee it is more than likely that they will turn to improving the market. They may try to work out some sort of a voluntary marketing scheme.  I am not sure that there is <Col N="298" /> any improvement to be got out of the market.  If any Senator will look at the prices quoted for Irish bacon on the British market he will find that they are very good; in fact, sometimes they are better than the prices for English bacon, while they are always better than the prices for Danish or any other class of bacon.  I do not think there is any undercutting, as there was alleged to be in the case of butter.  Even so, there may be some room for improvement.  If some sort of voluntary scheme was devised they might be able to do better than they are doing at the present time.  There is nothing to prevent a voluntary scheme.  I do not like to support anything else for the moment.  I think it would be somewhat foolish to force any sort of scheme for a few years, even if there was one standing out, until the other clauses of this Bill had become operative.  I think it is hardly likely that this Bill will operate for two years without requiring some amendment and when an amending Bill is brought in there will be an opportunity of doing this.  While I am not in favour of the amendment, I cannot find any strong arguments to resist it.  I would be willing to leave it to the Seanad to decide.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot see any objection to this amendment.  I cannot see why the Minister should not be in favour of it because it is not compulsory; it only states that the board may do so-and-so, with the approval of the Minister.  If the Minister does not approve of the setting up of this marketing scheme nothing will happen. I think the Minister should accept the amendment?  It does not in any way interfere with his power.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not sure that the amendment, as it stands, would be a workable one.  I agree thoroughly with the principle of it.  I think it would be a very good thing for the industry if we had had a marketing board since the year 1926.  I have often mentioned that.  It is of such great importance that it is no harm to mention it again.  I believe that if we had a marketing board since 1926 our <Col N="299" /> exports of bacon would have been greater and our quota would be four or five or perhaps ten times as much as it is now.  I think the amendment would require some alteration for the reason that there are two distinct classes of bacon to be dealt with.  I do not think that the curers themselves would agree to marketing the two kinds of bacon that we produce.  I think this would require a joint board, representing those who produce wet-cured bacon and those who produce dry-cured. It is admitted that for the dry-cured bacon there is a high price.  I think it would be a good thing if there were a marketing board to deal with the two classes.  I am sure they would be able to get a great deal of business in the British market.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be very dangerous on the Report Stage of the Bill to introduce an amendment of this kind.  Senator Counihan says that this cannot do any harm because it is not compulsory.  From my reading of the amendment, I would say it is compulsory as against a dissentient curer.  If you have agreement between the lot you can have a marketing board under the general clauses of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>The section says that the board may do all or any of the following things.  That implies that the board may not do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The board may, but the constituents of the board may not be agreeable to what the board may do in regard to marketing.  Some house in the trade may not agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Then the Minister would decide.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has the final word.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>He has not the final word.  He may approve subject to conditions, one of the conditions being that the trade is unanimous.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It might be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister has power to impose a condition like that, then my submission to the House is <Col N="300" /> that the amendment is unnecessary because if they are unanimous there is no necessity for this amendment.  If they are not unanimous the thing may be compulsory as regards one curer or a section of the curers; therefore it is a compulsory piece of legislation and I think that it has not been sufficiently considered.  For that reason, I do not think the amendment ought to be pressed at this stage, seeing that within 12 months probably we will have an amending measure to deal with matters of this kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to point out, with reference to what Senator Comyn has said, that they may be permitted to do things as far as the English trade is concerned but that they may not be permitted to operate this scheme for our internal trade.  We may not like the marketing organisation to squeeze the last penny out of the consumer here.  This thing might be done voluntarily, when the Minister may have no control.  It might be better that the scheme would have to be submitted to the Minister and considered by him.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Government amendment No. 25:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 113, sub-section (4).  To delete in line 40 the word &ldquo;account&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;document.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 26:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 117, sub-section (3).  To delete in line 19 the word &ldquo;seven&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;eight.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is one of a series of amendments which have to do with the Pigs Marketing Board.  I argued this on the last occasion.  I do not know what weight my argument had with the Minister &mdash; whether I convinced him <Col N="301" /> that what I was urging was the right thing to do.  I am satisfied that it would be a better way to meet the situation.  The bacon curers are very much in this Bill; they are buying pigs and they control the Bacon Marketing Board.  You cannot blame the farmers when they say that they are in the hands of the curers.  You meet farmers coming home from town, and you ask them how they did.  They tell you what price they got and ask: &ldquo;what could we do?&rdquo;  We know what that means, that they just have to take what they get.  They think that in different circumstances the price would be better. Whatever sort of competition there may have been in the past between curers and buyers, this Bill is going to go all the way towards eliminating that competition.  I am satisfied that the producers of pigs will be just as dissatisfied in the future as they have been and as they now are; they will feel that the dice are loaded against them in the constitution of the Pigs Marketing Board.  I think, in the first place, that such an argument ought not to be left to them.  There ought to be no justification for them making such a case.  The Minister possibly will say that the board is constituted of three and three with a Chairman, and the producer is going to get a fair crack of the whip.  The farmer-producer in this country always feels that whatever others are able to accomplish he always seems to come in for the knocks.  Generally, he feels that he is in the hands of the other fellow, and he finds it very difficult to hold his own.  While I am not going to suggest that the curers' representatives on the Pigs Marketing Board will not be prepared to give the producer a fair crack of the whip, I believe that the curers' representatives there will argue that the price of pigs ought to be reasonably low.  It may be that the line of the producers' representatives will be to fix the price as high as they can.  I somehow feel, with that constitution of the board, you are going to have a rather unreasonable attitude. I think if the constitution of the board were different&mdash;if it were in accordance with what I set down in my series of amendments&mdash;it would lead to a better <Col N="302" /> spirit on the whole.  Now my view is that if you have a composition of four and three, the curers' representatives, realising the position of a four and three vote, would take the line that reasons would have to be produced to convince the other people that they were asking something that was unreasonable, and because the other people found that it was within their power to get decisions favourable to themselves, I think their attitude would be, not to show themselves so much as strong, but as reasonable men. I think the spirit of the board instead of being an attitude of defensive tactics, one group against another, would be one of reason and fair play. I feel that if you had a board constituted of four producers' representatives and three curers' representatives, you are going to have the four producers' representatives voting for a price, no matter what may be said by others, which, in the circumstances, is fair.  I suggest that if you have a board constituted as I have outlined, you would have the attitude every time on the part of the producers' representatives, of being fair all round.  I think a three and three decision is going to be practically impossible, and each side will try to compel the Chairman to give a decision favourable to itself.  The Chairman's position is going to be practically impossible.  He will be the friend of none.  He will not be looked upon as fair by either side, and the people of the country, who are interested, will not consider that they have got a fair crack of the whip.  I think if the producers felt that the board, because of its members, was tilted slightly in their favour, and that if things were going slightly against them that they would get fair play, it would be a great advantage.  They would feel that a decision arrived at was taken because of the facts, and people would feel convinced that everything was done that could possibly be done.</P>
    <P>I think the Minister ought to accept these amendments.  If this particular amendment was accepted I think it would create a sense of justice and confidence in the board on the part of pig producers in the country.</P>
    <Col N="303" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I support this amendment, but I would prefer if the Minister would accept an amendment of mine later on which would provide that a member of the Pig Buyers' Association should be added to the board.  The pig buyers of the country have been treated very badly.  They are a very important body as far as the pig producers and bacon curers are concerned.  The Minister may say they are not interfered with.  They are, because anybody who knows anything about the pig trade knows that pig buyers going to a fair have often to buy on speculation and send in their pigs to obtain the price ruling in the day.  The Minister must know that many pig buyers are producers and exporters as well.  For the benefit of the Pigs Marketing Board, I think it would be as well to have representatives of the Pig Buyers' Association on that board.  If the Minister would accept that form of amendment, he could then nominate a member of the Pig Buyers' Association upon the board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we in order in discussing Senator Counihan's amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That amendment is not before us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I tried to impress upon the House on another occasion that the pig dealers themselves do not want representation on this Board.  I think that Senator Baxter has no great case for this amendment.  If you have three producers arguing they are as good as if you had four producers, because if any of the six on the Board dissents, the chairman has to decide.  It does not matter whether the Board consists of three and three or three and four. There was fair agreement in getting together the sections of this Board.  I think it would be going back on the various interests if I were to accept this amendment.  I therefore have to oppose it as strongly as possible.  As I explained in the Dáil, three producers should be able to make as good a case as four.  If the producers and the curers agree, then the chairman does <Col N="304" /> not come into it at all.  If they agree, I say again three producers would be as good as four and I do not know what advantage would be gained by having four instead of three.  There may be something in the psychological effect that would follow from having four producers instead of three.  But I do not think there is much in that. The Board will not be long in existence before it will be learned that when a good case is made in the producers' favour that is all that is necessary.  No useful purpose would be served by this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to me Senator Baxter has made a very good case for this amendment.  It strikes me in addition that practically every class engaged in this industry is protected except the producer.  We have passed amendments protecting the workers in their conditions of work and wages. We are giving this Board full powers over the allocation of pigs and the marketing of pigs and over the grading of bacon in the factories.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand it was so; but, of course, I agree if the Minister corrects me.  There are other clauses protecting the interests of certain classes interested in this industry and surely it is not too much to ask that the producers should be represented by having four of their members on the Board.  I have no objection to Senator Counihan putting in an amendment with regard to the pig buyers.  I think it is quite fair that on this Board the producers should have a little extra influence.  The producers must have a big interest in the efficiency of the Pigs Marketing Board, because it is their raw material that will be marketed, especially that of the small producers.  We have 6,000 shareholders in our society with an average of 10 shares each.  I think it is not asking too much that this amendment should pass.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand from the Minister that he has discussed this matter with the interests concerned and he has indicated that there was <Col N="305" /> general agreement.  I do not want to press a point that would create a difficult situation for the Minister and, on the understanding that there has been general agreement I would ask leave to withdraw the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it quite certain that the chairman can decide provided there is no unanimity?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>He has very special powers, certainly in regard to fixing prices.  If there is not unanimity he fixes the price.  There must be unanimity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>Where is that provided in the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 134.  I think if the Senator will read that he will find it very clearly set out there.  The cases in which the chairman decides are:</P>
      <P>the making of a price order, a freight allowance order, a buying allowance order, or an order amending a price order, a freight allowance order or a buying allowance order.</P>
      <P>In all these cases, unless there is unanimity the chairman decides, so that everything in regard to the cost of pigs is decided by the chairman unless there is unanimity.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 27 not moved.</P>
      <P>Government amendments Nos. 28 and 29:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 120, sub-section (1).  To delete in line 49 the word &ldquo;biennial&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;triennial.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Section 120, sub-section (2).  To delete in line 2 the word &ldquo;biennial&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;triennial.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 30 and 31 not moved.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 32:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 123, sub-section (1).  To delete in line 30 the word &ldquo;two&rdquo; and <Col N="306" /> to substitute therefor the word &ldquo;three.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Agreed.</P>
    <P>
      <i>The Leas-Chathaoirleach took the Chair.</i>
    </P>
    <P>Amendments Nos. 33 and 34 not moved.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 35:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 127, sub-section (2).  To delete in line 31 the words &ldquo;and committees of agriculture&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the words &ldquo;consisting of persons whose names are entered on a register of pig producers established by the Minister.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The Minister either intends this section to be operative or he does not. I take it that at some time or another he intends that it should be operative. The section reads:&mdash;</P>
      <P>The Minister may by order ... direct that there shall be formed in the election year specified in such order and each subsequent election year a panel of the specified number of persons eligible for nomination by the Minister as producer members, that the persons whose names are to be entered in such panel shall be nominated by approved associations and committees of agriculture. ...</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to delete &ldquo;committees of agriculture&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;consisting of persons whose names are entered on a register of pig producers established by the Minister.&rdquo;  My idea is that this panel shall be formed by a vote of members of approved associations, composed of individuals on a register of pig producers.  My view is that the words &ldquo;and committees of agriculture&rdquo; have no meaning really.  I think, further, it would be unwise to ask Committees of Agriculture to make suggestions with regard to this panel.  The House will note that I am not here asking that this register of pig producers should be used for the purpose of electing to the Pigs Marketing Board representatives of the pig producers.  What I seek is that a register of pig producers should be compiled from which associations would be formed, and that these <Col N="307" /> people would vote for persons whose names would go on the panel, from which panel the Minister would select three persons to go on the Pigs Marketing Board.  Any thought I have been able to give the matter&mdash; and I thought a certain amount about it and have studied the debate in the other House&mdash;convinces me that this is the best way to try to get the producers directly represented on the Pigs Marketing Board.</P>
    <P>Three persons are to be put on the Board as representing the producers. The present position is that these people will be nominated direct by the Minister.  As far as I know the country, I think it would be very difficult for the Minister at present to find anybody who would nominate them for him.  I do not see what group of people he could ask to nominate a panel from which a selection might be made, and I think such a method of selection would be very inadequate in present circumstances. You would possibly get a group of people who would be supposed nominally to represent producers but who in fact did not represent the producers. My view is that unless the producers are fully and fairly represented, and unless selections like these are fairly made, it would be better not to pretend that the producers are being represented at all.  It would be better for the Minister to take the responsibility on himself.</P>
    <P>My amendment would mean that the Minister would have compiled a register of pig producers, and from a selection made by the people on that register would be drawn the persons who are to go on the Pigs Marketing Board.  Apart altogether from the desirability of compiling a register for this purpose, it would be advisable, I think, that this register should be compiled for other purposes.  The register might be useful in other ways. There was an amendment moved and withdrawn by Senator The McGillycuddy on the Committee Stage which sought to do certain things with regard to the limitation of pig production. There is a possibility that <Col N="308" /> that step might be necessary yet.  I put it to the Minister that if such a step had to be taken it would have to be taken because there were attractions about pig production and because, in fact, people had gone into pig production who had not been in it before.  The old producers were going out, and perhaps were being driven out by the newcomers.  I think it would be a very good thing to have a register of pig producers immediately compiled in this country to meet a situation of that kind.  You would then see who the real producers were and where they were located.  You would have a full and complete geographical survey of pig production in the country.  It would, I believe, give our people a much more intelligent interest in pig productivity than the kind of haphazard interest they have had up to the present.</P>
    <P>The Minister may argue&mdash;I do not know whether he will or not, but he suggested it in the other House&mdash;that it was not his obligation to organise these people.  I think it would be possible to compile such a register on the present voters' register.  You could easily have a letter after the name of a voter indicating whether he was entitled to vote in a certain specific election or not.  It is not impossible to do that, and I think the time to do it is now, when you are not going to use it immediately, and when the people are in a calmer state than they would be if they thought you were going completely to transform the whole situation in the country from the point of view of pig production or of doing something very new.  Certainly by the compilation of such a register you will have a record of the people who have a right to say who should represent them on the Pigs Marketing Board.  There is no other means by which you can get these people to express their view in the way you want them to express it.</P>
    <P>I considered whether I should attempt to delete that part of the section dealing with the panel and whether it was possible to elect direct to the Pigs Marketing Board and I came to the conclusion that possibly <Col N="309" /> the better method was to elect a number of people to go on the panel and that from that panel of eight or nine, the choice should be made. I think you can start all sorts of activity, even political activity, around an election like that if you start it at a particular time.  I think the time to start to compile the register is now.  You can do it quietly without creating any disturbance by outside considerations.  You could do it through the Gárda when they are taking their census.  They can do it when they are making out their returns.  They know every individual who is a pig producer, and they have nothing to do but to sit down and compile a list of such people.  Then when you want your register later you have got it.  Other people, if you desire to prevent it, cannot rush into the industry in that sort of fever that can be worked up around movements of this kind.  From every point of view, it is desirable to see how many people are in pig production at the present moment.  If later, steps have to be taken to limit pig production, the Minister would have at hand an instrument which he could use.  He could operate it just as the Minister for Finance, for the purposes of the Budget, can impose restrictions to prevent certain people rushing into a certain line of business or getting in certain imports. Just as the beet growers were cut down in their acreage, the Minister for Agriculture may reach a point when certain people, and certain people only in particular zones, will be permitted to continue in pig production. If that were necessary he would have this register.  I would prefer that we should not reach that point; that we should have a market which would make such a step unnecessary, but if we ever did reach such a point this register would be of incalculable benefit.  The Minister could have it prepared quietly and unostentatiously now and it would be there when he wanted it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I strongly support the amendment moved by Senator <Col N="310" /> Baxter.  Of all bodies, I think the most objectionable through which to get representation for pig producers are the committees of agriculture.  I would very much prefer to leave the selection of members of the board entirely to the Minister without any recommendation from the committees of agriculture.  As Senator Baxter has pointed out, it would be very easy to organise a strong canvass of the committees of agriculture and to get them to nominate persons as members of the Pigs Marketing Board who would have no connection whatever with pig production and who would be most objectionable from the pig producers' point of view. For that reason the Minister should delete the words referring to committees of agriculture and should set up, as Senator Baxter suggests, some organisation of pig producers.  When the time comes when that organisation could function, the members would have responsibility for nominating members for the Pigs Marketing Board or nominating panels from which the Minister could select members.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that Senator Baxter is achieving very much by this amendment because in sub-section (2) it is laid down that if approved associations, that is associations approved by the Minister, are in existence, they will elect the members.  Sub-section (2) was put in because it was feared there might not be an approved association that would represent the whole country and then the words were added &ldquo;or committees of agriculture&rdquo;&mdash;not &ldquo;and committees of agriculture&rdquo; as given in the Bill.  I am not very keen on this section at all.  It was forced on me more or less in the Dáil, but I think Senator Baxter's amendment does not alter the situation to any great extent.  Senator Baxter's amendment merely aims at deleting the words &ldquo;and committees of agriculture,&rdquo; but the section would still have the same effect as the members would still be nominated by an approved association. An approved association is <Col N="311" /> defined lower down in the section as &ldquo;an association of pig producers in Saorstát Eireann for the time being approved by the Minister.&rdquo;  The only difference is that Senator Baxter wants it established by the Minister whereas the section says it shall be approved by the Minister.  I do not think any Minister should be asked to establish an organisation of that kind.  That is surely not his job. We have trade unions established by Labour leaders and surely the farmers' leaders should be able to establish an organisation of pig producers. In fact it would be wrong for the Minister to interfere at all by setting up an organisation of that kind.  I do not believe it would be very difficult at all to get a pig producers' organisation if there was a group to organise it because every factory keeps a register, a list of those who deliver pigs.  If you got that list from the factories you would have a register of all pig producers.</P>
      <P>I do not think that there can be any great fraud about who is a pig producer and who is not.  I do not think anything would be gained by the acceptance of the amendment unless the Senator's point is that the Minister should establish the organisations rather than that the Minister should approve of them, as the section says.  That is the only difference there is.  Senator Counihan said that he would prefer direct nomination by the Minister rather than selection from a panel submitted by the county committees of agriculture.  I would not like to go that far.  Even if we leave the section out, the Minister can still adopt that system.  If I were to nominate producer-members now, even if this section were out of the Bill altogether, I could, of course, as Senators know, write to all the county committees and ask them to submit two or three names each.  Out of that panel I could select members representing the producers.  So far as the Minister is concerned, the putting in or taking out of those words in the Bill is not going to make the slightest difference.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="312" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I am still of opinion that there is much more in this amendment than the Minister has stated. I still hold to the view that it is highly desirable that a register should be compiled.  That does not mean that the Minister should form associations. Let the producers do that for themselves; but if a register were compiled the Minister could have it for his own purposes at the appropriate time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Am I to take it that Senator Baxter prefers that the Minister should nominate rather than that the members should be elected as they can be under sub-section (1)?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I prefer sub-section (2). Otherwise, I am afraid you will have all sorts of campaigning, and that you will not get the right men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>If I am in order, I move that the amendment be accepted with the deletion of the words &ldquo;committees of agriculture.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think there is much to be said for Senator Counihan's suggested amendment&mdash;that the amendment would be more perfectly drafted with the omission of the words he mentions.  I do not know if that would meet Senator Baxter's view.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to have the register compiled.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the permission of the House to have my suggested amendment put now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment has been declared lost, and, therefore, no amendment to it can be moved.  We will now take Government amendment No. 36:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 127, sub-section (5).  To delete in line 49 the figures and words &ldquo;1938, the year 1940&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the figures and words &ldquo;1939, the year 1942, the year 1945.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask leave of the House to take amendments Nos. 37 and 38 together:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="313" /> Section 140, sub-section (5).  To delete paragraph (e).</P>
    <P>Section 140, sub-section (6).  To insert before the sub-section a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(6)  No price order shall fix for the highest grade of pigs a price lower than the cost of production of such pigs as shown by costing accounts kept in connection with farms owned by the Department of Agriculture.</P>
    <P>Leave granted.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>These two amendments deal with the one matter.  The idea in both is that the price fixed for the higher grade pigs should not be lower than the cost of production as determined by the accounts kept in the Department's own farms at Ballyhaise, Clonakilty and Glasnevin.  The Pigs Marketing Board, which will fix the price of pigs, is to be composed of farmer-producers and of curers.  The farmer-producer is undoubtedly concerned with the cost of production. The curer is probably only concerned with it in so far as it is liable to raise the price of the pig to him.  He may not be producing pigs at all himself. When the price for pigs is being fixed, it ought to be brought home to the curer, as well as it is to the producer, that the producer is at least entitled to the cost of production.  Possibly, Labour members of the House may ask why the producer should be so modest as to ask for the cost of production only, and that for the highest grade of pig.  The Minister for Industry and Commerce is in the House at the moment.  I do not want to bring him into this debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>Lucky Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>But I have before me his point of view on the cost of production with regard to the growing of cereals and other agricultural products. He is reported to have said that there is no good in growing beet, or any other crop, unless the producers can be guaranteed a price that will leave them the cost of production&mdash; leave them a profit.  I think the Minister was quite right in saying that. <Col N="314" /> There is no use in growing any crop unless you can guarantee to the producer a price above the cost of production. We have to get our minds clear on this&mdash;as to whether tillage and the growing of cereals is more important than the production of pigs.  Pigs come off the farm as a finished product. The production of cereals is of no value unless they are fed to animals which can find a market.  These cereals will only be produced so long as the growing of them covers the cost of production.</P>
      <P>The Minister for Industry and Commerce, in his speech, was obviously dealing with beet and with other crops. I am sure he was also thinking of oats and barley.  The Minister for Agriculture was responsible for introducing and passing through the Oireachtas legislation, the effect of which has been to raise the cost of pig production. That is beyond question.  He has raised the cost of pig production to what has now come to be a real danger point.  The legislation that we pass here can only be said to be fruitful when it brings benefit to the people. This measure can only be said to be a fruitful one when we are able to see good results coming from it at our fairs and markets through the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The pig population of the country is not increasing.  It may be said that it has increased to a trifling extent.  No one, I think, will deny that there is great depression in the agricultural industry.  The present position is certainly very bad, but I suggest that things would be much worse if it were not for the extent to which our people have gone in for pig production, and have kept in that branch of agricultural productivity in recent years. Taking the figures for last year and the previous year, our pig population has only increased by 4.1 per cent., while in the Six Counties the increase for the corresponding period has been 40.6, or ten times more than it has been in the Saorstát.  The Minister and all of us know the reason for that.  Bacon prices in the Six Counties range to-day from 62/- to 65/- per cwt., while the price in Cavan town yesterday was only 48/-.  But there is a further very <Col N="315" /> great disadvantage, and it is this&mdash;this is what we do in my county and I suppose those are the conditions of which one can speak best: We go in and buy our 2 cwt. bag of meal.  The price of meal is 14/6 at present.  The pig feeder in the Six Counties will buy his bag of meal for 10/- or 10/6.  There was a fair in Cavan yesterday in which there were not less than 2,000 young pigs.  Half of that number went home unsold.  That is quite a change.  A fortnight ago, I was standing beside some carts of pigs in the same town.  I saw three pigs, about 11 weeks old, bought at £3 10/-.  I should think that they weighed about 2 stone each. Let the Minister make the calculation that the farmer would have to make in dealing with this type of problem.  It is calculated that 4 lbs. of feeding stuffs will give approximately 1 lb. of meat.  That means 4 cwt. of grain for 1 cwt. of pork.  With us, 4 cwt. of grain would cost £1 9/- at present. One of the pigs would cost £1 3/4. Therefore, to the man who bought these three pigs the initial cost was £2 12/4.  For that outlay, without putting anything against his skim milk or his leavings of potatoes, if there are any, his cwt. of bacon at 48/-, plus his initial 2 stone, will give him £3 when the pig is sold.  The cost to him at present is £2 12/4, and that is putting nothing on skim milk, potatoes or labour.  There is nothing in that sort of pig productivity.</P>
    <P>I met a man in one of these hundreds of carts which went home from our fair with pigs unsold.  He had six pigs in the cart, and I asked him why he did not sell.  He said: &ldquo;I could not sell; I was not asked what brought me to the fair.&rdquo;  I asked him how many bags of meal he had bought for the pigs already.  He said he had bought three.  That is to say, he had spent 43/- on them.  I do not think he could get anything like 15/- each for the pigs yesterday.  At 15/- each, he would get £4 10/-, while, on meal alone, he spent £2 3/-.  That is the problem with which our people are faced.  The initial producer has to buy meal at the inflated price to which legislation has <Col N="316" /> raised it.  If that is passed on to the man who is going to finish, he will be up against the same problem.  He has to buy these cereals which the Minister for Industry and Commerce believes will not be produced unless the producer is guaranteed the cost of production, plus a profit.  What about the thousands of small farmers engaged in pig rearing?  In my county, 13,000 out of 19,000 holdings are of £10 valuation and under.  These are the people who have to buy this raw material at this guaranteed price and when they bring their products into the market there is no guarantee that their cost of production will be covered.  If the State is going to legislate so that the producer of grain and cereals in the good tillage land is to have his cost of production covered, plus a margin of profit, I do not think it ought to be at the expense of the type of men for whom I speak.  These are the people who are going to increase the pig population. Unless we are able to bring to the notice of a wider circle of people than those who are doing this kind of work, unless we are able to bring to the notice of Senators, engaged not in agriculture, but in other walks of life, to the notice of the Bacon Marketing Board, and to the notice of the bacon curers who are not engaged in pig production and sometimes do not concern themselves to any great extent with the costs in that branch of the industry&mdash;unless our people can bring to the notice of the parties I have mentioned the factors in the cost of the finished article, justice will not be done to them.  It is not too much to expect that the pig producer here would get what, apparently, every other producer, with the exception of himself and the cattle producer, is getting.  In the case of the industrialist, it does not matter what the type of industry&mdash;it may be the pettiest factory in the State employing a dozen people&mdash;the factory cannot be set going until the owner is guaranteed the cost of production and a profit.  His capital must be assured and trade union rates of wages must be assured to the workers before a stone is laid upon a stone.  If all that is essential to the <Col N="317" /> encouragement and development of industries employing a few thousand people, at most, why are the pig producers, who employ thousands and thousands and who provide the raw material for the bacon factories, employing a couple of thousand people at least, put in a position in which they are expected to continue in production when the cost of production is not covered, and cannot be covered because of legislation which the Minister for Agriculture deems wise and necessary in the interests of another section of farmers?  If the Minister gives guarantees, through legislation, to certain farmers, I hold he has no right to withhold these guarantees from others.  If he gives a guarantee to the producers of cereals, the consequences are inevitable.  We saw them in our fair yesterday and we shall see them elsewhere. We see them reflected in the statistical return, which shows that the farmer across the Border has been going into pigs by the thousand while we are only increasing production by tens.  In justice to our pig producers, I think the Seanad ought to accept my amendment as a just and equitable proposal.  If the cost of production to farmers engaged in the rearing of pigs must be increased, then those farmers, who are so essential to the growers of cereals, should not be left unprotected, as they are at the moment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I strongly support this amendment and I believe it is the most important amendment we have had to-day.  Senator Baxter has given the figures and has left very little for anybody else to urge in support of the amendment.  He stated the realities of the situation clearly and accurately.  I can endorse practically every word he said.  I can scarcely agree that legislation has benefited the tillage farmers to any tangible extent.  It has injured every other class, with small and poor results to the tillage farmers.  Some hand-to-mouth farmers are trying to grab a few shillings by growing wheat, but the whole wheat scheme is a fraud and is doing infinite injury to the land of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not the <Col N="318" /> Senator getting away from the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I disagree.  What I say has a very strong bearing on the amendment. Pollard&mdash;the by-product of the milled wheat&mdash;is at the moment at a prohibitive price.  In my part of the country, white pollard is 7/3 a bag and, when a pig feeder has to face that, you can realise his position.  Evidently, white pollard is dearer in my part of the country than it is in Senator Baxter's part of the country.  I read the report of a meeting of millers a couple of weeks ago at which one miller said that offals had accumulated to such an extent that he was offering them at £4 a ton.  I rubbed my eyes when I saw that and I should like to have some explanation of it.  I shall not go into the question of the growing of wheat further.  I regard this as a vital amendment because it goes to the root of the problem.  People must go out of the feeding of pigs, as they are doing at the moment, if there is not some guarantee that feeding stuffs will be sold at a price which will enable them to derive a profit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Baxter knows quite well that the principle of the Bill does not permit of this amendment.  I have explained that already in the other House and in this House.  The principle we are trying to establish is to get the best possible price for pigs, and to do away with the variation in price as between factory and factory and from day to day, under the ordinary economic law of supply and demand.  Any Senator ought to see that, if this amendment is carried, there will have to be some sort of control of production.  I do not think it can be established, as Senator Baxter argued, that, as a result of our cereals legislation, the cost has gone up to any great extent.  The position, before we brought in that legislation, was that offals were imported at Liverpool price, plus freight.  For some months, they have been below the Liverpool price. It is quite true that millers have been looking for permits to export offals but they have not got them.  The result is <Col N="319" /> that certain offals have gone down in price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>Where are they sold?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Any farmer who uses white pollard where brown pollard can be got a couple of shillings per cwt. less, does not know much about farming.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>Not at a couple of shillings per cwt. less.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We must remember that we have certain markets for pigs at home, a certain quota in Great Britain, as well as small markets outside, and that we cannot produce more pigs than will fill these markets.  If we produce more what is to become of them?  Supposing farmers go on producing pigs when we fill our own market requirements, the foreign market, and whatever other markets we get, and if there are pigs over and above the numbers required, what can we do?  We cannot guarantee prices.  If prices go down, and consumers get the benefit, then the ordinary law of supply and demand will operate.  If you want the other principle, to which I am not very much opposed, it is to limit production, so that we can lay down a definite limit and only have so many thousands of pigs produced for which we know we have a market.  Then we could have a fixed price.  But that is another way of tackling the problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As to Senator Baxter's remark, &ldquo;look at what has been done for manufacturers,&rdquo; I ask &ldquo;what have we done for manufacturers that we have not done for pig producers?&rdquo;  If a manufacturer wants to come here do we say, &ldquo;you can come and supply not only the home market but the whole world and we will guarantee you a certain price?&rdquo;  We have never done that.  We told manufacturers that we would put tariffs against foreign goods, but if they exceeded the demands of the home market there was no further protection. We have done the same for pig producers. We put a prohibitive tariff on bacon, a higher <i>ad valorem</i> tariff than in the case of any class of manufactured goods.  At the price of the bacon that was coming in, the tariff put on must have amounted to 200 per cent. <Col N="320" /><i>ad valorem.</i>  We did not do that for manufacturers.  We preserved the home market for our own bacon, the same as we did for manufacturers.  There is no use in the Senator saying that we did more for manufacturers than we did for producers of agricultural products. There is a different situation here.  This amendment would be impossible in this Bill.  I appealed to the Seanad on a previous stage to give this Bill a trial. Senator Baxter mentioned that 62/- was paid for pigs in Northern Ireland, and 48/- in Cavan.  That position will be made right under the Bill.  I do not think it is fair to have such a comparison, because the 62/- in Northern Ireland is subject to a reduction of a couple of shillings.  The 48/- in Cavan is comparable to 55/- in the South of Ireland.  If they can pay 55/- in the South, they will be compelled to pay it in other places because the price will go to 55/- automatically.  According to the report of the Tribunal curers are not paying as much as they should. We expect the price will be a few shillings more, possibly 57/- or 58/-, when the Bill is in operation.  That is as much as this Bill can do.</P>
    <P>If the number of pigs increases beyond the number that can be dealt with at home, and on the foreign market, what can anyone suggest except a fall in prices, in order to try to have a greater consumption of bacon?  A fall in prices usually results in decreased production.  Then when bacon gets scarce prices go up again. That is the principle we are following. If the amendment were carried it would be equivalent to a rejection of the Bill.  I do not want any Senator to say that I am against giving farmers the cost of production.  I am not.  If the Seanad wishes to pass the amendment, and to reject this Bill, I will have a try at the other system, that of cutting down the number of pigs.  I am afraid that will meet with just as much opposition.  If we have to go and tell individual farmers that they are keeping too many pigs, and will have to cut down the number by one-third, or that it would a penal offence to keep more pigs, Senators can realise the enormous administrative difficulties of carrying out such a scheme.  Apart <Col N="321" /> from that, it would be a hardship on certain farmers to have to cut down the numbers.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like the Minister to deal with the figures.  Is there any relationship between the cost of production and feeding costs?  Is not that a considerable factor in keeping the pig population so low?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>In spite of that the number of pigs is going up rapidly.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Government amendments Nos. 39, 40, 41 and 42:&mdash;</P>
      <P>39.&mdash;Section 147, sub-section (1).  To delete lines 52 to 55, inclusive, and to substitute therefor the following:&mdash;&ldquo;subject however to the following limitation, namely, that the total amount payable under this paragraph in respect of all pigs of that class purchased by licensees and registered minor curers during such sale period shall not, unless the board is of opinion that it is just and equitable that the said total amount should not be so limited, exceed a sum calculated by reference to the total weights of such pigs and a price equal to the difference between the appointed price for pigs of that class and the hypothetical price for pigs of that class.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>40.&mdash;Section 147, sub-section (2).  To delete lines 29 to 34, inclusive, and to substitute therefor the following:&mdash;&ldquo;class, such sum as the board thinks proper, subject however to the following limitation, namely, that the total amount payable under this paragraph in respect of all carcases of that grade of that class purchased by licensees and registered minor curers during such sale period shall not, unless the board is of opinion that it is just and equitable that the said total amount should not be so limited, exceed a sum calculated by reference to the total weights of such carcases and a price equal to the difference between the appointed price for carcases of that grade of that class and the hypothetical price for carcases of that grade of that class.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="322" /> 41.&mdash;Section 147, sub-section (3).  To delete lines 6 to 10, inclusive, and to substitute therefor the following:&mdash;&ldquo;proper, subject however to the following limitation, namely, that the total amount payable under this paragraph in respect of all carcases of that grade of that class purchased by licensees and registered minor curers during such sale period shall not, unless the board is of opinion that it is just and equitable that the said total amount should not be so limited, exceed a sum calculated by reference to the total weights of such carcases and a price equal to the difference between the appointed price for carcases of that grade of that class and the hypothetical price for carcases of that grade of that class.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>42.&mdash;Section 147, sub-section (4).  To delete lines 45 to 49, inclusive, and to substitute therefor the following:&mdash;&ldquo;board thinks proper, subject however to the following limitation, namely, that the total amount payable under this paragraph in respect of all carcases of that class purchased by licensees and registered minor curers during such sale period shall not, unless the board is of opinion that it is just and equitable that the said total amount should not be so limited, exceed a sum calculated by reference to the total weights of such carcases and a price equal to the difference between the appointed price for carcases of that class and the hypothetical price for carcases of that class.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>These amendments deal with the same question.  As the section stands the board is more or less tied to giving no greater bounty than the difference between the appointed and the hypothetical price.  It is conceivable, with prices changing rapidly on the British market and curers sending bacon there, it might not be possible for the board to change the hypothetical price from day to day. The easiest way to manage is to make it up afterwards by exceeding at times the difference between the two prices. I do not think it will be necessary to do that often.  It may be well to give <Col N="323" /> that power.  That is all that is involved in the amendments.</P>
      <P>Amendments agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government Amendment No. 43&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 147, sub-section (5).  To delete in lines 56-57 the words &ldquo;with the consent of the Minister.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Dowdall, I move Amendment No. 44:&mdash;</P>
      <P>New section.  After Section 154 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>155.&mdash;This Act shall continue in force for six years after the passing thereof, and shall then expire.</P>
      <P>Senator Dowdall thinks this Bill is not by any means a good one.  Generally speaking, the Senator believes that the Bill is bad <i>in toto.</i>  One reason he gives is that it discourages initiative.  He also feels that the quality will not be up to what we would like it to be, because once people have got a quota they will be indifferent regarding the quality. These are the Senator's views, not mine.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is essentially a permanent Bill.  We are going to set up registration of factories, and we may have to compel the owners to reconstruct their premises or to make structural alterations at big expense. In going to the expense of structural alterations there will have to be a certain amount of security in the trade. Then we come to the point of inspection, grading and so on.  We have to appoint a veterinary staff of specially trained men.  We cannot appoint these men unless they are permanent.  Are we to have 20 or 30 veterinary officers on hands in six years?  If so I do not know what will be done with them. They are going to be on a permanent basis.  It is hard to see how we could do otherwise.  Senators will agree that these Pigs and Bacon Boards will be permanent.  I am prepared to admit that there will be an amending Bill brought in, in two or three years. It is almost certain from our experience that there will be something <Col N="324" /> wrong in the working of this Bill and that an amending one will be necessary. I do not remember any Bill within the past ten years that did not need an amending Bill.  It would be a wrong principle to let the Bill lapse in six years.  Our inquiries go to show that the basis of Bills such as this is that they are to be permanent.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill, as amended, be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Road Transport Bill," RHead="1935.&mdash;Report">
    <Title>Road Transport Bill, 1935.&mdash;Report</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Leas-Chathaoirleach Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Government amendment:&mdash;</P>
      <P>New section.  Before Section 5 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>5.&mdash;(1)  Section 63 of the Principal Act is hereby amended in the following respects and shall be construed and have effect accordingly, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  by the substitution in clause (1)  of paragraph (a) of the said section of the words &ldquo;and was continuously employed (whether such employment commenced before or after the grant of such licence) whole-time, for a period of five years ending on the day preceding the critical date in the operation of the said vehicles, either by such licensee or by such licensee and his predecessor or predecessors in title to such business&rdquo; for the words &ldquo;and was so employed continuously for a period of five years ending on the day preceding the critical date&rdquo; now contained in the said clause;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(b)  by the substitution in paragraph (b) of the said section of the words &ldquo;(whether such employment commenced before or after the grant of such licence) whole-time, in the operation of the said vehicles, either by such licensee or by such licensee and his predecessor or predecessors in title to such business&rdquo; for the <Col N="325" /> words &ldquo;whole-time by such licensee in the operation of the vehicles used for the purposes of the business authorised by such licence to be carried on&rdquo; now contained in the said paragraph;</P>
    <P>(c)  by the substitution in paragraph (c) of the said section of the words &ldquo;either by such licensee or by such licensee and his predecessor or predecessors in title to such business&rdquo; for the words &ldquo;by such licensee&rdquo; now contained in the said paragraph.</P>
    <P>(2)  This section shall have and be deemed to have had effect as from the passing of the Principal Act.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRobinson" hpid="Mr. D.L. Robinson Mr. D.L. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.L. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that there was an arrangement made with Senator Kennedy that the Minister would introduce this section.  Senator Kennedy, I am informed, approves of it.  Accordingly, I beg to move the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickLynchKC" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I second it.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to make a statement before this Bill is passed.  On the Committee Stage Senator Wilson brought in an amendment which brought in the question of the drawing of beet as it is affected by this Bill. I only supported Senator Wilson's amendment because it affected a small number of people in whom I am interested. I tried to get in an amendment on the Report Stage to take in this small section of people, but I was told that the amendment was not in order because an amendment which was nearly the same had been defeated in Committee.  I should like to make a special appeal to the Minister on behalf of a few farmers and growers of beet.  I am not interested in any other carriers or hauliers.  A number of small growers of beet have appealed to me during the past week.  They put up to me&mdash;what I knew already&mdash;the great hardships under which they will labour <Col N="326" /> unless some special arrangement is made for them under this Bill.  During the Committee Stage a number of Senators including, I think, Senator Wilson, said that they were quite satisfied with the arrangement under the Bill, because the farmer or beet grower who had a lorry could draw his neighbour's beet for nothing.  Those people are very simple if they think that the farmer or beet grower who owns a lorry is going to draw his neighbour's beet for nothing.  I would like to make a special appeal to the Minister to exempt the very few farmers and growers of beet who are not ordinary carriers, and to allow them to charge their neighbours the small amount which they have been in the habit of charging them, a much smaller amount than is charged by the regular carriers.  Otherwise, I am quite satisfied from what I know that a number of these small growers would be put out of the business of growing beet altogether.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is another matter to which the Minister referred on the last day.  He said, when replying: &ldquo;I was very glad to hear certain Senators referring to the fact that the price of beet is not high enough.&rdquo;  He went on to say that certain people were carrying on a campaign to force down the price of sugar. I interjected that when the price of sugar was smaller the price of beet was higher.  The Minister denied that, and said that my information was wrong. I have here certain figures showing that when the price of beet was 46/- a ton the price of sugar was 25/3 a cwt.  The price of sugar remained in or about that figure until September, 1934. When the price of beet went down to 37/6 the price of sugar went up to 28/6. Now, when the price of beet is, as it will prove to be, still lower at the flat rate, the price of sugar has gone up by 5/9 per cwt., or 11/6 a bag.  If I were to go back further, to the beginning of the year 1926, I think the price of sugar beet to the three years guarantors was 54/- a ton or 15½ per cent. of sugar which realised a price of over £3 a ton to a very large number of growers&mdash;every good grower, in fact, who cultivated his beet properly.  The price of sugar at that time was about <Col N="327" /> 4½d. per lb., which, of course, was a very small price then compared to the very high price of beet.  Then, of course, there was a different arrangement in regard to the price of beet. Those who guaranteed a three years' supply were paid 54/- a ton.  So the Minister, when he said my information was wrong, evidently had not gone into the figures or he was trying to make out that the price of sugar was raised in the last Budget to pay for the price of beet, which is a ridiculous contention. It was raised to bring in revenue, regardless of everything else.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass) Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>The matter of the transportation of beet was discussed on the earlier stages of this Bill.  As I stated then, the situation is being carefully reviewed.  If it should happen that the railway companies are unable to cope with all the traffic of that kind, those other licensees will be available to deal with them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>At the same rate?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The rate at which beet is carried by the railway company, whether by road or rail, is not subject to the Department of Industry and Commerce, but to the Railway Tribunal.  The rate will have to be fixed on a basis that will cover the cost of transportation but, subject to that, any individual or association that feels that the rate is too high can avail of the machinery of the Railway Tribunal for the purposes of having a rate order made, if necessary, fixing a lower rate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The matter concerning the price of sugar is somewhat irrelevant to the debate.  I want to make it clear, however, that there are only three ways by which the price of sugar can be decresed: one by decreasing the cost of production in the factories, another by reducing the excise duty on sugar, and the third by decreasing the price of beet.  So far as the costs of production are concerned they will, of course, come down this year, when all the four factories will be worked to their fullest capacity.  Last year because the beet acreage was too low all the beet factories were not fully worked.  This year the full acreage will be grown and, <Col N="328" /> consequently, the cost of production per cwt. of sugar will be lower.  So far as the revenue is concerned, I merely point to the fact that the total revenue which the State hopes to secure from the taxes on tea and sugar this year will be about £100,000 less than the revenue secured by our predecessors in 1931 from sugar alone.  The only other way by which the cost of sugar can be brought down is by reducing the price of beet, and I am glad to know that the campaign against the price of sugar is not being worked for the purpose of forcing down the price of beet.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>It could not honestly be so.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Control of Imports" RHead="Orders&mdash;Motion of Approval">
    <Title>Control of Imports Orders&mdash;Motion of Approval.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRobinson" hpid="Mr. D.L. Robinson Mr. D.L. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.L. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the motion standing in the name of the Minister for Lands:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Eireann hereby approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 11) Order, 1934, made on the 21st day of December, 1934, by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass) Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>This Order prohibited the importation of coal, culm, shale and slack into Saorstát Eireann except under licence.  The object of the Order was to give effect to the informal arrangement entered into with the British Government regarding coal and cattle.  The quota appointed under the Order for the first quota period effects no reduction in the normal imports of coal, but the Order appointing the quota prescribed that out of a total of 1,000,000 tons of coal for the first period, that is from the 1st February, 1935, to the 31st July, 1935, 1,099,000 tons should be shown to the satisfaction of the Revenue Commissioners to have been purchased in and consigned from the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland.  There is a slight difference between the working of this Order and the working of other Orders, in so far as it is not designed to reduce the imports but to direct trade into other channels.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="329" /> In the case of most Quota Orders the purpose is to reduce imports.  When making them we contemplated the possibility of imports ceasing altogether. On that account, in the allocation of the quota, preference is given to those who have been in the business of importing this class of goods, so that they may continue to get what is coming out of that business as long as it remains.  In the case of this Order we contemplate that the importation of coal and slack will continue, and there is no desire to prevent new people entering into competition, operating for the purpose of increasing the business of one firm and decreasing the business of another.  It is, however, very difficult to combine that idea with the idea of restricting imports. Certain difficulties did arise; I think these difficulties have been got over. 75 per cent. of the quota was allocated at the beginning of the period in accordance with the Act.  The balance of 25 per cent. was used usually for special cases that arose where the quota allocation would be, say, less than a cargo of coal, and it was necessary to make it up in order to enable the coal to be imported at all, in so far as a small quantity could not have been brought in economically, and similar cases of that kind.  It was also operated to give limited quotas to any firms that had come into the business of importing coal since last year.  Generally speaking, the coal was allocated on the basis of the importation of last year.  The whole quota is now allotted, and it will possibly be necessary to make additional quotas for the quota period, not because the quota was too low, but because of licences not used.  I have no means of recalling a licence unused, or of cancelling a portion of the licence that is unused, and that has created certain difficulty in other Orders, but we hope that that difficulty will be obviated by amending legislation which we intend to introduce.  We have no powers in that direction after the licence is issued and not used, and our calculations are upset.  But in this case there is no difficulty.  The difficulty will be met by making an additional Order which will be done in the course <Col N="330" /> of a week or two.  In fixing the quota for the next period a liberal margin can be allowed to meet that situation if it arises again.  The Order was effective in carrying out our obligation under the coal-cattle arrangement.  It was an informal arrangement.  It consisted in this: that the British Government agreed to increase the normal cattle quota allotted to this country by 150,000 head, on the understanding that we would purchase coal to a value corresponding to the additional number of cattle exported.  The cattle are purchased at the ordinary market price and exported in the ordinary way.  It is anticipated that in order to carry out our obligation under this Order it will be necessary to purchase all our coal from Great Britain for this year.  Whether it will be renewed or not I am not in a position to say.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>Judging by the subdued and unostentatious manner of the Minister's explanation, one who knew nothing of the background of this motion would be inclined to think it was a mere matter of routine and of very little consequence indeed.  I think anyone who would draw such a conclusion would assume something that was very inaccurate.  The first question I mean to ask is why a motion of this kind has been so long deferred? The period with which it deals expires on the 31st July and is not very far away.  This Quota Order was made on the 21st December last year.  It is a very belated procedure to introduce an Order for approval, almost at the end of the period for which approval is sought.  I make that by way of preliminary comment, but, I think, that comment draws attention to a procedure which is not exactly the most desirable.  The Government makes an Order dealing with a certain period. That Order, to be operative and legal, must have the approval of the Oireachtas; and to defer seeking the approval of the Oireachtas until the period with which it deals is almost entirely run out, is a very wrong procedure. It may be a small matter in some cases, but this can hardly be described as a trivial or light matter. <Col N="331" /> When I first saw this motion tabled I was tempted to table an amendment asking the Seanad to defer approval of the Order until the terms of the informal agreement, to use the words of the Minister&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Informal arrangement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>Until the terms of the informal arrangement had been submitted to the Oireachtas.  However, I decided not to pursue the idea of moving an amendment for reasons that it might be calculated to be a waste of time.  I prefer to rest my criticisms direct upon the motion itself. I think the Oireachtas is entitled to know what are the terms of that informal agreement.  Surely that agreement took some tangible recorded form, which is capable of being presented in some tangible way to this House, and to the other House, so that we could see whether that informal agreement is one that meets with our approval.  Why should it be necessary to ask for this at all?  Is this informal agreement or informal pact something which is not fit for publication?  We have heard a good deal about our invisible imports and exports.  We have heard something of the invisible benefits of the economic war.  We have heard something even of the invisible man who fills the position of Governor-General, and I think we are entitled to know something about this invisible pact.  Now when this motion, based upon this invisible pact, or within this invisible pact, was reached&mdash;the terms of which never yet have been submitted to the people and the country&mdash;it was greeted with pæans of praise from nearly every section. Even the critics of the Government were inclined to withhold criticism in the hope that it was a foreshadowing of the return to values in the major lines and policy of the Government.  The organ of the Government itself gave it a conspicuous place of honour.  Glaring headlines were displayed on the front page of that paper.  The President himself, commenting on it, said:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;The present arrangement is complete in itself.  It is a business <Col N="332" /> transaction based on the mutual interest of the two countries.  It is a type of understanding that the Irish Government has always indicated its willingness to make.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The Minister for Land and Forests, in a notable speech where he reiterated his statement that although it took 100 years to establish the cattle trade, with God's help it would not take 100 years to kill it, said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The coal-cattle pact was a pound against pound agreement&mdash;what was generally called a fifty-fifty deal.  It had been arrived at entirely independent of other and conflicting issues. It was a business deal.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Now I think we ought to know a little more about that business deal.  Ministers have been very reticent about this invisible pact&mdash;I will not call it a secret agreement.  There are certain things that are public knowledge. It has been disclosed that, out of 1,100,000 tons of coal to be imported into this country, England is to get a monopoly of 1,099,000 tons.  We know that as a sort of <i>quid pro quo</i> there is to be an increase of 150,000 cattle to be exported.  These are the facts that we have been enlightened of. But I would like to ask the Minister can he give us information as to what is going to be the cost of implementing this pact&mdash;this informal arrangement, as the Minister calls this, or this invisible pact, as I prefer to call it. For every head of cattle that goes out of the Free State to Britain carries with it a tax or tariff duty, assessed at a figure by some at £5 and by others at £6 per head.  Probably it would be safer to assume it at the smaller figure.  Will the Minister tell us if I am correct in estimating that 150,000 cattle under this pact that are exported from this country into the British market each will bear this tax? If so, that would amount to £750,000. Will he inform us also what revenue his colleague, the Minister for Finance, will secure as a result of the coal tax that this additional import of coal will impose?  We know there is a tax of 5/- per ton.  My rather primitive knowledge of arithmetic works out that 1,099,000 tons of coal at 5/- per ton <Col N="333" /> will yield something like £270,000. Will the Minister tell us also what is the cost to the State of the bounty which it will be necessary for the Saorstát Exchequer to pay in order to get the whole 150,000 head of cattle across to the British market?  I read in the debates in the Dáil last week one estimate of that figure which put it at £140,000.  If that figure is correct, and the other calculations I have made are correct, then this informal pact or arrangement &mdash; this fifty-fifty arrangement of Senator Connolly's &mdash; is going to cost the taxpayers of Saorstát Eireann anything between £1,000,000 and £1,250,000 to implement.  Am I right or am I wrong?  If I am right, then I think it is deluding the Oireachtas and deluding the people, for the Minister to come before the House and make such a disarming, disingenuous kind of a speech and not reveal to people that this particular informal arrangement carries with it these implications.  If this arrangement does not carry with it these consequences, then, of course, the Minister will be able to show that that is so, but I certainly will be astounded and I think that the country will be astounded if the Minister can show it does not.</P>
    <P>This fifty-fifty arrangement is going to cost the taxpayers of Saorstát Eireann, as far as I can see, over £1,000,000, and it is going to cost the other party to the fifty-fifty arrangement not a single penny.  On the other hand it is going to secure them a handsome revenue and secure them work for 5,000 miners in the British coal-fields.  That is the great fifty-fifty arrangement.  President de Valera says that &ldquo;that is the type of understanding that the Irish Government has always indicated its willingness to make.&rdquo;  In other words, an arrangement which costs the taxpayers of Saorstát Eireann over £1,000,000, puts 5,000 English miners to work, costs the British taxpayers not a penny but gives them a handsome subsidy with which to fight the economic war &mdash; that is the type of arrangement which the Irish Government has always indicated its willingness to make! This is the most comical economic war <Col N="334" /> carried on since Cain and Abel fell out!</P>
    <P>Some people have called it &ldquo;a gentleman's arrangement.&rdquo;  If it were permissible to describe it in terms of American slang, I would call it a &ldquo;suckers&rdquo; arrangement.  I have no doubt that when Mr. Thomas was making this informal arrangement he was in agreement with Barnum's dictum that there is one born every minute.  At any rate, this seems to indicate that on the coal sector of our offensive on the eastern front, the economic war has broken down and the cattle have broken through.  It would not be perhaps an accurate simile of this phase of the economic war, or caricature of an economic war, to say that the Government have got another white elephant on their hands. I would be inclined to think, since they discovered this peculiar sort of warfare, that they have got the tiger by the tail.  They are afraid to let go; they have got to keep hold of him for fear of their lives.  The result of that will be that the tiger will drag them into the economic jungle that this country is approaching where he can devour them at his own sweet will. I have no particular objection to the tiger devouring the Government so long as he is prevented from devouring the people as well.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>He is devouring the farmers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>There will be nothing but the bones of the farmers for the tiger very soon.  There is one aspect of the question to which I want to refer particularly, and that is the Coal Pact.  Before I come to that I want to anticipate the reply which the Minister will possibly make.  I can imagine the Minister saying: &ldquo;Does the Senator want to deny that this has been a great relief to the farmers, that it has given us an outlet for our cattle?&rdquo;  I can imagine his saying that with one eye on the Seanad and the other on County Dublin.  It has been.  No one denies it but when we consider the circumstances, that something &mdash; the export of 150,000 cattle &mdash; which would have been an ordinary <Col N="335" /> routine matter in normal times, and in ordinary sane conditions, should now cost the Saorstát over £1,000,000 to secure it, when that is considered a relief to the farmer, I ask the Minister, when he is making his reply, to bear that in mind.</P>
      <P>To come back to the point I was making, we should like to hear something about this Coal Pact.  I think it is not irrelevant to the matter under discussion but I want to be guided by the Chair.  This tax was originally imposed as a war measure against England.  The purpose of that particular tax having ceased, seeing that we have arranged a partial truce in that matter &mdash; we are no longer trying to keep out British coal; we are to secure that no coal other than British shall come in&mdash;why was the coal tax continued?  Why was it continued as a tax upon the Saorstát taxpayers themselves?  I think we are entitled to some explanation of that.  The statement is made repeatedly, and with every appearance of truth, that since this arrangement was made, not only has there been a substantial increase in the price of coal but that an inferior quality of coal is coming in under the new arrangement.  If that is so, it is something very curious, something that requires some further disclosure.  Of course, the Minister may plead that it is not good taste to display undue curiosity about a gentleman's arrangement, that a gentleman's arrangement should not be judged by the standards of a virago. But the description of &ldquo;gentleman's arrangement&rdquo; in that sense does not fit this agreement.  It is an arrangement that affects the people of this country vitally, which means an additional impost on it.  This arrangement, which will give certain partial relief, throws a flood-light on the position which is thus relieved, a flood-light of disclosure which is not by any means complimentary to those who are responsible for public policy in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Another aspect of the matter is that this additional export of cattle enables the British Government to collect from this country an amount far in excess <Col N="336" /> of the amount they claim in respect of withheld annuities and the other matters in dispute.  Surely when that gentleman's arrangement was being made, it might not have been too much for one of the contracting parties to have said: &ldquo;Well, while a certain amount is in dispute, can we not agree, if you are going to keep on your penal duties, that you will so arrange them that you will at least collect no more than the amount in dispute.&rdquo;  But they apparently acquiesced in this.  We are financing the British to carry on this war.  I think if Bernard Shaw would only apply his mind to this matter and describe how Saorstát Eireann, having declared war against the British Empire, is not only beggaring the people of the Saorstát to keep the fight going on this side but is also financing the British to carry on the fight on the other side, he would have one of the greatest themes for a comedy that could possibly be conceived.</P>
    <P>There is another arrangement that the members of the Government have been describing as a thing of shreds and patches.  I do not know how far, not having seen the terms of this pact, the description of shreds and patches could be made applicable to it, but I think, surveying the national policy of the Government from the angle that this reveals, one can only come to the conclusion that their policy &mdash; economic, political, internal and external &mdash; is a thing of shreds and patches, without character, without coherence, without any hope of success, so long as the obsession that at present dominates them prevails.  It is a policy which can only lead to a continuance of the farcical tragedy that is being enacted to-day, namely, the driving of the people to destitution and the country to chaos and disaster.</P>
    <P>I am not going to ask the Seanad to disapprove of this motion, but I think it is a motion which raises issues concerning which it is right that we should have sober criticism.  The time has come for this Government to realise that playing politics with the rights of the people is a gamble which does not pay in the long run; that <Col N="337" /> being dressed with a little brief authority does not justify them, or any set of men, in imagining that the lives and welfare of the people are just pawns on a chess board to be moved according to the political game that the Government at a particular time are playing.  Things have reached such a stage in this country that a halt will have to be called to that playacting. I want to say, of course, that I can see a Government that makes a bold departure from the established traditions having to meet with many difficulties and to encounter criticisms which are not always far-seeing or profound. I hope that I am not viewing the policy of the present Government from that angle.  There is one thing that, I think, I can take a pride in, and that is that during my life I have done something to try and establish this State.  It is because I see that the considered policy of this Government is shattering the stability of the State, is beggaring the people and leading them to despair, that I ask the Government to weigh well what they are doing before they reach the stage when there will be no retrieving the position; when there will be nothing but a state of beggary and misery even though Ministers may be sitting enthroned in Government Buildings.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the most audacious of all the motions that the revolving Minister, Senator Connolly, has ever brought before a House which is under sentence of abolition because it stood in the way of the dishonest and disastrous policy that he and his colleagues have adopted.  He comes to us to ask us to approve of a dishonourable and a disastrous policy from which even he and his associates have stampeded.  In spite of his prayer &mdash; I do not want to use the Belfast lingo although it is terse enough &mdash; that &ldquo;it took 100 years to build up the cattle trade of this country, but, thanks be to God, it will not take so many years to break down that system,&rdquo; he comes to this House to ask us to approve of this motion to help him in swopping Irish cattle for English coal.  The President ran the Irish treasure ship on the rocks in spite of <Col N="338" /> many warnings from the Seanad and he wants to be applauded because he gets away in the lifeboat with a quarter of beef and a lump of coal.  When Senator Connolly was throwing out his innuendoes that the annuities would not be collected by England&mdash;the suggestion, of course, was that they would not be collected at all, and that was made for vote-catching purposes &mdash; we said that that was a dishonest method of dealing with the matter; that it was a matter more for Scotland Yard than for the English Government.  In spite of that the Irish people were invited to imagine that there would be no collection of annuities.  His interpretation of the psychology of John Bull was very poor indeed because, at any rate, John Bull has one obstinacy, and that is that he likes to stick to a bargain. When we reneged the payment of the annuities, John Bull at once imposed a tariff on our cattle, a tariff which was not sufficient to bring in the full amount lost on the annuities to meet the interest and sinking fund on the £75,000,000 that had been advanced to buy out the land of Ireland from Irish landlords.  This coal-cattle pact has enabled John Bull to get more than the annuities were bringing in.  Can the Minister deny that Mr. Thomas said: &ldquo;Hitherto we were not getting enough from you; now we are getting too much but we will give it back.&rdquo; The President qualified the position with that extraordinary logic of his by saying: &ldquo;No, we will not take it back; this is a business deal and it has nothing to say to the economic war.&rdquo; What can you do with a mentality like that?  An appeal was made to the Opposition not to oppose the President's motion now before us.  An appeal was made that this motion should be passed without comment; and why?  Because the farmers said: &ldquo;Oh, for God's sake leave him alone; we can get rid of a few cattle at any rate, and you never know what he will do next.&rdquo;  Is that a dignified or an honourable position for the President of a State to be in &mdash; to have to be humoured as the Mad Mullah, <Col N="339" /> running amok with the farmers waiting to see when his run will end and the loot drop out of his pocket?  We are asked to approve and be grateful for his lucid interval.</P>
      <P>This sorry business really began in 1923 when President de Valera tried to break down the Parliamentary seat which he is now filling at a fine salary without paying income tax. He cost Ireland the blood of Collins, he broke the heart of Arthur Griffith, and he has now broken the heart of Ireland itself.  I will give you an example.  Last month, in Longford, there was a witness being cross-examined. This arises <i>apropos</i> because I want to show you what can happen when a Mad Mullah elects to cut off a country's income and mixes the prosperity of the country with politics.  When that happens you bring nearer the Socialist Republican State of Senator Connolly.  That gentleman always leaves himself loopholes. He is now in his second Government. He was with Mr. Cosgrave in 1928 and he is now with President de Valera.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order.  Is this relevant to the motion before the House?  What has this to do with Senator Connolly's politics?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Connolly's politics are certainly not relevant on this motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>It is relevant to the point I was making about the country's heart being broken and the people having lost confidence are losing adherence to the old and established foundations of Ireland on the eternal truths of religion.  Last month, as I was saying, a witness was being cross-examined in Longford and he was asked this question: &ldquo;Is it or is it not true that at Mass on Sunday last you interrupted the parish priest because he was talking against Communism and that you rose up in church and called him a liar.&rdquo;&ldquo;I did not,&rdquo; he said.  &ldquo;I said &lsquo;you are a low scoundrel and a liar&rsquo;.&rdquo;  An old man who was questioned about the incident: &ldquo;Is it true that that man <Col N="340" /> is allowed to live in an Irish village?&rdquo; said that 20 years ago such a man would not have been allowed to live here.  But now the country's heart is broken.  And we do not know which Party will do the most for us.  In other words, the Government are indistinguishable from the Communists. Here we are with the most naturally endowed fertile country in the world. The Government have cut off an income of £32,000,000 a year.  They have half-beggared and twice taxed us in the last three years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What is the other side of the picture?  It is this: I am full of misgiving because I doubt if there is a man in the Government with sufficient vision to imagine a country wherein anyone can live except as a pauper. In other words, their whole outlook is to reduce this country to a state of pauperism.  They are specialists in disasters.  They want to reduce the country to such a state of despair that they will be complete masters.  When all are paupers, they will be masters of the workhouse.  The battle was lost at Ottawa, where John Bull was staged as Public Enemy No. 1 and made to play the part of the great vote-catcher for his opponent, Mr. de Valera &mdash; the stage on which President de Valera sets him up as Public Enemy No. 1 of Ireland.  Mr. Seán T. O'Kelly was at Ottawa.  I suppose President de Valera did not go, fearing that he would have no one to repudiate.  If he had gone he should have been able to hold a pistol, or half a dozen pistols, to John Bull and say: &ldquo;We are buying £38,000,000 worth of goods from you; we are selling you cattle and agricultural products to the value of £32,000,000.&rdquo;  If President de Valera said: &ldquo;We want to take £60,000,000 worth of goods from you and we want you to take as much from us,&rdquo; John Bull would have asked: &ldquo;Where will I get it?&rdquo;  He could have been told: &ldquo;You are buying £40,000,000 worth from Denmark and, in return, Denmark is only buying £10,000,000 worth from you.  There is a deficit of £8,000,000 or £11,000,000 in what the Argentine sends to you and what you buy from her.  We want you to increase <Col N="341" /> your purchases from us and in return we will buy all the hardware that we require from you as well as the goods which your people who live in your Black Country and in Lancashire produce.&rdquo;  Of course, that was not done.  Mr. Seán T. O'Kelly was not so much concerned with that question as he was as to whether he should wear a tall hat or drink the toast of the King.</P>
    <P>The present position is that we have lost most of our trade with the people on the other side.  We got promises from the Government about the wheels of industry rolling here, but the true position is that the present Government have destroyed our greatest industry.  Nature has endowed this country with a soil that cannot be surpassed for its richness in producing food of the highest nutritive value. Our calves are being killed.  The Government are only able to cope with poverty that has been deliberately brought about and all that this motion means is that the Mad Mullah is to be approved and placated.  Dean Swift wrote that we should burn everything English except its coal. Now in order to placate the Mad Mullah we have nothing to burn except English coal, since the lamentable loss of Senator Connolly's factory at Navan.  That is what we have got from the blind idea of merging politics and prosperity, selling the country to England and putting Ireland on the dole.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I must ask you, Senator, to keep a little more to the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>I will keep to coal. The Irish people have been encouraged to cut turf but the turf cutters have been more or less dropped.  The same has happened in the case of kelp.  In the case of coal.  England has been given a monopoly in the Irish market.  The Irish people have no say with regard to the quality of the coal that comes from England.  They have to take what they get and be thankful for it.  They have been left with no alternative.  The country was not consulted as to how its wealth should be disposed of.  It is being bled to death. <Col N="342" /> The calves are being killed and we have lost the finest market in the world.  All that we get out of this pact is that the English coal which has a monopoly here will be 5/- dearer and they are to take 100,000 more cattle from us.  That is what we get out of the pact.  This is heaping coals of fire on John Bull's head!</P>
      <P>There is another issue in this.  I do not believe from the manner in which President de Valera started this so-called economic war that he cared whether the Irish farmer lost so long as the battle was joined. He wanted to make the conditions so impossible that he would bring John Bull to heel.  Why John Bull should not be brought to deal instead of to heel I do not know, but for some peculiar reason President de Valera seems to think that there can be no settlement by any kind of negotiation. Now he finds himself in a cul-de-sac: in a position of absolute distress.  He is attempting now to terrify John Bull into the fear that he will lose extra sources of food supplies in case of war so that the policy of the Government now is to intimidate John Bull by making Ireland into a desert with barely enough to keep the people from starving.  That is the position that the country has been reduced to, a country that has been so bountifully endowed by nature. Other countries have to produce intermediate crops before they can raise a beast because the soil in those countries is so poor.  But we are offered silk stockings from turf and gramophone records from sand.  This is a fight with our best market and, really, with our best friend, because the only thing John Bull has said is practically: &ldquo;You can have your republic if you like.&rdquo;  But not one of the Government is going to touch it.  That republic is going to be &ldquo;far from the land&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is again digressing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>We are left with no choice except in one market. We have no outlet for our cattle except through a quota.  The farmer is left, instead of paying his annuities to the Suspense <Col N="343" /> Fund of the Government, in a position in which he is paying them three times over.  In the first place, he is paying them to Mr. Thomas in the form of a tax on cattle.  That is not sufficient. They are, therefore, taken off the quota under the coal-cattle pact, which is over-plus for John Bull.  Then he pays the annuities in the form of the duties put on every article and commodity that comes into this country, whether they are raw material or whether they are such things as motor cars, on which revenue taxes are imposed.  He pays the annuities in an invisible way also by the descent of the standard of living and the broken heart of the nation.  What sort of future or what sort of country or what sort of policy are the Government capable of envisaging?  Is it their idea to smash the country by cutting off its income and then try to go round and round making unnecessary commodities or commodities that other people would be better employed in supplying?  Is it necessary to swap eggs for Spanish oranges or to sell shamrocks in exchange for Canadian snowballs?  Why all this unnecessary farce?  If the Government cannot envisage an Ireland fit for anything but a pauper, it is only fair that I should give them my idea.  We should have had, like the people of certain Southern States of America, no income tax whatever.  We could have lived on the surplus of the countries which do not buy anything from England and who do not require to state that John Bull is their Public Enemy No. 1.  My idea would be an Ireland with twice its present income, where, instead of having the so-called greatest betrayal in history, with the gentry running out of the country, the gentry would be able to remain without having their houses burnt.  That is an Ireland that might be capable of an education equal to Sweden's, but the Government has stupefied the electors and expanded what they call the Gaeltacht so that they will get undiscriminating and dole-fed votes.  On this coal-cattle pact, we have had a most impertinent confession from Senator <Col N="344" /> Connolly.  He asked the House, which warned him that dishonesty could only lead to disaster, to approve of his adopting part of our policy by selling a modicum of stock where we told him we ought to have three times the trade. The lifeboat is now off, but where is the treasure ship?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall not deal with the so-called speech delivered by the last speaker, except to say that it was the most rambling, the most abusive, and the most ridiculous speech that has ever been delivered on a subject of national importance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>It was all truth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>It reminds me of a little boy who goes to a dirt heap, makes little pellets of mud, and flings them at decent people as they pass.  Sometimes the Senator has been witty and, for the sake of his former wit, he is more or less tolerated now.  But the day comes when wit ceases and buffoonery only remains.  I think he has passed his little hour upon the stage.  He is no longer amusing.  He is getting old and dull.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>Why not deal with the agreement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall deal with the speech that had some relation to the subject matter of this debate &mdash; the speech of Senator Milroy.  The Senator, in the course of his speech, said that his opponents were &ldquo;disingenuous.&rdquo; I suppose he meant that they were &ldquo;disingenuous.&rdquo;  I should say that, in his observations, the Senator was disingenuous.  In the first place, he complained of the delay in bringing forward these resolutions for the approval of the House.  He approves of them.  At any time within the last five or six months, if he disapproved of them, he could have originated a debate upon the question.  Let us deal with the merits of the motion itself.  It deals with what has been described as the coal-cattle pact.  We agreed to sell 150,000 head of cattle to Great Britain, and Great Britain agreed to send to us coal of equal value.  I think that that was a good arrangement, because, if there is one <Col N="345" /> thing which Great Britain can export to Ireland with the greatest advantage to herself and the greatest benefit to this country, it is coal.  In the present state of agriculture here, it is of advantage to us that we should have an opportunity of exporting cattle to Great Britain.  Senator Milroy made an allusion to the Garden of Eden.  I suppose he has been reading that story. If he studies it closely, he will find that, even after the fall of our first parents, there was, in the Garden of Eden, some balance in our agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>An invisible balance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Cain was the tiller of the ground, and Abel was the keeper of sheep.  We want to have cattle in this country, but we also want to have agriculture.  We want to till the soil. We want, if possible, to supply from the fertile fields of this country all the food.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should confine himself to coal and cattle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am following what you allowed Senator Milroy to say.  I did not make any objection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that Senator Milroy made one statement that did not refer to the coal-cattle pact.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>He made statements in relation to the Garden of Eden.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is quite right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Gogarty made statements in reference to the President of the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Gogarty made many statements which I tried to prevent him from making.  I do not think that Senator Milroy made one statement which was not entirely relevant to the motion before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The coal-cattle pact was a reasonable pact and advantageous to this country.  Senator Milroy agrees with that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>Who told you that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>He said that the duties arising from this pact are altogether <Col N="346" /> in favour of Great Britain.  I put this consideration before the House.  It is said that £1,250,000 has been collected upon cattle exported free from this country to Great Britain.  I ask Senator Milroy who pays that tax?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>The people of this State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a free country where defeatist misstatements of that character are allowed.  I say that we do not pay all that tax.  I assert, with as much authority as does Senator Milroy, that that tax is, to a great degree, paid by the farmers of Great Britain and would be almost wholly paid by the farmers of Great Britain if there were not so much smuggling from this country across the Border.  I hope that that smuggling will soon be stopped.  If it is stopped, it will be found that the cattle will fetch their ordinary, economic price and that, if Great Britain puts a tariff of £2, £4 or £6 on cattle, her own farmers will have to pay.  I do think that Great Britain would never have imposed these taxes on cattle if they had not been hounded on to do so by the present Opposition &mdash; hounded, encouraged and forced to do so by the present Opposition.  It is alleged that, in the measures which have been taken by this Government, we are playing politics.  I submit to the House that, when this Government came into office three years ago, they found a condition of agriculture which could not continue. They found the land untilled. They found that wheat and other necessary food for the people was not produced in the country.  They found a state of things in which the country could not possibly exist.  They also found that farmers were simply grazing cattle for one market &mdash; a market which might have been stopped at any time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have suffered considerably in the last two or three years.  But what have been the gains?  We have gained in this way &mdash; that we have become almost independent of the one market for our cattle.  We have gained also inasmuch as we are now in a position to supply a great part of the food of the people and, in a year or two, even with this <Col N="347" /> economic war, we shall probably be able to supply all the wheat and all the flour required for our entire population.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that related to the coal-cattle pact?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like you to reconcile it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I have listened to the most irrelevant speeches but now people who are not half as irrelevant are interrupted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am trying to preserve order as best I can.  I am the sole judge of order, and I will not allow you, Senator, or anyone else to criticise my ruling.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not criticising any ruling of the Chair.  I must confess that I have been annoyed at certain observations that were made by some Senators on the other side.  I do not say that the Chair could have stopped them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I quite agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to hear that expression of opinion coming from the Chair.  I do not say that the Chair could have stopped them.  Some people come here occasionally and fling filth and then run.  The Chair cannot stop that.  I make no objection to any ruling of the Chair, but I make the statement, that three years ago the country was faced with a situation of considerable difficulty.  The situation was this, either to submit to the people of the sister island, simply because they were powerful or to pay a debt or an alleged debt that was not due or to assert our rights. The people chose to assert their rights.  A conflict has ensued, and in the course of that conflict we have done very well, considering that we had to fight on two fronts.  We had opposed to us opponents abroad, and we had also opposed to us unscrupulous persons at home, who have been ready to come to the Seanad and to make disgraceful speeches, such as have been made by Senator Gogarty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="348" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I approve of the pact. As a representative of the farming industry, and particularly of the cattle trade, I am very pleased at the pact.  If Senators who comment and object to the pact had cattle for sale at half a dozen fairs or markets and had to walk them home again, they would approve of the pact.  They would be very pleased with it and would not try to censure the Government for making it.  It has been stated that my attitude and that of the farmers in approving of the pact is like that of a drowning man grasping at a straw.  The position of the farmers at present is desperate.  The coal-cattle pact has relieved the situation to a certain extent, because we can sell 150,000 more cattle.  All I say to the Government is: For God's sake make more of these pacts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Comyn to this extent, that I deprecate anything in the nature of personal attacks at any time, and particularly on a question of this kind.  I do not agree to a certain extent with all that he thought it necessary to say in his reply.  Senator Comyn thought that it would be a good thing if Senator Milroy read the Book of Genesis again. I suggest to Senator Comyn that it would be a good thing if he did the same thing, to see if Senator Milroy's statement was correct, and if Cain and Abel were living in the Garden of Eden.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I said after the Fall.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to make it clear that we approved of this quota order. We have before us a large number of quota orders, which may be divided roughly into two categories, one designed to protect and encourage industry here, and the other to encourage the exchange of trade between countries.  As far as the second class is concerned, without hesitation, I say it is an excellent thing to make a bargain for the exchange of trade with another country.  It is an excellent thing that the bargain should be made with Great Britain.  As far as I am concerned I hope that will continue.  My criticism is not of this order, but of <Col N="349" /> the conditions that the Government saw fit to attach to this quota order which I consider is liable to injure its continuance in the future.  It is liable to create a wrong impression of a bargain of this kind by placing a tax on the commodity about which the bargain was made with another country under which we will take the bulk of our supplies from that country.  In this case we had a special Imposition of Duties Act with which I want to deal.  I do not want to follow other speakers into what is commonly called the economic war. In my view that is an entire misnomer. Special powers were given and we had an assurance from the Minister that the Government would see that care was exercised so that no undue hardship was imposed on the people.  Most Governments would adopt that attitude.  As far as the majority of the Orders made under that Act go I think that has been carried out.  In the case of coal a tax of 5/- a ton was imposed for the definite purpose of strengthening the position in dealing with England and reducing the amount of coal taken from that country.  The proper thing to do would have been to cease that tax as soon as it ceased to serve its purpose.  If it was required, like the tax on tea or sugar, it should have been imposed in the Budget.  Except as a member of the Government I do not think the Minister for Industry and Commerce was responsible for that tax, but I want to suggest to him that if the Minister for Finance is to continue with this idea it may be very disastrous to his policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There was, later, a special quota order dealing with oranges, as a result of which we take a large portion of our supplies from Spain.  It would not hurt Spain if we put a special tax on oranges, and it would be an excellent way to get revenue.  We are assured by medical people that oranges are very good if there is any juice in them.  It would be very nice to put on a little tax and to get revenue in that way.  But if that idea was to spread it would have a very bad result in the way of extending agreements <Col N="350" /> of this kind.  The group I represent welcome the agreement.  We do not worry about the fact that it has not been made as the result of a former agreement.  The actual carrying out of it is worth tons of paper, and I do not want particularly to know much more about it.  But I suggest to the Government that it will not help towards an extension of agreements by continuing the 5/- tax on our side, and by making our people feel that instead of being a real gain it is imposing a hardship.  I do not think it is a hardship on farmers because they may not use coal, but it is a hardship on industrialists who have to pay tax.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I can claim to speak for the farmers, because I represent the class that conducted a balanced economy.  I come from a stall-feeding county, and I can say that the praise given to this coal-cattle pact will not be backed up by any farmer who stall-fed cattle in County Wexford last year. The condition of these people is most lamentable.  A few extra cattle have been sent over to England, but at an enormous cost to our people.  That is nothing to boast of.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>150,000 cattle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>What is it out of the millions of cattle we sent in the past, considering that we have to pay a tax of £6 a head to England?  I agree with every word that Senator Milroy said about this pact.  It is the truth.  I am not surprised at Senator Comyn being vexed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not vexed by the argument, but by the form of the speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>You were vexed because you heard the truth.  Both Senator Milroy and Senator Gogarty gave it to you to-day.  The real farmers who count are not a bit enthusiastic about this pact.  What is it but tinkering, trying to put a sticking plaster on the terrible wounds that have been opened up in this country?  Senator Comyn said that the country was not <Col N="351" /> producing enough for the people before the Fianna Fáil Government came into office.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>The people were producing more than they are producing now.  What they produced was then worth an extra £35,000,000 yearly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>There was not that variety that the Senator would desire. There was not flour and other things.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not used to any variety.  I am used to plain living.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator lives on beef.  That is the reason she is so pugnacious.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I submit the people most concerned about the coal-cattle pact know very well the small benefit they have got at such an enormous cost. I can tell the Minister that the dictum of the Government, to turn the bullocks off the land and to put men on it, is a silly policy.  The only way to deal with that in the proper way was told by one of the audience at an election meeting, who said: &ldquo;Glory be to God, we will have to mind the few teeth we have, because we will have to go and eat grass.&rdquo;  That was the proper answer to such a foolish proposal.  Does not everyone know that the more bullocks there are, the more men must be on the land?  Does not everyone know that there is no use in having tillage unless you have a market for the finished article &mdash; the fat stock?  The tillage policy and the wheat policy which has been so much boosted, have done infinite harm to the land.  I saw Irish flour the other day stuck together. It was only on the premises a short time, and it was already caked with the damp that it had absorbed, as well as showing signs of life.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Do you mean milled flour?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="352" />
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I saw it.  I got expert opinion on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You are going outside the question before the House now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I back up everything that Senator Milroy said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know if I come under the designation of a real farmer. As my activities include tillage I was very pleased to hear of the agreement reached with Great Britain in connection with cattle.  The situation was a very serious one.  I hope we will have a continuation of the agreement next year.  Senator Miss Browne is objecting to the Government dealing with 150,000 cattle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not objecting in that way, but I am objecting to the Government selling them at such a cost to the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>The people must sell the cattle, and it is a very good thing that the Government made the agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenBrowne" hpid="Miss Browne Miss Browne">
      <NameTxt>Miss Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>What about getting the penal tariffs off?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>Farmers know that it is by a series of agreements of this sort that we may get out of the difficulties that we are in.  As far as I am concerned, as a representative of farmers, and as a tillage farmer, I congratulate the Government on having secured the agreement for this year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Milroy said that I introduced the motion as if it were a matter of routine.  It is very largely a matter of routine.  An arrangement was made, and it was left entirely to ourselves as to the manner of its implementation at our end.  The Government decided, as a matter of routine, to use the machinery of the Control of Imports Act rather than some other method of ensuring that the coal required here would be purchased from Great Britain to the quantity that would meet the obligation <Col N="353" /> that the Government had undertaken under the arrangement.  Senator Milroy also spoke in criticism of the Government, arising out of the fact that the resolution is brought here close to the end of the first quota period.  The Control of Imports Act requires that a resolution of this kind shall be passed by each House of the Oireachtas in respect of each Quota Order within six months of its being made.  The fact that we are now approaching the end of the first quota period has no bearing on the matter at all.  There is no period mentioned in the Quota Order.  The Quota Order continues in operation until it is repealed, but periodically a new quota period is fixed, and for that period a definite quota is announced.  It was purely a matter of administrative convenience that the first quota period was for six months.  We might have made the quota period for 12 months or three months.  But, after consultation with the coal importers, having regard to the nature of the trade, this six months period, being the most convenient, was fixed.  The second Order will also be for six months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>At that stage Senator Milroy must have seen Senator Gogarty coming into the House.  Senator Gogarty has a reputation for being humorous, I understand, but I have had no personal proof of it.  Senator Milroy apparently decided to steal some of Senator Gogarty's thunder by making a witty speech himself, because he proceeded to rid himself of a maze of figures which I could not hope to follow.  He preceded his remarks by referring to what he called his primitive knowledge of simple arithmetic.  His modesty was unnecessary. This arrangement is going to cost this country nothing.  The fact that there is a tax of 5/- a ton being levied on coal is something concerning which Senators may have opinions to express.  The coal-cattle arrangement had nothing to do with that imposition.  The collection of that tax on coal is an entirely different matter, something that concerns ourselves only.  It is a fact that it will bring in £600,000 of revenue this year to the Exchequer, and therefore its <Col N="354" /> imposition avoided the necessity of raising that £600,000 in some other way.  £600,000 would have had to be got in any event because Governmental services and Central Fund services were fixed and taxes had to be imposed designed to bring in the amount of money required to meet them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>It was a revenue tax therefore.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Mainly a revenue tax. It is true that it has some protective value.  It will possibly help to some extent the consumption of turf and of native coal.  I am not proposing to defend it on that basis at all.  The turf situation will have to be dealt with in a different manner, I think.  The tax is being maintained really because it is producing revenue and that the circumstances were such that the revenue could as easily be secured in that way as in any other way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I might say that the tax is not being imposed on coal used for industrial purposes where that coal is required in connection with the process of manufacture. There may be industrialists using coal who could as easily use electricity or turf.  These industrialists are not getting licences to import. The transport industry and industries like grain dryers, lime burners, cement works&mdash;if cement works were in operation &mdash; and industries of that kind, where coal is a raw material and used in the process of production, are receiving their coal free of duty.  The 150,000 extra cattle are being purchased at the market price.  The fact that Great Britain has a tax upon our cattle is something we deplore, but the tax was not imposed by us.  Whether it was imposed, as Senator Comyn said, on the advice of some members of this House or not, the tax is there. The 150,000 extra cattle, however, are not going to have any effect on the market price.  Whatever the market price would be, whether this pact was made or not, it is at that price the cattle are going to be purchased, and the calculation that we are paying Britain another £750,000, therefore, is entirely fallacious.  Furthermore, it is <Col N="355" /> not going to involve any extra cost in export bounties.  The amount of export bounties for this year is, in fact, lower than the amount provided last year.</P>
    <P>Senator Milroy asked us also what were the terms of the agreement.  He spoke as if he thought the Government did not think them fit for publication. He must not have been listening to my remarks because I gave the whole of the agreement in the course of the few remarks I addressed to the House before the debate commenced.  The agreement was precisely what I said it was, an understanding between the two Governments that the quota allocated to the Free State in respect of cattle for 1935 would be increased by 150,000 head and the Free State would take in return coal to a corresponding value.  There was no written document; the agreement was based upon mutual trust.  The agreement was published at the time.  It was in fact published in the newspapers, &mdash; where they got the information I do not know &mdash; some days before the date agreed upon between the British Government and ourselves as the date for the release of the information.  The newspaper publicity which it received at the time was so considerable that I cannot imagine any person in this month of June, several months later, asking for publication of the terms of the agreement, implying that we were keeping them secret.  The only thing I want to say is that there was no written document. The fact that there is no written document is a matter of not very great importance.  The whole business was of such a nature that it did not really call for any formal understanding, any formal agreement, because the arrangements necessary to bring it into force were in the hands of each party.  The pact was made because it is going to be of considerable relief to the farming community of this country.</P>
    <P>Senator Miss Browne referred to a few extra cattle being of no great importance, having regard to the millions we were exporting.  I am afraid her information about our export trade is very limited; 150,000 <Col N="356" /> extra cattle represents an increase of 33? per cent. in the quota allotted to us this year.  The total number of cattle which will be sent out of this country this year will be considerably higher than the number exported in 1931.  In fact, we will have in the course of a very few weeks reached the position where there will be no cattle surplus at all.  The requirements of the English market, the requirements of other markets, and the requirements of the home market will absorb all the cattle that are available. The cattle scarcity that has developed in the American continent is keeping Canadian cattle entirely out of the British market and will further increase the demand for our beasts.</P>
    <P>Reference was made by Senator Milroy to the price and quality of British coal imported.  I do not think that we have any reason to be satisfied with either the price or quality of the British coal that has come in.  The people of this country have learned, for the first time, that better coal and cheaper coal can be procured from countries other than Great Britain and, if there is any extension or continuation of this arrangement, we shall have to have a clear understanding with the British Government as to the price at which coal is to be supplied and as to the quality of the consignments sent.</P>
    <P>Senator Gogarty spoke on this matter.  I could not quite follow him in all his remarks, and I am afraid I learnt nothing from them.  I am not quite clear as to what his objection to the motion is.  He said he objected to the Government asking the House to approve of it.  I do not think there is any reasonable ground for such an objection.  We are not asking Senator Gogarty to approve of it.  In fact, I would dislike very much seeing any decent member of the House going into the same lobby as Senator Gogarty. We are asking the House to approve of the motion because we are required by law to do so.  Senator Gogarty also made some statement which appeared to indicate that Senator Connolly had appealed to the House not to oppose the motion and, therefore, <Col N="357" /> not to cross the Government in this matter.  We are making no such appeal to Senator Gogarty.  If he wants to vote against the motion he will have an opportunity to do so and we would be very glad to see him do it.  Apart from that, I do not think there is anything in his speech that calls for comment.  I suppose he has a certain licence, not a poet's licence, but another kind of licence, by which he can refer to the President of the State as the &ldquo;Mad Mullah.&rdquo;  I do not know that anyone would take that very seriously.</P>
    <P>Senator Counihan said that he would like to see the Government making some more of those pacts.  Well, we hope to do so.  It is not a matter entirely for ourselves.  We are willing to make pacts of this kind with Great Britain or with any other country, pacts under which the produce of this country will be exported on the one hand in return for purchases by us to a corresponding value of the products of Great Britain or the other countries concerned.  The Government has made it clear on several occasions that it is quite willing to enter into discussions for the purpose of effecting arrangements of that kind and it is our hope that the opportunity of doing so will arise.  So far as the tax on coal is concerned, it does not properly arise on this resolution at all. This resolution would be necessary whether the tax had been kept on or removed.  This whole matter could more properly be discussed when the Finance Bill comes before the Seanad.</P>
    <P>There was nothing in Senator Miss Browne's remarks relevant to the motion with which I could deal.  She said that she could claim to speak for the farmers.  There was a philosopher who once gave the advice that we should try to keep our illusions alive. I do not want to try to destroy Senator Miss Browne's illusions.  I would be interested to see the flour that became alive after it was milled, but that has nothing to do with the motion.  The only other point concerning it is that I am anxious to ensure that there will be no dislocation in the ordinary run of <Col N="358" /> the coal trade because of this Quota Order.  We may have to interfere with the coal trade, for the purpose of encouraging the use of Irish anthracite coal or Irish turf, but in so far as an Irish trader, by enterprise, good business methods, or advertising, may get increased trade, we do not wish to see him unable to avail of it because of this Order.  In so far as the other Quota Orders are concerned, as I explained in the beginning, the necessity of reducing imports makes it necessary to confine the remaining trade to those who previously engaged in it.  Each trader is given a licence based upon his imports in previous years.</P>
    <P>In this case there was no desire whatever to limit the trade in that way. Consequently, we will allocate licences in the next quota period with regard to other circumstances besides the previous year's imports, so that a trader who could get a larger market for his supplies will be able to get an amount of coal supplied to him even if that means a falling off in the business of another trader.  There is no limit to other firms going into the business. There is no idea of restricting importation in that direction.  If any Senator knows of any case in which the operation of these quotas is such as to prevent freedom of trade in the country I would be glad if he brings that case to my notice.  There is 25 per cent. of the quota that need not be allocated at the beginning, and is at the discretion more or less of the Department and can be used for the purpose of supplementing licences issued at the beginning of the period to those on the register.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>The following motions in the name of the Minister for Lands were approved of:&mdash;</P>
    <P>That Seanad Eireann hereby approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 12) Order, 1935, made on the 15th day of January, 1935 by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).</P>
    <P>That Seanad Eireann hereby approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 13) Order, 1935, made on <Col N="359" /> the 12th day of March, 1935 by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).</P>
    <P>That Seanad Eireann hereby approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 14) Order, 1935, made on the 22nd day of March, 1935 by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).</P>
    <P>That Seanad Eireann hereby approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 15) Order, 1935, made on the 22nd day of March, 1935 by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).</P>
    <P>That Seanad Eireann hereby approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 16) Order, made on the 22nd day of March, 1935 by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRobinson" hpid="Mr. D. Robinson Mr. D. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of the Minister for Lands, I move motion No. 10:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That Seanad Eireann hereby approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 17) Order, 1935, made on the 30th day of April, 1935 by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask whether there is any danger of the oranges that Spain is sending in being of an inferior nature.  I do not know much about oranges, but I know that there is great grumbling amongst some people in the fruit business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The agreement provides that the Spanish exporters shall provide the type of orange required by the Irish importer.  Spain provides various types of oranges, including oranges of the Jaffa kind.  The types of oranges that are imported here must satisfy the desire of the importers.  I am not sure whether this is a good time of the year for oranges, but the arrangement between this country and Spain contemplates not merely world prices to be charged, but that the type of orange specified will be supplied.  It <Col N="360" /> is not like the coal pact.  There is a very substantial import not allocated, and under that arrangement oranges can be imported from any other country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>My information is that the oranges from Spain are very bad, much worse than those of South Africa and other countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Prices have gone up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>That is due to other causes.  The oranges are consigned by the exporter to the importer here.  The importer here auctions the oranges and remits the price to the seller.  That is the procedure.  The only control the exporter has is that if he does not get a sufficient price he does not consign the oranges to that particular agent or country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the money value of our imports from Spain be equal to our exports to their country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>No, in this case it is only a matter of quantities.  The agreement is based upon the calculation as to what the value of the quotas is likely to be, having regard to 200,000 cwts. of oranges against certain quantities of eggs.  The whole quantity is 330,000 cwts.  Of this amount 200,000 is allotted to Spain and 100,000 is free.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>My objection is that the oranges are allotted to Spain, which produces the worst oranges. American, Brazilian and Java oranges and so on are very much better.  Difficulties, I am afraid, will arise over this.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Motion No. 11 agreed to:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That Seanad Eireann hereby approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 18) Order, 1935, made on the 3rd of May, 1935, by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRobinson" hpid="Mr. D.L. Robinson Mr. D.L. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.L. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I move motion No. 12:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That Seanad Eireann hereby <Col N="361" /> approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 1, Amendment) Order, 1935, made on the 22nd day of March, 1935, by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>This particular amending Order is of a different character from the other.  The original Order applied to both covers and tyres.  This amending Order divides both covers and tyres.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRobinson" hpid="Mr. D.L. Robinson (for the Minister for Lands) Mr. D.L. Robinson (for the Minister for Lands)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.L. Robinson (for the Minister for Lands)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move motion No. 13:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That Seanad Eireann hereby approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 2, Amendment) Order, 1935, made on the 22nd day of March, 1935, by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>This, I know, is an amending Order.  I would suggest to the Minister that he might go a little too far in regard to No. 3, as there is considerable difficulty in getting delivery from Irish manufacturers, and a good deal of scarcity.  I know that there has been a vast improvement in the administration of the Quota Order. The improvement, I think, is due to the fact perhaps that people are better able to understand them and to put in their own orders better.  There had been, as we know, a great deal of grumbling.  Now I find that that has largely ceased and there is more satisfaction at the working of the Quotas. I think that is very largely due to the firms themselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRobinson" hpid="Mr. D.L. Robinson Mr. D.L. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.L. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Senator Douglas is referring to Quota No. 3, but, as a matter of fact, we have not yet passed No. 2.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRobinson" hpid="Mr. D.L. Robinson (for the Minister for Lands) Mr. D.L. Robinson (for the Minister for Lands)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.L. Robinson (for the Minister for Lands)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move motion No. 14:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="362" /> That Seanad Eireann hereby approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 3, Amendment) Order, 1935, made on the 22nd day of January, 1935, by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Order is to extend the quota arrangement to cover children's and infants' boots and shoes.  All other boots were previously subject to the quota, and now this brings within the Quota Order children's and infants' boots and shoes.  At the same time the whole quota is increased.  It is possible that we were, to some extent, unduly restrictive in the first period.  We had not data upon which to go in fixing the quota and decided to start with the same percentage as for adults.  We have experience now of the operation of the Order, and any demands made upon imports to any extent that it is possible to meet while definitely seeing that protection takes place at home will be met.  We can fix additional quotas with more precision in future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Part of the difficulty arises from the fact that children's and infants' boots and shoes are much lower in price and do not yield anything like the same profit.  If you increase the quota without including infants' boots and shoes which give no profit and cannot get into the Saorstát, you cannot expect people to bring them in at the expense of other boots and shoes for which there is a good demand. That is bound to occur, humanity being what it is, and that is why at the moment there is a considerable shortage of infants' shoes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It might be better if we had two Orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="363" />
    <Speaker pid="DavidRobinson" hpid="Mr. D.L. Robinson (for the Minister for Lands) Mr. D.L. Robinson (for the Minister for Lands)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.L. Robinson (for the Minister for Lands)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move motion No. 15:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That Seanad Eireann hereby approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 4, Amendment) Order, 1935, made on the 22nd day of January, 1935, by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister say whether rubber shoes are likely to be made here?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="364" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  We will be able to have them soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a good chance for next year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I think so.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>As we are not likely to have any business next week the House stands adjourned <i>sine die.</i></P>
      <P>The House rose at 7.45 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>