<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="27" Month="Nov" Year="1991" Vol="130" No="11" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 27 Samhain 1991" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 27 November 1991" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1065" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator O'Donovan that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Government to provide additional Custom and Excise officials and gardaí to curb and prevent the trafficking of large quantities of drugs off our south west coast.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Ross of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The urgent need for improved sewerage treatment in Greystones, County Wicklow.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Hederman of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Finance to proceed with the cycleway around St. Stephen's Green as prepared by Dublin Corporation in 1980 and as discussed with the Office of Public Works at a meeting on 21 April 1983.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I regard the matters raised by Senators O'Donovan, Ross and Hederman as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment. I have selected Senator O'Donovan's matter and it will be taken at the conclusion of business. Senators Ross and <Col N="1066" /> Hederman may give notice another day of the matters they wish to raise.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take all Stages of item No. 1 &mdash; the Liability for Defective Products Bill, 1991 &mdash; to 6 p.m. to have a sos between 6 p.m. and 6.30 p.m. followed by the Fine Gael Private Members' Bill, the Suicide Bill, 1991, for one hour and a half.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Order of Business, may I say to the Leader of the House that as we are speaking there is a body of a person who was shot brutally last night lying on the roadside in County Armagh. It is the latest in a list of unspeakable crimes that have taken place on both sides over the past number of months, and yet it is as if it was happening in a different country. Over and over again, I have asked if we could have a discussion in this House on Northern Ireland and also hear from our Government their views towards helping to achieve a solution in Northern Ireland. May I once again ask the Leader of the House if he would give us the guarantee of a debate on Northern Ireland before Christmas.</P>
      <P>I am very puzzled that at the beginning of this session we were told there was a very heavy corpus of legislation to be introduced in this session but so far we have had only one small Bill and one bad Bill. May I ask the Leader what other legislation we are going to get this session? If there are other Bills ready &mdash; there is a Family Planning Bill, for example, and other Bills &mdash; why can they not be brought to this House? We are waiting for legislation. The whole purpose of this House, above everything else, is that we discuss Bills in detail. I wish to complain to the Leader of the House about the paucity of legislation and ask him to do something about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>May I also ask the Leader of the House if the enthusiasm which was shown last week for a debate on the banking system <Col N="1067" /> will be translated into a debate in the foreseeable future?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to pick up the same item which was raised by Senator Manning and that is the question of legislation which I have now raised for a fourth week in a row. I have to say to the Leader of the House, without in any sense denigrating his office, that I feel this House has been treated with contempt and I think he has been treated with contempt by the Government. The lack of legislation in this House over the past number of months has been pathetic. It certainly belies all that has been said about the need to introduce legislation. I have consistently asked the Leader of the House to outline the legislation it was proposed to introduce in this House. It is quite clear the Government continue to treat with contempt the efforts of the Leader of this House to have legislation introduced in this House and the situation at this stage is totally unacceptable. We are being pushed out to the periphery of Irish politics and it is no wonder people question our role and our relevance.</P>
      <P>We are wasting time. Yet, we will again find ourselves before the end of this session trying to rush through legislation which we will be told is needed to be enacted with great urgency and we will have legislation being processed without getting due consideration. It is disgraceful and I think the Leader is failing us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I forecast five weeks ago the need for a debate on the Maastricht Summit. I prefaced my comments on it last week and the week before by saying that I fully believed the Leader of the House would not get a debate in this House until it had first been debated in the other House and I have been proved right on that one. It is the old story. This is an issue which is going to affect every aspect of Irish life, socially, educationally, politically, in terms of foreign policy, sovereignty, neutrality. Yet, half of the people know nothing about it and we have not even discussed it. It is disgraceful that the <Col N="1068" /> Leader has also failed us on that one. I wonder about the relevance of what we are doing here at this stage. I believe we have lost touch with what is happening out there.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>We have not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>It might be different down in Clare.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatUpton" hpid="Dr. Upton Dr. Upton">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Upton</NameTxt>
      <P>May I support the call for a debate on Northern Ireland? Things are in a terrible state up there and I cannot see how a debate in this House could make things worse. For that reason I am hopeful the Leader of the House might reconsider the attitude he has taken to this debate and perhaps accede to the request to hold it.</P>
      <P>May I also ask the Leader if he is prepared to have a debate on the problems of vandalism in the Clondalkin area of Dublin? It is a major problem and whole communities are in a dreadful state because of it. I certainly think a debate on that topic would be useful, given what we have seen in the past few days and particularly the appalling attacks that have been made on the Garda and the fire service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I rise, as I know other people in the House would like to do, to condemn totally the atrocities that have been carried out by satellites of the Israelis in the southern part of Lebanon. Over many months we have heard the Israelis condemn the Arabs for their terrorist activities all over the Middle East, yet they are arming, clothing and paying an army which is called the DFF, <i>de facto</i> forces, in the south of Lebanon. We ask that this House totally condemn the activities of the Israeli Government in their payment of the <i>de facto</i> forces in southern Lebanon who daily are committing atrocities not alone against the natives of southern Lebanon but in the past couple of weeks they have killed an Irish soldier and severely injured another Irish soldier.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>These people are Israeli funded and Israel should be condemned. They are <Col N="1069" /> operating against the wishes of the United Nations. Could we extend a vote of sympathy here to the family of a nine year old girl who was brutally murdered? After her murder her family were sent back to their house and the South Lebanese Army blew up the house and the mother of that child had to have her leg amputated&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>While the House would be at one with you probably in relation to the death of the nine year old child, at the same time it is not wise that we should establish a precedent here to pass votes of sympathy in that type of area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I say I think it would be appropriate for the House to extend a vote of sympathy to the family and indeed I wish to extend a vote of sympathy to the Chief of Staff on the death of Corporal McCarthy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The House will decide that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of Order, I do not disagree with the sentiments at all, but there was a ruling in the House some short time ago that all votes of sympathy would be handled in a particular way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to thank Senator Manning for making that comment. At the same time we have procedures well established and the types of votes of sympathy and the areas in which they are made are also well established. However, if the House wants to alter or change that situation, I will be guided by the House. In the meantime I think we will have to adhere to the established practice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to raise two matters with the Leader of the House. The first is in relation to the business for today. Regarding Item No. 1, Liability for Defective Products Bill, 1991, while I see no reason why this matter should not be concluded or be very close to <Col N="1070" /> conclusion today, I do not want a situation to arise in which a decision of the House is arrived at that all Stages must be concluded today.</P>
      <P>The second point I want to raise with the Leader of the House is that on 29 May last this House, by resolution, decided to set up a public inquiry, a tribunal of inquiry, into the meat processing industry. We did this in the public interest. I ask the Leader to make a considered statement to the House &mdash; maybe not even today &mdash; as to the extent the public interest is being represented or is not being represented at that inquiry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Again, I have to point out that we are dealing with the Order of Business. I do not want to cut across Senator Howard as he has always been very co-operative but I would like to point out that that is a matter for the tribunal and not for this House. It would be unwise for this House to get into any debate on matters associated with the tribunal because of the usual practice that has been well established in relation to such inquiries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to be in conflict with the Chair and I have no such intention, but I feel that there might be a misunderstanding as to what my objective is here. My objective is this. In the last analysis, we were the guardians of the public interest and considerable confusion has existed as to the extent that the public interest is represented there. I understand some finality was brought to the matter in the past day or two to the extent that it was decided counsel for the Attorney General would represent the public interest. But a number of weeks have gone by and, therefore, it is implicit in the decision arrived at that the public interest was not taken care of during those weeks. I am asking the Leader will he consider&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader has no function in this matter and neither has the House. I want to make that quite clear. I cannot allow any further discussion in respect of that matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1071" />
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>May I join with other Senators in asking the Leader of the House again to provide time to discuss the atrocities in Northern Ireland, the revolting kidnappings, murders, and other acts? At present many innocent people are going about their normal business in fear, because moving about in the dark winter evenings in the North at present is a dangerous business. I am trying to explain to the Leader that people who are not involved and people who do not support violence in the North are finding life nearly impossible. A person would be afraid to go out after dark because of the atrocities being committed by the IRA. This is a priority matter and if we continue to refuse to discuss it in this House then I believe we are not aware of the position. Far too many Senators do not realise the importance of having a debate on what is happening in the North of Ireland at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with my colleagues who are calling for a debate on Northern Ireland. I do not believe that democracy is ever served by not talking about things.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not often do it, but I took the liberty of sending something to all my colleagues in this House and to which Senator Lanigan kindly referred: a specific and graphic account of an atrocity in southern Lebanon, which he has described. I agree with him that we should specifically refer to this. I do not want to enter into an argument with you, a Chathaoirligh. The account is graphic in itself, but there is a quote from an Irish Army officer which says there will be no condemnation. Therefore, both for the sake of this nine year old girl whose chest was blown apart by either an Israeli soldier or one of their allies, and for the sake of the morale of our troops in southern Lebanon who are trying to keep the peace, we ought to condemn this atrocity. It was done within earshot of Irish troops, one of whom was killed recently trying to do his job. It is not good for their morale and it is not fair if we who commend <Col N="1072" /> them so often here do not respond to their obvious frustration, their obvious annoyance and their deep sense of not being able to do their job. What we can do is say that when a small child, is murdered, it is murder no matter what the pretences of the Government responsible. We can do that for the sake of her family and also for the sake of our troops. I fully agree with Senator Lanigan that this is to be condemned completely.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator McGowan in asking the Leader of the House for a debate on the Six Counties. Like Senator McGowan, I too drive through the Six Countes every weekend. One never knows when a road is going to be closed or open. The people there suffer and, as Senator Ryan said, democracy is never served by not debating a subject.</P>
      <P>I would also ask the Leader to have a debate on the Maastricht Summit. I believe the other House is being afforded one next week. There are many issues which need to be debated such as defence, subsidiarity, majority voting and so on. We need to look at these matters very carefully. We will be joining in political union with an organisation whose Court of Human Rights recently defined murder of the unborn as a service. We need to debate this matter openly and publicly to see whether we can obtain a derogation on this or a protocol. I ask for a debate on that matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MylesStaunton" hpid="Mr. Staunton Mr. Staunton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staunton</NameTxt>
      <P>I support fully Senator Lanigan's comments on the violence being perpetrated in south Lebanon by paramilitary allies of the Israeli Government who are directly funded by them. He spoke very eloquently and it would be superfluous for me to extend it further. The Irish Government should take a very strong stand on that issue. Not only are they murdering and maiming people in that part of the world, but they are doing the same to our troops who are in that region.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In relation to the Maastricht Summit, <Col N="1073" /> which is due to take place on 10 December, would the Leader of the House agree that it is an outrage to the parliamentary institutions of this State that while we speak today we do not know, officially, whether we are going to debate Maastricht. My understanding is &mdash; and I have been told unofficially &mdash; that we are to debate it next week, but I think that is putting out fires. Even if the Maastricht debate takes place next week, we have to order our business in a much more appropriate manner if serious issues arise in the future.</P>
    <P>I put it to the Leader of the House that the purpose of the Maastricht debate in this House is not the self-aggrandisement of us as Senators nor is it the articulation of our views for the Irish public: it is to have some impact, if possible, from this House of Parliament on what may happen in Maastricht. When will the proceedings of next Wednesday and Thursday be published which might influence the Taoiseach or others for a meeting which is to happen within three or four days? It is totally unacceptable; it is windowdressing and it is a highly unsatisfactory approach.</P>
    <P>Finally, in view of the fact that sanity is beginning to prevail with amendments being introduced to broadcasting legislation by the Minister, will the Leader of the House concede that an open ended debate in relation to the broadcasting issue should take place in this House before the Christmas recess.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HelenKeogh" hpid="Miss Keogh Miss Keogh">
      <NameTxt>Miss Keogh</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to support the call for a debate on the situation in Northern Ireland. I expressed the opinion here before that I do not believe the men of violence on either side could really care less about what we say. But the people of Northern Ireland care. We should reinforce our Government's conviction that talks must and should start no matter when the general election in Great Britain may or may not take place. What we could do is communicate to the people of Northern Ireland, and to the politicians on all sides, that we care about what is happening, we condemn violence <Col N="1074" /> and we want to see progress as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I have called virtually every second week for a debate on Northern Ireland. The response we have invariably got on that issue has been that there have been talks for the past 18 months at least and that we are at a delicate stage. There are no Brooke talks at present. There is no reason we cannot have a full scale, comprehensive, wide-ranging debate on Northern Ireland. We must condemn the cold-blooded murder of the young Protestant man in County Armagh last night or this morning. In that context I would like to be associated with the remarks in relation to the other atrocity in south Lebanon by the Israeli-backed militia where a young girl was cold-bloodedly killed. We should also condemn that.</P>
      <P>We should have also a debate on the <i>Programme for Social and Economic Progress.</i> When that was negotiated less than 12 months ago with the social partners &mdash; the trade unions, the employers and the farmers &mdash; we had no say in this House. We were not allowed to debate it. Now that it is about to be renegotiated, which seems to be outside the terms of the agreement, we are still not going to be allowed to have a say in it. We are still not going to be allowed have a debate on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>We had a debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Not before it was negotiated. We were allowed to debate it subsequently and now that it is going to be renegotiated perhaps we will eventually be allowed to debate it subsequently as well. Is that the way we carry on our business? It is an insult to the House.</P>
      <P>The real issue I would like to raise is one I have been raising since the beginning of this term, the complete lack of business before us in this House. There is no legislation here. We have two Mickey Mouse pieces of legislation before us. That is the only way I can describe them. It is not legislation that has originated here&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1075" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that kind of remark does any service to the business of the House. All legislation must be and will be treated by this House as important. On the Order of Business we should not continue to make speeches because that is not making a contribution. There is repetition here on many subjects.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I am referring to the corpus of legislation we have got. It is really a corpse. There are two miserable pieces of legislation&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When Members are making contributions I would like them to bear in mind that parliamentary language is important and that we should not make disreputable comment on legislation programmes for the House. I do not think it does the House any service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I am being descriptive about what we have had before the House. I am asking the Leader of the House to go to the Ministers in the Dáil. I know they are queueing up, jostling each other, to get legislation through the Dáil, but they simply do not have the time to do it. There is absolutely no reason a substantial amount of that legislation could not be initiated in this House. The Leader of the House told me before that he is doing his best. He is checking with the other House, but nothing has been forthcoming. There is really not much purpose coming into this House if we do not have some substantial legislation to discuss. That is the point I want to emphasise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>To get back to European matters, I would like to congratulate Miss Judith Ironside of the Ennis Soroptimists on yesterday achieving the Irish Women of Europe Laureate in relation to caring for the carers. I would also ask the Leader of the House if he would convey to the new Minister for Health, Deputy O'Rourke, the need for realistic funding, not means tested, because we know that the allowance last <Col N="1076" /> year came to 10 per cent of the applicants for the carer's allowance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like first to refer to an item on the Supplementary Order Paper, that is, Government's response to the European Court case ruling which I obtained over three years ago. I think I have been fairly restrained on this. It has been many years through the Irish courts and through the European courts system. I understand the Government's difficulties, but we did receive assurances from the Minister for Justice that this matter would be dealt with before Christmas. I would like to ask the Leader if he can give me some update on this, otherwise, with reluctance, I will be forced to&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>To which item are you referring, Senator?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Supplementary Order Paper up to the summer recess, it was Item No. 17. I do not have the supplementary list that is relevant. I have the one up to the summer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are past summer now, we are into winter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware of that. I was attempting to be helpful.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is an invitation to catch up with us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>With respect, summer is on the way round again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>It is also, I may say, summer in Australia.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>But you are in the Irish Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I am prepared to be a member of any parliamentary assembly, a Chathaoirligh, as, I understand, you are yourself. You show a marked interest <Col N="1077" /> in being a member of all kinds of parliaments. I share your enthusiasm.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be delighted if you would be more specific so that you can allow the Leader of the House to reply in a specific way. To which item are you referring?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot give you the precise number but I can read it into the record:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann expresses concern at the Government's total lack of action in meeting the requirements of last October's judgment in the European Court of Human Rights concerning discrimination against homosexual citizens of Ireland.</P>
      <P>I do not know the number on the Supplementary Order Paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is No. 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, a Chathaoirligh. I would like also to support the call for a debate on Northern Ireland that has been very generally made today. I think I have been consistent in either initiating this or supporting the many other Members who have called for this. It seems absurd that we are told the situation is too delicate, may I say with regard to consistency that the Labour Party made this point from time to time, that the situation was too delicate? I have never believed this was the case. I believe it is important that we should not be mute when people in an area of the country over which we technically claim jurisdiction are being wantonly murdered on both sides of the divide.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Finally, may I support what Senator Lanigan and Senator Ryan said with regard to the situation in southern Lebanon? May I, as a consequence of that, suggest that the appropriate time to ventilate these issues publicly would be in a debate on the Middle East? I would like to ask the Leader of the House if he will allow such a debate. Although as a supporter of Israel, this is an occasion on <Col N="1078" /> which I join completely and unreservedly in the condemnation of this appalling crime committed without justification against a family and condemnation of the kidnapping of people. I am asking if we can have a debate soon on the Middle East in which, for example, the absence of a foreign affairs committee and the absence of an Israeli ambassador resident here who could be called to account over this matter, will be discussed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask the Leader of the House for a debate on item No. 49 in view of the increasing violence in west Dublin, in Ronanstown, Neilstown and Killinarden and in view of the statement made by the chairperson of the Oireachtas Committee on Crime, Lawlessness and Vandalism, Deputy Quill, that she was outraged at the appalling violence and thuggery which has been rampant in west Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Bearing in mind the Cathaoirleach's remarks about the necessity to avoid repetition, I support the pleas for a debate on Northern Ireland not least because Senator McGowan articulated it so sincerely. Though he may not think so, I am always impressed by what he has to say because of his day to day contact with the North.</P>
      <P>With regard to a debate on the Maastricht Summit, among the reasons mentioned by Senator Staunton was a desire for more information on what is happening. The most extraordinary thing about the debate on the forthcoming conference is that we know so little about what is meant, for example, by a common defence policy. There is a sinister phrase now being used about the need for an &ldquo;out of area&rdquo; dimension to some hypothetical European defence force. We need to be given more information about what people think they mean when they use these phrases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I regard it as rather unfortunate that the issue of the atrocity in the Middle East has been raised. It would not have been raised, I suggest, but that it was the <Col N="1079" /> subject of an article in <i>The Irish Times</i> by a very eloquent journalist, Robert Fisk. It begs the question about other countless and unrecorded atrocities committed all over the Middle East. If this House is to attend to its business properly, I suggest we adhere to the rules already laid down. This is very emotional stuff and partisan attitudes are taken, invariably, in these proposed votes of sympathy. It does not do any service to our troops in the Middle East for us to be so partisan in our expressions of sympathy here. I regret that the matter was raised in the first place.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CarmencitaHederman" hpid="Mrs. Hederman Mrs. Hederman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Hederman</NameTxt>
      <P>In response to Senator Neville's call for a debate on item No. 49 in the light of what happened in the suburbs of west Dublin, the suggestion that what is needed is more law and order is rather facile. We need proper resources to create some sort of social fabric in the area, such as community and sporting facilities, etc. A debate on item No. 49 should not be considered as an answer to the problems in west Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the views of Senators Manning and O'Toole in relation to the lack of legislation before the House. Perhaps the Leader could indicate what legislation will come before this House between now and Christmas and what might be initiated here. I disagree with my colleague, Senator Costello, when he indicated that Ministers were queueing up with legislation. They were certainly queueing up to cross the bridge across the way a couple of weeks ago, but that was a different matter.</P>
      <P>I call for a debate on local government funding. We are all aware that totally inadequate funds have been provided by the Minister for the Environment to local authorities to carry out their work. I am sure my colleagues from Dún Laoghaire, Senators Keogh and Conroy, will join with me in this regard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with Senator Cosgrave in urging the Leader of the House, <Col N="1080" /> as a matter of urgency, to have a debate on the funding of local authority services. As Senator Cosgrave has indicated, many local authorities find it impossible to fund and finance important programmes, such as the roads and housing programmes. Many urban authorities, such as Limerick and Cork, are facing financial bankruptcy. I urge the Leader to have a debate on this very important and vital matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>A number of Senators, including Senator Manning, asked for a debate on Northern Ireland. I have been consistent in saying that I am hopeful that the talks will resume. If that is not the position I will continue to endeavour to have a debate. I will make renewed efforts over the next few weeks to have a debate, if possible, on the situation in Northern Ireland. I cannot guarantee we will have a debate but I will renew my efforts on this very important and pressing issue.</P>
      <P>In regard to the point made by Senator Manning about the banking system, I am pursuing this with a view to having a debate. There are some problems and if we can overcome them we will have a debate.</P>
      <P>Senator O'Toole referred to legislation. I and the Chief Whip have been active over the last week pursuing with the new Ministers the question of legislation for this House. We have been in touch with all of them and we hope something will come to us soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>No answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to the Maastricht Summit, I am aware that there is a lack of understanding of the problem generally. The implications for this country are enormous. That being so, as I indicated last week, we will have a debate on the Maastricht Summit and I propose that we have a two day debate next Wednesday and Thursday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Upton and others referred to youth vandalism and Senators Neville and Hederman referred to it in the context of item No. 49 on the Order Paper. <Col N="1081" /> I have no immediate proposals for a debate in that regard but item No. 49 is very suitable for Private Members' time. I urge the Labour Party to consider that.</P>
    <P>I noted what Senator Lanigan and others said in regard to the Middle East and south Lebanon in particular. In reply to Senator Norris, I have no proposals at this time for a debate on the Middle East. Senator Howard queried item No. 1 on today's Order Paper. If the debate does not conclude today, we have it ordered for tomorrow also; if it is not completed this evening we should complete it tomorrow.</P>
    <P>Senator Brendan Ryan referred to Northern Ireland, the atrocities in the Lebanon and Maastricht. Senator Staunton referred to the broadcasting legislation. I have no plans for a debate on broadcasting at this time. It was suggested last week that a White Paper was being issued on broadcasting. I have checked that out and my information is that that is not the case. In reply to Senator Costello I have no plan for a <Col N="1082" /> debate on the renegotiation of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> and I do not regard Bills, such as the Sea Pollution Bill, as unimportant.</P>
    <P>I have noted what Senator Jackman said in relation to the carer's allowance. It was a great innovation by the previous Minister for Social Welfare, Deputy Woods and, as he said at the time, hopefully it will continue to improve over the years.</P>
    <P>Senator Norris referred to item No. 5 on the supplementary list. I have no information about this at present but I will make inquiries and inform the Senator.</P>
    <P>Senators Neville, Hederman and Staunton referred to motion 49. Senator Cosgrave referred to local government funding as did Senator Kennedy. We all share his concern but I have no proposal for a debate in this area at present.</P>
    <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the Order of Business be item No. 1, that business be interrupted from 6 p.m. to 6.30 p.m. and that item No. 6 be taken at 6.30 p.m.&rdquo;.</P>
    <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 30; Níl, 18.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bennett, Olga.<br />Bohan, Eddie.<br />Byrne, Hugh.<br />Byrne, Sean.<br />Cassidy, Donie.<br />Conroy, Richard.<br />Dardis, John.<br />Fallon, Sean.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Finneran, Michael.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Foley, Denis.<br />Haughey, Seán F.<br />Honan, Tras.<br />Hussey, Thomas.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Keogh, Helen.<br />Kiely, Dan.<br />Kiely, Rory.<br />Lanigan, Michael.<br />Lydon, Don.<br />McCarthy, Seán.<br />McGowan, Paddy.<br />McKenna, Tony.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />Ó Cuív, Éamon.<br />O'Keeffe, Batt.<br />Ormonde, Donal.<br />Ryan, Eoin David.<br />Wright, G. V.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Cosgrave, Liam.<br />Costello, Joe.<br />Doyle, Avril.<br />Hourigan, Richard V.<br />Howard, Michael.<br />Jackman, Mary.<br />Kennedy, Patrick.<br />McMahon, Larry.<br />Manning, Maurice.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Neville, Daniel.<br />Norris, David.<br />Ó Foighil, Pól.<br />O'Toole, Joe.<br />Ross, Shane P.N.<br />Ryan, Brendan.<br />Ryan, John.<br />Staunton, Myles.<br />Upton, Pat.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1083" />
      <Col N="1084" /> Tellers: Tá, Senators Wright and Fitzgerald; Níl, Senators O'Toole and Cosgrave.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Liability for Defective Products Bill," RHead="1991: Committee Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Liability for Defective Products Bill, 1991: Committee Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That section 1 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Leyden, to the House. I am glad he survived the storms of recent times and is with us this afternoon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not relevant to the Liability for Defective Products Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I was simply getting my breath and being courteous to the Minister who is always courteous.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a common practice in Clare.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes. On section 1 I raised a difficulty that I could foresee arising in relation to the processing of agricultural produce. The Minister of State, Deputy Kirk, on the last occasion, gave me a substantial reply but it was a reply to questions I never asked and now I want to raise one or two specific points with the Minister.</P>
      <P>Section 1 refers to the processing of agricultural produce. The initial processor is the person to whom liability will attach for a defect subsequently arising. I am concerned that the section is silent in relation to defects which would arise from further processing or reprocessing. I made that point in relation to meat and in view of current developments with which we are all familiar. Beef is produced as a primary agricultural product and hopefully the primary producers are conscious &mdash; apart from that tiny minority who are prepared to abuse the trust placed in them &mdash; of the fact that they should be extremely careful in relation to the administration of chemicals or other matters where livestock are concerned.</P>
      <P>They are very fortunate that primary producers are excluded from the ambit of this legislation. As the legislation stands, the primary producer is not responsible for defects arising but the initial processor is responsible. I put this scenario to the Minister: the initial processor does a satisfactory job and the meat is put into cold storage, a freezer or wherever. At that time it is in perfect condition. Sometime later &mdash; if we are to believe media reports it could be five years later &mdash; that meat is taken from the cold store, thawed and reprocessed, and at that point the defect arises. As this legislation stands, if a defect arises, no liability will attach to the reprocessor. In fact, the liability will revert back to the initial processor who, very likely, did a first-class job. I want the Minister to directly address that specific point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to take the opportunity to explore further and ask the Minister what is meant by the phrase &ldquo;initial processing&rdquo; which is defined in section 1 (1) of the Bill as meaning in relation to primary agricultural products, any processing of an industrial nature of those products which could cause a defect therein. As we said previously, the essence of the directive is contained in Article 1 of the directive and in section 2 (1) of the Bill. Section 1 (1) of this Bill provides that the producer shall be liable in tort for damage caused wholly or partly by a defect in his product. This statement of principle contained in section 2 (1) is subject to the very important qualification that it only applies to a product. A &ldquo;product&rdquo; is defined in section 1 (1) as including all moveables with the exception of primary agricultural products which have not undergone initial processing, even where the movables are <Col N="1085" /> incorporated into other movables or into immovables whether by virtue of being a component part or raw material or otherwise.</P>
      <P>Primary agricultural products are defined in section 1 as meaning the products of the soil, of stock-farming and of fisheries and game, excluding such products and game which have undergone initial processing. The dividing line between products which have undergone initial processing and those which have not may sometimes be difficult to draw.</P>
      <P>Therefore, I ask the Minister a number of questions: what about slaughtering and butchering, the use of hormones, antibiotics and other additives in foodstuffs? Do any of these amount to intitial processing of an industrial nature? What about the pasteurisation of milk? What about the use of pesticides and fertilisers on fruit and vegetables? Does the use of pesticides and fertilisers which, we all know, occasionally hit the wrong target or are used in the wrong concentration, constitute initial processing of an industrial nature? Is the freezing of chickens and peas for the supermarket initial processing of an industrial nature? If it is not initial processing, then what is it? If initial processing means the beginning process, what about the subsequent processes? Are they covered by this legislation?</P>
      <P>The Bill contains the implication that while initial processing may disqualify goods from this exemption or exception, processing which comes after the initial processing is all right. That would seem to be a ridiculous situation but if we adhere to the exact wording of this Bill that interpretation is possible. Sir Gordon Barry, QC, Director of Fair Trading in the United Kingdom said in an article entitled &ldquo;Product Liability in the European Economic Communities&rdquo; and published in the Dublin University Law Journal 1987 that none of these operations removes the exemptions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a difference between the UK legislation and ours because we mentioned initial processing specifically. The United Kingdom's Government view of the intentions of the directive has been enbodied in their domestic legislation so <Col N="1086" /> that the exemption for agricultural products is lost only where the essential characteristics of the products have been altered through the use of machinery on a continuous basis. The exemption is lost when, for example, fruit, vegetables or chickens undergo freezing in a factory or when meat is turned into meat pies.</P>
    <P>While discussing similar legislation in the United Kingdom Lord Lucas of Kilworth put forward a useful and perhaps a practical twofold test for exemption. First for processing to take place some essential characteristic of the product must have been altered and, secondly, the process must be an industrial one, that is, carried out on a large scale continuously and with the intervention of machinery.</P>
    <P>Under the definition of primary agricultural products, the phrase &ldquo;products of the soil&rdquo; raises interesting questions about the modern technique of hydroponics whereby crops are grown in vitamin enriched sand and water. Lord Radner pointed out in the House of Lords during a debate on similar legislation that many vegetables, particularly cucumbers, tomatoes and lettuces are grown by a process known as hydroponics where no soil is involved. I would like the Minister to look at that very important modern technique. A ridiculous situation would arise if one of two cucumbers offered for sale fell outside this legislation while the other was covered by it because of the kind of definitions contained in this Bill.</P>
    <P>I know the Minister of State is concerned that we accede to exhortations from the European Commission to comply with European legislation but a little while longer would help to tease out this legislation. I suggest that in page 3, line 6 of this Bill, after the word &ldquo;soil&rdquo; the phrase, &ldquo;of hydroponic culture&rdquo; be inserted otherwise the phrase &ldquo;products of the soil&rdquo; may have to be interpreted as referring to products that are capable of being grown in soil in order to extend this definition to cover hydroponic methods of production.</P>
    <P>Finally, I would like to ask the Minister about a most topical matter. Will a <Col N="1087" /> person injured by contaminated water supplies, for instance where a local authority is responsible, whether the contamination is by sewage or by an excessive concentration of aluminium sulphate, be entitled to claim damages under this legislation?</P>
    <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Industry and Commerce (Mr. Leyden) Terry Leyden">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Industry and Commerce (Mr. Leyden)</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume we are dealing with section 1 of this Bill in a general sense. The agicultural side of production is very important and it has been referred to already in the Dáil and Seanad. The definition of &ldquo;product&rdquo; exempts primary agricultural products which have not undergone initial processing. Such products were also exempted by the EC directive but that directive allowed member states, under article 15, the option of bringing such products within the scope of the regime of no-fault liability. The Government have decided not to avail of this option and I concur fully with that decision.</P>
      <P>There were calls in the Lower House to include primary agricultural products within the scope of the Bill, contending that their inclusion would enhance the image and reputation overseas of Irish food products. This contention is poorly based on a number of grounds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Of the nine member states which have to date implemented the directive, only Luxembourg has included primary agricultural products. Agriculture is not a significant percentage of Luxembourg's gross domestic product; it comprises 2.6 per cent compared with 10.2 per cent in Ireland's case. Equally, Luxembourg accounts for only 0.1 per cent of total EC agricultural production whereas for Ireland the figure is 2 per cent. In the other eight markets, that is, the UK, Germany, Italy, Belgium, Denmark, Holland, Greece and Portugal primary agricultural products are excluded from the implementing legislation. If we were to include them consumers in other European markets could, erroneously, get the impression that our primary agricultural products were in some way suspect and I <Col N="1088" /> cannot afford the consequences of such a message. I presume the majority of Senators would not like that message to go out either.</P>
    <P>The principal reason the Government decided to exclude primary agricultural products is that such products are particularly prone to hidden defects caused by environmental factors beyond the control of the producer, for example acid rain, nuclear fallout, industrial pollution or whatever. Producers of primary agricultural products, however, continue to be liable under tort and contract law. Under the law of tort the consumer has rights against the producer for damage caused if negligence can be proved. Under contract law goods are required to be of merchantable quality and fit for the purpose intended. There is also a variety of enacted legislation to control various quality aspects of agricultural production.</P>
    <P>Some examples of this type of legislation are as follows: the European Communities Classification, Packaging and Labelling of Pesticides Regulation, 1985, as amended, prescribes various conditions which must be complied with in relation to the placing on the market of pesticides; the Animal Remedies Act, 1956 regulates the import, manufacture, sale and advertisement of animal remedies; the European Communities Veterinary Medical Products Regulation, 1986 controls the licensing and manufacture of veterinary medical products. In accordance with these regulations all such products may be sold only with an authorisation granted by the Minister for Agriculture and Food. These authorisations are granted on the recommendations of the National Drugs Advisory Board who first test the preparation in question with particular regard to quality, safety and efficiency.</P>
    <P>Regarding primary agricultural products which have been subject to initial processing, even in a case where a defect in this type of product was not caused by the processing operation itself, the onus is on the processor to discover any hidden defects no matter how they were caused. In an attempt to clarify what constitutes <Col N="1089" /> initial processing, we have included the definition &ldquo;any processing of an industrial nature which could cause a defect,&rdquo; drawn from the recitals to the directive. It is accepted of course that it will ultimately be a matter for the court to decide whether liability applies in any particular case.</P>
    <P>The Department of Agriculture and Food, the Creamery Milk Suppliers' Association, the Irish Insurance Federation, the Confederation of Irish Industry and the Industrial Cost Monitoring Group concur with our thinking in respect of the exclusion of primary agricultural products. The main opposition to this exclusion is represented by the Consumers' Association of Ireland who feel there is no relevance to the argument that primary agricultural products are subject to environmental factors beyond the conrol of the producer. Because of the extent to which fresh vegetables are sprayed with chemicals and because the land in which they are produced is artificially fertilised, no valid distinction, the association claims, can be made between natural and processed products.</P>
    <P>Given that the majority of other member states have excluded such products from their implementing legislation, it would be inadvisable for Ireland to take any measures which might place farmers at a disadvantage with respect to their Community counterparts. To include primary agricultural products within the scope of the Bill would oblige farmers to carry product liability insurance adding substantially to their production costs and having a negative effect on their competitiveness with other EC members.</P>
    <P>The definition of product in the Bill will be wide and questions about whether a particular product is covered by the legislation will ultimately be determined by the courts. This situation is very clear-cut as far as I am concerned and I represent a rural constituency where farming is going through a difficult period. I could not stand over a Bill which would make farmers carry product liability insurance for a product which is of the highest possible quality; 99.9 per cent of the farming community produce quality products <Col N="1090" /> which meet international standards from the fresh clean environment we are fortunate to enjoy. Wrongdoers exist. The former Minister for Agriculture and Food, Deputy O'Kennedy, made a special issue of so-called angel dust or devil dust as he called it. Those people are engaging in national sabotage and will be dealt with effectively by the courts. Any new legislation required in that regard will be bought in.</P>
    <P>Farming organisations such as the IFA and the Irish Creamery Milk Suppliers' Association, are clear in their condemnation of this proposal and of the effect it would have on their membership if any person were caught introducing angel dust into the food cycle in this country. I do not believe that a responsible organisation would allow those people to continue as members.</P>
    <P>As Minister for Trade, I feel that this proposal would have a disastrous effect on our exports. I visited the Islamic Republic of Iran on 3 October 1991 where I invited the Minister for Reconstruction and Jihad to visit Ireland. During my attendance at the 17th Teheran Fair I made a strong case to him on behalf of the quality of our agricultural products. He visited Ireland and was so impressed by the quality of our products that he lifted the embargo on the sale of Irish primary products to the Islamic Republic of Iran. Consequently we may be able to sell 250,000 of our cattle to that country and I hope as a result that we will also resume cattle trade with Libya.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>What about Iraq?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden" hpid="Mr. Leyden Mr. Leyden">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Leyden</NameTxt>
      <P>When the UN decide to lift the trade embargo on Iraq we will be there as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Will Larry get his money back?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden" hpid="Mr. Leyden Mr. Leyden">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Leyden</NameTxt>
      <P>When those embargos are lifted it is my policy to ensure that we sell to any trading nation acceptable under UN and EC law. I am glad that my colleague, the Minister for Industry and Commerce, is now in South Africa on <Col N="1091" /> an important trade mission. I have no apologies to make in that regard and I fully support his decision to go there.</P>
      <P>It is vital that we ensure that this Bill exempt primary agricultural products from this legislation. I put it to the Seanad that that is the policy to be pursued by Government and I stand by that recommendation.</P>
      <P>I wish to apologise, a Cathaoirligh, but I have to go to the Lower House to debate the Patents Bill. I will be represented here by the Minister of State, Deputy Kirk.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I am surprised that any Minister would gloat over the conclusion of a beef deal with the Islamic Republic of Iran, particularly when the representative involved was described &mdash; if I heard the Minister corectly &mdash; as the Minister for Development and Jihad, a rather unsavoury title. I opposed all export credit guarantees for Iraq and I was told that what I was suggesting with regard to foreign policy might be the moral approach but could Ireland afford it? I take a sardonic interest in the fact that we are now £187 million down the drain plus, we did not have moral&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely) Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely)</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator keep to section 1.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I am replying to the Minister's remarks. I am in the same field as the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that but if the Minister goes off the line, the Senator should not continue in the same direction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I have two points to make. In some respects this Bill is itself a mildly defective product because some things absent from this Bill ought to be included. It does not address a couple of issues, of which one was the subject of an amendment put down by the Fine Gael Party and the Labour Party &mdash; the question of consequential loss. I am surprised that this important matter is not <Col N="1092" /> addressed in the Bill. I am sure Senator Cassidy would agree that if one runs an establishment providing music, in the case of a discotheque or a dancehall, a failure of musical or electrical equipment of some kind would result in consequential loss of earnings. Such loss is assessable. I have had personal experience of running a charitable concern involving discotheques and when this unfortunate situation arose we were able to claim consequential loss. In a Bill dealing with liability for defective products, if through bad workmanship, or a defective product a company or employees lose earnings there should be provision for consequential loss claims as part of general liability.</P>
      <P>My second point is also brief. I am concerned with the restrictiveness for example, of section 1 (1) (b) where it says:</P>
      <P>electricity where damage is caused as a result of a failure in the process of generation of electricity.</P>
      <P>Would the Minister agree that this is a variation from the directive itself?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>That was the subject matter of amendment No. 5 and was disposed of the last day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I am addressing the principle; I am not supporting the amendment which deleted something. I would like to put a slightly different point, I would not restrict this to electricity. The Minister gives a further definition, where &ldquo;damage is caused as a result of failure of the process of generation of electricity&rdquo;. That narrows the definition, it should be extended to cover, for example, the distribution of electricity and pylons. A defective pylon may leak microwave radiation and cause damage to livestock and individuals, and as this section is framed, the manufacturers of defective pylons would be excluded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 1 is important because it gives the various definitions under which this legislation operates. Essentially the points that have been <Col N="1093" /> made so far on this side of the House have recommended broadening the parameters within which strict liability will apply. That is the difference between what we and the Minister have said.</P>
      <P>Where do we draw the line? Do we adopt a minimalist approach or a maximalist approach, if there is such a word? We have, in general, adopted a minimalist approach to all European legislation coming to this House. First, we have been very lethargic about introducing it, only introduced this Bill when proceedings had been initiated so that we had no choice but to do so. It should have been introduced by the middle of 1988 and we are almost into 1992 now and still have not dealt with it. Second, if we are introducing a process of strict liability in relation to defective products, are we going to establish a one or two tier schedule? If we are going to have strict liability for the consumer on one level and not on another, we will end up with a mish-mash and a curate's egg, to say the least. It would be more desirable to establish a broader set of parameters for the application of legislation particularly in section 1 where the narrow definition of damage does not apply to the actual product nor to damage caused by death or personal injury. Criteria for claims are limited to private use with no provision for professional or occupational use which should be covered.</P>
      <P>The major area of consequential loss covering damage, economic and financial loss, pain and suffering has been excluded. A discretionary line has been drawn. I know that drafters of the legislation in the context of the directive must draw a line somewhere, but the line is drawn too narrowly. We are not thereby going to effect the purpose of this legislation, namely, to shift the burden away from the tort situation onto strict liability for the producer. We have not achieved that and I would have preferred the Minister to have accepted some of our amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The definition of initial processing is a major concern and the Minister has not given a satisfactory answer. Initial processing means, in relation to primary <Col N="1094" /> agricultural products &ldquo;any processing of an industrial nature of those products which could cause a defect therein&rdquo;. The problem is to determine where processing starts. There is no clear indication of that. &ldquo;Primary agricultural products&rdquo; includes products of the soil, stock-farming, fisheries and game excluding such products which have undergone initial processing. This is a very grey area. When we consider what is going on in the present tribunal and what happened in the Goodman factories where initial processing took place, I wonder if countries which have already passed this legislation and who have received beef from this country that may have been tampered with in processing will be looking for compensation?</P>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I request that Senator Costello not refer to the tribunal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I have completed my point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Any tribunal matter is for the tribunal only.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>It was not so much the tribunal I was referring to as processing in our beef industry. I was giving an example of processing.</P>
      <P>The question I would like to ask is how do we protect the initial product, whatever about the initial processing? It is very easy for us to say that we have a huge agricultural industry but we also have a massive manufacturing export industry. What is paramount for us is high quality goods that can compete with the best in Europe and control standards as high as anywhere else. Because we are the garden of Europe we should be the first to implement defective product legislation in relation to our primary product, agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I disagree with the Minister of State, Deputy Leyden, when he said we must be very protective of the farmers and not place them at a competitive disadvantage or add to production costs. It is desirable, rather, that farmers produce high quality products. We have had a terrible history <Col N="1095" /> of failed bovine tuberculosis eradication; We spent £1 billion on this scheme. There have been abuses in the management of agricultural produce and of the national herd. The same abuse occurred in other areas such as the scandal which was the cause of our losing the Iranian market in the first place.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Senator should refer to that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has already said that the Iranian market has been opened up again and I am delighted to hear that. It is relevant to what I am saying. We are talking about the quality of the product.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it relevant to section 1 of the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I refer to the definition at lines 28 to 30 of &ldquo;initial processing&rdquo;; at lines 6 to 10 of &ldquo;primary agricultural product&rdquo;; and at lines 10 to 13 of product. &ldquo;Product&rdquo; means all movables with the exception of primary agricultural products which have not undergone initial processing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate the Senator's quoting separate lines but he is inclined to stray into a Second Stage speech and that is not appropriate on Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeCostelloLAB" hpid="Mr. Costello Mr. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I am addressing the definition and expanding on how we should have leeway in relation to that exemption given for primary agricultural products. I am explaining this because it is important to have high quality control on any exempted area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Kennedy raised a question about products that are not quite products of the soil under the normal definition and I am not sure if we got an answer to that. The expression Senator Kennedy used was hydroponic culture and it is possible now to grow certain items in sand and in water. Hydroponic culture <Col N="1096" /> does not seem to fall within the definition of primary agricultural products.</P>
    <P>We seem to be exempting anybody who might have been responsible for a defective product not covered by the definition of initial processing, for example, chemicals, hormones, growth promoters and pesticides which may cause change in the product administered prior to the processing stage. I do not see why there should not be strict liability there as well. If there was it would ensure we had the finest agricultural industry and the finest agricultural produce anywhere and that is the best way to ensure that.</P>
    <P>Will the Minister clarify section 1 (2) where it says: &ldquo;A word or expression that is used in this Act and is also used in the Council Directive has, unless the contrary intention appears, the meaning in this Act that it has in the Council Directive&rdquo;. That seems to be tautology because every word defined in the Council Directive has been defined in the Bill. Why state the same thing? It seems to be unnecessary duplication. Why is it presented in this way?</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>Since I raised the initial queries in relation to section 1 the debate has expanded considerably. This highlights the concern of Senators that the Bill, as passed, should be adequate to deal with the matter.</P>
      <P>There are one or two matters I want to respond to before I come back to my specific question. The Minister of State, Deputy Leyden, referred to his successful marketing trip to Iran. He was justified in feeling pleased with the outcome of his visit and I congratulate him on that. A market for 250,000 cattle from this country is extremely valuable at the present time and, to whatever extent he was responsible for ensuring that, he deserves to be complimented. I sincerely hope that when the Minister of State Deputy Kirk goes marketing, he will be equally successful in his own sector of agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In case the implication of the point I raised in relation to primary agricultural <Col N="1097" /> produce may have been misunderstood, I agree it is important and the correct approach, to exclude primary agricultural products from the effects of this measure. As the Minister pointed out, Luxembourg is the only EC member state that has included agricultural produce. A very high percentage of agricultural producers, in the high nineties, find it in their economic interest to produce the best possible product. They are conscious of that, and are doing so. A tiny percentage has abused the system and put certain aspects of agricultural produce at risk. I accept that the full rigours of the law are being applied to them, but seriousness of what they are doing is such that those convicted of being engaged in that practice should never be allowed to farm again. In the trade I represent in this House, as Senator Honan is well aware, if we transgress on three occasions we can be permanently banned from participating in our profession. If there is as serious an abuse in relation to such a primary product the same penalties should apply.</P>
    <P>I am concerned that my question has not been answered. I do not want a lengthy reply. I am asking a very specific question in relation to meat and the reprocessing of meat. When livestock leaves the farm, there is no liability at that stage. Initial processing in the meat factory then takes place and liability can attach to defects at that point. My point is that, where no defects occur at that initial processing but years later the meat is extracted from cold storage and reprocessed and the defect occurs at this point, this Bill brings back liability to the initial processer, not the reprocessor. That is wrong. Is my interpretation of the section correct or not?</P>
    <P>My question was not answered the last day and has not been answered today and in so far as I can insist, I want a reply on that specific point. I do not wish to involve other institutions in this, but our heads would be in the sand if we were not aware of certain disreputable practices that have taken place in this industry. We would be failing to fulfil our duty if we did not ensure the presence of <Col N="1098" /> safeguards in any legislation before us when we have the opportunity to prevent and to deal with such situations.</P>
    <P>Again, I will repeat the query. I refer to a situation where no defect occurs in the initial processing of the meat, but years later it is extracted from cold storage, reprocessed, and a defect occurs then. Under this measure there is no liability at that point for defects arising then. In fact, if a defect arises at that point, it goes back to the initial processor who may not be and very likely was not at all responsible for the defect that has arisen at a reprocessing stage. I want a simple answer. Is my interpretation correct or not?</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>Like other Senators, I am rather disappointed the Minister of State, Deputy Leyden has not endeavoured to reply to a number of questions that were asked. Senator Howard has repeated the basic question. The Minister should endeavour to answer the questions, and if he cannot answer them he would be as well off to say so.</P>
      <P>Towards the conclusion of my remarks I asked, for example, if this legislation covers the modern technology of hydroponics. The Minister did not reply to that or make any reference to it.</P>
      <P>Secondly, I asked what would be the position of a person who was injured, for example, by contaminated water supplies, where the water supply had been contaminated by sewage, for example, or by excessive concentration of aluminium sulphate. I mention those matters because they are very much in the news at the moment. Many areas of the country appear to be in breach of EC guidelines and standards in regard to water supplies. If the Minister is not in a position now on Committee Stage to refer to the points we have raised, perhaps he might be in such a position on Report Stage. I would like to know the position of local authorities, and of a person who has suffered injuries, and also the position regarding the new technology.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture and Food (Mr. Kirk) Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture and Food (Mr. Kirk)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture and Food (Mr. Kirk)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am <Col N="1099" /> glad to have the opportunity to return to the House to recommence the debate on this matter. Having listened to the contributions of various Senators I noted that many of the points had been raised during the debate the previous day.</P>
      <P>On the question of initial processing, I listened to my colleague Minister Leyden and I thought he dealt quite adequately with the query under that heading. I should also say, in the context of this legislation, there is no question of this measure having been suddenly put together over a very short period. This matter has been in gestation for some time. There has been considerable consultation with the various interest groups involved and as a consequence of that consultation, the provisions in the legislation reflect what is best having regard to the need of the consumer at this time and the need of the primary producer.</P>
      <P>Senator Howard referred to the defect in, for example, meat which has been processed and subsequently defrosted. In those circumstances the individual who carried out the defrosting would be liable for any defect which might subsequently arise.</P>
      <P>Senator Kennedy referred to hydroponic culture. We are in the process of getting the exact, definitive, technical definition of hydroponic culture. We will have an opportunity to come back to that point at a later stage. Senator Costello referred to section 1 (2) which states:</P>
      <P>A word or expression that is used in this Act and is also used in the Council Directive has, unless the contrary intention appears, the meaning in this Act that it has in the Council Directive.</P>
      <P>That is a standard provision in all legislation giving effect to Community instruments. Together with section 1 (3), it is designed to ensure that in matters of interpretation a precedent is given to the Community instrument over national law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We feel that the Bill fully meets the requirements of the legislation. It is the view of the Government that the Bill strikes the balance between the interests <Col N="1100" /> of the consumer and the producer. We sell perhaps 80 per cent of our produce overseas and that is the vital artery for our economy. We must have regard to that fact in any legislation brought before the Houses of the Oireachtas. I believe the Government have succeeded in getting the balance right in the prevailing circumstances.</P>
    <P>I must have regard to the very considerable interest a number of Senators on the Opposition benches have in this legislation. We welcome their interest and their endeavours to tease out and get clarification on various points in the sections as we go along. I will do my best to deal with them as they arise. When we get the exact, technical definition on hydroponic culture, I will endeavour to respond to Senator Kennedy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to thank the Minister of State for endeavouring to respond to the specific questions raised, but he has not responded to the final question I asked: what is the position of a person who is injured by contaminated water supplied by the local authority? Does that person come within the scope of this legislation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardConroy" hpid="Professor Conroy Professor Conroy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Conroy</NameTxt>
      <P>Could that in any sense be regarded as a product under this section?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so. The position is that the point Senator Kennedy mentions is not covered in this legislation. Naturally, the exact circumstances in which the contamination to which he refers would happen is not intended to be covered in this legislation. I am sure there are various other remedies in legislation under which the matter can be dealt with adequately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>In the definition section, section 1 (1), it states quite clearly that &ldquo;product' means all movables with the exception of primary agricultural products which have not undergone initial processing&rdquo;. Is it now suggested that local authorities are to be exempt from the definition of product here?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1101" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardConroy" hpid="Professor Conroy Professor Conroy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Conroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am intrigued by the Senator's intervention here. In what sense would water be regarded as a product? Is the local authority now, in some sense, producing water?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>It would certainly be a movable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we have adequately covered the point in relation to water and the local authority. We have clearly indicated that it is not intended to be <Col N="1102" /> covered here and that is, I hope, the explanation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not our intention to prolong the discussion beyond what is a reasonable attempt to obtain clarification on the measure, particularly in relation to section 1. We proposed five amendments to the section, we argued about it the last day and have continued the discussion here again today. It is our belief that section 1 is seriously flawed and for that reason we will oppose it.</P>
      <P>Question put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Committee divided: Tá, 30; Níl, 17.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bennett, Olga.<br />Bohan, Eddie.<br />Byrne, Hugh.<br />Byrne, Sean.<br />Cassidy, Donie.<br />Conroy, Richard.<br />Dardis, John.<br />Fallon, Sean.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Finneran, Michael.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Foley, Denis.<br />Haughey, Seán F.<br />Honan, Tras.<br />Hussey, Thomas.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Keogh, Helen.<br />Kiely, Dan.<br />Kiely, Rory.<br />Lanigan, Michael.<br />Lydon, Don.<br />McCarthy, Seán.<br />McGowan, Paddy.<br />McKenna, Tony.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />Ó Cuív, Éamon.<br />O'Keeffe, Batt.<br />Ormonde, Donal.<br />Ryan, Eoin David.<br />Wright, G.V.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Cosgrave, Liam.<br />Doyle, Avril.<br />Hederman, Carmencita.<br />Hourigan, Richard V.<br />Howard, Michael.<br />Jackman, Mary.<br />Kennedy, Patrick.<br />McMahon, Larry.<br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Manning, Maurice.<br />Naughten, Liam.<br />Neville, Daniel.<br />Norris, David.<br />Ó Foighil, Pól.<br />O'Toole, Joe.<br />Ross, Shane P.N.<br />Ryan, Brendan.<br />Staunton, Myles.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators Wright and Fitzgerald; Níl, Senators Cosgrave and Howard.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanDoherty" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we deal with section 2 I would like to inform Senators that we are honoured by the presence of the Nigerian ambassador in the House. I am sure the House would like to join with me in giving her a special welcome.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 2 of the Bill establishes liability for damage caused by defective products. There are a few points in section 2 which I would like the Minister to clarify but, irrespective of what is said on section 2, by the time we come to section 6 there will be adequate defence for everything contained in section 2 in relation to the placing of liability. However, I wish to take up a point made by Senator Kennedy on the last section &mdash; I am sure he will develop <Col N="1103" /> this point himself &mdash; relating to the liability of local authorities in respect of the supply of contaminated water.</P>
      <P>Section 2 states that a &ldquo;producer&rdquo; means the manufacturer or producer of a finished product, the manufacturer or producer of any raw material or the producer of a component part of a product. In relation to the treatment of water supplies there is no doubt about the situation with regard to the local authorities under those three headings. Section 2 (1) (d): &ldquo;any person who, by putting his name, trade mark or other distinguishing feature to the product or using his name or any such mark or feature in relation to the product, has held himself out to be the producer of the product&rdquo;. Can any local authority deny they are the producer of the finished product that comes through our taps?</P>
      <P>I raise that point because while a response was given to the matter on section 1 that response will be inadequate in relation to the various headings under which liability can occur in section 2. Therefore, I would like the Minister to respond to those points.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senator Howard indicated, section 2 is very comprehensive. It defines in a most comprehensive way the definition of &ldquo;producer&rdquo; under six headings, and Senator Howard rightly adverted again to the question of the responsibility of local authorities under this legislation. Will the Minister of State consider that matter again before Report Stage?</P>
      <P>I would like to ask one or two questions in regard to section 2 (1) (d). It provides that a producer shall be liable for damages in tort for damage caused wholly or partly by a defect in his product and the producer is then defined as any person who, by putting his name, trade mark or other distinguishing feature on the product or using his name or any such mark or feature in relation to the product, has held himself out to be the producer of the product. I would like to ask three questions in regard to that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What is the position of a pharmacist &mdash;<Col N="1104" /> generally referred to by many people as a chemist, but we will use the word &ldquo;pharmacist&rdquo; in this case &mdash; who puts his or her name only on a prescription as is typically done? This can arise, as we all know, in the case of a drug which is in fairly common demand in the form of pills and the pharmacist draws his supplies from time to time from various manufacturers of that drug or pill. If a batch is faulty and a customer suffers injury, what is the position in regard to such a pharmacist? Those questions were not teased out in the other House.</P>
    <P>In regard to licensing, what is the position in relation to a company who develop a product and license another company to manufacture it? In general, what is the overall position with regard to licensing? What is the position in regard to the setting up of a subsidiary company where, for example, the assembly, manufacture, patent, trade mark and the licence all are vested by the parent company in a subsidiary company? In such case against whom will an injured person have recourse where, for example, the subsidiary company are capitalised at, say, £100 and the damage is assessed at £1 million? I appreciate there is other legislation in place, such as company law legislation and so on, that covers this matter but it also arises under this legislation. Therefore, I ask the Minister to indicate the position in regard to those matters and if he cannot do so now, perhaps he might do so on Report Stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 2 deals with liability for damage caused by defective products. Surely my colleagues on the other side are not suggesting that the water for which supply all county councils and local authorities are responsible is anything but top class? If there is damage to water it happens somewhere down the line. We are all delighted money has been allocated to the county councils to deal with water problems if water is contaminated &mdash; and I am not saying we do not have polluted water &mdash; it is not caused by the local authority; the water could have been contaminated at some point down <Col N="1105" /> the line. I am disturbed the Senator would think that water leaving a local authority plant would be polluted. Perhaps I misunderstood the Senator but we must be clear on who we blame, whether it be Clare County Council, Kildare County Council or Limerick County Council. I will stand by the county councils.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no great difference between Senator Honan's view and mine. My concern is that where a public water supply becomes contaminated, under this legislation the liability, in the event of inability to identify those responsible would go back to the producer which in this case is the local authority. That is what I want the Minister to clarify.</P>
      <P>I am not trying to get at the local authorities. I have no doubt it is the intention and focus of local authorities to produce a quality product but if, for some reason, the tap water in a particular local authority area has been contaminated, in this Bill we are placing liability on the manufacturer or the producer of the finished product. All tap water has undergone treatment. In this Bill &ldquo;producer&rdquo; means the manufacturer or producer of any raw material or the manufacturer or producer of any component part of a product, and any person &mdash; and I assume any person includes any body &mdash; who, by putting his name, trade mark or other distinguishing feature on the product or using his name or any such mark or feature in relation to the product has held himself out to be the producer of that product.</P>
      <P>I know no local authority will deliberately contaminate a water supply, but if a contamination occurs we are placing liability on the manufacturer or producer of the product, and in this case it is evident who is involved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps on Report Stage the Minister of State might be in a position to make a more detailed statement on this matter because it seems that a local authority could, indeed, be covered by this. If the evidence in court <Col N="1106" /> suggests that the water supplies were contaminated &mdash; this is only hypothetical in the vast majority of cases, Senator Honan, of course, is right &mdash; we should not suggest that local authorities will never be responsible. There was a case in Chicago where more than 400 per cent of aluminium sulphate in excess of what should have been in the waters was put in the waters and there were 19 fatalities as a result.</P>
      <P>There is always the possibility of a mistake being made, nobody is suggesting that these things are done deliberately. The Minister seemed to suggest that under this legislation the water supply is not the concern of local authorities, but I suggest that it is. This is a genuine question because I am not sure whether it is.</P>
      <P>In Britain the legislation applies to the Crown and, therefore, applies to all Departments of State, State agencies, nationalised industries and so on. If, under this legisation water is defined as a product and the local authority are the producer of that product within the broad terms outlined by Senator Howard, it seems extraordinary to exempt local authorities from liability.</P>
      <P>Of course, there is the historic case of Byrne <i>v.</i> Ireland where the Supreme Court ruled that local authorities, State industries and that nationalised industries could not be exempt from the normal liabilities of negligence in tort. It may well be that the European Communities have no intention of exempting local authorities from the scope of this legislation. Why should the private sector be subject to strict liability when a local authority or any other such authority that supply a product are exempt? Perhaps the Minister will clarify this on Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to the water supply, the Bill does apply to public bodies if they are the producers of a product. The question of whether a local authority is a product for the purposes of the Bill naturally would be a matter for the courts to interpret if there was a difficulty at any given time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1107" /> We have to look at the practicalities of water supplies generally. A local authority or a combination of local authorities abstract water from a particular source, whether it is the Dublin Mountains, the Cooley Mountains or elswhere, treat it by way of chlorination or some more advanced treatment and supply it to the homes of the people within the catchment area. The question then arises as to contamination, intentionally or accidentally, and who is liable in those circumstances. The Senator raised a very worthwhile point but I envisage that there will be considerable heart searching in the context of a court case to decide whether a natural resource abstracted from a surplus or underground source could be classified as a product delivered to the homes of people within the catchment area of the system. We would be ill advised to try to interpret that here; it might be better left to the courts to decide.</P>
    <P>Where somebody produces a product under licence the licensee would be liable. If a pharmacist makes up a drug using various compounds and the drug subsequently causes injury, then the producer of one or possibly more of those compounds which are shown to have caused the injury would be liable. I hope, to some extent, I have clarified the points the Senator raised.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>As a result of a communication, which I am sure we all received, from the Consultative Committee of Accountancy Bodies, Ireland, I wish to raise another matter with the Minister. It is not clear whether products designed to reduce damage, for example, car safety features such as fire alarms, and so on, could give rise to liability if they fail to operate properly due to a defect. The communication states that the Bill should clarify whether a failure to prevent damage or warn of impending damage could be deemed to have caused damage. I am sure this has already been raised with the Minister, but I am not aware of a reply. This is an interesting point, particularly with regard to car <Col N="1108" /> safety features and I presume safety belts, fire alarms and so on are included there. The communication asks if those features would give rise to a liability if they fail to operate properly due to a defect. It goes on to state that the Bill should clarify whether a failure to prevent damage or warn of impending damage could be deemed to have caused damage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>In the Bill a &ldquo;producer&rdquo; means the manufacturer or producer of any raw material or the manufacturer or producer of a component part of a product. That clearly sets out the point the Senator has in mind. Again, a &ldquo;producer&rdquo; means the manufacturer or producer of any raw material or the manufacturer or producer of a component part of a product, or in the case of a product of the soil, of stock farming, and of fisheries and game.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for replying to two of my questions. However, he did not deal with the question of a parent company setting up a subsidiary for the purposes of manufacturing and supplying a product. Obviously, this is covered under company legislation but will it be covered under this legislation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>For the purpose of the Act, whoever produces the product will be liable if the product is defective. In the incidents which the Senator cited, if the subsidiary company produce the product then, obviously, they will be liable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I was hoping that that would not be the reply. That seems to blow a hole in this legislation. If it is the opinion of the Minister that the subsidiary company is liable and that that is the end of the matter, then obviously the subsidiary company will only be responsible as I indicated, for £100 and the damages may be assessed at £1 million. Does the Minister not see the implications of suggesting that the liability rests with the subsidiary? I hoped the <Col N="1109" /> courts would see through this and hold the parent company liable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>May I intervene to clarify the point I made? Naturally there would be a reference to the relevant company law to establish the structure of the subsidiary company. The liability would be considered in a more global context. If the subsidiary company were the producer of the product, it is fairly obvious that under the law they would be liable but that would be having due regard to the interpretation of company law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to raise another point on section 2 (3) which is quite complicated. It deals with what has been described not alone in Europe but in the United States as the problem of the unknown or the unidentifiable defendant. This section deals with the liability of the supplier of defective products and states any person who supplies a product shall be liable for the damage caused by that product if the supplier fails to identify the person who supplied the product to him, thereby, in my view, going up the chain of supply to the ultimate consumer who, as is intended, should bear liability for the defect under this legislation. Thus, the finished product would usually consist of a large number of separate components and those components may even have components within themselves. Therefore, the intention of section 2 (3) is that the liability of the supplier should only extend to identifying the producer of the finished product and not to the producers of the component of that finished product. Will the Minister clarify that because there is a certain confusion as to what should be identified?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It appears to apply only to the manufacturer of the finished product. For example, in the case of a person who is supplied with a motor car, a part of which is defective, under section 2 (3) the product which was supplied and was defective is quite clearly the motor car and, accordingly, the retailer who, through his showroom or wherever supplied the car, is only bound to identify who actually made the car. He is not expected to identify the <Col N="1110" /> manufacturers of the various component parts nor is be bound to identify who made the defective part which has been part of the manufacturing process and ultimately forms part of the finished product which is then sold. It is unclear how that section will operate. In my view it will only apply to the manufacturer of the finished product.</P>
    <P>The problem of the unknown defendant has arisen in various shapes and forms in the United States and is also likely to arise here. In the United States the problem arose in that persons who were injured, usually by a prescribed drug, due to the passage of time, were unable to establish which of several possible manufacturers had produced the drug that caused the injury.</P>
    <P>One can imagine the problem where hundreds of manufacturers produce the same type of drug. Indeed, a drug which caused widespread product liability problems in the United States was DES, a synthetic product which was widely prescribed for pregnant women to prevent miscarriages during the years 1947 to 1971. That drug was supplied by hundreds of drug manufacturers in the United States. In 1971, following reports linking DES with the subsequent development many years later of cancer in the daughters of those women who had taken the drug, the Federal Drug Administration in the United States effectively banned the drug. The problem which those women were than faced with was that of establishing which of the vast number of manufacturers had produced the DES which was taken by their mothers during pregnancy. Therefore, the practical implementation of section 2 (3) needs to be considered.</P>
    <P>The courts in the United States responded very well to the problem because it is a tradition in the United States to impose strict liability on manufacturers. In response of this fairly widespread problem, the courts there evolved a number of new principles on which strict liability may be founded. Without going into the details, these principles include such theories as enterprise liability, alternative liability, the market <Col N="1111" /> share theory, the risk contribution theory and so on. Basically we should try to apportion blame where a number of manufacturers produce the same type of drug or product. I ask the Minister to consider this before Report Stage because it is something about which the European Commission and the courts are concerned. In the United States a case has been taken to the Supreme Court in this regard. I do not expect the Minister, unless he wishes to do so, to reply to it in detail now.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>Subsection (3) is based on article 33 of the directive and is designed to facilitate an injured person who wishes to take an action against the producer of a defective product but who has difficulty in establishing who is the producer. By virtue of this subsection any person in the supply chain, from the retailer back, will be liable unless he identifies his supplier or the producer within a reasonable time of being requested to do so by the injured person. The phrase &ldquo;within a reasonable time&rdquo; is not defined in the Council directive and will ultimately be a matter for the courts to decide. It is clear from subsection (2) and (3) that an injured person should have little difficulty to establishing a liable party in those circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I believe the opposite to be true where there are a number of manufacturers of a drug which some years later is seen to have caused problems. The drug I mentioned obviously caused problems and the whole case law in the United State clearly pinpoints the fact that it is very difficult to identify what has been referred to as the problem of this defendant. I hope we would look at that because it is going to arise here. This is becoming a modern country, there is modern technology developed here. We should be aware of that. To suggest that the plaintiff would have little difficulty in identifying the defendant would not be true so far as drugs of this nature are concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we conclude I <Col N="1112" /> want the Minister to confirm that I understood his reply to my query on safety features. I am talking about manufacturers and suppliers of fire alarms. The Minister referred me to section 2 (2) (a) and (b) &ldquo;manufacture or producer of a finished product &ldquo;and&rdquo; manufacturer or producer of a component part....&rdquo; My understanding is that the Minister's reply confirms that a company manufacturing and supplying a fire alarm is liable under the provisions of this legislation should the fire alarm due to a defect, fail to warn and, therefore, cause the householder to suffer damages. Is it correct that the manufacturer or supplier, or both, of that fire alarm are responsible and that liability rests on them should the fire alarm fail to function due to a defect?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>My advice is that if the fire alarm fails to be activated because of a fault and there is subsequent loss or damage as a result, there would be liability in those circumstances. The Senator did not differentiate between that case and where the fire alarm did not go off and there was no resultant damage. It would appear that, where it failed to be activated and there was damage and loss, there would be a liability.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>This section sets a threshold of £350 for damages, which is reasonable. We have to protect against frivolous claims. In the Dáil the Minister referred to the fact that a small claims court was close to coming into existence and that that court would take care of that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I welcome this section. The threshold of £350 is reasonable. I do not think any one of us would like to see a situation where there were thousands of claims coming into the <Col N="1113" /> courts every day. Like Senator Howard, I will be glad to see the operation of the small claims procedure in the District Court. In the debate on the Courts (No. 2) Bill and the Minister indicated that a pilot project was being set up in the Dublin area for the operation of the small claims procedure. That has been very effective in the United Kingdom and the idea of a pilot scheme is almost a necessity. I think the rest of the country would benefit greatly from a small claims procedure. Therefore, I welcome the provision in section 3 and hope it can be linked and perhaps we could have some indication from the Minister as to the wider availability of the small claims procedure for the rest of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not my Department, but, with regard to pilot schemes, it is a question of learning from the experience of their operation. If the results of the experience of their operation is satisfactory, the question of their further extension would be considered and dealt with expeditiously.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 4.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 4 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this provision. It brings clarity into the legislation, which is important. In order to prove a case in court the plaintiff knows exactly what he or she has to prove. There are three things that have to be proved: (1) the damage, (2) the defect and (3) the casual relationship between the defect and the damage. That is the type of clarity I was pleading for in section 1; and I welcome it in section 4.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 5 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1114" /> SECTION 6.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 6 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>As we went through the Bill I felt that the substance is in sections 2, 4 and 6. Section 5 deals with defences. We spent a lot of time dealing with the interpretations in section 1 and liability in respect of defective products in section 2; the responsibility of the manufacturer and producer of a finished product, raw material or a component part, somebody putting their name or trade mark to a product and we felt liability should attach there. Now we come to section 6. I believe section 6 provides an adequate defence to practically every liability we discussed earlier. Whether in relation to a finished product, raw material or a component part, all a producer has to do to prove he is not liable is (a) show that he did not put the product into circulation and (b) having regard to the circumstances, it is probably the defect which caused the damage did not exist at the time the product was put into circulation by him. That defence is as wide as the proverbial barn door and my colleague, Senator Kennedy and his colleagues in another establishment here in town will find scope for their talents in the series of defences provided for under section 6.</P>
      <P>I suggest to the Minister that it is going to be virtually impossible, because of the range of defences provided here, to establish liability.</P>
      <P>Section 6 (b) says:</P>
      <P>that, having regard to the circumstances, it is probable that the defect which caused the damage did not exist at the time when the product was put into circulation by him or that the defect came into being afterwards...</P>
      <P>I think that is a very safe defence for any defect that may be found in a product, that it probably did not exist at the time the product was put into circulation. Who is to say it did or did not or that the defect came into being afterwards?</P>
      <P>Section 6 (c) says:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1115" /> that the product was neither manufactured by him for sale or any form of distribution for an economic purpose nor manufactured or distributed by him in the course of his business...</P>
    <P>The manufacturer, for example, could claim that the product was produced as a result of a hobby.</P>
    <P>Section 6 (d) says:</P>
    <P>that the defect concerned is due to compliance by the product with any requirement imposed by or under any enactment or any requirement of the law of the European Communities...</P>
    <P>If that is an example of a clear explanation, I am toally baffled by it. Section 6 (b) and (c) provide an adequate defence to any of the liabilities we dealt with earlier.</P>
    <P>Very briefly, I refer to section 6 (e): &ldquo;that the state of scientific and technical knowledge at the time when he put the product into circulation was not such as to enable the existence of the defect to be discovered&rdquo;. This has been referred to elsewhere as the state of the art defence and it is there for manufacturers. It is clearly giving them an out and it looks comparativley reasonable at its face value. The true effect will be to render it impossible for a wronged person to succeed against a chemical company. That can scarcely be desirable when we think of thalidomide children and so on. I am sure I will be replying as a result of the Minister's response but at this stage I wish to say that section 6 provides a battery of defences.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senator Howard has indicated, this Bill provides quite a number of defences, indeed what might be called primary defences, in the sense that what you have to do in court is obviously to disprove a number of assumptions in regard to primary facts. The Bill itself, as he has indicated, provides six statutory defences to the principle of strict liability. The one I want to deal with is the defence provided in section 6 (e) &mdash; that the state of scientific <Col N="1116" /> and technical knowledge at the time he put the product into circulation was not such as to enable the existence of the defeat to be discovered; in other words, a producer shall not be liable under this legislation if he proves that particular point.</P>
      <P>As Senator Howard has indicated, section 6 (e) provides for the development risks or the state of the art defence. Thus, a product will not be liable if, but only if, he proves that the state of scientific and technical knowledge at the time of the supply was such that he could not have discovered the defect. The inclusion of this defence has aroused much controversy. It has aroused controversy in the European Community. It has been regarded as a defeat for the European Commission. It is here in any case and it is open to us to have it included in this legislation or to seek a derogation from it. On the one hand it has been said that without the development risks defence innovation would be stifled. That would not be in the interest either of industry or consumers. On the other hand the state of the art defence undoubtedly leaves a gap in the compensation cover through which the victims of another thalidomide disaster or another Chinook helicopter disaster might slip.</P>
      <P>This defence has been included to meet the needs of high risk industries in which innovation is often crucial. It excludes not only development risks as regards dangers unknown at the time of distribution but also liabilty for injury caused by, and I quote, &ldquo;established products with previously unsuspected propensities&rdquo;. It is of enormous importance to the pharmaceutical sector in respect of undiscovered side-effects in new drugs and to the aerospace sector in respect of design defects in aircraft.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This exemption for the pharmaceutical sector is particularly ironic because the Pearson Commission, which boosted the move towards strict liability for defective products, has been established in the wake of and because of the thalidomide disaster. However, under this legislation, and because of the inclusion of this defence in this legislation, it appears <Col N="1117" /> unlikely that the victims of such a drug today would be able to recover under this legislation, or indeed under the British legislation. The defence reintroduces the concept of fault, albeit in a limited way, and thereby blurs the distinction between the two systems of liability.</P>
    <P>The most compelling argument against the defence is that a consumer should not have to bear the risk of the unknown and that liability should be strictly imposed on the person who created the risk, albeit innocently, for commercial gain. In Germany &mdash; and it is interesting to see developments there &mdash; liability in respect of defective drugs is strict and has been for many years. Personal injury claims relating to such products are settled under the German Pharmapool, a compulsory system of insurance which encourages a high degree of co-operation between the German pharmaceutical and insurance industries.</P>
    <P>There is a suggestion abroad now that this is the appropriate way to go. I know the Confederation of Irish Industry and the British Confederation of Industry have taken a different view. It may well be indeed that the inclusion of this defence in this Bill may prove a significant flaw in the legislation and that we should have opted for the derogation which indeed is open to us in respect of this defence. We have been rather cautious in our approach to this matter. The defence, it can be soundly argued, gravely undermines the ability of the injured person to claim compensation in matters of very serious injury in respect of the industries I have mentioned.</P>
    <P>It seems to me that perhaps in the long term Lord Hanworth has got it right when, speaking on similar legislation in the House of Lords, he stated that on balance &mdash; and I appreciate there are good arguments on both sides &mdash; the loophole should be closed and that perhaps this defence should not be in the Bill. If injury does occur it seems the manufacturer, and especially multinational manufacturers, are in a much better position than the victim to meet costs arising from such injury. Therefore, in respect of those two industries &mdash; the <Col N="1118" /> pharmaceutical industry and the aerospace industry &mdash; and other very big companies it seems to me they should be able to get their house in order to cover the necessary type of insurance.</P>
    <P>I posed the problem. I do not think this side of the House will be voting against the legislation unless Senator Howard, who is our spokesperson on the matter, decides otherwise. The parties in the other House seem to have been fairly united. However, it may happen that in a few years from now future Senators will say we got it wrong and that this defence should have been left out of this legislation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>The grounds on which the producer may be exonerated from liability are listed in this section. However, it is the responsibility of the producer to prove that these circumstances obtain in any particular case. These defences are as follows: Paragraph (a): &ldquo;That he did not put the product into circulation&rdquo;. A product has been put into circulation when it has been delivered to another person in the course of business. He would not, for instance, be liable in a situation where the product had either been stolen and/or resold. Paragraph (b) states: &ldquo;That having regard to the circumstances, it is probable that the defect which causes the damage did not exist at the time the product was put into circulation by him or that that defect came into being afterwards.&rdquo; The producer cannot, for instance, be held responsible for defects caused by improper handling of goods in the course of distribution or by the injured person himself. This provision would apply also to products with warnings or instructions for use which might be detached for the final supplier, thereby causing the consumer to injure himself or damage his property.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This aspect is an integral part of the presentation of the product which is one of the criteria set out in section 5 (1) for determining a defective product. Paragraph (c) states: &ldquo;That the product was neither manufactured by him for sale or any form of distribution for an economic <Col N="1119" /> purpose, nor manufactured or distributed by him in the course of his business.&rdquo; This derogation would apply in the case of private transactions &mdash; for example, the private sale of motor vehicles or other items of property. Paragraph (d) states: &ldquo;That the defect concerned is due to compliance by the product with mandatory regulations issued by public authorities within the European Communities.&rdquo; The producer would have to show, however, that the defect was the direct result of compliance with such regulations, that is, that it was impossible for the product to have been produced in accordance with the regulations without causing the product to be defective. It is important to note that this defence could only be used in a country where such national regulations exist or in a member state with similar national provisions.</P>
    <P>Paragraph (e) states: &ldquo;That the state of scientific and technical knowledge at the time when he put the product into circulation was not such as to enable the existence of the defect to be discovered.&rdquo; Member states were allowed by Article 15 of the directive to exclude this defence, known as the &ldquo;development risks&rdquo; or &ldquo;state of the art&rdquo; defence. It has been decided to include the defence in the provisions of the Bill.</P>
    <P>During the discussions on the directive at Community level some member states argued that the inclusion of this defence was contrary to the principle of strict liability and in certain cases would leave the consumer with no avenue for compensation. This defence would, it was claimed, also bring about problems relating to proof and the courts would have to give lengthy consideration to cases where the defence was used. Other member states, however, argued that the absence of such a defence would cause enormous problems for manufacturers, such as the high cost of insurance and the stifling effect on innovation, especially in high risk industries like pharmaceutical production where considerable research is involved in the development of what are in many cases life-saving drugs.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1120" /> Regarding insurance costs, the Irish Insurance Federation feels that the exclusion of the development risk defence would have a serious inflationary effect on liability insurance costs. In any event the burden of proof will be on the producer to show that because of the state of scientific and technical knowledge at the time the product was put into circulation he could not have been expected to discover the existence of the defect and providing such proof is likely to be difficult.</P>
    <P>In its report on implementation of the directive on product liability, the fifth report of the Joint Committee on Secondary Legislation of the European Communities favoured the inclusion of the development risk defence as it felt the higher insurance premiums which would probably result from its exclusion would damage producers' competitive positions both on the home and foreign markets. Of the nine member states who have so far implemented the directive, eight have included the development risk defence in their national provisions. Of these eight, Germany has extended the defence to all products except pharmaceuticals, for which strict liability provisions had already been in force nationally for a number of years.</P>
    <P>Article 15 of the Council directive also states that the option relating to development risks will be reviewed by the EC Commission ten years after the date of notification of the Council directive, that is, after 25 July 1995. The Commission may, in the light of the experience of member states in relation to this option, make proposals to the Council for change.</P>
    <P>In the case of the manufacturer of a component or the producer of a raw material, no liability will be incurred if either can prove that the defect in the component or raw material is attributable to the design of the product of which the component or raw material is a part or to the instructions given by the manufacturer of the product. The expression &ldquo;instructions given by the manufacturer&rdquo; is taken to mean that in cases where the defect in the component is the result of <Col N="1121" /> compliance with the specification or design of the finished product, then the manufacturer of the finished product will be liable.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to briefly recall that the Minister of State in introducing the measure in this House stated that the directive that gave rise to this legislation was the most significant piece of EC legislation in the area of consumer protection. The Minister is perfectly right to praise his Bill, and he did that. Today and last week we spent quite a time clearing our minds on what section 1 dealt with and, in section 2, defining more liability would attach and so on. We then come along in section 6 and put adequate defence to the measures of protection we introduced earlier. Therefore, I feel we would be misleading the consumer to a degree to suggest that this is an answer to the problems caused by defective products. It is not, because although we have defined liability we have included adequate defences against that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I share the Minister's concern that <Col N="1122" /> legislation should not inhibit or act as a disincentive to the provision of new drugs and experimentation. At the same time, I have to bear in mind that the effect of section 6 is to render it virtually impossible for a wronged person to succeed against a chemical company. I know Senator Kennedy referred to a convergence of views in the other House in relation to the approach to this section of the Bill, but I do not think that we in this House are obliged to follow suit at any time. Therefore, I feel, as I do, that we are nullifying a lot of our earlier good work by the all-embracing effect of section 6, it would be wrong for me to agree to section 6. Despite a very eloquent defence of its provisions by the Minister, I have expressed my reservations and his lengthy and comprehensive defence has not been adequate to convince me I should give my consent in its entirety to what is contained in the section. I will be opposing section 6.</P>
    <P>Question put.</P>
    <P Just="Center">The Committee divided: Tá, 26; Níl, 19.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bohan, Eddie.<br />Byrne, Hugh.<br />Byrne, Sean.<br />Conroy, Richard.<br />Dardis, John.<br />Fallon, Sean.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Finneran, Michael.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Foley, Denis.<br />Honan, Tras.<br />Hussey, Thomas.<br />Keogh, Helen.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kiely, Dan.<br />Kiely, Rory.<br />Lanigan, Michael.<br />McCarthy, Seán.<br />McGowan, Paddy.<br />McKenna, Tony.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />Ó Cuív, Éamon.<br />O'Keeffe, Batt.<br />Ormonde, Donal.<br />Ryan, Eoin David.<br />Wright, G.V.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Cosgrave, Liam.<br />Doyle, Avril.<br />Hederman, Carmencita.<br />Hourigan, Richard V.<br />Howard, Michael.<br />Jackman, Mary.<br />Kennedy, Patrick.<br />McMahon, Larry.<br />Manning, Maurice.<br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Naughten, Liam.<br />Neville, Daniel.<br />Norris, David.<br />Ó Foighil, Pól.<br />O'Toole, Joe.<br />Ross, Shane P.N.<br />Ryan, Brendan.<br />Ryan, John.<br />Staunton, Myles.<br />Upton, Pat.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators Wright and Fitzgerald; Níl, Senators Cosgrave and Neville.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1123" /> Question declared carried.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 7.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 7 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to ask the Minister of State if he would set the provision in regard to the limitation period of three years and the extinguishing period in the context of the Civil Liability Act, 1961 and the Statutes of Limitation, 1957 and 1991 and set this legislation in the context of existing legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 7 (2) provides that the right of action conferred upon the injured person under the Bill shall expire by the end of a ten year period from the date on which the actual product was put into circulation by the producer, not the date on which that type, model or product was first marketed. If judicial proceedings are pending at the end of the ten year period, liability does not expire but runs until a final decision is made. Injuries arising from any defect in the product after the expiry of the ten year period would not be covered by the Bill.</P>
      <P>The ten year period referred to is not intended to be interpreted as a standard safe working life for all products. Reasonable life expectancy of a product which will vary from case to case is one of the factors that may be taken into account in assessing whether a product is defective. Section 5 (1) of the Bill states that: &ldquo;For the purposes of this Bill a product is defective if it fails to provide the safety which a person is entitled to expect taking all circumstances into account.&rdquo; The ten year limitation is intended to protect the producer against claims after an unreasonable length of time when evidence for his defence might just be difficult to obtain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 7 (2) (b) states that the ten year period laid down in paragraph (a) &ldquo;shall have effect whether or not the right of action accrued or time began to run&rdquo; during that period. In other words, the <Col N="1124" /> ten year limit shall apply once proceedings have not been instituted against the producer. They will also override the three year period allowed in subsection (1) of this section. Even where damage to property or personal injury are caused and discovered during the year period but proceedings have not been instituted then the injured person's right of action is still extinguished.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 8.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 8 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 8 provides for joint and several liability and it does so within the meaning of Part III of the Civil Liability Act, 1961. Perhaps the Minister would again indicate the operation of this Bill in the context of the Civil Liability Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>This section provides that the principle of joint and several liability as concurrent wrongdoers as defined in Part III of the Civil Liability Act, 1961 should apply to two or more persons liable under this Bill for the same damage. Part III of that Act defines concurrent wrongdoers as two or more persons who are responsible to an injured person for the same damage whether or not judgment has been recovered against some or all of them. The expression &ldquo;whether or not judgment has been recovered against some or all of them&rdquo; means that in cases where two or more persons are responsible for damge or injury caused even though damages may have been recovered in respect of one of the responsible parties, right of action will still accrue to the injured person aginst the other liable persons. Another advantage to the consumer in respect of joint and several liability is the protection of the rights of the injured person in the event of one or more of the responsible parties being unable to pay their shares of the damages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1125" /> Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 9.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 9 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHoward" hpid="Mr. Howard Mr. Howard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howard</NameTxt>
      <P>On section 9, without prejudice to Part III of the Civil Liability Act, 1961 concerning the right of contribution, the liability of the producer shall not be reduced when damage is caused both by a defect in a product and by the act or omission of a third party. I am not clear what we are providing for here. If damage has been caused by a defect in a product by an act of a third party, are we lifting responsibility from that third party because the act of the third party in some way, perhaps even in a major way, contributed to the damage suffered by the consumer? I imagine what we are dealing with is the balance of liability. I assume that it would be for a court to ascertain the balance of liability between the producer and the third party whose act or omission caused the damage. Are we making the producer totally liable despite the fact that an act or omission of a third party contributed to the damage caused, perhaps in a major way?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 9 (1) provides that a producer cannot avoid or reduce his liability under the Bill when damage is caused both by a defect in the product and by the act or omission of a third party. In other words, if a product was defective when put into circulation and if this defect was subsequently compounded by, for instance, a distributor of the product before the defect was caused by a distributor or any third person, then because the product was defective to begin with the liablity of the original producer cannot be reduced or avoided. However, the provisions of Part III of the Civil Liability Act, 1961, relating to rights of contribution shall apply in all cases covered by this Bill. Under the provisions of Part III of the Civil Liability Act, 1961, where responsibility for damage is shared by two or more persons, <Col N="1126" /> for instance, concurent wrongdoers damages are apportioned according to the degree of fault of the concurrent wrongdoers and one concurrent wrongdoer has a right to recover a contribution towards damages from any other concurrent wrongdoer.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 10.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 10 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the prohibition on exclusion from liability. All too often we see various contracts and so on which exclude liability. I welcome this provision whereby the liability of a producer to an injured person cannot be excluded by any exclusion clause in a contract or by any notice or, indeed, by any other provision. That is very important to the consumer. I welcome section 10.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 11.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 11 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 11 states: &ldquo;This Act shall not effect any rights which an injured person may have under any enactment or under any rule of law.&rdquo; I would like to link section 11 with section 1 (1), the definition section. It comes back to what we said originally. I would like the Minister of State to give us examples of the operation of this section. That is the major concern I have with this legislation. While parts of the Bill are very clear I am disturbed and concerned about the lack of clarity regarding the definition of damage and the type of injury for which injured people will be entitled to claim under this legislation. As I said, I would like the Minister to give us examples.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The section states that an injured person is basically not to be deprived of <Col N="1127" /> any of the benefits that they would have under any legislation or under any rule of law, but the definition section, section 1 (1), puts in doubt the whole question of recovery for consequential economic loss, loss of wages and so on, that are the normal elements of damage. I would like the Minister to comment on that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>This subsection provides that a claimant's rights under existing contract and tort laws shall not be affected by this Bill. Accordingly, under contract law the consumer will retain his rights against the supplier and under the law of tort any victim of a defective product may bring an action against any person in the chain of supply who has been negligent.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 12 to 14, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SCHEDULE.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Schedule be the Schedule to the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand the concern of the Minister of State that for convenience of reference, the directive should be set out in the Schedule. I acknowledged this earlier. However, in relation to international agreements, we have been accustomed to adopting two approaches. The first approach is by means of a Schedule setting out the international agreement, to incorporate it in our general law; the second approach, which in a sense has been heralded by Articles 19 and 20 of the directive, is that member states synthesise by setting out in terms that may be familiar to national courts, to parties who may be litigants and to others, the force of what is within the directive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The law on product liability is set out within the confines of this Bill itself. Accordingly, the provisions in this Bill are to be construed according to the directive and the legislation is essentially derived from the directive. However &mdash;<Col N="1128" /> and it is important to stress this for the convenience of everybody and in the interests of clarity &mdash; it seems to me, and I would like the Minister to confirm, that this Bill stands on its own and that there should be no need to refer directly to the directive because what is being done is to synthesise this for the purpose of national law. Obviously this is what is intended in Article 19. Statutory precedents might require and indicate that the directive itself should not be a Schedule to the Bill and the courts and the judges may refer to the directive for elucidation of any points.</P>
    <P>The annexing and scheduling of this directive to the Bill could give the impression that the directive is governing the Bill. The Bill stands on its own. It incorporates the key provisions in the directive, but there are provisions in the directive that are not included in the Bill. I suggest that if we adopt the second approach, to synthesise the two situations rather than to incorporate the international agreement directly into the Bill, it should not be annexed no matter how convenient because it could cause an element of confusion. I ask the Minister to consider that matter as well.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>The intention behind the Bill was to give effect to the substance of the EC Directive. Certain flexibility was given in relation to different areas but nonetheless, the Bill was produced first in the Dáil and second in the Seanad directly as a result of the Community putting the directive into effect. The Bill is intended to give effect to it in Ireland. The interpretation reads:</P>
      <P>1. &mdash;(1) In this Act, except where the context otherwise requires &mdash;&ldquo;the Council Directive&rdquo; means Council Directive No. 85/374/EEC of 25 July 1985 the text of which in the English language is set out for convenience of reference in the Schedule to this Act;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister relying totally on the English version of the directive because it is quite clear that when <Col N="1129" /> this directive was discussed in other Legislatures, the English language was certainly not the predominant medium so far as the interpretation of this directive was concerned. Is he suggesting that we are relying 100 per cent on the English version of this directive?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot give a direct answer to that but no matter from what language we draw it, the translation within the Community would be sufficiently accurate to ensure there was no substantial variation from one State to another.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
      <P>Report Stage ordered for Thursday, 28 November 1991.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 6 p.m. and resumed at 6.30 p. m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Suicide Bill, 1991:" RHead="Order for Second Stage">
    <Title>Suicide Bill, 1991: Order for Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Bill entitled an Act to amend the law relating to suicide, and for purposes connected therewith.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That Second Stage be taken today.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Suicide Bill, 1991:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Suicide Bill, 1991: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>For the information of the House, by agreement, the Second Stage debate on this Bill is being treated in the same manner as a non-government motion. The same procedural arrangements will apply in relation to the rota of speakers and time allocations, that is, half an hour for the opening speakers and 15 minutes per Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to welcome the Minister for Justice, Deputy Burke, <Col N="1130" /> to the House and thank him for taking the Bill.</P>
      <P>The Bill before the House, the Suicide Bill, 1991, sets out to bring the provisions of criminal law in this area into conformity with the needs and outlook of the present day. Its purpose is simple. It provides that it shall no longer be a criminal act to commit suicide, or to attempt to commit suicide.</P>
      <P>The successful suicide, of course, puts him or herself beyond the reach of the law. A law that says that such a person could be charged with a crime would be regarded as silly if it was not so tragic. It is a bad law and on that grounds alone should be repealed. Because suicide is a crime it follows that an attempt to commit suicide is also a crime, punishable by criminal law. The basis of the Bill presented is that in the humane outlook of today it is recognised that those who attempt suicide are in need of compassion and assistance and not the implementation of criminal law.</P>
      <P>It is ridiculous to suggest, as does the present law, that people who attempt to commit suicide are people with criminal tendencies in the ordinary sense. They are actuated by a variety of motives &mdash; mental illness, despair, depression, feelings of acute rejection and sometimes merely intense loneliness.</P>
      <P>Suicide is as old as the human race itself. In ancient Greece the bodies of suicide victims were buried outside the city walls, the right hand severed and buried separately. Ancient Roman citizens could get permission from the Senate to take their own lives but slaves and criminals were refused on economic grounds. The traditional Christian approach was very strict. From St. Augustine onwards condemnation of suicide strengthened and by the start of the eighth century, suicide was deemed to be a grave mortal sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Christian theology on suicide was quickly incorporated into civil legislation and for 1,000 years the families of suicide victims were ostracised and persecuted. This severe approach did not wane until the late 17th century when many of the legal penalties fell away by default. Desecration <Col N="1131" /> of the corpse, denial of burial in consecrated grounds, forfeiture of goods to the State were being sidestepped by the judiciary who devised an approach of bringing in verdicts of suicide, &ldquo;whilst the balance of the mind was disturbed&rdquo;. Hanging for attempted suicide took place in London up to 1860. There are people alive in Ireland who remember victims being denied burial in consecrated grounds.</P>
    <P>Suicide was decriminalised in France in 1898 and in the UK in 1960. Ireland is one of the last Christian countries to treat suicide as a crime. It is well past time that the State changed this cruel and uncivilised approach to what is a social disease and not a criminal act. It is criminal to regard it as such.</P>
    <P>There is extreme anguish, anger, disbelief and spiritual confusion among the family and friends of a suicide victim. Bereavement counselling of a high professional standard is required. The presence of the stigma of criminality adds to the stress of the bereaved. This Bill removes this stigma and brings Irish law into conformity with the views of the Irish people. It begins to recognise the fact that suicide must be regarded as a social disease. The fact that suicide and attempted suicide still remain a crime in Ireland is an indication of our failure to understand or to recognise the outcome of research into the area and reflects a tendency by Irish society to view suicide as a scandal rather than a tragedy.</P>
    <P>It is time that Irish society re-evaluated its head in the sand approach and opened up to understand the reasons and growing pressures on people which was caused the suicide rate to increase almost six times since 1970. Society must accelerate its change in attitude and recognise suicide as a public health problem.</P>
    <P>Understanding, compassion and professional counselling must be the response to the families of victims. In this area I wish to pay tribute to the work of the Samaritans, the Cork based Friends of the Suicide Bereaved and other such organisations who do excellent work in <Col N="1132" /> counselling and are available at the end of a phone to potential suicide victims.</P>
    <P>In the 1960s officially recorded suicides averaged 60 per annum; this is how in excess of 300 per annum. In the sixties Ireland had one of the lowest suicide rates in the world. As in other countries, there was a level of under-recording but this cannot explain the low level of suicides as Irish emigrants to other countries retained this very low rate of suicide, although somewhat higher than the Irish living at home. The rate in Ireland at that time was, therefore, genuinely low.</P>
    <P>The increase in suicide incidents cannot be attributed to a change in recording practices. If this was the case there would be a consequential fall in the numbers of accidental drowning, accidental poisoning and cases of open verdicts. This is not the case. The overall rise since the 1960s among men has been about 400 per cent and among women 200 per cent.</P>
    <P>Notwithstanding the low level of suicides in Ireland in the past, it has long been accepted that there has been an under-recording of suicide incidents. It is accepted that the true figures are 2.5 to three times the official rate.</P>
    <P>In a study in County Limerick in 1989, Dr. Peter Kirwan of the Mid-Western Health Board found that the true suicide rate was 18.04 per 100,000 population &mdash; the official figure for the period was 7.1 per 100,000 &mdash; two and a half times the official rate. Figures reported from Galway for the year 1978 give a rate of 13.1 per 100,000 is contrast to the official rate for the same year of 4.6 per 100,000 &mdash; again three times the official rate. These studies add further weight to the view that the official rates for suicide greatly underestimate the true position which, on the basis of these studies, is in the region of 1,000 deaths per year. Compiling true figures is hampered by the fact that the coroner is precluded from returning a verdict of suicide. This makes the collection of accurate figures very difficult.</P>
    <P>This legal impediment was further confirmed in the 1989 judgment of Justice <Col N="1133" /> Johnson in which he found that the coroner is precluded from inquiring into the mental capacity of the deceased &ldquo;even in order to produce an innocent explanation for the actions of a self killer&rdquo;. This has significant public health implications with regard to our understanding of suicide and the planning of appropriate services to deal with its consequences.</P>
    <P>Our statistics do not derive directly from coroners' reports. Since 1967 confidential police reports are supplied to the Central Statistics Office on deaths suspected of being unnatural. These reports are influenced by the individual garda's opinion as to whether a case is suicide or not. This is unsatisfactory. In Switzerland two certificates are issued on death. The attending doctor fills two certificates, one to the family recording the cause of death, the other to the General Statistics Office which is confidential.</P>
    <P>I wish to refer to the system of the coroner's court hearings. Attendance at the inquest is one of the hardest parts of the suicide bereavement. The trauma experienced in public by members of the family is extreme. The bereaved must wait around in court, often listening to many sad, tragic cases. This system must be modernised. Surely waiting rooms could be provided where relatives could remain until their case is heard. Everything should be done to ensure that the dignity of the bereaved is respected.</P>
    <P>The major increase in suicide rates has been in the early and middle age with a fall off in the fifth decade. This is in contrast to the usual international pattern where suicide rates increase in each decade to the seventh decade. This would suggest that late middle aged and elderly people are secure in value systems which protect them emotionally from the secular changes in Irish society. One may deduce from this that a person who is depressed or under extreme pressure is more likely now to consider suicide than such a person would do 20 years ago.</P>
    <P>Kelleher and Daly, in their study of suicide in Cork between 1980 and 1985, looked at the methods used to terminate life. The majority of men, 103 out of a total of 147 either drowned or hanged <Col N="1134" /> themselves, only 15 or approximately 10 per cent taking overdoses of medication. Hanging was more common in the rural areas and drowning in the urban areas. Hanging was uncommon among women whereas death by drowning occurred in over half the sample. Thirty per cent of women died by taking drug overdoses.</P>
    <P>Among the factors which, in other countries, have been found to correlate highly with the suicide rate, have been the crime rate, level of alcoholism, the illegitimacy rate and the divorce rate. These can be taken as representing the level of integration or cohesiveness within society. Let us examine these rates in the Irish context.</P>
    <P>The Irish illegitimacy rates show an increase in each succeeding year since 1970 with a rate then of 5.7 per 1,000 unmarried females aged 15-49 and in 1983 of 12.7 per 1,000. The number of indictable crimes between 1975 and 1985 doubled. The increase in alcoholism is measured by admissions to hospital for alcholism between 1971 and 1983 and the increase in <i>per capita</i> consumption of alcohol. These show an increase similar to the suicide rate. Between 1971 and 1984 the Irish marriage rate fell from 7.4 per 1,000 population to 5.8 per 1,000.</P>
    <P>These four measures &mdash; the illegitimacy rate, the crime rate, the alcoholism level and the fall in marriage rate &mdash; confirm international findings in an Irish context. This does not offer a causative explanation but suggests that the same forces that lead to these changes are also influencing the rise in suicide.</P>
    <P>Unemployment has a causative effect on the increase in suicide rates. Unemployment has a profound effect on a person, especially on the young and on those in early middle age. Irish society awards status and prestige according to a person's position and contribution at work. Unemployment is associated with loss of face and of prestige. The unemployed are six times more likely to be suffering from a psychiatric disorder than those in employment. Studies show that there is significantly more unemployment, job instability and occupational problems among suicide victims <Col N="1135" /> compared to those who did not commit suicide. Of the men who took their lives in the Kelleher-Daly Cork study, some two-thirds were out of work at the time of their deaths.</P>
    <P>Financial poverty is not related to suicide rates; rather it is affected by the poverty of relationships and the absence of social opportunities for many. Employment supplies a ready made set of relationships.</P>
    <P>The influence of traditional religious values has waned, particularly among the young. The growing secularisation of society has changed value systems. Social controls are less strict and people feel more alone and more lost. There is no longer a pre-arranged set of relationships with certainty within these relationships as was the case in past generations.</P>
    <P>Part I of the Bill establishes that suicide ceases to be a crime. Part II of the Bill creates an offence of complicity in another's suicide. At present because it is an offence to commit suicide, complicity in another's suicide is automatically an offence. By decriminalising the act of suicide, aiding, abetting, counselling or procuring the suicide of another is legalised. Part II of the Bill makes complicity in another's suicide liable on conviction for a term of imprisonment not exceeding ten years.</P>
    <P>Nothing must undermine the sanctity of human life or the general view of society that suicide, even though it will not be illegal, is regarded as a dreadful offence against nature. The sanctity of life is the rock on which our society is built. We must ensure that there is no movement towards putting a cost on preserving life.</P>
    <P>In a recent article, Kelleher, Daly and Kelleher &mdash; who are regarded as the foremost researchers in Ireland into the area of suicide &mdash; state in relation to euthanasia:</P>
    <P>For the caring professions, the dilemma is even more starkly cut. How can doctors, nurses or social workers reduce suicide and rehabilitate self <Col N="1136" /> poisoners and those who harm themselves if beneath the surface they countenance these behaviours. It is not far-fetched to envisage a time in the western world when the cost of maintaining and preserving life will be seen as too great particularly when the individual is no longer productive even though he may have been productive when age and health was on his side.... If doctors enter into the business of assisting suicide then those who see the treatment of the chronically disabled as being an unproductive loss of society's resources may also find means to reward surreptitiously those professionals who put a medical stamp of approval on the dispatch of the disagreeable.</P>
    <P>It cannot be too clearly emphasised that nothing must undermine the sanctity of human life or the general view that suicide is a dreadful offence against nature.</P>
    <P>It must be identified as unjust that those who are successful in suicide can bring about serious consequences for their heirs because they have been guilty of the offence. They can forfeit rights under a trust and there are other side issues under the civil law as a consequence of suicide.</P>
    <P>The global increase in what is seen as attempted suicide or para-suicide &mdash; nonfatal deliberate self-poisoning by prescribed drugs &mdash; has been phenomenal. Deliberate self-poisoning is the second most common cause of admission to British general hospitals.</P>
    <P>Research has shown that para-suicides are different from attempted suicides. They are younger, more often women, and do not intend to commit suicide. These occur during stress periods and are facilitated by alcohol. The motivation seems to be a cry for help which often goes unanswered by a society confused by such behaviour. Most para-suicides never come to the notice of the medical authorities.</P>
    <P>What is the result of current research into the area of suicide? Recently it has been found that the brains of suicide victims have an unusually low level of an <Col N="1137" /> important chemical called serotonin. The lack of this chemical is believed to cause severe depressive illness. There is an expectation in medical circles that in the future would-be suicides will be identified in advance and effectively treated.</P>
    <P>The Bill before us asks Seanad Éireann to take the first step to decriminalise suicide. The House has a unique opportunity to set a headline in law reform in an area crying out for such reform. Professor Tom Fahy, Professor of Psychiatry, University College Galway, has stated in relation to decriminalising suicide.</P>
    <P>To fail to do this, now that the cat is out of the bag, will be to confirm that pagan fears of the suicide's ghost still linger in the minds of the Irish people. Suicide is nothing if it is not a tragedy. It is not a scandal. It is scandalous to regard it so. We should not of course encourage it but it must be decriminalised. Until this is done, we cannot overcome the stigma conferred on families. There is no evidence that decriminalisation stimulates more suicide. On the contrary, it has long been known to psychiatrists that it is a relief to the suicidal to know they are not alone (and that extreme despair is at most a transitory emotion). And is there not something unacceptable about an archaic law which serves no purpose and which is merely a relic of an age when the State used weapons of taboo and magic to control not only the lives but also the deaths of ordinary people.</P>
    <P>The decriminalising of suicide is the prerequisite of a more enlightened understanding of the problem. More resources must be made available for research. Resources must be also made available for counselling the bereaved. Nowadays seven out of ten people will be affected by the suicide of a friend or relation.</P>
    <P>In asking the House to support the Bill we are seeking to remove the aura of criminality from suicide. The churches have begun this process by allowing the bodies of victims to be buried in consecrated ground. In asking for support <Col N="1138" /> for the Bill we are asking for understanding of the anguish of the bereaved who see their loved ones in law branded as criminals. Let us remove this outdated approach to the problem. Sympathy and understanding must be the humane response to the bereaved. We are asking the House to recognise that those who attempt to commit suicide are in need of compassion, understanding, medical treatment and perhaps spiritual advice.</P>
    <P>In asking the House to support the Bill we are seeking to put the debate on this social disease on a new plane. We recommend research into the issue and the development of anti-suicide programmes, greater understanding of the issue and a greater awareness of information on the help available to potential suicide victims. It is time the State came into the 20th century and ended this cruel and uncivilised law.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RayBurke" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Burke) Raphael P. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Burke)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am happy to be present in this House this evening to speak on this important matter, and I wish to thank Senators for giving me the opportunity of putting forward the Government's position in relation to it.</P>
      <P>The death of a person under what I might term ordinary circumstances is a very traumatic event for family and friends but when the death occurs as a result of suicide, the situation becomes even more tragic and difficult to come to terms with.</P>
      <P>People immediately begin to search for a reason and begin to wonder if there were any warning signs that should have picked up. The question on everyone's mind is &ldquo;Could I have prevented this?&rdquo; Some may even take partial blame by entertaining doubts about their lack of care and attention. People who were particularly close to the person in addition to the sense of loss may have very strong feelings of rejection. Feelings of guilt and shame abound.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As time goes on it becomes accepted that there is no point in looking for a cause. The reasons a person takes their own life are complex and varied. There <Col N="1139" /> can be an underlying medical or psychiatric cause but I do not believe that research has produced conclusive results and simplistic explanations are not accurate. It seems to be part and parcel of the human condition.</P>
    <P>The psycho-analytical theories of suicide prove perhaps only what is already obvious, that the processes which lead a man to take his own life are at least as complex and difficult as those by which he continues to live and I use &ldquo;man&rdquo; in the sense of man/woman.</P>
    <P>The tragedy of the death in the case of a suicide is compounded shortly afterwards by the formality of a police investigation and the necessary inquest. At that stage the harsh realities of the criminal law make their appearance and the message is hammered home that suicide above everything else is a serious crime. All this comes at a time when the relatives have to deal with the attitudes of society to the suicide. As a society we have not yet learned how to deal with suicide. There are no cultural guidelines. It has been said that there is a stigma of silence. People may be shunned and cut off from normal social contact because of it.</P>
    <P>To what extent the criminalisation of suicide has a part to play in that process, I do not not know, but it is clear to me that if the crime is abolished, it will represent a start in the social education process to enable us to come to terms with the problem in a more humane way.</P>
    <P>Under our criminal law today, suicide is a felony, an attempt at suicide is a misdemeanour and is punishable with imprisonment. A person who persuades another to commit suicide or to enter into a suicide pact or, who aids another in committing suicide, is guilty of murder.</P>
    <P>Prosecution for attempted suicide have not been taken in recent years. The last such prosecution was in 1967. The view of the prosecuting authorities &mdash; which is one shared by me &mdash; is the people who attempt suicide are in need of sympathy and treatment, not punishment. In the four and a half year period from the beginning of 1987 to the end of this year <Col N="1140" /> the number of suicides recorded is provisionally estimated to be 1,253. I must say I am inclined to share the view of Senator Neville that the official figure is understated relative to the actual figure.</P>
    <P>Why has society decided that suicide is a crime? I suppose the origins of this go back to early times. Religious approaches to suicide were to condemn it absolutely. This, in turn, led to the common law regarding it as self-murder. A number of consequences, which happily are now obsolete, flowed from this, for instance, the law provided for the forfeiture of goods and chattels of the person who committed suicide and there was a denial of a Christian burial, as was referred to by Senator Neville. The confiscation of goods of suicides was abolished by the general abolition of forfeiture of goods for felony by the Forfeiture Act of 1870. The Internments Act, 1882, removed all penalties, except the purely ecclesiastical one.</P>
    <P>With the development of a more enlightened attitude to mental instability and illness, such as schizophrenia, attitudes have changed. For example, how could a person be guilty of self-murder when, almost by definition, they would have to be mentally unstable to proceed with this suicide in the first place? I know that raises another problem because it is recognised that a person in full possession of all his or her mental faculties can quite logically and methodically plan to take their own life in particular circumstances and for particular reasons.</P>
    <P>I think that today we all would agree that it is wholly inappropriate for society to treat suicide as a crime under the law. There are very sound reasons for this and for the abolition of the felony of suicide. Obviously, the suicide is beyond the reach of punishment and second, the legal sanction is not an effective deterrent.</P>
    <P>The only effect of criminalisation is to compound the distress and pain of the bereaved relatives and friends. That is totally undesirable and wrong and it is my intention and that of the Government to remedy the situation as quickly as possible. Indeed, there are proposals going <Col N="1141" /> back to 1967, and shortly before that, to abolish the offence, but unfortunately, they came to nothing.</P>
    <P>While the Government fully agree with the principle of Senator Neville's Private Members' Bill &mdash; I share his motives and intentions &mdash; I have my own proposals in the context of a criminal law Bill, which as well as providing for the abolition of the offence of suicide and making necessary ancillary changes, will also abolish the distinction between felonies and misdemeanours generally in the criminal law.</P>
    <P>It is complex legislation that is nearing completion. I hope to publish it before Christmas. In the context I have outlined &mdash; that I fully accept the principles outlined in the Senator's Bill, that I will be in a position to publish this Bill very shortly, that it will have been drafted with the full benefit of the Attorney General's Office and the parliamentary draftsman, and that it will be more comprehensive in its approach taking into account other items, such as the distinction between felonies and misdemeanours &mdash; I ask the Senator to withdraw the Bill rather than divide the House on it. Otherwise, I would have to say that this side of the House will oppose the Bill in its present form. I would be reluctant to see the House divide on such an issue because it is an issue on which I think all Members would share the views expressed by Senator Neville.</P>
    <P>I hope that in my contribution I have expressed my abhorrence of this throwback to other days, the criminalisation of suicide. I know Senator Neville and his party will welcome the Government Bill in this area when it is published. It would be my wish that the House would not divide on this issue. It would be preferable if the Seanad were to await the Government Bill which is more comprehensive than the legislation we have before us, excellent as it is; I take nothing from it. I fully share the principles behind it as I have already said.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryJackman" hpid="Mrs. Jackman Mrs. Jackman">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Jackman</NameTxt>
      <P>I second this Bill on the decriminalisation of suicide and the <Col N="1142" /> criminal liability for complicity in another's suicide. I would like to compliment Senator Neville for taking the initiative in bringing this Bill before the House. I know this is legislation he has thought about for quite some time and that he was very involved in this process and in drawing up the legislation.</P>
      <P>It is ludicrous that anybody would be charged for attempting suicide. As Senator Neville said, the last prosecution was in 1967, so it is obvious the legislation is not being enforced. Is there a need to have that legislation on the Statute Book? If it were to be enforced, the legislation would be inhuman.</P>
      <P>The United Kingdom was one of the last countries to decriminalise suicide in 1961. A typical picture of that time was PC Brown sitting at the bedside of the person who had attempted suicide, with his notebook in his hand, leading to the charging, prosecution and eventual imprisonment of the individual. That was quite common in Britain up to 1961.</P>
      <P>Going back much further in history, let us look at the Romans and how they dealt with suicide. They considered it an offence against the state and they confiscated the property of the individual. It is interesting that while doing that, the Romans accepted the taking of life in battle. It appears to have been accepted that it was preferable to die by one's own hand in battle rather than to be taken by the enemy. I find it hard to imagine how they were able to cope with conflicting attitudes to the importance of life.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Neville referred to a general study of psychiatric morbidity in County Limerick made by Dr. Peter Kirwan, acting chief psychiatrist in the Mid-Western Health Board area. He did this study in a newly created, community-based, rural psychiatric service. The data was collected from the relevant coroners, for the year, January to December 1989. During that time there were a total of 11 suicides in a population of 60,735, giving a suicide rate of 18.04 per 100,000. The official figure for the same period was 252 deaths due to suicide, that is, 7.1 per 100,000. Those figures were taken from the population figures for electoral areas <Col N="1143" /> in the last census. The question of the validity of Irish suicide rates has been the subject of debate for the past 20 years. Official rates have always been low in relation to other EC countries, although it has been recognised that suicides are under-reported and that official rates differ considerably from the actual rate.</P>
    <P>The figures for Galway for 1978 gave a rate of 13.1 per 100,000 for the county as a whole in contrast to the official rate for the same year of 4.6 per 100,000. An issue, too, is whether there has been a rise in suicide over the past three decades. Another survey undertaken in County Kildare by Dr. Dermot Walsh called &ldquo;The Recent Increase in Reported Suicide in Ireland&rdquo; reports a steady rise in deaths returned as suicide by the coroner. The figure of 71 in 1968 rose to 176 in 1976. Also, an analysis of the vital statistics from 1970 to 1983 show an increase from 1.75 per 100,000 to 7.87 per 100,000. Again, the study, referred to also by Senator Neville, by Kelleher and Daly, &ldquo;Suicide in Cork and Ireland&rdquo;, written in 1990, reported a three-fold increase in suicide in Cork city and county for the period 1980-87. Obviously, the general feeling among many clinicians is that the rate is rising and is considerably in excess of the official figures. The Minister, Deputy Burke, referred to that and has accepted that fact.</P>
    <P>Returning to the County Limerick study &mdash; it was an intensive study, clinically and scientifically carried out &mdash; the coroner responsible was asked to forward the relevant data to Dr. Kirwan for all cases for the year 1989 in which a verdict of suicide would have been returned if this has been open to them. General practitioners were also involved. They provided data on the patients they felt had died as a result of suicide. There was also a report from community psychiatric nurses in the area investigating, independently, all anecdotal reports. The Minister says he does not believe that research has produced conclusive results and simplistic explanations are not accurate. The reason I am quoting in such <Col N="1144" /> detail from Dr. Kirwan's study is that there has been such detailed cross-checking between him and the community, the coroner, and the GPs, that I have no reason &mdash; and others in the field of clinical psychology have no reason &mdash; to doubt the accuracy of his figures. The coroner's data would include a copy of the Garda report, copies of statements of witnesses, a copy of the pathologist's report and a copy of the coroner's verdict. There are cross references between the GP surveys and the community psychiatric nurse's investigations. That speaks for itself. It is very thorough and detailed.</P>
    <P>The statistics are interesting &mdash; between the ages 25-65, average age 45.7, there were ten males, one female; and they gave the details of the suicides &mdash; how they were committed; two by carbon monoxide poisoning, which is car exhaust fumes; five cases of hanging; two cases of gramoxone poisoning; one electrocution and one drowning. I know this is gory but we have to face facts. Senator Neville said that women tend to take drugs rather than the more violent way, but it is very important to see that this happened in a rural area in 1989. It must be realised that these figures are two and a half times higher than the official figure. Therefore, the study adds weight to the view that the official suicide figure greatly underestimates the true picture. It is unlikely that this rural population is unique, in case people may dismiss this report and say the result is peculiar to that area. Obviously further study into the social economic and demographic profiles would be necessary. The official rates for Limerick city in 1985-86 were 14.6 per 100,000; the mean rate for Limerick county, excluding the city borough, was 12 per 100,000. There may not seem a significant difference between them but, taking underreporting into consideration, the real figure may be 27 per 100,000 which would be well above the official figure of 14 per 100,000 for the county as a whole. The typical picture that emerges from rural areas always points to the elderly man in his sixties living alone, perhaps suffering from some element of psychiatric disturbance or <Col N="1145" /> alcoholism, a man disconnected from society but this is no longer the picture. The real picture from the County Limerick survey showed married men, not on the lowest rung of the ladder either socially or economically, with no history of psychiatric illness. These studies are essential to get rid of the myths which may possibly have been prevalent in the past but certainly are not today.</P>
    <P>What are the recommendations? First, I would implore the Minister to set up a small task force to carry out a detailed national survey and establish figures. I would also hope that the task force would isolate the pockets with high suicidal rates and look at areas which are different. They should isolate the factors of causation and initiate a pilot preventative programme.</P>
    <P>Senator Neville referred to the Coroners Act which precludes him from returning a verdict of suicide and the fact that this makes the collection of accurate figures very difficult, because he may record death by misadventure, death through shock or gunshot wound, etc. We have heard of the High Court action in which a surviving spouse took and won a case against the coroner who declared a specific suicidal death.</P>
    <P>I would ask the Minister if Garda sergeants or superintendents fill up form 104 which has the question: is this death due to suicide? There are many other questions but that is the specific one with which I am concerned. Are gardaí given training in Templemore to deal with this specific area? Is the Garda sergeant the best person to make this decision or should there be clinical involvement at that stage? Are there criteria laid down in the Garda training programme in relation to suicide? Like other countries, perhaps there should be a scientific way to fill up that form and deal with the whole question of suicide at that point. I would recommend a new community-based service, particularly where there are new community psychiatric services. This was the reason Dr. Kirwan initiated his survey.</P>
    <P>There should be particular emphasis on help for the bereaved. I would ask <Col N="1146" /> the Minister to set up formal support structures to deal with the very complex area of guilt and anger, particularly for the wife &mdash; since apparently 90 per cent of suicides are male &mdash; and also for the whole family. I know the community, parish, friends and extended family are very supportive but, at that traumatic stage, intense specialist help is needed. Psychiatrists say this has to be handled very sensitively. It is very difficult to sit down and write a probing letter to the spouse of the bereaved. A support structure is essential from the emotional and the financial viewpoints where rights under a trust may be forfeited. I am not sure of the insurance aspect relating to suicide. One never knows the anguish suffered by the wile and children of a suicide victim and I ask that this formal support structure be set up. Another interesting factor seems to emerge which needs further examination in detail. I refer to the domino or ripple effect of a suicide in an area where other suicides emerge later.</P>
    <P>Everything that has been stated both by Senator Neville and myself this evening has shown the need for research, and for a task force to be set up immediatley the Bill is introduced. I ask the Minister to take into consideration the need for that care and professional support, and I ask for financial resources for the health boards to ensure that psychiatrists who want to carry out a very detailed analysis of problems in urban and rural Ireland have the money to do so. In other words, we must not have a Bill we cannot implement.</P>
    <P>Research has been undertaken by pioneers in the field because of their involvement through their commitment to psychiatric services in their areas and in day hospitals in rural and urban areas. This must go beyond the initiative of psychiatrists. It has to be State supported to ensure that we are not to be renowned for suicidal tendencies initiating a feeling of hopelessness among the population who really are crying out for something to be done.</P>
    <Col N="1147" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>Like the Minister, I congratulate Senator Neville on his interest and study in this area. He has been totally committed to this issue and for that I congratulate him. As the Minister said, it is sad enough to have a death from natural cases but death from suicide is very different; grief is intense and friends and family look for reasons. Were there any warning signs? Could it have been stopped? All these questions are in vain at that stage, because the reasons people take their lives are so complex and so varied one cannot figure them out. It is not just the family and friends who suffer but also communities and schools.</P>
      <P>I know it is perhaps incorrect to refer to a specific case but there is one that comes to my mind that was widely published in the local paper. A young leaving certificate student, for no apparent reason, took his own life two days before the examination. He was a popular, well loved, student. He was, indeed, an honours student and an outstanding foot-baller who almost certainly would have had a trial with a Scottish team or an English team very soon. He was buried on the morning of the English examination paper and the school will say that the results in the English examination for that year were the worst in the history of the school for the obvious reason. His football coach, to this day, is as confused and stunned and is a very sad man. Perhaps we should not cite individual cases but it was widely publicised and referred to and it a very sad case.</P>
      <P>We all know of cases of suicide and we cannot understand what triggered them. In my own town on the River Shannon there have been five, six or perhaps more deaths from suicide by drowning, cars driven into the Shannon or people just walking into the river and taking their lives. It is always very sad and it leaves the family and friends in a state of shock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister has confirmed that suicide is a felony. It was regarded at one time as self-murder and it carried with it certain consequences; thankfully, some are no longer in force, such as forfeiture of goods and chattels of the deceased and the denial of a Christian burial. The <Col N="1148" /> Minister has referred to the religious aspects. Attempted suicide, as we know, is a misdemeanour. In this age of entitlement it is inappropriate for society to treat suicide as a crime. Indeed, some 25 years ago there were proposals to abolish the offence but nothing happened.</P>
    <P>I congratulate the Minister for Justice for indicating that he will bring forward not just a Suicide Bill but a Bill that will deal with other aspects of the criminal law, such as punishment of prisoners, penal servitude, hard labour, whipping and so on.</P>
    <P>It is undesirable and wrong that criminalisation should add to the terrible tragedy and loss that accompanies such events, as well as compounding the grief of the family, friends and community. There is the subsequent inquest, the police inquiries, the sad funeral, at a time of great grief for the family and friends of the deceased.</P>
    <P>The Minister has indicated he agrees with the principle of Senator Neville's Bill. Therefore, it would be appropriate for the Senator to withdraw the Bill and await publication of the Government Bill which the Minister has indicated will be ready shortly. That Bill will deal with other matters relating to the abolition of suicide which are not covered in Senator Neville's Bill. Obviously that would be preferable, but it is a matter for the other side of the House. It is their Private Members' Bill, but if the Senator proceeds with it we, on this side of the House, will oppose it in view of the explanation given by the Minister.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>May I compliment Senator Neville on bringing in this Bill, on the research which he has obviously put into it and on the humanity and the feeling for people which was evident in everything he said this evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Bill has already received considerable attention outside the House. There have been a number of radio programmes, discussions and newspaper articles. That is certainly all to the good, even if this Bill and this debate achieve nothing more than that. It will have done a public service in that regard because <Col N="1149" /> suicide is one of the great untouchables, one of the great subjects that people do not talk about openly. It is certainly true of myself, and probably true of most people of my generation, that we find it very difficult to talk frankly about suicide. We have tended to regard suicide in a certain way and this has inhibited proper public discussion on the subject.</P>
    <P>Senator Neville made the point that there are researches in train which may very well produce drugs and if potential suicides can be identified in time the drugs may well be able to supply the chemical balance or redress the imbalance which may be a cause of suicide. If this debate focuses public attention on the question, if it encourages universities, medical schools and departments of psychiatry to undertake more research into the problem, if it dispels some of the myths that have surrounded the subject of suicide over the years, then this debate will have been worth while. I compliment Senator Neville on the campaign he has waged for some months, first to get his own party to agree to take this as a Private Members' Bill and then bringing it before the House this evening.</P>
    <P>I listened very carefully to the Minister and certainly my party will study what he had to say very carefully. His contribution was very humane, rational, sane and understanding and was impressive. If we go ahead and push this Bill to a vote it will not be because we have not taken into account what he said or that we, in any way, doubt his bona fides or his own very obvious compassion on this matter. My first instinctive reaction is that we will press ahead with this Bill for a number of reasons.</P>
    <P>Although this case may be different, promises of legislation in this House cannot always be fully depended upon, for reasons which may not depend on the person who makes them. We have seen, especially in times of political turmoil, how slowly legislation makes its way through both Houses. I mentioned today on the Order of Business how little legislation we have seen in this current session and there has been little legislation in the other House. If this Bill, which has <Col N="1150" /> already been long in gestation, has to take its place in the parliamentary queue we could very easily find, this time next year, that the Bill is still not on the Statute Book. We may well have elections in the meantime. We could have a change of Minister and have a Minister less committed. All of these things could happen, although they may not. It is not easy for an Opposition party to accept the promise of a Bill to subsume this short simple Bill, without at least giving it some consideration.</P>
    <P>I am also reluctant to withdraw the Bill at this stage because of a principle on which any party in Opposition feels very strongly, namely, the principle of Private Members' Bills being introduced and going as far as they possibly can, the principle that as far as possible Opposition Members should have the right to initiate and, hopefully, to enact legislation. For too long our political process has seen the exclusive domination of the Executive as far as legislation is concerned. This is a view which was expressed very strongly, as the Leader of the House well knows, in the recent debate on the reform of the Seanad and supported by all parties.</P>
    <P>A very important principle is being made with the introduction of this Bill this evening. I believe it is now almost 30 years since a Private Members Bill had a Second Stage reading in the Seanad. I may be wrong on that, but that is my belief. It would be wrong on our part, therefore, not to go as far as we can under the rules with this Bill.</P>
    <P>In speaking for the rights of Private Members' legislation, I would like to quote an authority whom I am sure is dear to the heart of the Minister and to whose utterances he listens very carefully. I refer, of course, to the chairman of the Progressive Democrats, Mr. Michael McDowell, the leader in exile, who in <i>The Sunday Independent</i> last Sunday under the heading of &ldquo;That Strange Species up in the Dáil&rdquo; stated:</P>
    <P>My experience since 1987 suggests <Col N="1151" /> that the executive thinks of every stratagem to obstruct and prevent the passage of Private Members legislation. It is easy to &ldquo;put down&rdquo; an Opposition Bill by pointing out a technical defect and deriding the measures as flawed.</P>
    <P>&mdash;&mdash;which the Minister did not do this evening&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>The bitter fruits of that policy of repressing legislators are to be found in our abject record as reformers of the law. Indeed the fact that Private Members stand so little chance of proposing changes in our laws makes for a situation in which they are little interested in the legislative process itself. In this context I remember&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>&mdash;&mdash;others might not remember it quite so well&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>&mdash;&mdash;that it was only because the Progressive Democrats insisted that Alan Shatter's two Bills on marriage breakdown and foreign adoptions were not voted down in the Dáil.</P>
    <P>How could the Minister refuse an authority like that on a subject like that? However, I make the point seriously that the right to introduce a Private Members' Bill is a very vital part of the small armoury open to the Opposition politician. We should make the point that not all legislation has to come from or go through the Government. It would be a good thing if Bills of this kind upon which there is a wide range of agreement &mdash; in fact nobody in the House disagrees with the principle or the contests of the Bill &mdash; could be seen to come from a House of Parliament, from politicians, not from the Minister, the Department, or the Civil Service, but from the ordinary politicians.</P>
    <P>If there are flaws in this Bill, if there are defects, if it does not go far enough, there is nothing to stop it having a full Committee Stage debate here, then going to the Dáil, where it will also have a Second Stage and Committee Stage debate. It is a simple Bill and there is nothing to prevent it emerging at the end <Col N="1152" /> of the process as a politicians Bill, a Bill which came from the ordinary Members as an answer to a specific problem. This Bill could be through this House in a matter of days and it could also be through the Dáil in a matter of days. There would be, I think, equal agreement there. It would redound to the credit of politicians generally if this were to happen.</P>
    <P>The Minister knows, and we all know, the criticism which is being levelled at politicians at present, that we are merely voting fodder, we merely rubber stamp the acts of the Cabinet or of the civil servants, and so forth. At a time when more of our power will probably be ceded to European institutions, anybody who values these institutions would want to fight for our rights, for a greater role for Members of both Houses of the Oireachtas and I can see no better way to establish such a sense of identity and purpose than a greater role in private legislation, especially a Bill which is non-contentious, is designed to meet a specific anomaly in the law, and which could go through both Houses in a short time. If it needs to be improved, this could be done without any great difficulty. That is why I believe it is important that we do go through the full process with this Bill. The one difficulty that might have been in this Bill, that is, the possibility that euthanasia might become legal has been specifically dealt with by Senator Neville.</P>
    <P>I may have been slightly mischievous in quoting the chairman of the Progressive Democrats, although on this occasion I do not disagree with him but the point he makes is a fair one. However, for all the reasons I have given, perhaps the Minister would change his mind on this Bill. If it goes through, as I believe it will, unopposed and the Minister brings in his Bill later, this Bill will be subsumed into it after a very short debate in the Dáil and Seanad. The Minister's Bill might not be introduced for a year or longer, and meanwhile the stigma of criminalising suicide remains. Senator Fallon spoke with great sincerity and obvious knowledge of the situation in his home town and the great distress and despair <Col N="1153" /> caused by suicides. Everyone of us could echo the experiences he recounted.</P>
    <P>As I said at the outset, this Bill goes only a small way; it is not a cure for anything. It will have done a great deal of good &mdash; and again I commend the Senator who introduced the Bill &mdash; simply by focusing attention, by getting public debate going, whether it be on the Marian Finucane programme, the Gay Byrne programme or in the newspapers, by allowing people to come outside their fears, their inhibitions and talk about this question. It will have done great good if it encourages companies to invest money in research into the causes and the possibilities of preventing suicide and if it helps people to focus attention on the support services needed for those who are bereaved by suicide. If it does all those things, and even if it goes no further, it will have done a signal public service.</P>
    <P>If the Minister accepts this Bill in the spirit in which it is brought forward here tonight, if he accepts it as a small Bill, worth while in itself, which could have fairly immediate effect, if he accepts it as an indication that Private Members, Opposition Members, ordinary Members, have a positive legislative function, however limited, in the Houses of the Oireachtas, and if a year or six months from now it is subsumed into his new legislation, then so be it. If the Minister accepts the Bill in that way this evening, it would be worth while and he will have shown himself as the open and reforming Minister we all believe he is.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Mr. Mullooly Mr. Mullooly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mullooly</NameTxt>
      <P>Like most public representatives, I attend a good number of funerals. Over the years I have come across some exceptionally sad and tragic bereavements. However, I have to say that the saddest and most tragic bereavements of all were those in which there was some reason to believe the deceased had a hand in his or her own death. The pain and suffering caused by suicide to the family and relatives, and indeed to the friends and acquaintances, of the victim are invariably deeper and more traumatic than where death, no matter <Col N="1154" /> how sudden, results from any other cause. The fact that suicide is a criminal offence adds to this trauma, as does the ensuing police investigation and inquest. All these factors have contributed to a perception of suicide as an act to which a particular stigma attaches. Until comparatively recent times someone who took his or her own life was denied a church burial. Thankfully, this is no longer the case, but even though it is not, I agree with the Minister when he stated that as a society we have not yet learned how to deal with suicide.</P>
      <P>In recent times there has been a growing body of public opinion that suicide o attempted suicide should no longer be a criminal offence. I was pleased to hea the Minister state that he now accepts this case and that he proposes to introduce legislation very soon to amend the law in this regard. I would like to join with the Minister and Senator Fallon in complimenting Senator Neville on his initiative in bringing forward this Private Members' Bill dealing with this matter. It is also worth remembering that, although suicide is a criminal offence at present, prosecution in this area are extremely rare. Many attempted suicides do not come to the notice of the Garda. I was pleased to note that the Minister stated that in the case of those that do, the attitude is taken that people who attempt suicide are in need of sympathy and treatment rather than punishment.</P>
      <P>Experience in other countries has shown that change in the legal status of suicide has had no adverse influence on the suicide rate. I believe, however, that it should continue to be a very serious offence to incite or assist another person to commit suicide. Indeed, I would consider that the maximum term of imprisonment which is proposed for this offence in section 2 should be substantially greater than ten years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I always understood that the suicide statistics which are available do not represent accurately the true situation and I believe most people will accept this as a fact. According to the figures in the official statistics in 1990 there were 311 self-inflicted deaths officially recorded in <Col N="1155" /> this country. Most people would agree that this figure seriously underestimates the true extent of death by suicide. It is also, regrettably, an accepted fact that suicide is on the increase, especially among young people. It is difficult, if not impossible, for the ordinary lay person to imagine the type of stress or pressure that drives a person to suicide and yet in many cases this stress or pressure does not manifest itself beforehand even to people very close to the suicide victim. This is one of the reasons in the case of such bereavement why there can be so much recrimination as the people left behind blame themselves for not having seen in advance the warning signs which they feel must have been there.</P>
    <P>I would like to pay a tribute to the self-help or support groups for bereaved persons which have been established in many parts of the country. Such groups can help to ease very considerably the sense of pain and loss felt by bereaved persons and they can be particularly helpful in the case of persons bereaved by suicide. I would also like to join in the tribute paid by Senator Neville to the Samaritans for the great counselling service they provide and which I am sure has helped very many people who may have been contemplating suicide to come to terms with the problems and pressures they experienced.</P>
    <P>I support the concept that suicide should cease to be a crime, but I am prepared to wait for the Bill which has been promised by the Minister. Therefore, I hope the Senators on the other side of the House will accede to the request of the Minister to withdraw the Bill which they have brought before the House since the Bill the Minister has promised will be a more comprehensive reforming measure than that which is before us this evening.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to do as the leader of my party in this House did, namely, to strike the Minister with a quote from one of his Coalition colleagues. I thought that was particularly unfair to a Minister who is known to <Col N="1156" /> be a great lover and supporter of his Coalition colleagues. I am sorry that the Minister of State present does not understand that because he has only just joined us in the House.</P>
      <P>I welcome this Bill and I am glad we have the support of a prominent member of the Progressive Democrats. While Senator Neville's introduction to this Bill was enlightened and forward looking, I have to say I thought the Minister's reply was very disappointing. I say that in the full knowledge that I believe &mdash; and I am on record as having said it &mdash; that the Minister for Justice has a fine record as a reforming Minister for Justice particularly in the Bills he has brought before this House in the past two years. He very cleverly dispensed with his other portfolio and handed it on as a poisoned chalice to another Minister. He now holds with a great degree of distinction the portfolio of Justice and he has a fine record of bringing to this House, reforming legislation of which he can be proud.</P>
      <P>Consequently, I am sorry the Minister did not accept this Bill in its entirety or in its principle, because it was the same Minister who brought forward in this House the Criminal Justice Bill to abolish hanging. It was the same Minister who gave us a pledge in this House some time ago that it was his intention to bring forward legislation to decriminalise homosexuality and it was the same Minister who also amended the Prohibition of Incitement to Hatred Bill in this House in a way which his predecessor refused to do. His willingness to accept liberal reforming amendments to legislation was in marked contrast to his predecessor. With that history in mind it was doubly disappointing to read the Minister's response to this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Manning said, quite rightly, that the response from this side of the House will be to study the Minister's reply. That will not be a particularly arduous task, because it is only five pages long in very large print, double spaced. It was a very disappointing reply in that context, because the Minister provided very few figures, very little analysis, very little thinking behind the enlightened view <Col N="1157" /> which he claims to have. It is even more disappointing when he says he accepts the principle of this Bill but goes on to say that work has been going on on a similar Bill since 1967. I do not know what has been going on and I do not know what studies have been going on, but after 24 years we have five pages. That is not good enough. The Minister has disappointed this House by coming in and by parading the virtue of accepting the principle of the Bill and then providing no analysis of the Bill and no support for what he has to say.</P>
    <P>I do not accept the assurance of the Minister that he intends to introduce legislation of this sort shortly. The disappointing aspect of the Minister's reply is that it is short of a full commitment. If he said that similar legislation would be introduced by February or March or some specific date next year, I would certainly accept the Minister's bona fides, but the fact that after 24 years of work he comes into us and he says &ldquo;I will produce a similar Bill very shortly&rdquo; is not acceptable, because, frankly, I do not fully believe him. We had a promise from the Minister that the Bill on homosexual law reform would be before this House before the end of this year but that promise has sunk without trace. I know and the rest of the House knows, that the Minister has particular problems within his party about that particular reforming legislation and that it is not going to see the light of day before this Chistmas. That is disappointing, and it is in that light that we have to consider the pledge he made on this Bill.</P>
    <P>Like the Minister, I would be very loath to see the House divide on an issue like suicide. It is not the sort of issue we should divide on. The Minister had an option which he did not take and it is an option which Governments are, unfortunately, very reluctant to take and very rarely take. He could have given the kudos to the party introducing this Bill and said he accepted it in principle but that there were faults in it and, as Senator Manning so rightly said, he could have amended it on Committee Stage either here or in the Dáil, but he did not. He <Col N="1158" /> said the principle was fine but that there were certain complications which he did not go into&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>And that the Bill was fine.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;but that he would shortly introduce his own Bill which would be about the same thing. That is unacceptable; it is insulting not only to those who framed this Bill but to this House. While I commend the Government for allowing the Bill to be published and discussed, I think they have fallen at the first fence by not allowing it to be passed. It is, unfortunately, a political decision on behalf of the Government not to allow this to go through. If their concern was as genuine as they make out, if there was a genuine worry about the implications of suicide, they would accept the Bill and amend it where they felt it was lacking. I do not believe that is their opinion. I believe that, in reality, they have taken the attitude that this Bill is all right but there is no way they are going to let an Opposition Bill through the Seanad. That is insulting to this House because this Bill was non-contentious politically in its introduction. There was absolutely no intention of embarrassing the Government or anybody else. If the Government want to oppose this Bill so be it, but I think it is a pity; I think it is churlish and I think it is petty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to say a few words about suicide because that is the subject of the Bill. There seems to be such a wide consensus about suicide in this House that I wonder why this Bill was not introduced sooner. Nobody wants to be seen to oppose it, but one or two people want to have an excuse to oppose it. I suppose the truth is that it is a rather thornier and more difficult subject to approach than many of us really believed. As Senator Manning said, suicide is really a taboo. It is still a taboo in Irish society and in society outside Ireland. It is something which is preferably swept under the carpet. It is something you do not mention if you can avoid it, to the relatives of those affected <Col N="1159" /> by suicide. The reason for that, I suppose, rests not in the State's view of suicide but the churches' view of suicide. The churches of all denominations &mdash; the Roman Catholic Church, the Church of Ireland, etc. find suicide very awkward to deal with, but it is something of which they know they have to disapprove. They also take the attitude that it is wrong, but against which they can take no sanctions.</P>
    <P>The appalling situation that we find ourselves in as a Government, a Parliament and a State is that we have taken this church attitude to absurd extremes by enacting into law the preaching of all churches, then making suicide criminalised and imposing a penalty for it. The absurdity of this Bill and this subject is that you obviously cannot impose a penalty for suicide. One cannot punish a dead person. It is very simple and the law looks very stupid imposing such a penalty, and imposing such a penalty for attempted suicide is quite unacceptable; and because, as the Minister said, it is 24 years since any prosecution was taken. All we are doing is legitimising something which is already acceptable, and yet the Minister will not accept the Bill.</P>
    <P>There is no conflict among all the parties in this House about whether criminalising suicide is a deterrent or not. It is very difficult to prove, but I do not believe anybody on any side of the House believes that the fact that you could be punished for attempted suicide is going to deter anybody in the anguished mental state people get into when they are contemplating suicide. It is not a deterrent. The reasons behind this Bill are unanimously agreed and the only thing we are disagreeing about is the minor detail, which is the reason apparently that the Government want to divide the House.</P>
    <P>I fully support what Senator Neville said about complicity. Obviously, complicity is a totally different crime and a different issue. What we are establishing here, whether we like it or not, is that, as far as the State is concerned, it is not wrong for people to take their own lives &mdash; in other words, that it is your own <Col N="1160" /> decision and it is not something in which the State has to interfere. That is something very new. In fact, it is quite revolutionary if we are going to establish it in statute.</P>
    <P>We are also establishing that complicity in suicide is complicity to murder. That is right. That is the civilised attitude we must take, and which is taken internationally. That distinction is very important and it is one I know is accepted by the Government &mdash; your life is your own to take but you cannot interfere with the life of anybody else or be an accomplice in their taking their own lives.</P>
    <P>Finally, I would like to banish the ghost of euthanasia which was raised by various commentators. This Bill has nothing to do with euthanasia and has nothing in common with it. It is not a Bill about euthanasia, nor does it tackle the subject. What this Bill recognises more than anything else is that suicide is an appalling mental condition. It is a medical condition, it is not in any way a criminal condition.</P>
    <P>While I welcome the Bill and I welcome this recognition from the Government side, I deeply regret that the Minister and the Government have seen fit to play politics with this Bill by not accepting it. This Bill is non-contentious and non-partisan politically, and is the type of Bill the Seanad should debate, accept and pass without any difficulties or opposition. It is a great pity the Government have not given us the opportunity to set a precedent for Private Members Bills of a non-party nature getting through this House.</P>
    <P>I commend the Bill to the House and congratulte Senator Neville for introducing it.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 28 November 1991.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>