<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Thu" Date="18" Month="Aug" Year="1921" Vol="S" No="3" DateIrish="" DateEnglish="" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="9">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="9" /> The Dáil assembled at 11.40 a.m. in the Oak Room, Mansion House, Dublin.</P>
    <P>SEÁN T. Ó CEALLAIGH, Leas-Cheann Comhairle,¹ in the absence of the Ceann Comhairle, took the Chair.</P>
    <P>1. Seán S. Ó Ceallaigh was elected Leas-Cheann Comhairle, 16 August, 1921 and resigned 26 August, 1921. Brian O'Higgins succeeded him in that office.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ROLLA" RHead="">
    <Title>ROLLA</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="D. Ó H ÉIGEARTAIGH D. Ó H ÉIGEARTAIGH">
      <NameTxt>AN RÚNAIDHE, D. Ó H ÉIGEARTAIGH</NameTxt>
      <P>, called the roll and the following members were present:&mdash;²</P>
      <P>2. No roll was included with the minutes.  The roll called at the public session of 16 August, 1921 is printed in Appendix 19.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfEoinMacNeill" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Eoin MacNeill">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>³ said the first business was to regulate the work and the hour they would adjourn for lunch and reassemble in the evening.  The President has suggested that tomorrow would be a free day as there was a good deal of Committee work to be done.</P>
      <P>3. Eoin Mac Neill held the office of Ceann Comhairle throughout the period covered in this volume.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOCeallaigh" hpid="SEÁN T. Ó CEALLAIGH SEÁN T. Ó CEALLAIGH">
      <NameTxt>SEÁN T. Ó CEALLAIGH</NameTxt>
      <P>proposed the Dáil would adjourn at 2 p.m. for lunch and reassemble at 4 p.m.&mdash;Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="TUARASGBHÁIL Ó'N AIRE UM GHNÓTHAÍ" RHead="COIGCRÍCHE - Discussion of Report">
    <Title>TUARASGBHÁIL Ó'N AIRE UM GHNÓTHAÍ COIGCRÍCHE - Discussion of Report</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="DEPUTY GAVAN DUFFY DEPUTY GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>asked who were the individual persons who saw the correspondence sent by their political correspondents abroad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="THE PRESIDENT THE PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>THE PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>(4) replied that he saw most of it except what was of a routine nature.  It went primarily through Mr. Brennan, the Under-Secretary for Foreign Affairs, to the staff in charge.</P>
      <P>4. Eamon de Valera.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesJosephWalsh" hpid="DEPUTY J.J. WALSH (Cork) DEPUTY J.J. WALSH (Cork)">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY J.J. WALSH</NameTxt>
      <P>(Cork) in moving the adoption of the report congratulated the Minister in charge on the excellence of the report.  He wished to draw attention to two matters, one on the advisability of a big propaganda in England by means of placards showing the atrocities committed here by English troops and the enormous expenditure the campaign was costing England.  In the second matter he suggested a more active campaign against enemy property in America which he believed would expedite their liberation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRiceKent" hpid="DEPUTY D. KENT (East Cork) DEPUTY D. KENT (East Cork)">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY D. KENT</NameTxt>
      <P>(East Cork) in seconding the adoption of the report stated he altogether disagreed with Mr. Walsh's views of a more active campaign in America.  Such action would, in his opinion, alienate all American sympathy from them. He maintained they should get all the sympathy possible from foreign countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexMcCabe" hpid="DEPUTY A. MACCABE DEPUTY A. MACCABE">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY A. MACCABE</NameTxt>
      <P>in supporting the motion asked if there was any further information about the Irish Race Conference than what was given in the report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="DEPUTY SEÁN MILROY DEPUTY SEÁN MILROY">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY SEÁN MILROY</NameTxt>
      <P>asked who was to be in charge of Irish interests in America during Mr. Boland's absence.  He would like to get an assurance that the person in charge would prevent any impression getting abroad that they were animated with hostility against America.  Any action that would alienate American sympathy would be a great mistake.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="10" />
    <Speaker pid="LaurenceRobbins" hpid="DEPUTY LORCAN ROBBINS DEPUTY LORCAN ROBBINS">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY LORCAN ROBBINS</NameTxt>
      <P>said he too was in disagreement with the views expressed by Deputy Walsh.  America was England's biggest trading customer and he suggested our friends in America and all other anti-English sections should be educated up to an economic boycott of England.  That would be a weapon of immense value to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="DEPUTY SEÁN MACENTEE DEPUTY SEÁN MACENTEE">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY SEÁN MACENTEE</NameTxt>
      <P>enquired as to who had the selection of the foreign envoys of the Republic.  He thought in a matter of that kind there should be some Committee of Appointments to examine the records and credentials and qualifications of candidates for important posts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamFPStockle" hpid="PROFESSOR STOCKLEY PROFESSOR STOCKLEY">
      <NameTxt>PROFESSOR STOCKLEY</NameTxt>
      <P>pointed out that from recent correspondence he had seen from Germany the impression was growing there that after all England was her friend and that she would get more justice from England than from any other country.  He suggested that they should support, if possible, the giving of information to Germany.  English propaganda and power in Germany was very strong.  He gave an instance of how an article on the Irish situation written in German at the request of the editor of a very important magazine in Germany would not be published when received by the editor for fear of offending England.  He also related that quite recently Professor O'Rahilly of Cork University was asked to give some corrections of a German encyclopedia.  He handed the offer to him (Professor Stockley) and he found that the encyclopedia gave a most distorted description of affairs in Ireland, picturing Sinn Féiners as a wild and rough lot whom no decent neighbouring people could put up with.  Even the other day, he said, friends of his who were travelling in Germany found that the people there had no idea of the real true facts in regard to Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KathleenClarke" hpid="MRS. CLARKE MRS. CLARKE">
      <NameTxt>MRS. CLARKE</NameTxt>
      <P>strongly disagreed with Deputy Walsh's suggestions regarding action in America.  She said American sympathy had meant more than meetings and money.  It had resulted in the defeat of the League of Nations.  If that League were carried through their position would have been a bad one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPColivet" hpid="DEPUTY M.P. COLLIVET DEPUTY M.P. COLLIVET">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY M.P. COLLIVET</NameTxt>
      <P>suggested with regard to Germany that writers be encouraged to come here and write up Ireland for the information of their own country.  Their favourable position in France was due to two sources, Irishmen who went to France and French writers who came to Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMcGuinness" hpid="DEPUTY JOSEPH MCGUINNESS DEPUTY JOSEPH MCGUINNESS">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY JOSEPH MCGUINNESS</NameTxt>
      <P>asked had the President anything to add to Mr. H. Boland's report that would make it clear to them how they stood with regard to the American Government.  If they knew exactly what were the possibilities of recognition of the Irish Republic in America it would have great bearing on the decision they would have to make on the peace question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamdeRoiste" hpid="LIAM DE RÓISTE LIAM DE RÓISTE">
      <NameTxt>LIAM DE RÓISTE</NameTxt>
      <P>remarked that there was no reference in the report to Egypt or India.  Did the Ministry discuss that question?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="DEPUTY GAVAN DUFFY DEPUTY GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>declared he had not a good word to say for the report. It was vague and misleading.  It might have been justifiable as a propagandist report&mdash; that was a matter for the House, but he considered the members should have a little inside knowledge of the actual facts. Their great difficulty abroad was that their communication was as bad as bad could be. If an urgent communication was sent from a continental city to Dublin, the methods of transmission were so slow that they could not be certain of an answer within any specified time.  It sometimes took from one to two months.  That was a matter in which improvement was very urgent. England opposed their propaganda everywhere abroad with all her power.  She had collared all the important Press agencies which were run in conjunction with Jews and Freemasons from London.  In Norway she threatened economic reprisals if the Government there did not shut up the writer of a review who had published articles in favour of Sinn Féin.  In Spain during the inquest on the late Lord Mayor MacCurtain the British Embassy issued an official statement to the press saying this man was murdered by the extremists of his own party who had also sworn to murder Lloyd George and the prominent members of the British Cabinet.  In Italy also word was given officially to the Press that they were not to speak of Ireland.  He said he mentioned these matters to show the Members that the state of affairs abroad <Col N="11" /> was not as rosy as pictured by the report.</P>
      <P>He submitted very strongly that part of any terms they would come to with England should be that Ireland had separate representation abroad.</P>
      <P>He alluded to his expulsion from France and protested against the sending of a friendly message by the President to France recently.  He considered the French Government should first atone for the insult of having compelled their envoy to leave the country.</P>
      <P>They could expect no help from France because on the one hand she was obsessed with the fear of Germany coming to attack her again in which case England, she thought, was the only country she could look to for assistance and on the other hand the country was in an acute stage of bankruptcy.</P>
      <P>The position of their envoys abroad was a very difficult one as they alleged to represent a government which was not recognised by foreigners.  Most of the people who mattered were afraid to be seen with them.  There was also another objection; diplomatic work of that kind cost a lot of money and it was questionable if they got their money's worth.  He thought it essential in future to concentrate on having press representatives rather than diplomatic envoys abroad who would supply the press and foreign writers with matter.  Press work was the work that told.</P>
      <P>Another matter he would like to mention, he said, in the case of certain Latin countries a woman who is serious and talks business is regarded as a disagreeable woman; therefore if a woman is head of affairs in any of these countries they could not get the best results for expenditure.</P>
      <P>Everyone who had been abroad would tell them that what won publicity and sympathy abroad was the enormous interest created by the military events here at home.  The deeds of daring done here had enormous effect on the Continent. People had said to him abroad that those at home were fighting a hopeless cause but they admired them, and later on when he met the same people their whole attitude was changed when they saw the things that were done here, and that was why in countries sympathetic to them it was recognised that the Irish Republic was on top.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesJosephWalsh" hpid="DEPUTY J.J. WALSH DEPUTY J.J. WALSH">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY J.J. WALSH</NameTxt>
      <P>said he had assumed the report was correct as to the position abroad.  He anticipated that his proposal re America would be turned down as it was a bit wide.  He was satisfied that they were not getting the full value of the force of their 20 millions of kith and kin in America.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonalOCallaghan" hpid="DEPUTY DONAL O'CALLAGHAN DEPUTY DONAL O'CALLAGHAN">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY DONAL O'CALLAGHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>pointed out that it was all a myth talking about 20 millions of their people in America.  There never was more than half a million in the Irish movement in America.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamJMellows" hpid="DEPUTY LIAM MELLOWES DEPUTY LIAM MELLOWES">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY LIAM MELLOWES</NameTxt>
      <P>said he was afraid many of the Teachtaí, like Deputy J.J. Walsh, were under a grave illusion regarding America.  When considering this question they had to take into account the fact that they would only get from America value for what they were prepared to put into it themselves.  They could not expect the Irish in America to be better than the Irish at home.  It was only during the last eighteen months that they were getting in America the repercussion of the events of Easter Week.  When they spoke of the Irish in America they had to consider two classes: (1) those who were American citizens and (2) those who were not.  These latter were aliens and did not count a single iota except so far as they may be representative of this country.  The first class were powerful only as American citizens and Deputy J.J. Walsh's suggestions were all sheer nonsense.  It was nice to talk of 20 million Irish but it was not true.  There might be 20 million descendants of Irish blood but they were Irish of such a kind that they did not recognise it themselves.  As far as America was concerned, they had an Irish movement there to-day as the direct result of events in Ireland.  They had in America to-day an Irish movement for the first time for a generation and as long as the fight was kept up at home so long would they get support from the U.S.A.  They could not expect more from America than from their own people at home.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOCeallaigh" hpid="SEÁN T. Ó CEALLAIGH SEÁN T. Ó CEALLAIGH">
      <NameTxt>SEÁN T. Ó CEALLAIGH</NameTxt>
      <P>stated that as Deputy Gavan Duffy had given the Dáil such an excellent review of the position on the Continent he himself need not say very much.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It was his opinion that their position abroad to-day was vastly superior to what it was two and a half years ago when the <Col N="12" /> first representative went out.  Then in France everyone was hostile to Ireland. Now things had changed and everyone was interested in Ireland and in all the papers they had special correspondents for Irish news.  The whole basis of the movement was the work at home.  It gave them something to talk and write about.  However, it was not likely that France of her own volition would recognise the Irish Republic. That was absolutely out of the question. She was deep in debt to England and other countries and was seized with the fear that Germany would come back.</P>
    <P>With regard to the other States in Europe, England was master of the political situation and all other countries had to act on her beck and call.  Germany's policy was to divide France and England, and she was succeeding.  He maintained in a recent report, that if America could be induced to say that she would, if other countries could be got to join her, give a kind of conditional consent to recognition of the Irish Republic, that perhaps France and Italy would recognise the Irish Republic if America took the lead.  But they would not stand out on their own against England and recognise it.  Italy was almost in a similar position to France and the people were sympathetic to Ireland.</P>
    <P>All the smaller countries were with Ireland; they could not help financially, but their sympathy was very valuable.  Yesterday Mr. Childers gave them a resumé of a number of foreign and continental papers and they saw the number which were hostile was very small.  He believed none were hostile save one directly subsidised by the British government.  The day before he left Paris the Chairman of the Turkish Foreign Affairs Commission called to see him and asked him to convey to President de Valera and the members of the new Dáil the cordial felicitations of his Parliament and he told him he was directed to convey this message to him.  The representative of Poland also called and asked that he would convey a similar message here to this Parliament.  From Egypt also the President had a telegram the other day.  In India they had also the same story.  They were copying Irish methods and utilising Irish propaganda for inspiring their own men.</P>
    <P>The men who had been sent abroad had succeeded in changing the whole views of the continent of Europe on Ireland.  Now there was not a country nor province nor people anywhere that were not deeply interested in Ireland.  One instance of that was the extraordinary interest displayed in the noble sacrifice made by the late Lord Mayor MacSwiney.  The French papers, even the most hostile of them, were full of it from day to day, and after his death the Irish Office was inundated with callers and pressmen.  All were struck to the foundations of their hearts by the magnificence of the sacrifice.  He knew, he said, the expense of all this work was great and he did not know whether it was all justified or not, but looking back on what had been accomplished he thought every penny they had spent had turned out well.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamFPStockle" hpid="PROFESSOR STOCKLEY PROFESSOR STOCKLEY">
      <NameTxt>PROFESSOR STOCKLEY</NameTxt>
      <P>asked why Deputy S.T. Ó Ceallaigh thought the ruling classes in America were more likely to be more friendly in [<i>recte</i> to] Ireland than say French or other European governments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOCeallaigh" hpid="SEÁN T. Ó CEALLAIGH SEÁN T. Ó CEALLAIGH">
      <NameTxt>SEÁN T. Ó CEALLAIGH</NameTxt>
      <P>said he believed the American government to-day was not friendly to Ireland.  But there was a powerful movement in favour of Ireland which might yet be able to force the government there to do by fear what it would not do by choice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="THE PRESIDENT THE PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>THE PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>said as he had been in close touch with this department he would answer the questions.  With respect to the complaint that the report was propagandist, he said the report was based on their representatives' reports from abroad. If there was anything misleading in it, it was their own fault.  The actual fact was that no nation would recognise the Irish Republic until she wanted to go [to] war with England.  The report was not meant to deceive anyone.</P>
      <P>With regard to the appointment of envoys abroad they were, he said, nominated by the Minister in charge and ratified by the Cabinet.</P>
      <P>The practice about the staffs engaged was that they were chosen by the heads of the departments.  If they wanted to set up a Civil Service Commission to regulate employment of staffs it would be for the House to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>They recognised their communications were very faulty but to overcome that properly would cost such an amount of money that they would have to curtail their essential work.  They contemplated an actual service of couriers but the outlay <Col N="13" /> would be too heavy.  They were going to meet the foreign representatives tomorrow and see what their exact needs are and how they could meet them.  They had done everything they could to secure P.... O'B....¹ services but they had not succeeded so far.</P>
    <P>1. The shorthand notes do not give the full name.</P>
    <P>With regard to the world conference, the lady who organised Canada, Australia, and New Zealand was directed to come to Paris and set up an office there that would serve as a centre from which they could work this conference.  In reference to America, he was glad to see the idea of the 20 millions hit on the head.  He would like them to remember that the people of German blood in America went out as American citizens to fight against Germany and tomorrow if there was a war against Ireland those citizens of Irish blood would go out to fight against Ireland.  When he went to America, the Friends of Irish Freedom had only a membership of 20,000. At present the new organisation had, they were told, half a million.  The Irish were very influential in Irish centres like Boston in local or municipal politics but they had no influence in national politics.  He believed if the most influential Catholic of Irish blood went forward for the Presidency in America he would not have the slightest chance of being chosen.  If tomorrow any of the Deputies here went to America, became a citizen of it and had the same love for the old country as they had now and it so happened was elected President, he believed that man would refuse to recognise the Irish Republic.  He himself would refuse to recognise it, if it could be imagined that he was elected President of the United States, because the American people would not back him and would turn him down at once if he dared to do it.  Nations were more selfish than individuals and they could not expect more from another nation than they would do themselves.  The League of Nations question enabled Ireland to be brought into international politics as the matter happened to be an American one as well as an Irish issue, and they got in.  The Friends of Irish Freedom at the time told him if the League of Nations would mean the freedom of Ireland they would not have gone into it. I told them they had every right to talk as Americans but not to dictate to Ireland what she should do when it was an Irish matter.  My attitude simply was that Ireland's foreign policy was to be directed by those at home and that if help was to be given to Ireland it was to be help that would be sanctioned here.  He was trying to make it impossible for individuals in America to use the name of Ireland for any purpose but the one Ireland wanted.  He stood for that principle and any differences he had with the people there were on that basis.</P>
    <P>As far as France was concerned they had been told the position there.  They could only get sympathy from her; but they had to use that sympathy and when people were sympathetic it was a good time to state your case.  One of the chief functions of representatives of a foreign government is diplomacy, but as their government was not recognised their representatives' functions were to represent Ireland to those foreign people and hence they were only a part of the Publicity Department.</P>
    <P>It was said they should have press representatives abroad.  If Ireland had a paper like &ldquo;The Times&rdquo; they could afford to get that paper to send correspondents abroad.  When the American representatives of the big papers were over in foreign countries they were acting as secret agents for their government.  But the unfortunate thing here was that Ireland had no large papers or group of papers which could afford to send their foreign representatives abroad.</P>
    <P>He pointed out that they had no control of the wires or cables.  They had no resources that way.  It was one of the features of the problems they had to solve and one of the chief difficulties under which they had to fight.</P>
    <P>As far as getting recognition was concerned, they might put it out of their heads. When a nation wants to fight Britain she will be very glad to make Ireland's claim a moral issue but that was a very vague hope.  He might say with regard to the message he sent to the President of France that they would do very little work in France if they stood by waiting for apologies.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurGriffith" hpid="DEPUTY ARTHUR GRIFFITH DEPUTY ARTHUR GRIFFITH">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY ARTHUR GRIFFITH</NameTxt>
      <P>said he was in charge of Foreign Affairs Department at the time of Deputy Gavan Duffy's expulsion from France.  At the time there were hopes of saving poor Terence MacSwiney's life by working up public opinion all over the world.  Deputy Duffy <Col N="14" /> as Irish Envoy in Paris addressed a letter of protest to the French President and published it.  He considered Deputy Duffy was acting with the best intentions but he acted on a great error of judgment.  No representative should have sent such a letter as he made it incumbent on the French President to recognise the Republic or expel the envoy.  The fault was with Mr. Gavan Duffy.  It was their envoy made the mistake and not the French government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="THE PRESIDENT THE PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>THE PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>said the suggested action in America would be wholly impossible and wrong.  It would put public opinion against them.  They should remember that those who were really in favour of Ireland would not amount to more than four or five millions.  They could not judge the feeling of America from the crowd of 20,000 who might attend a special meeting in New York.  What was that number in seven millions?  If a person went into one of the big picture houses there and saw something of Irish interest on the screen he would find people in one part of the house who would clap and others elsewhere who would hiss.</P>
      <P>The boycott of English goods was an example of how little could be done.  It was only by appealing to the Irish as Irishmen and the anti-English section as Americans to help American industry to oust British manufactures that it could be worked up.</P>
      <P>In America they could afford to do things they could not afford to do in other countries simply because there was a certain amount of sympathy on which they could count; but there were limits and narrow limits on which they could operate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="DEPUTY GAVAN DUFFY DEPUTY GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>desired to say that was the first occasion on which any expression of opinion had come from the Cabinet as to the propriety or impropriety of his action.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="DEPUTY DR. MACCARTAN DEPUTY DR. MACCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY DR. MACCARTAN</NameTxt>
      <P>said he did in America exactly what Deputy Gavan Duffy did in France and was not driven out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="THE PRESIDENT THE PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>THE PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>replied that they could do things in American they could not do in other countries.  It was not necessary to refer to Deputy Duffy's action, nor would he refer to it now only the matter was brought up here.  The thing was done and finished with.  The Cabinet did not think it wise in the conduct of their foreign affairs to harp on the one thing they might regard as not tactful when all other things were done splendidly.</P>
      <P>Adoption of the Report put and agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="AIREACHT AIRGID:" RHead="REPORT">
    <Title>AIREACHT AIRGID: REPORT</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="THE MINISTER OF FINANCE THE MINISTER OF FINANCE">
      <NameTxt>THE MINISTER OF FINANCE</NameTxt>
      <P>¹ said he presumed all had read his report. On page 2 in the Estimate for the Department of Foreign Affairs there should be an addition of £1,000, and in Publicity there should be a deduction of £1,000.  That was the £1,000 paid to the South African envoy charged to Publicity but afterwards changed to Foreign Affairs.  There was a slight mistake in [the] tot² which increased balance by 10/-.  He had with him all the details under all these headings and he suggested it would be better if members interested in any particular Department would ask him personally in writing any questions, otherwise they could spend all day on it.</P>
      <P>1. Michael Collins.</P>
      <P>2. In the original typescript this reads, &lsquo;in tot of page...&rsquo;.  The shorthand note shows the entry as given above.</P>
      <P>Since he wrote the account a statement had come from America but the figures he gave were substantially correct.  The amount they spent exceeded the Estimate by £2,000 and therefore the balance shown should be reduced by that amount.  He took it that details of the various Departmental Estimates would be found in the reports.  He considered most of these Estimates too large.</P>
      <P>With regard to the last paragraph in his report &ldquo;other payments of funds to the English government&rdquo;, he was contemplating under that heading the possibility of making recommendations to the Dáil for legislation on general lines under which there would be something in the nature of a D.O.R.A. and that all activities of the English government whether by way of collecting taxes, operating in Courts, or other functions of any kind would be dealt with under this Defence of the Realm Act by Orders in Council.  This, of course, could not be done during the Truce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The matter of Irish societies had become so important that he felt it necessary to <Col N="15" /> make a report to the Ministry on their general condition and he was not satisfied that any of these societies were in a solvent position.  None of them were founded on a thoroughly sound basis.  The tables of these societies were being gone into and he would be prepared to make recommendations later.  He said the only possible proposition was amalgamation.  It might mean a very heavy burden on national funds but it would be worth it if after a few years these societies were enabled to meet their liabilities.  As the complete position could not be put before the members, he asked that the House should leave these activities to be continued by the Ministry and through the Ministry to the Department of Finance to continue its examinations and that with the authority of the Dáil.</P>
    <P>There was also another matter in which the same position arose&mdash;the Sinn Féin Bank which was in an unstable position. The accounts showed that the liabilities exceeded the assets.  The position was that many small investors had their life's savings in the Bank and it would have to be faced by the Ministry and the Dáil whether all these small investors should be allowed to bear the loss of the monies they put in.  He had seen the Account himself and with the exception of a few they were all small amounts, from £70 to £150.  With regard to Land Annuities, he recommended that the Department of Agriculture should deal with that matter.</P>
    <P>As agreed, the Dáil here adjourned till 4 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="FINANCE DEPARTMENT REPORT:" RHead="DEBATE RESUMED">
    <Title>FINANCE DEPARTMENT REPORT: DEBATE RESUMED</Title>
    <P>House resumed at 4.15 p.m. and before resuming debate on Finance Report, the Secretary read Standing Order No. 75 re expenses for the benefit of the new Teachtaí.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="DEPUTY SEÁN MACENTEE DEPUTY SEÁN MACENTEE">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY SEÁN MACENTEE</NameTxt>
      <P>called the Speaker's attention to the non-observance of Standing Order No. 8 referring to the Rules of Debate.  He asked that the names of the constituencies be circulated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfEoinMacNeill" hpid="THE CEANN COMHAIRLE Eoin MacNeill">
      <NameTxt>THE CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>said he was afraid such a list was not available and until such time as it was he would not be too severe on the Teachtaí as to how they addressed their colleagues.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMcCarthy" hpid="DEPUTY DAN MCCARTHY DEPUTY DAN MCCARTHY">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY DAN MCCARTHY</NameTxt>
      <P>proposed the adoption of the report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMcGuinness" hpid="DEPUTY JOSEPH MCGUINNESS DEPUTY JOSEPH MCGUINNESS">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY JOSEPH MCGUINNESS</NameTxt>
      <P>seconded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDwyer" hpid="DEPUTY SÉAMUS Ó DUIBHIR DEPUTY SÉAMUS Ó DUIBHIR">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY SÉAMUS Ó DUIBHIR</NameTxt>
      <P>urged the Dáil to give the Ministry of Finance permission at once to appoint an official to look after the business of the Assurance Societies and the Sinn Féin Bank.  All the monies invested were in jeopardy.  There was no necessity for panic, but the situation should be dealt with at once and the proposition of the Finance Minister was a good one.  He thought it would be time lost examining the Tables.  These Tables were made out in England to suit English conditions which were far different to Irish conditions, a case proven by the fact that British companies were making fortunes while Irish companies were losing huge sums.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMichaelMacDona" hpid="DEPUTY JOSEPH MACDONAGH DEPUTY JOSEPH MACDONAGH">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY JOSEPH MACDONAGH</NameTxt>
      <P>pointed out that when the tables were made out to suit English conditions there was also in the mind of the people who were making them out the conditions on which these insurances were taken out.  It was a well-known fact that the English person who insured was much less thrifty than the Irish person and the first thing to go was always the insurance premium; the result was they had a tremendous number of lapsed policies in England which went to make the societies self-supporting.  The Irish people take insurance very seriously and the last thing that would go would be the policy.  Therefore he considered the question of going into the Tables the most important of all.  They must take things as they were and he hoped the Dáil would set up a Commission to enquire into the question of Irish insurance societies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="DEPUTY WILLIAM COSGRAVE DEPUTY WILLIAM COSGRAVE">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY WILLIAM COSGRAVE</NameTxt>
      <P>said he did not find himself in agreement with the member for Rathmines.  He thought the Tables were one of the main causes of the non-success of these insurance societies, the calculations for which were made, he thought, in 1780 and were based on the death rate of some town in England.  They would see that in some of the encyclopedias. From experience they found the length of life in Ireland was not as long as in England.  In Dublin the death rate was <Col N="16" /> very much higher than in any other town of the same size in England and they were operating under very hard circumstances because the best blood of the country was exported&mdash;a regular drain on the best and most valuable lives.  Then, again, the big English companies who come over here had huge funds at their disposal.  They had weathered the worst period of their existence and were in a position to swamp out any Irish society.  Irish societies started at the very worst time when securities were at the very highest pitch and when the charges for income tax, etc., were also at the highest, and consequently the revenue would be lowest.  They had every possible disadvantage that could be conceived.  He understood the working expenses had reached 60% or 70% - 80% in some cases. How, he asked, was it reasonably possible for these societies to invest in order to be in a position to meet their liabilities.  Any State insurance should guarantee either a return of the money or at least a return of the premiums paid in the case of people unable to continue.  It was a wrong principle and morally indefensible that any society should benefit by policies lapsing.</P>
      <P>The Australian societies were about the soundest.  Societies there could invest free of income tax and that was an inducement to the people to become thrifty.</P>
      <P>He believed the proposal would involve the State in some loss but it was due to the people to see that their money was soundly and safely invested for them.  He considered insurance should be a State business.  There was a good deal of money in the business if run economically by the State.  At any rate it was a serious business for them that so many members of the Dáil were attracted to these boards.  They had no previous experience to enable them to do justice to those who invested.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephOByrne" hpid="DEPUTY P.J. O'BYRNE DEPUTY P.J. O'BYRNE">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY P.J. O'BYRNE</NameTxt>
      <P>said as far as he knew most of the public bodies in Ireland transferred their insurances from British to Irish insurance companies and if the statement of the Minister of Finance was known it would cause grave panic. They wanted to encourage Irish industry but they could not possibly take the risk of being at the loss if a fire occurred and the companies were insolvent.  He certainly thought in the interest of public bodies in Ireland they should be told which were the unsound ones and to get an opportunity of reconsidering their position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCollins1919" hpid="THE MINISTER FOR FINANCE Michael Collins">
      <NameTxt>THE MINISTER FOR FINANCE</NameTxt>
      <P>replied in regard to the remarks of the Deputy for Tipperary that what attracted his attention to these societies was the fact that he saw one company advertising they had received insurances from public bodies and he communicated with the Ministry for Local Government.  There was one company, as far as he was concerned, as sound as any company in England.  That company was not concerned in any way with these societies.</P>
      <P>With regard to the Sinn Féin Bank, the people who were hit were the same type. The man who had saved £70 in the past 10 or 15 years was the same as the man who was going to save £70 by insuring for the next ten years.</P>
      <P>There was no comparison whatever between English societies and Irish societies. The former could do all sorts of other business, and did business on such a scale as operating overnight.  The day's collection would be lent overnight and a considerable revenue derived from these sums they got in in one day.</P>
      <P>His main desire was to save their own credit as a nation, to save the credit of the Dáil and to save their own people who were putting their small savings week by week into these societies.  Anything done would be done with the full approval of the Ministry.  When he wrote his report he was unaware of the particular situation of one society, and having knowledge of that now the matter was more pressing and he would recommend the Ministry to take action within the next week.</P>
      <P>Another great difference between the English and Irish societies was that the English societies did not compete against one another.  They left whole areas to each other by agreement, which meant the cost of collection was greatly reduced and when compared with the cost in Ireland was as low as one tenth of the cost in Ireland.  It was that cost made all the difference between solvency and insolvency.  Some of the Tables were all right but others were not sound, that was to say the Table at its termination could not show the necessary profit for the collection of the premium and the working of the society for the time it operated.  The matter was very urgent and he would like there should be no public discussion over it as it would be disastrous to have it in public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>He did not want to single out any society, but he had been asked by some of <Col N="17" /> the public bodies whether a certain company was an Irish company and could be said to be solvent, and he answered that question in the affirmative.</P>
    <P>Deputy Cosgrave had made one point of extra importance.  It had been said to him that some of the societies invested in the capital of companies on whose shares there was a liability.  That, he said, was not an investment but a loss and they might be called upon to meet that liability when they could not.  No bank would advance a penny on security of that kind.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusRobinson" hpid="DEPUTY SÉAMUS ROBINSON DEPUTY SÉAMUS ROBINSON">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY SÉAMUS ROBINSON</NameTxt>
      <P>thought that the amount shown for Defence, £39,000, was rather small and thought that a larger sum should have been given.  He would like to get details. He also pointed out there was no estimate for the coming half-year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCollins1919" hpid="THE MINISTER FOR FINANCE Michael Collins">
      <NameTxt>THE MINISTER FOR FINANCE</NameTxt>
      <P>asked for written notice of that question. Items would be available on Monday morning.  The reason no estimate was shown was that Defence was covered by the balance of a Vote available in America. It was explained at the last Dáil meeting. The position was that out of the Vote of 500,000 dollars, there was a balance left of 289,000 dollars which would cover all requirements for the coming half year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="THE PRESIDENT THE PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>THE PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>said that any sum of money they could profitably spend in Defence they were willing to spend it.</P>
      <P>Ceist curtha agus aontuithe.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="AIREACHT COSANTA:" RHead="REPORT">
    <Title>AIREACHT COSANTA: REPORT</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="THE MINISTER OF DEFENCE THE MINISTER OF DEFENCE">
      <NameTxt>THE MINISTER OF DEFENCE</NameTxt>
      <P>¹ said he had nothing to add to his previous verbal report.  He was ready to answer any questions if he got notice.</P>
      <P>1. Cathal Brugha.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="FIONÁN Ó LOINSIGH FIONÁN Ó LOINSIGH">
      <NameTxt>P. Ó MÁILLE</NameTxt>
      <P>proposed and <b>FIONÁN Ó LOINSIGH</b> seconded the adoption of the report.</P>
      <P>Ceist curtha agus aontuithe.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="AIREACHT OIBREACHAIS:" RHead="REPORT">
    <Title>AIREACHT OIBREACHAIS: REPORT</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMcGuinness" hpid="DEPUTY JOSEPH MCGUINNESS DEPUTY JOSEPH MCGUINNESS">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY JOSEPH MCGUINNESS</NameTxt>
      <P>asked how this Department came to spend £5,357 which seemed very large in comparison with amount spent by Defence, Agriculture and Fisheries Departments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamdeRoiste" hpid="DEPUTY LIAM DE RÓISTE DEPUTY LIAM DE RÓISTE">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY LIAM DE RÓISTE</NameTxt>
      <P>referring to the paragraph re Relief of Distress said it would be well if the Minister gave some idea of the relation between the Labour Department and the White Cross Department. The report referred to a particular scheme in a particular district.  If that scheme were worth taking up, to help industrial revival, as it was stated, it should be taken up in a proper manner. He put that to the Minister and asked that the department should, if possible, get in touch with the White Cross Committee. The reason he suggested that was that in some districts the work of the White Cross was not properly co-ordinated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMichaelMacDona" hpid="THE MINISTER FOR LABOUR, DEPUTY JOSEPH MACDONAGH THE MINISTER FOR LABOUR, DEPUTY JOSEPH MACDONAGH">
      <NameTxt>THE MINISTER FOR LABOUR</NameTxt>
      <P>, DEPUTY JOSEPH MACDONAGH², replied with regard to the expenditure of £5,357, that when the Belfast boycott was taken over on the 25th January last he asked the Dáil for a sum of £2,500 for a period of 13 weeks, and he explained then that it was necessary to appoint at least 12 organisers and set up offices in Dublin and at least 600 committees throughout the country.  In addition it was found necessary to appoint two extra organisers for Dublin City and to pay secretaries in Derry, Belfast, Limerick and Cork.  The result was that in salaries alone £140 per week was spent.  They had to go into a very strenuous press campaign and put advertisements into the Dublin papers and into 20 or 30 of the leading provincial organs, the bill for which amounted to over £100 per week.  A million circulars and 50,000 posters were got out. He asked £5,000 for a further six months and he was well inside that sum and he thought that the Labour Department had achieved what it had set out to do and that the money, in view of the success of the boycott, was very well spent.</P>
      <P>2. Joseph MacDonagh was substitute Minister for Labour.  Countess Markievicz was Minister for Labour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the question put by the Teachta from Cork (L. de Róiste), he was a member of the Executive Committee of the White Cross but he had not been able to attend any of the meetings till the Truce started.  At the first meeting he attended the question of relief of distress was discussed and Dr. Kennedy had the rough <Col N="18" /> draft of a scheme for giving employment to people in different parts of the country. The scheme was for the conservation of water power and Dr. Kennedy hoped it would mean this, an equivalent for coal at 6/- per ton.  Dr. Kennedy had shown him enough to convince him there was something good in the scheme.  He hoped to have it before the committee very soon. It was suggested the sum to be spent would be £60,000.  That was no haphazard measure but a step in the right direction; it would give money to people for work instead of doles and would help to put industries on a proper basis.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOMahoney" hpid="DEPUTY JOHN O'MAHONY DEPUTY JOHN O'MAHONY">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY JOHN O'MAHONY</NameTxt>
      <P>wished to know what instructions were given to organisers of the Belfast boycott when appointed.  Some of them had exceeded their orders and traders were informed in some places that the embargo was placed on the whole Six Counties.  He complained the paid Secretary in Limerick had not done his duty and that a certain institution in that city had repudiated the Decree of the Dáil.  He had reliable information that a certain commercial firm there had got permission to sell Belfast goods while one he was interested in was refused leave to sell £100 worth of Belfast biscuits which they happened to have in stock before the declaration of the boycott, and had to give them for pig-feeding.  If the Dáil Decree was to be carried out it should be respected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="DEPUTY SEÁN MACENTEE DEPUTY SEÁN MACENTEE">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY SEÁN MACENTEE</NameTxt>
      <P>in proposing adoption of the report said he failed to see where Deputy O'Mahony had a grievance against the Labour Department. He presumed if a certain town refused to trade with another one which had the reputation of acting as a dump for Belfast goods and actively concerned in attempting to defeat the boycott, the Labour Department could not be blamed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMacBride" hpid="DEPUTY JOSEPH MCBRIDE DEPUTY JOSEPH MCBRIDE">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY JOSEPH MCBRIDE</NameTxt>
      <P>seconded the adoption of the report and said he was not happy about the boycott. He would be very sorry that the intolerance of Belfast should spread through the rest of Ireland.  He was in favour of the boycott but he was afraid the banking industry of Belfast was not properly boycotted. The small deposits in local branches had not been withdrawn.  He would impress upon the Minister of Labour to get his organisers to induce the farmers and those small depositors in the Belfast banks to withdraw their accounts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPColivet" hpid="DEPUTY M.P. COLLIVET DEPUTY M.P. COLLIVET">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY M.P. COLLIVET</NameTxt>
      <P>considered the Deputy for Fermanagh (J. O'Mahony) was labouring under a misapprehension. The incident of the shutting out of Portadown goods occurred before the paid secretary was working.  The people of Limerick decided to exclude the goods of all the Six Counties.  He thought it would be a good thing to have it adopted generally. On very few occasions have the Dáil given a lead to the country in any of these things.  The shutting out of Portadown goods in Limerick was done very successfully and he sympathised with Mr. O'Mahony to the extent that perhaps due notice was not given with regard to the Six Counties and individual manufacturers and agents who sent goods there chanced getting let down.  He considered Limerick was perfectly justified in doing what it had done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurGriffith" hpid="DEPUTY ARTHUR GRIFFITH DEPUTY ARTHUR GRIFFITH">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY ARTHUR GRIFFITH</NameTxt>
      <P>explained when the Ministry here decided on the Belfast boycott they discussed the whole situation, the position of the Six Counties and whether it was wiser to cut off that portion of Ireland.  Now, he said, it was the considered decision of the Ministry that the boycott should be confined to those areas that drove out the Nationalist population and that the areas where that was not taking place should not be touched.  If the city of Limerick started on its own behalf to boycott the Six Counties, it was acting in defiance of the Dáil.  It was no use for the Dáil to pass a Decree against Belfast if Limerick decreed a boycott against the Six Counties. Portadown was expressly excluded because the Portadown people got frightened and there was no pogrom or driving out of Catholics there and their action in confining the boycott to Belfast had kept two-thirds of the Six-County area free and open to the Nationalists and Catholic workmen.  If Limerick was going to act against the Six Counties they were playing the game of Belfast.  What they wanted to do was to make Belfast and two or three other towns be ostracised by their own people.  The action of Limerick in extending the boycott was absolutely indefensible.  He thought it was the duty of Mr. Collivet to go back to Limerick and tell the citizens <Col N="19" /> that what the Dáil ordered was what they should do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPColivet" hpid="DEPUTY M.P. COLLIVET DEPUTY M.P. COLLIVET">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY M.P. COLLIVET</NameTxt>
      <P>explained that the Decree was carried out and in addition the citizens considered they were quite right in saying they were not going to buy any goods from the rest of the Six Counties also.  Was the Dáil going to tell them they would have to buy goods from the Six Counties?  The thing had been going on for six or seven months and the Dáil never pointed out it was wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurGriffith" hpid="DEPUTY ARTHUR GRIFFITH DEPUTY ARTHUR GRIFFITH">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY ARTHUR GRIFFITH</NameTxt>
      <P>said this was the first time he had heard of it.  If it had come to his knowledge in time he would have told them they were acting just as much in defiance of the Dáil as if they refused to carry out the Decree at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="THE MINISTER FOR LABOUR THE MINISTER FOR LABOUR">
      <NameTxt>THE MINISTER FOR LABOUR</NameTxt>
      <P>¹ said he specifically wrote to the Limerick committee telling them the only towns included in the boycott were Belfast, Lisburn, Dromore, Banbridge and New-townards, and that anything outside that was outside the Dáil Decree.  He was not so much concerned with the Six Counties as that he got instructions to carry out the Decree to the letter.  With regard to Deputy O'Mahony's statement that a Limerick firm got leave to sell Belfast biscuits, he had it in black and white from Mr. Casey, the local secretary, that Deputy O'Mahony was misinformed. Limerick did more to prevent Belfast goods getting through than any other town.  Woolworths had a series of conditions put upon them and have put up a fine of £50 to be forfeited the first time they were caught breaking any of these conditions.</P>
      <P>1. This appears to be the substitute Minister for Labour, Joseph MacDonagh.</P>
      <P>With regard to the Belfast banks, they had done a great deal.  In general, they issued notices not to have anything to do with the Belfast banks.  In Limerick, out of 450 accounts in the Ulster Bank there were now only six and in a few days there would only be five.  He did not agree that the banks were far more important than the commercial business.  To destroy the distributing trade would be a very strong lever to bring Belfast to its knees.  In the year 1919 Belfast got in about £23,000,000 worth of drapery and distributed 17 or 18 millions of it to the rest of Ireland.  In the first half of 1920, it got only £5,000,000. The result was a great deal of unemployment in Belfast.</P>
      <P>He referred yesterday to the number of bankruptcies which was the result of the boycott of the Belfast distributing trade. Mr. McBride's constituency was one of the worst in Ireland as far as the boycott was concerned.  If the counties in the West of Ireland did only half or quarter as much as Limerick, Cork, Tipperary, Waterford or Clare, they would have gone much further with the boycott.</P>
      <P>He tried to impress upon the Deputies why the boycott should be confined to the five towns decreed by showing that Belfast was the heart of the Six Counties and if they destroyed Belfast they would destroy the trade of the Six Counties.  It was far better to aim at one objective than at five or six.  It would be unfair to put on a boycott on people who had not been guilty of the crime for which this boycott was put upon the others.  The rest of the Six Counties did not victimise the Catholics or drive them out of their business and therefore they were not subjected to the boycott.  Referring to Portadown, he said it was not altogether spotless with regard to this boycott.  There were a number of &ldquo;dumps&rdquo; for the five boycotted towns and if they could get proper inside information from Portadown they might find that a number of traders there were acting as distributors for Belfast firms.  He had stated before there were four towns acting as &ldquo;dumps&rdquo; but he did not indicate they should be boycotted.  He got no complaint from merchants in Portadown.  In one case a letter stating a particular trader was not within the area was requested from him and he gave that letter.</P>
      <P>He was not concerned with the politics of any traders, he was only concerned with carrying out the boycott in the five towns. Any boycott outside that area was done without his consent and he could not be responsible for anything done by people not under his control.</P>
      <P>With regard to Deputy MacEntee's asking for the boycott area to be extended to the Six Counties, he thought it would be very unjust to do so.  In the first place it would destroy the boycott, secondly it would be unjust and thirdly it would be a recognition on their part of the Partition Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRiceKent" hpid="DEPUTY D. KENT DEPUTY D. KENT">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY D. KENT</NameTxt>
      <P>asked if it was the <Col N="20" /> intention of the Ministry to put an embargo on importation of English cloth and leather-goods, but the Ceann Comhairle ruled the question out of order.</P>
      <P>Ceist curtha agus aontuithe.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="AIREACHT UM GHNÓTHAÍ DÚITHCHE:" RHead="REPORT">
    <Title>AIREACHT UM GHNÓTHAÍ DÚITHCHE: REPORT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurGriffith" hpid="THE MINISTER FOR HOME AFFAIRS Arthur Griffith">
      <NameTxt>THE MINISTER FOR HOME AFFAIRS</NameTxt>
      <P>¹ informed the Dáil that he intended to ask for £5,000 to pay Brigade police officers, as these men would be whole-time officials.  The Relief Bureau had been established to co-ordinate the work of the White Cross and other relief societies.  He asked the Deputies to forward any cases they had to this subdepartment and every effort would be made to expedite the payment of relief.</P>
      <P>1. Austin Stack.</P>
      <P>With regard to emigration, they had got the shipping agents to sign an undertaking that they were observing the regulations issued.  He regarded the returns for recent months very satisfactory.  These returns had been largely advertised by the British government which must be with the object of enticing young people out of the country and to give the idea there was a rush of people from the country.  The facts were the other way.  The emigration from Ireland in June 1914 was 1,208; in July 1921 it was only 787.  In June 1914 [sic] it was about the same.  The figures the British reports quote for the last year are about half the average for the ten years before the war.  That figure was 30,000 people and the figure for last year was 15,000, and that notwithstanding the fact that 150,000 to 160,000 were held up during the war unable to get away.</P>
      <P>He said he would be bringing in a Decree at a later stage regarding enemy court officials and others.  If it was not passed now it might not be possible to meet again for some time.  Its enforcement could be held up till it was considered advisable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephOByrne" hpid="DEPUTY P.J. O'BYRNE DEPUTY P.J. O'BYRNE">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY P.J. O'BYRNE</NameTxt>
      <P>proposed the adoption of the report.  He was very glad to see that the police duties would be carried out in future by whole-time officers.  It was absolutely essential that these officers should devote their whole time to the work and it was necessary for the people to understand that the Decrees of the Republican Courts could and would be carried out.  He said he was acting on the Prisoners' Dependents' Fund Committee and he would like to know if those depending on men on active service with the I.R.A. were entitled to receive relief, and to whom application should be addressed.</P>
      <P>He thought it very essential that shipping agents should be impressed that they must carry out the Dáil regulations relating to emigration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesJosephWalsh" hpid="DEPUTY J.J. WALSH DEPUTY J.J. WALSH">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY J.J. WALSH</NameTxt>
      <P>seconded adoption of report.  In reference to emigration, he pointed out there was a big discrepancy between the figures the Minister for Home Affairs quoted and those the British government gave.  He heard there was a large number of Irish slipping out of the country by subterranean channels.</P>
      <P>He wished to remind the Minister for Home Affairs with reference to appointments in the new police force that a great number of the earlier police officers were now in jail and their claims should not be forgotten when a permanent arrangement was being made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="DEPUTY E.J. DUGGAN DEPUTY E.J. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY E.J. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>informed the Dáil that the enemy contended the holding of Republican Courts was a breach of the Truce.  He considered it was not, and no agreement had been arrived at.  He understood that the Minister for Home Affairs intended issuing an order to have the courts held as they were before the enemy activity became so strong as it had been for the past twelve months.  In some cases where courts were to be held the enemy warned the parties concerned they would break the courts up by force if any attempt was made to hold them, and they were not held.  Another point was, if decisions were given and could not be carried out it would be better the courts were not held.  The enemy said they had no official knowledge of any force like the Republican police.  If those police go to enforce a Decree by interference with person or property, they are liable to arrest by the enemy forces and trial as criminals.  He asked if courts were summoned were they going to hold them in spite of the armed forces of the Crown? If the police are instructed to make a seizure, how are they going to do it?  As far as he saw, if the courts were held in a public way the enemy would not back down from his position of opposition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="21" /> He understood an agreement might be come to.  What the enemy complained of was that we wanted to do things now that we could not do during the war.  That was justices who were afraid to sit before were now anxious to sit publicly.  The enemy objected strongly to that.  He thought it was possible there might be an understanding that the courts could be held in private, as they were previous to the Truce, and do their work efficiently in such a way that the enemy police might pretend they did not know anything about them.  Otherwise a very serious situation would arise and would undoubtedly lead to the breaking up of the Truce.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="THE MINISTER OF DEFENCE THE MINISTER OF DEFENCE">
      <NameTxt>THE MINISTER OF DEFENCE</NameTxt>
      <P>disagreed with Deputy Duggan.  He said there was a condition in the Truce terms to the effect that the British police and soldiers could not interfere with any Irishman during the Truce.  If that guarantee had not been given there would have been no Truce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="THE PRESIDENT THE PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>THE PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>believed they could settle this matter very quickly.  When the Truce was arranged there was an understanding that there would be no ostentatious demonstrations on either side.  He thought the courts could go on as they did before, and in the same method, without being ostentatious.  As regards the police, there would be a difficulty there, but he did not see the necessity of enforcing decrees overnight and they could be deferred for the time being.  He felt strongly that the courts should go on, but should go on quietly, as before.  This was a time for reorganising and doing work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexMcCabe" hpid="DEPUTY ALEX MACCABE DEPUTY ALEX MACCABE">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY ALEX MACCABE</NameTxt>
      <P>said he did not see any difficulty in carrying on the courts.  His principal objection to the courts was that they were too centralised.  In times of stress the organisation was not able to meet the circumstances. It should be decentralised as much as possible, first because the District Court area was altogether too large to have in a court area.  They found they could never summon a District Court during the war without attracting the attention of the enemy.  They had to go back to the old system of getting Parish Courts together. They found the next appeal should be, not to the District Court, but to a court comprised of four or five parishes, and they found this worked very well and stood the stress of a very difficult period in their history.  He had in his mind that there should be another appeal to something like a County Court from that as it was altogether impossible to have an appeal carried through to Dublin during the war.</P>
      <P>Another objection he had was the handicap it would be on the poor people who wanted to appeal against local decisions to be forced to send the case to Dublin.  He was not familiar with the judicature nature of this central body in Dublin but they found the second appeal was necessary to settle cases.  There were a few people down with them who did not accept the decision of the superior court and who if there had been a County Court would have been satisfied.  People who were well off secured in Dublin reversals of the local court decisions.</P>
      <P>He objected decidedly to the control of the police force from Republican headquarters here in Dublin.  He thought they should not have a second Dublin Castle working here but at once follow the procedure of other countries that had their own government and decentralise the police authority and hand it over to the county authorities to control these forces.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephRuttled" hpid="DEPUTY P.J. RUTTLEDGE DEPUTY P.J. RUTTLEDGE">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY P.J. RUTTLEDGE</NameTxt>
      <P>said from his experience the court areas fixed by the Minister for Home Affairs so as to have a constituency area for each district was the most expeditious and best.  The amended scheme by which one District Justice could act with two parishes covered any difficulty which might have arisen owing to enemy action.</P>
      <P>With regard to the police, he thought it was inadvisable to pay them at present. His principal reason for making that suggestion was he could not see how these chiefs of police could be whole-time officers especially if the military activity was resumed.  A good deal of stress might be laid on the fact that a chief of police was essential, but he took it, and he thought it was the experience of many Teachtaí that the working of a court depends on a good registrar.  It was on him they had to rely solely for the carrying out of the courts and in parts where there was a good registrar the courts never cease to function.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>He strongly favoured the promulgation of a Decree against the enemy courts.  The fact that no such Decree had been made <Col N="22" /> up to this led people who were more or less favourably disposed towards the Republic to go into those courts.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMcGrath" hpid="DEPUTY JOSEPH MCGRATH DEPUTY JOSEPH MCGRATH">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY JOSEPH MCGRATH</NameTxt>
      <P>said he welcomed the proposal to appoint whole-time police officers to enforce Decrees, etc. He would like to mention a case in connection with the Increase of Rent Decree passed by the Dáil some time ago.  A very big housing corporation in Dublin increased their rents according to the Decree and the present position was that less than half the tenants were paying the increased rents.  The remainder, about five-eights, are paying no rent, have been taken to the enemy courts on two occasions and have been beaten, and he understood they were going to take it to the House of Lords now. He was concerned in so far as he was approached when the increase was made and he advised the people they should and must obey the Dáil Decree.  It would have been a very popular thing to do to say &ldquo;pay no rent&rdquo;.  He was very glad to say all the tenants in his constituency obeyed but they were being constantly assaulted and blackguarded by the others who said no such Rent Decree was passed by the Dáil and that they had this from their own member.  He suggested that the Dáil should insist upon each Deputy who is affected by this rent dispute going to his constituents and advising the people as to whether this was a Dáil Decree or not.  The matter was becoming a regular scandal and he appealed to the Minister for Home Affairs to give every protection he could to the tenants who obeyed the Decree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCollins1919" hpid="THE MINISTER FOR FINANCE Michael Collins">
      <NameTxt>THE MINISTER FOR FINANCE</NameTxt>
      <P>agreed with Deputy Duggan re the holding of courts in public.  Courts came out now because there was no danger.  During the war there was no proper effort made to keep them going.  There was no court held in South Cork for eight or nine months.  It was no good their getting up against a situation now they had not faced long ago. The courts broke down for the reason that the machinery was not held together. There was not enough work done locally or at headquarters.  He would like to know how many courts were held.</P>
      <P>He protested against the payment of police chiefs.  They were not necessary for the enforcement of Decrees.  He objected also to the remark passed about the Prisoners' Dependents' Fund.  There never was a case brought before the Prisoners' Dependents' Fund that was not seen to within two or three days.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRiceKent" hpid="DEPUTY D. KENT DEPUTY D. KENT">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY D. KENT</NameTxt>
      <P>said he could bear out what the Minister of Finance said re courts.  Their great difficulty was to get courts at all.  He had to constitute a court himself to prevent people going into the enemy courts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPColivet" hpid="DEPUTY M.P. COLLIVET DEPUTY M.P. COLLIVET">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY M.P. COLLIVET</NameTxt>
      <P>asked what machinery the Minister had for ascertaining whether the courts were functioning or not.  Since he came out of prison he had received one or two complaints that the courts in Limerick were not working satisfactorily.</P>
      <P>With regard to the Rent Decree, the people complained the increase was very big and came suddenly on them.  In many cases there was an increase of 50 per cent. People did not understand why they should be asked to pay such increases.  It was felt there was hardship, and arbitration courts outside the Republic were set up which settled a great many cases at a lower rate than the landlord would have got under the Decree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephOByrne" hpid="DEPUTY P.J. O'BYRNE DEPUTY P.J. O'BYRNE">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY P.J. O'BYRNE</NameTxt>
      <P>said he wished to make a personal explanation with reference to a statement made by the Minister of Finance that an attack had been made on the working of the Prisoners' Dependents' Fund.  He certainly did not mean to do any such thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="THE MINISTER OF FINANCE THE MINISTER OF FINANCE">
      <NameTxt>THE MINISTER OF FINANCE</NameTxt>
      <P>replied the reference was not to the Teachta for East Tipperary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonalOCallaghan" hpid="DEPUTY DONAL O'CALLAGHAN DEPUTY DONAL O'CALLAGHAN">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY DONAL O'CALLAGHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>said he was aware of the splendid work done in Cork by the police but if it was intended to pay them how were they to be chosen, and who was to control them?  He suggested they should be under local committees.  The people in Cork were paying no rent to the Cork Corporation and he asked the Minister for Home Affairs if he had any remedy to suggest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="DEPUTY RICHARD MULCAHY DEPUTY RICHARD MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY RICHARD MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>explained that the general idea for civil administration involved the decentralisation of the working and the problem of the smaller localities in the country.  There was not yet definitely formulated in their <Col N="23" /> minds what was to be the unit of civil administration in the country and they would not get out of a lot of petty little routine difficulties until they definitely defined what was their unit of area for civil administration.  The army could not work harmoniously unless they had very clearly defined units.  Now that the question of payment of police was raised this particular point was a very proper one for consideration.  He thought they should regulate their courts and police to fit in with the unit for civil administration, so that the local councils would be a petty government for that area.  This matter as far as decentralisation of powers was concerned was a matter of organisation and now that there was a necessity for re-organisation on different lines he thought that they should at once endeavour to define what would be this unit for local administration.</P>
      <P>He thought the courts should go on, and to go on properly they should go on in an unobtrusive manner.  Their police, he thought, should be able to control their areas without force just as the D.M.P. control traffic here.  There was no reason why it should be difficult to carry out Decrees now no more than before the war.</P>
      <P>With regard to the objection by the Minister of Finance to paying the police, at the present moment it was a question purely of finance.  He thought it was absolutely necessary to have these special officers, and he thought the areas should be adjusted before appointments were made as the present military brigade area would not suit.  He was in favour of payment of police.  He believed they would always require to have the forces controlled from Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelStaines" hpid="DEPUTY MICHAEL STAINES DEPUTY MICHAEL STAINES">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY MICHAEL STAINES</NameTxt>
      <P>referring to Deputy McGrath's complaint about the Rent Decree said when that Decree was passed he thought everyone understood it would be the maximum amount the landlord could increase rents. Deputy McGrath advised his constituents to pay up to the full amount, and it was not fair for him to say people who offered to submit the matter to arbitration refused to submit to the Decree.  After that there was a conference at which Deputy Cosgrave was present.  He thought the matter was fixed up long ago.  He did not agree the tenants should be blamed for any action they took and he was prepared to go and see them if the Dáil thought any good could be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="DEPUTY FITZGERALD DEPUTY FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>¹ said he thought the Court system an excellent one. He had twelve months' experience and if the courts did not work well in other districts the fault must have been with the people themselves.  In his area they conducted courts right through the war. They had over 300 cases in all, and during the past six months they dealt with 60 cases.  When the enemy pressure became great the constituency was slightly altered which enabled them to continue to do a good deal of work.  He thought the present scheme of organisation an excellent one and the Minister should push it on to the utmost limit.</P>
      <P>1. James Fitzgerald, a member for East Cork.</P>
      <P>He asked was there any scale of fees laid down for solicitors practising in the District Courts.  He had found solicitors charging the exorbitant fee of £20 for ordinary civil suits.</P>
      <P>With regard to emigration, he said the present passport system had broken down. It was too clumsy and it took too long with the result that in many cases the applicants had gone to America before the passports had been issued.  He submitted that the present system should be decentralised and local offices established in the country with the police in charge.  There was going to be a great deal of unemployment around Cork Harbour.  The type of workmen round there were wanted in Ireland.  If they had a decentralised passport office and sent on adequate particulars of applications to the Minister for Home Affairs he might get in touch with the Minister for Trade and Commerce and try to devise some scheme whereby employment might be provided for these men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="THE MINISTER FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT² DEPUTY COSGRAVE THE MINISTER FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT² DEPUTY COSGRAVE">
      <NameTxt>THE MINISTER FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT² DEPUTY COSGRAVE</NameTxt>
      <P>, said he was at the conference re Rent disputes referred to by Deputy Staines and Deputy McGrath.  The tenants who were agitating and refusing to pay their rent were not the best of the tenants.  The particular corporation in question had conferred untold benefit on Dublin.  It had provided for 5,000 tenants.  It was established in 1879 and consisted of very rich Dublin merchants. <Col N="24" /> It most reluctantly accepted the assistance of the Dáil in the matter but were brought into it by a particularly able member of their staff.  He went into the matter of those tenants who refused to pay and their whole case was that they would not assist capitalists.  This corporation had saved Dublin £100,000 a year and then they were faced with this kind of thing.  It had absolutely disgusted him with having anything to do with the Housing Acts.  The corporation had been promised and assured of the assistance of the Black and Tans to eject the tenants and it refused it. Deputy McGrath's case was a very good one and he thought the protection asked for should be given to those tenants who really paid what was an honest rent. Dublin Corporation was losing £20,000 a year on housing 2,000 tenants and one of those tenants refused to pay 1/6d. a week rent and £4 10. 0. wages a week coming into the house.</P>
      <P>2. William T. Cosgrave.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="THE PRESIDENT THE PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>THE PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>remarked that he did not like to see Cabinet Ministers showing divided counsels before the Dáil. The point was there had been a necessary clash between the civil and military sides of their work.  That was only very natural; they could not expect as much butter from churned milk as out of the cream.  Hence, it was the Minister for Home Affairs had a very difficult task; they could not expect from that Department as much efficiency as from the military.  It was absolutely necessary for the civil administration to decentralise.  The military side could operate from a centre because of their excellent communication system.  It was a wonder to him how the Local Government Department had been able to do work. They deserved great credit for the way they had been able to hold the country together.  Recently the member for Clare (B. O'Higgins) mentioned the matter of decentralisation to him.  He (the President) could see no way to get efficiency in civil matters unless they decentralised.  The natural unit for that would be the county council area.  He would suggest the House would set up a committee of members acquainted with local affairs, together with representatives from the Home Affairs Department and the military side, to go into the matter and it would be the best day's work they could do for the organisation of the civil administration of the country.  There were three possible units&mdash;the county council areas, the Sinn Féin area and the military brigade area. The Sinn Féin organisation had a certain claim to have this unit made the unit because they originally hoped that the Sinn Féin organisation would be the channel through which the civil administration would flow.  Taking the three units into consideration he was inclined to think that as the representatives of the county council were chosen by the people in a regular manner, the unit of administration should be the county council unit. He thought it was a question for the Government largely to decide upon.  He thought before they made their proposals the Ministry would like to have the opinions and advice of members from the cities, members of the House who were county councillors or members of corporations, and Ministers closely associated with the civil side of affairs and one or two from the army should be on the Committee which should be called together by the Minister for Home Affairs for Saturday morning instead of a sitting of the whole House.  The whole of their civil administration would depend upon this scheme of decentralisation and he believed if they adopted such a scheme there would be no complaints about the working of the Home Affairs Department.</P>
      <P>He could not understand the complaint about the increase of rent.  The Dáil Decree was a maximum sum and there was no compulsion that anyone should pay any rent as far as he could see.  If people who refused to pay rent were brought to court, he felt sure they would be dealt with.</P>
      <P>The police, he thought, were necessary and particularly necessary in the interests of the army.  It was not fair to have the army doing police work and they should not be asked to do it in future.  They did not want a big police force but a small one under the control of the Minister for Home Affairs for seeing that orders of the Court were obeyed and Decrees carried out without calling in the Army.</P>
      <P>When the Minister had replied he proposed the House would adjourn till Monday.  Tomorrow they wanted to have a conference with their foreign representatives, and Saturday would be given to the Committee on Decentralisation to draw up a proposal to submit to the Dáil next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamdeRoiste" hpid="DEPUTY LIAM DE RÓISTE DEPUTY LIAM DE RÓISTE">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY LIAM DE RÓISTE</NameTxt>
      <P>considered the question of decentralisation <Col N="25" /> should not be taken up in the manner suggested by the President but in connection with the drafting of an Irish Constitution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurGriffith" hpid="THE MINISTER FOR HOME AFFAIRS Arthur Griffith">
      <NameTxt>THE MINISTER FOR HOME AFFAIRS</NameTxt>
      <P>said he was very glad to see discussion on his department.  In the first place he wished to point out it was a gross mistake to speak of the District Court areas as the member for Sligo did.  The area of the District Court was the constituency, and besides the District Court there was a court in every parish and sometimes parishes grouped.  In addition to that, for some months past he had framed a District Court area by which one District Justice and two Parish Justices could carry on the work.  Deputy MacCabe told the Dáil he could never get into communication with headquarters.  He (the Minister for Home Affairs) had never been able to get any communication from Sligo.  Deputy MacCabe spoke of corruption at appeals in Dublin.  Well, he (the Minister) could dispose of that complaint very easily by informing the House that never yet was there an appeal from Sligo heard or listed for hearing in Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasODonnell" hpid="DEPUTY O'DONNELL (Sligo) DEPUTY O'DONNELL (Sligo)">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY O'DONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>(Sligo) interrupted to say that owing to his imprisonment and that of his colleague's also, they were not aware of the new scheme for courts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurGriffith" hpid="THE MINISTER FOR HOME AFFAIRS Arthur Griffith">
      <NameTxt>THE MINISTER FOR HOME AFFAIRS</NameTxt>
      <P>continuing his reply said there was a suggestion that his department was responsible for the courts falling through in places.  No doubt under ordinary circumstances he would be responsible, but several organisers he had sent out were arrested and he saw no good in sending out others in places where the courts were established but allowed to fall through by the local people.</P>
      <P>The Rent Decree Act was brought in on a motion of his to meet urgent cases arising out of the operations of the English Government.  In his draft Bill he provided for an increase of 10% plus increase in rates.  The Bill was referred to committee who fixed amount of increase at 15% plus increase in the rates and 6% on certain improvements.  That was a definite fixed sum and could not be altered at all unless by agreement amongst the parties concerned. If anyone came to court for an increase of rent, the court should give them that amount.  The Deputy for Limerick City (M.P. Collivet) spoke of an increase of 50%.  That was an exaggeration, as the increase was seldom, if ever, over 30%.</P>
      <P>With regard to the rent dispute mentioned by the member for St. James' area (Deputy Joseph McGrath), the matter was out of his hands as the parties had refused to come into the Republican Courts and had gone into the enemy ones.  But with regard to the question of protection for those tenants who were being abused, he assured the member for St. James they would receive all the protection his police force could afford them.  All he was sorry for was that the landlords did not bring in a test case in the Republican Courts which, he was sure, would have disposed of the matter satisfactorily long since.</P>
      <P>Regarding the Truce and the working of the courts, he was strongly of opinion they must carry on even without the sanction of Dublin Castle.  They were no more bound to cease functioning than the British were, and it was the intention of his department to carry on with the courts and improve them as much as possible with the approval of the Dáil.  Of course, he said, if the Dáil thought otherwise it would not be done.  He did not think there would be many Decrees to be enforced, but he would prefer to hold over any case that would be likely to be tough. At the same time he did not want the hands of the police to be tied in any way. So with the understanding that they were not going to bring about complications if they could help it, he asked the Dáil for a free hand to carry on the courts as usual.</P>
      <P>He had considered the question of payment of registrars over and over again&mdash; and he was afraid it would cost too much money at present, but any court that functioned properly could from its revenue easily pay its own registrar.  It would cost £30,000 to pay the registrars from Dublin and he could not recommend that.</P>
      <P>The registrars were the people on whom he had to depend for reports.  Many of them neglected to supply him with proper reports and he took it as evidence the court was not working when he got no reports.  One registrar came to him the other day and told him his court was working all the time though it sent up no reports.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In reply to the Lord Mayor of Cork (Deputy O'Callaghan), he stated that the <Col N="26" /> police officers were elected by the army and handed over to his department.</P>
    <P>He admitted there was a grave scandal in some places regarding solicitors' fees.  If cases were reported to him he would try and take some action against those solicitors who were charging exorbitant fees.  Locally he would suggest that they should be prevented from entering their courts at all.  If solicitors formed a ring and attempted to keep up an exorbitant scale amongst themselves, he would suggest and give instructions to the courts to hear pleaders who did not belong to the legal profession.</P>
    <P>Referring to the Relief Bureau, he said that was a matter put into his hands by the Ministry.  He did not desire to make any attack on the Irish Republican Prisoners' Dependents' Fund Committee. The Relief Bureau was included in his department by order of the Ministry and with the approval of the Dáil.  He intended to carry it on and keep the people in touch with the White Cross, Prisoners' Dependents' Fund, and any other existing bodies dealing with relief funds.</P>
    <P>There was the question of emigration permits.  If the Regulation that application for a permit must be made a month before date of sailing was adhered to, there would be no fear that the permit would not reach an applicant in time.  He saw no reason for establishing any other headquarters for issue of permits.  The suggestion with regard to the enforcement of the Decree against emigration and shipping agents was one that had been anticipated.  The new police had those matters in hands and it was through them future enquiries would have to be made.</P>
    <P>That finished all the questions and he would like to add that at any time any member had a complaint to make he might communicate with him and he would be only too glad to deal with it and any fair criticism he was only too glad to hear it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidRiceKent" hpid="DEPUTY D. KENT DEPUTY D. KENT">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY D. KENT</NameTxt>
      <P>asked if any fee was charged to solicitors or barristers for practising in Republican Courts or any licence issued to them.  He understood they had to pay in the English courts and he thought they should be made pay in their courts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ArthurGriffith" hpid="THE MINISTER FOR HOME AFFAIRS Arthur Griffith">
      <NameTxt>THE MINISTER FOR HOME AFFAIRS</NameTxt>
      <P>replied that matter had never yet come up for consideration and he did not believe the stage had been reached in which they could exact licence duty or pass their own men.</P>
      <P>Report was then adopted unanimously.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="THE PRESIDENT THE PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>THE PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>, proposed:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(<i>a</i>)  That the Dáil adjourn till next Monday at 11 a.m.</P>
      <P>(<i>b</i>)  That a Ministerial Committee on Foreign Affairs would sit tomorrow.</P>
      <P>(<i>c</i>)  That on Saturday a Home Affairs Committee on Decentralisation would sit, to consist of Minister for Local Government, Minister for Home Affairs, Secretary for Sinn Féin, Chief of Staff, Teachtaí who were members of the corporations of Dublin, Cork and Limerick and members of county councils, and any other Deputy who was interested in the matter.</P>
      <P>He said he was very anxious to have the discussion on the peace question taken first thing on Monday as it would be well to have the reply sent before the British House of Commons adjourned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="DEPUTY GAVAN DUFFY DEPUTY GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>asked how long did he propose to give to the peace discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="THE PRESIDENT THE PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>THE PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>replied that was a matter for the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesJosephWalsh" hpid="DEPUTY J.J. WALSH DEPUTY J.J. WALSH">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY J.J. WALSH</NameTxt>
      <P>asked if the President's ruling in regard to foreign appointments was definite.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="THE PRESIDENT THE PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>THE PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>replied that the Dáil was supreme and anything the House wanted to insist upon it could do so.  He thought those appointments should be ministerial appointments.  If there be a policy for the Government, it must be able to select its own agents to carry it out.  The House was supreme and if there was a motion to any other effect it could be discussed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesJosephWalsh" hpid="DEPUTY J.J. WALSH DEPUTY J.J. WALSH">
      <NameTxt>DEPUTY J.J. WALSH</NameTxt>
      <P>said he would put a motion down to that effect.</P>
      <P>The President's motion was put and agreed to unanimously and the Dáil adjourned till Monday at 11 a.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>