<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="4" Month="Mar" Year="1993" Vol="135" No="5" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 4 Márta 1993" DateEnglish="Thursday, 4 March 1993" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="389" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Ross that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Health to honour the commitment to provide adequate funding for the Adelaide Hospital and to ensure the ethos of the Adelaide is maintained in the proposed new hospital at Tallaght.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Farrelly of the following matter:</P>
      <P>To ask the Minister for the Environment to outline the Government policy on toxic waste disposals in Ireland.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Cregan of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for the Marine to outline the up-to-date position of the report submitted by the Cork Free Port Committee.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Reynolds of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry to establish an office of his Department in Carrick-on-Shannon, County Leitrim, to deal with headage grants and other agricultural matters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="390" /> I also received notice from Senator Cosgrave of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The need for the Minister for Transport, Energy and Communications to give permission to Cablelink networks to show local advertisements which would enable them to provide a full service.</P>
    <P>I also received notice from Senator Cotter of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry to make a statement on the requirement that a fire certificate be provided with a grant application for cattle housing in view of the huge cost of providing the certificate.</P>
    <P>I also received notice from Senator Enright of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The question of imposing more severe penalties for the use of illegal growth promoters in Ireland.</P>
    <P>I regard the matters raised by Senators Ross, Farrelly, Cregan, Reynolds, Cosgrave, Cotter and Enright as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected Senators Ross' and Farrelly's matters as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.  Senators Cregan, Reynolds, Cosgrave, Cotter and Enright may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>In response to yesterday's Order of Business there are some changes to today's Order Paper.  I hope with the agreement of the House that we will get through the items I would like to see dealt with today.  Item 1 is the National Stud (Amendment) Bill, 1993, and we propose to take all Stages between now and roughly 12 noon.  We will take Item 2, Statements on Greencore, between noon and 1 p.m.  Then we propose to take an item not on the Order Paper but requested yesterday.  Between 1 p.m. and 2 p.m. the Minister for Health will come <Col N="391" /> into the House to make a statement on the inquiry into the Kilkenny incest case. From 2 p.m. to 4 p.m. we will take Item 3, Statements on GATT.  On the Greencore issue and the Kilkenny incest case, I suggest ten minutes per speaker.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>May I thank the Leader of the House for responding so quickly and comprehensively to the requests made yesterday.  Of course there is agreement on the Order of Business today.</P>
      <P>In view of the fact that there is no mention in the Programme for a Partnership Government of proposed reform of this House would the Leader of the House as a matter of urgency, try to ensure that the Committee on Procedure and Privileges is established and put at the head of the agenda so that we can begin by looking at changes we might wish to make in the House.</P>
      <P>On the Order of Business, I raised the question of an early debate on Northern Ireland.  The Leader of the House said he would inquire into the matter.  Does the Leader have any news for me today on that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Leader's proposal to include statements on the items raised on yesterday's Order of Business.  I am pleased it was done with such rapidity.</P>
      <P>I want to raise an issue which created a problem last term.  There have been changes in the speaking order at times.  I understand that the first four speakers' statements are taken in the order of the Order of Business speakers.  After that it goes over and back across the House. That was the arrangement at one time but recently it has been done in different ways.  I have had arguments about this matter with the Cathaoirleach at various times but it was not the Cathaoirleach's fault; the official order of speakers has never been properly established.  I understand that the first three statements should follow the order of the Order of Business before continuing as normal; I would like that clarified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I notice on the Order of Business today <Col N="392" /> the matter of organisation or preparation for the establishment of Oireachtas joint committees.  Senator Norris among other Senators has raised the need for other joint committees many times.  I ask the Leader to indicate when those committees will be established.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The order of speakers is a matter for the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I join Senator Manning in thanking the Leader for ordering today's business to include statements on Greencore and the Kilkenny incest and rape incident.  In respect of next week's business, would the Leader allot time to a debate on the report of the Second Commission on the Status of Women?  This is an important and comprehensive document which should be considered in this House.</P>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, I will leave it to your good offices to determine the order of speaking but I think you will agree that it has been Seanad tradition and ethos to enable all shades of opinion to be properly represented in debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Mr. Sherlock Mr. Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity to debate items Nos. 2 and 3 on today's Order Paper.  To avoid confusion about the order of speakers, what is the order for today's debate?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The order of speakers is a matter for the Chair.  You can be assured, Senator Sherlock, that I will be fair in the alternation of speakers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Mr. Sherlock Mr. Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you very much.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That has been the tradition of the House.  It is for the Chair to decide on the order of speakers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Mr. Sherlock Mr. Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you very much, a Chathaoirligh.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the call for reform of the House.  Most Senators have just completed a Seanad campaign and the message we received on the ground <Col N="393" /> is that the public wish to see this House reformed.  I support the call to the Leader to organise an early debate on reform as is within the Leader's powers.  Reform will be welcomed by everybody; it is long overdue.  Most of us have expressed a desire for Seanad reform here and during Seanad election campaigns.  We must respect the wishes of the people in this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader of the House if he can give a time-table for the introduction of the Government's law reform in response to the case I took in Strasbourg.  I have seen definite statements in the press that indicate the existence of a clear time table but in the draft programme of legislation for this session I could not detect anything about it.  Perhaps I was looking under the wrong heading. I ask the Leader to reassure the House on this matter.</P>
      <P>I support what Senator McGowan said about the need for Seanad reform.  A debate on this matter is not sufficient because you, a Chathaoirligh, participated in a wide ranging debate in the last session on Seanad reform but marginal areas only were reformed.  We need not only a debate but action and I am glad that only Senators are coming under pressure about Seanad reform.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The kind of change you want, Senator, it seems to me, is constitutional change and we cannot effect that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>That is an element of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Unfortunately that is the position.  I call the Leader of the House to reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Not entirely though.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>On the issue of reform that has been mentioned by Senator Manning, Senator McGowan and Senator Norris, we are totally committed to reforming the House.  It would not have been possible a year ago to change the Order of Business as has been done <Col N="394" /> today to bring in Item 2 and the added item of the Kilkenny incest case.  We have made progress even if it has been slow.</P>
      <P>The Committee on Procedure and Privileges will be dealt with next week I hope; I look forward to that.  I repeat I am in constant touch with the Office of An Tánaiste regarding a Seanad debate on Northern Ireland and I hope to have some definite news on that next week. With reference to the joint committees, I understand some announcements will be made next week regarding the two committees mentioned.  Regarding the report of the Second Commission on the Status of Women I understand, subject to agreement of the Whips, that it will be dealt with next Thursday.  In relation to the European Court's judgment, I understand that legislation is imminent and I will convey the news to the Senator.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="National Stud (Amendment) Bill, 1993:" RHead="Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>National Stud (Amendment) Bill, 1993: Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="BillyKelleher" hpid="Mr. Kelleher Mr. Kelleher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelleher</NameTxt>
      <P>A coherent development plan must be drawn up for the National Stud.  That would be the first step in the process of making the Stud a viable entity again.  As I said previously the horse industry is one of our greater national assets and it is important that we are seen to be enhancing its image internationally.  We must buy suitable stallions and advertise them correctly so that the features for which the Irish horse is famous will be reinforced internationally. Increased exports of horses would help, also, to make the Irish equine industry more viable.</P>
      <P>The Minister might usefully increase the share capital and borrowing ability of the National Stud.  I recommend this Bill to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillCashin" hpid="Mr. Cashin Mr. Cashin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cashin</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister, a fellow Cork man.  For a considerable number of years the Irish National Stud in Tully, County Kildare has been the show case for Irish horse breeding.  It has <Col N="395" /> acquired a reputation as one of the best studs internationally, attending to many foreign buyers, and a source of much needed revenue.  The Stud's success in the breeding of thoroughbreds is a source of national pride.  Mindful of its role in the equine industry, the Stud organises a horse breeding training course for 25 to 30 people each spring.  The course, which has been in operation for over 20 years, is recognised within the blood stock industry as the best of its type in the world.  Graduates of the course manage some of the biggest stud farms in the world and trained winners in three continents last season.  In recent times the Stud has also directed its attention to the tourist industry.  The Japanese Gardens and horse museum attract 80,000 visitors annually.</P>
      <P>To date the National Stud has operated without any State subsidy and now, in times of world depression, has requested assistance.  We are obliged to support an enteprise which has been of such value to the State.  I support Senator Henry's suggestion that the National Stud should consider the breeding and development of the show horse as a worthwhile project. The Irish show horse performs well, nationally and internationally, and a merger of the show horse and thoroughbred sectors of the industry would resolve the financial difficulties of both sectors to some extent.  In my area of Cork northwest the sport horse breeding tradition has supplemented many a small or medium farmer's income and as a result one of the finest international show-jumping arenas in the country has been built in Millstreet.  The Millstreet horse show has gained European recognition and within two months will feature a European contest of a different nature.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Miss Ormonde Miss Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Miss Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  Coming from Munster and being familiar with Cork, Kerry and Waterford I have a special interest in this matter and, though still cutting my teeth in the Seanad, I would like to contribute to this debate on the development of the National Stud.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="396" /> I welcome this Bill.  We had the choice of injecting more money into the National Stud or closing it down and I am glad the Minister has decided to generate activity there through an injection of shares and money.  The Stud has been recognised worldwide for is success in the horse breeding and horse racing and for its development of equine education programmes. Graduates of its training course have trained winners in many parts of the world and it would be a great pity if we did not enhance that reputation.  Farming is an ancillary activity of the National Stud and I know that its profitability is questionable at the moment.  It is time to look at ways of generating farm related activity at the Stud.</P>
    <P>The success of the National Stud depends on having a suitable number of stallions standing at the Stud to facilitate high class horse breeders.  Anything that would help the racing world must be encouraged.  Racing is a major industry in terms of horse breeding and of horse racing; one need only count the number of race meetings held through the country each year between now and October to realise that it is a great national asset.</P>
    <P>I welcome the opportunity to talk about the museum and Japanese Gardens which are run by the National Stud and I hope the Minister will look at ways of promoting them.  I am a career guidance teacher yet I know little about the Japanese Gardens or about the generation of employment at the Stud.  The Department of Education might organise trips for school leavers who may be interested in apprenticeships or employment in the horse industry.  The Minister might also look at ways of co-ordinating the activities of the Departments of Education, Tourism and Agriculture for the good of this important industry.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackWall" hpid="Mr. Wall Mr. Wall">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wall</NameTxt>
      <P>As a resident of Kildare, one of the most important horse racing areas in Ireland, I consider the support the Minister is giving to the National Stud as essential for the survival of the bloodstock industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We must invest in the bloodstock <Col N="397" /> industry on a national basis and I support this Bill.  When buying bloodstock for the National Stud we must be prudent and responsible aiming for quality rather than quantity of stock.  The time form ratings of classic winners indicate that a rating of between 120 and 140 has produced the highest percentage of classic winners. Consideration should be given to that fact and to expert advice which no doubt the Minister and the National Stud executive will seek when purchasing new horses.</P>
    <P>The Minister might consider additional development of the Stud's training course.  The course, to my knowledge, carries a registration fee of £1,000 which might be prohibitive to persons on low income.  A considerable number of the 38,000 or 39,000 people involved in the racing industry in Ireland are on low incomes and the Minister might ensure that persons interested in taking the course are not debarred for financial reasons.</P>
    <P>The farm, as already mentioned, is a viable entity and would help to ensure the viability of the National Stud as a unit.  We might look at what benefits could be derived from the farm for the racing world.  Trials to ascertain the types of wheat, oats or grasses most beneficial to horses could be carried out there.  The Stud farm could become a basis for the further development of our bloodstock industry and in that regard we must ensure that the Stud retains a permanent rather than a part-time workforce.  Permanent workers are required to ensure that the knowledge gained from constant contact with the racing fraternity will be passed on to the benefit of those involved in the industry and of people visiting the Stud.</P>
    <P>I am delighted that the Minister is considering developing the present Stud museum or building a new one.  Last year I visited Tralee and saw the benefits which the heritage centre there, a magnificent structure, has brought to the town.  Similar benefits could be created at the National Stud and should be done so urgently.  An attractive Stud museum <Col N="398" /> would be of enormous benefit to tourism and to the racing fraternity.  One can see the potential for tourism at the Stud in the substantial figure the Minister gave &mdash; 80,000 visitors to the Stud last year. In view of the proximity of many Kildare racecourses to the National Stud &mdash; the Curragh racecourse is about three miles away, the Naas course is about 11 Miles away and the famous Punchestown course is about ten or eleven miles away &mdash; it should be possible to market a block ticket which would admit persons to a racecourse on a racing day and also to the National Stud.  An offer like this might attract visitors interested in racing and the Stud.  It could also increase the gates at the racecourses in Kildare.  I ask the Minister to look at the situation with the Bord Fáilte board and to ensure that if such a deal was implemented it would be of benefit to the National Stud and to Kildare racecourses.</P>
    <P>As a Kildare follower of racing I support this Bill.  It could be said that Kildare is the home of racing.</P>
    <P>I ask the Minister to consider the position with regard to bloodstock which is of the highest calibre.  Many small breeders, in most cases small farmers, depend on this to supplement their income.  We do not want to see the cost to the small breeder increase because of a sudden input of finance.  The National Stud must be seen to be involved at all levels of our racing industry.  I hope the Minister will look at the points I have raised.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Regrettably no winners from Senator Wall.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  Although this Bill contains a modest set of proposals, I welcome its introduction to the House.  The National Stud, since its inception, has served this country well.  Last year the Oireachtas Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies produced a report on the National Stud and some of the issues raised in that report are addressed in this Bill.  A number of important issues were raised at the time and perhaps the Minister could <Col N="399" /> deal with some of the outstanding issues on Second Stage.</P>
      <P>For example, one of the concerns of the Oireachtas joint committee was the need to review the corporate objectives of the National Stud.  It might be an ideal opportunity for the Department to consider doing this in the context of this Bill.  A considerable amount of time has passed since the National Stud was established and times have changed dramatically within the industry.  Now that the National Stud is being refinanced this is an ideal opportunity for the Department to look at this issue, especially when there was agreement to do so in the Dáil last year.</P>
      <P>The second issue which concerned the committee was the apparent lack of planning within the National Stud and, in particular, the lack of a long term corporate strategy.  The Oireachtas joint committee recommended two specific things.  First, that a five year plan be produced and, second, that a detailed forecast on a current year basis be provided by the National Stud to the Department. As I understand it, the five year plan has been produced.  The Minister referred to it in his speech and it is currently under examination in the Department.</P>
      <P>Given the way the National Stud has operated over the years, it would be a good idea if there were regular corporate reviews of its operations.  If the five year plan, which is currently available, was operating on a rolling basis we could examine its operations at departmental level and at the appropriate level in both Houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Another issue which the Oireachtas joint committee was concerned about was training.  We suggested that there should be a joint financial arrangement between FÁS and the National Stud with a view to the Stud becoming a training centre, expanding its training activities while being funded partly by FÁS.  This recommendation was made in the Oireachtas joint committee report and I would like to hear the Department's view on it.  It is an important area where there <Col N="400" /> is employment potential and where the Stud has proven its excellence in the past. A joint operation between FÁS and the National Stud would be beneficial.</P>
    <P>The National Stud owns important heritage assets.  The Minister referred to the museum, which is a little gem but its potential is not fully realised.  The Japanese Gardens is a long established tourist asset.  The Oireachtas joint committee felt there was scope for greater cooperation between Bord Fáilte and the stud with a view to marketing these minor, but nonetheless significant tourist assets abroad.</P>
    <P>The committee was also concerned about the complement of stallions at the National Stud and the necessity to maximise their earning potential.  The committee believed that the company should reconsider its policy of standing national hunt stallions at the Stud if they were taking up capacity which could be allocated to more remunerative flat stallions. I am not well versed in the esoteric activities in question so I do not wish to expand on this, but when it comes to using the resources at the National Stud it would be prudent if, from time to time, we looked at more cost effective ways of using them.</P>
    <P>Another matter of concern to the committee and particularly members who were more familiar with the racing aspects, was the question of a quality stallion, how it should be managed, how the financial burden which would be associated with it could be overcome and the possibilities of joint ventures.  We were also concerned about the statutory limit of borrowing.  We suggested that it should be replaced by a requirement that the company get ministerial approval for its borrowings.  This has been dealt with in the Bill which is following the recommendations in the report of the Oireachtas joint committee.  This is a welcome development and one I wish to endorse.</P>
    <P>There were two other issues of concern to the Oireachtas joint committee.  One was the discussion that the National Stud could be considered for privatisation.  I would like to put on record that it was <Col N="401" /> the unanimous view of all members of the committee that this would be an inappropriate state body for privatisation; I am sure that view is shared by the Minister and his Department.  The second issue of concern to the management of the National Stud centred on decisions being made by Kildare County Council about a road.  I am not sure if that matter has been resolved, but last year there seemed to have been a deficit of information about the proposals of the local authority in this matter.  Although it is not directly related to the Bill, the environmental impact of that proposal could have had a significant effect, not just on the location of the stud but on its primary activities.  Could the Minister clarify if this matter has been resolved?</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill and compliment the Minister on its introduction.  While it touched on a number of important points raised by the Oireachtas joint committee, there are one or two issues on which neither House has heard from the Department.  Perhaps the Minister could enlighten us.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. Walsh) Joe Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. Walsh)</NameTxt>
      <P>I take this opportunity to thank the Senators who contributed to the debate on this Bill last week and this week.  Each Senator made a very helpful and constructive contribution and suggestions which will be extremely helpful.  I can guarantee they will be taken into account by myself, and by the board of the National Stud.</P>
      <P>This Bill proposes to increase the borrowing powers of the Stud from £0.5 million to £5 million and its share capital from £5 million to £10 million.  The power to borrow will continue to be subject to the consent of the Minister for Finance and of the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry.  There is also a technical provision concerning the control of staff pay included in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A number of Members suggested last week that in addition to thoroughbred breeding the National Stud should get involved in the sport horse sector.  While I have no objection in principle to this suggestion, I would have some concerns <Col N="402" /> about its feasibility given the very different cost structures which obtain in the two sectors.  At the lower end of the scale in the thoroughbred sector, there are so many no sale appendages one would have to question that divergence, because sport horses are making very considerable sums in many cases.  However, if the National Stud were to get involved in sport horses it would have to look for a minimum stud fee of at least £3,000 to cover its costs, which is far in excess of the going rate in the general sport horse industry.</P>
    <P>Members will be aware that a range of schemes have been introduced under the operational programme for rural development to assist the sport horse sector.  One of these schemes offers generous grants to stallion owners to encourage them to purchase top quality stallions for use in the sport horse sector. These stallions are located throughout the country thereby reducing the time and transport costs involved in having mares taken to them.  As I have already stated, I have no objection in principle to the National Stud becoming involved in this area.</P>
    <P>I like Senator Henry's suggestion that specimens of native Irish breeds should be maintained by the Stud in its visitors' section and I will be recommending to the board that consideration be given to this idea.  It would be an additional attraction for visitors to the Japanese Gardens, the museum and the core activity itself.  They have a large herd of cattle which I hope they will make optimal use of from now on.  If they had some Connemara ponies, Irish draught and other native breeds it would be another tourist attraction.  There is a considerable amount of land in the National Stud &mdash; approximately 800 acres.  It has not been very remunerative up to now and I believe it could be used for that purpose.</P>
    <P>The question of the proposed Kildare by-pass was also raised by a number of Senators.  I have been assured by the Department of the Environment and Kildare County Council that every effort has been made to minimise the effect of the by-pass on the National Stud.  I have <Col N="403" /> been assured that there is no realistic alternative to the proposed route and while it will cause some disruption to the Stud, I believe that the Stud is capable of coping with these difficulties.  I understand that about 80 acres of the 800 acres are affected.  Senator Dardis and Senator Roche raised this matter.  Senator Dardis was also concerned that the by-pass might direct visitors to the Stud and away from Kildare town.  I will draw the attention of the Minister for the Environment to this concern.</P>
    <P>Senator Fahey expressed disappointment at the delay in the provision to increase the Stud's power to borrow. While it is true that this proposal has been under consideration for some time, it must be realised that the purchase of stallions is high risk business and to do so on borrowed money in a period of high interest rates would compound the risk. I see the borrowing facility of benefit principally to enable the Stud to move quickly when a suitable stallion becomes available.  Unless a source of permanent capital is available to be tapped, the purchase of a stallion with borrowed money would not, in my view, be advisable.</P>
    <P>The point has been made repeatedly that in regard to the quality of the stallions a well known name would be required.  The Stud should wait for the most worthwhile name before endeavouring to purchase.  The delay might have been gratuitous in that the price of bloodstock generally has come down very substantially since the Arabs were more heavily involved.  While I am not making excuses for the delay, it might have worked to our advantage in this case.</P>
    <P>I will also pass on to board members a number of recommendations in regard to sponsorship, syndication or partnerships in the ownership of stallions.  At present, a number of stallions are owned by outside interests.  If you want to get a top quality stallion, you have to pay a considerable sum of money and it would make sense to have some form of syndication.</P>
    <P>I was very interested in the suggestions on training.  It is seldom, if ever, you find <Col N="404" /> a student, on completion of the course, not being able to find a job.  A number of students have been successful in getting very high profile jobs at a number of prestigious international studs, including the British National Stud.  I will be discussing this with the board.  I know that the board and management are already in contact with educational institutions and the Department of Education to enlist their support to broaden the base of this course and make it more exciting. In most courses in agricultural colleges, for example, and in a number of vocational schemes, FÁS is directly involved and there is a degree of subsidisation. I will also look at that matter.</P>
    <P>Improving the tourist amenity of the Stud as well as the core activity was also referred to.  There is no doubt that the Japanese gardens are outstanding.  The Stud's capacity to cultivate and look after rare plants is as good if not better than its capacity to breed thoroughbred horses.  I have always enjoyed visiting the Japanese Gardens and the visitors section of the Stud, especially when there were race meetings in the area.  That suggests the possibility of linking tourism with race meetings.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Minister was not suffering from withdrawal symptoms after the races.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I was going to make the point that I always ensured my visit to the Stud was before the race meetings rather than afterwards.  I am glad to say that the Stud has invested a considerable amount of money in the Japanese Gardens and Bord Fáilte has made a grant of £300,000 available.  There is a total investment of £600,000 in the Gardens and I look forward to that improved facility being available to tourists this summer.  I know that the board and management have looked at better ways of advertising this unique facility because many people are not aware of its existence. You do not see signposts for it and there is no reference in literature to the Japanese Gardens.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The horse museum is fascinating. <Col N="405" /> There are many artifacts and memorabilia relating to the horse industry. Arkle's skeleton has been mentioned and we are still searching for Shergar's skeleton; maybe some day we will put that there too.  We could do more, particularly in the area of videos.  I enjoy watching videos of the great Irish bred, owned and trained Gold Cup and Grand National winners.</P>
    <P>A number of other matters were raised during the debate, including the accounts.  Generally accounts are a bit behind the times.  Only recently we laid in the Library in the House of the Oireachtas, the 1991 and 1990 accounts. The 1992 accounts will not be available for a while but the board is planning to produce draft audit accounts on a current year basis so that financial details will be completely up to date in the future.  I welcome that because we hear of many organisations and companies getting into financial trouble, deep trouble, before you know it.  It is important particularly in the case of State bodies, that the Oireachtas is kept up to date on how matters stand financially.</P>
    <P>This Bill should be seen in the context of a five year plan for the Stud.  The five year plan has been mentioned by a number of people.  Senator Kelleher talked about the desirability of having a plan and a programme.  One of the things I asked the new board to do was to update this five year plan because it was good but it became dated.  Apart from the core business and the impact of the plan, there is the question of the farm and the type of farming to be done there.  Senator Dardis referred specifically to that matter.  He is a farmer in the locality and he said it was possible to make money from farming in County Kildare.  With 800 acres, in County Kildare, it is difficult to see, under certain farming enterprises how you could not break even but to lose money there raises questions because even if the land is leased you should at least come out on the credit side.</P>
    <P>I have asked the board to update the five year plan and I should have it shortly. The plan will consist of a number of elements.  The first priority will be the <Col N="406" /> overall financial viability of the core business in the Stud.  I am very concerned about the financial activities of State bodies under my aegis.  I see no reason why State bodies should allow their finances to get into such a serious situation that the only recourse is for the good old taxpayer to bail them out.  If the finances are going in a certain direction, corrective action should be taken at an early stage. The second priority will be the rationalisation of the farm activities.  I feel very strongly that it should be possible to make an income from that asset.  The third priority is updating the tourist attractions.  The fourth priority will be having resources available for the purchase of stallions, in order to ensure that the Stud continues its valuable contribution to improving the thoroughbred sector.  There are about 25,000 people directly and indirectly employed in this section and there is potential for a substantial increase in those numbers.  There is also a capacity to increase exports and the number of jobs in the industry.</P>
    <P>I want to thank Senators for their constructive contributions which will take into account, and I will ask the board to take them into account.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="National Stud (Amendment) Bill, 1993:" RHead="Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>National Stud (Amendment) Bill, 1993: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 1 is out of order as it involves a potential charge upon the Revenue.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 1 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 2, between lines 14 and 15, to insert the following new subsection:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="407" />&ldquo;(2) Notwithstanding anything contained in the Principal Act (or the Act of 1976) shares may be subscribed for by any person, with the consent of the Minister for Finance.&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>The reason for this amendment is that the Stud would need to raise a substantial amount of money for a more effective breeding programme.  We all agree that the Stud has a responsibility to smaller breeders, the majority in the industry who do not have many mares and by standing stallions of reasonable merit at a reasonable cost they help the industry. However, I believe there are opportunities at the top end of the market.</P>
    <P>The Stud is a flag-ship for the industry in Ireland.  If people come from abroad to look at the bloodstock industry one of the places we should be proud to bring them is the National Stud.  It has a very fine tradition.  It had Lord Gayle, Ahanoora and other good stallions standing there which made a good deal of money.  One good stallion would cost £7 million or £8 million.  I agree with the Minister about asking the taxpayer to bear the burden in respect of charges to the Stud; that is the background to the amendment.</P>
    <P>I am not suggesting that the Stud should be privatised; I made that clear at Second Stage, but I am suggesting there is an opportunity to invest in the Stud. My understanding of the management of the Stud is that they would welcome such a development.  There is one stallion there at the moment called Dancing Dissident. There are 17 shares in it but the nomination to that stallion has fallen from £6,000 to £3,500 a year.  That is a symptom of what is happening in the industry.</P>
    <P>I agree with the Minister that the delay may be to the Stud's advantage because of the state of the industry, but it is a highly skilled job to buy a successful stallion.  There are very few people in this country with the competence to consistently buy the best stallions.  Such people, whether Irish or foreign, should be encouraged to participate in the work <Col N="408" /> of the Stud, for two reasons, one, what it could do for the industry, generally, and the other, to enable us to buy the best stallions.  We want to be able to say to visitors to the Stud that we are proud of it as a flagship for the industry.  Those are the reasons I recommend the amendment to the House.</P>
    <P>The Minister said he was concerned about the financial activities of State bodies and about to have recourse to the taxpayer to bail them out.  The intention of the amendment is to ensure that it will not be the taxpayer who bears this cost but the equine industry.</P>
    <P>People have enormous amounts of money to invest in this industry provided they see that it is run properly and that it allows for a genuine sense of participation. In Kildare we have seen Arab investors transform the industry and the countryside.  They have provided an enormous number of jobs on an area of land which if used for ordinary farming would provide only a fraction of those jobs.  That is the background to this amendment which I commend to the Minister.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDarcy" hpid="Mr. D'Arcy Mr. D'Arcy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D'Arcy</NameTxt>
      <P>I support this amendment which I signed along with Senators Dardis and Honan.  Senator Dardis said correctly that the equine industry is going through a serious recession at the moment, not only in Ireland but all over the world.  The requirements of the industry may change radically in a short period and I would like to point that out to the Minister.  There must be scope to broaden the interest of the National Stud. Syndication has been normal practice for the last 25 years in the horse industry and in other industries as well.  It has been rightly stated that a top class stallion may cost £6 million or £7 million.  It is difficult to expect any organisation, even the National Stud, to pay that amount of money.  If the Stud has that amount of money it would be well advised to invest a million pounds in each of seven stallions rather than £7 million in one stallion. The risk which the Minister has already referred to is thereby reduced.  In order to allow the Stud this flexibility I appeal <Col N="409" /> to the Minister to accept this amendment which does not interfere with any provision of the Bill.  Overall, its adoption would be of benefit to the Stud.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. Walsh) Joe Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. Walsh)</NameTxt>
      <P>I oppose this amendment.  The most important consideraton is to put the National Stud on a sound financial footing.  I have no difficulty with syndication or part ownership and I know the board do not envisage having the means to buy any stallion of international repute outright.  In future the Stud expects to participate in the purchase of stallions through part ownership, syndication joint venture or other partnership possibilities.  I do not see why a stallion in which the National Stud has no stake could not stand at the Stud if the owner wanted to house it there for some time.  The possibility of investing in a stallion and investing in the share capital of the Stud are two different matters. Rightly or wrongly people would see the latter, on however small a scale, as a drift towards privatisation.  This matter has not been considered by the Government and therefore I cannot accept this amendment which I appreciate was put down for the best motives.  I repeat that I have no difficulty with the idea of shares in stallions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDarcy" hpid="Mr. D'Arcy Mr. D'Arcy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D'Arcy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am disappointed the Minister is taking a narrow view on this issue.  We are giving the Minister what he is asking for but he is putting a restriction on the amendment by saying he is not prepared to accept it as such.  If this amendment is passed I presume it then has to go back for approval by the Dáil and could create a problem there.  Even if it does, it is worth the waiting period of returning it to the Dáil if the amendment is accepted, ultimately.</P>
      <P>I have spoken in this debate about privatisation but the word has been taken out of the context in which I used it. Privatisation here means syndication and partnership, which is normal practice for a national stud.  I am not prepared to accept the privatisation of the National Stud under any circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="410" /> I had intended an amendment similar to this one by Senator Dardis.  I appeal to the Minister to reconsider it even if there is a waiting period involved in respect of getting it through the Dáil.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister would agree that there is not a great deal of difference between his objective and that of this side of the House.  All want to place the Stud on a sound financial footing. Nevertheless there should be a means by which private enterprise could have a stake in the Stud.  We need not confine this debate to stallion purchase; the Japanese Gardens are part of the Stud, also and I am sure there are business people in Kildare who would be happy to help promote and develop that resource.  The Minister could insert safeguards into the Bill to ensure that the fixed assets of the Stud could never fall into private ownership.  This was done in respect of Greencore.  I would go along with those safeguards as I believe it should remain a State stud.  The Stud could become a flagship for the Irish horse industry, demonstrating our capacity to reach international equine standards.</P>
      <P>On the syndication of expensive stallions, I am sure that indigenous companies in the agri-business sector if given the opportunity would participate in that type of activity.  Greencore might consider buying a share in a stallion and having it stand at the National Stud since Greencore market horse feed.  That aspect might be explored.  Our argument here is about how best to achieve an objective we are all agreed upon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no reason why an individual, company or organisation should not invest in a stallion along with the National Stud, in joint ownership, partnership or joint venture involving any number of shares or percentage of ownership.  I would welcome that development as I know the board do not envisage being able to own any world class stallion outright again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have difficulty however, with the major question of part ownership of the <Col N="411" /> share capital which is what the amendment suggests.  This proposal would require the most careful consideration and the building in of safeguards as Senator Dardis said.  I cannot accept this amendment but if that proposal is put forward at a future date it will be considered in detail by the Government and by the Departments of Finance and Agriculture. It is not a proposal I am prepared to accept today.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDarcy" hpid="Mr. D'Arcy Mr. D'Arcy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D'Arcy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister said he would object to part ownership of the Stud's share capital but not to part ownership of a stallion.  They amount to the same thing moneywise, because the share capital is intended for the purchase of stallions as far as the Stud and the taxpayer are concerned.  All we are asking is for a vehicle to be provided.  I appeal to the Minister to reconsider.  As Senator Dardis said there is very little difference between what we and the Minister are saying, but part ownership of the share capital is the same money as part ownership of the stallion.  In fact, there is more risk in part ownership of the stallion because the share capital is used to purchase the stallion.  That is the situation and it should be accepted at this stage.</P>
      <P>The Minister has learned from experience how difficult it is to get legislation through the Dáil to the Seanad or even to get it on the agenda.  It has taken six to eight years to get this legislation through both Houses.  When I was in Government in 1984-86 this legislation was requested.  It takes six to eight years to get legislation on the agenda.  For that reason we are offering a vehicle which would be beneficial to the National Stud and to the horse breeding industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>For the reasons I have stated I cannot accept this amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDarcy" hpid="Mr. D'Arcy Mr. D'Arcy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D'Arcy</NameTxt>
      <P>I put down an amendment <Col N="412" /> on section 2 which was ruled out of order and I do not question that decision. However, in putting down the amendment I took into consideration the safeguards needed.  Under my amendment the share capital of the company shall be as determined from time to time by the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry with the consent of the Minister for Finance.</P>
      <P>It is difficult to run a stud by legislation. I was attempting here to remove the cap but build in a safeguard to ensure that any proposals made for moneys in respect of the National Stud would have to be approved by the Minister for Finance, not by the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry.</P>
      <P>During the debate on amendment No. 2 we argued about the same issue.  The provisions the Minister is making now take into account a five year plan.  If the horse industry improves as I hope over the next couple of years, the existing facilities will be used up within two years. The Minister will then be in a similar situation to that which occurred in the National Stud a few years ago when Ahonoora had to be sold to get money to run the Stud, which I said at the time was a great mistake.  Without amending legislation it was not possible to approve further moneys for the National Stud.  If the Stud wants to buy a stallion costing £2 million or £3 million, £1 million of the share capital will be used up and if it cannot get a partner in the syndicate to invest too, under the present legislation that stallion cannot be bought.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have given the Senator enough scope.  He can only deal with what is in section 2, not the amendment which was ruled out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDarcy" hpid="Mr. D'Arcy Mr. D'Arcy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D'Arcy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not dealing with the amendment but with what is in section 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If the Minister or the board of the National Stud has a good proposition but the money allowed under the legislation is spent, the Minister should be able to make an order, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, to remove the cap and allow further borrowing.  This facility <Col N="413" /> would benefit the board and the Minister who might have to wait four or five years to get legislation through.  I envisage this £10 million being spent in two years and, for the next three years, the Minister arguing with the board, and probably the Taoiseach, to get further legislation through.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I know the amendment was ruled out of order but I would like to comment on the section.</P>
      <P>In this Bill the share capital is increased from £5 million to £10 million.  Perhaps it is my west Cork background, but I tend to be very prudent about financial matters.  I invited a financial person to take over the chairmanship of the National Stud and said that the Stud had been losing an average, about £0.5 million per annum and I did not want that to continue.  I asked him to turn it around.</P>
      <P>Although we are increasing the share capital from £5 million to £10 million, I would not wish to give a wrong signal to the board.  This does not mean that on any occasion the board wants a few million pounds all it has to do is get the permission of the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry and the Minister for Finance.  The State is being extremely helpful to the board by increasing the share capital from £5 million to £10 million.  That should see the Stud through this millenium, and I know the chairman and the board are also viewing it in that light.  If in the next millenium additional share capital is required, the amending legislation will have to go through both Houses.</P>
      <P>It is no harm to have very strong financial guidelines because stud fee income has come down in the last couple of years from £1.5 million per annum to £0.25 million, and they still have more or less the same stock.  I would like to see the Irish National Stud at Tully and its ancillary activities, go from strength to strength.  If, for some reason, in a number of years' time, additional finance is needed, if we are still around we will seek to provide it.  However, I would not wish to give a signal that we were making additional finance freely available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="414" /> Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I want the Minister to clarify a point.  He mentioned the need to resource the Stud properly.  There is the question of how much stallions are likely to cost; £5 million will not buy many stallions.  Is it intended that the purchase price of the stallions will be funded out of the additional £5 million share capital or will it be funded out of borrowings?  I am not clear about how the purchase of stallions will be funded. If stallions are to be purchased out of borrowings, is £5 million enough?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDarcy" hpid="Mr. D'Arcy Mr. D'Arcy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D'Arcy</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a cap on borrowing of £5 million.  I ask the same question as Senator Dardis: with what will the stallions be purchased?  Will it be with the share capital or the borrowings?  Will the borrowings be used to develop other farming activities at the Stud?  The Minister says that borrowing capacity will not exceed £5 million.  On what calculation does he base that figure?  Without additional information it is difficult for us to understand how the Minister arrived at that figure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>We are increasing the borrowing capacity from £0.5 million to £5 million and the share capital from £5 million to £10 million.  It is for the Board to decide to use borrowings or share capital, or a combination of both, for whatever purpose they see fit.  The £5 million ceiling on borrowing and the £10 million ceiling on share capital were agreed on the basis of a five-year programme put forward by the Stud.  To restore the Stud to financial soundness and stability, this level of borrowing and share capital was considered adequate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDarcy" hpid="Mr. D'Arcy Mr. D'Arcy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D'Arcy</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we see the text of the five-year programme?  There is surely nothing secret about it since the Stud is a public body.  It would have been useful <Col N="415" /> to this debate if that programme had been made available to us.  I would have liked to have seen it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarianMcGennis" hpid="Mrs. McGennis Mrs. McGennis">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGennis</NameTxt>
      <P>It is extraordinary when the Minister brings forward a Bill to facilitate the needs of the National Stud based on its programme of requirements, that the Opposition should seek to extend it all over the place.  We are criticised daily for the insufficient amounts of money available to various departments.  This Bill is a direct response to a request from the National Stud, yet the Opposition wishes to give the Stud a blank cheque with little accountability.  The Minister's efforts to make the Stud economically viable seem to be turned on their head.  Can we not show some common sense and let the matter proceed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>On the contrary, we do not want to give anybody a blank cheque and we have been making that point clear since&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarianMcGennis" hpid="Mrs. McGennis Mrs. McGennis">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGennis</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what it sounded like&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>We want to ensure that this commercial activity, which is a high spending and capital-intensive one, will be properly funded.  That is the intention.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDarcy" hpid="Mr. D'Arcy Mr. D'Arcy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D'Arcy</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this House is to tease out Bills with the Minister. I am not being irresponsible with regard to section 2 of this Bill; I am acting responsibly on behalf of an important industry.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 4 and 5 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="416" />
      <i>Sitting suspended at 11.55 a.m. and resumed at 12 noon.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Greencore:" RHead="Statements">
    <Title>Greencore: Statements.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Each Senator has ten minutes and statements will conclude at 1 p.m.  I call on the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Mr. Sherlock Mr. Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>A Leas-Chathaoirligh, we have lost five minutes.  It was agreed this morning to give one hour to this debate.  Would you allow for that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the House agree to sit until 1.05 p.m.? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeWalsh" hpid="Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. Walsh) Joe Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. Walsh)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Seanad will be aware of the recent press statement issued on behalf of the Minister for Finance in relation to the Government's shareholding in Greencore plc.  The Minister for Finance indicated that it is the Government's intention to proceed with the disposal of its residual shareholding of 30.4 per cent in Greencore plc.  A major international food group and a number of Irish food companies have expressed interest in acquiring these shares and the Government has decided to give all interested parties until Wednesday, 24 March, to put forward proposals to the Department of Finance for their purchase.</P>
      <P>When the Irish Sugar Company was restructured, and floated on the Stock Exchange in April 1991, certain safeguards were put in place to ensure that the Irish sugar industry was protected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Under section 2 of the Sugar Act, 1991, the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry acquired a special share in Greencore, the holding company of Siúicre Éireann cpt.  The rights attached to this special share, which the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry may not dispose of, are set down in the Articles of Association of Greencore plc.  The special share ensures that none of the following events can arise without the <Col N="417" /> Minister's prior consent in writing: (a) any change in certain specified articles in the Articles of Association of Greencore; (b) the winding up of Greencore; (c) the sale of more than 49 per cent of Siúicre Éireann cpt. which is a subsidiary of Greencore; (d) the disposal of specified sugar assets, including the Irish sugar quota which is held by Siúicre Éireann; (e) the creation of a new class of shares in Greencore and (f) the building up by one shareholder or a consortium of shareholders, other than the Minister for Finance, of more than a 15 per cent shareholding in Greencore after flotation.</P>
    <P>In summary, the special share prevents the disposal of the controlling interest in Siúicre Éireann or the sugar assets including the Irish sugar quota, and prevents a single shareholder, or a group of shareholders acting together, from gaining control of Greencore plc.</P>
    <P>Now let me deal with any concerns which arise in connection with the Irish sugar quota.  Ireland is allocated a sugar quota of 200,200 tonnes under EC legislation. Member states are required to allocate sugar quota to each sugar producing undertaking in their territory.  As Ireland has only one such undertaking, viz. Siúicre Éireann cpt., the entire quota is allocated to that company.</P>
    <P>Current EC legislation does not provide for the transfer of any quota, or part thereof, from one member state to another.  The question of relocating Ireland's sugar quota in another member state does not therefore arise.  It is precluded under national legislation, section 2 of the Sugar Act, 1991 and under Community legislation, so there is a double protection there.</P>
    <P>I should mention also that at the time of restructuring of Siúicre Éireann cpt in 1991, special arrangements were made to protect the workers engaged in the sugar industry, and Greencore employs up to 2,000 workers.  A provision was made in the Sugar Act, 1991, to ensure that every employee of Siúicre Éireann prior to flotation, enjoyed the same rights and was subject to the same obligations after flotation of the company.  In that regard <Col N="418" /> also Siúicre Éireann and the unions drew up an agreement and lodged it with the Labour Relations Commission and registered with the Labour Court.  This agreement related to employees conditions, pay, continuity of employment, recognition of trade unions and continuation of existing procedures.  This agreement gave reassurance to workers whose interests were already protected under the European Communities (Safeguarding of Employee's Rights on Transfer of Undertaking) Regulations, 1980.  I want to stress that I fully endorse the contents of this agreement which I have no doubt constitutes a major protection for the rights of the employees in Siúicre Éireann.</P>
    <P>The Irish sugar industry is of immense importance to the Irish economy.  Some 1.3 million tonnes of beet are grown each year by about 5,000 beet farmers.  The value of this beet is nearly £60 million per annum.  The value of our sugar quota, which is over 200,000 tonnes would be conservatively estimated to be worth over £1 billion so we are talking about a considerable national asset and an important part of the agricultural and national economy.</P>
    <P>I want to assure this House that the disposal of any remaining Government shares in Greencore will not affect the operation of the Irish sugar industry which as I have already outlined is adequately safeguarded because of the special share which stays in operation irrespective of the profile of the shareholding and Community regulations.</P>
    <P>May I recall that one of the major justifications for restructuring Siúicre Éireann was to enable the development of a major food enterprise based on indigenous resources with a view to maximising added value, exports, and, critically, the creation of additional jobs. Since its formation Greencore has progressed and developed well and is managed most professionally.  Greencore is one of our largest and most broadly based industries, involved not only in beet growing and sugar production but also in flour milling, malting and various other <Col N="419" /> activities.  It is one of our finest indigenous companies.</P>
    <P>I would welcome a bid for the residual shareholding from Irish companies.  Here is a golden opportunity to develop an indigenous company with Irish management. Irish based companies are already doing a fine job, not only in Ireland but also in Europe and in the United States.</P>
    <P>Proposals for the purchase of the Government's residual shareholding in Greencore will not be viewed solely on the basis of the price of the shares.  The existing bid is for £2.60 per share bringing in about £70 million.  That will not be the critical consideration.  The critical consideration will be the strategic development of this agricultural industry, this indigenous resource and its value in terms of turnover, contribution to the economy and potential for retaining existing and creating additional jobs.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  Everybody shares the Minister's concern about the Irish sugar industry and agrees that it should be allowed and encouraged to develop to the economic advantage of the State and of all employed in the industry.</P>
      <P>It is unfortunate that while the Minister said a great deal with which we agree, he said little about the events of the last few days.  This Government and the last Government have not been able to sell shares in a semi-privatised company without a major row.  Last year when the then Minister for Finance, quite rightly, sold shares the Irish Association of Investment Managers objected as did a large number of financial institutions.  There is now much more going on behind the scenes than is conveyed by the Minister's factually correct but not sufficiently informative speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Irish people fear foreign investment and foreign industrial presence especially in investment matters.  It is ironic that last week we were pleading with Digital to maintain their presence here and this week we are trying to scare off a multinational company making a bid for 30.4 <Col N="420" /> per cent of Greencore.  Why this fear of selling 30.4 per cent?  Indeed we will not be selling 30.4 per cent &mdash; I am sure the Minister will agree &mdash; but 29.9 per cent; the other 0.4 per cent will have to go to the market because of Stock Exchange rules.  Why are we so frightened of selling a small minority holding which will not give control of the company to any foreign buyer?  It will give the buyer 29.9 per cent, not over 50 per cent.  We are apparently balking at selling even 29.9 per cent to a foreign investor.  Greencore &mdash; the Minister can correct me on this &mdash; set up this deal with a foreign investor because it received support neither from Government nor from Irish investors. There were no funds available from Government in the event of a rights issue or of any other call on funds.</P>
    <P>Greencore has been badly frustrated during the last year or two; it cannot expand for lack of the capital and the Government is not a supporting shareholder. The Government has been sitting on its shares waiting for a buyer; it has not been prepared to put money into the company.  Although the Government &mdash; or some members of Government &mdash; obviously agreed in principle that this sale should go ahead, we are now looking for a so-called &ldquo;Irish&rdquo; buyer to purchase the shares at a similar price.</P>
    <P>The Minister said there has been a firm bid of 260p per share which seems like a good price.  I do not know if that reported bid of 260p is accurate but the Minister is undoubtedly well informed on this.  The market price jumped 29p yesterday to 267½p.  It has fallen slightly this morning. The Government was offered extraordinarily good value for its shares.  It is unusual for a bid for a large amount of shares to be made at considerably more than the market price.  Suddenly the Government hesitated.  There were internal problems and now the shares must be put out to tender to what is called an Irish buyer.  That is a faulty principle given our unjustifiable fear of multinationals in Ireland.  The best hope for Greencore is a multinational shareholder with funds to expand the company and to allow it to go on the acquisition trail it <Col N="421" /> has wanted to follow for the last year or two.  Jobs are more likely to be created by a multinational shareholder than by Irish companies scraping around, as they have done in the last few days since this became public &mdash; I suspect against the wishes of the Government &mdash; looking for partners to get involved in a company not necessarily compatible with their own.</P>
    <P>Can the Minister tell me if an Irish company bids less than 260p, will the Government sell to that company?  Is it prepared to sell the shares at a discount to ensure the company is kept in Irish hands even though only 30 per cent of the company is for sale and the majority shareholding will remain Irish?  Is it Government policy now to forego commercial criteria?  Perhaps somebody on the Government benches could tell me why it is necessary to keep the company in Irish ownership when the Minister says blatantly that he would retain control over the sugar quote even if we sold 100 per cent of the company.  This is muddled, confused and wrong thinking. In the Minister's own words the company is protected.  It does not matter whether we sell to an Irish buyer or not because the quota is protected.  The Minister's thinking is confused like that of other members of Government when they see anything falling out of Irish hands.  We should not adopt that attitude but welcome the fact that multinationals are prepared to invest in a thriving Irish company.  The board of Greencore is to be congratulated for setting up the deal and selling the Government's share, which is apparently what they did.</P>
    <P>I understand fully what the Minister said in an aside, about creating jobs. However, it is misleading to suggest that by keeping the company solely in Irish hands jobs will be created.  We need to be honest about this.  The Government made a decision which it revealed in last week's budget, to raise £150 million by selling its stake in Greencore to a private sector.  At present, it can only do so by selling to a single buyer.  The Minister knows as well as I do that it would be almost impossible to place these shares on the Stock Market in the current environment. <Col N="422" /> There is insufficient liquidity in the Stock Market to sell this shareholding to a variety of institutional shareholders. The Government is lucky to have received this bid and if I were the Minister I would thank the board of Greencore and sell the shares to a constructive overseas company prepared to inject capital into Greencore at a critical time thereby helping the Government's budgetary arithmetic.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. R. Kiely Mr. R. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>May I share my time with Senator Roche?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. R. Kiely Mr. R. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister and his statement of intention to sell shares in Greencore.  The Minister for Finance in his Budget Statement indicated the Government's intention to proceed with the disposal of its residue shareholding of 30.4 per cent in Greencore and also stated that an international food group and a number of Irish food companies have expressed interest in acquiring these shares.</P>
      <P>There are fears among farmers, beet growers and workers in Greencore as to what the consequences might be if these shares were sold to a multinational.  Some people, however, have no fears about multinationals buying these shares.  As Senator Ross pointed out, the buying of such shares would not give the buyer complete control.  However, given our unfortunate experience of multinationals over the years, and lately, some of the objections to multinationals buying these shares can be justified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It appears Greencore approached a multinational food group in the United States to interest them in the shares without the knowledge of Irish groups.  It is surprising that a multinational should be made aware of the proposed sale of these shares before an Irish company.  It is a poor reflection on all the money invested in Irish education that we should look abroad first for people to manage our affairs.  We must be assured whatever sale takes place that the interests of beet <Col N="423" /> growers and Greencore workers will be protected.  I live close to the sugar factory at Mallow which gives great service to local beet-growers.  At one stage it was compulsory for farmers to grow beet and now there is a quota to restrict it.  I am delighted to see under Article 2 of the Sugar Act, 1991 that the golden share will protect our quota and cannot be interfered with.  That will allay the fears of farmers with quotas and also allay the fears of Greencore workers.</P>
    <P>The farming organisations that favour rationalisations, generally &mdash; the ICMSA and the IFA &mdash; are in favour of the shares being sold to an Irish company.  It is not long since there were four sugar factories in Ireland.  That was under General Costello who did a great job managing Siúicre Eireann as it was known at the time.  Now we have two sugar factories.  We should also be aware of the fear that with selling, privatisation and rationalisation, we could be reduced to one sugar factory.  I am sure the Minister will allay those fears when he replies.</P>
    <P>Many workers are involved in the Mallow sugar factory, processing beet and making cattle feed products vital to the farming community in the Mallow and Carlow areas.  It is important whatever sale takes place that the interests of farmers, beet producers and workers are protected.  Some people favour a multinational shareholder on the basis that it might invest money in Ireland.  I would prefer if the shares were sold to an Irish company.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank my colleague for sharing his time with me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I compliment Senator Ross on his contribution; I agree with much of what he said.  There has been a kneejerk reaction from certain public representatives to plans to dispose of the remaining parcel of shares in Greencore.  These kneejerk reactions could result in the Irish taxpayers getting less than true value of Greencore shares.  They could result also in prohibiting the company establishing long term international connections which would be valuable not only to suppliers, <Col N="424" /> but in the long term, to employees. Criticism is particularly hypocritical when it comes from persons who participated in the Government of 1983-87, which effectively gave away a partly State owned company producing non-sugar sweeteners.  Some of the recent adverse reaction could also have a major detrimental impact on the yield to the people of this country from any future disposal of State assets.</P>
    <P>I can understand why people should be disenchanted with multinationals.  I certainly have no remit for them, but we need to be a little more cautious in our comments than some commentators have been.  Placing the balance of the shares with Irish institutions and pension funds without competition would undoubtedly result in the shares being bought at below their true price.  Senator Ross is correct when he suggests that something we do not know of may be going on in the background.  The reality is that managers of institutional shareholdings in recent months have not been overly anxious to boost the share prices of either Greencore or Irish Life because they were fully aware that further placement was to come.  An arrangement to sell off these shares to an Irish buyer without overseas competition would not prevent the buyer from selling on to a multinational subsequently at a considerable profit.  Such an arrangement would not only deny the Irish taxpayer the true price of the asset but would allow a privileged few to make an additional killing in further dealings.</P>
    <P>Confining the sell-off to the Irish market could, as observed by Fine Gael's finance spokesperson in the Dáil, have the additional undesirable effect of absorbing any liquidity in the Irish capital market, to the detriment of small and medium sized firms currently seeking capital for expansion.  Senator Ross touched on that issue too.</P>
    <P>In the current context and in the light of historical facts, criticism from politicians who supported the Government between 1983 and 1987 could be considered hypocritical.  That Government allowed Wheat Industries Limited, a company partly owned by Ceimicí Teo., <Col N="425" /> to be effectively given away at its written asset value.  That was and remains a national scandal that has never been adequately explained or examined.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Mr. Sherlock Mr. Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>That was another Fianna Fáil Government and Deputy Lenihan was the Minister.  The Senator should check his facts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Roche, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I have checked my facts. The Ministers for Industry and Commerce and for Agriculture prevented the Irish sugar company from buying that company in 1984.  As a result of this a major Irish producer of non-sugar sweetners was disposed of to a multinational. The company has changed hands several times over the intervening years and it is interesting to note its current owner.</P>
      <P>We need a more balanced debate on the issue of the disposal of a minority shareholding in a company which is already privatised.  We need to be careful in the criticisms we make.  Other shareholdings currently owned by the Irish people will need to be disposed of.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there an agreement on that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>Some of the commentary and interference of recent times will contribute towards having the present proposal approved and made it likely that in future disposal of State shares Irish taxpayers will receive less than the true value of their shareholdings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand Seantors Quinn, Sherlock and Dardis will share time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I had not planned to speak but I am using this opportunity to make a brief contribution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Business is difficult all over the world and is becoming more so.  To survive and to thrive in business one needs competitive advantage for which international links are necessary especially in <Col N="426" /> the food business.  We should not be concerned about who owns the business, but about how that competitive advantage might be obtained.  If competitive advantage is best given by a company with international links, we should support that partnership wholeheartedly rather than be concerned about enabling a more familiar Irish company to acquire ownership. Let us seek the competitive advantage in this case.  Whichever company Greencore chooses as its preferred partner, let us sell the shares there to make sure that Greencore survives.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Mr. Sherlock Mr. Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>My party believes the public interest will not be served by the decision to sell the 30 per cent public shareholding in Greencore and will resolutely oppose any such move.  As a former employee of the company I feel strongly about this proposal.</P>
      <P>The circumstances surrounding the reported bid for the 30 per cent share by a US company require immediate clarification. In particular, the Minister for Finance must say if he discussed with the management of Greencore the possibility of finding a buyer for the State's share. How can the Minister claim to have been unaware of the move?  Was the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry consulted in this matter?  As the holder of 30 per cent of the shares is he not represented on the board of the company? Do his representatives not let him know what is happening?  In a partnership Government why was the matter not discussed with An Tánaiste?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The only way to protect the jobs of Greencore employees and the interests of growers and hauliers is for the State to retain its present shareholding in the company which last year made a profit of £30 million.  The sale of its 30 per cent shareholding to outside interests apparently supported by the executives of the company would jeopardise an important element of our food industry.  The golden share would not protect the sugar quota as there is no obligation to produce the full 200,000 tonnes of sugar in this country. The Minister can have a golden share in the Articles of Association but there <Col N="427" /> is nothing to stop the company importing sugar; sugar has been imported into Ireland previously.</P>
    <P>The Labour Party should see this for the anti-public enterprise move and short-sighted decision that it is.  They should respond to the calls of workers and unions to retain the present element of public ownership, when the unions contributed so generously to the election campaign of many of the Labour TDs, up to £6,000 per constituency.</P>
    <P>One aspect that particularly concerns me was referred to by Senator Roche. In 1982 Ceimicí Teoranta joined with Wheat Industries Limited to establish in Ringaskiddy a plant to manufacture fructose corn syrup.  A limit was placed on the quantity that could be produced there.  I am not aware that that restriction has been lifted although another company ADM, has been looking at the factory obviously seeking a back door into the European market.</P>
    <P>When the food industry was separated from the sugar industry in the late sixties and linked to the great Heinz company, what happened?  We had vacant food factories in Mallow, Midleton and at Fastnet in Skibbereen.  Heinz was not interested in Irish workers or growers but was in profit and the company gobbled up our food industry.  The proposed link up between American multinationals and the Irish Sugar Company does not give grounds for hope when we see what happened when Erin Foods was linked to Heinz.  I call on the State to retain its 30 per cent shareholding in Greencore and on the Labour Party to support that call. It is the only way to protect jobs.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Quinn for sharing his time with me.  This debate reminds me of the point made on the Order of Business that all shades of opinion should be represented in the House.  I disagree with some of Senator Sherlock's statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Progressive Democrats support the disposal of the State's 30 per cent shareholding in Greencore under certain specified conditions.  The first condition <Col N="428" /> is that the best possible price for the holding should be obtained for the taxpayer. Second, the strategic interest of Irish farmers and in particular of the 5,000 sugar beet growers should be fully protected.  The Irish quota must be fully protected also and I have been reassured by what the Minister said about that in his statement.  Thirdly, the vital interest of Greencore in the Irish food industry should be fully protected in the event of a disposal, together with the jobs of 2,000 food industry workers.  I am satisfied that the golden share protects the vital national interest in the industry adequately.</P>
    <P>I would like an Irish company to take up this shareholding but like Senator Quinn and Senator Ross I have no difficulty about large cash rich multinational companies coming into Ireland.  Our experience with Digital has not been the most fortunate but nevertheless that experience should not deter us from encouraging future international investment. If this country is seen as a haven for international investment, so much the better for the country.</P>
    <P>It is unquestionable that Greencore could be greatly helped by a company with money to inject into it.  It is badly in need of cash.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Mr. Sherlock Mr. Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>After making £30 million profit?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>We were generous to the Senator this afternoon and allowed him to have his say.  The Senator should not abuse the privilege.</P>
      <P>It is my absolute conviction in respect of some proposals in the budget that money raised from the disposal of State companies such as this should not be devoted to current spending.  It should be used for capital expenditure; otherwise we go down the dangerous road of selling the family silver to fund current spending.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It seems to me from statements made by the Minister for Finance, Deputy B. Ahern, in the Dáil that he and his Department were not aware that Greencore seemed to be touting the world for business <Col N="429" /> partners.  The shareholding for sale is not Greencore's but the State's.  It is for the Government to decide on its disposal, not for Greencore executives to seek pals in international financial markets.</P>
    <P>I support the proposal to dispose of the holding on the conditions I have mentioned and reiterate that the sale should not be used to fund current sending.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to share my time with Senator Cashin and Senator O'Kennedy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald) Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Dardis's objection that the board of Greencore should tout Government shares.  That board did not cover itself with glory on the occasion of the company's flotation as we well know.  There has been an attempt to railroad the sale of this shareholding through on the basis of the tick tack operations common to financial circles here and abroad &mdash; an operation Senator Ross understands.  I do not blame Senator Ross who moves in a world that possibly does not understand fear of multinationals.  If the Senator got on his bike and visited the towns and cities of Ireland he would learn about the fear of multinationals.  Ask people in Galway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Ask the Labour Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>When significant control is transferred to interests outside the State the hope that that outside interest will involve itself deeply in advancing the future of Irish industry is a forlorn one. Every Government since the foundation of the State has said that the way forward for Ireland is to develop an indigenous, highly efficient food industry.  This has been done to some extent.  Companies seeking partners outside the State ignore Kerry Co-op and Waterford Co-op, success stories of immense proportions. There are other sectors within the food industry more than capable of developing <Col N="430" /> a highly efficient and profitable enterprise in tandem with Greencore.</P>
      <P>Greencore is a private company with a State shareholding; it is not a State company.  It was clearly signalled in the budget that £150 million would be raised by the disposal of some assets but there are ways of disposing of assets which take account of the national interest.  The way to do that in this case is to ensure that those shares are sold to an Irish company. I make no apologies for that.  We have seen the result of transferring power outside the State and of then trying to persuade people in Boston, New York, Chicago or wherever to come to our rescue.</P>
      <P>The fear of multinationals is real.  In my view, the board of Greencore acted highhandedly and without regard for the national interest.  The Government must now ensure that that interest is fully protected by whatever action is taken in relation to the disposal of shares.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Magner for sharing his time with me. Having listened to the contributions I feel vindicated by the provision I inserted in the Sugar Act, 1991 when it came before the Oireachtas.  This was the special provision of the special share which sought to ensure that the interests of the Sugar Company workers, the beet growers who supplied the company and the interests of the Irish people, because of this industry's national significance, would be protected and could not be ignored except with the sanction of the Oireachtas.  I do not expect the Oireachtas at any time to sanction the transfer of the sugar quota which, under European legislation, cannot be transferred from one country to another.  This is why I am reassured by the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry's notification this morning because it is the Minister, who carries the responsibility in relation to the special share.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have to achieve a balance between a vigorous effective indigenous company consistent with the recommendations of the Culliton report, and the reasonable promotion, and not just the protection, <Col N="431" /> of the interests of beet growers who supply Greencore and of workers who have contributed much to its success.  The profits that prepared Siúicre Éireann, as it was then, for partial privatisation were achieved as a result of redundancy packages. This was a hard reality and I had some reservations about it because it meant job losses in former Siúicre Éireann factories.  Profit is important in the world of international competitiveness but it should never be pursued without due regard to the contribution and dignity of workers.</P>
    <P>At this critical time of high unemployment in Ireland everything must enhance the capacity of our indigenous sector.  We must get out there and compete on a level basis with any other sector in any other country.  We have many advantages.  I believe this proposal based on the original legislation will facilitate that development but I accept that the legitimate concerns of workers and farmers must be protected.  I support the proposal before the House on the basis that the special share in the remit of the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry, affords adequate protection.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BillCashin" hpid="Mr. Cashin Mr. Cashin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cashin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Labour Party agree in principle that if 34 per cent of the State shareholding of Greencore is to be sold, it should be sold to an Irish company.  I agree with that.  In the fifties and sixties in Mallow, as Senator Sherlock said, the great General Michael J. Costello developed food processing factories &mdash; Erin Foods &mdash; in Mallow and other areas of County Cork.  We had the drive, the technology and the workforce to create something great for Ireland had it continued.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>At that time we had 300 steady jobs in Mallow.  Unfortunately, there was a change of management and the company merged with one of the American giants &mdash; Heinz &mdash; and the company was known as Heinz-Erin.  That merger benefited the few rather than the many.  In time, the company diminished in size to become a private factory with 60 workers and no conditions for the workforce.  That factory <Col N="432" /> is now for sale and the 300 jobs that could have been there are gone forever.</P>
    <P>If the Greencore shares should be sold, I believe they should go to an Irish company.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the proposed sale of shares in Greencore.  What is astonishing is that, after six weeks in this new Government, the Labour Party has agreed to the sale of shares in Irish companies, a privatisation they opposed during the election campaign.  The workers in Aer Lingus must look forward to the same fate as is happening here; the family silver will be sold to pay for the day to day expenses of running the country.</P>
      <P>I was a Member of the other House last year when the 15 per cent share was sold without anybody knowing.  The present Minister for Finance told us that it had been sold at the best time and on the best advice available.  On this occasion, he told us he did not know about the proposed sale or what the Greencore board is doing.  Is this another example of having his eye off the ball in these developments?  Is that the way the Government is going to continue?  In the space of a week we have learned that both parties have not got their eyes on the ball in relation to major issues.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a distortion of the facts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>The facts speak for themselves. Mr. Summers, who represents the workers, says it is a complete reversal of the policy on which the smaller party in Government fought the election.</P>
      <P>I did not accept, when the Greencore shares were sold last year, that the money should be used for day to day spending. If we sell State assets the money should be used for reinvestment in new jobs or in the reduction of our national debt.  I am sorry that this Government, at its first opportunity to make capital out of State shares, will use the moneys for day to day spending and there is more to come.  That is the reality.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I object to the Government deciding &mdash; and we do not know whether it has <Col N="433" /> been agreed &mdash; that only an Irish company can buy the shares.  In other words if I have a property to sell, one neighbour cannot buy it but two or three neighbours down the road can, and I must take whatever price is available.  That is what we are talking about.</P>
    <P>I hope the Minister will explain to his partners in Government that if some of the Irish companies mentioned by Senator Magner, for example, Waterford Co-op or Kerry purchase the 30 per cent share, they will be in direct competition with Greencore for about 34 per cent of their business in Ireland.  In other words, there will be rationalisation of part of the business of Greencore because if an Irish company buys Greencore and some of its business is in the same area as Greencore's, the company will rationalise and jobs will be lost.  Nobody has mentioned that aspect of this proposal.</P>
    <P>The other important point is that if we have something worth selling and the main Members of the Board being appointed by the State will have control of the board and we sell it to an outsider, we will have badly needed money coming into the State.  I do not believe you can compare this development to Digital as Digital was solely owned by an American multinational.  There are questions to be answered in connection with the fertilizer business in which, if an Irish company buying the shares was involved in that business, rationalization will take place and ultimately there will be a loss of a substantial number of jobs.</P>
    <P>I do not believe that thought has been given to the long term effects of the proposal by certain members of the Cabinet who say Greencore has to be sold to an Irish company.  Why put it up for sale at all if it is to be restricted in that way?  I do not believe this is on.  This decision has only come about recently because the union's representative, Mr. Summers, said that the Government was not elected on this policy.</P>
    <P>If this is an indication of the type of decision that will be made, we will have one hand behind our back when the next decision is made to sell the other part of the £150 million of shares agreed in the <Col N="434" /> budget by the Cabinet to be sold over the next 12 months and we will not receive the best price.  That is not the road we should take and I do not agree that we should sell assets for day to day spending because of inadequate budgeting on the part of the Minister for Finance.  This is only the beginning of what is to come.  If we do not use moneys to reinvest in job creation or to reduce the national debt, then it is a waste of a decision.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BillyKelleher" hpid="Mr. Kelleher Mr. Kelleher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelleher</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no ideological hangups about the sale of assets.  It baffles me to hear from the other side of the House that the money raised in this way will be used for the day to day running of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what happened last time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillyKelleher" hpid="Mr. Kelleher Mr. Kelleher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelleher</NameTxt>
      <P>It is irrelevant&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not irrelevant, it is paying with tomorrow's dinner&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillyKelleher" hpid="Mr. Kelleher Mr. Kelleher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelleher</NameTxt>
      <P>The money has to be raised either through the sale of assets or by another form.</P>
      <P>The Greencore issue has caused much contention because there is always a certain amount of suspicion due to what happened in the past.  I am concerned that there has not been enough time allocated to other companies to negotiate and investigate the possibility of a purchase or a takeover bid.  I have no problem with a multinational being involved in a takeover, but we must look at the circumstances, now that three or four weeks have been given for companies in Ireland, besides the one that has been mentioned, to make a bid for Greencore. I fear that Greencore might not realise its true value and the taxpayer will not receive the full benefit.  The shares have jumped in value since this was mentioned; this is an indication that this company is profitable and there is great interest in it.  When the people concerned contemplate this sale, they should realise its full value to the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In recent years Greencore has made <Col N="435" /> rapid advances in technology.  We must give time to those concerned to negotiate this matter with care and it is important to make the details public to avoid future problems.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Kilkenny Incest Case:" RHead="Statements">
    <Title>Kilkenny Incest Case: Statements.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to remind the House that Statements should be confined to the inquiry into the Kilkenny incest case.  Comment on the decision of the court in this case is not in order. Court decisions may be referred to but should not be criticised.  It is in order to refer to factual matters decided in a court but to comment on the decision of a court would not be in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarianMcGennis" hpid="Mrs. McGennis Mrs. McGennis">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGennis</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a very sensitive issue and I know the House will treat it as such.  To condemn this crime sounds extremely hollow.  I want to express my sympathy and the sympathy of all Members, to the victim of this crime.  We should congratulate Garda Agnes Reddy for her excellent work on this case and on a previous case, the substance of which is not related to this crime.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Minister's commitment to carry out an investigation and inquiry on this matter.  I join with the Council for the Status of Women in asking that the results of this inquiry be made public.  If action needs to be taken both Houses should not be found wanting.  The horrific details of this crime &mdash; and I am sure we do not know all the details &mdash; would not hold a candle to some of the video nasties which we would ban and condemn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A number of issues need to be discussed and I will deal with one or two of them now.  The sentencing and the discretionary powers of the judge in this case were referred to by the Minister for Justice, and she also stated that she had no power to intervene in such matters.  I ask her to pay particular attention to sentencing for the crimes of incest and rape because under the Criminal Justice Bill, which has been initiated in the Dáil, <Col N="436" /> there is a seven year sentence for incest. This is appalling.  The victim in this case stated that she had suffered for 17 years, yet the court sentence was for seven years; this would probably amount to three and a half years with remission.</P>
    <P>The Council for the Status of Women has called for mandatory treatment for sex offenders.  I support this but there is an urgent need to ensure that victims of these crimes receive help and support.  It is particularly poignant that the victim, who is a mother of an 11 year old child, has asked the State to help her rear her child; she did not ask for help to get over what surely must be a most horrendous experience.  As Members of the Oireachtas we have a great responsibility and duty.</P>
    <P>It appears that something has gone terribly wrong with the system which is supposed to protect children.  I will not preempt the outcome of the inquiry, but the statement that social workers were not empowered to make the child press charges seems ludicrous.  Why should social workers need to be empowered to make the child press charges?  We should have a system which enables our social services and our Department of Justice to take that initiative.  Young children and women who are the victims of abuse look to us for protection.  They do not expect to have to cope with this situation single-handed nor do they expect to see themselves, as the victim in this case feels, on the run.  She believes that she will be in danger when her abuser is released.  This is a view held by the whole family.</P>
    <P>It is easy for the House to spend an hour debating the rights and wrongs of this case while offering platitudes and sympathies, but we must accept our responsibilities.  The fact that our child care agencies and welfare services are acting under the Children's Act, 1908, is a condemnation of all in this House.  We must ensure that the Child Care Act, 1992, and its components are speedily introduced.  At least then we will have done more than utter empty phrases, and we will have faced up to our responsibilities. <Col N="437" /> I thank the Minister for attending here today.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister, Deputy O'Dea, to the House.  Having raised this matter last night and criticised the Leader of the House for not allowing debate, I now compliment him for the opportunity to discuss this sad case.  I express my sincere sympathy and support to the victim of this terrible crime, a person who has suffered appallingly for 17 years.  It is only right that this House should express the revulsion and anger of the people at what this unfortunate person experienced.</P>
      <P>It is a sad reflection on society, and on all of us, that this crime continued for 17 years.  It is apparent that many people who had been in contact with her knew that the abuse was taking place.  I do not want to criticise anybody because the system did not allow them or give them access to a resolution of the difficulties experienced by this person.  The investigation initiated by the Minister for Health must expose why the abuse continued for 17 years when so many people knew about it but felt their hands were tied.  We must ensure that such violations do not continue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What has been revealed this week is an example of what many people may have experienced during childhood and young adulthood.  We must have systems in place to ensure that similar incidents cannot happen.  If such systems are in place, some good will have come from this week's revelations which opened our eyes to the incidence of incest.  I am not criticising the Government or anybody else because this is not a political issue. The authorities, especially the Garda, were powerless under present procedures. The Garda needed a written statement accusing her father of the terrible acts that he was carrying out. They did not receive it and therefore could not act.  How could she accuse her father who was committing such acts of violence against her, and expose herself to further violence because she had made such a statement?  The situation must <Col N="438" /> change to allow exposure of such incidents.</P>
    <P>I would like to congratulate and pay tribute to Garda Agnes Reddy who exposed the situation and stayed with it. Society is not facing up to the problems of child sexual abuse.  Six months ago a report by Adapt House in Limerick on abuse exposed the severe circumstances many women and children endure in violent family situations.  We, the legislators, should ensure that proper legislation to deal with this subject is introduced.  It is important that a full investigation of all the facts surrounding this case be made.  The Minister must ensure that proposals to investigate the Kilkenny case will expose all aspects.  A full investigation into the difficulties experienced by professionals who tried to help the victim and her family over the seven year period is required.  A clear explanation must be given as to why action was not taken for so many years, why protection was not given, especially since when the woman became pregnant at the age of 15 she claims she then informed social workers of her plight. Some answer should be given as to why her horrendous suffering continued for 10 to 11 years after the pregnancy.  It is important that the inquiry should be an independent one and I fully accept the independence of Catherine McGuinness, a former Member of this House who will chair the inquiry.  She should be allowed to select her own team of investigators.</P>
    <P>It is accepted by all reasonable people that a sentence of seven years is too linient in such cases.  The judge had to deal with the situation he was presented with under section 1 of the Protection of Incest Act, 1908.  The maximum sentence for such acts is seven years although some uncertainty surrounds this and the Minister, being a legal person, could inform us as to what areas could be looked at. The Minister should take the earliest opportunity to ensure that the maximum sentence for such cruel acts and crimes be raised to 20 years.  The Criminal Justice Bill may be the Minister's first opportunity to deal with this situation, therefore I respectfully ask her to consider <Col N="439" /> allowing the Judiciary to impose proper sentencing in such cases.</P>
    <P>This incident unfortunately is not an isolated one.  We must ensure that help is more readily available to people in similar circumstances.  We must curb our hesitancy to interfere in family situations where authorities believe that criminal acts are taking place.  Traditionally the autonomous family unit is protected but cannot remain so under all circumstances. We must be prepared to intervene, and even without being asked. I call on the Government to implement the Child Care Bill in full.  Seventeen out of the Bill's 74 sections have been implemented to date.  It is a step the Minister can take without coming back to the legislature.  It has been passed by both Houses of the Oireachtas and I ask him to implement it as soon as possible.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WillieFarrell" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with other Senators in congratulating Garda Agnes Reddy on uncovering this crime and I ask the Minister to take particular note; a woman of that calibre deserves to be acknowledged and promoted.</P>
      <P>Last week a horrific murder case, in England prompted Patricia Redlich to write an article entitled &ldquo;Who failed Jamie?&rdquo; in the <i>Sunday Independent</i> of 21 February 1993.  I quote:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In all its horror, it parades before us the sins of deed, and more particularly of omission, that we have committed over the last 30 years.  It has taken this tragedy to stir the slumbering conscience of the '60s generation of liberal lefties.  We were the first community of elders ever in the history of mankind to declare that there was no such thing as evil.  Instead we argued that criminals really want to be good, and need guidance rather than the guillotine.  We went even further.  We declared criminals to be victims of poverty, lack of parenting, of society itself.  In the process we said that the individual is not responsible for his actions.  He is preprogrammed, has no choice, is merely an automaton set loose by an uncaring <Col N="440" /> world.  We stripped man of his individual conscience, abolished the concept of personal responsibility.  In its place we put &ldquo;society&rdquo;, created the welfare state, with the task of not just minding everyone at a physical level, but also charged with the responsibility of being the sole moral guardian of our world.  We handed over responsibility to social workers, probation officers, school councillors, psychologists and the courts, with the liberal imperative to reform rather than attribute blame and punishment.</P>
    <P>....We have also created a world where people are not just horrified by the brutality of James Bulger's murder, but are also surprised, disbelieving, that evil like this can exist.  And psychologists are appearing on television, telling us that such murders are not the norm, that the deed does not fit any particular picture, any pattern they can distinguish of familiar criminal behaviour. What they are really saying is that this crime defies definition within the victim culture we have so consistently cultivated.</P>
    <P>I would love, if I had the time, to read the whole article because it is a brilliant one.</P>
    <P>This type of crime would not have happened in years gone by.  We have now built up a society now where nobody interferes any more.  Society has lost respect for teachers, priests and the Garda.  Nobody has authority to intervene any more.  People do not tell others their problems because everyone says there is an official paid to do that and why should I do it.  We have built up a society where somebody who interferes is likely to be dragged before the courts. Under the Irish judicial system the Good Samaritan can be penalised because what he did was not his job, he should not have interfered in that he took the law into his own hands.</P>
    <P>Poverty and lack of jobs are not to blame for this situation.  A friend of mine had a flat in Ballymun.  At one time I could visit him at 12 midnight or in the early hours and nobody bothered me.  A <Col N="441" /> person could park his car anywhere in the city, walk and window shop and no one would touch him.  What has changed society?  We have more money now but there is no happiness because we have a society that is less caring and we have handed over all our responsibilities to professionals.</P>
    <P>There was a lot to be said for the fireside law and the hob lawyers, when everything was discussed in the locality. If anything untoward was happening a word was whispered to the school teacher, the priest, the doctor or the local sergeant.  There was the meitheal system, where people went from house to house helping each other.</P>
    <P>Because people are better off they can afford to furnish and carpet their houses. Nowadays, you cannot walk into a neighbour's house uninvited; they are wary of opening their doors to strangers.</P>
    <P>The day we abolished the small two-teacher schools was the day we started to demolish society as we knew it.  In the two-teacher schools the teachers knew every child and they were part of the family of that school.  They knew if there were problems in a family.  The Garda visited the area once a year checking dog licences, school attendance books, etc. All these people kept in touch with what was happening.  Society has become very impersonal.  Now we press buttons and accept whatever answer the computer gives.</P>
    <P>I disagree with a headline in today's newspaper from an organisation for whom I have great respect and admiration, the ICA.  They are doing a great job in rural areas &mdash; even though they will not allow men to join their ranks.  I do not believe that one in three women in Ireland today is sexually abused.  That is a statistic that remains to be proved and I would like to see more facts.  I appeal to the ICA to let us know where they got those figures because if they are true, we are sitting on a time bomb and we are the most immoral country in the world today.  I do not believe that is so.</P>
    <P>My sympathy extends to girls, as in the recent case in Kilkenny.  It is a very sad case.  In the past, if an unmarried mother <Col N="442" /> had to go into a convent the nuns would have investigated and found out her story.  When the health boards were advised to appoint social workers, we were told they would solve all our problems. In this case, the social workers and the legal and medical professions were blind.  They saw this girl with horrific bruises going into hospital for treatment and to have a baby.  I believe these people have a lot to answer for.  My sympathy goes out to the girl and I sincerely hope we will bring the human touch back into society.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand Senator Henry wishes to share her time with Senator Honan and Senator Norris. Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I rise with great rage to speak on this matter.  I welcome the Minister to the House and inform him that the Department of Health could set up inquiries into cases like this all over the country.  This case is particularly horrifying because of the length of time the abuse went on and the terrible injuries the girl received but let me assure the House that it is not an isolated case.</P>
      <P>I was on the original committee set up by the Department of Health to establish the Sexual Assault Unit in the Rotunda Hospital in the early 1980s.  It was set up to deal mainly with rape victims and to get forensic evidence.  The Garda were naturally anxious, with improved forensic methods to collect better evidence for rape cases so that they could obtain convictions.  When the assault unit was set up in the Rotunda Hospital, we thought we would be dealing with general rape cases from the Dublin area.  That was not the case.  Within about six weeks we were flooded with cases of child sexual abuse.  I have to tell Senator Farrell that television did not bring incest to Ireland. There are many women older than I am who were subjected to the appalling crime of incest.  It is wrong to suggest that this is a new phenomenon in our society; it is not.  I do not know if it is worse here than elsewhere, it probably is not, but we have a much better way of hiding it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="443" /> We have talked here about not interfering in the family home.  I do not want to see social workers and doctors being the scapegoats in this inquiry.  The girl from Kilkenny said that people used to pass her in the street and just say hello, although they knew what was going on. We have got to a situation where a married man can do whatever he likes in his home without anyone querying the situation or asking why that family is so isolated &mdash; and often they are desperately isolated.</P>
    <P>When we started the Sexual Assault Unit in the Rotunda Hospital, the most astonishing thing was the way teachers came to us.  They came because they had nowhere else to bring the children.  There is no rape crisis centre in Kilkenny.  If there had been, the girl or her mother could have gone there.  The Programme for a Partnership Government promised increased funding for the rape crisis centres. Most people agree it is probably the best place for these women to go &mdash; and some men also.  It is ridiculous that there is no provision in the budget for rape crisis centres.</P>
    <P>Senator McGennis mentioned the 1991 child care legislation but that measure cannot be implemented without money. Irrespective of any inquiries established or pious statements made we must put our money where our mouth is and pay for services to prevent this happening again.  In my view, Catherine McGuinness is the ideal person to head the inquiry but, as I said, unless we are prepared to pay for the services required to deal with these cases, there is no point continuing with them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CathyHonan" hpid="Ms Honan Ms Honan">
      <NameTxt>Ms Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and the setting up of this inquiry.  I wonder, as the Irish Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children said yesterday, if he could not structure a speedy and simple inquiry by making eight phone calls to the eight directors of community care in the health boards throughout the country.  They will tell him what is needed to bring about a change in a system that is failing, or <Col N="444" /> potentially failing, all Irish children.  I welcome the pledge given by the Minister for Justice that she will give priority to considering an increase in the penalties for incest.  Women have been appalled by the sentences imposed in rape and incest cases.  As a society, we should not be giving this signal to women.</P>
      <P>In the present case and the Lavina Kerwick case both women said after their trials that they were sorry they had taken the cases to court.  That is an appalling indictment of this society.  As a woman I do not want to be a member of a society that treats women like that.  I welcome the Minister's statement and I hope action will soon be taken.  I ask the Ministers for Health and for Justice to look at the recommendations of the Second Commission on the Status of Women. The constitutional legal issues chapter and the health chapter of that report make several recommendations in relation to the issues all Senators have spoken about today.  Recommendations are made regarding counselling for victims and offenders in violent assault cases and in cases of rape, treatment of complaints in rape trials, sentencing in rape and incest trials, combating child sexual abuse and implementing the provisions of the Child Care Act.  Under the health section we have recommended that funding for rape crisis centres would be the responsibility of health boards and that centres should be given multi annual funding so they would know that they could continue in existence, as Senator Henry said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What kind of society is this in which people feel they have no right to interfere in family situations?  It is appalling that children, one of the weakest sections of society are not adequately protected. What sort of people are we who convey this message so that children are afraid to come forward believing that they will not be supported.  We must welcome the two women who have come forward and convince children and women throughout Ireland that if they come forward with incidents of abuse, action will be taken.  Inquiries are not the answer.  As Senator Henry said incidents of sexual <Col N="445" /> abuse are numerous in Ireland; we know what is going on and what needs to be done.  I welcome the appointment of Catherine McGuinness to head this inquiry if an inquiry has to take place.  I think she will be in agreement with the recommendations of the Second Commission on the Status of Woman of which she was a member.</P>
    <P>We should not continue to rely on inquiries for solutions.  As Senator Henry said we must put our money where our mouth is.  Senator Farrell asked earlier who failed Jamie, the child murdered recently in England.  We as legislators are failing the women and the children of this country unless we move on this issue swiftly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, a Chathaoirligh. I cannot say I am glad to take part in this debate.  I welcome the fact that it has taken place so speedily and I am glad that we have the Minister for Health here with us this evening because I know that as a caring man he will be as concerned as the rest of us about this matter and in particular about the length of time the abuse continued.  For about 20 years while this unfortunate woman passed from childhood through adolescence to maturity she was continuously abused by her own father.  It is astonishing that this was allowed to happen.  As Senator Henry said with great passion and concern, neighbours must have known. People in the community must have known.  I read an interview that said people passed by because they were embarrassed.  Again and again in my own work I come across circumstances where people say they are sorry but they do not want to get involved because they feel there is nothing they can do and they might expose themselves to some kind of risk.  I feel for the impact on the unfortunate son who apparently discovered yesterday for the first time what the real circumstances of his family are.  That must have a serious effect on his psychological wellbeing and development.  It is a great pity that this news was allowed to filter through to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to pay tribute to Garda <Col N="446" /> Reddy.  Thank God for a garda with the sensitivity, the decency, the humanity, the compassion and the courage to interfere, because we are told so often that we cannot interfere in families.  I comment on the deafening silence from Family Solidarity and from all rightwing moralistic groups who talk about the family.  This is a family problem.  Why are they not talking about it?  Where are they when they are needed to talk about a case of cruelty and family misery?  I look forward to their belated response.  When we consecrate the family we should examine its reality instead of holding it up as an icon or totem.  There are many things wrong with Irish families.  There is not only incest but rape within marriage, drunkeness and wife battering.  Before we fall down and worship the golden calf of Irish marriage we ought to examine that institution and try to correct what is wrong.</P>
    <P>I know as a teacher that frequently it is teachers who detect abuse; they notice an absent-minded, forgetful, distressed child who does not do homework; often they think it may be drugs but frequently the cause is child abuse.</P>
    <P>I will make two final points.  Some Senators spent an enormous amount of time on the Child Care Bill, 1991, as the Minister will remember.  We actually had amendments accepted in this House inroducing the guardian <i>ad litem</i> clause until a caring Fianna Fáil Minister voted it down.</P>
    <P>The Minister is right about the need for penalties and nobody knows that better than I do.  A friend of mine was murdered in this State because he was gay and his murderer was let off with a suspended sentence.  I assure you I will be interested in seeing how sentencing policies can be reviewed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Sullivan, I understand you are sharing your time with two of your colleagues.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will share my time with Senator Kelly and Senator Gallagher.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="447" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister for Health to the House and thank also the junior Minister who was here previously, Deputy O'Dea.</P>
      <P>I have felt anger and horror at this case and I would like to stress the lessons to be learned from it.  This is not an isolated case by any means.  This girl spent 16 years in fear and horror and misery and nobody intervened until the garda who has been commended here today.  I read in the papers today that the Dublin Rape Crisis Centre say that at least four cases similar to this one will be coming before the courts in the near future, and I know that other rape crisis centres throughout the country are dealing with similar cases. The majority of cases that come to the attention of rape crisis centres are adult female victims of incest in childhood.</P>
      <P>As Senator Norris said it is of absolutely no use to pay lip service to an ideal of the family if we do not face up to the reality of what has happened in many Irish families over the years and what continues to happen.  In that context I welcome the intention of the Minister not just to investigate this specific case but to make recommendations for the future investigation and management by the health services of suspected cases of child abuse.  As Senator Norris also said the health services are not the only services involved because the educational system will have to take account of this matter as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Neville described the initiative taken by the Mid-Western Health Board to combat child abuse.  Under a welcome new scheme a social worker has been seconded to schools in the area to help teachers identify signs of abuse in children. The scheme should be extended because not only the health of children is endangered in abuse incidents but their entitlements to justice and to education. Each citizen has a duty to care for children and to notice signs of abuse.  We organise neighbourhood watch schemes and community alert schemes to look <Col N="448" /> after our property; we must also be alert to people and their problems.</P>
    <P>My colleagues will deal with aspects of justice and child care.  I want us to learn lessons from this case.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryKelly" hpid="Ms Kelly Ms Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Ms Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Howlin to the House.  I would like to focus on a slightly different aspect of this case and consider the physical punishment endured by this girl who regarded her rape as punishment.  Our constitution does not protect children. Children are regarded as the property of a family; we do not give them individual rights.  The Irish Government has not signed the UN Convention on Childrens' Rights.  In that we are failing in our duty to our children.  I take exception to some of Senator Farrell's remarks about Ireland being a caring society long ago.</P>
      <P>Practically every person here grew up in an age when physical punishment was meted out in schools and at home.  It was considered a parent's right and duty to beat a child.  Teachers were then allowed to inflict horrendous punishments on children and children were expected not to complain and were not listened to if they did.  That is the attitude of adults today who grew up in an environment where the infliction of physical punishment was seen as a parent's right.  Parents were given the right to vent their frustrations on their children.  We, as adults, have to turn that around.  We have to say that children should no longer be beaten or punished.  That cycle of violence often includes the abuse of spouses as well as children.  Women are treated like children by many husbands.  They are seen as his property to be used, abused and controlled.  That attitude was there in the 1950s, 1940s and 1930s and remnants of it are still there.  Women and children are seen as the property of their husband and that is an attitude which we, as a nation, must change.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnGallagher" hpid="Ms Gallagher Ms Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Ms Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to share my time with Senator Maloney.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="449" />
    <Speaker pid="AnnGallagher" hpid="Ms Gallagher Ms Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Ms Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>I raised this matter yesterday in the House because it is urgent and important.</P>
      <P>Senator Farrell said this type of crime did not happen long ago.  Human nature has not changed.  Man's desire to obtain power through sexual abuse has always existed.  We have only recently begun to talk about it, to some extent.  Most callers to the rape crisis centre and other voluntary agencies are women who suffered abuse in their childhood.  It is only now they feel brave enough to come out and talk about it.</P>
      <P>Obviously the Kilkenny case and others highlight the serious flaws in our system and gaps in legislation which result in protecting the offender rather than the victim.  Sadly, this is not a one-off case, as has been pointed out.  Certainly, it is horrific and extreme in every sense, but similar crimes are perpetrated against women and children in our society every day of the week.  In fact, I have come across many of them in my work as a solicitor.  It takes an extreme case such as this hitting the headlines to awaken us to the need to examine our legislation in this area and do something about it.</P>
      <P>Many a woman's life is in shreds because of abuse inflicted on her by a relation or other person.  They cannot develop normal relationships or get on with their own lives in a rewarding way. The dignity of life of an abused woman is forever shattered, yet the perpetrators of such hideous crimes serve a few years in prison and then walk free.  Where is the justice in this system?  It fails to recognise the serious nature of such crimes.  Is it because the laws of 1908 and 1935 were formulated by men and are today enforced by male judges in the main?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The judge has a discretion in imposing sentences in these cases to allow for the varying degree of abuse which is right but that discretion should only be allowed to move upwards from a minimum sentence. There is little point in the Oireachtas introducing maximum sentences which are on the books and are not intended to be used or implemented. With particular reference to the Kilkenny <Col N="450" /> case, the judge could have imposed a life sentence on the offender but chose not to do so.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>He should have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnGallagher" hpid="Ms Gallagher Ms Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Ms Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The House can reach its own conclusions on that point.</P>
      <P>Regarding a charge of incest with a female over 15 years, a maximum seven years' imprisonment can be imposed; that is the law as it stands.  That is a serious flaw and, in my opinion, must be increased to 20 years.  The introduction of legislation on this point must become a matter of urgency for both Houses and I ask the Minister, Deputy Howlin, to take cognisance of this.  There are other issues involved here.  Increased penalties will help but a more co-ordinated approach is necessary.</P>
      <P>The victims need help.  The use of Child-line and other agencies show the need we have in Ireland for a Government backed service to provide counselling and practical help and advise to those whose lives have been shattered by abusers.  The offenders need help.  I believe there should be compulsory therapy for all convicted sex offenders.  Until such help is provided we are wasting our time, we are banging our head against a brick wall; we are trying to deal with the symptom rather than the cause.</P>
      <P>We need to provide the Garda with the necessary powers to intervene in family cases of abuse.  We need to introduce rights for social workers to act on cases which come to their attention rather than being forced to wait until appalling abuse forces the matter into light.  There is a need to be careful however in light of matters which have arisen in Britain where over-zealous social workers overstepped the mark.</P>
      <P>However the law as it stands waits for the victim to provide a case of abuse and to pursue it through our criminal system. That in my opinion is a nonsense.  The victims of abuse are mostly children who do not know what has happened to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the Minister's appointment of Catherine McGuinness to head our investigation.  I hope that matter will be <Col N="451" /> dealt with quickly, made public and acted upon to ensure that we learn something from this.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister for Health to the House.  I sympathise with the person concerned in the Kilkenny case, and the hundreds of women who find themselves in a similar position today.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Minister's decision to immediately set up the inquiry into the circumstances surrounding the suffering of this girl.  It is not a time for casting blame because I feel we, as a society are to blame.  This sexual abuse has been going on in Ireland since time began. For years, women have been abused by clergy, teachers, husbands and brothers. I have been a psychiatric nurse for the past 26 years and it is the issue which has come to the fore in the last ten years.  Not only young girls but middle-aged women suffer in silence.  There have been suicides which were never properly investigated, and abuse was often the cause. Where do these people go for help, to the Garda, the social worker, the clergy, neighbours or their mothers?  They tell you that when they approach these individuals they are told they do not want to get involved.</P>
      <P>The point that has been missed is that this abuse may start at an early age.  At school going age, where does the child go?  Does she understand what is being done to her body?  Sex education in schools has to be looked at as a matter of urgency.</P>
      <P>I organised a seminar on sexual abuse in Letterkenny two years ago and all sections of the social services, including the Garda, attended.  I was amazed to learn that there was no comprehensive policy to deal with sexual abuse.  Every area of the social services seems to go its own way and we had no specific plan to deal with this problem collectively.  I hope this will be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What difference does it make if a person is sentenced to seven years or 20 years?  The programmes are there to help <Col N="452" /> offenders.  Action must be taken early to let those people know help is available.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate the Minister a former Senator on his appointment as Minister for Health.  I had the pleasure of working with him when he was a Senator and I give him a very warm welcome to the House as Minister for Health.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHowlin" hpid="Minister for Health (Mr. Howlin) Brendan Howlin">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Health (Mr. Howlin)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very flattered by your kind comments.  I wish that my first address to the Seanad was more auspicious and friendly than the awful situation with which we are dealing today.</P>
      <P>We were all shocked and horrified by the revelations earlier this week of the brutal and inhuman ill-treatment and abuse of the young woman over a 16 year period in Kilkenny.  The unfortunate victim's heart-rendering account of the appalling suffering she endured for so long has deeply moved us and our hearts go out to her and her mother.</P>
      <P>I share the widespread concern about this tragic case and I am particularly anxious to establish why the girl's plight was not brought to light earlier so that appropriate action could have been taken to protect her.</P>
      <P>I have, accordingly, directed the South-Eastern Health Board to carry out an immediate investigation of the circumstances of this tragic case, in so far as the health services are concerned, and to report back to me as a matter of urgency.</P>
      <P>The terms of reference of the investigation team are: to carry out an investigation, in so far as the health services are concerned, of the circumstances surrounding the abuse referred to in the case heard in the Central Criminal Court on 1 March 1993; in particular to establish why action to halt the abuse was not taken earlier; and to make recommendations for the future investigation and management by the health services of cases of suspected child abuse.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>An investigation team has already been appointed by the South-Eastern Health Board in response to my direction. <Col N="453" /> This team is headed by Catherine McGuinness, Senior Counsel, who will be assisted by Martin Hynes, Programme Manager for Community Care Services, South-Eastern Health Board; Dr. Sheila Ryan, Director of Community Care and Medical Officer of Health, Midland Health Board, and Bríd Clarke, Head Social Worker, Eastern Health Board.</P>
    <P>I hope that the investigation team will complete its task within four weeks at the outset, and that it will report to me shortly thereafter.</P>
    <P>I want to emphasise to this House that I am concerned to ensure that every measure possible is taken to prevent a recurrence of what happened in this case. Towards this end, I will be discussing the matter with the chief executive officers of the eight health boards when I meet them next week.  In particular, I will be stressing the necessity to ensure that satisfactory arrangements are in place in their areas for the identification, investigation and management of child abuse cases.</P>
    <P>In the light of these consultations with the chief executive officers and the results of the investigation being carried out by the South-Eastern Health Board, I shall be reporting to the Government at an early date with recommendations for the introduction of whatever new measures are necessary to improve existing services and procedures for dealing with child abuse, and child care services generally.</P>
    <P>It is most unfortunate that the dreadful sexual abuse suffered as a child by the young woman happened at a time when the existence of child sexual abuse was not even publicly acknowledged.  For example, the Task Force on Child Care Services which reported in 1980, made scant reference to the incidence of incest and other forms of sexual abuse against vulnerable children.  This task force was composed of a number of experts in the field of child care and its report focused on the major issues of the time.</P>
    <P>I make this point not in any way to denigrate the excellent work undertaken by that task force, but to illustrate the general lack of awareness of child sexual abuse at the time.  Since then, we have <Col N="454" /> all become far more conscious of the nature and scale of this frightening problem. A number of important initiatives have taken place since the mid-1980s, when our awareness of child abuse and particularly child sexual abuse, began to increase dramatically.</P>
    <P>In response to the increase in the reports of child sexual abuse, my Department revised its child abuse guidelines to include specific reference to child sexual abuse.  These guidelines were specifically designed to provide guidance for all those likely to be professionally involved with children who are victims of any form of child abuse.  They spell out clearly the respective responsibilities of, and the steps to be taken by, the key personnel involved in the identification, investigation and management of suspected cases.</P>
    <P>In the Eastern Health Board area, units for the investigation and management of alleged child sexual abuse were established early in 1988 at Temple Street Hospital and Our Lady's Hospital for Sick Children, Crumlin.  During the same year, a special allocation was made to each of the other seven health boards to enable them to establish appropriate services in their areas.  Services are now in place in each health board area; some of them are based in a particular hospital in the region while others are provided on a community basis.  I might mention that in the South-Eastern Health Board area, there is now a regional child abuse unit based in Ardkeen Hospital in Waterford.</P>
    <P>The Department of Education, for its part, has circulated guidelines to schools setting out procedures for dealing with suspected cases of child abuse that come to light within the school setting.</P>
    <P>My Department is currently preparing, in consultation with the Garda Síochána, new guidelines for health boards and the gardaí on a co-ordinated approach to the investigation of suspected cases of child abuse.  These new guidelines will focus specifically on the need for greater co-operation between the key personnel involved from both authorities, in order to ensure the protection of the child as <Col N="455" /> well as facilitating the full investigation of any crime.</P>
    <P>Apart from the continuing process of refining procedures for the identification and investigation of child abuse cases, it is also vitally important to develop programmes aimed at preventing the incidence of all forms of child abuse.  In this context, I would like to refer to the child abuse prevention programme known as the &ldquo;Stay Safe Programme&rdquo;, which is currently being implemented in primary schools around the country, with the active support of my Department, the Department of Education and the health boards.  I have met some of the teachers involved in that programme in recent weeks.</P>
    <P>The aim of this programme is to prevent all forms of child abuse including bullying by other children, by equipping parents and teachers with the knowledge and skills necessary to protect the children in their care.  Children are then taught safety skills in the normal classroom context and these skills are reinforced through discussion with their parents.  This approach increases community awareness and makes children less vulnerable to abuse of all kinds.</P>
    <P>The response of parents, teachers and children to the Stay Safe Programme has been very positive.  The programme has also been instrumental in fostering good working relationships between teachers and members of the local health board community care teams.  This has resulted in better co-operation and co-ordination at local level between the main statutory authorities concerned with the welfare of children.</P>
    <P>While primary responsibility for investigating allegations of child abuse rests with the professionals, all members of the community should play their part in combating the incidence of abuse by assisting persons such as the unfortunate girl at the centre of this case, if and when they become aware of difficulties or problems.</P>
    <P>I conclude by reiterating that I am committed to ensuring that every possible measure is taken to prevent a recurrence <Col N="456" /> of what happened in this tragic case.  I assure the House that, in the light of the report of the investigation team and my forthcoming discussions with the chief executive officers of the health boards, I shall bring before Government, at an early date, proposals for whatever new measures or new resources are required to improve present arrangements for dealing with child abuse and for the care and protection of children generally.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MadeleineTaylorQuinn" hpid="Mrs. Taylor-Quinn Mrs. Taylor-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Taylor-Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to this House and welcome also the establishment of this inquiry, the terms of reference of which the Minister has placed before us.  I am pleased that the inquiry team will report to the Minister within four weeks.</P>
      <P>It is important for the Minister to enter into urgent discussions with the chief executive officer's of the eight health boards but discussions alone will not be sufficient.  The matter should be addressed by ensuring that proper services are put in place in each of the health board areas.  One facility in each health board area is inadequate because it is a recognised fact that cases of incest and rape occur in every town and village and across rural Ireland.  Health board regions cover a wide area and people in isolated and peripheral parts may not be aware of or have access to facilities that are available to them.  It is important to try to localise facilities for victims of abuse.  I hope the Minister when he comes back with the report of this enquiry will tell us if money will be allocated specifically to such facilities for which commitment is vital and extremely urgent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is unfortunate that it has taken a case as serious as the Kilkenny case to highlight serious flaws in our legislation. It is a well known fact, as Senator Henry said, that child sexual abuse has been happening for many years so it is not a recent phenomenon.  Irish people in their sixties and seventies are currently being treated by psychologists and psychiatrists for childhood incidents of sexual abuse and incest.  Unfortunately, social conditioning and prevailing attitudes due to the position of the family within the constitution <Col N="457" /> as Senator Kelly mentioned and religious conditioning contribute towards community reluctance to deal with any issue associated with sex.  This reluctance is particularly obvious in cases of sexual abuse where many people say that they do not want to become involved for fear of breaking up a family.  That is not acceptable.  In most circumstances the victims of abuse are women and girls but the number of young boys being sexually abused is increasing.  This serious problem cannot be set aside.</P>
    <P>There has been official reaction and response to the Kilkenny case because of the publicity involved.  The Departments of Health or Justice should not be forced into action because of the publicity surrounding this case.  I hope that shortly the Minister for Justice introduces a Bill outlining specifically the type of penalties that should be imposed.</P>
    <P>As a public representative, I have dealt with family cases of sexual abuse and the common factor in all cases is &ldquo;the poor man must have a problem&rdquo;.  However, the victim is still a victim.  This is an unfortunate and unacceptable reaction.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I hope the Minister will return to the House in four weeks with definite recommendations in the report and that we will have an opportunity to discuss them.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="GATT Negotiations:" RHead="Statements">
    <Title>GATT Negotiations: Statements</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Statements are to conclude at 4 p.m.  I congratulate the Minister, a former Senator, on his appointment and I welcome him to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianOShea" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. O'Shea) Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. O'Shea)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and Forestry (Mr. O'Shea)</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá áthas orm a bheith ar ais ag labhairt sa Seanad don chéad uair ó 1989. I thank you for your warm welcome and your congratulations and I am pleased to be back in the Seanad to speak for the first time since 1989.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am happy to have the opportunity to outline to this House the current state of play with regard to the GATT negotiations. <Col N="458" /> I also wish to take this opportunity to spell out the difficulties which we have with the current proposals for concluding the negotiations and the stance we are taking in the negotiations. As Senators are aware, the Lower House debated this matter last month when the Government's handling of the negotiations was endorsed.</P>
    <P>The objective for agriculture, contained in the Ministerial Declaration which launched the Round, was to bring stability and balance to agriculture world trade through the correction of the market restrictions and distortions which had increasingly become a feature of the trading regime in that sector.  This objective was further refined during the midterm review of the negotiations in April 1989 when it was agreed that a fair and market oriented agricultural trading system was to be achieved through negotiations of commitments on support and protection levels and the establishment of more effective GATT rules for this sector.  Agriculture is, of course, just one element in the negotiations which cover 14 other sectors, including such complex issues as services and intellectual property rights.</P>
    <P>Apart from being the most ambitious round of multilateral negotiations ever undertaken in the GATT &mdash; it is the eighth Round to date &mdash; the Uruguay Round is the first to deal with agriculture trade in a comprehensive way.  The focus on agriculture trade must be seen against a background of increasing structural surpluses, budgetary costs and trade friction between the major agriculture producing countries throughout the late seventies and eighties.</P>
    <P>The problems in the agriculture sector are clearly evident if we look at the experience within the Community.  When Ireland joined the EC in 1973 agricultural policy was one of price support for unlimited production.  This was of great benefit to our producers and led to rapid expansion and increased output in almost all sectors, which was aided by technological advances.  However, from the late 1970s onwards, structural surpluses emerged in all major product areas <Col N="459" /> which, together with increased pressure on the budget, forced the Community to implement a series of adjustments during the eighties to address the problem. These measures were not sufficient, however, to correct the problem and the Community continued to have sizeable quantities of products, particularly beef and cereals, for which there were no real outlets.  At the same time, the budget continued to grow but producer incomes were not being sustained.</P>
    <P>The situation could not continue indefinitely and last year there was a major reform of the support arrangements involving a partial switch in support away from market price support to direct income payments to producers for a range of commodities.  Although not all agricultural interests in Ireland are completely happy with the outcome, there is general acceptance that changes were necessary and recognition that the days of over-production of commodities, for which there are no real markets, are drawing to a close.</P>
    <P>Returning to the international scene, the discussions on agriculture and in a number of other areas in the GATT have proved to be very difficult and that is why the negotiations have long exceeded their expected conclusion date of December 1990.  This difficulty has arisen mainly from different interpretations of the already stated objectives for the negotiations. This was particularly so in the case of agriculture.</P>
    <P>The US and the CAIRNS Group, which includes Australia, Canada and New Zealand, set their sights from the start of the negotiations on the virtual elimination of all agricultural supports, in particular the EC's export refunds system.  Although they subsequently modified this extremist position, they continued to insist on deep cuts in export supports together with large increases in market access opportunities.</P>
    <P>The Community, on the other hand, argued that reform should be gradual and balanced and that agreed reductions in support should be dealt with in an overall way by addressing all production and <Col N="460" /> trade impacting policies.  This aggregate or global approach was seen as necessary because of the complementary and interrelated nature of the various support mechanisms of the Common Agricultural Policy.</P>
    <P>Although in the early negotiations the Community managed to successfully defend this global approach, the Commission negotiators, under pressure from other trading parties, indicated in December 1991 that the EC might be prepared in certain circumstances to make some commitments on minimum market access and on the volume of subsidised exports.  This was done despite strong reservations from Ireland and a number of other member states that the Commission was going well beyond the negotiating mandate given to it by the Council.</P>
    <P>In an effort to conclude negotiations, Mr. Arthur Dunkel, the Director General of GATT put foward proposals, known as the Draft Final Act, to conclude the negotiations in all sectors in December 1991.  The Community refused to accept these proposals arguing that they were unbalanced, particularly in relation to agriculture and the Commission was instructed to participate in further negotiations with a view to securing a more balanced and global package.</P>
    <P>After several false starts, the US and the Commission, representing the EC, began intensive negotiations last autumn resulting in a meeting in Blair House, Washington, at the end of November where an outline agreement was reached on agriculture and oilseeds in the context of the Uruguay Round.  The outline agreement covers a six year period and the main elements are as follows: the Common Agricultural Policy reform compensatory payments and similar payments elsewhere would not be subjected to GATT disciplines: other internal supports would be reduced by 20 per cent and credit would be allowed for reductions already undertaken since 1986; border measures, e.g. levies, would be converted into tariff equivalents which would be reduced by 36 per cent; minimum <Col N="461" /> access commitments of up to 5 per cent of domestic consumption would be provided for and current access would be maintained; average 1986-90 subsidised exports would be reduced by 36 per cent in budgetary terms and by 21 per cent in volume terms; a &ldquo;peace clause&rdquo; which provides that once domestic support and export subsidy commitments are complied with, there would be no resort to GATT disputes procedures; and on oilseeds, the Community agreed to limit support for production to that produced from a certain hectarage and also to a minimum set-aside arrangement.</P>
    <P>Following the draft EC/US deal, the Commission, despite objections from some member states, again undertook its negotiating responsibilities and submitted revised schedules to GATT in general based on the elements contained in the Washington deal.</P>
    <P>The draft agreement between the Commission and the US negotiators has yet to be approved by the US Congress and by the other parties to the GATT. Within the Community, the agreement has not been formally accepted by the Council of Ministers.  If the Congress and Council were to approve this or another agreement, it is likely to be accepted in due course by all GATT participants. The expectation among many commentators was that once the agriculture sector was agreed it would be easy to conclude an agreement on the other aspects.  This has not proved to be the case and severe difficulties are now being experienced in a number of other sectors especially market access and services in addition to agriculture.  The question of acceptance or rejection of a GATT deal will not arise until an overall package covering all sectors has been agreed.</P>
    <P>At this stage I would like to make it clear that Ireland in the various negotiating fora has always recognised that a fair and balanced outcome to the GATT negotiations would give a valuable boost to the world economy.  In fact, the Irish position in relation to the Round has been consistently positive and supportive and this stance was fully reflected in the statement by Dáil party leaders on the <Col N="462" /> Round on 6 November last.  We have at all times accepted that failure to conclude an overall GATT deal would not necessarily mean a return to the <i>status quo.</i> This clearly will not be the case and the increasing recourse to unilateral actions and to challenges in GATT by some countries which was a growing trend in international trading conditions in recent years are worrying.</P>
    <P>The agreement on oilseeds, which was concluded at the same time as the deal on agriculture, prevented a damaging trade war which could have affected some of the major Irish exports to the US, including Waterford glass, cream liqueurs, casein and cheeses.  However, while a stable trade environment is clearly in our interest, I have always stressed throughout these negotiations that any final GATT agreement would have to be balanced and global and take full account of our particular concerns.</P>
    <P>The Community's negotiating mandate for the agricultural aspects makes it clear that there cannot be an agreement which, in effect, only covered agriculture or which would result in the Community being asked to bear an unequal share of the burden of reform of international markets.  It is also worth recalling the Council's position that any agreement must be compatible with the Common Agricultural Policy reform outcome, already referred to, which was concluded only after long and arduous negotiations last May.  The measures agreed in these reforms are only now being implemented within the Community and it would be extremely unreasonable to ask EC producers to make even further sacrifices in the context of GATT.</P>
    <P>It is against that background that we must assess the EC/US agreement.  We have, of course, examined the Commission's outline of the agreement and its assessment of its compatibility with Common Agricultural Policy reform.  We have also seen statements made by the US side on the outcome, but we also needed to have a more detailed explanation of the agreement and to have it evaluated line by line at Community level with full particulars being provided by <Col N="463" /> the Commission.  For these reasons the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry, Deputy Walsh, sought and obtained a Council commitment at the January meeting of Agriculture Ministers that this detailed evaluation should be undertaken immediately at expert level so that Community negotiators could be given appropriate instructions in the on-going GATT discussions in Geneva.  This analysis has been on-going for some weeks and it is expected that a report will be made to the next Agriculture Council on 16-17 March.  That Council is likely to ask the experts to continue their analysis of the agreement.</P>
    <P>As a result of our preliminary analysis of the draft deal, we can accept that improvements have been secured over the Dunkel formula, in particular the exemption of Common Agricultural Policy reform and disadvantaged areas payments from GATT disciplines.  We have welcomed this and will continue to insist that this element is transposed into a final GATT agreement.  Likewise, we welcome the Commission's assurances that the US has accepted the Community's tariffication and access proposals.</P>
    <P>However, despite the improvements secured <i>vis-a-vis</i> the Dunkel approach, we have major difficulties with the overall agreement.  The analysis which we have carried out to date, and which in my view has not been reflected in the discussions at expert level, show that the Community would be required to bear a disproportionate share of the reform burden.  We also believe that the undertakings could not be accommodated within the parameters of the Common Agricultural Policy reform agreement in a number of sectors.  In fact, this view is also accepted in the Commission's own analysis &mdash; specifically for beef and implicitly for some other sectors.</P>
    <P>Given the contribution which agriculture makes to our econmy, such an outcome would create major problems for Ireland and we have made this very clear in all the relevant fora.  Our concerns are exacerbated by our heavy <Col N="464" /> reliance on export markets which leaves us particularly exposed in an over-supplied market.</P>
    <P>From our point of view, the main risk arises from the proposed volume restraint on subsidised exports and the methodology to be used in meeting commitments. The 21 per cent reduction together with the access arrangements would inevitably require the Community to reduce production much further than was envisaged in the Common Agricultural Policy reform in a number of sectors, especially beef, and the problem is made even more acute by the requirements to reduce exports in the first year below 1986-90 levels and by linear cuts thereafter with minimum flexibility.</P>
    <P>In the beef sector, this would require the Community to reduce exports by more than 200,000 tonnes on current levels in the first year and by 400,000 tonnes in the final year.  The Common Agricultural Policy reform measures will not reduce Community output by these amounts and, even if we wanted to do so, it is extremely difficult to put measures in place now to reduce beef output by the start of any agreement.  It is also of concern to me that the restriction on subsidising exports to East Asia would remain.  This makes the situation even more difficult.</P>
    <P>While similar problems will arise in other sectors &mdash; milk is a major concern of ours also &mdash; the problem is particularly acute in the beef sector.  Other questions such as the precise terms of the peace clause and the way in which sizable intervention stocks will be disposed of before the commencement of the agreement must also be answered.  The Commission acknowledges that stock disposals will be a problem but a solution has not been proposed.  This aspect is of particular concern given the current very high levels of Community stocks of cereals and beef.</P>
    <P>With regard to the domestic support aspect, the EC would not have to do anything additional to meet the proposed 20 per cent reduction.  The reason for this is that estimated current support, which takes account of Common Agricultural Policy reform, is significantly lower than <Col N="465" /> in the base years put forward by Mr. Dunkel.  The Commission estimates that there would be a surplus of some 13,000 mecu which could be used to cushion the impact of measures in other areas.  But of course, additional budgetary resources would be required to fund such measures.</P>
    <P>The domestic support aspect also covers the now infamous &ldquo;green box&rdquo; of policies which will not be subject to reduction under the GATT agreement. The Commission has confirmed that headage payments in the disadvantaged areas would be exempt from reduction and the provisions of the final text will have to cover this.  This is one of the aspects that we will be seeking to clarify in the on-going discussions at expert level.  It should be recalled that when the Council was finalising the negotiating mandate in November 1990, the Commission gave a firm undertaking that the level of these payments would not be reduced.  Our aim is to ensure that not alone is this commitment respected but that nothing in the agreement would preclude the level of payments from being increased in the future.  The proposed &ldquo;peace clause&rdquo; gives rise to some concerns in this respect and we will be clarifying the position with the Commission during the discussions already referred to.</P>
    <P>Border protection covers the tariffication of border measures such as variable levies and commitments on current and minimum access.  The proposals put forward by the EC in relation to tariffication, together with the suggested safeguard clause, should provide adequate protection for almost all sectors of interest to Ireland.  A risk was identified in respect of skim milk powder and sugar but the Commission is proposing a lower rate of reduction for these products. The minimum access commitment, and in particular the level of aggregation that will be permissible, is the most critical concern in this area.  The Commission has proposed an aggregation approach in its submissions to Geneva and has assured the Council that this has been accepted by the US.  We are seeking to ensure that the final agreement makes <Col N="466" /> this explicit.  It is absolutely essential that there is no misunderstanding on this point and that all parties accept it.</P>
    <P>There are, of course, some positive aspects to the minimum access commitment since all other parties, including the US, would have to open up their markets so as to meet the 5 per cent commitment, if it is not already being met.  Thus EC producers would be able to export dairy products to the US market within these limits but they would of course be in competition with the other parties in the GATT.</P>
    <P>The timing of the final stages of these negotiations is not clear at the moment. When one considers that every deadline in this Round of talks has been broken, I think it unlikely that there will be an early conclusion to the negotiations.  A lot will depend on the attitude of the new US Administration and our latest information from Washington suggests that the new US Administration will be seeking an extension of the fast-track negotiating procedure but the timing, conditions and duration are not yet known.  The accepted view is that the Administration will seek a six to nine month extension of the procedure and so negotiations will probably not be concluded until early 1994 and not implemented until 1995.  Recent comments from Washington suggest that the US side itself may have some problems with certain elements of the EC/US outline accord, on agriculture, and in other areas of the talks, which the new Administration will wish to take up in the ongoing negotiations.  A special review group is now examining the US concerns in relation to all aspects of the Round and the position should become clearer when this group has reported.</P>
    <P>As has already been stated the GATT negotiations cover some 15 sectors, including agriculture.  In due course a decision may have to be taken on acceptance or rejection of a GATT deal.  That decision will take account of Ireland's balance of interests in all sectors.  The implications for future employment levels will of course be an important element in that decision and the impact <Col N="467" /> on agriculture, our largest indigenous industry, will be the principal consideration in that decision.  The Minister for Tourism and Trade who has overall responsibility for GATT and these negotiations will shortly authorise a consultancy study to examine the impact on all sectors.  The study will be carried out in co-operation with the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry and with the Ministers for Finance and Foreign Affairs.  The conclusions of this study and the resulting recommendations will be submitted to the Government as soon as possible.</P>
    <P>In conclusion I would like to summarise the position and our major concerns again.  We would have major difficulties with any agreement on agriculture not compatible with Common Agricultural Policy reform; volume restraints on subsidised exports pose a serious difficulty for Ireland and no one should under-estimate the extent of the problem which this aspect creates for us. The agriculture aspect cannot be dealt with in isolation or before a complete analysis of the overall GATT outcome has been undertaken.  Ireland has always been committed to a comprehensive and balanced result to the Round.  Equally we have been absolutely clear that our critical interests in agriculture, and indeed other relevant areas should not be sacrificed to this end.  That remains our position and only when all issues have been negotiated to the point of maximum possible consensus can the Government adopt its final position on the Round.  In regard to agriculture, I would emphasise, however, that in that final position we will not accept an outcome which goes beyond the Common Agricultural Policy reform parameters, unless we secure explicit commitments that our vital agriculture and food interests will be protected.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDarcy" hpid="Mr. D'Arcy Mr. D'Arcy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D'Arcy</NameTxt>
      <P>I compliment the Minister on his appointment and wish him well in his difficult job.  A Chathaoirligh, it is impossible to deal with the question of <Col N="468" /> GATT and agriculture in ten minutes so I will deal with a few aspects only</P>
      <P>We need, at this stage, to examine the background to the agriculture industry. Lately the Minister, Deputy Walsh, mentioned an 18 per cent increase in agriculture incomes in 1992 but he omitted to state that there had been a 12 per cent decrease in those incomes in 1991.  The overall increase in those two years would be about 4 per cent.  The only two products to receive substantial price increases in 1992 were milk and pigs.  Sheep farmers, cereal growers and beef producers had bad returns in 1991 and 1992.</P>
      <P>I would like the Minister's opinion on the study in progress at present in Brussels, on whether the MacSharry proposals will conflict with Common Agricultural Policy reforms.  I understand this study will report back by the end of March.  Can the Minister say, if the study report clearly states that the proposals do not conform with Common Agricultural Policy reforms, whether it will be sent back for negotiation or will there be a renegotiation of the entire deal?  We need this information now.  I was unaware that this study was in progress as it had received little publicity, nevertheless I consider it important.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Agriculture and food products account for approximately 40 per cent of Irish net exports.  Seventeen per cent of total employment is based on agriculture and agriculture exports are worth approximately £4 billion annually.  GATT proposed that between 1993 and 1999 the level of EC exports in volume terms would be cut by approximately 21 per cent and the value of export refunds by 36 per cent.  It also proposed to allow an increase in imports of between 3 and 5 per cent in each product sector.  These cuts would cost Irish agriculture between £200 million and £250 million.  This has not been accepted by the Department.  It is hard to arrive at an accurate figure, but it would be reasonable to say that the loss to Irish agriculture would be in that region.  That is a large sum of money.  This is in addition to already having 300,000 people out of work.  This will have a <Col N="469" /> devastating effect on employment in the agriculture industry.</P>
    <P>It is impossible to go into all areas of agriculture in the time available but I will say a few words about beef.  It should be remembered at the outset that the price for beef is 40p per lb. in Argentina and about 50p per lb. of carcase weight in Australia.  EC beef output is about 8 million tonnes of beef per annum.  As consumption stands at about 6.8 million tonnes, this leaves a surplus of approximately 1.2 million tonnes annually.  The post-GATT limit for beef exports for 1994 will be less than 1 million tonnes. This means a reduction in exports of over 200,000 tonnes compared to 1992 levels and eventually the reduction will be 400,000 tonnes.  I wish to inform the Minister this will have a serious impact on the beef sector.  From time to time there is a surplus on the market and last year there were approximately 200,000 extra beef cows and their progeny will come on the market in 1994 and 1995.  The same applies in France and Germany.  They have increased numbers of suckling cows, as they are known in Ireland and we are paying a subsidy on them.  Not alone will there be a reduction in our exports but there will be substantial increases in our production levels.  This will have a serious impact on the amount of beef available on the European market and a devastating effect on the overall price.  Beef prices in other countries, particularly in Australia and New Zealand of 40p to 60p per lb. are unrealistic in relation to our production costs.  We cannot, under any circumstances, produce beef at those prices.</P>
    <P>The proposed 21 per cent cut in the volume of EC dairy exports will mean a cut of 24 per cent to milk producers in the 1991 levels of production.  The Common Agricultural Policy reforms for dairying outline two 1 per cent cuts.  This will not be sufficient to meet GATT requirements. It is proposed that dairy imports will rise by 5 per cent on the domestic market.  This combination will require a 5 per cent reduction in our national milk quota.  The position will be especially critical for cheese exports.  GATT may <Col N="470" /> allow an increase in EC butter exports but, as we know, there is very little demand for this.  Irish dairy production is now facing the same fate as the Danish dairy industry.  Over the past 30 years in Denmark the number of milk producers has dropped from 185,000 to fewer than 15,000.  The goal is to have a single dairy co-op.  At present 85 per cent of Danish milk production is controlled by such a co-op.  This is something we cannot visualise for this country.  We have six or seven large dairy co-ops.  It can be argued that allowing the dairy co-ops to work together gives them more power in marketing and cuts down production costs. However, I cannot see the two large dairy co-ops &mdash; Avonmore and Waterford &mdash; getting together over the next four to five years.  I have been involved in negotiations that have been going on for approximately five years.  Under the existing structures it is impossible to bring them together.</P>
    <P>We cannot compare ourselves to Denmark. Milk is very important to our agriculture industry.  We have approximately 2 million dairy cows and they form the foundation for the agriculture industry because they also supply beef.</P>
    <P>I want to say a few words about sheep meat.  Sheep meat is very important to this country.  We have a large sheep herd. I have argued in the Dáil over the past two years about the importation of New Zealand lamb.  I again appeal to the Minister on this matter.  A GATT agreement allows New Zealand to export to the EC approximately 200,000 tonnes of lamb.  I have no problem with that because there is a slight shortfall and we are unable to fill requirements on the home market. What I object to is importing lamb into the EC when the markets are loaded, as they are continuously from April to September.  These imports cost Irish lamb producers approximately £10 per head and the Irish consumers get no value from this.  We have seen through the years that while sheep meat is bought on the open market cheaply, it is not sold cheaply either through butcher shops or supermarkets.</P>
    <P>The British are the greatest abusers of <Col N="471" /> this system.  In May, June and July in particular they continuously import low quality lamb and flood the British market.  I have described this as dumping and will continue to so describe it.  We have built up a good sheep flock which has been very successful for farmers.  This abuse is costing them the difference between making a reasonable profit and no profit.  Were it not for subsidies many sheep farmers would have to get out of producing lamb.  I appeal to the Minister to look at the situation in respect of sheep meat.  Little is being said about it.  I also ask him that arrangements be made in respect of the New Zealand imports, so that in the six months from October to March we would accept their imports into the EC based on the GATT agreement.</P>
    <P>The beef regime is due to be reviewed later this year.  I am advised there is likely to be a reduction in the aid quota and a price drop also.  This must be thoroughly resisted since it is one of the few profitable sectors of farming currently.  While progress was made in such matters as exempting direct income aids from GATT cuts, it is clear market related premia, such as the ewe premium, may be affected in further negotiations.</P>
    <P>The GATT agreement is complicated and people fail to understand its implications. Over a number of years the Americans have allowed farmers to increase the volume of all their products, particularly milk and beef.  They are still arguing that the EC should cap all levels of production.  I am not against that, provided everybody does the same.  The same argument is going on in New Zealand and Australia, but they are allowing their farmers to increase the volume of production in the hope of getting into the European market because their costs are much lower than ours and they can make profits considerably easier.</P>
    <P>Only when GATT is tried in practice will we see what the results are.  No one knows how the set aside of cereals is going to work; neither does anybody know what the volume of production will be.</P>
    <P>It is not expected that the GATT negotiations <Col N="472" /> will be complete before 1995.  I am glad of that because it will give us more time for debate and our farmers more time to get used to what is going to happen.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. R. Kiely Mr. R. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to this House.  I congratulate him on his reappointment which is well deserved and justified.</P>
      <P>I am pleased to speak on this most important subject.</P>
      <P>I commend the Leader of the House for agreeing to put this important debate. On our first sitting day he was asked by several Senators to have a debate on GATT and he responded.  He was commended also for responding to requests yesterday for many items of importance on the Order Paper today.</P>
      <P>Many people, especially those in farming organisations, are concerned about the GATT deal reached in Washington last November and its implications for Irish agriculture.  It is generally accepted that that agreement went beyond the Common Agricultural Policy reform package agreed last May.  The Minister in his speech said:</P>
      <P>The objective for agriculture, contained in the Ministerial Declaration, which launched the round, was to bring stability and balance to agriculture world trade through the correction of the market restrictions and distortions which had increasingly become a feature of the trading regime in that sector.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The GATT was first signed in 1947 and is both a unilateral treaty providing a code of rules for the conduct of world trade and a forum where countries can discuss and resolve their commercial problems and negotiate the reduction of barriers to trade.  The dual purpose of the GATT is embodied in the main principles and the multilateral trade negotiations. The main principles of the GATT include the following: non-discrimination between trading partners, achieved particularly by the application of the most-favoured-nation clause; protection of national industries solely through use <Col N="473" /> of custom tariffs; binding of custom tariffs in &ldquo;tariff schedules&rdquo;; negotiations with trading partners in order to compensate for increases and consultation and dispute settlement procedures.</P>
    <P>The GATT regulations also state that derogations from the rules can be granted to regional trading groups, to developing countries and in emergency situations. That provision is important for Ireland which should be considered a developing country.</P>
    <P>This is the eight Round of negotiations and began in September 1986 with a ministerial meeting in Uruguay.  Having overcome some difficulties, the participants decided to include agricultural services and intellectual property rights in the list of subjects for negotiation. In addition traditional subjects such as tariffs and non-tariff measures and safeguards were to be discussed.  With immediate effect the participating countries adopted a so-called stand-still and roll-back clause, whereby they undertook not to introduce any restrictions inconsistent with GATT privileges during negotiations and to gradually dismantle existing restrictions of this nature. With all that was undertaken it is understandable that the talks have been underway for almost six and a half years and, according to the Minister, will not be concluded until 1994.  Senator D'Arcy welcomed this date and I agree it will allow more time for discussion and for the teasing out of decisions that will affect our country.</P>
    <P>At the start of the agriculture negotiations a ministerial declaration stated that there was an urgent need to bring more discipline and predictability to world agriculture trade by correcting and preventing restrictions and distortions, including those related to structural surplus, so as to reduce uncertainty, imbalances and instability in world agriculure markets.  A mid-term review of the negotiations in April 1989 agreed that a long term reform objective for agriculture should be to provide for substantial progressive reductions in agricultural supports and protection sustained over an agreed time so that for the first time <Col N="474" /> agriculture could be brought under the general rules and disciplines of GATT with a serious attempt to reduce international protectionism.</P>
    <P>The CAIRNS Group, that is Australia, New Zealand, Canada and the United States, has for a major part of the negotiations been insisting on the total elimination of all agricultural support with special reference to the EC's export refund system.  Border protection measures and export refunds are an integral part of the dual pricing system of the Common Agricultural Policy and are linked inseparably to the overall support. Separate and specific commitments, market access and export refunds could have a serious adverse effect on Common Agricultural Policy and result in major changes in trade.  These changes would have serious consequences for Community markets and in particular for the Irish economy which is heavily dependent on export markets both within the Community and in third countries.  Singling out export refunds, for instance, for special treatment would have serious consequences for Irish farmers, processors, the Irish food industry and related industries.</P>
    <P>Since the beginning of this round of negotiations the Community has defended its strategy on agriculture successfully. There were isolated occasions on when it was indicated that the Community, subject to certain conditions being met, would be prepared to undertake some commitments on minimum market excess on the volume of produce which would be exported with export subsidies.  Ireland completely disagrees with this policy, stating that such commitments are beyond the Council of Ministers' negotiating mandate.  I understand other EC member states also object to this policy and I am sure Ireland will continue to object to it with vigour in the future.</P>
    <P>After intensive negotiations between the United States and the Commission last year an agreement was reached in Washington at the end of November that Common Agricultural Policy reform compensationary headage payments and <Col N="475" /> similar payments would not be subject to GATT discipline.  This was a satisfactory aspect of the agreement but the next main element of the agreement will be disastrous for Irish agriculture.  This element provides for the reduction of internal supports by 20 per cent over six years. Border measures, i.e. variable levies, will be converted to tariff equivalents, based on a system suggested by the Community, to be reduced by 36 per cent over six years.  Average 1989 subsidised exports would be reduced by 36 per cent in budgetary terms and 21 per cent in volume terms from 1994 over six years. The Minister outlined all of these proposals in his introductory speech.</P>
    <P>Within the Community the November GATT agreement will have to be accepted by the Council of Ministers. However, I understand the Commission has submitted revised schedules to the GATT headquarters in Geneva based on elements contained in the Washington agreement.  There should be no question of an agreement on agriculture only which required the Community to bear an unequal share of the reform of the international markets.  It is worth recalling that in this connection the Council's position is that any agreement must be compatible with the outcome of Common Agricultural Policy reform which was concluded after long and arduous negotiations last May.  The impact of these reforms is only now being fully appreciated within the Community and it would be totally unreasonable and irresponsible to expect European Community producers to make further sacrifices in the context of GATT.</P>
    <P>The results of the Common Agricultural Policy reform negotiations were satisfactory for Ireland.  There was a definite need for Common Agricultural Policy reform but it was important that the reform include an effective support policy which would ensure a more equitable distribution of support and that the position of developing countries on the periphery of Europe, such as Ireland and poorer countries, would be recognised.</P>
    <P>With regard to the preservation of the <Col N="476" /> traditional family farm, especially in Ireland, protection restrictions must be kept at a minimum and there must be adequate compensation for any further necessary restrictions on production.  I suppose farming production can be increased easily through fertilisers and intensive farm management.  Production restriction is necessary, probably, for the the purpose of control and especially tight maintenance.</P>
    <P>With regard to Common Agricultural Policy reform, our negotiator, the Minister, Deputy Walsh, did a good job.  He ensured that the herd limit for suckler cows was abolished, that the proposed milk and price quotas were dropped and direct headage and premia payments were increased from about £330 million to £620 million.  I congratulate the Minister for negotiating a good deal for Ireland on Common Agricultural Policy reform.  I am confident he will make sure that Ireland's position will not be affected and that our interest will be maintained in the outcome of the GATT negotiations.</P>
    <P>As Senators said, agriculture is vital to our economy.  It is a great source of employment, especially in its spin-off industries.  With regard to agriculture, our position must be that any outcome of the GATT meeting which goes beyond Common Agricultural Policy reform cannot be accepted because agriculture is vital to this country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I also welcome the Minister, Deputy Hyland.  However, he is not here as Minister for the Department of Agriculture alone, but of Food and Forestry. I would like to talk about the food area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The task facing us is one of providing jobs and success in the future.  Those jobs will not be created in agriculture.  The figures show there is less potential for employment growth in agriculture than in the food industry.  I welcome this debate because it will highlight to the Irish people that the future of the GATT negotiations is important to us.  The fact that the outcome of these negotiations is once again in some doubt is bad news for Ireland.  That the world seems to be slipping <Col N="477" /> back into protectionism is something we should be concerned about.</P>
    <P>There are three reasons the GATT agreement is of importance to us.  First it is important in regard to the EC and the wider European area and that area's trade with the outside world.  Our membership of the EC has removed the trade barriers between us and other EC countries, but trade with the rest of the world, with perhaps one exception which I will mention later, is of vital importance to us.  Our ability to sell within the EC depends on the ability of the EC economies to survive and thrive.  They are the ones to which we sell and they depend on their ability to trade outside EC borders. We tend to forget that one of the major aims of the Single Market is not just to increase the trade flows inside the EC but also to increase EC strength in world markets.  If Europe is to prosper and not be left behind, the next move forward to world economic growth will need favourable trading negotiations at the Uruguay Round of the GATT talks.</P>
    <P>The second reason GATT is important to Ireland &mdash; and I acknowledge its importance for agricultural exports &mdash; is that if we get this agreement it will extend the concept and practice of free trade into services.  That is a wider area in addition to manufactured goods and agriculture. The broadening of the GATT approach is of vital concern to this country because, potentially, nobody stands to gain more than we do in a liberalisation of world free trade in services.  I am convinced that our biggest task over the next ten years or so must be to bring to the development of tradeable services the same energy, resources and effort that we put into the development of manufacturing industry and agriculture in the past.</P>
    <P>Services is the area in which we can overcome the disadvantages we have, being on the periphery of Europe, by using the telecommunications that have become available in recent years.  Services is also the area where we can employ larger numbers of people because services, by their nature is a job intensive industry.  It is the area where we can get <Col N="478" /> that competitive advantage out of our key resources, our well educated young people and a tradition &mdash; which stretches back over centuries &mdash; of imagination and creativity that has very often only shown itself when our people have gone abroad. We have dipped our toe into this pool already with activities such as financial services and remote data processing of which there are many successful stories, particularly in the west of Ireland.</P>
    <P>In the years ahead this is the area we need to develop more aggressively alongside our continuing efforts to broaden our manufacturing and agricultural capabilities. If a large part of our future is in services, as I believe it will be, it becomes of vital national interest that we have a world in which there is free trade in services as well.  That is the new ground the new GATT agreement can open up.  That is why a failure to achieve agreement would be a serious setback to our development, even in areas outside agriculture. While we must take agriculture into account in the GATT negotiations, it is only one of a number of cards that we have to play.</P>
    <P>The third reason GATT is important to us in Ireland is that the United States is our fourth most important export market after Britain, Germany and France.  In fact, to say it is our fourth most important market is to understate its importance by a long shot.  To indigenous Irish companies that are usually small and medium in size, the US is a key market, probably export market number two and, in some cases, even export market number one. What this means is that our trade relations with the United States are of vital importance to the economy and they are of vital importance particularly in the area of trying to create jobs.</P>
    <P>It must be a matter of considerable concern to us that the new American Administration seems to be considerably more hawkish to trade than the previous Administration.  They seem to be considerably less ready to move forward on GATT and they seem to be about to turn the clock back towards protectionism instead of towards a freer world trade.</P>
    <P>I make this point because of the apparently <Col N="479" /> conciliatory remarks of President Clinton at the end of last week.  On that occasion he took an upbeat, almost a free trade, approach but unfortunately we are getting conflicting signals from the Clinton Administration, and even from the President.  In the first five weeks of this new Administration we have seen threats of punitive duties against European goods, including Irish goods.  We have also seen the rowing back on the agricultural agreements between the US and Europe which were concluded with such difficulty at the end of last year and which are an essential prelude to making further progress on GATT.</P>
    <P>We have seen an escalation of the dispute between the US and Europe over aircraft manufacturing, a dispute in which the President, speaking to the Boeing workers in Seattle, made some rather aggressive remarks about protectionism which is bad news for Ireland, and for the world.  This hardline attitude of the new American Administration to international world trade threatens recovery around the world.  A point which I made at the University of Southern California in Los Angeles last week was that this approach could rebound on the Americans and lead to a trade war. The United States has the most to gain from a global economic recovery and most to lose in the long run, if it focuses on short term gains only and tries to keep for itself the benefits of the current recovery.</P>
    <P>I would like to make a practical suggestion on this matter.  In a fortnight's time, around St. Patrick's Day, Government Ministers will travel overseas particularly to the United States.  They might put Ireland and the GATT at the top of their agenda ahead of the usual local issues. The future of GATT and the current flexing of muscles by the Americans on the trade scene is an issue of direct and vital concern to us and our Ministers should say so.  The present stance of the United States endangers their own position as well as the rest of world trade.</P>
    <P>Increased world trade can be an <Col N="480" /> important stepping stone to world peace and may help to establish justice, firmness and fairness between developing nations.  This vision should be part of Ireland's approach in day to day trade negotiations.  Let us wear an agricultural hat but let us not forget the food hat, the services hat and the other benefits we will receive from the conclusion of a successful GATT negotiation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JimTownsend" hpid="Mr. Townsend Mr. Townsend">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Townsend</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  Many Senators declared their interest before they spoke and I would like to declare mine.  Before the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Spring, and the Taoiseach, Deputy Reynolds, took pity on me and offered me this job I was a full-time farmer.  I lived and reared my family on what I produced from 50 acres and therefore, I see Common Agricultural Policy and GATT in a different light from others.  I would prefer if people did not take what I have to say as criticism but as a difference of opinion.</P>
      <P>Last week when the redundancies at Digital were announced all hell broke loose.  I work at the coalface of an indigenous industry in which, at a conservative estimate, 800 workers are forced into redundancy every month. There is reliable indication that when Common Agricultural Policy and GATT are in place, monthly farm redundancies will be equivalent to the closure of two Digital factories.  I am amazed that we kick up such a fuss about Digital, a multinational company over which we have no control, while we remain silent over the number of small farmers, equivalent to the workforce of 12 Digital factories who leave the land each year.  That number could be reduced with a bit of common sense and at no cost to the Exchequer or to the PAYE sector.</P>
      <P>When the former EC Commissioner for Agriculture, Mr. MacSharry, set about reforming the Common Agricultural Policy he wrote in a foreword to his proposals:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Our policy has not prevented large numbers of farmers leaving the land. <Col N="481" /> Furthermore 80 per cent of Common Agricultural Policy resources go to 20 per cent of the farmers because of the systems linkage of price support to food volume.</P>
    <P>As a small farmer I was delighted when I heard Mr. MacSharry say that because I believed he was a man who knew what was wrong and was in a position to do something about it.  Unfortunately I was wrong.  It is a case of the best laid schemes o' mice an' men Gang aft a-gley, an' lea'e us nought but grief and pain, for promised joy.</P>
    <P>The revised Common Agricultural Policy, which relies heavily on indirect income aid &mdash; some might call it dole &mdash; continues the system which puts small farmers at a disadvantage.  For example, a large farmer who in 1992 was able to buy 100 cows secured for himself £400 of indirect income aid per week.  The small farmer who purchased ten cows only received £40 per week.  It is no coincidence that when agreement on Common Agricultural Policy was reached the British Agriculture secretary, John Gummer, was loud in his praise of Mr. MacSharry.  Mr. Gummer was not thinking of small Irish farmers.</P>
    <P>In addition to Common Agricultural Policy being loaded against small farmers, there is evidence of a well organised campaign to encourage small farmers to leave their holdings.  Farmers are told in order to survive that they must have large acreage and do things on a large scale. According to figures I received from Teagase this is not the situation throughout Europe.  We are being told one side of the story only.  For example, there are 1.5 million dairy farmers in the EC with an average of 16 cows per holding.  Seventy five per cent of them produce less than 22,000 gallons of milk while 15 per cent produce over 44,000 gallons.  Cattle rearing takes place on 2.6 million holdings in the EC.  The average number of animals is 32 animals per holding and 80 per cent of holdings have less than 20 animals.  One million farmers keep sheep in the EC; 50 per cent of these have fewer than 50 ewes.  There are 4.3 million <Col N="482" /> farmers growing cereals and the average area under cereals per holding is 17.6 acres.  However, 88 per cent of cereal producers sow less than 44 acres.  We are reminded constantly about the large farmers in England and France but we are not told about the small farmers throughout Europe.  I wonder why?</P>
    <P>It has been Government policy for many years of successive Administrations to encourage small farmers to leave the land in order to take up jobs.  Those jobs are non-existent.  That policy should be reversed so as to discriminate in favour of small farmers.  If a proper direct income payment &mdash; I use the word &ldquo;direct income&rdquo; intentionally &mdash; was made relating to the adjusted acreage of the holding and family numbers and not to production or animal numbers, many of the estimated 8,000 to 10,000 farmers who leave the land each year would not do so. A family income supplement of the type which the ICMSA leader has called for, could be provided out of a small pecentage of the £1,500 million Ireland receives in Common Agricultural Policy transfers. If three per cent of the Common Agricultural Policy transfers was reserved &mdash; this could easily be done, given the amount of money fraudulently claimed for beef intervention &mdash; £90 per week could be given to 10,000 farmers to keep them on their holdings.  This measure would be of great help and should be seriously considered.  Farmers are leaving the land because they do not have enough money to remain.</P>
    <P>There has not been a national agricultural scheme which treated farmers equally since Deputy Blaney was Minister for Agriculture.  At present there are some pilot schemes in operation, one of which is known as the &rdquo;bottoms up&rdquo; scheme.  We thought that had something to do with sex and we did not apply for it.</P>
    <P>We have the Leader programme in parts of the country, and I hope what is happening in Tipperary is not an indication of how much is going to the small farmers.  Before we conclude the GATT negotiations something will have to be done about the Common Agricultural <Col N="483" /> Policy and some income given to smaller farmers.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I endorse the remarks made about the Minister and I welcome him here this afternoon.  Senator Kiely said that the Minister's re-appointment was deserved and I share that view because I know the work he did in the previous Administration.</P>
      <P>There is an implication in much of what has been written and spoken about in relation to GATT that an agreement has almost been reached.  That, of course, is not the case.  What we have is a bilateral deal between the EC's Commissioner for Agriculture and the United States, and it is only a bi-lateral deal if it stands up.  We are in the position of almost excluding the 94 other countries which are party to any proposed GATT deal.  That is important and needs to be borne in mind. Several Senators have talked about the importance of agriculture to the Irish economy.  There is no need to go into the figures in detail other than to say that about 42 per cent of our net foreign earnings are derived from food exports and about 26 per cent of our exports are agricultural compared to about 9 per cent for the Community as a whole.  That puts the position in relation to Ireland into perspective, and the outcome of the GATT agreement is crucially important for us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I support the view expressed by Senator Quinn that it is important for us, as a small open economy, to have an agreement on GATT but I do not subscribe to the view that that agreement can be achieved at the expense of agriculture and the farmers whom Senator Townsend has so eloquently defended.  Farming is an indigenous industry and, while I take the point made by Senator Quinn in relation to food, the two matters are intimately connected.  We cannot look at one to the exclusion of the other; we must look at both together.  Culliton has pointed the way in relation to how we can create jobs and how we can develop our indigenous food industry.  I support <Col N="484" /> the findings made by Culliton in that regard.</P>
    <P>The concern my party had about GATT was such that in June 1990 in this House we put down a motion &mdash; which I am glad to say was supported at the time &mdash; rejecting the negotiating position of the United States of America on the GATT Round.  Subsequently Deputy O'Malley, in his capacity as Minister for Industry and Commerce, told the GATT partners that the negotiations must allow the EC to continue to support agriculture and that strong rural society must be maintained not just in Ireland but throughout the Community.  That is the position which needs to be maintained by all our negotiators in the weeks and months ahead.  To do otherwise would condemn us to even more of the rural blight about which Senator Townsend has spoken.</P>
    <P>The food sector has been identified as a source of growth in jobs but it is bound up with agriculture.  If, as almost inevitably will be the case, as a result of Common Agricultural Policy reform we are faced with decreasing production of our land to supply the food industry, the dairies and beef factories, then the consequences are apparent from the point of view of unit costs and competitiveness within the industry.  The greatest problem is that our competitiveness is based on our undoubted ability to produce grass to the extent that no other country, with the possible exception of New Zealand, can produce.</P>
    <P>In Common Agricultural Policy reform we are faced with giving cereals a competitive advantage and allowing them to replace grass in the diet of cattle and sheep.  That is very serious from an Irish point of view.  If the indigenous food industry is to expand, it is important that we defend the competitive advantage underlying that industry in terms of our basic production.  We do need a GATT agreement but it cannot be at any price.</P>
    <P>The Minister, Deputy O'Shea, said that what was required was a fair and balanced outcome.  That is correct but he did say something in his concluding remarks about which I have a degree of <Col N="485" /> disquiet.  He said he would re-emphasise that the final position will not accept an outcome which goes beyond the Common Agricultural Policy reform parameters unless we secure explicit commitments that our vital agriculture and food interests will be protected.  In my view, he should have said we will not accept an outcome which goes beyond the Common Agricultural Policy reform parameters full stop, not &ldquo;unless&rdquo;.  That is to defend the people who are trying to live and survive in the rural environment.</P>
    <P>There has been a lot of concern about what happened at Digital in Galway.  It is right that that question would be debated in both Houses of the Oireachtas and examined in great detail.  There is, however, a rural blight in Ireland which is as devastating, and in many instances more devastating, than what is happening in Galway.  If these proposals are implemented it has been estimated that we will lose 450 jobs in the dairying sector and another 440 in the beef sector.  That is as many as were lost at Digital.</P>
    <P>Historically about 11 people a day have been leaving the land.  That is a catastrophe of far greater scale than the undoubted catastrophe which has faced the people of Galway.  It is a dignified, hidden catastrophe, with rural poverty and desperation, which is just as severe as any urban poverty and is going unnoticed.  We must bear this in mind when we debate these matters and reach agreements in international fora.  We have a duty to defend those people and it would be remiss of us if we were not to do so.</P>
    <P>There is a proposal that the reduction in internal Community support would be of the order of 21 per cent.  That is a very easy figure to mention but a lot of the time we do not establish the baseline, or the year of the baseline and there have been disagreements about how we calculate the measures of support.  We need to be very careful that we know exactly what these figures mean and what the consequences are.  Are we going back to 1986 when we started the Uruguay Round at Punta del Este?  Are we taking those figures?  My understanding is that <Col N="486" /> we are; we are looking for credit for the reductions in support that have taken place since then.  These matters however, have to be looked at again if, as seems to be the case, we are going to find it difficult to reach an agreement immediately, that it will not be reached, as the Minister indicated, until 1994 and will not be implemented until 1995.</P>
    <P>We all know what the United States is thinking about and doing at the moment. Will there be retrenchment?  One of the most unfortunate aspects of what has taken place in the GATT negotiations has been the intimidatory tactics used by the United States to browbeat people with a different view into thinking that they should accept the United States view of life as the only one that prevails. Threats of trade war and threats against individual products, such as Baileys Cream, are unacceptable in the civilised negotiating of a deal which is to world advantage.  I sometimes think that the plausible ideas put forward by the United States in respect of trade liberalisation and levelling the playing field are simply for US domestic advantage and not for philanthropic reasons.</P>
    <P>We must defend the national interest. These proposals could have disastrous consequences for rural Ireland.  Liberalisation is acceptable but destitution is not.  What is good for farming is good for the economy, and the fundamental role of the family farm in our society and in European society must be defended. That can be done by consensus; we are all on the same side of the fence on this. I hope the Minister will bring those thoughts to bear in future negotiations.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCalnan" hpid="Mr. Calnan Mr. Calnan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calnan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister and the Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and Forestry, Deputy O'Shea, who was here earlier.  I also welcome the speech made by the Minister last night on the reformed Common Agricultural Policy because all these matters are intertwined with the GATT debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This document deals mainly with the Uruguay Round which covers agricultural aspects.  Many years ago, the <Col N="487" /> implementation of a cheap grains policy led to widespread evictions throughout western Europe, especially in England and Ireland.  I hate to see trade wars developing between groups as strong as the EC and the CAIRNS Group which includes Canada, the United States, Australia and New Zealand, whose economies have a strong agricultural base. Let us learn from history; it is better to negotiate early and reach proper agreements than to indulge in brinkmanship with the result that many smaller producers and those who are less well off will suffer.</P>
    <P>In the United States there are big ranches.  If a person with 1,000 acres makes only £1 per acre he is making £1,000 but a man with only 20 acres will make £20.  From those figures it can be seen why America can produce goods much more cheaply than we can.  We cannot just bring it down to economics. We have talk about the social fabric of Irish society.  In some areas in this country such as south-west Cork, many families have been raised on small farms.  I am glad to see that the Common Agricultural Policy as reformed will be exempted from GATT disciplines.</P>
    <P>I also welcome the fact that disadvantaged areas will be excluded from GATT disciplines.  I live in a borderline area &mdash; a few miles up the road is a severely handicapped area and a few miles on the other side there is good land that is not included in disadvantaged areas.  I know the problems faced by people in the disadvantaged area and I am glad they will be excluded from the GATT disciplines.  In my area the town-lands on a hill overlooking valleys are not included in the disadvantaged areas but the valleys are.  This is an anomaly which I hope will be rectified shortly; there are three or four of these areas close to my home.</P>
    <P>Many other countries, including the United States, Australia and Canada, have looked for the elimination of all supports for agriculture.  That is not good enough because if an agricultural economy has been working, year after year, <Col N="488" /> getting these supports and that lifeline is taken away people will be left bankrupt. There is no way that can be done.  Since the early 1970s we have accumulated surpluses in beef, cereals and sheep.  Opening the American market to Irish goods and promoting it properly would be a big advantage if a GATT agreement was reached with proper limits.  American cities, especially on the east coast, have huge markets.</P>
    <P>I come from an area where the quality of the land many not be the best.  There are many mountains and hills but we have fresh vegetables, clean air, a pollution free countryside.  If the early ripening season in the extreme south-west could be exploited, and if there was proper marketing, many small farmers could make a good living from new enterprises. The Leader programme is working well in the area and many of the projects aided are doing extremely well.</P>
    <P>I hope the new administration will look on Europe with a view to co-operation rather than competition.  Europe has much to offer the United States and other GATT countries.  While the Uruguay Round deals only with agriculture, there are 14 other sectors that have to be dealt with, and there will have to be some bargaining.  I hope factories will not have to close, as happened in my own town in a factory employing 240 people, some lost their jobs because it was cheaper to produce the goods in a similar factory in Thailand and import them into the EC. I do not know how we can prevent that but something should be done to ensure that this does not happen to other factories. The IDA and FÁS spend a great deal of money promoting industry here and we do not want to see this money being wasted.</P>
    <P>We do not want a deterioration in the Common Agricultural Policy as reformed and we do not want to give anything on the Common Agricultural Policy in return for benefits for other sectors in future GATT agreements.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerryReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>Thee was a discussion on today's &ldquo;Morning Ireland&rdquo; about farmers in north Longford, Leitrim and <Col N="489" /> parts of Roscommon who are looking to have severely disadvantaged areas &mdash; I am not sure what the term is&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamHyland" hpid="Mr. Hyland Mr. Hyland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hyland</NameTxt>
      <P>Severely disadvantaged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerryReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it disadvantaged at present?  As somebody who lives there, I can say it is severely disadvantaged from an agricultural point of view which will have serious consequences for the future development of the area.  I would be grateful if pressure could be put on the European Commission to have the area brought into the severely disadvantaged category.  According to the Irish news this morning the grants per livestock unit range from £40 to £60 and for cow and cow suckler grants range from £80 to £100.  That money is needed because over the last couple of years it has become very difficult for farmers in Sligo and Leitrim to earn a livelihood from their farms.</P>
      <P>My county has suffered greatly from emigration; the number of young people remaining on family farms is small.  Financial incentives are necessary because the farming land is insufficient to provide a living.  Farms are not big enough, land is marginal and the available incentives are not adequate.  We must try to keep people in rural Ireland; de-population is a national problem.  Rural development is a main focus of the Minister's Department. I know the Minister is committed to it and that he visited Arigna last week. Increased financial incentives could help retain population in rural areas.  I would be grateful if the Minister would endeavour to have this area termed &ldquo;severely disadvantaged&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Recommendations have been made for early retirement schemes for farmers and I noticed that £1,000,000 has been set aside for this purpose in this year's budget.  If the number of requests and inquiries about farmer retirement I have received since my election to this House is a guide £1,000,000 will not provide the necessary finance.  It is a worth-while scheme and I would be grateful if it could be looked into also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="490" />
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be presumptuous of anybody to try to understand fully the complex and detailed GATT negotiations that have taken place over several years.  Suffice to say that a global settlement framework is necessary to avoid the disastrous consequences of a trade war.  The Government, the Minister and his Department are to be complimented on the detailed work carried out for these negotiations over many years by technical people in various Departments.  We support the Government's stand in the GATT negotiations.</P>
      <P>Last night we discussed an international situation in which, despite talk of surpluses and over production, 40 million people are dying of starvation.  Surely it is within the capacity of international politicians today to achieve a balance between food requirements and food production.  It is reasonable to expect imbalances here and there no matter what system is used, but it is an indictment of past and present economic policies that millions of people are currently suffering from lack of food.  Additional millions are threatened with starvation because we cannot deal effectively with the food crisis.  The food supply situation in southern Africa is deteriorating rapidly because of drought and mismanagement while we discuss control of production levels.</P>
      <P>It would be easy to condemn outright the international effort being made in this regard.  Nevertheless, there is serious cause for concern in international trading when global arrangements have to be made for massive curtailment of beef production at a time when millions of people worldwide, suffer from starvation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is difficult to understand the implications of the GATT negotiations at local level.  I am glad that the Minister has indicated this afternoon that an evaluation will be carried out between Ministers with reponsibility for foreign affairs, agriculture, tourism and trade to assess fully the implications of the GATT when it is finally agreed.  We have a general idea now of the shape it is taking.  There may be some delays but we cannot afford a delay which would threaten the stability <Col N="491" /> of international trade generally.  Nevertheless we need to know precisely how the negotiations will impact on the farmers and others.  Agriculture is not the only sector involved in GATT; there are 15 or 16 other sectors involved also.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Minister's commitments this afternoon, that at the European Commission, the Council of Ministers including the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry will continue to ensure that the impact of the negotiations on the Irish agricultural industry will be minimised. I am concerned that compliance with the Common Agricultural Policy reforms will be observed so as to ensure the maximum benefit to Irish farmers, bearing in mind that direct payments to farmers over the next three to four years will be in the region of £700 million. Those who cannot organise their business to get the maximum benefit from the scheme will lose out heavily.  I welcome the commitments given here last night by the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry that every assistance would be given by the Department to help farmers claim their entitlements under the new arrangements resulting from the Common Agricultural Policy changes so that the maximum benefit will be paid directly into the farmer's pocket.</P>
    <P>I welcome a continuation of the strong line adopted by successive Ministers in these negotiations insisting that Ireland should not have to bear a disproportionate reduction in production levels.  The GATT negotiations bring home to all of us the necessity to streamline our economy to avoid a recurrence of our fast dependence on export markets. At present, we are losing jobs in a range of Irish industries because we are not able to avail of available opportunities especially in the food sector.  Yesterday, An Bord Tráchtála announced opportunities for massive job creation in 40 or 50 different areas of the food processing industry, through the use of agricultural produce.</P>
    <P>In view of these GATT negotiations, it is timely that we start to examine carefully how we can transform our excellent <Col N="492" /> opportunities for agricultural production into real jobs, based on the strength of our agricultural resources.  This is an opportunity to develop many more jobs in the food area.  I am pleased that the Minister of State for Agriculture, Food and Forestry is here because it is in this area that we can minimise the impact of any GATT negotiations on our economy.</P>
    <P>We can minimise the impact of any GATT negotiations to a large extent by giving the proper support to Irish industry to avail of the opportunities provided by substituting Irish produced goods for imports.  I am sorry Senator Quinn is not present because recently, in one of the large supermarket chains in Ennis, it was almost impossible to buy an Irish produced commodity.  On the shelves there were Scottish biscuits and beef steaks from Denmark, at a time when we have serious problems with agricultural production.  This issue needs to be debated on another day.</P>
    <P>I want to encourage the Minister to proceed as soon as possible with the review he promised of the impact of these negotiations on our econmy, and on various sectors, including the agriculture industry.  Now, after years of debate about the GATT negotiations and how they will affect the livelihood and the lives of people in agriculture and elsewhere that the European Community is thinking of setting up a committee of experts to see what the real impact will be.  That is putting the cart before the horse.  This should have been done many years ago.</P>
    <P>I welcome the commitments given by the Minister today and I hope he will continue the good work done in the Department.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>We were fortunate in having a Commissioner of the calibre of Ray MacSharry to steer not alone the Common Agricultural Policy negotiations but also the GATT negotiations. The former Minister for Agriculture and Food, Senator O'Kennedy, also lent his hand to that enormous task on behalf of the Irish people.  The present Minister, Deputy Walsh, and the Minister of State, <Col N="493" /> Deputy Hyland, have a grave responsibility to carry in the weeks and months ahead.</P>
      <P>As Senator Daly said, much needs to be done, especially when we see multinationals, such as Digital, leaving the country.  Many of our State bodies which were supposed to be promoting our dairy, beef, sheep and pork products, have only been shadow-boxing and playing around.  They went on the grand tour of Europe in the last number of years but we did not get value for money.</P>
      <P>Some years ago I spoke to a man involved in the importation of intervention beef into Italy.  He told me that the feeble efforts made by CBF representatives over the years to promote the sale in Italy of our high quality, grass produced beef was a national scandal. CBF had an office there but, the gentleman in change was an invisible figure, he was never available.  Later, that gentleman started up in the meat business &mdash; he was too busy with other issues to deal with what he was sent out to do.  Our meat factories were dumping the finest quality beef into intervention, causing other problems down the line.  Certain bodies were supposed to promote our top class products over the last 15 years or more but all they did was pay lip service to it.  That is sad and reflects on the present situation where there is a constant drift from the land.</P>
      <P>I wish the Minister and the Minister of State success in the months ahead in these critical Common Agricultural Policy and GATT negotiations.  It is important to keep people in rural areas and to create jobs in the towns and cities.  I would hate to think what would have happened if the Commissioner for Agriculture at that time had been British.  We would probably be in an even worse situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The support reductions are supposed to apply over a six year period commencing in 1994.  All those regulations and the cuts in the protection of supports are irreversible.  The levels of protection of support applying in 1999, the last of the six year reductions, cannot be subsequently increased by the EC, in other <Col N="494" /> words, they would be permanent.  That is very serious.</P>
    <P>The US-EC agreement would involve a 36 per cent cut in the value of export refunds and a 21 per cent cut in the volume of products covered by export refunds.  These cuts are calculated from a base which is the average for the years 1986-90; that is unfair and should be changed.</P>
    <P>In cereals alone the cut will be 11.1 million tonnes, or a 32 per cent cut.  The farmer will be affected but thousands of jobs will be lost downstream and we will be flooded with cheap imported junk from all over the world.  We will no longer be allowed produce high quality feed grain.  In the sugar beet area, a 3 million tonne or 19 per cent cut in volume, will cost jobs.  In the beef area the cut will be 480,000 tonnes or 38 per cent in volume. That will have major implications for us. We have failed miserably down the years to market our products.  We went for the easy option.  It was a failure of the Common Agricultural Policy that it was more profitable for beef processors to dump their beef into intervention.  We are now at the end of that road.</P>
    <P>I question the accountability of the various bodies which were supposed to be supporting and promoting our beef, pig meat, lamb, butter or cheese products, abroad and if they got value for taxpayers' money over the years.  I appeal to the Minister to look at that.  The day for shadow-boxing or people globetrotting and producing very little is long gone.  We want to see markets.  We have a high quality grass-produced commodity.</P>
    <P>We want to keep people on the land. It will be a long haul to create more jobs in the industrial area.  The pig meat industry is in serious trouble &mdash; a cut of 270,000 tonnes or 41 per cent.  That too will backfire on the farmer because fewer pigs will be produced to consume the home-grown grain.  Our butter quota will be cut by 20,000 tonnes or 6 per cent; our cheese quota will be cut by 170,000 tonnes or 35 per cent.</P>
    <P>On the other hand support was obtained under Common Agricultural Policy negotiations.  Both Ministers <Col N="495" /> Walsh and Hyland fought hard for this support but it might not be sufficient to diminish the impact of these severe cuts although I know that the cuts will not apply to disadvantaged areas.  The proposed cuts in beef production mean that Ireland would have to progressively cut its volume of beef exports to non-EC countries by 200,000 cattle per annum, a frightening figure, given that non-EC markets have only recently been opened up.  We are going to be hemmed in.  In the dairy industry, a combination of increases of import access to the EC and a cut in export volumes by 570,000 tonnes will result in a cut of EC milk quota by at least 5 per cent.  This agreement therefore is riddled with dangers.</P>
    <P>In addition to the loss of 11 million tonnes of cereal exports, the cereal sector will have to cope with additional substitute imports.  We will be flooded with low cost junk from all over the world.</P>
    <P>The proposed cuts envisaged for Ireland are serious, but should be looked at in conjunction with Common Agricultural Policy reform.  We appreciate the hard work put into Common Agricultural Policy reform which was necessitated by overproduction.  Over-production was neglected for many years, particularly in the meat industry, where with high class beef being dumped into intervention. Nobody tried to market our excess products, nor did the system encourage that. The quantity of produce dumped into intervention was a national scandal.  Surpluses built up and we were left eventually without a market.  Farmers should be paid higher premiums in compensation for cuts in intervention and in premium payments, considering the cuts in production likely to take place under GATT. Cuts in cereals will be compensated for by paying farmers to set aside 15 per cent of their cereal growing land.  There is also a premium of £29 a head payable to farmers who reduce their bull numbers. We are returning to dog-and-stick farming. The average to small farmer will not survive; the bigger farmer will cope.  If the small farm is removed, it will be a sad day for rural Ireland.  Worries have been <Col N="496" /> expressed that the Common Agricultural Policy reforms will not be enough to subsidise farmers for losses under GATT. The GATT reductions should then be modified and implemented with a view to keeping the maximum number of people on Irish farms and the base period used should be 1990, and not the average of 1986-90.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely) Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. R. Kiely)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry to interrupt you but it was ordered that speeches should last for ten minutes only.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>Have I exceeded it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>You have exceeded it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Give him more time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanByrne" hpid="Mr. Byrne Mr. Byrne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Byrne</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish Minister Hyland and Minister Walsh every success in the months ahead because they have much to do to rescue the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald Mr. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>At 2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 10 March 1993.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 3.55 p.m. and resumed at 4 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. -" RHead="Tallaght Hospital Project">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Tallaght Hospital Project.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>With the permission of the House, I would like to share my time with Senator Cosgrave and Senator Norris.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I raised the subject early in the life of this new Government because of the commitments given by the Labour Party in particular, but also by other parties during and since the election campaign on the future of the Adelaide <Col N="497" /> Hospital.  I welcome the Minister to the House in whose constituency the Tallaght Hospital will be located.  It is appropriate that he should be here and I am grateful to him for coming.  I should remind the House of the commitments made.  The Programme for a Partnership Government states that the ethos and traditions of the Adelaide Hospital will be fully protected in the broad structure and management of the new hospital.  The second commitment was specific and was given by Mr. Barry Desmond, MEP, the Labour Party's Director of Elections, during the negotiations on the Programme for a Partnership Government. He said that not only would it be a major issue within the discussions but that the Labour Party had always been emphatically supportive of the Adelaide's position. The Adelaide Hospital was extremely grateful for this statement, both during and since the election campaign.</P>
      <P>This story has been going on for a long time.  The Minister will be aware that negotiations between the Meath Hospital, the National Children's Hospital and the Adelaide Hospital have broken down on two occasions.  There have been 39 meetings and they have been unable to reach agreement.  I was disappointed to hear that, following a meeting with the Minister, a third round of negotiations was proposed.  I do not believe there is hope that yet another round of negotiations will resolve this problem which has proved so intractable. It is time for the Government to take direct action, to put its money where its mouth is, to fulfil the commitment it gave before, during and after the election campaign and in the Programme for a Partnership Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The first question I would like the Minister to answer is what plans the Government have to honour this commitment? Will structures be put in place, or is the Government going to toss this problem back into the court of the three hospitals who cannot agree?  The Government, and in particular the Labour Party, has committed itself to a principle that the liberal ethos of the <Col N="498" /> Adelaide Hospital will be preserved and protected.  Given that the three hospitals cannot agree on this principle, Government protection is needed.  The Adelaide Hospital must have more than reassuring noises from the Labour Party and the Government; it must have action and it must have that action as soon as possible. It is no secret that the Adelaide Hospital was disturbed by the lack of commitment from the last Government to the protection of this ethos.  People became impatient with the reassuring noises which were followed by no action.</P>
    <P>A bigger issue here is how we, as a nation, treat minorities.  It is more than just the Adelaide Hospital that is involved in this.  Senator Norris and I represent a significant number of people from Northern Ireland in this House &mdash; in relation to this, I am delighted to see Senator Wilson in the Chamber &mdash; and the one issue which keeps recurring in correspondence is the Adelaide Hospital and what the Government in the Republic is doing about it.  They see this as a litmus test for how we, as a Catholic country, treat our Protestant minority and if we are liberal minded.  If we are to convince them that we are serious about liberalism &mdash; I doubt if we all are although I believe the Labour Party's commitment is genuine but we want to see action on it &mdash; we should give the Adelaide Hospital guarantees that the liberal ethos and the nursing school will be preserved. It is an issue of a medical ethos as well; it is an issue of doctor-patient confidentiality. It is important that issues, such as fertility, contraception and genetic counselling, are respected as a matter of doctor-patient confidentiality and that the Adelaide Hospital is given these guarantees immediately.</P>
    <P>We can make a fresh start today by getting a solid commitment from the Minister that action, other than sending the parties back for talks which have already broken down, will be forthcoming. This is a vital issue in North-South relations.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to have the opportunity to speak in this debate.  I do <Col N="499" /> not want to start the discussion because I have not had an opportunity to consult with the board of the Adelaide Hospital. I understand delicate negotiations are in progress.  I hope there will be a degree of flexibility.</P>
      <P>Both I and the Minister know that the people of Tallaght need a hospital and that this wrangling ought to stop.  It is important that the ethos of the Adelaide Hospital be preserved.  One deprecates the phraseology of Protestant ethos versus Catholic ethos.  The difficulty, however, is that there are Catholic ethics committees in almost all the other hospitals and they reflect a narrow view in which certain perfectly legal procedures are prohibited and which the Adelaide Hospital allows.  As Senator Ross said, it repects the primacy of the confidential relationship between the patient and the doctor.  For that reason, the Protestant ethos can include the Catholic ethos but not the other way around.  I also ask the Minister for a satisfactory response.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GordonWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>May I make a comment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ross can decide as Senator Cosgrave is not here and there is one minute left.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I am happy to share my time with Senator Wilson.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GordonWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not represent the Protestant people of Northern Ireland but I am one of them.  I assure you this is an issue about which many Protestant people in Northern Ireland are greatly concerned.  I hear this subject from pulpits, I read it in papers, and as Senator Ross has said, it is perceived as a litmus test of the Government's intention to abide by its undertaking in relation to the Adelaide Hospital.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Minister for Equality and Law Reform (Mr. Taylor) Mervyn Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Equality and Law Reform (Mr. Taylor)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad the Senator has given me an opportunity to reiterate the Government's commitment to the Tallaght Hospital project.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The hospital will have 467 beds with <Col N="500" /> full state of the art support facilities and will incorporate the Meath Hospital, the Adelaide Hospital and the National Children's Hospital, Harcourt Street.</P>
    <P>The Government is committed to the protection of the ethos and traditions of the Adelaide Hospital and the other two hospitals.  This reassurance has been given on many occasions by previous Ministers for Health and I am happy to repeat it again today.</P>
    <P>In relation to the question of adequate funding for the Adelaide Hospital, I would like to emphasise that the allocation of Government resources to the health sector for 1993 represents some 21 per cent of overall Government supply services spending.  This represents an increase of some 5 per cent to 6 per cent on the 1992 out-turn figure.  It is the Minister for Health's intention to make available to each health agency a level of funding sufficient to maintain services at the 1992 approved levels generally.</P>
    <P>Inherent in the achievement of this aim is the need for individual health agencies to utilise resources as efficiently as possible and, in order that this might be achieved, efficiency targets have been set for agencies in payroll, non-pay and income areas.</P>
    <P>With particular reference to the Adelaide Hospital, I wish to make it clear to the House that the Minister for Health will be providing the hospital with the funds necessary to maintain the service levels approved by his Department for 1992.  Following the notification to the hospital of their non-capital allocation for 1993, which will issue shortly, discussions will take place between officers of his Department and the hospital regarding the management of the funding and service levels during 1993.</P>
    <P>The ethos of the Adelaide Hospital has played a distinctive role in the development of Irish healthcare.  This is in no small part due to the quality of its nurse training.  In this regard, I am particularly pleased to repeat again to the Seanad the categorical assurances given by previous Ministers for Health that this tradition will be maintained in the new hospital at Tallaght and that 40 places in the new <Col N="501" /> nursing school will be reserved for nurses from the Adelaide tradition.</P>
    <P>The Protestant Community has expressed its concern that the hospital's valuable tradition may in some way be diminished if it were to join with the Meath and the National Children's Hospital, and move out to Tallaght. Indeed, the two other hospitals may well echo those sentiments in relation to their own particular traditions, which have also made a substantial contribution to the delivery of health services in this country.  It is important that the unique traditions associated with all three hospitals are protected so that the transfer to the new hospital in Tallaght will be successful and that the high quality of patients care which has always been their hallmark can be strengthened and developed at Tallaght.</P>
    <P>I can again confirm that the construction of Tallaght Hospital is the top Government priority in the health capital programme and will commence as soon as possible this year.  The project is proceeding with all possible speed.</P>
    <P>On Friday, 19 February last, the Minister for Health met with the Tallaght Hospital Board and the three hospitals involved &mdash; the Adelaide, the Meath and the National Children's Hospital to ensure that the necessary planning and tender documentation changes were finalised as quickly as possible.  The Minister also met with the Tallaght Hospital Action Group and Tallaght Community Council on 26 February to inform them of progress on the project.</P>
    <P>The Tallaght Hospital Board was asked by the Minister for Health to finalise the revised functional content of the hospital within two weeks and I am glad to report that the agreed revised functional content document was submitted to the Minister for Health this morning by the Tallaght Hospital Board Chairman, Professor Richard Conroy.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Health has also informed the Meath, Adelaide and National Children's Hospitals that Professor David Kennedy and Mr. David Kingston have agreed to act as facilitators with regard to an agreement between the <Col N="502" /> three hospitals on the Board structure and management for the new hospital. The Minister has asked for this work to be completed by June of this year.  I understand that this process is now underway.  The Minister for Health and I are confident that with the necessary goodwill and co-operation on all sides it will be possible to reach an agreement which fully protects the interests of all parties.</P>
    <P>Senator Ross in his statement asked for a Government guarantee that the ethos of the Adelaide Hospital would be preserved in Tallaght.  I refer Senator Ross and the other Senators to the Programme for a Partnership Government in which the Tallaght Hospital project is the only project singled out for specific mention.  I draw the attention of the House to the specific written guarantee given in that Programme that the ethos of the Adelaide Hospital will be preserved in Tallaght.  There could be no greater commitment to the Adelaide than that written statement specifically and unusually put into the Programme for Government.</P>
    <P>Finally, I wish to confirm again to the Seanad and to the people of Tallaght in particular that the Minister for Health has put in place an action plan to ensure that the building commences at the earliest possible date in 1993.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for his reply.  I am not sure that I share his confidence about goodwill and co-operation on all sides ensuring the success of these negotiations in view of the fact that they have already broken down once.  I ask the Minister what action he intends taking if they break down on this issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MervynTaylor" hpid="Mr. Taylor Mr. Taylor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Taylor</NameTxt>
      <P>Ideally it would not be advisable for the Minister for Health to impose a solution or an agreement on the three interests concerned.  I am sure the Senator will agree that it would be preferable for the three parties concerned who are going to have to work together as doctors and hospital staff during the coming year to reach their own agreement by mutual discussions and <Col N="503" /> negotiation.  That may be difficult and may require compromise and give and take on all sides; these elements are part and parcel of all negotiations.  Talks may be difficult and complex given the different interests to be considered.  The Minister for Health will provide every encouragement and facility possible to ensure that in this part of Ireland sufficient goodwill can be generated to establish a hospital incorporating two distinct ethoses.</P>
      <P>Nobody suggests that Tallaght Hospital is going to be the Adelaide Hospital or the Meath Hospital or the National Children's Hospital transferred to Tallaght.  It will be a merger of the three which should give strength and value to all sides.  I have no hesitation in reiterating the guarantee included in the Programme that the ethos of the Adelaide will be preserved.  It should be possible with goodwill on all sides to reach mutual agreement on a <i>modus operandi</i> for this hospital which is needed not only by the people of Tallaght but all the people in Dublin south-west.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, Minister.  I understand it is the Minister's first time in this House.  I welcome him to the House and wish him every good luck in his Department.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. -" RHead="Toxic Waste Disposal">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Toxic Waste Disposal.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Farrelly that on the Motion on the Adjournment of the House today he proposes to raise the following matter: To ask the Minister for the Environment to outline the Government's policy on toxic waste disposal in Ireland.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Browne, and wish him luck in his new appointment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to raise this matter and to join with him in welcoming the Minister, Deputy Browne.  I wish him well in his new position, but we <Col N="504" /> hope that people will have an opportunity to give an opinion on what is happening.</P>
      <P>The motion asks the Minister for the Environment to outline the Government's policy on toxic waste disposal in Ireland.  I asked this question because I do not know of a policy on the disposal of toxic waste in this country.  The Minister is aware that the only site to store toxic waste is located in the middle of rural farm land in County Meath.  Since the planning application was granted in 1986 for the operation of a distillation plant on a site at Lobinstown a number of problems have arisen from spillages, work at the site and danger to health from storage.  In consequence of these spillages, the council have issued a section 12 notice and asked for work to be discontinued on the site.  However, there is still toxic waste on the site which is a danger to the health of the children in the community, if it is not handled properly.  The local doctors have been treating children more often because of fumes and contamination than had been the case before this site was developed.</P>
      <P>I ask the Minister what is Government policy, if there is a policy?  If there is not a policy, does he agree that commodities produced for human consumption by dairy, sheep and beef farmers should be stored in a rural area?</P>
      <P>The site is close to a river supplying water to the town of Ardee.  Would the Minister agree that because of the risk of spillages the siting of this or similar plants in such areas is not acceptable?</P>
      <P>This debate should at least ascertain Government policy in this area.  Will instructions be issued to local authorities stating that the rules and regulations must be adhered to in the event of planning permission being sought for such sites? Is the Minister aware that toxic waste is being stored in or around the city of Dublin until it can be transported to the United Kingdom?  There should be proper regulations and storage facilities on sites where such materials are stored. There should also be full-time supervision where these products are stored.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am not aware of any toxic waste site in the country but this one.  If local authority <Col N="505" /> approval is given for a licence to operate, such a site could be worth in the region of £5 million to £10 million.  This means there are mega bucks involved for the owner of such a site.  The haphazard way we have dealt with toxic waste products from different companies must not be allowed continue.</P>
    <P>If there is no policy in this area, will the Government produce one?  Will proper rules and regulations be sent to the local authorities to ensure that these plants will be sited some distance from agricultural land so that they will not be a health hazard if there should be accidental spillages?  It is only right to point out that in 1989 there was a spillage and an emergency plan by Meath County Council had to be put into operation and the local people had to be evacuated from their homes.  We are not dealing with a substance such as vegetable oil.  It is more serious than that.  There is a lot more at stake for the people in the area if all the licences applied for are granted.</P>
    <P>Every government should have a policy to deal with these matters.  It should instruct local authorities if and when applications are made that they can only consider sites that, in the event of spillages, will not endanger the agricultural community or the health of the local population.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrowne2" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Browne) Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Browne)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Browne)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank you, a Leas-Chathaoirligh, for your good wishes and thank Senator Farrelly for this important question.  I also thank him for his good wishes and assure him I will be available for four or five years to answer any questions he may raise.  I compliment him on his election as Senator.</P>
      <P>I assure Senator Farrelly that many important measures in relation to hazardous waste policy are already in place in Ireland, and that more are being developed in response to new requirements.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Under the 1982 European Communities (Toxic and Dangerous Waste) Regulations, each local authority is responsible for the planning, organisation and supervision of operations for <Col N="506" /> the disposal of toxic and dangerous waste in their functional areas and for the authorisation of the storage, treatment and deposition of such waste.</P>
    <P>In addition to the 1982 Regulations, a wide body of regulatory controls has been developed in relation to hazardous waste transport and various specific categories of hazardous wastes.  I refer for instance to regulations dealing with waste oils, asbestos waste, and PCB/PCTs.</P>
    <P>Important new provisions are contained in the Environmental Protection Agency Act, 1992.  This will bring all operations with significant polluting potential within the scope of integrated pollution control.  The chemical, food production, paper, textiles and metals sectors are among those which will be subject to Environmental Protection Agency licensing, this will clearly include waste control aspects, as well as all aspects affecting air and water pollution.</P>
    <P>Current Irish policy in relation to hazardous wastes rests on the strict enforcement of relevant EC and national legislation in accordance with special waste management plans prepared by local authorities.  The Government is however committed to improving arrangements for hazardous waste planning. There is provision in the Environmental Protection Agency Act for this function to be taken over on a national basis by the Environmental Protection Agency, and we intend that this will be done as soon as practicable.  The Programme for a Partnership Government contains a clear commitment to the early introduction of a Waste Bill, which will provide an even wider framework for future waste management policies.</P>
    <P>National quantities of hazardous wastes are estimated at some 60,000 tonnes, with organic and chlorinated solvents representing the large bulk of this amount.  It is worth pointing out that while total usage of such solvents has increased considerably, so too has their rate of recycling, which now stands at around 70 per cent.  Virtually all of the remainder of hazardous wastes is disposed of on site or exported.</P>
    <P>There are obvious economic and <Col N="507" /> environmental advantages in the minimization of waste at source.  The Environmental Action Programme indicated the Government's determination to promote, primarily through the industrial development agencies, the adoption of clean technologies and low waste production processes by industry.  Through my Department, funds are being provided under the EC Stride Operation Programme for the establishment of a cleaner production programme centre at UCC.  Funds have also been provided for a clean technology centre based in Cork regional technical college.  The Department of the Environment has also commissioned a study on means to promote greater uptake of clean technologies by industry.  We hope to have this study completed before long.</P>
    <P>Finally, Senators will be aware from the recent Budget Statement that the Cohesion Fund is to be used to support a further development of waste infrastructure in this country.  I hope the House will agree this combination of new and planned legislative measures, as well as research based activity and infrastructural development, represents a serious and systematic approach to hazardous waste management in Ireland.  We have not underestimated the requirements of this difficult area and will not do so in the future.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="508" /> In relation to Senator Farrelly's question about his own county, I understand Meath County Council will be taking action under the 1982 European Communities (Toxic and Organic Waste) Regulations to have the company remove the last of the material on site.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for his response and I would like to clarify some points.  Is it true that each council will get rid of its own toxic waste?  Is it not true that the only site in the country for the storage and preparation of toxic waste for export is the site I mentioned in County Meath?  Is it also true that no toxic material is exported from its county of origin but is brought to one point in County Meath?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrowne2" hpid="Mr. Browne Mr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>What I said was that each local authority was responsible for the planning, organisation and supervision of operations for the disposal of toxic and dangerous waste in its functional areas and for the authorisation of the storage treatment and disposition of such waste. I did not say that each county council was doing this but each has the responsibility to arrange for it.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 4.30 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 10 March 1993.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>