<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="24" Month="Mar" Year="1993" Vol="135" No="8" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 24 Márta 1993" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 24 March 1993" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="781" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Warrington (England) Bombings:" RHead="Expression of Sympathy">
    <Title>Warrington (England) Bombings: Expression of Sympathy.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I call the Leader of the House who wishes to make a statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>Tomorrow we have an opportunity for an extensive debate on Northern Ireland.  I know the House joins with me in expressing revulsion at the shocking act of IRA terrorism in Warrington last Saturday.  I extend the deep condolence and sympathy of the House to the parents of Jonathan Ball, the three-year-old child who lost his life in the bomb attack.  To all those injured in this act of violence, I wish a speedy and full recovery from their grievous injuries.  I am sure Seanad Éireann joins with me in expressing outrage at this appalling atrocity.  I convey our deepest sympathy to the families affected and the residents of Warrington.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Leader of the House has indicated, Members will have an opportunity to speak tomorrow in the debate on Northern Ireland.  I was appalled at this act of violence.  I was ashamed of being Irish.  It was an outrage of the worst possible kind.  I ask Members to rise and say a prayer in memory of the young boy who lost his life.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="782" />
      <i>Members rose in their places.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Maloney that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for the Environment to outline the allocation which has been made for the provision of a proper water supply to the Manor-cunningham and St. Johnstown area, known as the &ldquo;Lagan Desert&rdquo; in County Donegal and if the moneys were allocated from the EC Structural Fund.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Quinn of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for the Marine, in the light of the official report on the <i>Celtic Pride</i> incident, to set up a pro-active and comprehensive system of regular inspection on ferries serving Irish ports, so as to identify and eliminate at an early stage all potential causes of tragic accidents on our key tourism routes.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Reynolds of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Forestry to establish an office of his Department in Carrick-on-Shannon, County Leitrim, to deal with headage grants and other agricultural matters.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Neville of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for the Marine to approve the Foynes Harbour Development Plan 1992 to 1999; and to submit it to the EC for Structural Fund and Cohesion Fund Grant Aid.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Kelly of the following matter:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The need for Revenue Sheriffs to take into account in their activities the <Col N="783" /> preservation of jobs and the problems faced by small businesses.</P>
    <P>I also received notice from Senator Mooney of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The need for the Minister for the Environment to provide a special £1 million grant from the national lottery to restore stocks of library books which have been severely depleted in recent years.</P>
    <P>I regard the matters raised by Senators Maloney, Quinn, Reynolds, Neville, Kelly and Mooney as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected Senators Maloney and Quinn's matters and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.  Senators Reynolds, Neville, Kelly and Mooney may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>Today's Order of Business will be items 1 and 10.  Item 1 will be taken from now until 6 p.m. and from 8 p.m. until 10 p.m.  I suggest the contribution of each Member should not exceed 30 minutes for spokespersons and 20 minutes thereafter.  Item 10 will be taken between 6 p.m. and 8 p.m.  Matters on the Adjournment will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Order of Business, could I ask the Leader of the House about Oireachtas reform?  One of the main items in the Programme for a Partnership Government was the setting up of four new committees of the Dáil.  This House has been completely excluded from the process of reform.  It is not mentioned in the Programme for a Partnership Government.  One of the main themes on the first day of this session was that we wanted to be involved in updating our procedures, particularly in extending the committee system.  In view of the fact that this House is totally excluded from the main business committees, has the Leader of the House any proposals as <Col N="784" /> to how this House could set up its own committee system or be involved in the present system?  If not, would he consider calling a meeting of the leaders of the various groups to see if an agreed programme could be put together that would enable us to be part of this process?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>For some weeks I have been attempting to get decent and acceptable facilities for the Members of the Independent University Group.  I have failed to do so.  I have reached the limit of my endurance.  We have been treated disgracefully.  We have the worst membership to secretarial ratio.  We have the poorest space facilities, and we have no meeting facilities.  I will not put up with it any longer and neither will the Members of this group.  I would ask you to use your good offices to intervene in this matter.  I have raised it with the Leader of the House and I am now raising it formally with the Chair.  As and from next week I intend to make my presence felt at every moment of the operation of this House until I get some satisfaction.</P>
      <P>I listended to Senator Manning talk about the need for reform to get this House working more effectively.  We are unable to continue to operate in the current system.  I intend to raise no other point and will not object to the Order of the Business.  I will, however, be outlining for the House next Wednesday the precise facilities every other group has, the ratio of secretarial help to Members and the space available.  I will not accept anything less.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You are making a speech.  I am prepared to talk privately to the Senator at any time.  I can give him an assurance that when we have a meeting of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges next Wednesday it will appear as a specific item on the agenda.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that, but I have waited long enough already.  I have spoken to everybody available and I wish for some intervention before next Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="785" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee on Procedure and Privileges meeting can be held tomorrow if that suits.  I had arranged for next Wednesday but if you want it more urgently I will arrange it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be happy to talk to you about it, a Chathaoirligh.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I support what Senator O'Toole has said.  You will notice that I have placed an item on the Order of Business for today, Item 11, which deals in strong terms with this issue.  Although Senator O'Toole made the point that the Independent University Senators are by far the worse treated, everybody in this House is labouring under conditions that do not make us efficient and this should be looked at.  Members from all sides will agree that we would be much more efficient, and would contribute in a far better way, if we had better facilities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You are making a speech, Senator.  I note your concern.  I, too, am concerned about the matter and will endeavour to rectify it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>We very much appreciate your concern in this matter.  I also want to support what Senator Manning has said.  I seem to be in a very supportive role today.  Could we have some specific information on the establishment of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WillieFarrell" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted the Leader of the House has announced a debate on Northern Ireland for tomorrow.  I congratulate Senator Gordon Wilson on the initiative he has taken to speak with the IRA in an effort to bring peace to Northern Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not appropriate to the Order of Business.  We all agree totally with what you are saying but it is something for tomorrow when we will have statements on Northern Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it intended to continue with Second Stage of the Unfair <Col N="786" /> Dismissals (Amendment) Bill, 1992?  I was surprised to discover a gap of three weeks in the middle of dealing with this Bill.  When we have the opportunity to initiate a Bill in this House, it is a shame that we do not give it the priority it deserves.  If we have to have a gap, the time for that is after Second Stage when we would have time to consider how we are to handle it on Committee Stage.  I would urge that priority be given to any Bills initiated in this House in future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarianMcGennis" hpid="Mrs. McGennis Mrs. McGennis">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGennis</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the huge increase in drug abuse in Dublin and throughout the country, and the fact that members of the Garda Síochána and the public are being threatened by HIV infection with syringes, can the Leader of the House indicate if it is his intention to arrange for a debate on the increase in drug abuse?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Leader of the House if he intends to introduce a motion to call on the Government to change the budget proposals which led to 10,000 people demonstrating outside the Houses of the Oireachtas yesterday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not a matter for the Order of Business.  It is a matter for the Finance Bill and I am sure the Senator will make his comments at the appropriate time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Since we had a motion here two weeks ago&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not having a debate on this matter on the Order of Business, Senator Farrelly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that.  Since the Government parties voted against the motion we had put down, 60, 80 or 100 jobs have been lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not allowing a debate on this issue.  The Senator will have ample opportunity to deal with this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="787" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask for your guidance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>My guidance is very simple.  You will have plenty of opportunity to make your point on legislation coming to this House in the near future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the people who lose their jobs in the meantime?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have made my ruling Senator, and I would ask you to abide by it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask for your guidance? When there is a serious threat to jobs, can we initiate a procedure so we can have matters of great urgency discussed, such as that which brought 10,000 people out on the streets yesterday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There are methods available within Standing Orders for raising matters of concern to Members.  It is not relevant to today's Order of Business. I call on the Leader of the House to reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Maybe we could ask for an adviser.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Farrelly, I do not wish to be unfair to you, but I object to this sniping at me or other Members.  We have a very good reputation in this House for making speeches. Sound legitimate political banter is in order but not that kind of comment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>In response to Senators Manning, O'Toole and Norris, I agree that the Committee on Procedure and Privilege should meet regarding the Seanad's involvement in committees. Regarding the point made by Senator McGennis one of the topical debates in the near future will be related to the issue of drug abuse.  On Senator Quinn's point, we will be sitting on Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday next week to deal with Bills on social welfare, unfair dismissals, gas, and social welfare again on Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="788" /> Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Criminal Justice Bill, 1993:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Criminal Justice Bill, 1993: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaireGeoghehanQuinn" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mrs. Geoghegan-Quinn) Máire Geoghegan-Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mrs. Geoghegan-Quinn)</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá mé buíoch de na Seanadóirí as ucht deis a thabhairt dom chomh tapa sin an Bille tábhachtach seo a chur faoi bhráid an Tí.  Tá súil agam go mbeidh díospóireacht fhada againn ina thaobh agus go nglacfaidh na Seanadóirí uilig páirt inti.  Is cinnte go bhfuil an-chuid gnéithe sa Bhille ina mbeidh suim ag gach duine anseo.</P>
      <P>I thank the Members of the Seanad for their co-operation in dealing with this Bill so promptly.</P>
      <P>This is the first piece of criminal justice legislation that I have brought before the Seanad.  It is but one in a series of measures which I will be introducing during the term of the Government to update and reform our criminal law and, as a result, I expect to be a frequent visitor to this House.  I look forward to co-operating with Senators in processing these changes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Criminal Justice Bill, 1993, is a relatively short but extremely important piece of reforming legislation.  It forms part of a number of measures which have been or will be introduced to improve the criminal justice system.  Briefly the four main objects of this Bill are: First, to enable unduly lenient sentences to be reviewed by the Court of Criminal Appeal at the instance of the Director of Public Prosecutions; Second, to increase the maximum penalty for incest against a female person aged 15 years or older from seven to 20 years imprisonment; Third, to place an obligation on sentencing courts to take into account any effect a sexual or violent crime has had on the victim; Fourth, to authorise criminal courts to require offenders to pay compensation <Col N="789" /> to their victims for any injury or loss.</P>
    <P>This Bill is oriented towards the victim and represents a significant step towards making the criminal justice system more responsibe to the needs of the victim by providing for compensation and empowering the courts to take into account the effects of crime on victims as people.  The victim normally only gives evidence for the prosecution and is subject to often scathing cross examination. Until recently, the emphasis of all reform of the criminal law was either on ensuring that there were adequate laws to allow persons engaged in criminal behaviour to be prosecuted or on ensuring that there were adequate safeguards to allow an accused person receive a fair trial.  The situation of the victim was virtually ignored.  I am glad to say that that attitude is now being changed and greater account is being taken of the position of the victim subject to the framework of the criminal justice system provided for in the Constitution.</P>
    <P>One of the first serious attempts to improve the situation of victims in the criminal process was taken in the area of rape.  A rape trial is particularly traumatic for a rape victim.  In recognition of this, the Criminal Law (Rape) Acts, 1981 and 1990, provided for anonymity for the victims of serious sexual assaults, excluded the public from such hearings and imposed restrictions on the adducing of evidence relating to the complainant's past sexual history.</P>
    <P>Administrative measures were also introduced to ensure rape victims receive copies of their statement from the gardaí, to provide for pre-trial consultations with the prosecuting team and to allow victims to consult, subject to the normal conditions, a legal aid solicitor who may accompany the victim into court.  The Garda now have elaborate procedures in place for the proper and full investigation of such cases.  For instance, female members of the Garda are invariably involved in the investigation of such crimes.  It is important that women generally know that the Garda care greatly about preventing, detecting and prosecuting <Col N="790" /> crimes of violence against women and children.  Their training and procedural instructions in this area have been greatly revamped in recent year in consultation with the key voluntary agencies.  In order to ensure consistency in the investigation of cases of violence against women and of child abuse, and to enhance the dialogue between the Garda and key social agencies in this field, a new Garda unit has been established in the Dublin Metropolitan Area in recent days.  This unit, consisting of a woman sergeant and three gardaí, will act as a policy development unit as well as over-viewing all such investigations in the Dublin area.  The question of extending the mandate of this unit to investigations outside the Dublin area will be considered in due course.  As a follow up to last October's conference on safety to women, a further conference on this issue at which representatives of womens organisations will be present is to be held in the Garda College in Templemore in July.</P>
    <P>The process of making the criminal justice system more victim orientated was continued by the Criminal Evidence Act (1992) which included provisions to make it easier for victims of physical or sexual abuse to give evidence by allowing the use of live television links and video recording.  The relevant sections of that Act were brought into force by Ministerial Order on 15 February 1993.</P>
    <P>The two main victim-orientated provisions included in this Bill will focus the court's attention on the impact of the crime on the victim.  When determining the sentence to be imposed, the court will have to take into account any effect the crime has had on the victim.  Furthermore, the court will be empowered to order the convicted person to pay compensation to the victim.  In so far as compensation orders are concerned Senators may be aware that the Criminal Justice Bill (1993) now before them differs from the Criminal Justice Bill first presented to Dáil Éireann in September 1992.  The changes I introduced, which I will deal with later, mean that once the trial is finished the victim does not have to have <Col N="791" /> any contact with the accused in order to secure payment of compensation.</P>
    <P>I turn now to the question of sentencing. There have been a number of decisions made by the Judiciary in relation to sentencing which have given rise to serious public concern.  As a member of the Executive it is not for me to comment on any particular case that has come before the courts, but as Minister for Justice and an elected representative I do have a duty to consider issues which have given rise to genuine concern and to take whatever action is appropriate in the circumstances.</P>
    <P>Sentencing is not an exact science. There can be an enormous variation in the circumstances in which an offence is committed and in the effect it has on the victim.  The sentencing judge must take into account any mitigating circumstances such as a plea of guilty, the offender's age and mental capacity, the possibility of rehabilitation and so on. The judge must reflect society's abhorrence of particular offences and bear in mind the need to deter others who may be minded to commit them.  In view of the number of factors involved it is not surprising that differences of opinion can arise as to what is the appropriate sentence in a particular case and it has long been accepted that a convicted person can appeal against the severity of a sentence imposed upon him.  To ensure a proper balance is maintained between the interests of a convicted person and the interests of society at large it seems appropriate that, in addition to requiring courts to have regard to the effects of the crime on a victim, the Director of Public Prosecutions, who acts on behalf of the people, should be allowed appeal against unduly lenient sentences.</P>
    <P>By providing a statutory basis for such appeals this Bill sets out a mechanism to deal with those exceptional cases where the sentence is so lenient as to cause justifiable public concern.  I would stress that such cases are exceptional and that there is no problem in the vast majority of cases.  I should also point out that the provision applies to sentences passed in <Col N="792" /> the case of any serious offence and is not limited to sexual offences.  Under our Constitution the imposition of a particular sentence in a criminal case is part of the administration of justice and as such is a matter for the Judiciary.  This Bill does not propose in any way to interfere with this constitutional principle. The final decision as to the appropriate sentence in a particular case will remain with the courts.</P>
    <P>I turn now to the detailed provisions of the Bill.  Section 1 is the interpretation section.  The definition of &ldquo;sentence&rdquo; in the section makes it clear that the Bill applies to all orders of the court and not just a sentence of imprisonment. However, the Bill does not apply to sentences of detention required to be passed by law on accused persons found to be insane.  I should say that I will be bringing forward a Bill to amend the law on criminal insanity.</P>
    <P>Section 1 also provides that the Bill will not apply to sentences imposed on persons convicted before it comes into force.</P>
    <P>Sections 2 and 4 deal with the procedure for initiating a review.  The Director of Public Prosecutions will have 28 days after a sentence is imposed to decide whether to ask the Court of Criminal Appeal to review it.  It is essential that this limit should not be so short that the Director would not have enough time to consider the matter thoroughly.  On the other hand, it would not be right that a convicted person, whose sentence may have been suspended or who may not have received any custodial sentence, should be kept too long in a state of uncertainty as to whether or not the sentence will be reviewed, with the prospect of having to face a custodial sentence ultimately.  I believe that the period of 28 days in section 2 meets both these criteria. The sentences that can be reviewed under the Bill are those imposed on conviction on indictment or on persons who have pleaded guilty in the District Court to serious offences and have been sent forward for sentence to the Circuit Criminal Court or the Central Criminal Court.</P>
    <P>Section 2 is concerned only with unduly <Col N="793" /> lenient sentences.  Before a question of review arises, the sentence concerned must be seriously out of line with what a judge who had taken all relevant factors into account could reasonably have imposed.  It is not a question of asking the Court of Criminal Appeal to review, say, a ten-year sentence when it might be thought that a sentence of 11 years would have been appropriate.</P>
    <P>Section 3 provides for an appeal to the Supreme Court where it can be certified that a point of law of exceptional public importance is involved and that such an appeal is desirable in the public interest.  As in the case of appeals from other decisions of the Court of Criminal Appeal, the certificate can be given by that Court, by the Attorney General or by the Director of Public Prosecutions.</P>
    <P>Section 5 enunciates an important principle to be followed when courts are sentencing for sexual offences or for offences involving violence or the threat of violence to a person, that is, the court should take into account the effect, including any long-term effect, of the offence on the victim.  I believe this provision will lead to fewer sentences having to be reviewed under the Bill by the Court of Criminal Appeal.  It will normally be up to the court to decide how it will inform itself on the effect of the offence on the victim.  The victim, however, does have a right to insist on giving his or her own evidence to the court if he or she so wishes.</P>
    <P>Section 6 extends the present powers of criminal courts to award compensation to all cases where the victim has been caused personal injury or loss.  At present that power is available only in cases of criminal damage.</P>
    <P>It is appropriate that the sentencing court should make the decision as to whether compensation should be paid, what its amount should be, what the convicted person can afford and so on.  These factors vary from case to case and the court is in the best position to make an informed judgment on them.  Section 6 provides for a compensation order to be made for any injury or loss unless the <Col N="794" /> court, and I quote: &ldquo;sees reason to the contrary&rdquo;.  The law will now be such that the making of a compensation order will be the norm rather than the exception. Of course, if an offender cannot pay anything, that is sufficient reason to the contrary.</P>
    <P>Section 6 does not apply to injuries or losses caused by road accidents by insured drivers who are subsequently prosecuted.  In those cases the victims are compensated by the insurance companies concerned, but it does apply to injuries or losses caused by uninsured drivers, whether compensation is payable by the Motor Insurers' Bureau of Ireland or the criminal injuries compensation scheme. Moreover, if a car is taken without the owner's permission and damaged, it will be presumed for this purpose that the person who took it caused the damage, whether he did so or not, so that he can be made to pay compensation for it.</P>
    <P>Both the convicted person and the victim may apply to have the compensation order reviewed where there has been a substantial reduction, or increase as the case may be, in the convicted person's means.  There are also provisions for an appeal by the convicted person against the compensation order and about the effect on the order of any civil proceedings taken by the victim.</P>
    <P>Section 7 provides that all payments of compensation are to be made through the local district court clerk and that it will be the district court clerk who will, on request, take proceedings to enforce payment under the order in his or her own name.  This provision will ensure the victim does not have to have any direct contact with the offender once the trial has been completed.</P>
    <P>Section 11 deals with an amendment of the Criminal Procedure Act, 1967.  The Criminal Evidence Act, 1992 has special provision making it easier for witnesses in cases of physical or sexual abuse to give evidence by allowing evidence to be given through a live television link at the preliminary examination and enabling a video recording of the evidence to be admissible at the trial.  However, it was suggested recently that a technical <Col N="795" /> amendment to the Criminal Procedure Act, 1967 might be necessary to remove any doubt as to whether a written deposition should also have to be taken in those cases.  Section 11 removes any such doubt.  Clearly, it is unnecessary to have a written deposition when a video recording is available either to be shown or to have a transcript made from it.</P>
    <P>Section 12 provides for an amendment to the Punishment of Incest Act, 1908. The 1908 Act provides in section 1 that incest committed by a male against a female is an offence.  If the female person is under the age of 15 years the maximum penalty is life imprisonment.  If she is 15 years or older the maximum penalty is seven years imprisonment.  If the act takes place without the consent of the female then the male can always be charged with rape which carries a maximum penalty of life imprisonment. That is the existing law.</P>
    <P>To turn now to the change proposed, section 12 of this Bill proposes to increase the seven year penalty in section 1 of the 1908 Act to a maximum penalty of 20 years.  Because of the power relationship between a father and daughter, situations will and do arise where the daughter is a victim of incest but it would be difficult to prove in a court of law that rape was committed because of the issue of consent. It is to cover such situations that the maximum penalty is being increased from seven years imprisonment to 20 years imprisonment where the female is 15 years or older.</P>
    <P>I think it is appropriate at this point to refer to the question of treatment programmes for prisoners committed and sentenced for sexual offences.  As was stated in the Dáil during the debate on this Bill, a small specialist group in my Department has been carrying out a feasibility study since last September of what could be made available by way of treatment which is practical, achievable, sustainable and open to evaluation.  I understand the group's work is almost finished and that I may expect to have its report in a week or two.  When I have <Col N="796" /> assessed its recommendations I will make a further announcement.</P>
    <P>Persons imprisoned already have available to them a range of medical, psychiatric, psychological and welfare services to assist them in coping with their problems.  I want to make it absolutely clear, however, that I see the provision of special treatment programmes for sex offenders as a priority issue.</P>
    <P>A number of constructive proposals were put forward during the debate on this Bill in the Dáil.  I have given careful consideration to all the points raised in the debates in the Dáil and I think it would be useful if I commented on one or two of them.  There was one proposal in particular which warrants further consideration and it was a matter raised by a number of Deputies.  The proposal, broadly speaking, was that the courts should have power to order an accused person or a convicted person to avoid contact with the victim and to avoid areas where the victim works or lives.</P>
    <P>A restricted form of this is already in operation.  Conditions can be imposed by a judge when granting bail, including one to the effect that the accused must not come into contact with the victim. Indeed, a belief that the accused might interfere with a witness, including the victim, is a ground for refusing bail.  Conditions are also regularly imposed on prisoners who are released before they have served their full sentence.  Under the existing law, however, no conditions can be imposed on a person who has served his full sentence and he is regarded as having paid the full penalty for his crime.</P>
    <P>I have asked officials in my Department to explore this matter fully with a view to introducing provisions in future criminal justice legislation which would give the courts comprehensive powers in this area.  While the idea is good, time is needed to work out the full details of the proposals and its implications.  I could not justify delaying the passage of this Bill until that work has been completed so I do not propose to deal with it now but, as I have said, I have given instructions for the matter to be pursued and, if <Col N="797" /> appropriate, I will include it in the next criminal justice legislation I bring forward.</P>
    <P>Another question raised was the possibility of making it lawful for prosecution counsel to address a court before it imposes a sentence on the nature and severity of such sentence.  I have had the opportunity to have this matter raised with the Attorney General who sees no constitutional objections to such an approach.  I am advised, however, that there is no rule of law in existence at present which would prevent prosecuting counsel from addressing a court on sentencing so a provision of the type envisaged is not required at this stage.  If difficulties arise in the future I will look at the matter again.</P>
    <P>I thank the Senators once again for their co-operation in dealing with this Bill and I look forward to hearing their views.</P>
    <P>I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Criminal Justice Bill, 1993.  Procedures in our criminal justice system to review lenient sentencing are long overdue.  It is vital that the courts when sentencing for sexual or violent offences be required to take into account the effect on the victim. For many years Fine Gael has demanded legislation to give the courts power to require offenders to pay compensation to their victims for any personal injury or loss resulting from the crime.  At every opportunity to debate this issue in this House I asked the Minister to take such an approach and I welcome the provisions in this Bill to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In addressing the issue of unduly lenient sentences, of the effect on the victim and compensation for injury or loss, the Minister is addressing only part of the problem.  I call on the Government again to gear the criminal justice system towards meeting the needs and concerns of the victims of crime because it is not right that it has ignored the victims of sexual and violent crimes.  Under the present system, victims are called to court as witnesses and the serious personal trauma they have suffered because of the crime is exacerbated by the suffering, and <Col N="798" /> often the humiliation, of recalling the events.  Their presentation is incidental to the proceedings and this should be changed.</P>
    <P>Proper support systems must be introduced for victims of crime both before and after proceedings to assist them in coming to terms with the trauma they have experienced.  They must be helped to overcome the stress of giving evidence and the disorientation caused by the unfamiliar surroundings of the court.  I stress again the need to reduce the formality and the need to dispel the austere atmosphere of courts.  This is intimidating to witnesses who are not used to court surroundings and it is unnecessary.  I ask the Minister to abolish the stupid, unnecessary and intimidating apparel of wigs and gowns in court.  It is time the aura of superiority engendered by such dress was dispelled.  The courts should take example from the informality of the Employment Appeals Tribunal where concentration is focused on obtaining the full facts of a case.  The informal approach of that tribunal has enhanced rather than hindered its success.</P>
    <P>Changes in court dress while necessary are only part of what needs to be done to reduce the trauma of court appearances for victims of crime.  We need a charter of rights for victims.  Victims of crime should be treated with courtesy and compassion and with respect for their personal dignity and privacy.  Victims should have access to services and receive early information from the courts and from police about their cases.  In the case of loss as a result of theft, property should be returned as soon as possible.</P>
    <P>It is wrong that victims of crime should have to listen in court to mitigation pleas on behalf of criminals who may have attacked them.  Victims who may have been raped, shot, beaten, robbed or who have had their property destroyed may be expected to listen to character references from clergy or employers on behalf of the criminal.  In cases where a defendant has pleaded guilty and a strong case for mitigation is entered by a barrister, the victim of a serious offence may witness the <Col N="799" /> offender being praised and then escaping with a light sentence.</P>
    <P>It is not enough to provide for appeals against lenient sentencing.  The Government must take seriously its responsibility to support organisations which help the victims of crime.  These organisations are doing the Government's job in a voluntary capacity.  The Government must ensure that institutions like rape crisis centres are not inhibited in their work by lack of funding.  The Government must further ensure that the services provided by rape crisis centres are available throughout urban and rural Ireland.  The health boards should have responsibility for the provision of these services and be adequately funded to do so.  It has become clear in recent times that crimes of rape and incest are committed frequently throughout the country.  Victims of such crimes must be afforded the opportunity to attend centres which will help them to deal with their physical and mental sufferings.</P>
    <P>Sentences imposed on those convicted of violent and sexual crimes should reflect the seriousness of those crimes.  It is important &mdash; and the Minister has referred to this &mdash; that those convicted of rape, sexual assault and incest do not continue to pose a threat to victims after their release.  A treatment programme should be devised for perpetrators of violent sexual crimes and I welcome the Minister's statement that a report on this subject will be issued within two weeks. A treatment programme should endeavour to ensure that perpetrators of violent crimes take responsibility for their actions and understand the consequences for their victims.  It is regrettable that the programme introduced in Arbour Hill has been discontinued.  Perhaps the Minister would comment as to why it was discontinued.  The results of that programme could, surely have been used to determine the effectiveness of introducing similar programmes elsewhere.</P>
    <P>Unless Government introduces treatment and counselling programmes for sex offenders in Irish prisons as a matter of urgency offenders will return to their <Col N="800" /> communities without understanding the grave consequences of their crimes. Treatment and counselling would reduce the likelihood of recidivism and this Bill may be the appropriate means for the introduction of suitable programmes.</P>
    <P>Victims of sexual crimes, especially incest, live with the fear that an offender, when released will seek revenge on the victim.  This fear which the Minister alluded to in her speech deters many from revealing their terrible suffering to the gardai or making statements describing their ordeal in case their testimony provokes a more serious violent or sexual assault.</P>
    <P>The courts should have power to make barring orders preventing a person convicted of an assault from making any contact whatsoever with the victims of the assault.  The victim should not have to relive the trauma of the assault in court in order to obtain protection following the release of the convicted person.</P>
    <P>There is widespread concern about lack of consistency in sentencing, especially in sentencing for sexual crimes. Consequently, great distress is caused to victims who rightly feel that the injury to their person and the psychological trauma suffered is not acknowledged by the court.  I hope public discussion of this matter over the past 12 months will assist the courts to fully comprehend the enormity of sexual offences.  I hope also that the concerns of the public, expressed here through the Oireachtas, will have the effect of improving the consistency of sentencing for sexual offences.</P>
    <P>I welcome section 5 of the Bill which takes into account the effect of the offence on the victim.  It is important to allow for evidence or submissions to the courts on that issue.  Consideration should be given to extending this provision to allow a victim who so wishes to be represented before the court before sentence is imposed.  The Minister maintains that this is permitted at present and I will seek advice on this.  If that is so, then heretofore it would appear that lawyers were unaware that they could, in fact, bring the view of the victim to the attention of the sentencing judge.  This would <Col N="801" /> allow the victim to have her own lawyer who would make a submission to the court on the severity of the sentence that should be imposed and inform the court of the impact of the crime on the victims.</P>
    <P>As I have said already, the present situation is that often the victim of a serious offence must sit in court and listen while their attacker, following his conviction, is first praised, character references are presented and pleas submitted on his behalf by people of standing in the community.  This can result in a light sentence for the perpetrator of the crime.  The opportunity for the victim to make a submission would balance the situation.  As well as hearing pleas for leniency on behalf of the convicted, the court would also hear why there should be a harsh sentence if the victim wished to present such a case.  It is important that the victim's position should be represented and legal advice should be provided for this purpose.</P>
    <P>I welcome section 6 of the Bill which gives the courts power to require offenders to pay compensation to the victim for personal jury or loss sustained as a result of the crime.  However, the Bill does not cater for a situation where the offenders have no funds or assets; in such circumstances they are not in a position to pay compensation.  Fine Gael calls for the restoration of the Criminal Injuries Compensation Board to make compensation awards to victims of crime. This could be funded by increasing the level of fines and, where difficulties arise in the collection of such fines, facilites should be available for payment by instalment or attachment of income.</P>
    <P>We urgently need a victim-oriented criminal justice system.  We need a charter for victims of crime, to ensure that victims of sexual and violent assault are compensated and to give social support to victims.  We need to ensure that a victim who gives evidence in court is protected against further assault when the offending person is released from prison. We also need groups dealing with victims of crime, such as the rape crisis centres and organisations like the Irish Association for Victim Support.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="802" /> I welcome the Bill which is similar to a Bill introduced by Fine Gael in Dáil Éireann.  This was not accepted by the Government and was not enacted in law. I accept that this Minister was not in her present post at that time.  I would like to make the point that it is unfortunate Governments do not accept legislation introduced by the Opposition.  If Bills are presented by the Opposition they should not be seen as a reflection on the Minister of the day but rather as a genuine effort by a Deputy or Senator to address an issue of importance to him or her.</P>
    <P>In November 1991 I introduced a Private Members' Bill to decriminalise suicide.  This was accepted by all sides of the House as a genuine effort to deal with a most sensitive and human problem.  The Minister for Justice at the time accepted that the Bill was in order, yet it was voted down by the Government parties.  A promise was made to bring in a Bill dealing with the problem within weeks but nothing happened.  We are now 16 months later; yet, the need to look seriously at the alarming increase in the incidence of suicide has not been addressed. The then Government should have used the opportunity given by Fine Gael to decriminalise suicide.  Allowing positive proposals on legislation to be brought forward by the Opposition would enhance the role of the Seanad and would allow for a more open and constructive approach.  I believe it would complement rather than threaten the role of the Government.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You have moved slightly away from the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I was making the point that a similar Bill was introduced in the Dáil and was not accepted&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You went on to talk about suicide.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>That was an example I gave of that situation.  I welcome the Bill which is long overdue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I would like to <Col N="803" /> welcome the Minister and congratulate her on introducing this Bill.  Any of us can fall victim to a crime.  Regrettably, many of us have direct experience of crime either personally or through our family and friends.  While much of crime is relatively petty in nature, there has been a disturbing increase in recent times in crimes such as rape, murder and other crimes of violence and crimes of a sexual nature.  Being a victim of crime is no longer unusual; unfortunately, it is increasingly a common aspect of modern Irish life.  Given this fact there is a clear onus on the Government, and indeed on all parties and on the apparatus of the State, to address the need for victim support and victims' rights.  For this reason I welcome the provisions in the new Criminal Justice Bill.  It represents a positive step forward in creating a more victim sensitive legal framework.</P>
      <P>What is a victim?  A victim is any one of us.  There are over 2,000 fatalities as a result of murder, manslaughter, dangerous driving, etc. each year.  What about the relatives who have to live their lives in loneliness and sorrow?  Hundreds of women and children are sexually assaulted every year.  What about them and the people who grieve with them? What about those families who have had their households violated by burglary?  A criminal act may be directed at only one person but the destruction it causes can affect more than one life.  A crime may be committed in a moment but its pain can last for years.  A burglary may occur in only one house but its reverberations can be felt throughout the neighbourhood.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We do not have to look very far to see the debilitating effect of crime in urban communities.  It erodes the quality of our life, our ability to live as an open and caring community.  I say with regret that the day of keeping the key under the mat at the back door is long gone.  Fear of crime makes us less open and more suspicious of people and when this happens we all become victims of crime.  Reported crime is only the tip of the iceberg as it <Col N="804" /> is generally accepted that only one in four crimes is notified to the Garda.</P>
    <P>It is vital that we become aware of the human aspect of being a victim of crime. Somebody working in the area of victim support once referred to the invisible wounds carried by the victims and their families who could be regarded as co-victims. The physical wounds may have healed but the inner trauma continues. The victim may be subject to a confusing range of feelings.  Grief and sorrow can follow the loss of a loved one or a valued piece of property.  Anger is also a common reaction and guilt, unfortunately, is also commonplace.  Victims tend to blame themselves despite the fact that the criminal is to blame.  Fear is hard to avoid.  Crime is often life threatening and unexpected.  Many victims, particularly old people, continue to live in fear after the event with consequent detrimental effects at a time of their lives when they have the right to expect the best the State can offer.</P>
    <P>Studies in the United Kingdom and in the USA indicate that a victim of a violent or sexual attack will be likely to suffer from post-traumatic distress disorder and other psychiatric and psychologically disabling disorders.  The individual often develops clinical depression and may manifest other anti-social conditions such as phobic reaction.  It can also trigger the onset of a more serious psychiatric disorder such as psychotic breakdown.  It is only when we are aware of this vital human aspect that we can establish and implement the necessary victim support measures and I believe this Bill acknowledges this human aspect in the practical measures that it proposes.</P>
    <P>The Bill introduces a fundamental principle into our judicial framework, that the court would take into account the effects, including any long-term effects, of the offence on the victim.  This principle is to be followed when courts are sentencing those convicted of sexual offences or offences involving the use or threat of violence.  This represents a breakthrough in that it acknowledges the basic rights of victims who, I regret to say, were often a forgotten constituency <Col N="805" /> in the past.  In each case it will be for the court to decide how it will inform itself as to the effect on the victim.  I hope that in each and every case the court will be sensitive to the trauma experienced by the victim.  Such compensation should take into account any physical, financial, social and psychological harm done to, or suffered by, the victim.</P>
    <P>There has been much justified disquiet in recent years about the lack of compensation from criminal to victim.  In the complexity surrounding an individual case the need to compensate the victim may be overlooked.  Therefore, I welcome the Bill's provisions to allow criminal courts to award compensation to victims who have suffered personal injury or loss.  The law will now create a situation where the making of a compensation order will be the norm.  This is only just.  The offender may plead inability to pay but this Bill allows for payment of compensation in instalments. There should be no excuse to let the offender off the hook.</P>
    <P>While such compensation is just and only to be expected, no amount of material compensation can make up for the trauma suffered by victims of some crimes.  There is no such compensation for pain and suffering.  Other forms of compensation are necessary &mdash; counselling, practical advice and other forms of emotional first aid.  I would like to thank the voluntary organisations which have been providing such invaluable services for some time.  These include the Irish Association for Victim Support, the ISPCC, the Rape Crisis Centre and Women's Aid.  These organisations provide important specialised help needed by victims of certain crimes.  Their importance in the area of victim support cannot be under-estimated and they deserve the support of our Legislature.</P>
    <P>I see this Criminal Justice Bill as an important benchmark.  It represents the beginning of a necessary process of making our system more victim-sensitive. We must evolve such a system from this point onwards.</P>
    <P>I would like to propose some suggestions as to how to progress from here.  A <Col N="806" /> variety of practical measures can be taken to improve the difficult situations faced by victims of crime.  Appearing in court can be a traumatic experience for victims. The appearance and customs of the courtroom are often intimidating and off-putting. Often the victim is placed in close proximity to the accused or his family and acquaintances where they can be subject to, at the very least, great discomfort and distress or, at worst, blatant intimidation.</P>
    <P>Each court should have a separate room where the victim can wait in comfort before giving evidence.  This may seem like a simple measure but we should bear in mind that, for the victim, meeting the accused can reawaken the pain and anguish of the crime itself.  Such facilities should be made available in existing courthouses and should be a prerequisite in the construction of future courts.  A suite of rooms has been made available in the Four Courts for this purpose with the backing of the Department of Justice and the Judiciary.  This simple measure is one way we can act upon what I believe to be the basic principle of victim support, that we should do what we can to make the victim of crime as at ease and as comfortable as possible.</P>
    <P>Counselling has a vital role to play in the victim support process.  Often the most valuable thing one can do for a victim of a crime is to be a patient and compassionate listener.  Offering help is one of the most curative things one can do for any victim of crime.  Obviously, for more serious crimes, such as rape, continuing counselling is necessary.  I believe that victim-support counselling should be an integral part of our judicial system.  A team of specially selected and trained individuals should be available to give emotional support and protection to vulnerable witnesses attending court. These individuals would not be present to provide legal advice but to provide the necessary understanding and support for victims and witnesses.  I look forward to a time when such a service is automatically available to all victims of serious crime. Such a service is currently available on a voluntary basis from the Irish Association <Col N="807" /> for Victim Support.  This represents another strand of their valuable work.</P>
    <P>It is vitally important that victims of crime are kept informed at all times of the progress of investigations into the crime that pertains to them.  Such information is a basic right.  It should include whether a person has been charged following the investigation and whether the person is in custody or on bail.  It is important that the victim be informed as to whether they will have to give evidence in court.  Being kept in the dark can only increase the victims sense of unease and pain.</P>
    <P>In the current climate, the Garda Síochána have a very difficult role to play, they face a wide variety of problems, including the threat of physical harm. They come into contact with the victims of crime daily.  They know the pain and trauma experienced by victims.  Victim counselling and crisis counselling in particular, should form an integral part of the new two year training programme for the Garda Síochána.  I was pleased to note that the Garda are establishing, under Deputy Commissioner Tom O'Reilly, a special unit within the Force to deal with sexual abuse cases.  This unit is part of the ongoing co-operation between the Garda, the sexual assault treatment unit at the Rotunda Hospital and the sexual abuse clinics at Temple Street and Crumlin Hospitals.  This type of co-operation shows us the way forward and I hope it is the beginning of a long and beneficial process.</P>
    <P>The media also have a role to play.  In recent times the media have played a valuable role in highlighting injustices and the sufferings of victims of crime.  It is important that the public are made keenly aware of the human aspect of crime.  However, the media have a responsibility to ensure that the victim's privacy is not needlessly violated and that the victim's trauma is not added to by insensitive reporting of the circumstances of the crime.  They should always exercise proper restraint and consideration towards victims.  By and large, our media have avoided the excesses of their English <Col N="808" /> counterparts and I hope this remains the case.</P>
    <P>This Bill represents the first stage in making the system more victim-oriented, and we should look at other models for future action in this area.  One such model is provided by legislation enacted in New Zealand in 1987.  This Act is devoted entirely to making better provision for the treatment of victims of criminal offences.  It provides for access to services and information for victims.  In the case of a charge of sexual or serious assault the views of the victim are taken into account when deciding whether to give bail to the accused.  In certain cases the victims should be notified of the release of an offender.</P>
    <P>This Act allows for the establishment of a victim task force composed of senior officials from the Department of Justice, the Commissioner of the Police and four nominees of the Minister for Justice.  The main function of this task force is to work with the Judiciary, Government Departments and community organisations involved with victims in order to promote the principle of victim support contained in the Act.</P>
    <P>The New Zealand Act was referred to by Mr. Justice Budd in a case in 1992 which was reported in <i>The Irish Times</i> on 14 October, when he called for victim impact statements in criminal trials.  He suggested that Ireland should adopt a system similar to that operating in New Zealand.  That system sets out clear guidelines on what the impact reports should contain, including physical injuries sustained and the treatment received, property damaged or stolen, financial costs incurred and the emotional and psychological effects on the injured party.  The judge favoured the police compiling these reports in all appropriate criminal cases.  I fully agree with him in this regard.</P>
    <P>This Act provides a suitable framework for future development and as such it deserves close examination by all of us interested in victim support.  Ten years ago the then Garda Commissioner, Lawrence Wren, stated that, in the overall debate about crime, law and order <Col N="809" /> and the judicial system, crime victims are the forgotten people.  There has been a slow improvement in the intervening years culminating in the welcome provisions of the Criminal Justice Bill before us.  However, this process must be ongoing.  We must never allow the victims of crime to be forgotten, on the contrary, they must be to the forefront of our thoughts and, more importantly, our actions.  Caring for victims is one of the marks of a civilised justice system and one to which we must continually aspire.</P>
    <P>I would like to take up a point Senator Neville made earlier about sentencing.  It is the practice of the Legislature in our jurisdiction and similar jurisdictions when drafting legislation to set maximum penalties and rarely to set minimum penalties for crimes.  If a minimum sentence is specified it does not allow judges margins within which to operate, especially in cases where an offender might have committed a morally blameless act, with no degree of culpability. Judges would not be able to show leniency in such cases.  By and large the Judiciary have been very consistent in sentencing.  There have been occasional hiccups but in general they are very good.</P>
    <P>I commend this Bill to the House and once again thank the Minister for her vision in introducing it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister and the introduction of the Bill.  I am glad to see a victim-centred approach to these cases and I particularly welcome the sections which deal with the short and long-term effects on victims, who will at last have a place within the court to give their opinion.</P>
      <P>It is also important that sentences which are considered unduly lenient can be challenged.  For a long time the offender has had the privilege of challenging the severity of a sentence but there has been no possibility of challenging a lenient sentence.  I do not share Senator Crowley's view regarding consistency of sentencing.  In common with the public I am quite often astonished at what is considered a suitable sentence for an extremely serious crime.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="810" /> The Judiciary will have trouble implementing parts of the Bill, particularly the section which provides that the long-term effects on the victim be taken into account.  These effects have always been grossly underestimated.  It is difficult to equate the effects of a minor assault on an aged woman whose bag is snatched on a canal bridge and the effect on a young man who receives a serious beating but who gets up and goes out again.  I know of elderly women who were prisoners in their own homes after their handbags were snatched and they were too terrified to go out again.  One constantly hears of women afraid to go out after dark.  It is extraordinary in a well-lit city that women are so terrified that they feel they cannot walk safely on the streets.  There may be difficulty in assessing the seriousness of the effect on the victim.  It may be equivalent to a prison sentence on them.</P>
    <P>We are all potential victims.  Any person's handbag can be snatched and anyone can have their car window broken.  It is very important that we identify with victims because that will ensure that we take a realistic approach.</P>
    <P>I am concerned that once compensation is awarded to a victim some people may attempt to wriggle out of paying by showing that they have no funds.  It is absolutely essential that there is no contact between the victim and the aggressor in getting compensation for the crime.  It seems to be very easy to plead inability to pay.</P>
    <P>It is very important that victims are to be given a voice in court.  In the past when victims have been asked to come forward and speak, I have been extremely surprised by how pleased they have been to do so.  It seemed to give them a great deal of psychological strength to have had some part in the case, whereby they at least had an opportunity to express how they felt.  The Minister's emphasis on this point, is to be welcomed.</P>
    <P>The increased sentence for incest from seven to 20 years where victims are over 15 years of age is very important because, particularly between father and daughter, <Col N="811" /> the discussion of consent is impossible. A victim may have been in a position where consent was not something that she could have been described as giving because, as in the recent Kilkenny case, she may have been so terrified that she, and perhaps her mother, felt there was no one they could approach.  Consent in such cases does not arise.</P>
    <P>I question how much the increased sentence will help incest victims, apart from keeping the offender away for longer. When a person has served a sentence there is no way he can be kept away from the victim because the offender is considered to have paid the price for his crime.  The Minister may have to examine this further and consider if some family agreement is required so that an aggressor can be accepted back into a family unit.  Crime does not affect just the victim.  It affects a whole grouping and in the case of incest it affects the whole family group.  I often wonder if incest is seriously considered a crime in this country.  Because so much emphasise is put on the family unit, any challenge to it appears totally disloyal.</P>
    <P>All the churches condemn incest but I often think it is just from the point of view of eugenics.  They speak out strongly against it because the progeny of an incestuous relationship are more likely to have either physical or mental abnormalities. I would like the churches to speak out more strongly against the horrific social implications of incest.  I have not seen many pastorals or sermons on the aspect.</P>
    <P>It is very important that we stop concentrating on figures for serious crimes within the family such as incest.  It does not matter if there is only one case in the entire island.  Surely it is sufficiently serious for us to want to deal with it.  It is irrelevant to say there are very few cases of incest because not many come before the courts.  Incest is a serious crime which destroys not only the victim's life but also the lives of those around them.</P>
    <P>Serious efforts have started in the Departments of Health, Education and Justice and I commend the &ldquo;Stay Safe Programme&rdquo; which the Minister for Education <Col N="812" /> has introduced in schools.  If there is one person outside the family that a child may feel able to approach, it is the teacher.  Strides have been made but I would like the Minister for Justice to cooperate with the Minister for Education in considering if reporting by teachers should be mandatory.  At present teachers must report to the head teacher but perhaps they should report to the community care officer, who is the only person with statutory power in these situations.</P>
    <P>There is a rhyme in the &ldquo;Stay Safe Programme&rdquo; which reads:</P>
    <P>Sometimes I get scared in this big world when bullied by boys and laughed at by girls or hugged in a way that makes me say no, it is never my fault and I must tell someone I know.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;It is never my fault and I must tell someone I know&rdquo; must be stressed.  If the crime is within the family the only hope for a child is to get help within school.  I urge the Minister to consider mandatory reporting by teachers.  I was involved in setting up the sexual assault unit in the Rotunda Hospital and we thought we would be dealing with cases of adult rape and looking for forensic evidence for the Garda.  However, within weeks we were flooded with teachers who had nowhere to bring children before.  I urge the Minister to look at this matter, although it does not come within the scope of this Bill.</P>
    <P>It is important that children know there are some adults who will take care of them.  People have a moral responsibility, not just a legal responsibility, to help abused children.  General practitioners should be obliged to report to the community care officer any cases where they think there is evidence of sexual abuse. They are more alert with regard to physical abuse.  However, GPs cannot deal with this on their own, since not only do they not have enough individual training, but they are already involved with the family.  It is important that the Minister considers mandatory reporting by the medical profession.  I stress that we have a moral responsibility to these children.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="813" /> Senator Crowley talked about victim support and about centres for victims of crime.  We are all aware of the good work carried out by the victim support units, the rape crisis centres and the ISPCC, but these services must be properly funded if victims are to have somewhere to go for help.  With regard to the Kilkenny case, had there been a rape crisis centre there the girl and her mother might have sought help.</P>
    <P>The Minister knows the cost of keeping persons in prison is astronomical compared to the money required by voluntary agencies to carry out their work.  It is not just the amount of money given to voluntary agencies that is important. They see this funding as a recognition of their work and, in my experience, respond with double the amount of work expected.  In comparison to what it costs to keep someone in prison, very little money is required for the provisions of the Child Care Bill, 1992.  No extra funding has been given for community care although this will be the support mechanism for victims.</P>
    <P>The Minister talked about the rehabilitation of the abuser and about the Garda. I rarely hear of complaints against the Garda in these cases as they do the best they can in the circumstances.  I suggest to the Minister that she seek to reduce the time delay between the charging of the abuser and the court case taking place.  This puts incredible strain on the victim and the family.  There is a weakening of the evidence within the family the longer the delay goes on because pressure is brought to bear on them from various sources.  The mother's evidence may become weaker and other members of the family may be inclined to say that the alleged abuser was not so bad after all.</P>
    <P>The Minister said the delay in the review of cases should be only 28 days.  I ask her to consider something similar for serious cases of abuse, to ensure that there is not a one or two year delay before the cases eventually get to court.  The alleged abuser in that time may have had to leave the family house and the turmoil within the family continues.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="814" /> The Minister did not mention the training of judges but it is something that will have to be considered for the sake of all victims, particularly victims of sexual offences.  Some of my best friends are High Court judges and I have nothing against them.  Generally speaking, judges have a rarified existence and do not meet outside the courts the victims of crime and sexual abuse.  It might be felt that judges should remain isolated from victims, but I think that judges would welcome some form of training or structured seminars.  I urge the Minister to consider this not just to ensure that sentencing is more consistent but also to instruct judges as to the long-term effects on victims, the frequency of these crimes and the effect on the broader society.</P>
    <P>The abuser may plead guilty or innocent in court.  The victim may suffer great trauma through facing the offender in court.  Sentencing policy should reflect that.</P>
    <P>In cases where sexual abusers within the family are convicted, the urgency of treatment in prison cannot be stressed enough.  I know the Minister has set up a specialist group to investigate treatment for sexual abusers within the family and it is a very difficult problem.  The difficulties were highlighted in a recent television programme on the Gracewell institution in Birmingham for sexual abusers.  The objections of the local people to having this centre within their community were forcibly made known as were their feelings that they were not consulted. Attempts to set up a similar centre in Coventry had to be abandoned because of the antipathy of the local community.</P>
    <P>The Minister has a problem here because if people are treated solely in a prison setting they are not allowed access to those people to whom they have a moral responsibility.  People in prison have little association with the outside world.  Many prisoners do not watch programmes showing the disgust for people who have offended against children or against anyone else.  People in prison become isolated from the rest of society. The Minister will have to set up programmes <Col N="815" /> in the prisons.  There are programmes in America and Canada which have tackled this problem.  One must not underestimate the difficulties.  It must be made perfectly clear to people with inclinations towards sexually abusing children that this is wrong and must be overcome. It is an extremely difficult problem and I am sure the Department is not underestimating it.</P>
    <P>Setting up group support for abusers should also be considered.  In these groups, previous abusers point out the seriousness of these actions to the newcomers. Abusers are always inclined to minimise the effect of their actions on the victim.  It is important that this be tackled immediately the person is imprisoned. Mothers also need counselling, because they also experience feelings of guilt, terror, and of rejection by the rest of the family for failure to protect the children. The siblings of the abused child also need to be counselled and family therapy must be undertaken.  All this is expensive, but so is keeping people in prison.  Long-term research has shown that abused children and their siblings experience low levels of self-esteem and as they grow older, they have difficulties in forming personal relationships.  They might go on to abuse alcohol, drugs etc.</P>
    <P>Children are not always violently attacked by their abusers.  Even in dreadful cases, they have been called &ldquo;daddy's good little girl&rdquo;.  Because they have been abused by somebody they should love and trust, they repress their hate, terror and anger.  I wonder if some non-violent situations are even more scarring for the abused child?  If violence is involved, at least they can see there is something wrong.</P>
    <P>The guilt felt by the child in keeping this relationship secret is another problem that must be addressed.  In some cases, they will have to be taken to places of refuge and there are no such State-supported houses.  There is only CARI, which is supported entirely on a voluntary basis.  The Minister will have to make sure that the victim is not abused again by the offender, who might be out <Col N="816" /> on bail.  I find it extraordinary that CARI, a house dealing with sexually abused children, should have a waiting list.</P>
    <P>When the abuser has finished his sentence he is free to return to his family. Could the Minister find out if this would be acceptable to them?  After all, they have rights too.  I do not know if there is any legal measure that could prevent this but it is important.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill and hope that the lessons we learned from minimising what happens in these cases will be taken up by the Minister.  I was pleased that she straightened out the situation with regard to video taping.  It looked as though we were going to have a red herring with regard to those cases.  I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AnnGallagher" hpid="Ms Gallagher Ms Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Ms Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to this House and I agree with the provisions of the Bill.  It has four objectives, which are quite diverse but have a common theme.  First, it will allow the Director of Public Prosecutions to order a review of unduly lenient sentences to be heard by the Court of Criminal Appeal. Second, in the light of recent sentences imposed by the Judiciary, this Bill seeks to increase the maximum penalty for incest against a female over 15 years from seven to 20 years, which redresses an existing anomaly.  Third, the Bill provides the criminal courts with the power to require offenders to pay compensation to their victims.  As a corollary, the Bill has a fourth objective, which is to place an obligation on the court to take into account the effect of sexual or violent crime on the victim.</P>
      <P>The law dealt with cases of sexual abuse or violence from one side only and did not provide any assistance for the victim who, in most cases, suffers physically and psychologically long after the case has been dealt with.  Therefore, I welcome the provision which allows the court to take into account the effect of the crime on the victim when determining a sentence.  At last, there is some practical assistance in the form of compensation, which is made payable by the convicted person to the victim.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="817" /> I compliment Senator Crowley on his marvellous contribution.  I agree with most of the points he made.</P>
    <P>I have no problem with the interpretations in section 1, but on reading section 1 (3), I would query whether the Bill, when enacted, could be applied to cases where the accused has been found guilty, or has entered a plea of guilty, but where sentencing may have been adjourned by the judge to allow certain reports to be submitted on the convicted person.  If so, this Bill when enacted could affect some people unfairly.</P>
    <P>Section 2 is important because it allows the Director of Public Prosecutions to apply to the Court of Criminal Appeal to review a sentence which appears to him to be unduly lenient.  The wording used is satisfactory as it will allow a review only where a judge is seen to stray significantly from the accepted principles of sentencing, i.e., where one sees a judge making a serious error in light of the relevant factors.  I welcome this move and feel that few cases will fall into this category.  We are not opening the floodgates and I do not believe it will overburden our courts.  It strikes a balance between the accepted legal principle that the sentence imposed by a criminal court shall be final &mdash; this entitles the accused to know that the sentence imposed will not be altered except in serious circumstances &mdash; and the need to review sentences by judges who stray from acceptable standards.</P>
    <P>Section 3 allows an appeal on a point of law to the Supreme Court by either party, where it can be certified that a point of law of exceptional public importance is involved, and where an appeal is desirable in the public interest.  I cannot see that happening very often as the issue of sentencing is unlikely to involve any disputed question of law.  Nonetheless, a mechanism for appeal should be available and I am glad this Bill expressly provides for it.  Will the Minister confirm that legal aid will be provided for the convicted person in any review case or appeal from same?  There is no point in providing rights if financial difficulties prevent one from availing of them.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="818" /> Regarding the right of appeal to the Supreme Court, can the Supreme Court, on hearing such appeal, review a verdict of acquittal on an accused person?  Such an acquittal will already have been decided by the trial court and subsequently by the Court of Criminal Appeal.  I do not wish to get technical on this, but it is something that I would query.  Can the prosecution be given a third chance to find a person guilty through this section by bringing a case to the Supreme Court?  I would hope not, and I ask the Minister to consider this matter.</P>
    <P>Does the Bill allow the defendant to appeal from the Court of Criminal Appeal to the Supreme Court where, on review, the sentence has been increased? The problem arises when the defendant is treated leniently by the trial court, and therfore, does not appeal.  If the Director of Public Prosecutions seeks review to the Court of Criminal Appeal and the sentence is increased, the convicted person has not had an opportunity to present his or her case for appeal.  This Bill may cause a problem in this regard by limiting an accused person's right of appeal to the Supreme Court on a point of law only.</P>
    <P>In relation to section 5&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Senator to refrain from referring to the sections of the Bill.  This is a Second Stage debate and we will deal with the sections on Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnGallagher" hpid="Ms Gallagher Ms Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Ms Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that but it is easier to discuss this Bill in sections.  I am not referring specifically to the wording of the sections.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A provision in this Bill allows the court to take into account the effect of sexual or violent offences on the victim.  At present, when an accused person pleads guilty there is no provision for the victim to give evidence even when the case is heard.  Evidence of the effect of a crime on the victim is currently inadmissible. Under the new legislation the court may consider the effect in whatever way it sees fit.  This provision will lead to fewer <Col N="819" /> sentences being reviewed by the Court of Criminal Appeal and this should be a help in an already overburdened system.</P>
    <P>Information regarding the effect of sexual or violent offences on the victim can be obtained through practical means, for example, a doctor's evidence, a report from relations or from others who will testify in court to the satisfaction of the judge.  Therefore, the victim will not have to return to the court to give further evidence.  There are other ways of dealing with this.  I welcome this provision which will greatly assist the victim.</P>
    <P>The provision of practical help which is necessary for victims is an important aspect of this legislation.  It introduces a means by which the courts can award compensation where the victim has been caused injury or loss.  At present, that power is available only in cases of criminal damage.  At this time when so many people suffer as victims of burglaries, mugging, joyriding, etc. it is good that at last one can seek compensation from the convicted uninsured joyrider &mdash; as is normally the case &mdash; and for a burglar or other criminal.  The Bill provides that the method of payment for compensation will be made through the District Court clerk.  This system is used in the case of maintenance and other orders.  I share the concern of Senator Henry regarding the efficiency of this system to ensure that the victims receive the moneys awarded.</P>
    <P>I suggest that the Minister establish a fund to compensate victims of crime, levied from fines and perhaps collected by the courts.  A system of levying fines to fund victims through a victims task force is in place in New Zealand under the Victims of Offences Act, 1987 and it is working well.  Perhaps the criminal injuries compensation scheme could be reintroduced in a revised fashion?  It is something worth considering.</P>
    <P>The Bill contains a technical provision which makes it clear that evidence given by video does not require a written deposition.  This is something which needed to be clarified, although I thought it was made clear in legislation introduced last year.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="820" /> The Bill deals with an issue first raised in this House in relation to the Kilkenny incest case.  It contains an important section which amends the Punishment of Incest Act, 1908.  In cases of incest against women over 15 years it increases the maximum sentence from seven to 20 years imprisonment.  Sadly, recent cases have shown the need for this provision. It reflects the serious nature of this crime which affects the victim badly and can happen easily in the uneven power balance which naturaly exists between father and daughter.  The sentence for such a hideous crime should reflect it seriousness. Treatment and counselling is necessary for victims and offenders in the case of sexual crimes.  Only then will we be able to work towards a society where the health and safety of women is not always in danger.</P>
    <P>I ask the Minister to consider an obvious anomaly, namely, a life sentence means an average of eight years in prison, while a 20 year sentence means 12 years in prison.  This affects all court sentences and it should be examined immediately in order to secure fairness and consistency of sentencing.</P>
    <P>This Bill is the first measure I have seen which focuses on the victim of crime. It is a significant step in making our criminal justice system more responsive to the needs of the victim by providing for compensation and empowering the courts to consider the effects of a crime on the victim.  It is long overdue but better late than never.  I have queries regarding the wording of sections which I will raise on Committee Stage.  I welcome this legislation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish the Minister, Deputy Geoghegan-Quinn, well in her new Department.  The Minister is hardworking and she will give this Department the attention it needs and deserves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This legislation is necessary and urgent and I welcome this Bill.  Most people are in favour of the proposals contained in it.  The Bill was brought forward as a reaction to recent events and it is a pity that such events make it necessary.  It is important that the courts are in a position <Col N="821" /> to impose a maximum sentence on a criminal.  In addition, a criminal may now be ordered to pay compensation to the victim.</P>
    <P>Much discussion has taken place in relation to sexual abuse within families. It is necessary that victims give their version of events to the relevant authorities, the Garda Síochána, social workers, etc. so that the case may be brought before the courts.  When the victim of a crime is prepared to come forward and give evidence to the Garda Síochána the offender may be prosecuted.  Tragically, few people are prepared to come forward with evidence against those who are inflicting these horrific injuries on them.</P>
    <P>The authorities must ensure that facilities are available to protect people who report such crimes to the Garda Síochána, the health board or the relevant authority.  Many daughters and wives would willingly report their fathers or husbands but for the fear that they would suffer worse injuries than those they have already endured.  That is a problem which must be tackled.</P>
    <P>There are also problems associated with evidence in such cases and the necessity to make statements to the Garda Síochána.  Some people suggest that the gardaí interview people and seek evidence against an individual when a crime is committed in the home but this is a delicate area.  We saw what happened in Scotland where over-officious health authority workers, who took children from their parents in the depths of night, caused division and tragedy of an unprecedented scale.  We must guard against that happening here.</P>
    <P>I do not think that a garda can call to a house and ask a daughter or wife if they have been molested or raped unless they are willing to report such crimes.  I know of medical practitioners who have been left in a difficult position when they tried to bring cases and the injured individual did not pursue the claim.  However, medical professionals occasionally make judgments and complaints that are not justified.  The bottom line is that 24 hour protection for a complainant is essential while their claims are investigated.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="822" /> I accept the necessity to review unduly lenient sentences.  I stress the words &ldquo;unduly lenient&rdquo; because there are sentences which some people consider too severe and others consider too lenient. There must be an obvious error whereby the sentence is lenient, and seen to be lenient.  In that instance it is essential that there be a provision in this Bill to review an obviously lenient sentence.</P>
    <P>In that context I would like the Minister to issue appropriate guidelines to the Director of Public Prosecutions.  It was obvious that the sentence in the Kilkenny case was unduly lenient.  However, there will be other cases and I do not want to see a hang them attitude prevailing where public opinion and media reaction, without having all the facts, decide that some individual has committed an offence and the Director of Public Prosecutions, the Department of Justice and the judicial system has no suitable means to combat that situation.  The Director of Public Prosecutions must work within proper guidelines and even if the media or some other section of the community decide a judge imposed a wrong sentence we would not be trapped in a situation where we react to every individual case.  I may be conservative in saying that but our judicial system in spite of its warts has worked reasonably well.  It is to the credit of our courts that in view of the number of decisions made &mdash; despite certain cases where sentences are considered too lenient, or too severe &mdash; decisions are within the guidelines and are acceptable to the general public.  The judges hear the evidence and try to be fair and impartial.  It is essential that a judge, when imposing a sentence of three years, five years, 12 years or 20 years should give his reasons. If it is an unduly harsh sentence or it is less than the public anticipate, the judge should explain the reason for the decision.  Then the general public, when the case is reported, will realise why the judge made his decision.  I am happy that the appeals will be to the Court of Criminal Appeal.</P>
    <P>I have reservations about the 28 day period during which the Director of Public Prosecutions has the opportunity <Col N="823" /> to have a sentence reviewed; I believe it is too short.  This takes place when a conviction is recorded.  I have an outsiders knowledge of the procedure in the offices of the Chief State Solicitor; the Director of Public Prosecutions and the Attorney General; when a case is reported the Director of Public Prosecutions sends for files which have to be reviewed, there must be consultations and the matter may go to a council to be investigated and reviewed.  The 28 day period is a short time in which this work must be done and, if this is a statutory provision the Director of Public Prosecutions must not be a day late in lodging his application for a review.</P>
    <P>Some years ago I had a case where a judicial review was sought and, as the State was a day late in lodging its application for a review, the case was struck out.  If the sentence for a horrific crime imposed on 19 December is considered unduly lenient, the DPP may be late in lodging an appeal against the sentence because of the holiday period.  Public opinion would be rightly outraged in that event.  A two month period would be more appropriate in this instance.  We are talking about the rare instances but we should ensure they are properly covered. I ask the Minister to examine that.</P>
    <P>In the Dáil and Seanad, the Minister referred to the effect of crime on the victim.  It is essential that the court have an opportunity to hear about such effects. This too must be examined.  Judges normally impose a lesser sentence when a person pleads guilty because the victim is not cross-examined.  This spares the victim and the family trauma, stress and worry.</P>
    <P>There has been no opportunity to date for the victim to give evidence about the trauma.  The Minister stated in the Dáil that if a person is convicted, no doubt in many cases a report by a doctor will suffice.  We have a duty to strike a balance. If the crime is serious the person convicted can be remanded in custody. During that period the State should be able to compile its evidence.  Unless by agreement, medical reports should not <Col N="824" /> be included in writing.  A doctor may think a crime is insignificant but another professional might also issue a report but not be cross-examined on it &mdash; they may have an interest in the case.  In fairness to everybody, that professional person's evidence should be subject to cross-examination. It will not affect the victim but the convicted person's lawyers should have an opportunity to cross-examine a professional witness.  I ask the Minister to look at that as well.</P>
    <P>I now turn to compensation in criminal cases.  Currently, judges are adjourning sentences to ensure that a person pays compensation.  This is commonplace in District and Circuit Court criminal cases. The majority of judges have common sense.  If a person is convicted for a crime they adjourn the case for sentencing.  If the person pays adequate compensation to the injured party that is taken into account in imposing sentence.  Nevertheless, since this procedure is only being implemented in some cases it is welcome that it is now put on a proper statutory basis.  Section 6 makes certain compensation will be awarded.</P>
    <P>Overall, the Bill is welcome and I look forward to Committee Stage tomorrow afternoon.  The Bill can be very useful and it should be adopted by the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EddieBohan" hpid="Mr. Bohan Mr. Bohan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bohan</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, welcome this Bill. The Minister is to be congratulated for the speed with which she introduced these measures when the weakness in the legal system was brought to her notice. Like the Minister, all of us in this House were appalled by the insult and injury inflicted for many years on the young Kilkenny girl by her father and at the leniency with which these crimes were treated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Whether it is an original sentence or a sentence reviewed under the Bill, it is important that the Minister ensures that courts can be satisfied that if a sentence is imposed it is served.  I am referring to the lack of suitable prison accommodation and the fact that on a regular basis prisoners have been released without serving their full sentence to make space for others.  In many instances persons <Col N="825" /> sentenced to lengthy terms of imprisonment are released within weeks because of the lack of prison space.  This makes a mockery of the penal system and does nothing to discourage criminals from the error of their ways.  It must also be an inhibiting factor in the imposition of custodial sentences if the Judiciary are aware that such sentences are unlikely to be served.</P>
    <P>The provision of additional prison accommodation is an urgent necessity and I urge the Minister to take this issue on board in conjunction with the measures proposed in this Bill.  I appreciate the financial implications and the difficulties for the Government in undertaking a building programme at this time, when public finances are stretched. However, many private firms are prepared to undertake the capital cost of building prisons and to enter into leasing arrangements with the Government. Prison accommodation is provided in this way in many countries, notably the United States, Australia and Canada and recently in the United Kingdom.  I ask the Minister to explore this possibility if an early solution to the shortage of such accommodation.</P>
    <P>I am pleased to see the measures in this Bill requiring offenders to pay compensation to the victims for any resulting personal injury or loss and that the courts must exercise this power unless they see reason to the contrary.  For too long victims have been the losers.  It is time wrongdoers were made to pay.</P>
    <P>Over the past two decades we have developed a liberal attitude to crime and the treatment of criminals.  We must change this approach.  Ordinary law-abiding people need to see that we the Legislature are concerned about the problem.  Many people no longer feel safe in the sanctuary of their homes, on the streets, in their cars or elsewhere, particularly in the Dublin area.</P>
    <P>If crime and violence in our society are to be properly tackled, a number of matters must be taken on board by the Legislature.  We must introduce Bills like this, creating specific offences with specific penalties and with greater powers of <Col N="826" /> arrest for the Garda.  The bail system must be fully examined.  Bail must be restricted.  We cannot continue as a civilised society if we allow murderers and rapists out on bail, free to continue their criminal ways.  Crimes committed on bail must be subject to consecutive sentences. The present judicial practice of imposing concurrent sentences for such crimes makes a farce of the penal system.  It encourages criminals to commit as many crimes as possible while on bail as they know that invariably they will only serve a sentence in respect of one of their crimes.  For speedier trials and fewer adjourments the law must be seen to work, and work quickly.</P>
    <P>More prison accommodation needs to be provided.  It is said the greatest single deterrent to criminal activity is the fear of imprisonment.  That fear does not exist here as we do not have enough accommodation and prisoners are being released without serving their sentences. Criminals are aware of this fact and are laughing up their sleeves at the system. This must stop.  As I have already said, available options to provide more space must be explored.  I compliment the Minister on this excellent legislation.  Its purpose is to deal with specific problems and I hope it will help to reduce the level of violent and repulsive crimes.</P>
    <P>I compliment the Minister also on the actions she has already taken to improve the level of policing in Dublin.  However, I ask the Minister to look seriously at the other issues I have raised and to bring forward whatever Bill or measures that are necessary to deal with the very serious criminal problems that plague this city and this nation.  I commend this Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Everybody has been waiting for this Bill and its introduction. However, many will say it is somewhat late in arriving when we recall the outcome of the Kilkenny rape case last year which caused such outrage among the general public, and the recent Kilkenny incest case which provoked a similar reaction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The last thing I want to do in discussing <Col N="827" /> this Bill is to make cheap political points across the floor to the Minister.  I accept that the Minister has dealt with this situation in the best possible way and I applaud her and the Government for bringing this legislation to the House at this time.  However, I regret, that because the Dáil did not sit during the month of January this legislation is too late to deal with the recent Kilkenny case.  There was no reason the Dáil should not have sat in January.  The Minister of State made reference to this in a television programme saying it was legislation that might have been dealt with during that time when the issue was first raised.  I regret that was not done.  Because of that, I intend moving an amendment to the Bill which would make it retrospective.  I know this will be resisted by Government and by the other side of the House but I intend, nonetheless, to move an amendment to make the Bill applicable to all sentences passed from 1 January 1993.</P>
    <P>I would like to raise a question about the general prison population.  There was a report in one of today's newspapers that the percentage of members of the prison population in Ireland suffering from a mental disability or handicap was far greater than in any other country.  I want to raise a point which I have consistently raised in this House.  Why is it that a huge percentage of our prison population comes from the same socio-economic group, from underprivileged and deprived areas, mainly the inner city areas?  Why is it that 70 years into Independence a nation whose Proclamation talks of cherishing equally all the children of the nation has gone wrong?  One can walk into the maternity ward of a hospital and see babies whose parents are from Darndale, Ballymun or the inner city, and know even at this stage of their lives that their chances of making it through the system are reduced.  What have they done to deserve that?  Why is it that people in prison seem to come from the same area?  This is not a cheap political point; we all have to take responsibility for it but there is something wrong with a system that produces such a result.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="828" /> Succesive Governments and educational systems have reinforced inequity, have consolidated disadvantage and have ensured the continuation of underprivilege with the result that the people sentenced to prison largely come from the same social class and the same areas.  It sometimes strikes me it might be cheaper to build walls around some of our disadvantaged areas than maintaining our prisons.  It always saddens me to hear the point made now by Senator Bohan for more prison places.  Surely that is not the answer to the problems of society?  It is of no earthly use to an elderly woman living on her own who has been attacked, raped or simply frightened, to know that there are more prison places because there are always people to take up the places.  There is something wrong in such a system.</P>
    <P>Time and time again I have expressed the view that intervention must begin with education.  We have failed to do that.  The cost of keeping children who have been in trouble with the law in places like Trinity House or Ferryhouse is far in excess of what it might take to intervene with a solid, educational, psychological counselling service and support services at home level.  As long as we fail to do that we will continue to be faced with the kind of outrage we all share about cases such as the Kilkenny incest case.  Do not tell me that any caring, educated, sensitive person could have treated his daughter like that man treated his daughter.  There is a flaw in the system that brings us to that point.  If a person steps out of line, the law must be clearly seen to act.  People must have confidence in the law and they must be sure that those in charge of the law do everything possible to ensure that the sentence matches the crime.</P>
    <P>Every time there is a prison suicide somebody jumps up and blames the Government and calls for the resignation of the Minister for Justice.  That kind of knee-jerk reaction has always bothered me.  It is everybody's loss if somebody commits suicide, whether it be in jail or otherwise.  We have to look at the underlying causes.  I would like to ask the <Col N="829" /> Minister if it is true that the incidence of suicide among the Irish prison population is way above the average for Europe?  I do not know if that is the case; I have sought information on the matter and I would like to have clarification.  If there is a problem let us admit as much and see if we can deal with it rather than have the same predictable reaction on every occasion.</P>
    <P>Where a judge passes a sentence which the public feel is inadequate, it is only right that the whole panoply of the State should move into operation to ensure that an appeal can be made against too light a sentence.  This has been the case in the UK and other European countries and it is past the time it happened here. The sad part is the reaction it creates among people in many other places. There are many abused women and children who will not come forward to report their suffering, their private trauma, the extraordinary events which mark them for life because they see what has happened in similar cases and they do not think it is worth all the hassle.</P>
    <P>There is evidence to show that abusing adults have frequently been abused as children: Intervention is required to break this cycle of learned behaviour.</P>
    <P>It is through education that we should address the socio-economic disadvantages affecting growing numbers of our population.  Child sexual abuse prevention programmes are essential and it is unfortunate despite the seriousness of the problem that some influential people in this country object to making prevention programmes available to children, teachers and schools.</P>
    <P>The reality of child sexual abuse is that it continues from generation to generation, the abused child frequently becoming the abusing adult.  I hasten to add that this does not happen in 100 per cent of cases.  In 95 per cent of the cases I regret to say the abuser is male.</P>
    <P>We need to address the problem of child abuse in a number of ways.  Providing for appeals against lenient sentences is equivalent in a sense to closing the stable door after the horse has bolted. <Col N="830" /> It deals with the effect of the problem rather than the cause.</P>
    <P>I applaud the Department for bringing forward this Bill to which I will table a number of amendments on Committee Stage.  Causes of child sexual abuse must be examined.  We need to investigate also why much of the prison population is drawn from one social class.  These issues can only be addressed through the education system and I ask the Minister to ensure that greater emphasis is placed on education in projects in which the Department of Justice is involved, such as the North Clondalkin Project.</P>
    <P>Almost all children pass through the primary education system and the Minister should recognise that at that stage the juvenile liaison officer, the probation officer, the health visitor, the psychologist, the teacher and other caring professionals could come together to identify and help children at risk.  I ask the Minister to look seriously beyond the scope of this Bill to the underlying cause of the problem and to respond through the educational system so that this kind of fire brigade action will not be necessary again.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCalnan" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Calnan) Acting Chairman (Mr. Calnan)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Calnan)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it agreed that Senator O'Toole share his time with Senator Norris?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill together with the Minister's opening remarks to the House that the Bill is intended to be victim oriented.  Traditionally criminal legislation has been oriented principally towards securing the conviction of the guilty party and there has been little interest in the feelings of the victim, particularly in cases of alleged rape or incest.  As the Minister indicated in her speech, very frequently a woman who has the courage to make an accusation of rape against an attacker, is subjected in court to a most rigorous and frequently offensive cross examination about her past sexual history.  I have always found this practice unacceptable. The sexual conduct of a victim whether married or unmarried, seems to me to have no bearing on the truth of her allegation. <Col N="831" /> It is regrettable that past sexual history has been taken into account by a male dominated legal system.  Victim oriented legislation is in tune with the times and with the objectives of groups such as the Irish Association for Victim Support.</P>
      <P>There is public concern about apparent anomalies in sentencing policy for a considerable number of years and in some circumstances this concern is clearly justified.  In the case of a person I knew who was murdered in Fairview Park simply because he was gay the judge did not even impose a custodial sentence.  I cannot remember whether the Probation Act was applied or whether some kind of suspended sentence was imposed but I found it offensive that later, the convicted persons paraded in victory around the block of flats where they lived.  This case is directly parallel to a case last year in the northern part of this jurisdiction where a woman was subject to sexual violence, and a court case ensued.  The several men convicted were given suspended sentences, light sentences or the Probation Act and, I understand from newspaper reports, were welcomed home by local people, like conquering heroes.</P>
      <P>This kind of behaviour creates considerable public concern and alarm and I am glad that the Minister is responding to this general concern.  There is clearly a string of anomalous cases in which legitimate public concern has been expressed and most people would agree that serious anomalies have arisen in sentencing policy.  However, case details and evidence presented in court cannot always be given the kind of media coverage required to illustrate the reasons for a judgment.  Sometimes where elements of a case are not disclosed to the press, the judge may have sufficient reason to impose sentence that appears anomalous to the casual observer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Not all sentences that appear anomalous are so and I know of cases in which it was only possible to secure a conviction on a lesser charge when the accused was manifestly guilty of a more <Col N="832" /> serious charge.  In such cases sentence for the lesser crime was imposed.  Occasionally, a discreet degree of plea bargaining takes place to enable the prosecution to put together a case that will stand up in court, so it may not be the judge who is responsible every time an apparently anomalous sentence is passed.  We should be careful not to pillory judges unjustly although there have been cases justifying concern.  If somebody convicted of rape or murder can be given a slap on the wrist and the benefit of the Probation Act, then something is seriously wrong.</P>
    <P>I use the word &ldquo;anomaly&rdquo; because clearly judges differ on sentencing policy. An attempt should be made to standardise sentencing policy and it might be beneficial to provide some form of seminar for judges on this matter, so that a kind of collegiality of policy could be established. I am not an unequivocal admirer of all things American but the American legal system is roughly similar to ours. Ireland and the United States have constitutional backgrounds and constitutional decisions of the Supreme Court of the United States are used as persuasive arguments in constitutional actions here.  The parallel does not extend, however, to the training of judges.  In Ireland judges are frequently appointed without any training except for their experience as an advocate or solicitor.  This practice is not satisfactory. In the United States of America prospective judges attend an educational institution for judges where they undertake a training programme which includes lectures and workshops on the sentencing policy.  It would be a good idea if the Houses of the Oireachtas established a similar programme.  Before judges in the United States are apprenticed to more learned judges they gain experience from somebody who has a greater degree of contact with the law before they hear cases on their own.  The Minister could examine this possibility, because it is perhaps a little unfair to expose judges to a situation where their judgments may be subject to question, if we, as a society, are not prepared to give <Col N="833" /> them any training for a role that has serious consequences for accused persons and victims.  After all, it is no slight thing to deprive a man or woman of liberty as a result of a sentence.</P>
    <P>Will the Minister state if the Department only considered allowing for the appeal of too lenient sentences?  There have been instances of sentences that were too harsh and there as no machinery by which this process could be reversed. If the Minister looked through the Department's files he would see that I raised on the Adjournment in the previous Seanad precisely such a case of manifest injustice to a person.  A mechanism for examining too harsh a sentence should also be considered.</P>
    <P>This Bill was introduced as an appropriate response to recent cases, particularly the Kilkenny case.  The victim in that case is concerned that after four or five years in prison her father might, on his release, pursue and attack her again. I hope that there will be protection &mdash; even years down the line &mdash; to ensure this unfortunate woman and her child will not be subject to harassment.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Minister's remarks on the rehabilitation of offenders: they are full of good intentions, but the Minister and the civil servants in the Department of Justice know that, there is no such provision in our system.  Case after case is reported in which people are directed by courts to have remedial psychological treatment but it never happens because the apparatus does not exist.  Perhaps we can have real commitment because I do not believe in just punishing people.  As my colleague, Senator O'Toole said, frequently the people who inflict this kind of misery on young people within their own families have themselves been victims of sexual abuse in their childhood. Therefore, if we intend to intervene and stop this nauseating chain of events there must be proper provision for rehabilitation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Miss Ormonde Miss Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Miss Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy O'Dea, to the House and I congratulate the Minister for Justice, <Col N="834" /> Deputy Geoghegan-Quinn, on dealing with this Bill so promptly.</P>
      <P>This Bill is orientated towards the victim as many Senators said.  One of its primary aims is to look at the victim's situation in criminal justice process with regard to rape.</P>
      <P>Section 12 deals with the penalty for incest.  The recent case in Kilkenny involved the inhuman treatment and horrible physical and sexual abuse of a young girl.  That case brought home the terrible problem of incest and some members of the Judiciary are so out of touch.  I agree with other speakers who said that our judges are living in ivory towers where they have little empathy with or sensitivity to real victims.  They are too clinical in their approach and perhaps new training for judges is needed.</P>
      <P>In the Kilkenny case the imposition of only seven years' imprisonment was a disgrace.  I understand he pleaded guilty to rape as well as to incest and the judge could have given him any sentence up to life imprisonment.  The excuse for not doing so, apparently, was that seven years' is the maximum penalty in a serious case of incest.  Increasing the penalty to 20 years will make it clear to those who impose sentences that where a father commits rape and incest against his daughter the proper sentence is in excess of seven years.</P>
      <P>One of the national newspapers claimed that the Government's decision to increase the penalty for incest is a panic response.  There was a public outcry and the Minister responded to a clear need to change the law swiftly and decisively. If she had not responded so efficiently there would have been articles in some papers complaining about the Government's inaction.  The Minister is to be praised for her response in this regard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Bill was not introduced to deal with incest so I do not wish to speak for too long on that subject.  I understand why there was full support in the Dáil for increasing the penalty for incest.  This Bill is a mine of common sense and I hope the Minister continues this approach in the other Bills she will introduce to the <Col N="835" /> House; allowing review of unduly lenient sentences, taking into account the effect of a crime on the victim and getting the offender to pay compensation to his victims are measures that everyone can understand and appreciate.</P>
    <P>The Bill empowers the Court of Criminal Appeal to review unduly lenient sentences at the behest of the Director of Public Prosecutions.  Of course sentencing is not an exact science and, therefore, we must consider variables such as an admission of guilt, age, mental capacity the relationship between father and daughter and rehabilitation in relation to sentencing in such cases.  Of course, society is rightly disgusted by such crimes and we must legislate to deter offenders.</P>
    <P>The court will have the power to review, not only sentences imposing terms of imprisonment or fines, but also other orders made by courts on conviction, such as probabation orders. Orders postponing sentences will be reviewable, unless the postponement is merely for the purpose of obtaining a medical or psychiatric report or a report from a probation officer.  This is important because, often, postponing a sentence is a prelude to not imposing a penalty.</P>
    <P>Courts should have the power to order an accused or convicted person to avoid contact with the victim in her home or workplace.  I realise it is not part of this legislation but it should be considered for future legislation.</P>
    <P>Section 5 of the Bill also places an obligation on courts when determining the sentence to be imposed for a sexual offence, or an offence involving violence or the threat of violence, to take into account the long-term effect on the victim.  This provision is of particular importance in cases where the accused pleads guilty.  In those cases since the victim does not have to give evidence, the court may not be aware of how the offence has affected the victim and in particular if there has been any medium or long-term effect.  I understand and welcome that the Bill will also apply in <Col N="836" /> cases in which a person is found not guilty to ensure that any such effects will always be borne in mind by a sentencing court.</P>
    <P>I examined carefully section 5(3) which was inserted following acceptance of an amendment by Deputy Shatter on Report Stage in the Dáil.  It is long winded but I am sure it could be improved.  It contained a lot of good work.  However, I know the Minister &mdash; like all Members &mdash; is keen, to see this Bill enacted although there is not much time to consider further details.  I compliment her for the speed with which she has introduced it to this House.</P>
    <P>The Bill gives the courts general power to require offenders to pay compensation for any resulting personal injury or loss. At present, compensation is payable by offenders only for criminal damage to property.  In future, courts will be able to order compensation to be paid for any personal injury or loss resulting from any offence, including an offence that is taken into consideration when imposing sentence, a welcome provision.  The means of the offender must necessarily be taken into account when assessing compensation. However, if those means improve substantially while the offender is still paying under the compensation order, the victim can have the compensation increased and the victim's civil law remedy against the offender will not be affected.  I welcome that the system of compensation provided for in this Bill will be so versatile.</P>
    <P>The Bill refers to appeals to the Court of Criminal Appeal and from there to the Supreme Court.  However, it has been brought to my attention that it does not consider the question of an appeal made directly from the Central Criminal Court to the Supreme Court under Article 34 of the Constitution.  The question of appeals direct from the Central Criminal Court is a general issue and it may not be appropriate to deal with it in this Bill. However, it is causing some concern and I ask the Minister to state if there are plans to deal with it in any future legislation. Essentially, it is a point of law in relation to appeals to the Court of <Col N="837" /> Criminal Appeal and from there to the Supreme Court.</P>
    <P>Section 3(1) deals with appeals on a point of law from the Court of Criminal Appeal to the Supreme Court.  A certificate must be granted by the court, the Director of Public Prosecutions or the Attorney General.  Does this follow existing practice or is the inclusion of the Director of Public Prosecutions a new measure, restricted to appeals under this Bill?  I would welcome the Minister's views on this.</P>
    <P>I welcome the provision proposing the establishment of a study group setting out the areas in relation to the new Garda unit and what it can do with regard to rehabilitation.  I am concerned about treatments for the victim and the offender.  The Bill does not seem to cover that in depth and I am sure the Minister will return with proposals on this issue. As a guidance counsellor, with particular knowledge of the procedures for dealing with sexual and other physical abuses, it concerns me that we appear unable to deal adequately with problems.  Many areas are not co-ordinated.  I refer to the Department of Education, the Department of Health, child guidance clinics, psychological assessments and the Department of Justice.  When one looks for a back-up service in relation to a problem when it first surfaces, it becomes clumsy to deal with.  Many professionals are doing a very good job, but the coordination has not yet been implemented to enable support systems to be available when necessary.  If the matter is not covered in the Bill, perhaps the Minister will address it at a later stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CathyHonan" hpid="Ms Honan Ms Honan">
      <NameTxt>Ms Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill and compliment the Minister on bringing it forward.  It is one in a series of measures which she will introduce during the term of this Government to update and reform our criminal law.  I welcome the four main provisions of the Bill which are (1) to give the Director of Public Prosecutions the power to appeal unduly lenient sentences; (2) to increase the maximum penalty for incest; (3) to place an obligation on sentencing courts to take into account <Col N="838" /> any effect a sexual or violent crime has on the victim and (4) to authorise criminal courts to require offenders to pay compensation.</P>
      <P>I am concerned that when cases such as the Kilkenny case which is regarded as exceptional and sensational, comes to public attention there is often an automatic demand from the public and politicians for new laws, procedures and regimes to put them right.  However, after a couple of months everything seems to return to normal and we tend to forget all about it.  That is why I welcome the Minister's earlier remarks that this Bill forms part of a number of measures which will be introduced to improve our criminal justice system.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Minister's assurance that the Bill is orientated towards the victim.  The most important question with which we have to deal is not the guilty party but the victim.  Because of the adversarial nature of our criminal justice system the victim has tended to be placed at the bottom of the heap and, as the Minister said, virtually ignored.  In our system the concerns, perceptions and effects on the victim have rarely been taken into account.</P>
      <P>We must examine how we have approached acts of violence, particularly acts of violence against women.  There is nothing new in violence against women. However, the focus of attention from the media, politicians and our Legislature is changing.  I welcome this and the fact that the silence surrounding these problems has been broken.  For that we owe a debt of gratitude to the courage of the women who have come forward in recent cases and brought these problems into the open.  Attitudes are important and it is the attitudes that are embedded in the various systems that have stopped us dealing with many of these problems to date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The mechanisms proposed in the Bill help the situation but other mechanisms also need to be implemented.  The report of the Second Commission on the Status of Women recommended a number of measures in this area and I urge the Minister to take them into consideration.  One <Col N="839" /> of the recommendations was that a monitoring mechanism could be set up in the Central Criminal Court to gather statistics on sentencing for rape.  The commission believes that if those statistics disclose an unacceptable discrepancy, the Government should consider introducing a mandatory minimum sentence in rape cases.  The commission also recommend that seminars should be organised on a regular basis for judges to keep them informed on the up-to-date nature of rape, sexual abuse and violence.  This is a very important recommendation and I urge the Minister to implement it as it would be most helpful.</P>
    <P>It is important that the Judiciary are informed of developments in this area.  It is also important that there is training for members of the Judiciary, that younger members are appointed and, in particular, that more women are appointed. I am pleased that the previous Government, late in 1991, appointed the first woman judge to the Supreme Court.  It was a welcome development.  There is also one woman judge in the High Court but that is insufficient.  I urge the Government to improve the ratio of women appointed to senior positions in the Judiciary.</P>
    <P>Senator Henry made the point that there is often a perception that the Judiciary are far removed from the lives of the victims and people coming before them and that they live in a privileged society.  It is important for the Judiciary to be aware of the effect of crime on victims.</P>
    <P>The report of the Second Commission on the Status of Women also recommended training for teachers at primary and secondary level on the appropriate steps to take if a suspected incident of child sexual abuse comes to their attention. It also recommended the establishment of a module on child sexual abuse in GP training.  Senators Henry and Enright said GPs should inform the director of community care in their health board area if they suspected incidents of child sexual abuse.  The ICA recently produced a statistic that one third of Irish <Col N="840" /> women were victims of sexual abuse which is a horrific figure.  I have spoken to teachers and GPs who said they must be coming across these cases but are not aware of them.  Training and education is necessary in this area.</P>
    <P>The commission also recommended the dissemination throughout the country of the Eastern Health Board's &ldquo;Stay Safe&rdquo; programme, a preventive education programme for children dealing with child sexcual abuse.  This is important. The way to get to the root of this problem is to tell children to come forward and to assure them that when they do so they will be helped, that there are support systems in our society to assist them.  Training and education are extremely important; the benefits of such training can be seen in the conduct of the garda involved in the Kilkenny case.</P>
    <P>Another recommendation of the commission was that immediately prior to trial, as a matter of course the complainant, namely, the victim in a rape case, should be given a copy of her statement by the Garda.  The Minister in her speech stated that administrative measures have been introduced to ensure that rape victims receive copies of their statements and I am pleased about that.</P>
    <P>The commission also recommended that the Department of Justice should commission and publish a standard booklet explaining the circumstances attending the investigation and the prosecution of sexual offences, with particular emphasis on the role of the complainant as a witness.  This booklet should be provided as a matter of routine to the complainant. This would make all victims more confident and restore their faith in the judicial system.  Many women in these cases feel sorry at the end of the day that they brought the case to court.  None of us wants that; we want the victims in these cases to be assured that the State and society will give them all the support they need.</P>
    <P>In addition to these mechanisms in our educational system and our health services, we must also examine the funding of agencies such as the rape crisis centres. People who work in these centres feel <Col N="841" /> politicians are guilty of a certain measure of dishonesty.  In this House we talk about enacting laws and increasing sentences but we give very little support to the agencies that deal with the victims of these crimes.  I welcome the recent proposal by the Minister to increase the funding to rape crisis centres and I urge that such centres should be set up throughout the country.  There is no rape crisis centre in my area, the Midland Health Board area; there are no facilities for women victims of these crimes.</P>
    <P>Appropriate treatment programmes must also be put in place for offenders. Despite the comments of the previous Minister for Justice, sadly, there is a lack of such programmes; in fact, there is only one programme for adolescent offenders. We need to develop more programmes throughout the country.</P>
    <P>The Minister said she did not envisage the appeals system being used very often and, generally speaking, this is the case. The trial judge is the person who has listened to the facts and is in the best position to impose a sentence.  The Minister said the Director of Public Prosecutions has powers in relation to appeals, powers that have never been exercised.  We cannot guarantee that just because this Bill is passed by the Oireachtas its powers will be used regularly. There is a tendency to assume that once a Bill is on the Statute Book everything will be all right.  It will not necessarily be the case that the Director of Public Prosecutions will immediately appeal a sentence any time the public or politicians consider too lenient an approach has been taken.  It may be years before the DPP ever seeks to exercise the powers invested in him by this legislation. The DPP is the appropriate person to bring the appeal because his independence is guaranteed under the 1974 legislation.</P>
    <P>I agree with the Minister when she said it is not easy to get uniformity in sentencing.  We need consistency in the decisions of the members of the Judiciary in so far as is possible.  We must accept that the public perceives a wide discrepancy in the sentencing for rape and <Col N="842" /> other crimes against women, which is not readily explicable by the circumstances. I know the Minister has to be careful not to jeopardise in any way the independence of the Judiciary but perhaps we could find an appropriate mechanism to make known to the presidents of the various courts that we want consistency in sentencing.  I welcome the Bill, I am glad it has been brought before the House and I will support it on Second Stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>This is worthwhile legislation and I compliment the Minister and her Department.</P>
      <P>When introducing the Bill in the Dáil the Minister commented that the circumstances and the atmosphere were similar to those which prevailed in the aftermath of the Lavina Kerwick case. That case was the catalyst which led to the publication of the 1992 Bill.  It is perhaps a sad reflection on both Houses of the Oireachtas that there was a second tragic case, the Kilkenny case, before we took steps to introduce legislation to deal with the issue.  Nonetheless, the Bill is welcome.  It is timely; in fact it is long overdue.</P>
      <P>Although it is a relatively short Bill it is an important piece of reforming legis lation.  Putting this Bill on the Statute Book will mean that some good will have emerged from those two horrific cases and from the countless other cases that get far less attention, or perhaps never come to public attention.</P>
      <P>The Bill addresses the issue of unduly lenient sentences, a matter which has caused a great deal of outrage in recent times.  I particularly welcome this element of the Bill, I am on the record in both Houses as being extremely critical of the sentencing policies adopted in cases by some judges in recent years.  I cannot begin to understand the approach adopted in the Kilkenny case.  No amount of special pleading by politicians who somehow regard the Judiciary, particularly their own friends, as being always above criticism will persuade me that anything approaching justice was done in that case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In any crime against the person, particularly <Col N="843" /> the crime of rape, it is vital that the sentence imposed should reflect the gravity of the crime.  There are many reasons for this, not least of which is that the sentence should represent the revulsion which society feels about this crime.  In Western society people in recent times have become increasingly revolted by what seems to be an endless litany of cases of crime and incest.  Reading newspapers and listening to media reports, sometimes it seems society is intent on debasing itself.</P>
    <P>Appropriate sentencing is important also from the point of view of the victim of a crime.  I say this not in any sense of vengeance but as an indication that society takes seriously the trauma suffered by the victim when the crime was perpetrated and also the trauma which the victim undoubtedly has to suffer when the trial is in progress.  Frequently in crimes against the person the only witness is the victim.  If victims have their confidence in the judicial system shaken by idiosyncratic sentencing or by excessive leniency towards the perpetrator, they may be dissuaded from participating in the task of bringing the criminal to justice and the whole of society suffers as a result.  At last the central provision of this Bill will provide a mechanism where the Director of Public Prosecutions, representing both society and the victim, can appeal an unduly lenient sentence.</P>
    <P>I have a query about the means whereby the provision will be put into operation.  In the Dáil debate a number of Members pointed out that they wanted to ensure that approaches could not be made to the Director of Public Prosecutions, in fact, it would be criminal to try to make approaches.  I am concerned that there may be a lacuna here, and the last speaker touched on this.  We do not know whether putting these powers on the Statute Book will mean they will ever be put into operation except in rare cases. I am not suggesting that it would be appropriate that there be a review in each and every case, obviously that would not be so.  The Minister also made this point. I would like to know how the central <Col N="844" /> provision in this Bill will be operated when it becomes law.</P>
    <P>The second element in this Bill I particularly welcome is the obligation it places on sentencing courts to take into account any effect a sexual or violent crime has on the victim.  This the Minister rightly recognised as being a victim-oriented provision.  Other speakers including the last speaker made the point that it is extremely important that courts be seen to sympathise with the victim and to see the victim's side of the argument.</P>
    <P>In recent times a great deal has been said about the inconsistency in sentencing in the courts.  This inconsistency has two distinct elements: one is where excessively lenient sentences are handed down; the second is where the sentencing judge ignores the impact of the crime on the victim.  In a recent case, for example, a judge explained that he was giving a custodial sentence to a rapist, that he was not giving the rapist the maximum sentence or as severe a sentence as he might otherwise do as the criminal led &ldquo;a nomadic lifestyle&rdquo;.  The judge was conscious of the impact that a custodial sentence would have on a person who led such a lifestyle.  I cannot understand that logic.  I cannot understand how the victim must have felt when she heard those words.  The media reports on that case do not record any reaction from the victim, but one suspects that this was a classic case of heaping insult upon serious and unspeakable injury.</P>
    <P>As the Minister and other Senators have said sentencing is not an exact science. As outside observers, we would not be aware of all the circumstances and would be more aware of all the facts and extenuating circumstances than anybody depending on media reports.  Nonetheless, I reflect on the last case and other cases and wonder how the victims felt. The least that society and more importantly that victims should expect is that sentencing should be consistent, reflecting society's abhorrence of the crime and it should act as a deterrent against future crime.</P>
    <P>While I commend the Minister on these two elements of the legislation, I <Col N="845" /> would like to express concern about victim representation in the courts.  The view that a victim should be allowed separate representation in the case of rape or incest is a valid one.  The Minister in this Bill, and her predecessor in the 1992 Bill, went a long way towards making the judicial process in such cases more victim-oriented.  However, given the trauma which any victim goes through in the cross-examination which is central to any crime where there is not an admission of guilt, it is vital that the victim be represented to protect her interests, both during the trial and, in particular, during the cross-examination, but also at the end of the trial when sentencing is being considered.</P>
    <P>At present, the court will hear of any special or extenuating circumstances that may favour the accused.  We are all familiar with worthy individuals who trot into court and, sometimes at the risk of public opprobrium, say there are good as well as bad aspects to the accused's character and ask for leniency.  The plea for a more rigorous sentence by the other side is never entered.  I share a view which has been expressed by Members of the Opposition in the Dáil that this issue requires further attention.</P>
    <P>The third element in the Bill which I particularly welcome is the increase in the maximum penalty for incest from seven to 20 years.  After the details of the Kilkenny case were made public I expressed my exasperation with and condemnation of the logic &mdash; if that is the appropriate word &mdash; which allowed incest to be treated, in some cases, as being a lesser evil than rape from the point of view of the sentences which could attach to the crimes.  The Minister explained that life imprisonment remains a maximum penalty where the victim is under 15; she also explained that life imprisonment is the maximum penalty where the victim is over 15 and it is proven that the act takes place without consent.  In those circumstances the life sentence can be imposed because the male can be charged with rape.  I appreciate the point made by the Minister that the issue of consent can present a difficulty <Col N="846" /> in many cases, and accept it as an explanation for the apparent difference in the standard of sentencing.</P>
    <P>I have mixed feelings about the provisions in the Bill which deal with compensation. I readily accept that there should be provision for compensation in cases where the extent of personal injuries can be measured.  How can compensation be gauged?  How do you put a monetary value on the trauma sufferer by a victim?  I have had some first hand experience of this.  A number of years ago I suffered a severe personal assault; I was mugged and spent time in an intensive care unit.  I suffered more from trauma than from the injuries I sustained. In personal cases the trauma is the greater burden.  I cannot see how trauma can be measured for compensation.</P>
    <P>I read recently a case in another jurisdiction where a rapist was requested to pay for a holiday for the victim; the cost of the holiday was put at £500.  While the intention of the court was undoubtedly a benign one, the very small monetary amount involved places a very low value on the trauma suffered by the victim, her feelings, and the trauma suffered by her family.  The reality is that no monetary amount can compensate for the injury suffered.  In that case the family said they would not avail of the holiday.</P>
    <P>How will the compensation be paid if the criminal has no resources?  Will a State-funded compensation scheme be established, or will compensation be received only by those who are victims of crimes perpetrated by the better off?  If the latter is the case, a double injustice will be suffered.</P>
    <P>The Minister touched on an issue not directly arising from the Bill, but one which has given rise to a great deal of public concern, that is, the protection of the victim from further harassment by the criminal.  The concerns expressed on this issue in the Dáil seemed to refer to the period following a trial.  However, we should also be concerned about harassment and intimidation not just of victims but also of witnesses in the lead up to a trial.  The question of protection was raised by the victim in the Kilkenny <Col N="847" /> case when she graphically described in a television interview her concern that when her father was released he would return to plague her.  I appreciate the concern of the victim in that case.</P>
    <P>Intimidation is not just there where a custodial sentence is handed down.  It is there all too frequently, it lies under the surface and may prevent many cases going to trial.  I am not aware of the existence of statistics on the extent of the problem but from experience in my constituency I am aware of cases of intimidation of victims and potential witnesses that prevented cases going to trial. There is no point in a public representative exerting a victim or a witness to go to trial and to co-operate with the Garda Síochána if they fear they will suffer further assault.  The anecdotal evidence available to me is corroborated by my contacts with other public representatives and with the Garda Síochána.</P>
    <P>There is a need for some form of legal process to empower the courts to prohibit either an accused person, or anybody acting on the person's behalf, or a convicted person at the end of a trial from contacting a victim or a witness where that contact is intended to intimidate a victim or to persuade a witness not to attend.  This is a growing issue which is causing major concern in another jurisdiction.</P>
    <P>I listened, for example, to a report about the Greater Manchester Police and it was suggested that as many as 12 murder trials were abandoned in recent times because either the families or witnesses had been intimidated.  There is intimidation in trials, in cases of rape and incest, and in cases involving crime against the individual.  It is an issue that requires a response and urgent attention. The Minister made specific reference to this issue in her speech and I compliment her because it indicates that she is conscious of the matter and of what was said in the Dáil in relation to it.</P>
    <P>I accept the Minister's point that she cannot address all issues in a single Bill, but the problem of intimidation is of <Col N="848" /> growing concern to me, to other public representatives and I am sure to the Minister. It is a growing plague within the community and I suggest it is a matter that we should perhaps return to in later legislation.  The Minister has indicated that she has a series of reforms in mind and perhaps this issue should be referred to the Law Reform Commission.</P>
    <P>There is another form of intimidation of witnesses and it applies particularly in cases involving rape or incest.  It is a form of moral intimidation and of moral cowardice; it comes from within ourselves and within society.  I do not wish to pre-judge the ongoing inquiry into the Kilkenny case but I find it incomprehensible that many people in caring professions were not aware of the difficulties. In the public sector, many people in the performance of their duty become aware of these cases.  There is, however, a form of moral, perhaps societal, persuasion or intimidation which suggests that we should not get involved or intervene in cases involving a family.  It is time that consideration was given to the creation of not just a statutory right but a statutory responsibility for people in public positions to notify an appropriate authority of cases which have come to their attention.  The issues of intimidation and of creating a statutory responsiblity on people in caring professions to bring forward knowledge or suspicions they have of incest or rape go beyond this Bill.</P>
    <P>I commend this Bill.  It is good legislation and I commend the Minister and the Minister of State for bringing it forward. I hope when it is on the Statute Book it will not be, like so many other Statutes, consigned to oblivion.  I hope the powers given here will be frequently used, and that there will be regular reviews.  Perhaps the Minister could respond to this point, that a year or two years after this Bill goes on the Statute Book its operation could be reviewed in order to establish if fine tuning or updating is necessary.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate the Minister of State, Deputy O'Dea, on his <Col N="849" /> reappointment to the Department of Justice. It was a good decision even though he would probably have preferred the senior position.  I had the pleasure of working with him in the Dáil on a number of Bills and I found him a very good person to have in charge of affairs.  He was very open-minded, willing to have discussions and he brought some very good legislation through the Dáil which was honed and sharpened as it went through the process.  I am glad the Minister is back in that position because I am sure he will continue the very good work he was involved in in the last Dáil.  I look forward to meeting him in this House from time to time over the next few years.</P>
      <P>I welcome this legislation but it is a pity we had to wait for a particularly gross and terrible crime involving child sexual abuse before it was decided that it was a matter of great urgency.  We tend to react to situations rather than being circumspect and revising legislation according to instinct.</P>
      <P>The Kilkenny case, as it has come to be known, created widespread revulsion throughout the community and, in common with many public representatives, I received letters from the public as a result.  I received one letter from a group of fourth year students in a secondary school.  They expressed their anger, they were terribly upset and wrote in a particularly vindictive manner about the judge who acted in that case.  They obviously had been reading the papers because they gave a very graphic description of the case.  I feel they would have over-reacted if they had had a part in sentencing and in the kind of legislation being dealt with here.  However the community, including children, were outraged by this case and it has to be said that the perpetrator of that crime got off easily.  It is a shame that proper legislation was not in place to deal with the case in an appropriate way.  Most people feel that this man should have been treated in a very different way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We can only imagine the terrible effects this abuse had on the child's personality and on her life; they are almost too awful to contemplate.  In this case a <Col N="850" /> young girl's personality was destroyed, and the pity of it is that the person who brought that about was her protector and, at some stage, he was probably her idol.  He was a figure of authority within the household and a man who at one stage was idolised by the child.  He was a figure of support and safety and who should have been the rock on which the child began to build her life.  He destroyed whatever chance that child had of living a satisfactory life and he did this in the interest of satisfying his own lust. He inflicted the most dreadful emotional and physical destruction on the young victim.  It was the worst case that ever came before the courts.  It shocked everyone and the reaction of the Department of Justice was swift.</P>
    <P>This case raises a number of questions, and Senator Roche dealt with some of them.  It is incredible that over a 16 year period, no one outside the family circle who came in contact with the child suspected the real nature of the victim's suffering, even though we are aware at this stage that the child, and later the young woman, came to the attention of a number of health board staff.  She was hospitalised on a number of occasions because of physical injuries and would have been at school during the time that this vicious crime was being perpetrated against her.  Normally when a child suffers sexual abuse they undergo personality changes and their behaviour tends to oscillate.  Anybody with an insight into normal behaviour should have recognised that there was a problem.</P>
    <P>I find it incredible in this most vicious case that nobody reported this abuse for 16 years.  This leads one to question whether people decided not to report it because of the social attitudes of the times or they thought they would raise difficulties.  I have questions about this case and the authenticity of some of the information.  The system let this young girl down and I wonder if the people who should have known and reported the case have guilty consciences.</P>
    <P>I produced a policy document on this matter some time ago and I believe that <Col N="851" /> the Minister of State should ask his colleagues in the Department of Health to review the Child Care Act, 1992, at once. While that Bill was going through the Dáil, I, and others, suggested that reporting these cases should be mandatory. This case strongly supports that suggestion. People who suspect these crimes are being committed should be required by law to report them and, having done so, should be given protection by the law. Protection would be necessary because crimes of this nature lead to problems within families.  There would always be a danger that unless protection &mdash; anonymity for example &mdash; was given to the person who reports the case they could suffer physically and emotionally.</P>
    <P>When the Bill was being debated in the Dáil I asked that this provision be included but the then Minister for Health felt it was unnecessary.  Why?  Maybe he felt he would disturb some professionals who work with children or that would be calling their integrity into question. Maybe he felt he would lose a few votes. I was surprised that suggestion was not taken on board, especially since the Law Reform Commission came down firmly in favour of that kind of legislative action in its report.  I hope we have learned a lesson and that there will be a review of the Child Care Act, 1992, with a view to updating the law in the areas to which we are referring.</P>
    <P>Thousands of adults and children have suffered sexual abuse.  I would like to give the House an indication of the figures we are talking about.  Reporting of this problem was almost unknown before 1984 and in 1984 only 88 cases were reported in Ireland; five years later, the number of reports increased to 1,241. That was a huge increase over a five year period and marked a change in thinking and a more open approach to sexual matters. It is generally accepted that the official figures are an under-estimation of the problem.  The Childline service operated by the ISPCC gives an indication of the under-estimation.  In 1990, according to the ISPCC report, there were 5,895 calls regarding child sexual <Col N="852" /> abuse on Childline.  That does not tally with the official figures but it shows we are dealing with a time bomb, particularly when we consider the effects that abuse can have on the victims.</P>
    <P>People may suffer serious personality disorders; this type of abuse disrupts the normal development of the child and prevents the formation of happy relationships in later life.  Victims suffer low self-esteem, guilt and depression.  They may become involved in substance abuse and that often leads to further crime.  They also tend to get involved in prostitution and many have suicidal tendencies.  One person who grows up in this kind of atmosphere can become a burden on society but if we multiply that figure by thousands, we could have an enormous problem.</P>
    <P>The increase in various forms of crime &mdash; for example attacks on the elderly &mdash; might be related to substance abuse. People who need money to buy the next fix will attack an old person who may have money in the house.  They will repeat this crime many times if they are successful.  Many crimes might be explained in this way.  We must look at this problem from a preventative and therapeutic point of view in an affort to undo the damage.  To date we have failed in that area.</P>
    <P>The Minister might consider making the law more victim-friendly as he has done in the past.  Criminal legislation should allow for consultation between the injured party and the judge as to the penalty to be imposed on the accused after conviction.  Where the victim wishes to be consulted on the sentence, the range of penalties should be made available and the victim should be allowed make suggestions to the court on the type of sentence which he or she considers appropriate.  The judge should be obliged to take the victim's suggestion into account when determining the penalty. The final sentencing decision would remain with the judge but consultation with the victim would help the healing process and give a proper sense of importance to the victim in law.  That <Col N="853" /> worthwhile suggestion should be examined.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Services for the Mentally Handicapped:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Services for the Mentally Handicapped: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann notes that the additional allocation for services for people with a mental handicap in 1993, at £8 million, is the highest increase in this allocation for many years; calls on the Government to bring forward an integrated plan, based on the Report <i>Needs and Abilities</i> and on the many submissions it has received, to ensure that services for people with a mental handicap are raised to the highest standard. Seanad Éireann further calls on the Government to ensure that&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  all policy is based on the recognition that people with a mental handicap have a right to education, training, employment, and residential care, as and when they need it;</P>
      <P>(b)  the highest possible contribution is made from the next round of EC Structural Funds to the elaboration and enhancement of these rights; and</P>
      <P>(c)  the parents of people with mental handicap are fully involved in the planning process.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Minister.  It will be interesting for him to hear the views of Members on an issue which is important to all of us.  We welcome the additional £8 million allocated to services for the mentally handicapped in this budget. That is an above average increase at a time of financial constraints for a service which has recently become the subject of public debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There has been a move towards community rather than institution based <Col N="854" /> services for the mentally handicapped. Perhaps I should not use the word &ldquo;institution&rdquo; but that is basically where services began.  I am sure the Minister will distribute the £8 million equally among all the health boards.  The North Western Health Board would have no trouble distributing the entire £8 million if it had it. I welcome any move which makes life more bearable for people with a mental handicap.</P>
    <P>Community residences for the mentally handicapped may be allocated much of this money, that is where people want to see money spent.  Funding is required to provide assistance for mentally handicapped people of all ages.  The elderly with mental handicap both in hospital and in the community deserve special attention.</P>
    <P>Many people with mild mental handicaps now living in the community spent 20, 30 or 40 years in psychiatric hospitals until the eighties when their situation was assessed and a more relaxed programme of care was introduced.  These people had been locked up in institutions for many years until somebody discovered that they were not as ill as had been thought. With a struggle, society began to accept mentally handicapped people as human beings.  Community based facilities were established, houses provided and after assessment many were allowed to leave psychiatric hospitals and move into the community.</P>
    <P>As a psychiatric nurse for many years I believe this development was a move in the right direction.  It is nice to walk downtown nowadays and bid the time of day to persons who, until five or six years ago, were locked up for no reason.  New facilities, training and education programmes were made available to persons caring for the mentally handicapped.  I admire RNMHs who undergo strict training and work in trying conditions.  Funds provided by the Department and the EC have made life more pleasant for persons with mental handicap and helped them integrate into society.</P>
    <P>Resource centres are being set up to provide programmes of care for the mentally handicapped.  More therapists are <Col N="855" /> required to give clients the benefit of a one-to-one relationship as they learn to survive in the community.  It is amazing how some people have progressed from incarceration in an institution to an active life in the community.  The wide range of mental handicaps needing specialised attention makes the job of the mental handicap nurse tougher all the time.  The nurse must keep his or her head and adopt an understanding approach in a demanding job.  RNMHs have performed well and have given terrific service to the community.</P>
    <P>The RNMHs organise activities to teach the person with mental handicap to cook and to care for personal hygiene. They also help with integration into the community.  Social activities such as going to the pictures or the pub were unheard of for such persons years ago. With help and education that is no longer so.  Society will accept persons with mental handicap if ongoing education is provided on the changes taking place in services for the mentally handicapped.</P>
    <P>Parents and relatives of persons with a mental handicap may feel that they are not sufficiently involved in the treatment which their child, brother or sister is receiving.  Clubs have been established where the client and parent or relative can socialise together.  Carers now come into the home to support families and to help the client get involved in the community.  This is a tremendous fillip for families.  Few families want to put the handicapped person into an institution or even a community home; they would rather keep them at home.  Help and support are available at present but more is needed.  It would take endless amounts of money to provide all of the support required but the Minister is moving in that direction.</P>
    <P>In emergencies residential facilities can be made available for members of families to allow their brother or sister to be taken into care at weekends.  While I am glad that respite beds will be made available, much more is required.</P>
    <P>I acknowledge the tremendous work of the voluntary organisations who provide <Col N="856" /> moneys for services for the handicapped. There is not a bottomless pit of money and, like many others, they are seeking an allocation.  However, as I said, they have done tremendous work in bringing moneys to mentally handicapped services, especially in relation to providing housing and leisure facilities.  I compliment them on the work they have done.  There should be more leisure facilities for the handicapped in hospitals. Gymnasiums and swimming pools should be provided as the handicapped are well able to participate in all there activities and it brings them closer to a normal way of life.  If the money is used to bring about improvements in that way, it will be a tremendous fillip to the people concerned.</P>
    <P>I welcome the money made available by the Minister and I know it will be well spent.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion. The report, <i>Needs and Abilities</i> was published in 1990 in relation to people with a mental handicap and on the basis of that document this motion was brought before the House today.  It is also based on the Programme for Partnership Government recently drawn up between Fianna Fáil and the Labour Party.  The report was incorporated in the <i>Programme for Social and Economic Progress</i> in 1991 and it was costed at £50 million at the time.</P>
      <P>There is a growing need for funding, commitment and co-ordination in the area of mental handicap of which I am aware as a member of a health board.  The number of people with a mental handicap has risen by 25 per cent since 1981 and continues to rise.  Both society in general and the various health boards are becoming more aware of the growing number of people in the community who need these services.  I came across a family recently in which three mentally handicapped adults were being cared for by their elderly parents.  Unfortunately, both parents died recently and the three dependants have been added to the statistics.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The motion is in three parts.  The first <Col N="857" /> is its introduction which talks about the need to bring forward an integrated plan. That is important because various Government Departments, voluntary organisations and health boards deal with the needs of the mentally handicapped, but there is an urgent need to co-ordinate and integrate them because many areas overlap and the services could be more coherently planned and delivered if there was co-ordination.  It is important that the plan is integrated.  Point 10 (a), the right of people to educational, employment and residential care, is most important and should be a statutory right.  There should be a means redress for those whose rights are infringed, because they are meaningless otherwise.</P>
    <P>I welcome the additional allocation from EC Structural Funds of £8.5 million, as even an extra £.5 million is urgently needed.  The figure of £50 million in the 1990 report, <i>Needs and Abilities</i> also needs to be updated because it is now a higher figure.  Even the £50 million would be difficult to raise through national resources, so we support the suggestion that we should get the highest possible contribution from the Structural Funds, because it is essential to provide for the mentally handicapped.</P>
    <P>In the Mid-Western Health Board, we submitted a report to the board approximately a year ago, in which we identified 499 mentally handicapped persons who did not have any service &mdash; I am referring to only one health board area &mdash; so it is essential that the funding continues.  The £8.5 million is the greatest increase to date and although it is welcome, we hope it will continue in future years because it is essential to address the needs of the mentally handicapped.</P>
    <P>Thirdly, the involvement of parents of people with a mental handicap is crucial. There are excellent parent bodies working in this area producing reports and working with service providers.  Indeed, I have a report here from my own health board which was drawn up by the health board, the service providers and the parents' organisations.  It is essential that the parents are involved in the planning <Col N="858" /> because they are probably more involved and give more of their time than any other parental group.  Because these people, even in adulthood, are still dependent on others I agree with Senator Maloney that carers must be considered and their views incorporated in the plan.</P>
    <P>Different levels and kinds of care are needed.  While some need full residential care, others might only require day care, just some help in the home, or respite care, which gives the carers a break for a couple of weeks.  The areas of preschool and early intervention is very important because progress could be made if the mentally handicapped were aided at an early stage, this has been proven elsewhere.  We should have an integrated multi-disciplinary approach and the various Departments dealing with the situation &mdash; the Department of Health, the Department of Education, the Department of Enterprise and Employment and those dealing with EC funding &mdash; should be involved as well as the health boards and the service providers. This motion needs to be followed up by the Minister for Health and others. These should be planned over a number of years until all mentally handicapped people are provided with services appropriate to their needs.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>We will also support the motion and I compliment the Members for tabling it.  The mentally handicapped are often forgotten, except by their families and those who look after them.  I welcome the Minister to the House and, I wish him well and congratulate him on his recent appointment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We support the motion and the proposed points in relation to education, training, employment and residential care.  We hope that mental health and mental disability will receive a portion of the money coming from Europe and that parents and professionals will be involved in the preparation of any plan as they are experienced in this area.  I compliment Senator Maloney because he sees the problem at first hand.  Some of us, through friends or individuals, may have come across it but unless one's family is <Col N="859" /> directly affected one is looking at it from the sidelines.</P>
    <P>We support every pound put into these services.  I have a query about the £8 million mentioned in the motion as I have been told it may be only £6.5 million. Perhaps the Minister will clarify where the moneys will be spent.  Despite our straitened circumstances I do not think any of us begrudge extra moneys for the development and care of mentally handicapped people.  Indeed, a portion of national lottery funding should, on an annual basis, be allocated to assist the health and development of the mentally handicapped.</P>
    <P>The motion refers to the <i>Needs and Abilities</i> report of 1990 which is a good document containing many recommendations. I hope it will not be left on the shelf like many other reports.  I am not sure how many of its recommendations have been implemented so far but I hope that the key points in relation to the policy for the intellectually disabled will be implemented.  Certain matters can be prioritised; for example Senator O'Sullivan mentioned that there are no services in some parts of her area and I suppose that may be the case in other areas.  It is important to make decisions and progress.</P>
    <P>A serious problem in the cases I have encountered is when parents are caring for a teenager, a stage that causes difficulties. Although parents put in a tremendous effort and work hard to do their best for their child, one of their biggest worries is about the future and what will happen to their child when they are too old to cope.  The Minister must address the problems of those parents in relation to the development of services for the mentally handicapped.</P>
    <P>The report's recommendations in relation to areas like the treatment of young children, residential treatment and treatment for older people should be implemented to ensure that people can live as normally as possible and to provide a back-up service to assist parents. Parents who live with a disabled child or relative throughout the year must get an <Col N="860" /> annual break, it should be part and parcel of the system.  An incapacitated relative's allowance or an extra allowance should be provided for carers.  The general carer's allowance currently provided is minimal when the care, treatment and attention involved are taken into account.</P>
    <P>The Minister might indicate what has been done, since the report was published in 1990, in relation to pilot schemes.  As it is nearly three years since then I hope some attention has been paid to it.  In my area there are three or four units attached to St. John of God's Hospital who do much good work for which they should be praised and thanked. There is also a shortage of speech therapists in some areas.</P>
    <P>The Minister should also deal with the needs of various hospitals as I am sure there are many applications for additional resources.  Progress has been made in our psychiatric hospitals where Victorian buildings are a thing of the past and a modern, newer and open policy is evolving.  The Minister should look at those areas and, although my colleagues can make valid applications for extra funding, he should heed the advice of professionals in regard to the greatest need and how we can respond to that need.  Money is probably the greatest necessity but, as in other sectors, just throwing money at the problem will not necessarily solve it.  We should look at where we will get the best value for the moneys spent.</P>
    <P>I pay a special tribute to the various voluntary organisations who daily assist families and organise outings.  As Senator Maloney said, families of handicapped people should have the same quality of life as any of us and, as far as possible, should be able to do the things that some of us take for granted.  A big annual event in Dublin is the outing for handicapped children organised by the city's taxi owners.</P>
    <P>I would ask the Minister to consider what I have said and to respond positively to it.  The Minister has our support in relation to the provision of extra moneys for services for people with mental handicap. <Col N="861" /> With regard to the lottery, I hope that some amount, no matter how infinitesimal, will be allocated to specific projects or needs in certain areas of the country.  Any programme for the provision of facilities would have our support.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WillieFarrell" hpid="Mr. Farrell Mr. Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister and congratulate him on his interest in the mentally handicapped and ensuring the allocation of £8.5 million for this very worthy cause.</P>
      <P>When I went into public life 26 years ago the only places for mentally handicapped people in my area were St. Columba's in Sligo and St. Conal's in Letterkenny, the psychiatric hospitals. We have come a long way since then.  Too much money is spent on institutionalised care.  Mentally handicapped people were taken from one institution and put into a better and more comfortable one, which was a step forward.  However, they must now be brought into the community.</P>
      <P>In the north-west a committee of parents, staff and health board officials work together.  Great co-operation and progress is being made.  When one makes changes staff are worried about being let go, what is to be done with them and where are they going to go.  One runs into problems.  Now parents and staff are represented on the committees and this ensures there are no problems and things get done.  This is a step forward; and something like this should be done in every health board area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Mentally handicapped people cannot and should not be institutionalised.  They have a right to live in the community.  It took a while to educate the community to accept mentally handicapped people. We have reached the stage now of providing them with bungalows.  In my village six people have lived in a four bedroomed bungalow for the last four or five years.  They are part of the community and are fully accepted by everybody. Unfortunately, the bungalows are only rented at the moment and that is a worry for patients, parents and staff. They worry that the lease may not be <Col N="862" /> renewed or the house may be sold.  I would like to see some of the £8.5 million made available to purchase bungalows in the community, in urban or rural areas, to allow the mentally handicapped to live in their own area, where parents and friends can visit them regularly.</P>
    <P>There should be more support for carers &mdash; those who look after the mentally handicapped at home because we are not giving them enough.  Some of the £8.5 million should be used to provide more professional help for carers and to provide more respite care.  At present voluntary organisations are providing a great service but they cannot accommodate every handicapped person who needs help.  Some of these units have been branded upmarket and some have been described as not so good.  We should ensure all units provide the same high standard of care and attention.  No one unit should be better than another.</P>
    <P>These services are profession led.  The professions say what should be done and we do as they say.  The time has come to listen more to the parents and to the handicapped.  They are being educated. They are reasonably intelligent, some very intelligent.  They should be asked what they want, they should be facilitated and given a say in what is being done. Although professionals are needed, they cannot lead the way all the time.  Giving the handicapped a say in their own lives is a way to give them independence.  It also helps us accept they are human beings capable of making up their own minds.  We should discuss matters with them, let them say what they like and, as far as possible, give them what they want. This will let them know they are playing a part in their own rehabilitation.</P>
    <P>Care for the mentally handicapped has come a long way.  We are bringing them all into the community.  We will never again have the secured institutions we had a quarter of a century ago.  Psychiatric patients are now accepted in the community and they must be kept there. It is not cheap.  The cheapest way is to provide a big unit; the bigger the unit the cheaper the service but that is not giving a proper service.  People cannot be treated <Col N="863" /> like that.  Extra money should be spent to make them part of the community and to give them a reason for living.</P>
    <P>In one of the units in North Sligo the handicapped people have a vegetable garden.  They are producing vegetables and selling them locally.  This is giving them a purpose in life.  They work in their greenhouse, and their tunnels, they go to the local shop, etc.  This would not have been seen years ago.  I see this transformation in the two units in north Sligo. This is also happening in Donegal, Sligo and Leitrim.</P>
    <P>As I said, permanent accommodation must be provided in my area because at present parents, staff and the mentally handicapped are worried.  They wonder how long they can remain in the rented bungalows.  It was said one of the bungalows might be sold and everybody involved was very anxious until they were reassured it would not happen.</P>
    <P>The £8.5 million should be evenly distributed. Because the North-Western Health Board is one of the best in the country, unfortunately, we do not get our fair share of cash.  A new hospital was built in Sligo at £650,000 below the estimated cost but the health board did not get that money to develop further services in the community.  The health board is not getting its fair share of the money that is available.  This money should be used to make permanent services available so that the mentally handicapped can be rehabilitated in the community and can feel they are people, not inmates. That image of the inmate must be abolished. Each person has a name and we call them by their names.  We want them to be part of the community and in permanent residence within the community.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHowlin" hpid="Minister for Health (Mr. Howlin) Brendan Howlin">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Health (Mr. Howlin)</NameTxt>
      <P>At the outset I congratulate the Labour Senators for raising this important issue of service for persons with a mental handicap.  I am grateful for the opportunity this affords me to put on the record my commitment and that of the Government to provide in accordance with the Programme for a Partnership Government <Col N="864" /> the highest possible level of service for persons with a mental handicap to create an environment in which all persons with a disability of whatever kind can freely exercise their rights as citizens of this country.</P>
      <P>Services for people with mental handicap are provided by voluntary organisations, both religious and lay, and by the statutory agencies, health boards. The expansion in the level of service provision can be seen in that the number of people in receipt of services increased from 8,600 in 1981 to 11,800 at the end of 1990, an increase of 37 per cent.  In addition, some 7,500 children attend special schools and classes operated under the aegis of the Department of Education.</P>
      <P>From the information currently available within the various health boards, there is a need now for about 1,300 residential places and 1,400 day places for about 2,200 with mental handicap as some persons require both a day and a residential place.  In addition, there is a need to expand early intervention services to develop the potential of every child, to improve services for the 942 people with mental handicap still resident in our psychiatric hospitals, and to provide for the special needs of disturbed clients.</P>
      <P>A substantial sum of money is being spent on health services for people with mental handicap.  In 1992, almost £200 million was spent on these services.  Of this, £158 million was spent on the provision of day, residential and support services. A further £36 million was spent on cash allowances.  Relative to other public services, funding for the mental handicap services has been protected.  The allocation of agencies funded directly by my Department increased from £39 million in 1981 to over £104 million in 1993, an increase of 167 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The objectives of the mental handicap services are to develop the person with mental handicap to the maximum of his or her potential by ensuring that people enjoy a life that is as normal as possible within the community for as long as possible; that people have access to personalised <Col N="865" /> programmes and their families have access to adequate support, that people who can no longer live at home are cared for in a supportive and appropriate living environment.</P>
    <P>This policy is set out clearly in the report of the Review Group on Mental Handicap Services entitled <i>Needs and Abilities.</i>  The recommendations of this report were accepted by Government in the context of the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress.</i>  The cost of their implementation is included in the financial commitment made in the programme for the development of community services over a seven year period, and I can assure this House of my resolve, and that of the Government, to implement as quickly as possible the recommendations contained in <i>Needs and Abilities.</i></P>
    <P>In the light of the recommendations and the priorities identified in the plans from each health board area, and in discussions with the National Association for the Mentally Handicapped of Ireland, my Department proposed that the shortfall in services be tackled on a broad front.  It was decided that any additional funding should be used to address a number of gaps in services.</P>
    <P>In 1992 an additional £5 million revenue and £1 million capital was made available to implement these proposals. The additional funding put in place last year helped to provide 127 residential places, 37 respite care places, 417 day places, home support services for over 1,000 families, and 26 emergency places. Six places for disturbed clients, including the replacement of Unit B at St. Loman's Hospital, Lucan, were also provided in addition to two early intervention teams and 48 child education and development centre places.</P>
    <P>With the special additional funding for services for people with disabilities announced in the budget, it will be possible to put in place this year significant improvements in services in addition to strengthening existing services for people with mental handicap.  I wish to confirm to the House that an additional £8.5 million will be spent over and above last <Col N="866" /> year's expenditure for people with a mental handicap.</P>
    <P>I am proposing to implement a package of measures similar to those put in place last year which will address the most acute needs for service developments. Additional funds will be made available throughout the country, with particular attention to the health boards with the greatest number of clients without services. This funding will be on top of the additional funding of £6 million made available last year, which is being repeated this year.  We are talking about an increase of £6 million last year plus £8.5 million on top of that which I believe to be a significant advance and a significant honouring of the commitment in the Programme for a Partnership Government.</P>
    <P>An additional 70 residential places will be available for people with a mental handicap and their families this year as well as an additional 200 day places, and an extension of respite services to support families.  This extension will make progress towards the point where planned respite breaks will be available, on a regular basis, to all families and carers.  The increased funding will mean additional home support services for 800 to 900 families, and improved services for those who are behaviourally disturbed.  Further transfers of people with mental handicap from psychiatric hospitals to more appropriate placements within the mental handicap services are planned this year along with an extension of early intervention and child development services.</P>
    <P>The actual services to be provided will be agreed in each health board area by the Regional Mental Handicap Co-ordinating Committee, and approved by my Department.  The boards will shortly be given details of the additional allocation of funding.  This additional funding of £8.5 million is the largest increase in any year in the amount of money made available to develop services for people with disabilities.  It is a measure of the high priority which the Government and I, as Minister for Health, attach to developing services for people with mental handicap and their families.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="867" /> The European Social Fund provides assistance towards the cost of training people, including people with mental handicap, for employment in the open market.  Our vocational training service for people with disabilities currently receives in excess of £26 million per annum of which almost half is for people with mental handicap.  However, the ESF does not aid sheltered work programmes or the training of people with disabilities for sheltered employment.</P>
    <P>The current ESF rules remain in force until the end of this year.  My Department is pressing strongly for a broadening of the role of eligible activities under the post-1993 ESF to include training for sheltered or supported employment.  Our views have been made known at EC level.</P>
    <P>I must also point out that the provision of sheltered work programmes and sheltered employment is an integral part of the services provided by voluntary and statutory mental handicap agencies. Again, I want to assure the House that this Government will leave no stone unturned to ensure the maximum possible contribution from the European Social Fund towards services for people with a disability.</P>
    <P>I agree with the motion that parents of people with mental handicap should be fully involved in the planning process.  I want to see this involvement extended and strengthened.  In the past year, parent representatives, nominated by the National Association for the Mentally Handicapped of Ireland, have become members of each of the regional mental handicap co-ordinating committees. Parent interests are also represented on these committees through the involvement of the many voluntary parents and friends organisations which provide services for people with a mental handicap. My Department meets on a regular basis with the National Association for the Mentally Handicapped of Ireland and is kept informed of the main concerns of parents.  While parents already make an important contribution to identifying needs and planning services, I believe <Col N="868" /> this contribution could be strengthened. In line with the commitment of the Programme for a Partnership Government, I have asked my Department to examine ways in which parents' involvement in planning services can be made more effective.</P>
    <P>As this House is aware the Government, through the Programme for a Partnership Government, is committed to improving the quality of life for people with mental handicap and their families. These proposals include the provision of additional funding to accelerate the implementation of the <i>Needs and Abilities</i> report; the enactment of legislation to put the rights of people with a mental handicap on a statutory basis, together with a means of redress for people whose rights are ignored; measures to ensure that the parents and families of people with a mental handicap are adequately consulted and involved in the planning and decision-making processes; measures to ensure greater co-operation among the agencies involved, in such areas, for example, as the assembling of financial and other information, and in the most rational and effective use of transport facilities; an educational programme based on the principle of choice-integration into mainstream schools and classes for those children whose families want it, and improved staffing and facilities in special schools for others; re-classification of special national schools, as junior and senior schools to recognise the fact that students attend such schools up to the age of eighteen.  Over time, the equipping of all such schools to the same standards as all primary and secondary schools; the establishment of a vocational training centre for people with a mental handicap on the campus of one of our universities, as a pilot project, to enhance the rights and perception of people with a mental handicap, and to encourage and facilitate research into their training and developmental needs.  All of these proposals I will pursue in conjunction with my Government colleagues.  I will be working closely with my colleague, the Minister for Equality and Law Reform, Deputy Taylor, to ensure that these proposals <Col N="869" /> become reality as speedily as possible.</P>
    <P>The Government is firmly committed to eliminating inequality for all groups in society that have suffered from disability, disadvantage or discrimination.  People with a disability are equal citizens of Ireland.  The full expression of that citizenship requires the mobilisation of community resources and an injection of political will.  We intend to ensure the equality of people with disabilities by ensuring that the services they need are theirs as of right.  We will ensure that people with a disability and their families have as much choice as possible in the use of services and that they are consulted about policy and service issues.  We will encourage the integration of services with those for the community as a whole, to the extent that people with a disability and their families so wish.  I ask the support of the Seanad in this task.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate the Minister on his report and on his enthusiasm for this task.  I liked his constant emphasis on integrating people with mental handicap into the community.  This motion was a good one to put forward today.  The number of people with mental handicap in the community can only increase over the next few years because of the increasingly longer lifespan of citizens with mental handicap.  The sooner we realise this the better.</P>
      <P>Persons with Down's Syndrome are often only mildly mentally handicapped. Their main problem can be the ease with which they are identified.  Twenty years ago these people had a lifespan of 20 years.  Now persons with Down's Syndrome live until their forties and fifties and in many cases can be integrated into the community.  I have a friend with Down's Syndrome who is an usher at a cinema.  It is a great pity that more of these people were not brought into the mainstream of community life sooner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the Minister's remarks about integrating persons with mental handicap into the community.  In matters of education it means a great deal to many parents and to the people themselves <Col N="870" /> if they can be integrated into the ordinary school system.  There is a need for training for persons with mental handicap. Not all of us are potential Einstein's with IQs of 130.  Many handicapped people are excluded from training schemes for which they might qualify.  I hope more generous assessment is introduced in this area.  Large organisations should be encouraged to employ persons with mental handicap wherever possible.</P>
    <P>Residential care in small units is preferable to accommodating people in large institutions.  Small units enable residents to enjoy greater freedom and choice.  It is desperately important to their relations that people with a mental handicap may lead ordinary lives.</P>
    <P>Parents of a child with a mental handicap experience considerable fear about what will happen to the child when they die.  I welcome the Minister's plans to invest money in this area but I am always fearful that money intended for one area may be diverted to another.  If the Minister allocates money to a particular project he must ensure it gets there. Sometimes one finds that a vacancy can not be filled because money has been diverted elsewhere.  Funding is better organised in some health board areas than in others.  I hope distribution of this new funding will be co-ordinated carefully throughout the country.</P>
    <P>I am anxious about the situation of persons with multiple handicaps.  There are persons with a mental handicap who may also be deaf or blind or suffer from a physical disability.  These people unfortunately seem to slip through the net. Those who deal with the blind say such persons should be catered for by mental health services; those, who deal with the mentally handicapped say they should be dealt with through services for the blind. As a result children with a multiple handicap may receive little teaching or training. I hope people with multiple handicaps will be carefully provided for. It is absolutely essential that persons with a mental handicap and their parents have more of a say in their treatment.  When I talk to patients with mental handicap I am pleased at the number who watch <Col N="871" /> more serious RTE programmes such as &ldquo;Questions and Answers&rdquo;.  When I have asked what they thought of the programme they say that such a person was hopeless and someone else was good.  We underestimate the number of choices that people can make for themselves and persons with mental handicaps must be encouraged to make their own choices.</P>
    <P>Respite care is marvellous where available and must be supported.  Voluntary workers in this area are doing a tremendous job.  Any funds, or moral support invested in respite care will pay dividends &mdash; people can cope with someone at home for a certain length of time, but a short break is essential then, to enable the carer to resume caring.  Caring for somebody with a mental handicap is a major responsibility and a source of constant anxiety to many parents.  I strongly recommend that the Minister divert funds into the provision of respite care.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>I support this motion. Over the years people have been classified into specific groups according to particular characteristics which are seen to make them different from those whom society considers normal.  Labels define individuals in such a way as to promote the denial of their equal rights within society.  One has only to reflect on the perceptions and conduct aroused by terms such as race, religion and sex to realise the restrictions and abuse imposed on so-called minority groups categorised by these labels.  While labels and classifications have been arrived at for clinical and administrative convenience they can be psychologically detrimental to the individual to whom they are attached. The same difficulties apply to the current use of the term &ldquo;mental handicap&rdquo; which is used to identify people who demonstrate varying degrees of learning difficulties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We must be sensitive to the usage of demeaning terms and behaviours and we must be pro-active on the issue of negative labelling.  I recognise that changing or removing labels would be effective only if it were done in conjunction with <Col N="872" /> professionals acting as advocates on behalf of the individuals concerned.  It behoves us as legislators to be supportive of positive attitudes already evident within some services that care for those with specific learning needs.  I refer to one of the pioneers in this area namely the Hospitaller Order of St. John of God who incidentially introduced a magnificent document on this area entitled <i>Enriching Lives.</i>  It is a policy statement and I would be glad to make it available to the Minister and any Member of the House.</P>
    <P>When we speak about those with specific learning needs I think we should be aware of the current Irish situation some of which has been outlined by the Minister. Approximately 13,000 people in this country have been classified as having a moderate, severe or profound degree of intellectual disability.  This represents 3.6 per 1,000 of the population; over 11,000 are in receipt of services on a day or residential basis and, approximately 8,000 children receive special education. Expenditure by the Department of Health on services to this population is in excess of £200 million.  This figure includes expenditure on those with learning difficulties in psychiatric hospitals and the payment of cash allowances and approximately £70 million is spent by the Department of Education on special education.</P>
    <P>The benefits of modern health care mean that people with specific learning needs can enjoy a near normal life span. Consequently, more people will require services over a longer time and it is incumbent upon us to provide the best possible services for them from birth to old age.</P>
    <P>In Irish society today a number of issues will influence the lives of individuals who attend services for those with specific learning needs.  Of particular significance is the continuing development of cosmopolitan and urbanised society, the emergence of an increasingly demanding environment and the changing patterns of employment.  It is becoming more difficult for some people to keep <Col N="873" /> pace with modern life which requires greater adaptability.  The challenge facing those who avail of services is the increasing complexity of modern society. Future society, it seems, will be dominated by large cities and sprawling suburbs and such environments are not generally conducive to community participation. Since people have to cope with more personal and social issues, it seems to be difficult for them to appreciate and tolerate those who are less able.</P>
    <P>It is our challenge to ensure that the individuals we serve are not only in the community but of the community.  We must support the development of localised, small, decentralised programmes that promote the concept of full integration. This can only be achieved by co-operation between the service caring for those with specific learning needs and their parents as was stressed by the Minister and other speakers, and also in association with other agencies within the State.  We should be attempting to provide services that are co-ordinated, coherent, continuous and comprehensive.</P>
    <P>I am glad that paragraph (c) of the motion calls for parents to be fully involved in the planning process and I believe that this must start at the earliest possible time.  The principal need of parents of young children is for clear information and support when it has been established that the child is at risk or is demonstrating developmental delays. Intervention for young children should aim to minimise the direct effects of their condition and to prevent the appearance of indirect effects.</P>
    <P>The preferred early services model should be in a home-based or in a local community-based setting.  The many variables necessary to deliver a home-based programme, such as cost factors, frequency of home visits and professional time, have to be considered in providing a comprehensive effective early services programme.  I believe that a comprehensive model for early services should be composed of the following elements; family input and participation, family support and information, a multi-disciplinary <Col N="874" /> team approach, optional programme settings in accordance with the concept of natural environments, developmental assessment and individual programme planning and programme evaluation.</P>
    <P>Many of our services are day services and in the past they tended to be based at a central location that served a large catchment area.  However, in keeping with the emphasis on improving the quality of life and incorporating the principles of normalisation future planning must provide for the development of small units situated as close as possible to the individual's home.</P>
    <P>For the individual to become fully integrated within the community, the following at a minimum must be in place: positive community attitudes, appropriately qualified staff, a variety of day services, including domicilary services, and family support and education.  While I am cognisant of the national policy of providing education to students with specific learning needs in special national schools supported by the Department of Education, I believe the time may have arrived when more can be done to bring the education of some or most students with specific learning needs back into the standard education system.  At present, while specific education and remedial education programmes are provided within the standard education system, some children are channelled along a road a separation to special pre-schools, special primary or post-primary schools and special vocational training centres. While we recognise that some students have special needs which necessitate their attendance at special schools, I believe we should be promoting the idea of incorporating levels of community based instruction, that is, skills should be learned and practised in real settings, partial main streaming should be pursued and flexible creative learning opportunities should be provided.</P>
    <P>With regard to training and employment, I believe that a new and radical approach is required in the planning and provision of programmes for the training and employment of individuals with specific <Col N="875" /> learning needs and that the traditional single-purpose workshop training centre may now be outdated.  I realise there is a severe shortage of vocational training and of employment opportunities for individuals with specific learning needs.  However, the emerging training and employment services should include clusters of small localised enterprise schemes to provide a variety of training and employment opportunities. These opportunities should concentrate on providing marketable labour intensive services to the local community.  As a result, training will be consolidated and skills will be developed relevant to open employment markets.</P>
    <P>At the same time, the individual's quality of life should be kept in focus. Individuals should be placed on programmes appropriate to their abilities and, in line with the concept of normalisation, be provided with work opportunities and given a just monetary reward.</P>
    <P>It is recognised that there is urgent need for development in training and employment and that additional resources will be needed to enable more enterprise schemes to be established. There has been some move in this direction. In the Hospitaller Order of St. John of God the experience of a number of enterprise type schemes have been very positive.  The endeavours of new voluntary groups to provide work, training and employment opportunities should also be supported.</P>
    <P>The motion also states that people with a mental handicap, or as I prefer people with specific learning needs, have a right to residential care.  Within the last decade new concepts based on the principles of normalisation and quality of life have been developed.  In upholding the concept of community-based living we should recognise the right of individuals to participate in choosing their own living arrangements.  With the growth of community-based services, the trend towards maintaining individuals within the home setting and the gradual transfer of individuals from large residential services to <Col N="876" /> small community residences, a changing role is emerging for the traditional residential centre.</P>
    <P>While favouring various options of community based living arrangements, it will be necessary nevertheless to update and make accessible residential centres for the purpose of providing necessary services for individuals with significant needs including: an aging population with significant special needs; the individual who, in addition to severe profound learning disabilities, has a serious medical condition or a major physical disability; the individual who, in addition to severe learning disabilities, demonstrates challenging behaviour and or mental illness; and in addition to the preceding specialist groups, I believe there is a need to provide respite services to families who are maintaining a son or daughter at home.</P>
    <P>I welcome the call on the Government to ensure that the highest possible contribution is made in the next round of the European Community Structural Funds, and I note what the Minister has said in this regard.  If any funds are available they should be for the elaboration and enhancement of the rights of those with specific learning needs.  We sometimes tend to forget that these rights include the involvement of individuals with specific learning needs in local social and recreational activities.  Benefits resulting from such participation include increased contact with members of the community, the opportunity to develop friendships, to develop social networks, to learn new skills and to achieve new goals, all of which contribute to a positive self-esteem.</P>
    <P>We should constantly remind ourselves that only a few short years ago, indeed until recently, many people with specific learning needs were referred to in terrible terms &mdash; as imbeciles and so on &mdash; and locked away in the back wards of institutions. Even today there are people, including some eminent professors, in some of our hallowed institutions of medicine and education &mdash; who would advocate killing these people before they were born but, thank God, we have <Col N="877" /> moved on from that.  Those who advocate such policies have never witnessed the love of parents for a special child.  Often times our aspirations are seen as ideals, however, I am always reminded of the words of Montaigne who said, ideals are like the stars, we never reach them but like the mariners of the sea we chart our course by them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and congratulate him on his appointment.</P>
      <P>I am disappointed at the level of contribution in the area of mental handicap over the years.  Those involved in providing mental handicap services were under the impression that the £8 million mentioned by the Minister was the contribution for 1993.  From the Minister's statement that amount is £14 million &mdash; £6 million, as in the previous year, plus an additional £8 million.  There is confusion with regard to this allocation among those who work with the mentally handicapped. Confusion also arises from the fact that of the £8 million, £1.5 million was to be directed towards the physically handicapped.  In fact, I understand from the Minister's contribution that this is not now the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHowlin" hpid="Mr. Howlin Mr. Howlin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howlin</NameTxt>
      <P>That money would be provided in addition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>Therefore £14 million in full is going to services for the mentally handicapped in 1993.  For the record, the Minister has just confirmed this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHowlin" hpid="Mr. Howlin Mr. Howlin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howlin</NameTxt>
      <P>You are underfunding it by £500,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>We have found an extra £500,000 since we started.  We are going well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>In 1990, the then Minister agreed to introduce the Report of the Review Group on Mental Handicap Services, <i>Needs and Abilities:</i> A Policy for the Intellectually Disabled at a cost of £50 million over five years.  That would be a contribution of £10 million on average <Col N="878" /> per year.  When the <i>Programme for Economic and Social Progress</i> negotiations were completed this was changed to a period of seven years and it was decided to pay or to contribute on average £7 million per year.  In the first year, 1990, £1 million was contributed by Government; in 1991, £2 million and in 1992, £6 million.  That is a total of £9 million where contributions were expected to exceed £20 million.  The Minister's contribution of £8 million will bring the total to £22.5 million while the agreement provides for a full contribution at this stage of around £30 million. That is the degree of underfunding on the agreement.</P>
      <P>The motion talks of an integrated plan to introduce the report, <i>Needs and Abilities.</i> In fact, this report and its recommendations form an integrated plan making further planning unnecessary. Therefore the part of the motion which states that it is going to bring forward an integrated plan is irrelevant.  The plan is there to be introduced and, indeed has been partially introduced at this stage.</P>
      <P>I believe that this report is now out of date.  It caters for 1,600 places, a figure which on the Minister's own submission is out of date.  I understand that in the Eastern Health Board area alone, 1,000 mentally handicapped people are awaiting a service and 362 in the mid-west. In just two health board areas this amounts to 1,362 people.  The report, <i>Needs and Abilities,</i> caters for just 1,600 people throughout all the health board areas.  The reason why the report figure is now outdated is that when the report was compiled, the waiting list in the Eastern Health Board area, was used as a criterion for determining the numbers of people who would require services nationwide and was generalised for the country.  However, now that the full figures are available, anticipated needs are much greater and the £50 million envisaged in the report is insufficient. A figure far in excess of £50 million is required to achieve the objectives set out in this report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>At the moment there are 362 people in the Mid-Western Health Board area <Col N="879" /> who require and who are not in receipt of residential or day care services.  The Minister in his speech proposed to provide 270 places for the country.  On any evaluation, that figure is totally inadequate to solve the problem.  Mr. Martin Duffy the programme manager in charge of services in the mid-west &mdash; Senator O'Sullivan and I are members of that health board and have spoken on the issue of services at health board level &mdash; has stated that £6.695 million is required to deal with immediate needs in this health board area alone before any programme whatsoever is introduced.  I accept that in the mid-west the problem may be more acute than in other areas but let us treat it as an example.  The £7 million required immediately by the Mid-Western Health Board is half of the 1993 allocation for the whole country.  In 1992 this health board received £275,000.  A <i>pro rata</i> allocation in 1993 would be approximately £500,000 or £600,000, sufficient to meet just 10 per cent of immediate needs.  I do not want to play politics with this serious and sensitive issue. However, I want to point out the inadequacy of the present contribution and to urge the Government to provide more moneys.</P>
    <P>The figure of £600,000 which we expect on a <i>pro rata</i> basis in 1993 will not provide the respite care required for the mid-west area.  On a political point, the Labour Party in its document for Government guaranteed, following discussions with the Mid-Western Health Board and Mr. Gerard South of the Friends of the Mentally Handicapped, that £25 million would be invested in services for the mentally handicapped in 1993.  It is disappointing that this guarantee has not been honoured.</P>
    <P>I agree with the sentiments expressed regarding the need to assist those who care for the mentally handicapped.  I congratulate the voluntary organisations who work so diligently in this area.  I was approached lately by the Sisters of Charity in Lisnagry regarding the provisions of houses for persons with mental handicap and consideration is being given <Col N="880" /> to applying to the voluntary housing scheme for funds.  A similar application has been made in Ballina and Limerick County Council are also hopeful that funds will be made available from that scheme.  Perhaps the Minister could encourage his Department officials to consider this application favourably.  As Senators Farrell and Lydon have said, people with a mental handicap deserve to be treated as full citizens.  As prospective tenants of houses surely they too, are eligible for funding under the voluntary housing scheme?</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCalnan" hpid="Mr. Calnan Mr. Calnan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calnan</NameTxt>
      <P>Unfortunately, the Minister is not here now but in his absence I want to compliment him on his responses to the motion set down by the Labour Party.  I know we have support from all sides of the House, despite what Senator Neville said a few minutes ago regarding figures, because I know that if the Minister, Deputy Howlin could obtain an extra £88.5 million instead of £8.5 million he could use it to provide services for the mentally handicapped.</P>
      <P>We are talking about a very complex and sensitive issue because, for too long in this Christian country, mental handicap was hidden, it was something of which to be ashamed.  Thankfully, those dark days are over and we can now face a problem of this nature openly.</P>
      <P>A physical handicap is a problem in itself but, coupled with a mental handicap, it causes dreadful difficulty for the person involved and the family.  In the past, a family with a handicapped child &mdash; especially a severe mental handicap &mdash; was tied down for life looking after that person.  This applied particularly to the mother of these children.  As Senator Henry said, where mental handicap especially severe handicap, exists very often there is associated physical handicap. Caring for people with a mental handicap was often a 24 hour, 365 days a year responsibility for parents or other members of the family.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am glad to hear from the Minister for Health, Deputy Howlin, that in addition to the 127 residential places and 37 respite care places, an extra 70 residential <Col N="881" /> places and only 200 day places will be provided this year.  These day and respite places interest me most because a family with a handicapped member benefits greatly when that person can go to a different environment for training or change.  We need even more places.</P>
    <P>As a teacher I know that unless special services are provided in the school, a person with a mental handicap cannot be adequately taught.  I am not talking about serious mental handicap but quite mild mental handicap; it needs specialised training to teach such a person.  We also need specialised equipment.  Recently I came across an instance of a young handicapped girl who required a special computer in primary school.  She is now leaving primary school to go to second level school and apparently the computer cannot be transferred from one school to the other.  We will have to try to acquire another computer in the post-primary school for her, otherwise she will not be able to continue her education.</P>
    <P>We also have to consider the effects of the ageing process.  When the parents of handicapped persons die, the handicapped children &mdash; now adults &mdash; are left on their own.  However, they need proper care and attention and must be accommodated in institutions.  Very often a handicap caused by an accident can create great difficulties for some people.  We need backup and training and finance has been allocated to provide a certain amount.</P>
    <P>The psychiatric hospital in Cork comprises grey and red brick sections.  In the past, if anybody went in there for treatment it meant the end of a normal life, if a person was in there for even a short time it carried a stigma for life. Thankfully, half that hospital is now closed and for sale, many of the former patients have returned to their own communities or been accommodated in smaller hospitals.  However, some people cannot integrate with the community after being locked up in institutions for many years and respite centres provide care in a proper and humane fashion.</P>
    <P>I thank the Minister for coming to the House and outlining the services which <Col N="882" /> he will provide.  The Minister, Deputy Howlin is very concerned about mental handicap.  I know that the extra £8.5 million allocated this year will be increased and that the targets set by the Labour Party for Government will be reached shortly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister of State, Deputy Stagg, is from Kildare so it is a particular pleasure to welcome him to the House.  I congratulate him on his appointment and wish him well.</P>
      <P>We all agree that persons with mental handicap have, over the years, been among the most neglected groups in our community.  They are still in many ways a very neglected group and I do not think any Government can be proud of its record over the years of funding and support for mental handicap.  I note that we began with the figure of £8 million which had increased to £8.5 million when the Minister spoke, which is welcome.  If we have that sort of progress over the next 24 hours we will do extremely well.</P>
      <P>The Minister indicated that an additional £8.5 million would be made available which is very welcome but it contrasts sharply with the money allocated in the budget to county enterprise partnership boards.  One would ask which of these two aspects of our national life is more important, the establishment of county enterprise partnership boards or the maintenance of a proper service for mental handicap?  There is no argument about it, the service to the mentally handicapped people is more important.</P>
      <P>The figure contrasts sharply with promises made during the election campaign by the Labour Party, that it would increase spending in this area by £25 million in 1993.  The Minister referred to the figure in the Programme for a Partnership Government and I am prepared to accept that this is a different figure.  Nevertheless, it is well short of the figure indicated to the electorate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senators asked how much of the £8.5 million is specifically for mental handicap and I am glad that the Minister indicated that the £1.5 million for physical disability <Col N="883" /> which I had thought would come out of the £8.5 million is additional to it.</P>
    <P>Will the Minister state how much of this figure will be allocated for staff, capital spending on workshops and hostels? Can it be broken down in a structured way?  The central planning committee of the Eastern Health Board has specified needs of £11.5 million in revenue and £10 million in capital to deal with the backlog in mental handicap services.</P>
    <P>People with a mental handicap were referred to at a meeting of KARE, the association of parents and friends of mentally handicapped people in Kildare, as &ldquo;daoine le Dia&rdquo;&mdash;God's people.  It is a very good description, they are indeed God's people.  They are fortunate people in many ways but they are unfortunate in others.  As they are unable to protest or lobby on their own behalf, they have often been forgotten and, without the excellent work of the parents and the voluntary bodies, their situation would be even worse.</P>
    <P>As the Minister is aware in County Kildare we have first hand experience of the wonderful work of the organisations for handicapped people, including KARE, the County Kildare association of parents and friends of handicaped people, Moore Abbey in Monasterevin, the St. John of God Brothers in Celbridge and the Camp Hill community outside Kilcullen.  Anybody who visits these establishments is struck by the degree of love &mdash; I use the word advisedly &mdash; and without it and the care which these organisations give to the mentally handicapped, the situation would be catastrophic.  The unfortunate aspect is that a great deal of their work goes into fund raising to keep afloat.  For instance, KARE over the past ten years has raised £1 million, a stupendous achievement in terms of dedication to the people they serve.</P>
    <P>Needs must be attended to as a matter of urgency.  Examples of these are facilities for people with behavioural problems and workshop space for people graduating from the educational system.  It <Col N="884" /> does not make sense to educate people and then lose them because they are unable to progress and develop their personalities. Will the Minister say if the unit at the St. John of God Hospital for people with severe behavioural problems will open in 1993?  There is also the problem of respite beds being used for other purposes because of a backlog in the system. It is necessary to have a backup system so that if people are bereaved and there is a need for temporary accommodation the necessary beds should be made available.</P>
    <P>Senator Henry spoke about the problem of the increased life expectancy of people with a mental handicap.  Elderly parents are very worried about what will happen to their children after they have passed on.  It is an area which needs a great deal of attention and sympathy.  It is causing serious concern at this stage and will probably become a growing concern.</P>
    <P>Regarding the aspect of the motion which deals with policy based on a recognition that people with a mental handicap have a right to education, training etc., when is it intended to honour the right to education for severe and profoundly handicapped people?  I welcome the Minister's assurance that he will press for a new way of looking at Structural Funds. From my discussions with people involved in the mental handicap area I know that they are most anxious that the EC Social Fund will allow for training for supported employment in addition to open employment.  The new programme should include assistance for capital spending, workshops and help in offsetting depreciation of buildings and special machinery.  I do not understand why that cannot be done and I am somewhat reassured by what the Minister said in that regard.</P>
    <P>We welcome the involvement of parents at all levels in planning and they are already heavily involved in the voluntary bodies.  This applies to the federation of the voluntary bodies in Kildare and the National Association for the Mentally Handicapped of Ireland.  As the Minister said there are representatives on the <Col N="885" /> regional committees and that is a good aspect.</P>
    <P>I am glad the Minister of State, Deputy Stagg, is here because I have a specific request.  Will he make more money available from his budget for the housing needs of persons with a mental handicap? I do not know if my next question relates to him or to the Minister for Equality and Law Reform but I appeal for an examination of the planning laws to prevent discrimination against people with mental handicap.  It should not be necessary for a group of people to seek a change of use if they wish to live in a house.  That is discrimination, it should not happen and a civilised society would not allow it to happen.  Communities have fears about mentally handicapped people coming to live in the locality. However, these fears are groundless because it will benefit society to have such people living locally.</P>
    <P>The Minister should also examine the way money is allocated through the Eastern Health Board.  One of the major problems is that voluntary organisations are forced to find money just to pay bank interest charges.  That is not very sensible.</P>
    <P>I support the implementation of the Needs and Abilities report and the introduction of a new mental health Bill.  Worries about service providers were raised by KARE earlier in the year relating to whether the Department of Health or the Department of Equality and Law Reform which has responsibility for services for people with a mental handicap.  The point is that the pressure on parents with children with a mental handicap is bad enough without the State adding to it. This must be the priority in all the State's efforts in this area.  We must ensure that the pressure is reduced, indeed eliminated, and that the energy of the parents is devoted to their children.</P>
    <P>The mentally handicapped are people of profound merit and can contribute significantly to our self esteem as a society. They reflect our behaviour as a society and the place for them, if it can be done, is in the community.  I welcome the Minister's commitment in that respect.  One of the most inspiring events I attended <Col N="886" /> last year was the presentation ceremony to people who had come back from the Special Olympics.  They received their medals from Michael Carruth and the enthusiasm of those young people for the event and the affection they had for Michael Carruth was inspiring.  It should be repeated all over the country and, therefore, I have pleasure in supporting the motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not delay the House but I would like to make a few points in regard to the motion.  I support it and I am glad that it has been brought forward to an early date so that the Minister, the Minister of State and the Government will know that people need more help, institutionalised and community based.  There is a growing need for funding and I welcome the additional allocation in the Programme for a Partnership Government towards this extremely worthy cause.</P>
      <P>In the past ten years the level of mental problems has become apparent as a result of big institutions closing or reducing their intake.  People with a mental handicap are living in the community.  I am sure if Members examined their areas they would agree that those people are capable, with a reasonable amount of help, of integrating quite well with the community.  For many years these people were kept in isolation from the community and the community was isolated from them and I am glad that has changed.</P>
      <P>It is also recognised, I have seen it at first hand, that a mental handicap does not mean people are incapable of playing a small part in the community if they have proper education, training and supervision. It is wonderful to see people who have been institutionalised for many years living in housing estates and taking care of themselves as a result of training programmes.  They are able to visit their local shops and are capable of doing to a large degree the things that so-called normal people in society can do.  I am seeking help from the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>An organisation called Grow, involved in community welfare in Ireland, may <Col N="887" /> be the missing link in our mental health network.  These people, who have gone through the trauma of mental illness and recovered are helping those who are suffering from mental illness or mental handicap.  They are better able to concentrate the minds of the people who have the handicap and give them the benefit of their experiences.</P>
    <P>Even if conventional resources, facilities and personnel were more readily available to tackle the daunting task of limiting the damage to those who are incapacitated.  One additional element would still be required, that is, the awareness and the commitment of the individual, strengthened and enhanced by interactive contact to achieve recovery, rehabilitation, reinforcement and prevention. Grow provides this element through its philosophy of personal growth.</P>
    <P>I have seen at first hand the great value of these projects on people who have developed through interaction on a one to one basis with people who have themselves suffered mental illness.  The Grow method is based on the conviction that habits, not diseases, make us ill and that learning together to change these habits can make us well.  This approach empowers sufferers to develop practical know-how for the rebuilding and transforming of disorganised, rebellious and tormented minds by rediscovering from experience a natural wholesome order in human living.</P>
    <P>It can be a profound experience to go into one of these Grow communities and see the development of people who were neglected in and rejected by society. Whether that development is in the arts or in education one can see the great joy that is given not only to the person with the handicap but to the person who passes on the knowledge in a caring and sharing way.</P>
    <P>The Grow community concept is one the Minister should look at carefully.  It is a group which was formed in Australia in 1957, and has expanded dramatically. From my experience of it in the southeast, it is a concept I would like to see <Col N="888" /> receiving funding for development.  A small amount of funding could be shared by groups who are caring, and who have the knowledge and motivation to share. This would be much less costly than caring arrangements provided by institutions or professional groups.  I am not suggesting that it is the only way forward but it is a way forward I would recommend.</P>
    <P>The concept of isolating people with a mental handicap is, thankfully, a thing of the past.  I am delighted that the large, old hospitals &mdash; and in many cases they were high-walled prisons &mdash; are fast disappearing. However, we have to be careful. I saw in a report from Wales yesterday that a man who had been institutionalised for many years was put into a small community of four or five people. On the first day he decided to have a bath but did not realise he had to check the temperature of the water.  The water was too hot and he died.  That can happen to any elderly person.  If people are taken out of the institutional environment they have been used to and go into a different environment, they need close supervision initially, but they can develop.</P>
    <P>Victor Hugo said nothing is so powerful as an idea whose time has come.  Institutionalisation is not just living in an anonymous and impersonal environment; it can also be a state of mind.  If the sentiments behind this motion are acted upon and if the money to implement an integrated plan in the report <i>Needs and Abilities</i> is forthcoming, I think this Government will help to create a more caring attitude and a better environment for people with mental handicap.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to share time with Senator Maloney.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald) Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Stagg, to the House.  It is appropriate that he take over this debate from the Minister for Health because it involves his portfolio in a real way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In his contribution Senator Dardis <Col N="889" /> made two points with which I agree. First, the idea that one has to seek a change of usage for a house to accommodate mentally handicapped fellow citizens is an abomination.  This situation arose in the housing estate where I live which is close to the COPE Foundation in Cork, a very sophisticated facility.  A house was bought and an application made for change of use.  A neighbour approached me and asked me to sign a petition protesting about the housing of four or five mentally handicapped people in our estate.  I was horrified but I understood the fears they were expressing about their cars, their gardens, their children not being able to play football and so on.  Two years on, these people are as much a part of our community as any of the other children.  It took a bit of getting used to but it was more than worth the effort; it was a valuable method of integration. This is an issue the Minister for Equality and Law Reform, Deputy Taylor, should examine; it is simply not justifiable in any circumstances.</P>
    <P>The second point Senator Dardis made related to housing allocation.  The Minister of State, Deputy Stagg, has special responsibility for providing houses for the citizens of Ireland.  We are talking about citizens of Ireland and I know that the Minister of State has a deep interest in this area; and I am sure, with the Minister for Health, he will do what he can to alleviate the problems associated with housing the mentally handicapped in the community.</P>
    <P>I was heartened by the attitude and support of Members of the Opposition. They received the motion in a generous way.  Some of their comments in relation to the Labour Party's commitment to provide £25 million for the mentally handicapped were valid political points but the reality is that in the present financial climate, with high unemployment and problems facing companies like Aer Lingus and Greencore, the provision of an extra £8.5 million to any area is a huge sum of money.  It is indicative that this Government which appointed the first Minister for Equality should decide to help a group where unjustified inequality <Col N="890" /> is rife and which does not have a political lobby.  In this country lobby groups are powerful and have voting rights but the handicapped do not have a vote or a powerful media lobby.</P>
    <P>There are 25,000 people with a mental handicap, and mothers are trying to keep 40 year olds at home.  It seemed to this Government that if there were extra resources this is where they should go.  I am glad that in addition to the £6 million allocated in 1992, we now have £8.5 million to relieve some of the burden on those people.</P>
    <P>I have been involved with groups and I have friends with mentally handicapped children.  When I visit their home I leave with a feeling of awe as to how they cope and stay sane.  We should do everything we can to help them, to share their burden and to alleviate their suffering. On the birth of a Down's Syndrome baby there is shock and fear as to what will happen to that child as they grow older. The other question is what is going to happen to them when the parents die. Parents should know what is going to happen to their mentally handicapped children when they die.  If ever the State was in <i>loco parentis,</i> it is in this area. Nobody should have to wonder what is going to happen to their son or daughter when they die.  That question should be answered and the information should be available.  It should not be a question which adds to the fears and burdens these parents already carry.</P>
    <P>The extra money will do a number of things.  It will help to reduce that fear.  It will also confer rights on all citizens with a mental handicap.  This is not charity; these are their entitlements.  As far as this Government is concerned, I hope it is the beginning of a process, and at the end of four years, if we can point to this one area and say we have effected real, fundamental, long lasting change, I would leave this Chamber happy.</P>
    <P>Responsibility for the handicapped is spread over the Departments of the Environment, Education, Health and Finance.  For the information of the media and Members of the Opposition, the much criticised programme managers <Col N="891" /> structure set up by this Government will work, and is working, to co-ordinate a planned approach to deal with this area. In the empire building structure of Government &mdash; and all parties are guilty &mdash; nobody wants to surrender either a part of their budget or a part of their responsibility.  They defend what they have.  I believe that under this Government people will recognise that one Department can co-ordinate the services for the mentally handicapped more efficiently than when it is fragmented throughout the system.  It will also allow the parents of mentally handicapped people to ascertain their entitlements throughout a child's development by contacting one Department.  That is how it should be.  The programme managers will make a considerable contribution towards streamlining the service and making it accessible.  As Senator Dardis said, that is the civilised thing to do.</P>
    <P>Sweden has one of the best health services in Europe.  It always struck me as a measure of their commitment to their fellow citizens that they were prepared to impose substantial taxes on themselves to provide facilities to those who are less fortunate.  Their record in terms of the mentally and physically handicapped is second to none.  It is a country from which we could take lessons.  When allocating money to this sector, the old Irish element of begrudgery does not come into play.  Nobody begrudges money spent in this area.  It is evident that these people deserve help and giving it has a civilising influence on us.  We can learn more from the mentally handicapped than we can teach them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister, Deputy Howlin, for listening to the views expressed over what were two of the best hours I have spent in the Seanad.  I also thank the Minister of State, Deputy Stagg, who I am sure was enlightened by what he heard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My mind goes back to St. Patrick's Day in Letterkenny.  I was walking up the street to the platform before the parade started and I met two former inmates of <Col N="892" /> the psychiatric hospital where I used to work.  In the early 1980s they were assessed as mildly mentally handicapped and had spent 20 or 30 years in the psychiatric hospital at that stage.  They left the hospital in the mid-1980s having been locked up for many years.  They came across the street, shook hands with me and asked me to go for a bottle of stout; it was one of the most enjoyable bottles of stout I ever had.  That kind of improvement is the result of more money being spent on the mentally handicapped services.</P>
    <P>I thank the Senators who contributed and welcome their views; we all learned from them.  There was no mention in the document of the Special Olympics; it was mentioned by Senator Dardis.  A small number of people will go from this country to the Special Olympics in Greece.  I would like more money allocated to that area to allow more people to participate. Maybe the Minister, Deputy Stagg, could suggest to the Minister that this money could be allocated from the national lottery. To paraphrase the motto of the Special Olympics, ask not that I win but at least give me a chance to win.  If what we have done here today improves the environment for people with disability of any kind to exercise their rights as citizens, we will have done a good day's work.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Criminal Justice Bill, 1993:" RHead="Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Criminal Justice Bill, 1993: Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MarianMcGennis" hpid="Mrs. McGennis Mrs. McGennis">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGennis</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and congratulate him on the speed with which this legislation was introduced.  It is the first of a series of Bills the Minister intends to bring before both Houses so as to update and reform our criminal laws and this move will be welcomed by the community.  I look forward to new provisions especially concerning loitering and order in public <Col N="893" /> places, which could be included in the new legislation.</P>
      <P>When I spoke in the House about the Kilkenny incest case I said I hoped that we would not just talk about it for an hour and then forget it.  We have a responsibility to ensure we do not just pay lip service to the need for reforms highlighted by that case.  I am pleased that this Bill is the second to come before the House since then.  Unfortunately, this legislation will not affect judicial decisions already taken, but victims of past crimes may feel that their suffering has achieved something worthwhile.</P>
      <P>The Minister referred to the Criminal Law (Rape) Acts, 1981 and 1990 and said they provided anonymity for the victim. I wish to inform the Minister and Minister of State that the media are arguing for a judicial review, to allow them appeal cases held <i>in camera.</i>  This request does not apply solely to rape trials but to all cases held <i>in camera.</i>  Victims should be kept foremost in mind if any changes are proposed in this matter.</P>
      <P>I welcome changes whereby rape victims will be given copies of their statement and pre-trial consultations.  Many victims of rape and incest have felt that it was they who were on trial.  Female members of the garda are heavily involved in the prosecution of sex offenders and increased recruitment of women to the force means that more victims of sexual and violent assault will be dealt with sympathetically.  That is not too say that complainants would not have been dealt with sympathetically by male gardaí, but complainants who are usually femle would feel more at ease with a female garda.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the fact that this legislation is easy to interpret and understand and that it is victim-oriented.  At many public meetings I have attended fears have been expressed that victims are forgotten except as statistics; this legislation should restore public confidence in that regard. Faith in the criminal justice system had diminished to the point where victims felt there was no point in reporting a case <Col N="894" /> because little was done for them at the end of the day.</P>
    <P>Section 6 deals with payment of compensation and I have questions about this provision.  The courts are authorised to require offenders to pay compensation to their victims for any injury or loss.  Does this authorisation extend to parents of offenders as there have been calls to make parents accountable for the offences of their children?  This part of the legislation could cause the Minister difficulty since if the perpetrator of an offence is incapable of paying compensation to the victim, this provision is weakened.  Could the Minister say he intends to introduce a provision to make parents accountable for the crimes of their children?</P>
    <P>This legislation differs slightly from the Criminal Justice Bill, 1992 in that in this Bill compensation for victims will be secured not by the victim but by a third party.</P>
    <P>Section 8 deals with appeals of lenient sentences.  I echo the sentiments of the Minister that we comment regularly on the apparent leniency of sentences.  Probably this is so because such cases are highlighted in the media while the vast number of appropriate sentences go unnoticed.  I would not like to suggest that the Judiciary are not competent to carry out their work but this provision is welcome, particularly in the light of the Lavinia Kerwick and Kilkenny incest cases.  The Minister said this Bill will not affect sentences handed down before it comes into effect.  I hope past victims will feel that highlighting their cases has been worthwhile.</P>
    <P>The Minister referred to the judicial power to take guilty pleas and the offender's age and mental capacity into consideration.  I know of a case where a father was sentenced and family members asked that the sentence be reduced.  There is a case for harsh sentencing for serious crimes but there is also a case for taking family wishes into consideration.  I support the right of judges to impose varied sentences. However, sentences which deviate considerably from the norm may need to be looked at.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="895" /> It is correct that the time limit for bringing an appeal against the leniency of a sentence should be no more than 28 days.  Could the Minister say on whose advice would a review of sentence be taken?  Would the Director of Public Prosecutions do so or would the victim have to request the Director of Public Prosecutions to do so?  Who decides that the sentence has been too lenient, the DPP or the victim's family?  The Minister's approach to the legislation in section 2 in relation to unduly lenient sentencing is sensible.  It would be sad if the legal process was impeded by cases being taken because it was felt that a sentence of six months to a year was too short or <i>vice versa.</i>  Our laws should be sensibly drafted and enforceable.</P>
    <P>Section 5 states that an impact assessment should be carried out on the victim, which is long overdue.  It humanises our legislation by asking what has happened to the person since the crime was carried out.  It is ludicrous that environmental impact studies have been carried out in relation to planning matters and yet, at this late stage, that we are only considering victim impact.  We cannot comprehend the trauma experienced by the victims of crime and it is wrong for our system of justice to treat them in a cold, clinical way.  The victim support group will probably feel that section 5 is a timely and welcome development.</P>
    <P>Will the Minister explain how compensation will be dealt with in cases specifically referred to in this legislation? At present, the criminal courts can award compensation.  Most of the people engaged in loitering and public disorder in the capital city are minors and the Minister will probably deal with this in other legislation.  Although the thrust of the legislation in relation to compensation is good, will it be effective if a large number of problems, other than sexual abuse crimes which are specifically mentioned in this legislation, are created by minors?  I referred previously to parental responsibility.  Will there be an extension of the criminal justice system to make parents responsible for their children's <Col N="896" /> behaviour?  Gardaí have told me that in cases in which minors were involved, not alone did the parents not accept responsibility, they refused to go to the Garda station.  How can we ensure that victims feel their case is being taken seriously and that there is justice if minors are perpetrating the crime and parents will not stand by them in court? Will provision be made for compensation to be paid in instalments and, if so, by what mechanism will this be done?</P>
    <P>The change in the legislation which allows video recordings of evidence to be admissible at trial is welcome.  The Minister mentions that a technical amendment to the Criminal Procedure Act, 1967, may be necessary to remove any doubt as to whether a written deposition should also be taken in these cases. I urge the Minister to put the necessary technical amendments in place immediately because the use of video recordings would involve children and sexual abuse. It would be undesirable, indeed horrific, if having tried to make it as easy as possible for children and victims of sexual assault to make their case, we then insisted that they must make a written submission or deposition.  We must do everything possible to ensure that children are not subjected to this procedure. If technical amendments are needed, I urge the Minister to introduce them immediately.</P>
    <P>I welcome the increase from seven to 20 years' imprisonment as the maximum penalty for incest against a female person aged 15 years or over.  The Minister also highlights the fact that there is &mdash; and always has been &mdash; a provision for a judge to impose a maximum penalty of life imprisonment for an offence against female persons under the age of 15 years and a penalty of seven year's imprisonment if the offence is against a person over 15 years.  I also welcome the Minister's statement in relation to treatment for a female person who has been a victim of incest.  Will the Minister state whether this legislation covers such crimes against a male minor?  Sexual abuse is certainly not limited to women.  Cases which affected young women have been discussed <Col N="897" /> here in the past.  However, I am quite sure that this is not solely the domain of young women and girls.  Perhaps the Minister will reassure me that this part of the legislation covers crimes of sexual abuse against young boys as well as girls.</P>
    <P>The Minister said that the existing law would have allowed for greater sentencing but, as I said, this was not the position.  The unduly lenient sentences imposed in the two previous cases meant that the Minister had to take the initiative and ensure that the Judiciary knew that public opinion did not consider the sentencing appropriate.  It is not our function to criticise the Judiciary but if the Minister had not taken the initiative the general populace would have felt that they had been badly let down.  I am grateful that the Minister acted with such speed.</P>
    <P>The Minister also said that treatment programmes for prisoners should be considered. In my submission on the Kilkenny case I made the point that locking up offenders and regarding it as treatment is an inappropriate way to deal with the crime.  I also said that the Minister should give consideration to ensuring that treatment for victims should be on a statutory basis.  As this legislation is very victim oriented I ask the Minister to consider doing so.  There was a reference in both Houses to the fact that the rape crisis centres are severly underfunded.  A number of Senators said that although the situation in Dublin is bad, there are areas throughout the country which do not have a rape crisis centre.  I urge that treatment for both offender and victim should be on a statutory basis, then we will have put our money where our mouth is.</P>
    <P>Arbour Hill prison has a good reputation for providing services for its inmates and these services should be extended to all places of detention.  The Minister also said that she was looking at a number of constructive proposals which had been put forward in the Dáil.</P>
    <P>With regard to the suggestion that the perpetrator of the crime should not be allowed to return to the house, that can <Col N="898" /> be one of the conditions when granting bail.  All too often, in the cases with which I am familiar and probably generally, the victim is removed from the home.  I know this is done for his or her safety but the victim usually feels that he or she has done something wrong.  If not, why would he or she be removed from their family? The safety of the victim is paramount but, because of the way our legislation is enacted at present, the victim is removed and the perpetrator is left in the home. Hence, there is a belief that the victim is penalised.  I know the Minister is aware of this and that he will consider any suggestions which would ensure that the victim does not suffer any further and that the accused or convicted person is told to stay away from the victim's house.</P>
    <P>Unfortunately, when an accused person has served their sentence, nothing can be done to keep them from the home environment or, indeed, the environment where the crime took place.  I know of a woman and her children who left their home.  It was not a case of sexual abuse but one of violence and, despite the fact that the woman had secured a barring order, her husband regularly arrived back at the house.  The Garda could only contain the situation so, in frustration, she and her children left the home and went to England.  Our legislation must protect people who are exposed to violent crime.</P>
    <P>I welcome the fact that the legislation has been introduced so speedily.  When I mentioned at a recent public meeting on law and order that the Minister would introduce the Criminal Justice Bill, the cynics in the audience said that it would never happen.  The manner in which the Minister has approached her portfolio gives lie to that and the suggestion that crime is treated in a lenient fashion.  The Minister is adamant that law and order will be a priority and I look forward to further reforming legislation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WillieODea" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Justice (Mr. O'Dea) Willie O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Justice (Mr. O'Dea)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Senators for their constructive contributions.  A number of technical points have been raised.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="899" /> I will deal with the legal points raised by Senator McGennis first.  The Senator asked about the circumstances in which parents must pay compensation for crimes perpetrated by their children.  In section 6 of this Bill the court will be enabled to grant a compensation order against the parents or guardians of children who have committed a crime in the same circumstances as the courts can now order parents or guardians to pay compensation for crimes perpetrated by their children; that is governed by section 99 of the Children Act, 1908.  It makes it mandatory for the court to order the parent or guardian to pay compensation when the child is under 15 years.  It gives the court a discretion to order the parent or guardian to pay compensation where the child is aged between 15 and 17 years.</P>
    <P>Unfortunately, there are severe legal constraints on the court.  It must be established, for example, that the parent in some way assisted in the commission of the offence.  Due to that provision and the inadequacy of the fines which can be imposed, that discretion has not been generally used.  In 1982 child care legislation in the UK was updated and a more flexible formula was used.  We will look at that formula and at the experience in the UK since the change in 1982 in the context of the Juvenile Justice Bill.</P>
    <P>The Senator asked in what circumstances or on whose advice would the DPP decide to appeal a sentence which he considers over-lenient.  The DPP will be advised by his prosecution team who will give him a report on the case and he will decide, on the basis of that report, whether he should look for the various papers, which he is entitled to get from the court registrar under this legislation. There is nothing in the legislation or in law to stop the victim communicating directly with the DPP.</P>
    <P>The Senator also asked if compensation can be paid in instalments. Section 6 (6) of the legislation provides that compensation can be paid in instalments. The compensation section of the legislation is taken directly from the Criminal Damage Act, 1991 &mdash; I participated, <Col N="900" /> as a backbencher, in the debate on Committee Stage of that Act. It provided that compensation can be granted by the courts in criminal cases to victims who have suffered damage to their property.  We are extending it to enable victims who have suffered personal injury or loss to be compensated. The compensation can be paid in instalments. The same provisions apply to cases of incest against males as apply to such cases against females.</P>
    <P>I thank Senators for their contributions and I appreciate the constructive approach taken.  I am pleased there is general agreement on the need for this Bill and the need to make the criminal justice system more victim oriented. Senator Crowley highlighted the problems facing victims of crime.  Senator Henry, Senator Honan and Senator Cotter raised the question of mandatory reporting of incest and child abuse cases. This issue was raised in the Law Reform Commission report on child sexual abuse.  The question of funding for the rape crisis centres also arose.  Both matters are dealt with by the Minister for Health, and I shall communicate the views of the House to him.  This year the Minister announced a 90 per cent increase on last year's grant for the rape crisis centres and, while we may be starting from a low base, it is not a bad start.</P>
    <P>Senator Gallagher raised a number of detailed technical points in the Bill.  She asked about section 3 (3).  Subsection (3) provides that the Act will not apply to sentences imposed on persons convicted before the Act comes into operation.  The Act will come into operation one month after it has been passed; that is provided in section 14 (2).  If we allow this to apply retrospectively or if we allowed it to apply to people who had been sentenced before the Act came into operation, that would certainly be unconstitutional.  There is a constitutional provision against retrospection in criminal legislation and one could hardly think of a better example of criminal legislation than giving the prosecution the right to appeal against leniency of sentence.  Senator O'Toole indicated his intention to put down such <Col N="901" /> an amendment but that amendment will be opposed because we cannot allow the Oireachtas to pass legislation which will be struck down by the courts.  That would be most irresponsible.</P>
    <P>The words in the subsection, &ldquo;on persons convicted&rdquo;, ensures that the Bill does not cover cases where people are convicted before the Bill comes into force.  The reason for the change in terminology was that there could be a case in which a person is convicted and the judge postpones sentence to await reports etc.  If a person is convicted on the day before the Act comes into force, from the point of view of the criminal justice system that case is complete; the sentence is postponed but the new legislation will not apply to that person.  It will only apply to convictions from the date the Bill comes into force, which will be one month after the Bill is passed.</P>
    <P>Senator Gallagher also asked if a convicted person would be entitled to legal aid in the case of an appeal.  Yes is the short answer.  Even if the case goes to the Supreme Court on a point of law the legal aid will continue into that court because the person has already been prosecuted through the courts.  However, if the prosecution authorities feel the sentence is too lenient and if they and the DPP decide to put this person through the further process of contesting the DPP's appeal to have the sentence increased, it is logical and right that that person should get legal aid.  Therefore, the answer to the Senator's question is yes.</P>
    <P>Senator Gallagher was also worried about a review by the Supreme Court of an acquittal.  I assure the Senator and the House there is nothing in this legislation to enable the DPP to ask the Supreme Court, the Court of Criminal Appeal or any other court to review an acquittal.</P>
    <P>Senator Gallagher also asked about the fact that a person who receives a 20 year sentence will normally serve longer than a person sentenced to life imprisonment. In some cases that has happened but it is very unusual.  There is no established norm as to the length of time a person with a life sentence will spend in custody. Each case is now reviewed by an independent <Col N="902" /> sentence review group who makes recommendations to the Minister having examined each case.  There is no foundation for the general statement that a person sentenced to a term of imprisonment for life will spend only eight years in custody.  A number of people with life sentences have spent considerably longer in prison.</P>
    <P>Senator Neville asked about the abolition of wigs and gowns to reduce the formalities facing victims giving evidence in our courts.  I agree with what the Senator said.  Wearing wigs and gowns has been abolished in certain family law cases.  The wearing of wigs and gowns by counsel is covered by the Rules of the Superior Court.  As a result of a debate in the Dáil on the Criminal Evidence Bill a year ago, I contacted the chairman of the Bar Council to ask him about the abolition of wigs and gowns.  He told me the Bar had set up a Dress Committee to consider this question and that that committee would be reporting to the annual general meeting of the Bar in that legal term.  That term started in October but I have heard not one word from the Bar Council, the Dress Committee, the registrar or chairman since.  I wish to thank my Limerick colleague, Senator Neville, for bringing this matter to my attention because I shall contact the chairman of the Bar Council tomorrow to tell him the Senator is most anxious about it.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Justice, Senator Roche and others expressed concern about the need to protect victims both before a trial takes place and after the convicted person is released.  This matter is being examined and, if appropriate, it will be dealt with in future legislation.  I listened carefully to what Senator Roche had to say about that and I agreed with him.</P>
    <P>Senator Bohan made a number of suggestions for improving the existing criminal justice system.  I will give careful consideration to these matters.  The Senator mentioned the courts have power to impose consecutive sentences for offences committed by a person on <Col N="903" /> bail.  Bail is a subject for another debate and I will not discuss it now.</P>
    <P>Senator Roche asked how the review process for sentence will be initiated.  I have already said in reply to Senator McGennis that the DPP will get a report from his prosecuting team.  He will decide on the basis of that report.  For the benefit of Senator Roche and other Senators who raised this, we have been in contact with the DPP about this issue and he feels he will be able to handle it adequately. There is nothing to stop the victim communicating directly with the DPP about this.  Under section 6 of the Prosecution of Offences Act, 1974, certain communications with the DPP are prohibited but this does not fall within the ambit of that section so there is nothing to stop the victim communicating directly with the DPP.  The victim can also communicate with the DPP indirectly through his or her public representative or any other representative.  Senator Roche also asked about reviewing the operation of the Bill. This area will be kept under constant review.</P>
    <P>Senator Norris raised the question of sentencing policy whereas Senator Enright raised the more specific point that the DPP should have guidelines on sentencing.  I would like to announce to the House that the long awaited Law Reform Commission Consultation Paper on Sentencing is expected to be published tomorrow and we look forward to it with great interest.  The commission paper will no doubt address a number of issues arising from the debate on this Bill and I look forward to hearing the views of the Law Reform Commission.</P>
    <P>This is an area where there is considerable scope for development. Senators may wonder why we brought this legislation in without benefit of this consultation paper.  We thought it would be published sooner.  Despite repeated signals that it would appear, it did not. In the meantime, the Lavinia Kerwick case came up, the general election delayed us further, then there was the Kilkenny case and I understand there are a number of serious cases of this sort in <Col N="904" /> the pipeline.  We thought it best to move ahead.  The report to be published tomorrow will be most interesting and it may require further changes here but it would be better to put this Bill on the Statute Book so that any sentences handed down in cases about to come before the courts can be reviewed if necessary.</P>
    <P>Senator Norris asked about a mechanism to review sentences that might be too harsh.  I do not understand what he was talking about.  The existing appeal system allows one to appeal in such a case.  The reason for the relevant section of this Bill is that there was no mechanism for the prosecution to appeal where the sentence is too lenient.  Senator Norris may be confusing this with the lack of a legal mechanism to bring a case back before the courts when the judicial process has been exhausted, such as there is in the United Kingdom.  Senators will be aware that a commission was set up under the chairmanship of Judge Frank Martin which made recommendations in that regard.  I assure the Seanad we will be moving ahead shortly to bring in legislation based on the Martin commission report.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Toole asked about making the legislation retrospective.  That would be unconstitutional and I have no intention of having any part of this legislation struck down because that would bring us back to square one.  He also asked whether the suicide rate in Irish prisons is higher than other European countries. I do not have the appropriate figures or statistics here but I undertake to get in touch with him.</P>
    <P>Senator Enright was worried about the 28 day period allowed to the DPP to seek a review of a sentence.  We have been in touch with the DPP about this and he is satisfied that the 28 day period is adequate.  I do not want to increase the period.  In many cases, such as the Lavinia Kerwick case, a non-custodial sentence is imposed.  If a person gets a non-custodial sentence, is it fair or just that he be waiting a long time to see if the DPP will seek to have a custodial sentence imposed on him?  I think 28 days strikes the right balance, although it is a short <Col N="905" /> period.  The important thing is that the DPP, the person charged with taking the appeal, is satisfied that he will be able to do his business within the 28 day period.</P>
    <P>Senator Ormonde asked about appeals from the Central Criminal Court to the Supreme Court.  The Bill only deals with the right of appeal of the DPP against unduly lenient sentences.  It provides a statutory avenue of appeal to the Court of Criminal Appeal.  We can all rest assured the DPP is not going to ignore the provisions of this Bill and attempt a direct appeal to the Supreme Court on a question of sentencing.  Direct appeal to the Supreme Court by a convicted person raises issues outside the scope of this Bill but this issue will be tackled in other criminal justice legislation to be introduced shortly.</P>
    <P>Senator Ormonde also raised a question about section 3 (1) of the Bill.  This provision follows the existing law as set out in section 29 of the Courts of Justice Act, 1924 and section 3 of the Prosecution of Offences Act, 1974.  Under these sections, those who may grant a certificate allowing an appeal on a point of law from the Court of Criminal Appeal to the Supreme Court are the Court of Criminal Appeal itself, the Attorney General or the Director of Public Prosecutions. I also assure Senator Ormonde we will be looking at how to improve coordination among the different services dealing with victims and the rehabilitation of offenders.</P>
    <P>Some Senators were concerned to ensure the victims views were adequately taken into account by the court.  Senator Cotter talked about a consultation process between the judge and the victim on the sentence to be imposed.  While I do not know whether this would be the best approach, I would like to make the following points.  First, the Bill obliges the court to take into account the effect on the victim in determining the sentence. Second, under the Bill the victim has the right to address the Court in this issue if he or she so wishes.  This should ensure the victim's views are fully taken into account.  The question of independent legal representation was looked at by the <Col N="906" /> Law Reform Commission, and more recently by the Second Commission on the Status of Women, and both have come out strongly against it and, in my view, for very good reasons.  The latest recommendations of that commission which have implications for the Department of Justice, are being examined and some have already been implemented.</P>
    <P>I have covered the main points in this Bill and do not think I missed any points raised.  Committee Stage is tomorrow from 4 p.m. to 9 p.m. when no doubt we will have further, more detailed, discussion on some of the technical aspects of this legislation and when we will deal with amendments put down.  I thank Senators from all sides for their constructive and helpful approach.  My approach to amendments will not be partisan or dogmatic.  My objective is to achieve the best legislation and I know that I will have Senators' co-operation.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage ordered for Thursday, 25 March 1993.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Sitting suspended at 8.45 p.m. and resumed at 8.50 p.m.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. -" RHead="County Donegal Water Supply">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - County Donegal Water Supply.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, I thank you for allowing this motion and I thank the Minister for attending.  This Adjournment Matter relates to an area outside Letterkenny nicknamed the Lagan Desert due to the fact that it does not have any piped water supply.  At the moment there are 2,500 people living there.  Some 29 years ago Donegal County Council first promised a running water supply, yet to date nothing has happened to relieve the water problem in the Manorcunningham and St. Johnstown areas.  In warm weather the school's well water dries up and the county council has to send in tankers to supply water for toilets and wash-hand basins in the school.  It is disgraceful that <Col N="907" /> people should have to endure such conditions.</P>
      <P>It is envisged that the Lough Mourne scheme will solve the Lagan Desert problem but the scheme requires funding of approximately £5 million by current estimates. The regional plan for the EC Cohesion Fund over the next four to five years includes provision for this scheme but there is no indication as to whether it will be undertaken.  I ask that this issue be given priority as it is a heartbreaking problem for residents of the area. Despite complaining and demonstrating for a number of years, they seem to have been ignored disgracefully by everyone.</P>
      <P>At the moment the people of Manorcunningham, living on two fairly large housing estates, get their running water from a stream outside the town.  On numerous occasions the water has been cut off, preventing people from using water for domestic and home heating purposes.  On one occasion four or five months ago the stream was polluted by silage effluent.  The water supply was cut off immediately leaving the people high and dry on a winter's evening and it remained off until the water was declared usable again.  The water is brown in colour and people are advised to boil it before use.  I ask the Minister to ensure that the Lough Mourne scheme is started as a matter of priority to provide water for people living in the area known as the Lagan Desert.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrowne2" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Browne, Wexford) Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Browne, Wexford)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Browne,</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>Wexford</i>): I thank Senator Maloney for raising this particular problem.  Water and sewerage infrastructure in Donegal has benefited under the public capital programme and under the existing round of Structural Funds.  Over £10.5 million has been allocated to the county in the past few years and a number of important schemes have been completed under the current water and sanitary services operational programme.  These include phase four of the Buncrana sewerage scheme, costing £3.5 million designed to abate pollution in Buncrana Bay, Ballyshannon-Bundoran <Col N="908" /> water supply interlink, costing £42.2 million; Cranford-Carrigart water supply scheme, costing £0.23 million; the Rosses water supply scheme, costing £0.65 million and Cornamona reservoir in Letterkenny, at a cost of £0.45 million.</P>
      <P>In addition, a major water supply scheme at Killybegs which is nearing completion at a cost of nearly £13 million involves the construction of two rock fill dams, treatment works, additional storage reservoirs and 4,743 metres of pipeline and is being grant-aided by the EC. The council is currently planning a water supply at Pollan Dam which would cater for the long-term industrial and domestic needs of Buncrana and its environs.  This very costly scheme will meet the water demands of Fruit of the Loom International, the largest industrial employer in the area.</P>
      <P>I am aware that there are water supply problems in the Lagan area of County Donegal.  To date the Lough Mourne regional water supply scheme trunk network has been laid to Milltown Cross, south of Raphoe town.  The design of the regional scheme provided for the further extension of the network to serve New-towncunningham, Manorcunningham and St. Johnston in the Lagan area.  The scheme involves the laying of 4,200 metres of water main and the construction of a reservoir at an estimated cost of £1.1 million.  However, the demand at Lough Mourne headworks now exceeds the capacity of the storage and treatment works.  Proposals to increase the improvement and treatment capacity form part of the next stage of development for which water rights are required.  The estimated cost of this proposal is £1.5 million.  My Department is currently awaiting the submission of contract documents from Donegal County Council to extend these headworks. I shall then be able to see more clearly the extent of the problem and how it can be resolved.  The question of Exchequer or EC funding does not arise at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. -" RHead="Inspection of Ferries">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Inspection of Ferries.</Title>
    <Col N="909" />
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>A Leas-Chathaoirligh, I welcome the Minister to the House and I thank him for the courtesy of attending to respond to my motion.</P>
      <P>At this stage the basic facts of the <i>Celtic Pride</i> ferry tragedy are very well known. The <i>Celtic Pride</i> was in operation last year on the Cork-Swansea ferry route. On the morning of 12 August two children, Catherine and James Tomlins, were found dead in their cabin just before the vessel arrived in Cork and last month the Department of the Marine published the report into the investigation of that tragedy.  From this it is clear beyond any doubt that the children were overcome by the toxic fumes from the ship's sewerage system which reached them through the toilet adjoining the cabin in which they slept.  This happened because, according to the report, the ship's sewerage system was badly designed and badly maintained. These deaths happened following repeated complaints by previous passengers about unpleasant smells and inefficient clearance of the flushing system on board ship.</P>
      <P>What happens next in regard to this case?  The investigation itself was excellent as far as it went and clearly its sole purpose was to establish the cause of the tragedy.  It has done this very clearly and my only quarrel with the report is that it took six months to complete and given the restricted nature of the investigation, six months seems an excessively long time to have to wait for a report.  However, the restricted nature of the investigation immediately highlights the need to go further.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We now know beyond all doubt what caused the deaths of those two children. What we do not know is, who is to blame? We need to know because we are talking about human lives.  These two innocent children were returning from a family summer holiday on the Continent.  Their deaths need not have happened; their deaths could have been foreseen.  In the chilling words of the Department's report, which leap out at us from the <Col N="910" /> pages, this was &ldquo;an accident waiting to happen&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>It appears wrong that the only function of the Department of the Marine in this matter is to ascertain the cause.  Not so long ago the British ferry, the <i>Herald of Free Enterprise</i> sank and there was a fullscale public inquiry which did not shrink from attributing blame.  If the Department of the Marine does not have the same powers should we not move quickly to ensure that it gets them?  Alternatively, if it has those powers, why were they not used in this case?  This was the immediate concern of the public.</P>
    <P>I stress that in seeking to attribute blame, people are not seeking retribution. The existence of a clear and effective mechanism for establishing blame is a very important part of the system for ensuring future safety on all our sea routes.  People who are responsible for the safety of passengers should be in no doubt whatever that they will be brought to account if they fail that trust, and they will be brought to account swiftly.</P>
    <P>Perhaps the Minister will have something to say about the progress of the Garda investigation into this matter, if indeed there is any progress to report at this time.  I hope he will not tell us that there are difficulties because of the clash of legal jurisdiction in this matter, and I certainly hope he will not say that it is up to the parents of the children to seek civil redress.  This is a matter of national importance and people affected by such a tragedy are entitled to feel that the State will protect and vindicate their personal interests.  However, even when our minds are put at rest about that aspect of this case there are further matters of imporance flowing from this investigation and from this report.</P>
    <P>What this tragedy has revealed is that there is an enormous gap in the regulations governing the safety of vessels at sea.  The sewerage system which caused the deaths of these children did not, and still does not, fall within the scope of the licensing system for ships.  This ship was certified as safe because the marine legislation does not cover the sewerage <Col N="911" /> system.  That fact will come as a profound shock to people who travel on ships because I am sure they thought they were better protected than that.  In this context I commend the action the Department took in the wake of the accident in immediately alerting the EC and the international maritime authorities to the need to include the sewerage system in the design and operation standards of all sea-going vessels.  I also commend the recommendations made in the report for further action in that area.</P>
    <P>While I commend that response, I have to say it is hardly adequate.  We are now shutting that stable door but other stable doors are still open.  We do not know yet what other accidents are waiting to happen.  Are we only to discover these hazards when tragedies happen such as that which befell the Tomlins children? Surely we cannot leave this matter there.</P>
    <P>I suggest the need &mdash; and I see it as highly urgent &mdash; to set up a system of regular inspection of ferries that would go beyond existing statutory inspections. That would be pro-active and comprehensive; pro-active in the sense that it would take the initiative to prevent accidents even of a type that had never happended before, and comprehensive in that it would go beyond the letter of the present law to cover any possibility of danger to passengers no matter what the source.  The aim of such a pro-active and comprehensive system of inspection should be to identify at the earliest possible stage and to eliminate all potential causes of tragic accidents.</P>
    <P>We owe it, first, to the memory of the Tomlins children to do so and second to the travelling public, who are entitled to expect the State to guard their interest effectively in such matters and third, we owe it to our tourism industry, which depends crucially on access routes to this island.  Irish tourism already suffers from the handicap that travel to Ireland is difficult and expensive for visitors and has no need of any shadow cast over the safety of the journey to Ireland.  These considerations oblige us to go that extra <Col N="912" /> mile and if this means leading the maritime world in matters of safety, so be it. There could hardly be a better reason to do so.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerryOSullivan" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. G. O'Sullivan) Gerry O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Marine (Mr. G. O'Sullivan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the courtesy extended to me by Senator Quinn when he raised this matter on the Adjournment.</P>
      <P>I would like to outline for the Senator the steps taken following this tragic occurrence and on foot of the Department's investigation.</P>
      <P>A preliminary examination of the vessel by marine surveyors of the Department immediately following the accident revealed that the vessel's sewerage system was the cause of the accident. Immediate modifications were effected and some days later the vessel was taken out of service to allow permanent technical modification to be carried out. These modifications involved, <i>inter alia</i>, the provision of two new permanent sewage vent pipes, the cleaning of all sewage tanks, modifications to the internal structure of the tanks and the fitting of new aeration systems to ensure a positive aerobic operation of the system.</P>
      <P>All ferry companies operating into Ireland were immediately requested to review and report on the sewage systems on their vessels in line with detailed guidelines and to review the operational procedures for crews in the detection of, and response to, smells and gasses.  The special meeting of the National Ferry Safety Committee, on which all the ferry companies are represented, was convened to review the accident and the lessons to be learned from it.  The ferry companies indicated that the sewage systems on their vessels were safe.  Subsequently, marine surveyors of the Department conducted a thorough examination of the sewage systems on the vessels. No major deficiencies or problems were identified.  No trace of lethal gas could be detected on any vessel.  The examination of sewage systems on board passenger ferries is now an ongoing feature of inspections carried out by the Department's marine surveyors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="913" /> We also took immediate action at international level by urgently requesting the International Maritime Organisation, last October, to introduce requirements for the standards of design, construction and the operation of sewage systems on ships and for periodic inspection of such systems.  The IMO accepted the need for standards in relation to the design and construction of sewage systems.  The matter is now being pursued through a specialist IMO sub-committee on ship design and equipment.  The Deputy Chief Surveyor of the Department of the Marine is taking the lead role at that forum in co-ordinating and drawing up the necessary requirements.  I went to London recently and met the secretary general of the IMO in order to emphasise to him the need for international regulation in this regard.  I am glad to say he assured me of his full support.  I would also like to put on the record the full support that we have got from the United States maritime organisation who fully backed the Irish stand on this issue.  The Department is also reinforcing safety and checking guidelines for sewage systems by a further detailed Marine Notice to all shipping interests.  Those are the specific measures taken on foot of the <i>Celtic Pride</i> tragedy.  In addition, ferries serving Irish ports are comprehensively and regularly inspected for compliance with a wide range of safety standards.  Irish registered passenger vessels undergo annual inspections for the renewal of their Passenger and Safety Certificates.  The vessels are required to be equipped, maintained and operated to the highest international standards and, in particular, to those laid down in the International Maritime Organisation's Safety of Life at Sea Convention. These standards are under constant review by the IMO and we will continue to press for further strengthening of standards both at EC and IMO level.</P>
    <P>Foreign registered passenger vessels operating from Irish ports are also inspected at least once a year to ensure compliance with all safety requirements, both domestic and international.  The International Agreement on Port State <Col N="914" /> Control, to which Ireland is a party, provide for regular inspections of all foreign registered vessels to ensure that ships comply with international safety standards.</P>
    <P>I am in full agreement with the Senator that when it comes to safety we have an obligation to go that extra mile and it is precisely for this reason that the National Ferry Safety Committee was set up.  This expert technical committee has the job of reviewing all aspects of safety procedures and standards regularly and critically and of advising on improvements.  The Ferry Users' Forum set up to deal with passenger complaints about safety adds a further important dimension to the review systems now in place and which are, may I point out, unique in international terms.</P>
    <P>The procedures and standards introduced following the <i>Celtic Pride</i> tragedy, together with those already in place, are designed to achieve the objective of identification and elimination of all potential causes of tragic accidents.  I can assure the Senator that I share his concerns to see this objective met.  All necessary additional measures at national level will be taken to reinforce international safety standards.</P>
    <P>Although six months may appear to have been a long time for a report when one considers that a report of this nature has to go back to the legal representatives of the other parties involved and given the nature of this tragedy it does not appear excessive.</P>
    <P>As Opposition spokesperson for the Marine in the last Dáil I considered it imperative that there would be no delay. When I was appointed Minister of State at the Department of the Marine the publication of that report was my first priority and I am glad to say it was published at the earliest opportunity.  I delivered it to the Tomlins family myself and I went to London to make sure that this report would get priority at the IMO.  It is now top of the agenda there for further discussion and regulation; regulation is the key word in this.</P>
    <P>At present the report is with the Garda authorities for their response.  It is not the function of the Department of the <Col N="915" /> Marine to take criminal action.  Another Department must look at the report and see whether criminal action is appropriate or whether new legislation is required.</P>
    <P>I welcome and share the Senator's concerns <Col N="916" /> and I would welcome any further assistance from him on marine matters.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 9.10 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 25 March 1993.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>