<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="7" Month="Apr" Year="1993" Vol="135" No="13" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 7 Aibreán 1993" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 7 April 1993" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1445" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Daly that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Enterprise and Employment to outline the number of EC programmes where funding is available for job creation and other employment related schemes, and if he has examined the present situation with a view to getting the maximum financial draw down, and the plans he has to make the programme more widely available throughout local communities.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Burke of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Health to outline if a kidney dialysis machine will be provided for Castlebar General Hospital, County Mayo.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Fahey of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Justice to address the concern of Galway city traders on the problems related to excessive alcohol consumption on city streets and to ensure acceptable behaviour in the city day and night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1446" /> I also received notice from Senator McDonagh of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The need for the Minister for Education to allocate funds for the proposed extension to Athenry vocational school.  County Galway, in order that the school will not have to turn away some first year students in September due to lack of space.</P>
    <P>I also received notice from Senator Cassidy of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The need for the Minister for Finance to accelerate the work programme at Fore Abbey, County Westmeath, and to improve facilities to cater for the increased number of visitors to this historic village.</P>
    <P>I also received notice from Senator Neville of the following matter:</P>
    <P>The need for the Minister for Education to ensure that the Stella Maris school in Foynes, County Limerick, continues as a second level institution after 1995 in view of the withdrawal of the religious community and the decision not to accept first year students from September 1993.</P>
    <P>I also received notice from Senator Farrelly of the following matter:</P>
    <P>If the Minister for Health intends to allocate sufficient funds in 1993 for new facilities at the outpatients clinic of Our Lady's Hospital, Navan, County Meath; and if work will commence on the upgrading of this hospital.</P>
    <P>I regard the matters raised by Senators Daly, Burke, Fahey, McDonagh, Cassidy, Neville and Farrelly as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected Senators Daly's and Burke's matters and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.  Senators Fahey, McDonagh, Cassidy, Neville and Farrelly may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Matters of Concern" RHead="to Members">
    <Title>Matters of Concern to Members.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have received <Col N="1447" /> notice of a two minute statement from Senator Kelly under Standing Order 29 (A) and it will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Items 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 and 19.  Item 6, the Roads Bill, 1991, Second Stage, will be taken until 6 p.m.  Item 19 will be taken from 6 p.m. to 8 p.m.  Items 1, 2, 3 and 4 are orders based on the Joint Services Committee, the Joint Committee on the Irish Language, the Joint Committee on Consolidation Bills and the Joint Committee on Standing Orders.  Item 5 relates to the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs.  This is an expediency motion.</P>
      <P>I would like to mention the retirement of two people who have given great service to this House in a friendly and courteous manner.  Mr. Paddy Crean has been here for over 20 years and Mr. Paddy Cullagh has been here for over 30 years. We wish them well in their retirement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I echo the sentiments of the Leader of the House in relation to the long-serving and distinguished members of staff who have been of great service to Members of the Seanad and the Dáil.</P>
      <P>At an early date, will the Leader of the House make time available for a debate or statements on primary education?  The Roads Bill was passed in the Dáil last night.  Bills should not be passed in one House and introduced in the other House the next day.  Members should be allowed time to consider a Bill, unless there is a need for haste.</P>
      <P>I am sure the Leader of the House welcomes the recent introduction and opening of Turf Club accounts.  Perhaps a debate could be arranged on this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee on Procedure and Privileges has postponed this afternoon's meeting.  The Leader of the House has given me an undertaking that the pressing matter of accommodation <Col N="1448" /> for the Independent Senators will not be delayed and that progress will be made over the next two days.</P>
      <P>We wish to be associated with the good wishes to Mr. Paddy Cullagh.  From a teacher's point of view he was always very popular with visiting school groups. Next September when there are a few extra all-Ireland tickets available, I hope they will not go in one direction irrespective of whether Tipperary is playing.</P>
      <P>Independent Senators have been asking for the establishment of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs.  Senator Norris has raised this matter on every second Order of Business for the past two years.  I would like to know when the Committe of Selection will be meeting in order to make the appointments to that committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>May I be associated with the good wishes to the members of staff who are retiring?</P>
      <P>I am unhappy about Item 5 being taken without debate because there are several elements in the motion which are worthy of debate.  I realise that it is an expediency motion and that there is a pressing need to establish this committee.  However, it is not satisfactory that consideration by the joint committee or a sub-committee on political and security issues relating to Northern Ireland should be held in private session.  That does not say much for open Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not relevant; I am sure the Leader will respond.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>With respect, it is relevant to the Order of Business as it is a matter worthy of debate in this House.  I would like an undertaking from the Leader that he will give time for such a debate in the near future, otherwise, it will be necessary to oppose the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the outrage expressed by the Seanad in relation to the Warrington bombings, it should be noted that today's memorial service for the victims, which will be attended by the President, will also be attended by a <Col N="1449" /> Member of this House, Senator Calnan. He is invited as chairman of Cork County Council who, I understand, have a twinning arrangement with Warrington.  It is important that the House note that the President, who is a former distinguished Member of this House and a current Member are attending on behalf of the Irish people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerryReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I ask Senator O'Sullivan through the Leader of the House if it is now official Labour Party policy that the British Government should notify their intention to withdraw from Northern Ireland?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not appropriate to ask questions of other Members. Senators should speak through the Chair to the Leader of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerryReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>To the Leader &mdash; excuse me for my ignorance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it is appropriate.  You are talking about policy.  I am concerned with the Order of Business for today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerryReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>We are talking about policy, a Chathaoirligh.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry Senator Reynolds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerryReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Foreign Affairs is the representative of both Houses of the Oireachtas and of this country&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not appropriate to the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerryReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;to Northern Ireland and a Labour Party Member has stated that Labour Party policy is&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not a matter for the Order of Business.  I ask you to accept my ruling.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is not in the Dáil now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1450" />
    <Speaker pid="GerryReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to know what is their policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You can query that on another date somewhere else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerryReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>How could I query it or have the matter raised?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly not on the Order of Business today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader if the Government intends to afford this House an opportunity to debate the attitude of the Government to the recent High Court decision on the use of angel dust?  The High Court ruled that the relevant ministerial order is unconstitutional as it is not backed by the necessary legislation. In view of the serious effects this High Court decison has on certain orders and legislation affecting industry, agriculture and so on, the House should be afforded an opportunity to debate it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You have asked the Leader to respond to your suggestion and I am sure he will.  I am not allowing a debate or a discussion on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>I intend to bow to your ruling.  I do not intend expanding further but owing to the profound effects on agriculture I ask the Leader if he could outline the Government's attitude and tell us if they intend appealing the decision or introducing new legislation?  What is their intention?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Again this is not a question time.  We are on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Mr. Sherlock Mr. Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with the other speakers in wishing Paddy Cullagh well. Much reference has been made to him as a tipster for racing, and it could be said in racing parlance that Paddy Cullagh was a stayer having given 52 years service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I oppose the Order of Business because of the proposal to decide Item 5 without debate.  The motion features the phrase &ldquo;the select committee shall&rdquo; repeatedly. <Col N="1451" /> In these circumstances and because we have waited for a committee on foreign affairs for so long, it should not be introduced without debate.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader of the House if it would be possible at some stage in the near future to discuss the growing difficulties arising from the problem of public liability.  The Law Reform Commission is examining the area but I am sure there are Members who share my view that some interim measure is necessary to deal with this problem.  I suggest that the &ldquo;no faults&rdquo; arrangements which exist in other member states could be considered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You are making a speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not making a speech. There was a question mark at the end of that sentence.  I will phrase the following as a question.  Would other Members also deprecate Senator Reynold's attempts to make political capital out of the Northern Ireland affair and out of the logic of Deputy Bree's excellent speech?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not on the Order of Business.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I expect you are rather sorry you did not call me earlier before these unruly Members were given their heads.  I have two matters to raise.  I welcome the establishment of a foreign affairs committee and I hope this is done as speedily as possible.  It would be useful if there were some provision for debate because there are matters about which questions could be raised.  It was in this House that the Minister gave a firm commitment about the establishment of a foreign affairs committee and yet this House is treated with a certain amount of discrimination: the committee will comprise five Members from this House and 25 from the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1452" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the Leader will respond positively.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>A number of us have concerns and would like to tease out some of the matters.  If that is not the usual procedure then I suppose it will not be possible.  In principle, I welcome the establishment of this committee and I am glad that we got the information today. Perhaps this could be followed up with some specific information &mdash; I am not doubting the Government's intentions&mdash; about a timetable for the introduction of a Bill reforming the law on homosexuality. I noticed in yesterday's newspaper that certain sections of the 1867 Act were activated in the Dublin courts in a case which involved sexual abuse.  It may be that this was the only instrument available but it is worrying that despite the Government's protestations, sections of an impugned Act are still being activated without reform.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Leader of the House if he intends to allow some time for a discussion on the economy.  We asked for this on a number of occasions in the past and no final decision has been made.  There are many economic issues affecting businesses at present and I would appreciate if time would be given in the near future.</P>
      <P>I support Senator Roche's request for discussion or new legislation in the area of public liability.  If there is a backlog in the Dáil we should be given the opportunity to discuss it in the Seanad first. Many people are in serious difficulties and there are signs up in certain areas of the country about liability and people not being responsible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the Leader will respond.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to be associated with the remarks about Paddy Cullagh. It is over 30 years since I first came in here with my father.  Paddy was always courteous to the family of Members.  I wish him well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1453" />
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms. O'Sullivan Ms. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of myself and my Labour colleagues, I wish Paddy Crean and Paddy Cullagh well in their retirement.  I regret Senator Reynolds chose to make political ground on the issue of Northern Ireland and I realise I am not to make a speech either.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Order of Business, please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerryReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, I am looking for a response and if the Senator does not want to give one she should sit down.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Can we deal with the Order of Business?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms. O'Sullivan Ms. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>We have already had a worthwhile discussion on Northern Ireland in the presence of the Tánaiste and I would like the tone of that discussion to continue.  I assure the Senator that all Labour Deputies and Senators fully support the Tánaiste and our party policy on the North.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillyKelleher" hpid="Mr. Kelleher Mr. Kelleher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelleher</NameTxt>
      <P>I am disappointed at the depths this debate has descended to in the past couple of minutes.  As I said last week, the issue of Yugoslavia must be at the top of the agenda and I ask the Leader to allocate time for a discussion on the matter.  Yugoslavia is less than three hours by plane from here and 15,000 people are, at present, being evacuated from their homes there.  Mass graves have been found.  I am not apportioning blame but this House must make its voice heard. I am a member of a Parliament of an independent country which is a member of the EC.  I consider the EC's inactivity deplorable&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree.  Well said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is making a speech.  I am sure the Leader will consider his request.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillyKelleher" hpid="Mr. Kelleher Mr. Kelleher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelleher</NameTxt>
      <P>This Chamber's silence <Col N="1454" /> indicates an acceptance of what is happening and I call on the Leader to provide time for this discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Leader of the House in the near future, provide time for a debate on the International Fund for Ireland.  This fund is contributed to by Americans, Canadians and by international bodies but it has not received the recognition it deserves.  This House should express its appreciation of the fund and recognise the valuable work being done by it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the Leader will take the request on board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Naughten Mr. Naughten">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Naughten</NameTxt>
      <P>I join the Leader of the House, the Leader of the Opposition and other Members in wishing Paddy Crean and Pat Cullagh good luck on their retirement.</P>
      <P>I support Senator Enright's call for a special discussion on the difficulties regarding EC directives and the use of angel dust.  I hope the Leader of the House will give time to discuss this problem and the future use of unnatural growth promoters.</P>
      <P>Finally, I ask the Leader of the House to allocate time to discuss the implications for the eight regional health boards of the statement by the Minister for Health that he was reviewing the hospital charges which were so unjustly imposed six weeks ago.  I am a member of a health board and if the charges are reduced the funding of health boards will be affected.  I would like to know how the Government intends to deal with this situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>I can tell Senator Cosgrave that there is no time limit to the debate on the Roads Bill, although that Bill was on the Order Paper of the other House before the last election and Members had a chance to read it.  I expect the Bill to be debated for many weeks in the Seanad as it is important legislation and all Members will have an opportunity to comment on it.  With regard to the Senator's request for a debate on the <Col N="1455" /> Irish Racing Board annual report, I welcome the report and I am sure the Whips will agree to a debate on it in the near future.</P>
      <P>Senator Dardis, Senator Sherlock, Senator Norris, Senator O'Toole and others commented on the foreign affairs committee and I am pleased it has been well welcomed by the House.  I assure the Senators that there will be a debate on the issue but not today.  The proposed date for the debate is 28 April when the motion is returned from the Dáil.  Senator O'Toole mentioned the Committee on Procedure and Privileges and I can assure him that will be dealt with through you, a Chathaoirligh and other members of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.</P>
      <P>Senator Enright and Senator Naughten raised the issue of angel dust and the implications of the High Court decision in a recent case.  Some of those issues have been referred to the Supreme Court.  The Cabinet approved the Animal Remedies Bill yesterday and it will be introduced after Easter.</P>
      <P>Senator Roche mentioned concerns about public liability.  The Whips will agree to a debate on that issue in the coming weeks.  With regard to Senator Norris' query about legislation on homosexuality, my understanding is that the Government is committed to introducing the legislation before the summer.  The Whips can agree a debate on the economy requested by Senator Farrelly.  I am sure Senator Kelleher will have an opportunity tomorrow to discuss the situation in Yugoslavia in the debate on overseas aid.</P>
      <P>Finally, Senator McGowan has suggested a debate on the International Fund for Ireland.  That debate can be scheduled with the agreement of the Whips.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Order of Business agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>I indicated I wished to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1456" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not see the Senator.  I am sorry about that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>I assumed my name was down.  May I make a point now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I am sorry, the Leader has replied.  We have a rule in this House that the discussion on the Order of Business concludes when the Leader replies.  The Senator may speak first in the morning.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Services Committee:" RHead="Message from Dáil">
    <Title>Joint Services Committee: Message from Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has made the following Order:</P>
      <P>(1) That a Select Committee consisting of nine Members of Dáil Éireann be appointed to be joined with a Select Committee to be appointed by Seanad Éireann to form a Joint Committee (to be called the Joint Services Committee)&mdash;</P>
      <P>(i) to direct and control the Oireachtas Restaurant;</P>
      <P>(ii) to assist and advise the Ceann Comhairle and the Cathaoirleach in the direction and control of the Oireachtas Library; and</P>
      <P>(iii) to regulate and supervise the operation of the research service for Members and to recommend to the Ceann Comhairle and the Cathaoirleach any improvements in the operation of the service which may appear to it to be desirable from time to time.</P>
      <P>(2) That the Joint Committee shall have power to appoint sub-committees and to delegate any matter comprehended by paragraph (1) of this Order to a sub-committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(3) That the Joint Committee and each sub-committee, previous to the commencement of business, shall elect <Col N="1457" /> one of its members to be Chairman, who shall have only one vote.</P>
    <P>(4) That all questions in the Joint Committee and in each sub-committee shall be determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting and in the event of there being an equality of votes the question shall be decided in the negative.</P>
    <P>(5) That the quorum of the Joint Committee shall be five, of whom at least one shall be a member of Dáil Éireann and one a member of Seanad Éireann, and that the quorum of each sub-committee shall be three, at least one of whom shall be a member of Dáil Éireann and one a member of Seanad Éireann.</P>
    <P>(6) That the Joint Committee shall report to both Houses of the Oireachtas within six months on the adequacy of the resources available for the library and research service for Members and on how these services might be improved.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Services Committee:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Joint Services Committee: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>(1)  That a Select Committee consisting of nine Members of Seanad Éireann be appointed to be joined with a Select Committee to be appointed by Dáil Éireann to form a Joint Committee (to be called the Joint Services Committee)&mdash;</P>
      <P>(i)  to direct and control the Oireachtas Restaurant;</P>
      <P>(ii) to assist and advise the Ceann Comhairle and the Cathaoirleach in the direction and control of the Oireachtas Library; and</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(iii) to regulate and supervise the operation of the research service for Members and to recommend to the Ceann Comhairle and the Cathaoirleach any improvements in the operation of the service which may <Col N="1458" /> appear to it to be desirable from time to time.</P>
    <P>(2) That the Joint Committee shall have power to appoint sub-committees and to delegate any matter comprehended by paragraph (1) of this Order to a sub-committee.</P>
    <P>(3) That the Joint Committee and each sub-committee, previous to the commencement of business, shall elect one of its members to be Chairman, who shall have only one vote.</P>
    <P>(4) That all questions in the Joint Committee and in each sub-committee shall be determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting and in the event of there being an equality of votes the question shall be decided in the negative.</P>
    <P>(5) That the quorum of the Joint Committee shall be five, of whom at least one shall be a Member of Dáil Éireann and one a Member of Seanad Éireann, and that the quorum of each sub-committee shall be three, at least one of whom shall be a Member of Dáil Éireann and one a Member of Seanad Éireann.</P>
    <P>(6) That the Joint Committee shall report to both Houses of the Oireachtas within six months on the adequacy of the resources available for the library and research service for Members and on how these services might be improved.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Committee on the Irish Language:" RHead="Message from Dáil">
    <Title>Joint Committee on the Irish Language: Message from Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has made the following Order:</P>
      <P>(1) That a Select Committee consisting of seven Members of Dáil Éireann be appointed to be joined with a Select Committee to be appointed by Seanad Éireann to form a Joint Committee (to be called the Joint Committee on the Irish Language).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1459" /> (2) That the Joint Committee shall from time to time review and make recommendations in relation to</P>
    <P>(a) the extension of the use of Irish in the proceedings of the Dáil and Seanad and in the environs of both Houses, and</P>
    <P>(b) the promotion of the Irish language in general,</P>
    <P>and report to the Houses of the Oireachtas at least once a year on aspects of each.</P>
    <P>(3) That the Joint Committee shall have power to appoint sub-committees and to refer to such sub-committees any matters comprehended by paragraph (2) of this Order.</P>
    <P>(4) That, subject to the consent of the Minister for Finance, the Joint Committee shall have the power to engage the services of persons with specialist or technical knowledge to assist it or any of its sub-committees in its consideration of any matters comprehended by paragraph (2).</P>
    <P>(5) That in the absence from a particular meeting of the Joint Committee (or of a sub-committee) of a member who is a Member of Dáil Éireann, another Member of Dáil Éireann nominated by the party or group within the meaning of Standing Order 89 to which the absent member belongs may take part in the proceedings and vote in his stead.</P>
    <P>(6) That the Joint Committee and each sub-committee, previous to the commencement of business, shall elect one of its members to be Chairman, who shall have only one vote.</P>
    <P>(7) That all questions in the Joint Committee and in each sub-committee shall be determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting and in the event of there being an equality of votes the question shall be decided in the negative.</P>
    <P>(8) That the Joint Committee and <Col N="1460" /> each sub-committee shall have power to take evidence in public; and that the Joint Committee shall have power to print and publish from time to time such minutes of evidence taken, together with such related documents as it thinks fit.</P>
    <P>(9) That every report which the Joint Committee proposes to make shall, on adoption by the Joint Committee, be laid before both Houses of the Oireachtas forthwith, whereupon the Joint Committee shall be empowered to print and publish such report, together with such related documents as it thinks fit.</P>
    <P>(10) That the quorum of the Joint Committee shall be four, of whom at least one shall be a Member of Dáil Éireann and one a Member of Seanad Éireann, and that the quorum of each sub-committee shall be three, at least one of whom shall be a member of Dáil Éireann and one a Member of Seanad Éireann.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Committee on the Irish Language:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Joint Committee on the Irish Language: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>(1) That a Select Committee consisting of four Members of Seanad Éireann be appointed to be joined with a Select Committee to be appointed by Dáil Éireann to form a joint Committee (to be called the Joint Committee on the Irish language).</P>
      <P>(2) That the Joint Committee shall from time to time review and make recommendations in relation to</P>
      <P>(a) the extension of the use of Irish in the proceedings of the Dáil and Seanad and in the environs of both Houses, and</P>
      <P>(b) the promotion of the Irish language in general,</P>
      <P>and report to the Houses of the Oireachtas at least once a year on aspects of each.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1461" /> (3) That the Joint Committee shall have power to appoint sub-committees and to refer to such sub-committees any matters comprehended by paragraph (2) of this Order.</P>
    <P>(4) That, subject to the consent of the Minister for Finance, the Joint Committee shall have the power to engage the services of persons with specialist or technical knowledge to assist it or any of its sub-committees in its consideration of any matters comprehended by paragraph (2).</P>
    <P>(5) That in the absence from a particular meeting of the Joint Committee of a member who is a member of Seanad Éireann, another member of Seanad Éireann may, with the authority of the absent member, take part in the Proceedings and vote in his stead.</P>
    <P>(6) That the Joint Committee and each sub-committee, previous to the commencement of business, shall elect one of its members to be Chairman, who shall have only one vote.</P>
    <P>(7) That all questions in the Joint Committee and in each sub-committee shall be determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting and in the event of there being an equality of votes the question shall be decided in the negative.</P>
    <P>(8) That the Joint Committee and each sub-committee shall have power to take evidence in public; and that the Joint Committee shall have power to print and publish from time to time such minutes of evidence taken, together with such related documents as it thinks fit.</P>
    <P>(9) That every report which the Joint Committee proposes to make shall, on adoption by the Joint Committee, be laid before both Houses of the Oireachtas forthwith, whereupon the Joint Committee shall be empowered to print and publish such report, together with such related documents as it thinks fit.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1462" /> (10) That the quorum of the Joint Committee shall be four, of whom at least one shall be a Member of Dáil Éireann and one a Member of Seanad Éireann, and that the quorum of each sub-committee shall be three, at least one of whom shall be a Member of Dáil Éireann and one a Member of Seanad Éireann.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Standing Joint Committee on" RHead="Consolidation Bills: Message from Dáil">
    <Title>Standing Joint Committee on Consolidation Bills: Message from Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has made the following Order:</P>
      <P>That, in pursuance of Standing Order No. 116 of the Standing Orders relative to Public Business, a Select Committee be appointed to be joined with a Select Committee of Seanad Éireann to constitute the Standing Joint Committee on Consolidation Bills;</P>
      <P>That the Chairman of the Joint Committee shall have only one vote; and</P>
      <P>That all questions in the Joint Committee shall be determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting and in the event of there being an equality of votes the question shall be decided in the negative.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Standing Joint Committee on" RHead="Consolidation Bills: Motion">
    <Title>Standing Joint Committee on Consolidation Bills: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That, in pursuance of Standing Order No. 105 of the Standing Orders relative to Public Business, a Select Committee be appointed to be joined with a Select Committee of Dáil Éireann to constitute the Standing Joint Committee on Consolidation Bills;</P>
      <P>That the Chairman of the Joint Committee shall have only one vote; and</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That all questions in the Joint Committee <Col N="1463" /> shall be determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting and in the event of there being an equality of votes the question shall be decided in the negative.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Committee on Standing Orders:" RHead="Message from Dáil">
    <Title>Joint Committee on Standing Orders: Message from Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has made the following Order:</P>
      <P>That, in pursuance of Standing Order No. 56 of the Standing Orders relative to Public Business, a Select Committee be appointed to be joined with a Select Committee of Seanad Éireann to constitute the Joint Committee on Standing Orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Committee on Standing Orders:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Joint Committee on Standing Orders: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That, in pursuance of Standing Order No. 56 of the Standing Orders relative to Private Business, a Select Committee be appointed to be joined with a Select Committee of Dáil Éireann to constitute the Joint Committee on Standing Orders.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs:" RHead="Message from Dáil">
    <Title>Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs: Message from Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has passed the following Resolution in which the concurrence of Seanad Éireann is desired:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(1) That it is expedient that a Joint Committee of both Houses of the Oireachtas (which shall be called the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs) be appointed consisting of 25 Members of Dáil Éireann and five Members of <Col N="1464" /> Seanad Éireann excluding the <i>ex officio</i> members of the Committee referred to in paragraph (7).</P>
    <P>(2) That the Joint Committee shall have power to appoint sub-committees and to delegate any matter comprehended by paragraphs (4), (8), (9) and (10) to a sub-committee.</P>
    <P>(3) That the Select Committee of Dáil Éireann shall consider the Estimates for Public Services submitted to Dáil Éireann in respect of Foreign Affairs and International Cooperation and report thereon to Dáil Éireann and the Select Committee shall have power to appoint a sub-committee for this purpose.</P>
    <P>(4) That provision be made for the referral to the Joint Committee of Bills initiated in Dáil Éireann by the Minister for Foreign Affairs or a Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Bills initiated in Seanad Éireann by the Leader of the House and originating in the Department of Foreign Affairs.</P>
    <P>(5) That the report of the Joint Committee upon every Bill which is referred to it shall be set down for Report Stage in the originating House.</P>
    <P>(6) That in the case of a Bill originating in one House, the motion of referral in the second House shall constitute a Second Reading of the Bill and the debate thereon shall be confined to the general principle of the Bill and where the Third Stage has been dealt with in the Joint Committee, the Bill shall on its receipt in the second House after being passed by the originating House be set down for Report Stage, the First, Second and Third Stages being waived.</P>
    <P>(7) That the Minister for Foreign Affairs shall be an <i>ex officio</i> member of a Committee or sub-committee which is considering&mdash;</P>
    <P>(i) a Bill referred to it, or</P>
    <P>(ii) Estimates for Public Services, <Col N="1465" /> and may nominate a Minister or Minister of State to be such <i>ex officio</i> member in his stead.</P>
    <P>(8) That the Joint Committee shall consider the impact on equality of policy and legislation in respect of the Department of Foreign Affairs and report thereon to both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>(9) That the Joint Committee shall consider such aspects of Ireland's international relations, including its cooperation with developing countries, and such matters arising from Ireland's membership of the European Communities and its adherence to the Treaty on European Union as the Joint Committee may select and report thereon to both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>(10) That the Joint Committee shall, in particular, consider:</P>
    <P>(i) such programmes and guidelines prepared by the Commission of the European Communities as a basis for possible legislative action and such drafts of regulations, directives, decisions, recommendations and opinions of the Council of Ministers proposed by the Commission,</P>
    <P>(ii) such acts of the institutions of those Communities,</P>
    <P>(iii) such regulations under the European Communities Acts, 1972 to 1993, and</P>
    <P>(iv) such other instruments made under statute and necessitated by the obligations of membership of those Communities</P>
    <P>as the Committee may select and shall report thereon to both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>(11) That any consideration by the Joint Committee, the Select Committee or a sub-Committee of political and security issues relating to Northern Ireland shall be in private session.</P>
    <P>(12) That reports relevant to the Department of Foreign Affairs may be <Col N="1466" /> referred to the Joint Committee for discussion, observations and recommendations, and the Joint Committee shall report thereon to both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>(13) That the Joint Committee shall make an annual report to both Houses of the Oireachtas which shall detail:</P>
    <P>(i) the work carried out by the Committee,</P>
    <P>(ii) the work in progress by the Committee,</P>
    <P>(iii) the attendance and voting records at meetings of the Committee,</P>
    <P>(iv) its future work programme, and</P>
    <P>(v) such other matters as the Committee deems appropriate.</P>
    <P>(14) That the Select Committee, the Joint Committee and each sub-committee shall have power to send for persons, but information need not be provided to a Committee or a sub-committee if a Member of the Government certifies in writing that such information is confidential or that its disclosure would be prejudicial to the State's international relations.</P>
    <P>(15) That the Select Committee and the Joint Committee shall have power, subject to the consent of the Minister for Finance, to engage the services of persons with specialist or technical knowledge to assist them for the purpose of particular enquiries.</P>
    <P>(16) That provision be made for the appointment of substitutes to act for members of the Joint Committee, the Select Committee or a sub-committee who are unable to attend particular meetings; and that Members of the Oireachtas, not being members of the Joint Committee, may attend meetings and take part in the proceedings of the Joint Committee and of its sub-committees without having a right to vote.</P>
    <P>(17) That Members of the European <Col N="1467" /> Parliament elected from constituencies in Ireland (including Northern Ireland) may attend meetings of the Joint Committee and of its sub-committees; and that other Members of the European Parliament may, at the invitation of the Joint Committee or of a sub-committee, attend particular meetings. Members of the European Parliament attending on such occasions may take part in proceedings without having a right to vote or to table amendments to Bills referred to the Committee under paragraph (4).</P>
    <P>(18) That the Select Committee, the Joint Committee and each sub-committee previous to the commencement of business, shall elect one of its members to be Chairperson, who shall have only one vote.</P>
    <P>(19) That all questions in the Select Committee, the Joint Committee and each sub-committee shall be determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting and in the event of there being an equality of votes, the question shall be decided in the negative.</P>
    <P>(20) That every report which the Select Committee or the Joint Committee proposes to make shall, on adoption by the Committee, be laid before Dáil Éireann or, in the case of a report by the Joint Committee, both Houses of the Oireachtas forthwith, together with any document relating thereto which the Committee proposes to publish, whereupon the Committee shall be empowered to print and publish such report and the said document, or documents, as the case may be.</P>
    <P>(21)  That notwithstanding paragraph (20) where the Joint Committee has completed Committee Stage of a Bill, it shall be empowered to print and publish the said Bill as amended, where appropriate.</P>
    <P>(22) That the quorum of the Joint Committee shall be eight, of whom at least one shall be a Member of Dáil <Col N="1468" /> Éireann and at least one shall be a Member of Seanad Éireann, the quorum of the Select Committee shall be six and the quorum of each sub-committee shall be a number to be decided by the sub-Committee when such sub-committee is appointed.</P>
    <P>(23) That no document received by the Clerk to the Select Committee, the Joint Committee or a sub-committee shall be withheld, withdrawn or altered without the knowledge and approval of such Committee.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>(1) That Seanad Éireann concurs with Dáil Éireann in its Resolution communicated to Seanad Éireann on 6th April, 1993, that it is expedient that a Joint Committee of both Houses of the Oireachtas (which shall be called the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs) be appointed consisting of 25 Members of Dáil Éireann and five Members of Seanad Éireann excluding the <i>ex officio</i> members of the Committee referred to in paragraph (7).</P>
      <P>(2) That the Joint Committee shall have power to appoint sub-committees and to delegate any matter comprehended by paragraphs (4), (8), (9) and (10) to a sub-committee.</P>
      <P>(3) That the Select Committee of Dáil Éireann shall consider the Estimates for Public Services submitted to Dáil Éireann in respect of Foreign Affairs and International Co-operation and report thereon to Dáil Éireann and the Select Committee shall have power to appoint a sub-committee for this purpose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(4) That provision be made for the referral to the Joint Committee of Bills initiated in Dáil Éireann by the Minister for Foreign Affairs or a Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Bills initiated in Seanad <Col N="1469" /> Éireann by the Leader of the House and originating in the Department of Foreign Affairs.</P>
    <P>(5) That the report of the Joint Committee upon every Bill which is referred to it shall be set down for Report Stage in the originating House.</P>
    <P>(6) That in the case of a Bill originating in one House, the motion of referral in the second House shall constitute a Second Reading of the Bill and the debate thereon shall be confined to the general principle of the Bill and where the Third Stage has been dealt with in the Joint Committee, the Bill shall on its receipt in the second House after being passed by the originating House be set down for Report Stage, the First, Second and Third Stages being waived.</P>
    <P>(7) That the Minister for Foreign Affairs shall be an <i>ex officio</i> member of a Committee or sub-committee which is considering&mdash;</P>
    <P>(i)  a Bill referred to it, or</P>
    <P>(ii) Estimates for Public Services,</P>
    <P>and may nominate a Minister or Minister of State to be such <i>ex officio</i> member in his stead.</P>
    <P>(8) That the Joint Committee shall consider the impact on equality of policy and legislation in respect of the Department of Foreign Affairs and report thereon to both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>(9) That the Joint Committee shall consider such aspects of Ireland's international relations, including its co-operation with developing countries, and such matters arising from Ireland's membership of the European Communities and its adherence to the Treaty on European Union as the Joint Committee may select and report thereon to both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>(10) That the Joint Committee shall, in particular, consider:</P>
    <P>(i) such programmes and guidelines <Col N="1470" /> prepared by the Commission of the European Communities as a basis for possible legislative action and such drafts of regulations, directives, decisions, recommendations and opinions of the Council of Ministers proposed by the Commission,</P>
    <P>(ii) such acts of the institutions of those Communities,</P>
    <P>(iii) such regulations under the European Communities Acts, 1972 to 1993, and</P>
    <P>(iv) such other instruments made under statute and necessitated by the obligations of membership of those Communities</P>
    <P>as the Committee may select and shall report thereon to both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>(11) That any consideration by the Joint Committee, the Select Committee or a sub-committee of political and security issues relating to Northern Ireland shall be in private session.</P>
    <P>(12) That reports relevant to the Department of Foreign Affairs may be referred to the Joint Committee for discussion, observations and recommendations, and the Joint Committee shall report thereon to both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>(13) That the Joint Committee shall make an annual report to both Houses of the Oireachtas which shall detail:</P>
    <P>(i) the work carried out by the Committee,</P>
    <P>(ii)  the work in progress by the Committee,</P>
    <P>(iii) the attendance and voting records at meetings of the Committee,</P>
    <P>(iv) its future work programme, and</P>
    <P>(v)  such other matters as the Committee deems appropriate.</P>
    <P>(14) That the Select Committee, the Joint Committee and each sub-committee <Col N="1471" /> shall have power to send for persons, but information need not be provided to a Committee or a sub-committee if a Member of the Government certifies in writing that such information is confidential or that its disclosure would be prejudicial to the State's international relations.</P>
    <P>(15) That the Select Committee and the Joint Committee shall have power, subject to the consent of the Minister for Finance, to engage the services of persons with specialist or technical knowledge to assist them for the purpose of particular inquiries.</P>
    <P>(16) That provision be made for the appointment of substitutes to act for members of the Joint Committee, the Select Committee or a sub-committee who are unable to attend particular meetings; and that Members of the Oireachtas, not being members of the Joint Committee, may attend meetings and take part in the proceedings of the Joint Committee and of its sub-committees without having a right to vote.</P>
    <P>(17) That Members of the European Parliament elected from constituencies in Ireland (including Northern Ireland) may attend meetings of the Joint Committee and of its sub-committees; and that other Members of the European Parliament may, at the invitation of the Joint Committee or of a sub-committee, attend particular meetings. Members of the European Parliament attending on such occasions may take part in proceedings without having a right to vote or to table amendments to Bills referred to the Committee under paragraph (4).</P>
    <P>(18) That the Select Committee, the Joint Committee and each sub-committee previous to the commencement of business, shall elect one of its members to be Chairperson, who shall have only one vote.</P>
    <P>(19) That all questions in the Select Committee, the Joint Committee and <Col N="1472" /> each sub-committee shall be determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting and in the event of there being an equality of votes, the question shall be decided in the negative.</P>
    <P>(20) That every report which the Select Committee or the Joint Committee proposes to make shall, on adoption by the Committee, be laid before Dáil Éireann or, in the case of a report by the Joint Committee, both Houses of the Oireachtas forthwith, together with any document relating thereto which the Committee proposes to publish, whereupon the Committee shall be empowered to print and publish such report and the said document, or documents, as the case may be.</P>
    <P>(21) That notwithstanding paragraph (20) where the Joint Committee has completed Committee Stage of a Bill, it shall be empowered to print and publish the said Bill as amended, where appropriate.</P>
    <P>(22) That the quorum of the Joint Committee shall be eight, of whom at least one shall be a Member of Dáil Éireann and at least one shall be a Member of Seanad Éireann, the quorum of the Select Committee shall be six and the quorum of each sub-committee shall be a number to be decided by the sub-committee when such sub-committee is appointed.</P>
    <P>(23) That no document received by the Clerk to the Select Committee, the Joint Committee or a sub-committee shall be withheld, withdrawn or altered without the knowledge and approval of such Committee.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Roads Bill, 1991:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Roads Bill, 1991: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister for the Environment, Deputy Smith.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1473" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelSmith" hpid="Minister for the Environment (Mr. M. Smith) Michael Smith">
      <NameTxt>Minister for the Environment (Mr. M. Smith)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is mian liom buíochas a ghabháil leatsa, a Chathaoirligh, as ucht an fáilte. Tá áthas orm a bheith ar ais sa Seanad agus mo chomhgáirdeachas a dhéanamh leis na Seanadóirí uilig a bhain suíocháin amach sa toghchán le déanaí.</P>
      <P>Tá mé fíor-shásta bheith anseo inniu leis an Dara Céim den Bhille seo a chur ós comhair an tSeanaid.  Níl aon amhras orm ná go dtuigfidh sibh, i ndiaidh daoibh dul tríd an mBille, cé chomh rí-thábhachtach is atá sé d'fhorbairt infrastructúr na mbóithre sa tír seo.  Ní haon áibhéil é a rá gurbh é seo an reachtaíocht is cuimsithí a cuireadh le chéile faoi bhóithre ó bunaíodh an Stát.</P>
      <P>Before discussing the content of the Bill, I thank all those who contributed to its development: individuals and organisations who put forward many suggestions and amendments and who were involved in fruitful discussions with officials of my Department.  Organisations such as the former Confederation of Irish Industry, the Construction Industry Federation, the County and City Managers' Association, the County and City Engineers' Association took the time to prepare detailed submissions on the Bill.</P>
      <P>During its passage through the other House, Deputies from all sides took part in valuable debates on the Bill and a number of Deputies gave of their time to sit on a special committee to deal with the Committee Stage during the summer recess.  The Bill was substantially strengthened and extended during its passage through the Dáil and is now a much more comprehensive piece of legislation.  Lastly and most importantly I thank the chairman and members of the interim National Roads Authority whose submissions were very useful given that the were based on practical experience of managing the roads programme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill does two things.  First, it provides for the establishment of the National Roads Authority on a statutory basis.  This body will spearhead the development of our national road network, <Col N="1474" /> which is of paramount importance to the development of the Irish economy. A top grade national road system enhances our accessibility and increases our export competitiveness by reducing transport costs which are an ever present problem given our peripheral location in Europe.  Secondly, the Bill consolidates much of the existing roads law and updates many provisions in order to provide a comprehensive legislative framework for roads which meets modernday needs.  It also incorporates some new provisions which I will go into later.  I will deal first with the National Roads Authority, the background to why it is being set up, its functions and powers and the task which lies ahead of it.</P>
    <P>It is only in recent years that we have started to give priority to investment in the national road network.  Prior to that we put very substantial resources into other areas of our economic and social infrastructure &mdash; housing, telecommunications, energy, health, education and so on.  In the case of roads, for a long time, we gave priority to non-national as distinct from national roads. Another factor which hampered the development of the national road network was the absence of a medium-term planning framework which was mainly due to uncertainty with regard to funding. It is only with the advent of the EC Community Support Framework, covering the period 1989-93, that guaranteed medium-term funding became available to enable a realistic medium-term plan for roads to be pursued.</P>
    <P>These days, however, roads and transport generally are very much on the agenda.  For the purposes of expenditure of EC Structural Funds, we have the Operational Programme on Peripherality, a major integrated transport investment programme covering road, rail, sea and air transport which was agreed by the EC Commission for the period to the end of 1993.  The NRA will provide the national roads element of future programmes and, indeed, the setting up of the NRA on a statutory basis will greatly assist in ensuring that the strategic plans for national roads in these <Col N="1475" /> programmes are carried through as effectively and efficiently as possible.</P>
    <P>The importance of having an efficient national road network cannot be over-emphasised and we need to ensure that available funds are spent on these roads in the most effective manner possible. The need for a central, single-minded, independent and far-seeing body is, therefore, very evident and it is against this background that the concept of the NRA as the focal point for such development has evolved.</P>
    <P>The task of the National Roads Authority will be a challenging one.  The NRA's primary function will be, as section 17 says; &ldquo;to secure the provision of a safe and efficient network of national roads&rdquo;.  It will have overall responsibility for planning and supervising the construction, improvement and maintenance of the network of national roads &mdash; which will include the access routes to the principal ports and airports.  These national roads represent under 6 per cent of total road mileage, but account for about 37 per cent of total road traffic, two-thirds of it work-related.  The long term development programme for these roads is estimated to cost £3.6 billion.  In view of the very high level of investment required and, consequently, the need for a body directing the use of such funds to achieve optimum value for money, very detailed consideration was given to the type of organisation which should be set up.  To this end, the views of a range of interests were listened to and examined.</P>
    <P>The NRA is being given very substantial powers to accomplish its task of overseeing and co-ordinating the development of our national road network. The Bill assigns it the following specific functions: it will be responsible for the preparation of strategic medium-term plans for the development of the national roads; it will prepare or arrange for the preparation of road designs, maintenance programmes and schemes for the provision of traffic signs on national roads; it will secure the carrying out of construction, improvement and maintenance works on national roads, mainly <Col N="1476" /> through local authorities but on its own initiative if it considers it appropriate; it will allocate and pay grants for works on national roads; the Authority will have power to issue directions to local authorities to carry out certain specified functions in relation to the construction, improvement and maintenance of national roads and will be able to carry out the function itself in the unlikely event that a local authority fails or refuses to comply with such a direction; while local authorities will normally be relied upon to prepare road designs and maintenance programmes and to enter into road works contracts, the NRA will have the power to carry out these functions itself where it decides that this would be more convenient, expeditious, effective or economical; the NRA will promote the case for EC assistance for roads.  This will include the preparation of the national roads element of future operational programmes covering the roads and other transport sectors; and the NRA will promote the provision of private investment for national roads and for this purpose will have the power to borrow up to £500 million subject to the usual ministerial consents and to enter into toll franchise agreements with private interests.</P>
    <P>While the Authority is being given very wide-ranging powers, it is not being given <i>carte blanche</i> to do as it pleases.  It will be answerable to me as Minister for the Environment.  I will retain overall policy and legislative responsibility for roads. The NRA's medium-term plans will be subject to my approval and its borrowings will require my consent and that of the Minister for Finance.  In addition, I will have general powers under section 41 to issue mandatory directions and advisory guidelines to the NRA.</P>
    <P>While I will retain some quasi-judicial powers, such as the approval of compulsory purchase orders and motorway schemes, neither I nor my Department will have any involvement in the day to day management of the national road development programme.  This work is being transferred in its entirety to the Authority.  State grants for national roads <Col N="1477" /> will be paid as a global amount by my Department to the authority, which will be completely responsible for the allocation of finance to individual projects.</P>
    <P>Up to now the work of constructing, maintaining and improving the national road network rested with the local authorities. It is not the intention of the Bill that this situation should change but rather that it should be improved.  My officials in drafting this Bill were at great pains to ensure that the resources, skills and vast experience of the local authorities in this area will continue to be availed of and that there will not be any overlap of functions or duplication of effort between the NRA and the local authorities.  To this end the Bill provides that local authorities will continue to acquire land for national roads, prepare road designs and maintenance programmes and enter into road works contracts on behalf of the NRA unless it decides that it would be more convenient, expeditious, effective or economical to carry out the work itself.</P>
    <P>In effect, the local authorities will continue to carry out most of the existing functions in relation to national roads &mdash; acting on behalf of the National Roads Authority and under its supervision.  The main change is that the NRA will provide a new strategic focal point for local authorities and it will harness their expertise in a more coherent and co-ordinated way. The NRA will, in effect, work in partnership with the local authorities as my Department has done in the past and I see no reason this relationship will not continue to be a harmonious one.</P>
    <P>The legislation seeks to preserve a balance by giving the NRA adequate powers to do its important job in the national interest, while ensuring that local authorities have a vital input into the road development process, particularly where it affects local interests.  I will take a few minutes to outline the checks and balances which have been built into the Bill.</P>
    <P>In section 18, the NRA is obliged to prepare a medium-term development plan for national roads at regular intervals. When preparing that plan it must <Col N="1478" /> obtain the views of local authorities. Before submitting the draft plan to the Minister for approval, it must send copies to each local authority.  The elected members can, as a reserved function, make objections or representations to the Minister and he must consider them before deciding whether or not to approve the plan.</P>
    <P>As I have said already, the National Roads Authority will normally carry out its functions through local authorities.  It will, however, in certain cases be able to carry out works itself under section 19 or to issue directions to local authorities under section 20.  If the effect of a direction would be to oblige a local authority to materially contravene its development plan, the NRA will be obliged to undertake a public consultation process similar to that for a proposed material contravention of a local authority development plan before it can proceed any further.  The Minister will also have a reserve power to &ldquo;call in&rdquo; certain classes of direction for approval by him.</P>
    <P>A key area of potential disputes between the NRA and local authorities is on road alignments and with this in mind the Bill was amended to give the elected members of the local authority a right in section 22 to make their views known to the NRA where they have objections to a particular road alignment. Where agreement is not possible or where there is a continuing objection, the local authority could then make representations to the Minister.  He would have the discretion to take action if he felt it appropriate, either by using his directive powers under the Bill or by intervening on an informal administrative basis.</P>
    <P>When carrying out its road development functions, the NRA will be obliged under section 22 to consider the proper planning and development of the area in which the road is located, to consider any environmental effects and to have regard to the local development plan and any special amenity area or tree preservation order.  As a reserve power, the Minister will, under section 41, be able to issue advisory guidelines or mandatory directions <Col N="1479" /> to the NRA.  While tolling powers in respect of national roads are being transferred to the NRA under Part V of the Bill, local authorities will still have an important input.  The elected members will be consulted when a draft toll scheme authorising tolls on a particular road, is being prepared.  If they are not happy with the outcome, they will be able to lodge a formal objection to the scheme when it has been submitted to the Minister and to have that objection considered at a public local inquiry.  They will also have the right to be consulted on toll by-laws, which, among other things, set the level of tolls.  I do not want to over-emphasise the potential for conflict between the NRA and local authorities. Like my Department before it, the NRA will foster a spirit of co-operation with the local authorities &mdash; they will work with, and not against them.  The procedures in the Bill are designed to foster consultation and co-operation, but in the final analysis, the buck has to stop with the NRA as the body with the prime statutory responsibility for developing the national road network.  While drafting the legislation setting up the National Roads Authority, it became apparent that existing roads legislation was in need of a major overhaul to make it more relevant to modern day requirements.  It was decided that we should have one single measure dealing with roads legislation covering the various roads provisions set down in previous Acts as far as possible.  This Bill covers a broad spectrum, updating elements of roads legislation as far back as the Summary Jurisdiction (Ireland) Act, 1851, right up to a comparatively more recently enacted legislation, like the Local Government (Roads and Motorways) Act, 1974.  This Act, together with the Local Government (Toll Roads) Act, 1979, is being completely repealed by this Bill and reenacted in a strengthened form in Parts IV and V respectively &mdash; taking account of practical experience in the operation of these Acts.  As I have said, provisions scattered throughout various Acts are being modernised and some entirely new <Col N="1480" /> powers are being introduced.  The following are some of the more significant proposed changes in the general roads law.</P>
    <P>The classification of public roads is being simplified in section 100.  Three classes are proposed: national, regional and local.  They will replace all the existing classes such as trunk and link roads, main and county roads and so on.  The category of local authority, which will be responsible for each class of public roads, is clearly defined in section 13.  County councils and county borough corporations will be responsible for national and regional roads, while the counties, county boroughs, boroughs and urban district councils will be responsible for all local roads in their areas.  This greatly simplifies the legal position but will invlove little or no change in existing <i>de facto</i> responsibility on the ground.</P>
    <P>The power to declare roads to be public roads is being modernised in section 11. The powers to abandon public roads and extinguish public rights of way are being devolved to the elected members of local authorities in sections 12 and 73 respectively. This is in line with the ongoing policy of devolving responsibility to local authorities so that there is no need for detailed day to day Ministerial involvement.</P>
    <P>The concept of a &ldquo;protected road&rdquo; is being introduced in Part IV.  This is in addition to the re-enactment of the existing legislative provisions for motorways and busways.  The protected road is intended as a &ldquo;halfway house&rdquo; between an ordinary public road (which usually has very limited access control or traffic restrictions), and a motorway (to which all access from adjoining land is prohibited and is also restricted to certain types of traffic.  Local authorities will now be able, under section 54, to provide and/or operate service areas along motorways and protected roads, as will the NRA.  Alternatively, they will be able to make agreements with private interests for their provision and/or operation.</P>
    <P>The Oireachtas Joint Committee on Secondary Legislation of the European Communities has frequently recommended <Col N="1481" /> that European Communities Regulations implementing EC directives should be transferred into an appropriate Act when the opportunity presented itself.  In compliance with that recommendation, European Communities Regulations implementing an EC directive in relation to the environmental impact assessment of proposed road development-including motorways, busways and certain other types of road construction and improvement &mdash; are being replaced by sections 50 and 51 of this Bill.</P>
    <P>Road authorities are being given power in section 68 to provide cycleways. Temporary dwellings on national roads, motorways etc. are being prohibited under section 69, as are unauthorised vehicles used for trading, and unauthorised signs and advertising hoardings on any public road under section 71.  Local authorities and the Garda are been given appropriate powers to enforce these prohibitions. The restrictions on roadside trading will not apply to the seasonal sale of fruit and vegetables.  Under section 70, local authorities will have improved powers to deal with dangerous trees and new powers to deal with dangerous structures along public roads.</P>
    <P>Under sections 74 and 75, local authorities are being given new powers to control road races and strengthened powers relating to the temporary closure of public roads.  Temporary closures will no longer need to be notified to my Department.  The Bill codifies in section 67 the existing common law duty of care imposed on road users, whereby they must take reasonable care for their own safety and that of other road users, and avoid damage to their own or other people's property.  A new power to control the use of rubbish skips is being introduced in section 72, allowing for a flexible approach by local authorities, who can decide how their use should be regulated depending on local circumstances.  In the spirit of devolution, local by-laws dealing with skips will not need Ministerial confirmation.</P>
    <P>Section 77 was introduced in the Dáil, giving the Minister power to make regulations requiring works to be carried out <Col N="1482" /> in order to mitigate the effects of road traffic noise, following the construction of new roads or the improvement of existing ones.  Powers relating to drainage of public roads and associated matters, such as the deposit of dung, grit etc. on public roads dating as far back as 1851 are being completely revamped in this Bill under sections 13 and 76.  I do not intend to go through the 85 sections of the Bill in detail at this point, but rather to leave that to the debate on subsequent stages. I know I can expect the usual searching questions and high standard of debate for which this House is rightly respected.</P>
    <P>This is extremely important legislation and because we have unique financial resources available for road development from the Structural Funds it behoves us to ensure that these moneys are spent in the most efficient and effective way so as to provide the best arterial road network possible.  Arguments are often made, when debating comprehensive legislation like this, regarding expenditure priorities. Emphasis is often placed on the need to provide additional resources for our country road network.  It is important to understand the need for ensuring that, as a small economy depending more on exports than any of our European competitors &mdash; we must export over 75 per cent of what we produce &mdash; our goods must be conveyed to sea and airports within certain time constraints.  All competitive features relating to transport are crucial in determining the growth of the economy.  Investment in that network has been recommended by the Culliton report, by Moriarty, by the Central Bank and by every economic review carried out in the last ten years.  We are seeking to co-ordinate local authorities under the management of the NRA, to ensure that over the next four to five years we have not only the financial stimulus but also the organisational structure, the commitment and the determination to obtain the best possible results from that investment, to provide jobs and the infrastructure essential for future development.</P>
    <P>I look forward to the Senators' contributions to the debate on this Bill, and <Col N="1483" /> to Committee Stage where we will have the opportunity to tease out different points of view and, thus improve the Bill.</P>
    <P>Tá mé ag súil go ndéanfar plé tairbheach agus bríomhar faoin mBille radacach seo, atá mar chlochmhíle tábhachtach i stair reachtaíocht na mbóithre.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House to debate this important Bill.  This Bill will have wideranging effects; it has already had a chequered career.  The delays in relation to this Bill have been similar to the delays in traffic common in this country.</P>
      <P>The Fine Gael Party welcomes the introduction of this Bill and will support many of its provisions.  Fine Gael will have to oppose parts of the Bill especially those relating to tolls for the use of roadways. Irish motorists, whether private drivers or operators of haulage businesses pay heavy cost in tax and insurance and for motor cars.  The Irish motorist deserves better.  Although recent improvements are welcome the State has been developing the network of roadways on a piecemeal basis: while part of the road is improved to speed up passing traffic a traffic jam is probably building up further down the same road.</P>
      <P>I hope that the establishment of the National Roads Authority will improve roads for the motorist.  The individual motorist who is taxed to the hilt deserves better roads.  Haulage fleet operators and those who run delivery vans need better roads because for them time is money. Time is money also for any business person who must travel from one part of the country to another.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Fine Gael would have preferred one Department or Authority to have had responsibility for the development of transport.  Instead the Minister for the Environment is responsible for roads, the Minister for Transport is responsible for CIE and other transport matters and the Minister for the Marine is responsible for the operation of the ports.  If Departments are not in contact with each other <Col N="1484" /> it is difficult to establish the best policy for the smooth passage of traffic throughout the country.  Small roads suitable for rural areas cannot cope with juggernauts.</P>
    <P>We should also consider the increase in carnage this year on our roads for which the roads authority and the Minister are only partly responsible.  In my area a set of traffic lights which were old and malfunctioning were switched off by the local authority prior to their replacement within a month or two.  The road in question carries lorries and juggernauts to Dún Laoghaire harbour.  Parents in this area are concerned for their children and for elderly people who cross that road.  People, not juggernauts, come off worse in accidents.</P>
    <P>I ask the Minister to clarify how much consultation there will be between the Authority and his Department on one hand and with other boards and with the Ministers for Transport and the Marine on the other.  One cannot look at the road networks without looking at the overall transport situation &mdash; the rural thoroughfares, the railways and even the ports.  In certain areas the development of a good rail network has persuaded people to leave their cars at home.  In other areas, unfortunately, commuters do not have this option and must use their cars.</P>
    <P>I hope the Authority will be an independent organisation with powers and not just a talking shop.  The Minister must not be able to hide behind the Authority when things go wrong and yet dictate policy totally.  I ask the Minister to indicate his specific role in relation to the Authority and to confirm that the Authority will be independent.  We have seen tremendous improvements since Telecom Éireann and An Post replaced the former Department of Posts and Telegraphs; An Post now deliver letters within one, or at most two days.  These have been some very notable developments in the whole telecommunications industry.  It is not before its time because in previous years it could take months or even years to have a phone connected.</P>
    <P>We must recognise the very important role the staff and members of the local authorities play, in the maintenance of <Col N="1485" /> our roads.  I hope, in the light of recent discussions and announcements, that members of local authorities are not going to be ignored.  I am sure Senator Finneran would agree with me in relation to this, given his long commitment to the local authority system of administration. It is important that the Minister does not interfere with the decisions of the Authority, and that the Authority is not hamstrung, whatever functions are transferred to it, given that the Minister will have the power to issue directions and guidelines to it.  I ask the Minister to discuss this role <i>vis-á-vis</i> the Authority in his reply.  The Authority must be independent, and must be able to get on with its business, part of which is the drawing up of a plan to develop the roads network in this country.</P>
    <P>If the economy is to prosper we must have a network throughout the country linking north and south, east and west. It is good to see various improvements in our cities and towns.  If and when this plan is brought forward I ask the Minister to implement it urgently within a definite time-scale.  If we spend £3 billion to £4 billion over a number of years &mdash; the time-scale will probably run into the next century &mdash; upgrading our road network, we must have a clear programme and we must stick to it.</P>
    <P>I am sure the Minister is aware of delays that have occurred in some of the half finished by-passes and roads around the country.  If there has not been full consultation at the planning stage, building half a by-pass is only clogging up the road network further.</P>
    <P>We must ensure that when plans are drawn up there is adequate consultation to ensure that work is not halted before the road is completed.  An efficient road network can improve our economy by providing infrastructure, attracting overseas investment, and increasing employment, not to mention the vast number of jobs that will be created by availing of EC Structural Funds to build the road network.</P>
    <P>With regard to the question of toll roads, because these roads are paid for with public and European money, we will <Col N="1486" /> oppose this move, save in exceptional circumstances.  This is a further unjust tax on the already heavily penalised motorist, a long way from the glory days of 1977 when there was no road tax, to paying a very substantial amount now.</P>
    <P>Whether one drives a very small car, a taxi, a van or a lorry, one is heavily taxed. Insurance and running costs are also very high.  Some 9 per cent of hauliers' costs are spent on transport.  This is double the European average of 4.5 per cent of costs.  We are over-taxed, the Government is bleeding the motorist dry and we will be opposing the imposition of further tolls tooth and nail.  The two toll roads in operation at the moment are very successful but if further tolls are imposed on newly built roads, people who are already paying very heavy motoring costs will have to pay again to use these roads. We propose to amend that provision on Committee Stage because motoring costs in this country are prohibitively high.</P>
    <P>A single independent roads development authority is to be welcomed if it is all it is meant to be.  This legislation was promised five or six years ago.  If it works it will be worthwhile.</P>
    <P>Road openings cause traffic jams and delays and are another matter for concern. Other countries seem to have a better system for dealing with this matter. Whether it is the local authority, Bord Gáis, Bord Telecom or the ESB, they seem to be very good at opening part of a road and erecting barriers to ensure that people do not fall into the hole, but they are very slow to go back and fix the roads.  We need a more co-ordinated approach to roadworks.  Work could be done at the weekend in some circumstances. Work could also be done during the night if the repairs are not extensive.</P>
    <P>If one weighs up the cost to the country of people who are delayed in traffic jams and are late for work and appointments it would come to a considerable amount. I hope the authority will have discussions with the various bodies to arrange for a more satisfactory way to deal with this matter.</P>
    <P>I ask the Minister to tell us the time-scale <Col N="1487" /> in relation to the preparation of a plan.  More importantly, when does the Minister expect the NRA will be operating, where are the staff to come from and how will it be financed?  I hope it is not going to be like the Ombudsman's Office which is doing a very good job and then suddenly is hard pressed to pay even the cleaning lady.  While some of these bodies are great for ideas, they are going to be independent.  Perhaps the Minister, when replying, would indicate the time scale involved in setting up this body.</P>
    <P>Section 72 of the Bill deals with skips on public roads.  While they are a part of life, they have been the cause of serious accidents.  There should be minimum requirements in relation to lighting, ideally, these skips should be moved before dark unless they are properly illuminated. I am glad provision will be made for cyclists on all roads.  I hope more cycle ways will be provided to ensure the safety of cyclists and that will become an integral part of our road network.</P>
    <P>To sum up, I ask the Minister to indicate when he expects the Authority to come into operation and when a plan will be brought forward.  I ask him to pay special attention to planned routes where maps have been drawn, particularly the Southern Cross route, as well as dealing quickly with improvements to junctions. There are many other items in the Bill which we will have an opportunity to examine on Committee Stage.  I look forward to a fruitful debate because our future depends on getting our roads network right as quickly as possible.  This applies as much to the individual out for a Sunday drive as the business interest or haulage contractor.  It is important that the plan we propose is right, and that, ultimately, the country will benefit.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, welcome the Minister of State at the Department of the Environment to this House.  By and large, I welcome the provisions of this Bill.  In 1988 when I was chairman of the General Council of County Councils, I had my first discussions with and made my first submission regarding the <Col N="1488" /> National Roads Authority to the then Minister for the Environment, Mr. Pádraig Flynn, now the EC Commissioner for Social Affairs.  It is a pity the National Roads Authority was not in place in 1988 because that was an opportune time.  We were about to put together an operational programme that would be funded by the European Community's Structural Funds Programme for 1989-93.  I felt it was of vital importance that the money available for our national routes would be spent in a cohesive and planned fashion.  While a lot of good work has been done since then, it would have been better had it started four years ago.  We are still in time for the second round of Structural Funds and are involved in putting together programmes that will cover the period 1994 to the end of this century.  It is important that the plan we present, and have implemented over that period and beyond, is of national benefit.</P>
      <P>We must be conscious of our situation in a European context.  First as we are the only State in Europe that does not have a road link with neighbouring countries, we have to plan our national roads network carefully and make sure that each national road leads to a specific point of exit from or entry to this country. Our national roads network must correlate with the location of our main ports and airports.  As part of our national plan we must provide attractive locations for industrial development, otherwise we will have wasted the money from the second round of Structural Funds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When this National Roads Authority is in place and has been given responsibility, it must deal with the country as a whole, and not with sectional interests on the east coast, south coast or elsewhere. It must be a truly national authority that will support the development of the regions.  I am worried by initial reports that roads earmarked for major development over the next couple of years, seem to favour the north, south and east coasts with no major thrust into the midlands or the west.  When the gas link was developed it crossed the centre of the country but ignored the west and northwest. The proposed national roads network <Col N="1489" /> should not leave one area less disadvantaged than another.  All the people of Ireland have the same constitutional rights, irrespective of their geographical location.  As politicians we have a duty to ensure equality of opportunity.</P>
    <P>The National Roads Authority should have a broad influence on Irish life.  It must be representative and it should reflect public opinion and the intention of Government, at local and national level. We would be walking away from democracy of we were to establish a body with overall powers, with some powers transferred from local authorities, which, then implemented a policy independent of central or local government.  There should be close liaison between the National Roads Authority and the local authorities.  Members of representative bodies for Irish local authorities, namely the General Council of County Councils and the Association of Municipal Authorities of Ireland, should be included on the National Roads Authority.  This would create balance, and allow local authorities to have their opinions represented.</P>
    <P>To some extent local authorities have had to work in isolation over the years. Individual planning by county and roads engineers has determined the extent of development on roads in each county. This has often led to the complication, referred to by Senator Cosgrave, where development in one county is not matched in another, thereby creating traffic problems.</P>
    <P>The National Roads Authority is responsible for the national road network. However, Senators and other elected representatives, should not consider that our interest in road development is at an end.  Only 6 per cent of the roads of this country are categorised as national roads and they cater for approximately 30 per cent of traffic.  Therefore, 94 per cent of Irish roads and 70 per cent of traffic is not directly involved in the national road network.</P>
    <P>We have a responsibility to ensure that neither the regional road network nor the county road network is neglected in the priority list following the establishment <Col N="1490" /> of the NRA.  Major funding is required over the next number of years for these networks as there are vast areas of this country that are miles away from a national road.  If funding for the future development of roads in this country is to be directed towards the national routes, then there is the danger that many regions will be denied road development. These regions would eventually be denuded of people and would become isolated and deserted, dependent on forestry or whatever activities are possible in such deserted regions.</P>
    <P>It is important that the House acknowledges its responsibility towards the regional road network and the country road network.  I will illustrate the possible effect on one country if attention is paid to the national network only.  In Roscommon, there are two national roads, one at the south from Ballinasloe to Athlone and one which it is proposed to upgrade to a reasonable standard in the north, from Tarmonbarry to Ballaghaderreen. There are some secondary roads, but the rest are county roads or what are now classified as regional roads, although no money has been allocated for their improvement.  The county is 70 or 80 miles long and there are 50 miles in the middle without a national road.  If it is intended to develop national arterial routes only, then large stretches of countryside and many smaller towns and regions will be denied opportunity for development.</P>
    <P>There is continuous debate throughout Europe and at European Commission level on regional development. However, there is little attempt to put this talk into action.  One only has to consider developments over the last number of years.  Executives of local authorities intend that no more rural council houses will be built and that people will migrate from the countryside to towns and villages.  The intention of An Post is that local post offices will close down with people going to the nearest town to collect mail or pensions.  Door to door deliveries will end in remote areas and post boxes will be placed on roadsides. The expected development is that <Col N="1491" /> if people have to travel to collect mail or pension, they will eventually move to the centre of activity, thereby killing off rural villages.  We must not continue this charade of pretending that everything decided at European level is being implemented on a national scale when the opposite is the case.</P>
    <P>If rural Ireland is to survive and to develop its full potential, then we have to support aspects of infrastructure such as the post offices, Garda stations and local shops.  We must create opportunities to develop these services rather than eliminate them; otherwise we kill off rural communities.  Similarly, we kill them off if we concentrate on the NRA to the detriment of our regional and county roads, particularly the regional roads.</P>
    <P>I wish to discuss county roads.  In most counties the vast expanse of miles that require maintenance are county roads.  As I heard a former EC Commissioner say, it is now an opportune time for the Government to take on board the suggestion that moneys from the Structural Funds should be made directly available to local authorities for county road maintenance, tar spraying and other improvements. I understand the figure mentioned by former Commissioner MacSharry was 10 per cent and if it was allocated over a period of three to five years, the entire county road network could be brought up to a standard where local authorities through their own revenue raising abilities would be in a position to maintain it from that point on.  Local authorities cannot return to the stage they were at ten to 15 years ago.  It is not long since the county road network was surfaced, dressed and tarred.</P>
    <P>A fellow county man and a parishioner of mine former Roscommon TD Jack McQuillan suggested in 1953 that local authorities should be given an opportunity to take over existing cow tracks, car tracks and pedestrian tracks and turn them in to roads that people could travel in reasonable comfort.  He was a man of foresight and he was politically courageous to suggest this at that time and to <Col N="1492" /> see it through.  His good work proved very beneficial in rural areas and most local authorities responded very well by taking over miles and miles of roads.  In my county there are approximately 2,400 miles of county roads.  Other counties might not have as many miles that require maintenance but that is because they do not have as many rural villages.</P>
    <P>In recent times county roads have not been considered a top priority.  Apart from reasonable allocations by former Minister, Mr. Flynn, up to this year, over the previous ten years the county roads network was allowed to deteriorate to the extent that the money now required to bring it back up to a good standard is hard to find given the present revenue-raising mechanisms, namely, rates on commercial buildings, service charges and in some cases block grants from the Department.  It is now time for the Minister for the Environment and the Government to direct 10 per cent of EC Structural Funds towards the county road network and if that is done, it will throw a lifeline to rural communities and villages.</P>
    <P>I wish to discuss another area and this is the long and good tradition of co-operation between local authorities in the construction of by-passes and bridges.  It has worked very well in most cases but section 59 agreements can be abused &mdash; I have personal experience of this as a member of a local authority &mdash; by an avaricious county manager who, through a backdoor, wishes to stake a claim in the functional area of another local authority. This is a very serious matter because a section 59 agreement is a reserved function of local authority members.  They do it in good faith on the advice of their executive and in conjunction with their colleagues across the county boundary so that duplication of administration and work will not take place.</P>
    <P>I was party to a section 59 agreement where the Manager of Westmeath County Council bought land for road development purposes which contained a house.  He subsequently placed a tenant in that house under a section of the 1986 Housing Act and against the wishes of <Col N="1493" /> the local authority in his functional area; that was an abuse.  The Minister should intervene in those situations and make sure that the rights of local authorities are protected.  If necessary, certain regulations and sections of particular Acts that can be abused should be amended.</P>
    <P>Up to now roads are constructed on the basis of an annual allocation to a local authority which, can be £0.5 million or £1 million.  There is no indication of the exact situation for subsequent years and this is poor and bad planning.  I hope that will not be the case with the National Roads Authority.  I agree completely with Senator Cosgrave on this matter.  It is offensive that a local authority will get sufficient funds to plan, develop and construct a road to a certain point but will have no funds to complete it.  This appears to be a national disease affecting many local authorities.  It appears that lack of commitment or lack of something along the way prevents the original intention being carried through.  The National Roads Authority will now have overall responsibility and I hope that that bad element of road construction will be removed.</P>
    <P>I also wish to mention a practice that has developed around the country in recent times and this is farmers feeding silage from a road onto their land.  In some cases farmers are using the sides of the road as a loading bay or as a retention area for silage to be fed at intervals.  This is an obnoxious practice and should be eliminated.</P>
    <P>I understand that included in the Roads Bill are references to debris and so on but feeding silage is not mentioned. I ask the Minister to declare his intention to include it, if it is not already mentioned.</P>
    <P>The Athlone bypass, in my area, is a massive development costing £34 million. I compliment the Minister, officials at the Department of the Environment, local authorities, construction companies and all involved in this project, which is a credit to them, a gateway to the west. However, it will only be effective and fully beneficial to the west if there are further developments.  Although the <Col N="1494" /> Department has been forthcoming in relation to the bypass, which has been completed except for some compensatory works, arterial routes must be developed.  The national secondary road into Roscommon town must be developed, as well as the Tuam road into north Galway and South Mayo.  It is important that life and industry do not stop west of Athlone.  Otherwise, we will create the environment I mentioned earlier. There should be further developments in County Roscommon and in the neighbouring counties so that people in Ballyforan, Tuam, Ballygar, Roscommon or Castlerea will benefit.  The same benefits would also apply to the people of Portlaoise if a bypass was built there.</P>
    <P>The National Roads Authority has a responsibility above and beyond the national roads network.  The network must faciliate the regions and not take people out of them.  It should help to develop the regions because people will not stay where there is lack of economic activity.  Indeed, there have been progressive developments in rural areas. However, I wonder would they have located in those areas if they had known that the road which was planned by the local authority would not be developed. While there should be a national road network with a national authority responsible for it, we must not forget our regional and county road networks.  If we concentrate on economics and infrastructure we forget the people's needs.</P>
    <P>As a Government our responsibility is to provide infrastructural development. However, it must also cater for an improvement in the standard of life. Unless we do this, we will not achieve what we were elected to do.  We will not fulfil our obligation either if we provide people with a standard of living in an area in which they do not wish to live.</P>
    <P>I believe in the development of our regions, the way to do this is to develop further infrastructure in these areas and support existing infrastructure.  Otherwise we are not supporting the local population.  We can patronise people from rural communities and we speak in <Col N="1495" /> regional terms when we address assemblies in Europe, but we need to do something practical about the regions.  The national road network is certainly a priority but our responsibility as Members of this House is to protect the regional areas which are not always on the west coast; indeed, they can be quite close to the capital and are often forgotten.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill.  The Minister has experience of the local county council and he understands the concerns which local authority members have in relation to the removal of certain responsibilities. I do not see it as a major problem, provided there is co-operation and liaison. It is good that we have a national body to plan a national network and I have no doubt that it is in the best interests of the country.  It is the most effective way to use our European funds.  However, we need co-operation and liaison between the National Roads Authority and the local authorities.  The Minister must ensure that this takes place because he said in his speech that it is the intention of the National Roads Authority to liaise with the local authorities and to use their expertise in areas such as the purchase of land and design.  I understand the Minister has responsibility for this and as a former local authority member I have no doubt that he will find common ground in the interest of the country.</P>
    <P>I commend the Bill to the House and I am sure it will receive a thorough examination. We will have a further opportunity to speak on the various sections on Committee Stage.  We are about four years behind schedule, but better late than never.  This Bill must be passed so that the National Roads Authority can be established to use the Structural Funds over the next six or seven years.  The Authority must ensure that our time and money are spent wisely in the interests of the people.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House, I also welcome this Bill.  It is an important Bill because it refers to the roads which, as Senator Finneran said, <Col N="1496" /> account for only 6 per cent of our roads. They are the important roads because they are the economic backbone of the country.  Without a modern European standard system of roads, we cannot compete effectively in Europe.  It could be argued that, given our peripheral position on the outskirts of Europe and our remoteness from our markets, we should look for a more efficient road system than the European norm.  When goods leave our roads they still have a time-consuming and costly journey before they reach Europe.</P>
      <P>Roads are also crucial to our development because of the hurdles we face in regional development.  It stands to reason that if it is a disadvantage for us to be on the periphery of Europe, it is a double disadvantage for any business which must operate on the periphery of the periphery. That is exactly what many of our companies must do.  If we want to sustain jobs throughout the country, not just on the eastern seaboard but, Senator Finneran said, on the western seaboard also, we must develop our transport infrastructure as one of our top priorities, particularly when Europe is coming closer together.  I welcome this Bill but it does not have the right sense of urgency. A large slice of European Structural Funds is being allocated to these roads and I hope that will also apply to the next round.  Nevertheless we must ask if we are treating the problem urgently.</P>
      <P>This Bill is an essential part of our roads development.  It has proceeded through our Legislature, not at motorway speed, but at a pace more in line with a boreen full of potholes.  In 1993 we are debating the Roads Bill, 1991, which has been in preparation for about 18 months. It is a highly complex Bill.  It was processed in the other House and went through the mechanism of a special committee. Even so, the time would not persuade anybody that the Legislature considers roads a high priority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Another doubt about our sense of urgency arises when we look at the plans for roads in the years ahead.  There are plans stretching into the next century. Long-term planning is certainly fine, but <Col N="1497" /> many of the plans should be implemented soon.</P>
    <P>Our roads system is crucial to our ability to compete in the European market. This means competing now, next year and the year after, not in the early years of the 21st century.  The manufacturing businesses, perhaps the people for whom this is most important, have not succeeded in getting across to the public how important roads are to our future prosperity.</P>
    <P>It is not only manufacturers who benefit from good roads.  It is not often realised that the price of goods in our shops, the kind of things people buy week in and week out, is considerably affected by the cost of getting them to the shelves. In this country, largely because of our roads system, the cost of distribution has been traditionally high compared to international standards.  This has had a direct impact on the Irish cost of living. If we put a new urgency into our roads development, we must decide from where we will get the money.  That is why I am concerned that there is very little emphasis in the Bill &mdash; and in Government policy in general &mdash; on attracting private sector investment for our roads system.  We have the mechanisms for that and there are a few examples of private sector involvement.  However, private sector involvement in road development has not taken off in Ireland, which is a lost opportunity.</P>
    <P>In France a partnership approach between the State and the private sector can work well for the State.  This is not privatisation, because in the end the ownership of the road or bridge reverts to the State.  Rather, it is speeding up the road development process.  The availability of private capital means more projects can be taken on and progress made in a much shorter period of time.  This is an approval and we should copy especially as the EC does not care whether the matching funds come from the private or State sector.  Even with full EC support, road funding makes considerable demands on the Exchequer. We should see what more could be done to attract private sector investment, <Col N="1498" /> because clearly not enough is being done at the moment.</P>
    <P>There are two matters which will arise on Committee Stage which are really points of general principle.  The first is the provision about the Chairman of the National Roads Authority.  The Bill specifically gives the Minister the power to appoint an executive chairman, in other words to amalgamate the functions of Chairman of the Board with Chief Executive of the organisation.  However this is a mistake as in the business world the notion of combining these two rôles is now completely discredited, not just in these islands, but right around the world. Public companies in many other countries are now being forced by shareholders to separate the two roles.  This is happening because it has now generally accepted each role needs a different perspective. The two rôles do not necessarily have exactly the same interests and the combining of them in one person is not in the interest of the shareholders.</P>
    <P>I should stress that in talking about the undesirability of an executive chairman I do not intend to comment on the recent appointment in Aer Lingus.  I am concerned about the principle and that we are setting out to incorporate this bad practice into legislation.  We should do the opposite, go through legislation and take out the power to appoint an executive chairman.  We should not seek to perpetuate, or extend the power, as is being done in this Bill.</P>
    <P>I have had experience of both rôles.  I am the Chief Executive of a private sector company and I was Chairman of An Post for many years.  As a result of that experience I strongly believe in the separation of the two rôles.  There is a Chairman's job and a Chief Executive's job and organisation suffers if those two jobs are combined.  Will the Minister have second thoughts in regard to this power and give consideration to bringing in an amendment at a later stage to overcome the problem?</P>
    <P>My final point also raises an issue of general principle, the question of how quickly State boards publish their annual reports.  The Bill gives the Minister the <Col N="1499" /> power to require the National Roads Authority to report each year at a date to be set by him, but it does not set the date.  That should be laid down in legislation and it should be no later than three months after the end of the year. Many of our State companies report to their share holders, the public, so tardily that it is nothing short of a scandal.</P>
    <P>Companies on the Stock Exchange must report within a very short, set time. There is no reason for State bodies not being bound by the same rules as companies in the Stock Exchange.  At present, the reports coming out are more like historical documents than documents to which we should be looking for information. The world and the company will have moved on by the time we see those reports.  When we are regulating this, we should also put a stop to the practice where by the annual reports have to be vetted by the relevant Government Department.  This unnecessary vetting take months, the State body is reporting to us, its shareholders not to the Government Department.</P>
    <P>What we need from the NRA and from all State bodies is fast reporting to the public arena.  Speed in reporting is an important aspect of public accountability and we have paid too little attention to this in the past.  I hope this Bill can be amended to set a precedent in this area which would mark the beginning of a new approach to State body accountability.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AnnGallagher" hpid="Ms Gallagher Ms Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Ms Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I wish to preface my contribution by saying that at last somebody is doing something about the road network. I am sure everybody has heard the jokes about the potholes in County Cavan.  One joke which springs to mind is that the ears seen sticking out of potholes there are not of a rabbit but of a donkey. It is no joke.  People in County Cavan have difficulty selling their cars because the suspension has often been destroyed. Flat tyres are a certainty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One day while campaigning during the general election I had three consecutive flat tyres.  I thought it was a political ploy <Col N="1500" /> by my opponents but instead it affects everybody using those roads.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>We would not do that to the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnGallagher" hpid="Ms Gallagher Ms Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Ms Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The people of County Cavan &mdash; and I refer to them because the roads in that county are the worst in the country &mdash; suffer daily trying to navigate between the potholes which line the roads.  Last week I saw a woman fall from a motor bike which hit a huge pothole. She suffered severe facial injuries and now has a steel plate on one side of her face, facial scars and damaged eyesight. She was told by doctors that she was lucky.  I am not an engineer but it is obvious to anybody doomed to travel the roads of Cavan that repair work is not sufficient.  The roads are subsiding on both sides and repaired potholes continually disintegrate.  A considerable amount of investment and planning is required.</P>
      <P>The Roads Bill, 1991, has two main purposes.  First to establish a statutory National Roads Authority and secondly to revise the laws relating to public roads. The establishment of a National Roads Authority is long overdue.  If we compare the standard of our roads to those in Europe we are the poor relation when it comes to concrete infrastructures. Senator Quinn referred to the long, straight, wide and level roads of France. When one sees the advantages other countries possess one realises what is required here.  We suffer the natural disadvantage of being an island nation on the periphery of Europe when it comes to trade, tourism etc., but added to that we suffer from appalling infrastructural disadvatages.  We need to focus our attention on infrastructure so as to achieve a standard equal to that of Europe.  This will enable us to compete with our European counterparts in terms of trade, tourism and general services.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the proposed setting up of the NRA.  This Authority will have responsibility for planning and supervising the construction, improvement and maintenance of our network of <Col N="1501" /> national roads.  However, it will only develop national roads which account for less than 6 per cent of the total road mileage.  It will not help those people, to whom I have referred, who are doomed to travel along the secondary roads of County Cavan and County Monaghan.  I hope it will work towards providing a network of high standard roads to link all major Irish towns and ports.</P>
    <P>Members of this House know what I am talking about when I mention the sudden bump in the road when one crosses from one county to another on the same road.  Each local authority works on stretches of road within its county boundaries; there is no co-operation between local authorities in these matters and no common standard to be attained. The NRA will be responsible for the preparation of strategic plans for the development of the national roads.  It can, under this Bill, issue directions to local authorities to carry out specific functions. It will prepare or arrange for the preparation of road designs and maintenance programmes.  The new authority is given, in this Bill, sufficient powers to ensure that a common standard of national roads is attained.  This is an urgent requirement.</P>
    <P>Last weekend I attended the Labour Party Conference in County Waterford and I was delighted to see the good condition of the roads in that county.  I am aware also of the investment in motorways in County Dublin.  It annoys me that the standard of roads where I live fall far behind.  I ask the Minister to ensure fairness and to place greater emphasis on upgrading the roadways in the neglected northern part of this country.</P>
    <P>Is the Minister, Deputy Smith, aware that the only primary route in County Cavan, the N3 ends up in a river at Annagh Bridge?  The Minister recently visited Cavan town and I hope he did not arrive by helicopter.  If he travelled by road I would like to know how many jolts and bumps he suffered while travelling on Cavan roads?  It is only by travelling along those roads that one realises the seriousness of the problem.  It is not good enough to pay lip-service to road problems <Col N="1502" /> faced by the people of County Cavan and County Monaghan.  It is not enough to say that more money has been allocated this year than in previous years. This may be the case but increased costs negate any increase in the amount.  A major programme of investment in all categories of roads is required.  I ask the Minister to treat this area as an infrastructural disaster zone.  Cavan and Monaghan are situated along the Border.  We are ashamed and angry to witness the high standard of roads in Northern Ireland in comparison with our own.</P>
    <P>County Cavan and County Monaghan, because of their location, have no rail or sea link.  These counties are forced to rely totally on roadways for transportation purposes.  We have been scorned and ignored by previous Governments.</P>
    <P>Every request to Government to address the appalling condition of these roads has been cast aside.  When the Minister visited County Cavan he gave us little hope that our roads might ever be on a par with those in other counties. That amounts to blatant discrimination against the people who live in that area.</P>
    <P>The purpose of the NRA is to create a high standard of national roads.  If that is the case people should get their spades out and book into the Slieve Russell Hotel in County Cavan, because there is work to be done.  If this Government is serious about creating a proper network of roads, time and money must be spent. I urge the Minister to acknowledge the atrocious condition of the roads in County Cavan and County Monaghan. I live in County Monaghan but having travelled along the roads in County Cavan I realise that the condition of the roads is no joke.  County Cavan has the worst roads in Ireland.  A considerable amount of investment is needed there and would be cost-effective.  Temporary repairs do not work; the surfaces continue to be dotted with potholes.  With proper investment those roads would not require major maintenance for up to ten years.  A decent network would allow for competition with other counties in the areas of industry and tourism.  How can business and visitors be attracted to an <Col N="1503" /> area which is not accessible?  I urge the Minister to examine the appalling situation in County Cavan as a matter of urgency and to tackle it with all speed. This county cannot afford to wait any longer.</P>
    <P>The Bill is worthwhile.  It will, I hope, achieve a network of decent roads throughout this country and facilitate competition with our European counterparts. I welcome the fact that local authorities will be involved in the process at all levels because being at ground level, they are aware of the priorities.  The local authorities have the resources, the experience and the skills needed and the National Roads Authority must recognise their advantages in developing an overall network.  I also welcome the fact that the new authority will focus on promoting our case for EC assistance.  This will include the preparation of the elements of future operational programmes covering the roads and other transport sectors.  I hope this will achieve results.</P>
    <P>I am pleased to see a co-ordinated approach to our road infrastructure.  This will allow experience and specialist skills in road design built up by one local authority to be shared with others.  Until now, each local authority had been forced to operate in isolation.  The Authority deals only with national roads.  What happens the vast majority of roads not covered by the Authority?  Can a co-ordinated approach not be developed to upgrade these routes?  Why can local authorities not get European funding directly for our secondary and local roads?  Why can local authorities not decide where that European money should go when they know better than anybody else what the priorities are?  This is a serious issue.  I am concerned that we are neglecting our biggest problem by not improving the local roads which the majority of people use. I resent the fact that while money is directed at national routes, counties Cavan and Monaghan automatically suffer because their roads are not categorised as such, although their needs are much greater.  Money is being <Col N="1504" /> pumped into ring roads and dual carriageways in the east but more of that money should be allocated to improve the appalling roads in County Cavan so that I will finally be able to move out of second gear when travelling those roads and be relieved of the burden of negotiating the potholes and bends on every road in that county.</P>
    <P>This Bill is a start in the right direction and I welcome it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to speak immediately after Senator Gallagher.  Listening to her one would not realise she lives in Castleblayney.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnGallagher" hpid="Ms Gallagher Ms Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Ms Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>As I said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>One would swear she was a Cavan woman.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnGallagher" hpid="Ms Gallagher Ms Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Ms Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>I travel the Cavan roads every day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>The people of Monaghan would not be pleased to hear her speech dealt with Cavan alone.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask you to direct your remarks to the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AnnGallagher" hpid="Ms Gallagher Ms Gallagher">
      <NameTxt>Ms Gallagher</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator was not paying attention.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>She spends very little time in second gear.  She was nearly elected in the last general election, and that did not happen by travelling in second gear.</P>
      <P>Senator Gallagher made a very good speech.  The content was excellent but she could have spoken more about Castleblaney, Ballybay, Carrickmacross and the national primary which runs to Ardee.  It is a national primary road in name only.  I am glad to have the opportunity to speak on this Bill.  I assume every Senator will take the opportunity to discuss the roads in their constituencies because regardless of what part of Ireland one comes from, the road network leaves a lot to be desired.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Quinn is fortunate to be living in Dublin.  Where I come from, people <Col N="1505" /> believe all the money for roads is spent in Dublin, that one never sees a pothole there, and the proposed Euro-routes will be on the east coast.  That is the impression people have.  They are right because most of our national resources is spent on the east coast.  It is our duty to draw attention to that and to try to put it right.</P>
    <P>I will be looking for a fair share of the Cohesion and Structural Funds for Cavan and Monaghan because these funds will be the last bonanza from the EC.  Cavan and Monaghan will be looking for an injection of funds commensurate with their population.  For example, if £1 billion is allocated to Ireland from the Cohesion Fund on a population basis we want £30 million but as we have been disadvantaged in the past, we would need double that sum; Cavan and Monaghan would require £60 million.  It will be interesting to see how much they actually get.  If this country receives £8 billion from the Structural Funds over the next four or five years, Cavan and Monaghan will be looking for £240 million as a base figure.  Given the history of expenditure over the last ten, 15 or 20 years, they would expect that sum to be doubled to £460 million.  These markers have to be laid down.  Senator Gallagher and I will be keeping an eye on that.  She will be closer to the Government for the next few years and I am sure she will be in a position to ensure that the figures I have given will be reached, and even exceeded.  This must be done because it will be our last opportunity to bring about any sort of proper development.</P>
    <P>The National Roads Authority is a positive development; it is better to look at national roads from a national than a local viewpoint.  The county councils tend to look after their own areas.  If the National Roads Authority were responsible for the allocation of funds, people would feel more confident of getting their fair share.</P>
    <P>All over Ireland people believe that the constituency of the Minister for the Environment always receives money for housing, roads, sewerage services, water, etc. and it seems to be true.  That is one <Col N="1506" /> of the reasons politics and politicians become unpopular.  It is a commonly held view that Ministers sometimes misuse their power.  I am not saying they do; I am pointing out what is a commonly held view.</P>
    <P>People expect fair play and an evenhanded approach but they do not believe this is happening.  Public perception is what is important.  I hope this new Authority will redress the balance and provide more transparency ensuring that money is spent on the basis of national planning rather than ministerial pleasure.  Establishing the National Roads Authority is a good idea.</P>
    <P>When the Minister visits Monaghan early in June I advise him to drive in second gear after Ardee.  Perhaps the Minister of State, Deputy Hyland, will pass the message to him.  If two lorries meet on the national primary road between Ardee and Carrickmacross they are compelled to stop as the uneven terrain of the narrow road could cause a collision.  They must slow to a halt, then drive slowly past each other.  That is not the case in Roscommon because I have driven through that county in fifth gear many times.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is because there is a public representative in Roscommon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>Driving at the speed limit from Ardee to Carrickmacross means taking one's life in one's hands.  I cannot drive at the speed limit on that stretch of road.  It is a disgrace.  During the Seanad election campaign I had the pleasure of travelling through Wexford, the constituency of the Minister of State, Deputy Browne.  I wish he would drive through counties Monaghan or Cavan and see how the other half lives.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is a disgrace that traffic on the N2 must stop on meeting vehicles travelling in the opposite direction.  An employer who sends goods to Dublin or to another part of the country pays &mdash; in driver's salary and in fuel costs &mdash; for the time it takes the driver to stop the vehicle and start again.  An old truck being driven in <Col N="1507" /> low gear consumes a lot of fuel which can lead to significant costs.  If that happens regularly when travelling from Donegal to Dublin the extra cost puts the employer and the industry at a disadvantage.</P>
    <P>If the departmental officials and the Minister saw the national primary route between Ardee and Carrickmacross, they would consider it scandalous.  The road between Castleblaney and Monaghan town is also too narrow and not suitable for drivers who wish to travel at a reasonable speed.  That will have to be rectified with a decent national primary road.</P>
    <P>County Monaghan sets an example in local development for the rest of the country.  There is little multinational investment in Monaghan; most investment is from local sources.  In the Dáil I suggested to the then Minister for Industry and Commerce that Monaghan should be a role model for the industrial development of the rest of Ireland.  It is obvious that he did not pay attention to me.  Throughout County Monaghan there are signs of modern industrial development.  Travelling the county one is liable to see a shoe factory, a furniture factory, poultry production and mushroom farming.  The farming community in Monaghan is the best in the country. While the rest of the country discusses unemployment, the community in Monaghan has developed these industries and received little thanks.</P>
    <P>Industries depend on adequate roads; for example, mushrooms must get to the marketplace quickly.  Due to the road conditions I have described mushrooms produced in County Monaghan do not get to the market as fast as they might.  I believe the county is the largest mushroom supplier to the top end of the English market and the condition of roads has not helped them to reach that position. To maintain it we need assistance. In addition to the usual commercial difficulties, like the value of the punt, road conditions etc., inhibit the development and competitiveness of industry in Monaghan.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1508" /> A good national primary route in Monaghan would benefit everyone in the county.  People would save time travelling, they would have more leisure time and would be happier as a result.  Industries which transport goods would save on fuel and time costs.  Monaghan is entitled to the same treatment as other areas.  Is the county's national primary route poorly developed because it ends at Aughnacloy and the rest of the road, before reaching Donegal is in Northern Ireland?  Why was a tranche of additional Interreg funding not sought for the development of that road?</P>
    <P>Although the Department officials and the Minister do not realise it, the road is comparable to a boreen.  I understand that we will receive about £1 billion from the Cohesion Fund this year.  That money can only be spent on what is called trans-European networks or national primary routes.  Every boreen in Monaghan is part of that trans-European network.  As lorries leave boreens in Monaghan and carry goods on our so-called national primary roads to travel across Europe, these boreens qualify under that programme.  I want the Minister to take that into account.</P>
    <P>The food and furniture industries in Monaghan demand that money is spent on roads.  Although roads are below standard in every county, the regional and county roads in Cavan and Monaghan are hopelessly below standard.  The County Monaghan engineer estimated a few years ago that it would cost £26 million to bring the county roads up to a decent standard.  Monaghan County Council should receive £30 million for that purpose from the Cohesion Fund.  It is the most important county in Ireland for utilising local skills and local funding, at little cost to Government, for industrial development.  The county needs that funding.</P>
    <P>Two years ago I conducted a survey and discovered that it cost the people of Monaghan &mdash; industrialists or private individuals &mdash; about £5 million for damage to vehicles and property.  The problem is that many people cannot afford to repair <Col N="1509" /> their vehicles.  Cars are being driven around Monaghan that are not road-worthy because people cannot afford to repair damage for which they were not responsible.</P>
    <P>Monaghan County Council should receive £30 million from the Cohesion Fund, most of which should be spent on the network of county roads which are so important to job creation and maintenance in the county.  The satellite industries in Monaghan cannot afford to pay the high additional costs incurred by the damage caused to lorries travelling on bad roads.  We used our initiative to develop these industries but we are being penalised by high costs.  For some reason we have not received the funding we deserve.</P>
    <P>There should be an examination of the kind of loads which lorries transport down the boreens of Monaghan.  Foodstuffs and poultry products are transported to a central location for processing and there is also the usual run-of-the-mill business of conventional farming.</P>
    <P>We need help because our own resources are minimal, which is another Government problem.  If Monaghan and Cavan County Councils had their own resources, the problem would not exist. Monaghan County Council are spending about £900,000 on roads this year out of their own resources which is all they can afford.  We do not have any more money and we have a huge problem which we cannot tackle.</P>
    <P>It is a disgrace that when the Minister announced the block grant for roads in Monaghan, he added the Interreg funding to make the figures look good.  That funding is supposed to be additional, it is intended for Border areas.  The Minister added it to the block grant so that his colleagues in Monaghan could announce that the figures look good.  However, without the £350,000 Interreg funding, the figures are bad.</P>
    <P>It is a misuse of power to include those funds with the conventional Exchequer funding for roads in County Monaghan. It is an attempt to fool the people and to pretent that the Exchequer is doing its duty and being fair when it is not.  Next <Col N="1510" /> year the Minister should announce the Interreg funding on a different day to avoid confusing people.  When the Government announces funding for national primary roads it should be divided into Exchequer and EC funding to enable people to see how much money is coming from the Exchequer and the EC.</P>
    <P>The Minister would like to give the impression that he contributed £3.5 million towards the national primary road, which is not the case.  There should be transparency and honesty about these matters.  I am very annoyed about this matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>We have an answer for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>I am worried about Senator McGowan who has to travel to Donegal once or twice a week</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>We have bigger problems than roads.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>We have many problems. We also have a difficulty with regional roads.  The road from Dundalk to Longford is of very poor quality, on some of it one spends more time in the air than on the road.  Are the Minister and his Department planning for the next century? We have finite world resources in conventional fuels such as oil and gas.  At some time in the future they will disappear and before that they will get very scarce.  We will then be faced with huge costs.</P>
      <P>As Senator Gallagher said, there is no rail link to County Monaghan or County Donegal, people have to go to Sligo.  It is time that we looked to the future, admitted that the decisions in the fifties were wrong and that the rail links should be developed while money is available.  I will be asking the county councils in Louth, Monaghan, Cavan and the Northern authorities to assist us in getting a rail link from Dundalk, an existing terminal, up to Derry and across to Donegal.  Interreg funding could also be used for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is difficult to convince people that <Col N="1511" /> we should engage in forward planning and look to the future from different aspects.  Good, national primary routes should be a priority.  I know that Senator McGowan will support me on that.</P>
    <P>I would not like to be an industrialist in the north of Donegal.  It is difficult enough to cope with a bad national primary road between Donegal and Dublin but if, in the next century, there are difficulties with fuel supplies and so on, how will somebody in Culdaff in the northern end of the peninsula deliver goods to Dublin if the cost is prohibitive?  People talk about keeping the west alive but, without forward planning, it will suddenly come to a halt.  That would mean that people would not be able to leave which might be a good thing.</P>
    <P>There are many problems in County Monaghan with regard to tourism development.  We have the lowest earnings from tourism, even though we have many natural resources such as approximately 300 lakes, although some of them are small.  Many people are interested in the development of tourism and are working very hard at it.  Occasionally, when talking to such people one wonders why they bother being involved in tourism.</P>
    <P>An individual in Ballybay who is involved in the development of tourism and does promotional work in France, was in contact with tour operators there. They said they could not send buses to Ballybay because the roads are too narrow and that the bushes would remove the paint.  A bus operator could not allow that to happen.  How can that man develop his tourism earnings and those of the town and the area?</P>
    <P>There is great potential for tourism in Monaghan.  The waterways in that county are very good.  There is a fantastic development at Lough Muckno which has tremendous earning potential, but we need help in regard to roads.  Individuals in the Truagh region are proposing to develop the Bragan mountains to provide an amenity for outdoor activities. However, tourists will have to travel by road, because we do not have an airport. <Col N="1512" /> When some tourists come here via Dublin Airport, they are surprised at the poor quality of the roads, as national classed, particularly when they travel on the national primary route from Ardee to Carrickmacross.</P>
    <P>The Government is holding up the development of Monaghan.  It will not allow the county councils to raise their own resources or disburse funds to them either.  It is holding up the development of the best county in Ireland and we will not stand for it any longer.  I know I will be supported by many Members on this matter.  I welcome the Bill and the opportunity to discuss it.  I hope we will have more debates like this in the future and that we will give Senator Gallagher the chance to get out of second gear soon.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, welcome the opportunity to comment on the new Roads Bill.  Members involved in local authorities appreciate this because we have sought a review of the structures managing finance and design and the road network for many years.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Browne, to the House and I congratulate him on having achieved tremendous success in regard to the new dual carriageway to Wexford.  I hope this Bill will enable similar road networks to be built all over the country.</P>
      <P>Senator Cotter's interest in Donegal is welcome and I am sure he is sincere in saying he wants a railway there. However, why did they not do something about it when his Government was in power?  Fianna Fáil has a good representation in Donegal and we have continually fought the case for a rail link. While there is still room for improvement, we have reasonably good roads. The Sligo-Donegal road through to Ballyshannon is evidence of this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the establishment of the National Roads Authority because there was always a difficulty in relation to the structures in the previous system.  When the Department of the Environment makes its annual allocation, its engineers compromise with their counterparts in local authorities in regard to planning, <Col N="1513" /> but the elected local representatives are not involved.  This is not the proper way to do business because the elected representatives get the blame if anything goes wrong.  I have been an elected member of Donegal County Council for many years, and we did not have a proper input to planning.  We could propose what we liked, but when our engineers met those from the Department many of our decisions were not accepted.  None of us knew when the meetings took place. Any new Bill will be an improvement on that.</P>
    <P>Donegal has 4,000 miles of regional and county roads, but only 60 miles of national primary roads.  On numerous occasions over the last ten to 15 years, when we sought to upgrade a particular road, the county engineer and those from the Department of the Environment stopped us and we never knew why.  For the last 20 years traffic to the Inishowen peninsula has not gone through Derry, as it did in previous years, but proceeds via St. Johnstown into Bridgend and Buncrana.  These are second and third class roads and are carrying heavy juggernaut traffic.  There is a meat factory in Carrigans in Donegal served by narrow third grade roads.  I cannot understand why the engineers from the Department believe that the traffic from Strabane could be carried by these dangerous roads.  I am enthusiastic about this new Roads Bill and Members should talk about the situation in their own counties. The country should have a decent road network.</P>
    <P>Not long ago, I travelled by car from England to Rotterdam, to Belgium and into Germany.  There were at least 100 miles of straight autobahn passing through two borders with traffic lights at various intervals.  Our road network should not consist of few straight roads but there is a happy medium and people should be able to travel in safety.  Our structures must also be modernised because we will then get the best results from the money provided.</P>
    <P>The introduction of this Bill is timely, in so far as the Structural Funds now available must consider roads serving <Col N="1514" /> areas where there is potential for jobs. Killybegs is the fastest developing port in Ireland; it also has a fishmeal factory and industry developing on a large scale. Killybegs problem is that engineers from the Department of the Environment only recognise the national primary route between Donegal town and Mount-charles. The road between Mount-charles and Killybegs is not recognised as a national primary route and, therefore, money has not been spent on the section despite the route's importance to Killybegs.  I have never understood the logic of such decisions.  I hope the new Bill will bring about a new approach to roads structure, road management and alternative routes.</P>
    <P>Donegal County Council recently decided it could make more progress by giving contracts for roadworks to private companies.  There is an opportunity to examine this possibility on a national basis now.  The resources of the Department and the National Roads Authority must be made available to local authorities. Together the National Roads Authority, the Department of the Environment and local authorities must be able to assess whether better results can be obtained by contracting out roadworks.</P>
    <P>When one considers engineering structure, road design, the legal acquisition of land to widen roads and the seasonal nature of building roads, it is clear that there is huge waste on the part of local authorities.  This is because of the stop-start nature of roadworks.  In Donegal we have a machinery yard with plant, equipment and new lorries costing up to £35,000 each.  Drivers are employed on a yearly basis even though trucks are only working for three months of the year. Such a situation cannot be efficient.  I suggest careful study of how to achieve more efficiency.  Overtime will not be required to establish that there is a better way of organising roadworks.</P>
    <P>The Minister said there will be consultation between the National Roads Authority engineers and local authority members.  I look forward to consultations every year.  It is vital that the elected members of local authorities have an <Col N="1515" /> input rather than be told how money is going to be spent.  It is unacceptable for a Minister to say that he is going to spend £1 million on a road between Donegal town and Ballyshannon and that Donegal County Council cannot alter the plan. The National Roads Authority will be very welcome in Donegal.</P>
    <P>Several current affairs programmes, Marian Finucane's show of 5 April and the &ldquo;Late Late Show&rdquo; have highlighted the bishops' case for developing the west. The bishops are making the case that it costs 40 per cent more to transport goods from the west.  If you say something often enough and if you cry long enough and hard enough, you will convince people you are right.  I can prove that regardless of the condition of our roads the disadvantages we suffer in the west in producing goods and creating jobs are not attributable to our roads.  I have been briefed by a company in Letterkenny who employ 850 people producing yarn and selling it in Germany to a company producing the same commodity.  The company is delivering quality goods on time at a competitive price and they are increasing the size of its factory in Donegal. During my briefing, the question of roads and transport was not mentioned once.</P>
    <P>A business that is doing well and delivering goods by container to any part of Europe will not be put out of business because of transport costs.  Transport costs are not a big factor in the price of goods because transport companies have a margin that is adequate to cover places as far apart as Wexford and Mayo.</P>
    <P>The people in the west, including the bishops, should stop crying about disadvantages because they will cry themselves out of business.  The bishops are using every current affairs programme and every available platform to cry in the hope that someone will provide a cheque to build super roads in the west.  I hope that the roads in the west will be upgraded but to start on the understanding that business will not survive in the West until there is a vastly improved road network is a folly.  If we continue to <Col N="1516" /> believe that, and to preach it, we will never provide jobs for our young people in the west.</P>
    <P>The west, including Donegal, has many advantages and those people who are already established in business will not leave.  Of course we have our disappointments and businesses fail, but those who compete on the European market are not at a disadvantage because of the road structure in the West.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not accept that thesis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will sit down with Senator Cotter and prove that what I am saying is not just a theory.  I will produce a film of people involved in industry in Donegal and I will take the Senator to Donegal to meet them.  I will show him that those who believe these industrialists are at a disadvantage because of the state of the roads are wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BillCotter" hpid="Mr. Cotter Mr. Cotter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cotter</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senator McGowan reads the report on the Naas bypass he will see the savings involved in having good roads.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am offering Senator Cotter proof that the roads will not put a well organised export business trading on the European market at a disadvantage.</P>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity provided in this Bill for the development of small roads, however they are classified.  In County Donegal there are 4,000 miles of regional and county roads.  Many politicians including those from Europe say they want to save the family farm.  They talk about emigration and about people with six sons and daughters living on the side of the mountain on a lovely farm who tragically have to emigrate. However, they only use this type of farm situation to illustrate a point about something else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>People must be taught about the advantages of living in rural Ireland.  I have seen Irish emigrants living in slums in New York who would give their right arm to come back honourably to the little homestead on the side of the mountain. <Col N="1517" /> These are the people we must help.  We must provide a decent road into every part of Ireland, especially in a county like Donegal which has major potential for tourism whether in Glencolmcille or Glengesh.  We would like to upgrade Donegal's 4,000 miles of regional and county roads.  I hope the new Authority will bring a new approach to road maintenance and that funding will be made available to upgrade the regional and county roads so that road upgrading work is not neglected.</P>
    <P>One problem which concerns me is not covered in this Bill.  Most counties have a number of housing scheme roads.  A housing scheme road is nobody's responsibility at the present time.  Once the local authority gives planning permission for a housing scheme, the developer moves in, does the minimum of work and moves out.  Within a few years the road is in bad condition, and local authorities do not carry out maintenance on housing scheme roads.  I ask the Minister to include a provision in the Bill for maintenance of housing scheme roads by local authorities.  I have thought about how we could achieve this.  I will shortly be proposing that FÁS, the Department of Social Welfare and the local authorities each contribute towards the maintenance of housing scheme roads.  At the moment in some of our towns housing scheme roads are totally impassable.  This matter has been neglected and I ask the Minister to make sure that there is some heading in the Bill under which even minimal maintenance can be carried out by local authorities.</P>
    <P>Serious consultation with the NRA will be possible under the new system.  I welcome the dual carriageway that will be built between Belfast and Dublin, and the major road development to the south east, whether it is by Wexford or by Naas, because it develops a part of the country which has major tourist potential.  I want to see the road from Dublin to Longford, Mullingar, Sligo and up to Donegal and Derry brought up to the same standard. That proposition will be put to the National Road Authority.  I want the European link roads coming into the <Col N="1518" /> county to be matched by Irish roads.  I do not want to see the roads which are classified as Euro-routes in the North not classified as such in the South, because the required standard has not been reached.  I want Euro-routes to be built right across the country.  We will have an opportunity to say to the National Roads Authority that the road development plan must be understood by those who are elected to the local authorities representing the people on the ground.</P>
    <P>There has been discussion recently about maintenance responsibility and insurance liability with regard to footpaths. I was interested to hear recently that £150,000 has been provided for maintenance of footpaths in Dublin city while compensation paid out in respect of claims amounted to more than double that.  I do not know who made the statement.</P>
    <P>The people of Ireland demand higher standards of maintenance for national routes, secondary routes and footpaths. Yet, I was in Brussels not long ago and to my surprise the footpaths in the smallest village in Donegal are of a higher standard than the footpaths of the principal streets of Brussels.  I do not wish to indicate that what we have is good enough, but people can demand a standard that for financial reasons is not attainable.</P>
    <P>People in the west expect a fair deal and they will demand that from the National Roads Authority.  We do not accept that a motorway should be built between Belfast and Dublin, a modern train service and an airport connection to Dundalk provided elsewhere while the west is neglected.  There must be a balanced approach.  I ask the Minister to ensure that all parts of Ireland, receive a fair share of road development funding. There should be no disadvantage to living in Dingle or Dungloe as far as roads are concerned; there must be a level playing pitch.  We will demand that approach from the National Roads Authority.</P>
    <P>The most important provision of this Bill is the opportunity for elected people to be involved at a senior negotiating level.  That is an achievement because elected members were not allowed to <Col N="1519" /> participate in or have any influence on where money was spent.  I hope that situation will be altered.  I welcome this Bill and I encourage the Minister to proceed with all haste because the country will benefit from this new Roads Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CathyHonan" hpid="Ms Honan Ms Honan">
      <NameTxt>Ms Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>Like all the Members who have contributed I welcome the Bill and the establishment of a roads authority on a statutory basis.  The roads that will be looked after by the National Roads Authority, however, account for only 6 per cent of our total road mileage.  I know they account for about 35 per cent of total road traffic, and two-thirds of this is work-related, but the main concern of most Members seems to be the other 94 per cent of total road mileage.</P>
      <P>Like all the other Senators who have spoken I am concerned about county roads.  I know that substantial funding is available from Europe for national primary roads; yet, it has already been allocated by the time it comes down to county council level.  Therefore, county councillors have no choice but to spend the funds on national primary roads, and the actual amount of money over which councillors have discretion is small.</P>
      <P>In 1982 Laois County Council spent £1 million on county roads.  Ten years later, in 1992, in order to keep at the same level, they would have needed to spend £2 million.  The funds available to Laois County Council in 1992 for county roads were approximately £120,000.  If I was the County Engineer I would have difficulty in deciding how to spend £120,000 on a job that requires £2 million.  It is extraordinary that Laois County Council can even keep the roads in their present condition, even though that condition is far below the standards most people in the county want.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>From a business and trade point of view and for people travelling throughout the country, it is important to have a high standard of national primary roads.  We should have roads as good as any other country in Europe, but the vast majority of people living here bear the brunt of having bad county roads.  In fairness to <Col N="1520" /> Laois County Council, the roads in Laois are not the worst in the country.  Having travelled throughout the country during the Seanad election campaign, I have to agree with Senators Gallagher and Cotter that there are other counties whose roads are far worse than those in Laois.</P>
    <P>The one issue that is brought to our notice as public representatives is the condition of the roads throughout the country.  We are talking about rural development, about keeping people on the land and in small villages and towns. There is general agreement in this House, and among public representatives, that it is vital to keep people in small rural areas, and if we want to achieve that we have to do something about the condition of our roads.  People in rural Ireland are disadvantaged because they do not have motorways going through their areas.  In my own county of Laois some school buses will not travel on certain roads because of their poor condition, and it is not fair that the children and the people who live in those areas should be disadvantaged. Farmers are also complaining that creamery lorries will not go down certain roads.  If we want to keep people in rural areas &mdash; and I think that is vital &mdash; then we have to keep our roads in good condition to make it easy for people living there.  Their roads should be as good as city roads.</P>
    <P>There has been a move among certain county councillors, particularly those who are members of the General Council of County Councils, to have a percentage of road funds allocated to county roads, but this does not seem to have been possible. Regarding the first tranche of Structural Funds we received from the EC from 1989 to 1993, we did not make a submission that some of that money would be spent on county roads.  We made a submission seeking funding for national primary roads; that is what we got the money for and that is what we have to spend it on.  It is open to the Government, however, to seek to have a share of the funds given under the European Regional Development Fund allocated to non-primary and non-national roads.  I would like to ask the Minister, <Col N="1521" /> in applying for the second tranche of Structural Funds if we can make that application because we are talking about small amounts of money.  Such funds would go a long way towards improving the standard of roads throughout the country and if we could get even a small amount of this funding it would make a huge difference.</P>
    <P>Building and maintaining national primary roads is very expensive; it costs in the region of £1 million a mile.  Smaller county roads would not cost anything like that, so a small percentage of the funding from Brussels, if allocated fairly throughout the country could make a huge improvement and, I would suggest to the Minister, might be one way of solving our road problems.</P>
    <P>The IFA has made a submission for EC Structural Funds to be allocated for agriculture and rural development and that organisation made the same point when seeking this realloation of resources for expenditure on roads from the Regional Fund.  The IFA is talking about maintaining life in rural Ireland, encouraging people to stay there and giving them the same advantages as people who live in cities and towns.</P>
    <P>We tend to talk about major motorways going through Dublin and Cork, and it appears to people outside these areas that this is the only concern of public representatives.  From the debate here today however, the Minister can be in no doubt that the majority of public representatives are concerned about the condition of roads in their own rural areas.  I welcome the establishment of a National Roads Authority because many rural areas have national roads going through them.  I also welcome, as Senator McGowan has done, the fact that there would be a consultation process between local representatives in the counties and the roads authority.</P>
    <P>One other area in the Bill I would like to talk about is the system of tolls on national roads.  Senator Cosgrave said he would fight it tooth and nail, and that his party did not accept this.  If one is talking about co-financing certain bridges or roads with private enterprise, then our <Col N="1522" /> party would be willing to accept tolls in such circumstances, if it was a way of providing funds for improving the roads structure even though I accept the argument Senator Cosgrave was making about the motorist being crippled with road tax, taxes on petrol and car tax.</P>
    <P>The other areas I was going to talk about have been covered by other Senators and I would go along with most of what they have said.  I welcome the Bill, as well as the opportunity to speak about it in the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to this House.  If matters had been left to ourselves, as it was a number of years ago, we would not have a National Roads Authority or have any need for it. However, the EC, and EC funding, has made the establishment of such an authority possible.  I welcome the formation of the National Roads Authority and the Roads Bill, 1991.  I congratulate those involved in preparing submissions in relation to the Bill, and especially those who worked on this matter during the summer recess.  This Bill gives the necessary legislative back-up for the National Roads Authority to meet present-day needs.</P>
      <P>Investment in a national roads network is important.  While there has been developments in other areas, such as housing and telecommunications, it is only in the past few years that we have started to highlight the condition of the road network.  On the question of road safety, for example, there is a need for good roads to prevent, if possible, the accidents and deaths that have taken place on the bad roads over the years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Most Senators who speak on the Roads Bill refer to their own county.  County Donegal is dependent on its road network as it does not have a railway system. There is only one small airport at Carrickfin near Gweedore and it is of no great benefit to the producers in the Gweedore industrial estate who depend on the road system to deliver their goods to the port of Larne.  From the time they leave Gweedore until they arrive in Northern Ireland and go onto the Derry <Col N="1523" /> roads, these producers have to travel on some of the worst roads in the country. It adds to their transport costs and makes them less competitive than other producers in the rest of the country where roads are better.  Similarly, in Inishowen, McCarters, the company that established the firm, Fruit of the Loom, has to use a dreadful roads system for their vehicles before they get into Northern Ireland.</P>
    <P>As a regular traveller on the roads from Donegal to Dublin, I am forced to accept that the roads in Donegal are terrible, while those in Northern Ireland are excellent. It is a delight to travel on them, to drive through Tyrone to Monaghan where the bad roads begin.  They remain in bad condition through County Louth until one comes near to Dublin when they start to improve slightly.</P>
    <P>Funding for the national roads in Donegal this year will be £4.5 million.  I welcome the increase from £2.5 million in 1992 to £4.5 million for this year. However, of this figure, £1.5 million is being spent on one area, from Ballyshannon to Donegal town and while it is welcome it does not leave very much for the rest of the national route in the county.  There are 4,000 miles of road in County Donegal and only 60 miles of it is primary route.  This leaves very little money to upgrade the county and regional roads which are in a disgraceful condition.  This makes it very difficult for the farming community who are depending on the roads to carry out their business. Machinery using the roads deteriorate very rapidly.</P>
    <P>Areas like Inishowen, which have a great potential for tourism will never develop because the roads system makes it impossible.  People will not visit it.  In comparison with the autobahns in Germany, or the motorways in England, the roads in areas such as Donegal are extremely narrow and bad.  It is impossible to drive a bus or coach on some of these roads.</P>
    <P>I welcome the consideration given in the Bill with regard to the use of green areas and cycleways which are a norm in France or Germany.  It is not only a <Col N="1524" /> matter of constructing a road; these countries implement plans for cycleways, and they provide for the planting of trees and greenery to enhance the appearance of the roads.</P>
    <P>Money must be spent on upgrading the roads between Dublin, where they are reasonably good, and Northern Ireland and also from Northern Ireland into Donegal.  Donegal does not have a port, railway or airport system for getting goods out of the country.  It depends on good roads and they are badly needed. I was interested in Senator McGowan's views on the Wexford roads and I am pleased to see that the Minister, Deputy Browne, looks after his area.  Having driven on the roads of Mayo I can report that Padraig Flynn did the same when he was Minister.  If there is a possibility of Donegal getting a Minister for the Environment it would be most welcome.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerryReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>Bring back Neil Blaney.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaloney" hpid="Mr. Maloney Mr. Maloney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Maloney</NameTxt>
      <P>That was a long time ago, Senator.  I welcome the fact that the roads in those areas are being upgraded.</P>
      <P>There is to be much greater planning in respect of the national road network and this is to be welcomed.  When plans are being prepared it is good that the views of the local authorities will be considered. If the elected Members are unhappy with proposals at least they can make representations to the Minister. Furthermore, if agreement is not possible one can refer to the Minister and that is important.</P>
      <P>Regarding restrictions on roadside trading, there is not much wrong with this trading especially in the summer, when fruit and vegetables are on sale. Regarding the powers to control the drainage of public roads and associated matters such as deposits of dung and grit, there are roads that are used in a disgraceful manner by some people who dump along the roadside.  Any measures that will improve this situation should be taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Structural Funds should be used to integrate the road network with Northern Ireland where there are excellent roads. <Col N="1525" /> Any improvement to the roads here would reduce costs to industry and the costs of transport.  It would improve the way of life for people who live in areas like Donegal.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Satellite Channel Programmes:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Satellite Channel Programmes: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald) Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald)</NameTxt>
      <P>The proposer of the motion has 15 minutes, the seconder has ten minutes the Minister has 15 minutes and the proposer ten minutes to reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann calls on the Government, as a matter of urgency, to see what steps can be taken to prevent the transmission of pornographic material on satellite channels.</P>
      <P>I welcome to the House our Minister for Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht, Deputy M. Higgins.  It is a great opportunity for him to display his many talents that we in the Seanad know he possesses.  He made a major contribution as a Senator and he was a great ambassador for Seanad Éireann.  I look forward to his contribution as a Minister.  I welcome him to the House and congratulate him on his appointment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This motion calls on the Government, as a matter of urgency, to see what steps can be taken to prevent the transmission of pornographic material on satellite channels.  I understand an amendment has been put down and this side of the House is glad to accept this as an addendum but not as an amendment.  I support the suggestion in the amendment that the Seanad should accept television as an instrument of education, whether the programmes are on home channels or satellite channels.  Television is one of the greatest assets of the modern world. It is an educational facility coming into our homes daily, all year round.  I do not know of anyone who has not learned <Col N="1526" /> something positive from television.  If used properly it provides an opportunity to update one's education for example, in the area of current affairs one can find out what is happening in places like Australia, the United States or any other country.  The power of television is brought home to us on a daily basis when it is used in a positive manner.  In common with many others in his House, including the Minister, I have worked in the medium of television and I know how positive it can be and how it has promoted sport, industry and many other facets of life by bringing them into the home.</P>
    <P>There are exceptions to the rule and the one I am highlighting this evening is the new satellite receiver which can beam up to 30 channels into our homes.  Many of these channels provide a 24 hour service while others start at 5 o'clock in the evening and go on until 3 o'clock in the morning.  Many of these channels are exciting and I watch the sports channels in particular when I am at home.</P>
    <P>I am very grateful that the Minister considers the situation that has existed for the last number of months sufficiently serious and that he has come into the House to take this motion this evening. I recommend that the Government bring in regulations to prevent people in Ireland receiving the pornographic satellite station Red Hot Television.  The Government should make it a criminal offence to supply the decoders required to receive this hardcore service from Denmark if the issue cannot be resolved during what I understand is a 15 day consultation period.  The service known as Red Hot Television has thousands of Irish satellite subscribers and the screening of its sexually explicit contents is unacceptable.  It has the potential to cause great harm to children and adults, who may view it.  This material should not be available in Ireland simply because it is broadcast overseas.  The growth of satellite television in Ireland is at a rate of over 300 new installations each week. It is a very popular service particularly the sports channel.  That is one reason the service is growing here.</P>
    <P>The EC Commissioner in charge of the <Col N="1527" /> audio-visual group has no desire to see the directive used to create a free market in pornography.  I read in a magazine last week that the Director General of the European Commission audio-visual group, Collette Flesch, said that member state authorities have the means to stop such broadcasts.  They can take whatever measures necessary.  As far as the European Commission is concerned, the situation seems clear: it is up to member states to suspend such broadcasts.  In a debate in the House of Commons on 19 March 1993 Mr. Peter Brooke, MP, said that the broadcaster of the Red Hot Television Service and the European Commission had been notified that the British Government proposed to take action under Article 22 of the EC Broadcasting Directive 89/552.  Article 22, which deals with the protection of minors, provides for a member state to take action, where warranted, against a service coming from another member state in relation to the contents of a programme.  Mr. Brooke said that Article 22 lays down a 15 day period for consultations with the transmission state and the Commission.  If it was not possible to reach an agreement or settlement during this period, the British Government intended to take steps to restrict transmission of the service within the United Kingdom.</P>
    <P>A country as liberal as the United Kingdom, considers this service unfit to be beamed into British homes.  We should bear in mind that when you get a satellite receiver, with a satellite dish and satellite amplifier, you do not need a card of any description, as you do for Sky, to receive this channel.  It is being transmitted and it is not necessary to pay a fee to receive it.  This station started transmitting on channels 11 and 12 about four months ago.</P>
    <P>I received five or six complaints from parents and my advice was to have their channels decoded by the person who installed the satellite equipment.  That was done in the midland area but five weeks ago the channels were changed and the service began transmitting on <Col N="1528" /> channels 15 and 16.  As a result of this, I am raising this matter this evening.</P>
    <P>The United Kingdom wants transmission of the service withdrawn and Mr. Brooke said that he proposed to make an order under section 177 of the Broadcasting Act, 1990, proscribing Red Hot Television.  The Independent Television Commission notified him on 15 October 1992 and again on 1 February 1993 that it considers this service to be an unacceptable foreign satellite service within the meaning of section 177 of the Broadcasting Act, 1990.  Subject to the outcome of consultations which were required within a 15 day period in relation to the directive, he was satisfied that the making of such an order would in the public interest and compatible with the national obligation placed on him at the time, and he had no hesitation in making the recommendation to have them banned. Mr. Brooke said that once an order under section 177 was in force, it would become a criminal offence to support any foreign satellite service specified in section 178 of the Broadcasting Act, 1990.</P>
    <P>With your permission Sir, I would like to share my time with Senator Roche.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion because it is a common sense one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not favour measures which limit civil liberties or the rights of artistic expression.  I believe that self-regulation is better than State regulation.  I think censorship can be a two edged sword. Indeed, there are a number of ways to avoid the censor and by doing so the activity becomes more attractive.  While I do not favour restrictions, as I said I feel that self-regulation is better than State regulation.  As a society we have our norms and standards as to what is acceptable behaviour; as a civilised society we place limits on ourselves.  For example, we decide what can be broadcast, what can be published and what can be circulated in society.  We accept limitation on our rights in these matters.  We do <Col N="1529" /> this, not to restrict the individual, but to safeguard society.</P>
    <P>I question the efficiency of some forms of censorship and restriction.  For example, I have on two occasions in this House asked if section 31 is a form of censorship, and on other occasions I think the Minister would share my view on this matter.  Other forms of restrictions are, unfortunately, a necessary adjunct to the type of society we live in and the kind of technology available.  In 1988 both Houses enacted a Video Recordings Act which provided that the State had the right to limit and control the distribution of video material.  The aim of that Bill was to limit the spread of violent and sexually explicit material. When that Act was passing through both Houses speakers on all sides agreed that pornography was an assault on values which society generally accepted.  Moreover, speakers also accepted that pornography was an assault on the individual and on his dignity.  It was felt that women were the main victims of pornography and they were portrayed as objects rather than as persons.  Violence, which is a hallmark of video pornography, was also seen as being dangerous.  These videos frequently portray violence in a manner which is uninhibited and promotes the view that what is abnormal is normal and what is horrific is acceptable.  People's decency and care for their fellow human beings can be eroded by exposure to this material.</P>
    <P>The satellite television transmissions offer a means to side-step the issue.  New technologies from Denmark, a country which does not share our values, provide an opportunity for unacceptable material to be beamed into our homes.  The proposals in the motion are sensible.  They are not an assault on liberty or on the right of expression.  They attempt to regulate new technology as we have regulated existing technologies, publications, material exposed on the stage or material broadcast on radio or television within the State.  It is sensible to accept this proposal.</P>
    <P>I would like to say a few words on the amendment.  If all the words after &ldquo;taken <Col N="1530" /> to&rdquo; were deleted an entirely different focus would be given to the motion.  Like Senator Cassidy, I would have no problem with the amendment as an addendum to the motion.  It would be a sensible addendum.  I do not think Senator O'Toole, Senator Henry or Senator Norris would accept that sexually explicit material which demeans the individual and attacks womanhood should be allowed to be transmitted without any form of control and I do not think this is what they would wish.  As they are not in the House at present we must wait to hear from them.  However, I think this would be the effect if their motion was accepted.</P>
    <P>The idea that satellite television should be used in an educational and positive manner is a good one.  I believe that there is tremendous educational material available on satellite channels.  I have been at war for a number of years with Cablelink about their refusal to transmit TV5.  It is an excellent French language channel which would offer positive benefits.  I know that recently French teachers asked for its transmission.  I suggest that the House endorse the motion and that Senator Norris's proposed amendment should be taken as an addendum to it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>No way.  I have never heard such drivel.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Norris has now arrived.  It is a pity he was not here to hear the earlier part of the contribution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I was listening to it and I have never heard such pompous drivel in my life.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a pity that Senator Norris, when he arrives late&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not late.  I was working in my office and I saw Senator Roche read every word of his speech.  He was fascinated by it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;tries to disguise his embarrassment by bluster and fuss.  He <Col N="1531" /> will have the opportunity to make his point and to defend pornography and the dehumanisation of the individual which pornography represents.  I will listen to Senator Norris with more manners than he listened to me.</P>
      <P>I was suggesting that little divides us on these issues and that the proposed amendment would be acceptable to all sides.  Certainly, I would accept it because I believe satellite television is a tremendous medium for education.  It is a pity Senator Norris cannot show some common sense.  However, I have seconded the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Patronising, pompous drivel.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I made the point that Senator Norris's amendment&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not my amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;the proposal by Senator Henry, Senator O'Toole and Senator Norris would negate the motion. I also made the point that the benefits of the motion and the amendment could be achieved if Senator Norris and his compatriots showed a little common sense.  However, this is not the case.  I have formally seconded the motion.  I think it is a sensible one but, unfortunately, I must oppose the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Minister for Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht (Mr. M. Higgins) Minister for Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht (Mr. M. Higgins)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht (Mr. M. Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>Ar an gcéad dul síos tá áthas orm a bheith arais sa Seanad.  Tá súil agam go mbeidh ócáidí fiúntacha ann amach anseo nuair is féidir liom ráitisí a dhéanamh agus páirt a ghlacadh i ndíospóireachtaí.</P>
      <P>I am grateful for the warm welcome I have received here today.  At times I look back on my period here form 1973-77 and 1982-87 and I am delighted the Seanad has lost none of its vigour or depth of its exchanges.  I thank Senator Cassidy and Senator Roche for their contributions on this topic and I look forward to hearing the views of other speakers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The technology of broadcasting has <Col N="1532" /> meant broadcasting services in one country could always be received to some degree in neighbouring countries.  In Ireland we have seen the development of significant cable and MMDS industries, based primarily on the accidental or fortuitous overspill of United Kingdom traditional television services.  I believe television viewers in this country have gained enormously from the variety and cultural diversity of the increased choice of programmes provided under the &ldquo;open skies&rdquo; policy adopted by successive Governments.</P>
    <P>Over the past five to ten years, broadcasting has benefited from the revolution which took place in communications technology.  We now have a plethora of satellite television services which deliberately cater for an international audience. In response to the growing internationalisation of broadcasting services brought about by these developments, it has been clear for some time that if broadcasting is to be regulated at all, such regulation should be international at least to some degree.  A vast European market for the work of European broadcasters has evolved and it is important that European programme makers, including Irish programme makers, get fair access to television airwaves.</P>
    <P>Free flow of broadcasting services across European frontiers is a basic requirement if the European audiovisual sector is to achieve its full potential.  I expect the audiovisual industry in Ireland to benefit from the legislative quotas on European works for which the Directive provides.  My views on the potential of the Irish audiovisual sector are well known.  My announced legislative intentions in relation to this have been welcomed by a wide range of opinion in this country.</P>
    <P>EC Directive 89/552 on transfrontier broadcasting activities was adopted on 3 October 1989 after much debate and consideration.  Senator Cassidy has already referred to this Directive, which brought together many strands of sometimes contrary opinion.  It was a breakthrough in broadcasting policy and <Col N="1533" /> evidence of the recognition of the importance of this sector.  The primary objective of the Directive is to promote the free flow of broadcasting services across national boundaries by means of cable and other retransmission systems.</P>
    <P>To achieve this objective, it was considered necessary to establish a common European set of standards in a number of critical broadcasting areas; advertising, sponsorship and programme responsibilities. With regard to programme responsibilities, Article 22 of the Directive states the following:</P>
    <P>Member States shall take appropriate measures to ensure that television broadcasts by broadcasters under their jurisdiction do not include programmes which might seriously impair the physical, mental or moral development of minors, in particular those that involve pornography or gratuitous violence.  [I am glad the seconder included remarks on violence.] This provision shall extend to other programmes which are likely to impair the physical, mental or moral development of minors, except where it is ensured, by selecting the time of the broadcast or by any technical measure, that minors in the area of transmission will not normally hear or see such broadcasts.</P>
    <P>Member States shall also ensure that broadcasts do not contain any incitement to hatred on grounds of race, sex, religion or nationality.</P>
    <P>Articles 2 and 3 of the Directive require member states to ensure that all television broadcasters under their jurisdiction, including satellite broadcasters, comply with the provisions of the Directive. Article 2 requires member states to ensure freedom of reception of programming and not to restrict the retransmission of such television broadcasts emanating from other member states.</P>
    <P>This Article also sets out a procedure whereby member states may provisionally suspend retransmissions of television broadcasts via cable or other relay systems from other member states if the broadcast concerned manifestly, <Col N="1534" /> seriously and gravely infringes Article 22. Such infringements have occurred repeatedly.  Responsibility for the regulation of cable and MMDS systems rests with the Minister for Transport, Energy and Communications.</P>
    <P>Under Statutory Instrument 251 of 1991, Irish broadcasters have to comply with Article 22 of Directive 89/552/EC. It is a matter for other member states to ensure broadcasters operating under their jurisdiction are obliged to comply with the terms of the Directive.</P>
    <P>I am aware of the transmission of satellite broadcasts intended primarily for reception in other EC member states which comprise almost entirely explicit sexual material.  However, as far as I am aware, such channels are not freely available here.  I believe such broadcasts are encoded and one would have to go to some trouble and expense to obtain them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>It is true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M. Higgins Mr. M. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>My information is that they do not fall unwanted into the living rooms of Ireland but require a conscious decision to obtain them.  Where parents have acquired the necessary equipment to view the channel, I consider they would have the primary responsibility for preventing minors viewing the programmes.</P>
      <P>I share the Senators distaste of and distress at the transmission of pornographic material on satellite television channels.  I would prefer to see a world where pornography &mdash; and I include gratuitously explicit violence as well as sexual pornography &mdash; was not made, was not transmitted and where there was no demand.  Over the years in broadcasting I have been more worried by the growth of gratuitous violence than by anything else on television programmes. It is important that we address this issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have to strike a balance.  Many <Col N="1535" /> people who want total freedom also want another form of regulation.  They are confined by a paradox from which I would like to release them but it is a difficult question to resolve.</P>
    <P>My view of television and broadcasting generally is a different one and it will become apparent as I comprehensively review broadcasting in television and radio.  I believe in a theory of the communicative order.  We are talking about citizens entitled to rights as opposed to a set of market segments with purchasing power.  I am consciously following this philosophical first principle in everything I do in film and broadcasting.  It is not confusing.  One has a right to a broadcasting system irrespective of one's income power.</P>
    <P>There are those who suggest we should all be viewed as market segments.  Raymond Williams put it much better than I when he said we must ensure we are the arrow, not the target.</P>
    <P>I share the concern of Senators.  Pornography and gratuitous violence degrades makers, participants and viewers. It is an affront to humanity &mdash; women and men &mdash; and to human values.  Let me stress immediately I am not against sex and violence being portrayed in a realistic and justifiable way.  Such matters are real issues which must be tackled by programme makers.  Again it is not easy when dealing with different cultures to define what is erotic and what is pornographic. There is the difficult issue of different standards of taste and decency between countries and between people. In some countries &mdash; and I do not believe this implies their populations are generally depraved &mdash; the transmission of pornography at certain times is permitted. In others, even where the sale or transmission of pornography is outlawed, so-called &ldquo;adult entertainment&rdquo; television services have been licensed by the authorities.</P>
    <P>The complex question of freedom of expression and how this is interpreted in different countries, where such freedoms came at enormous cost in human terms, also arises.  I must also make it clear that <Col N="1536" /> while I support a legislative regime which bans the transmission of pornography, I do not believe that the content of television programmes is a matter for which any Government Minister should have responsibility.</P>
    <P>Senators will be aware of measures announced recently &mdash; and they were referred to by Senator Cassidy &mdash; in the UK to inhibit reception of a particular channel known as Red Hot Television &mdash; red hot Dutch in a previous incarnation &mdash; recently gained some notoriety, this action is two-fold and involves both the provisions of the transfrontier broadcasting directive and domestic UK legislation. Under their national legislation they intend to ban the sale and advertising for sale of decoders necessary to receive the service.  There is no corresponding broadcasting legislation here. There is no equivalent to section 199 as quoted.</P>
    <P>The UK authorities have also indicated that they intend to prohibit the service from being relayed on cable services and my information is that they have informed the Danish authorities &mdash; the programmes are transmitted from Denmark &mdash; that they regard transmission of the service as a breach of Article 22 of the broadcasting directive.  They hope the Danish Government will respond by prohibiting transmission.  The Dutch authorities have already withdrawn permission for the transmission of the service from the Netherlands.</P>
    <P>It is likely that the action of the UK authorities will be challenged in the courts.  Indeed statements have already been given to the press indicating that those responsible will take court action. However, I understand that the UK action has the backing of the EC Commission and the Commission has reiterated the view that member states are obliged to take action against broadcasts which breach Article 22 of the directive.</P>
    <P>In my view, the prevention of transmission of such programmes is by far the most effective way of dealing with this type of difficulty.  The prevention of reception of pornographic material directly from a satellite presents practical <Col N="1537" /> problems &mdash; one would have to ban the sale or possession of the equipment necessary to decode the transmissions. This would be very difficult to police. One thinks immediately, for example, of how one would assert possession and use, what difficulties would be involved there, and which ones might infringe individual and domestic liberties.</P>
    <P>The experience gained by the Red Hot Television episode will be useful in determining if there are loopholes in the directive or in our own legislation which could be exploited by pornographic channel operators.  Under our broadcasting legislation no one can be licensed as a broadcaster other than RTÉ or a person under contract to the Independent Radio and Television Commission.  It may, however, become necessary to consider the introduction of legislative provisions such as those invoked by the UK authorities with regard to the sale of reception equipment, no matter how difficult they may be to put into practice.  If the measures taken by the UK authorities succeed in putting the channel off the air, there may be no need for new legislative provisions in Irish law.</P>
    <P>It is important not to be too narrow in our approach to matters such as these. We must try to ensure that quality programming remains the first choice of viewers.  We must give responsible and talented programme makers access to the television audiences.  We must make sure that our broadcasting regimes &mdash; both national and international &mdash; are such that audiences can feel that they are the most important element of broadcasting policy, the arrow not the target.  We must allow them to have the best in every sense of the term.</P>
    <P>We must guard against too much fragmentation of the market which will set up sections of our community as easy targets for all kinds of drivel.  As regulators we must refuse to allow our communities to be regarded simply as a market to be exploited without responsibility. I regard public service broadcasting as a major bulwark of this policy and I would add a fourth precept to the well tried trio of public service broadcasting <Col N="1538" /> fundamentals.  As well as being informed, educated and entertained, I believe the audience must also be involved.</P>
    <P>Regarding European educational programmes on satellite channels, I am not entirely sure as to the meaning of this part of the motion.  There are a number of satellites used for television broadcasts which give coverage to this country.  Any school or person with the necessary receiving equipment can receive these channels in the same way as those individuals who have already chosen to obtain satellite entertainment and sports channels.  I am sympathetic to the increased use of technology in education. However, better use of those channels and technology should be made for educational purposes.</P>
    <P>Obviously, I have no function in ensuring other administrations use satellite channels to disseminate their educational broadcasts &mdash; it is entirely a matter for the relevant authorities to decide on the transmission method of their choice. Once they are transmitted by a satellite, which gives the appropriate coverage, it is a matter for the schools or the person concerned to decide if they wish to invest in the necessary receiving equipment.</P>
    <P>Senators are, of course, correct in recognising the potential of satellite communications in education and dissemination of culture.  Indeed, one of the dilemmas of international communications policy is how, in a satellite age, we can retain democratic principles within a broadcasting policy.  The technology is already so far advanced one is bound only by one's imagination &mdash; and unfortunately money &mdash; in the uses to which it can be put.  I am aware of distance learning experiments which involved the transmission of material from this country rather than its receipt.  In so far as regulatory authorities enter this picture, the use of satellite transmission equipment is the function of the Minister for Transport, Energy and Communications.</P>
    <P>As I said, I am looking forward to contributions from other speakers. However, I ask the House not to take too hard a line at present.  Senators will <Col N="1539" /> be aware that I am formulating proposals for broadcasting legislation for the long term and can rest assured that I will take into account their views in relation to the matter raised and the future uses of television, satellite, etc., in my deliberations.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and congratulate him on an enlightened response which, I must point out is completely at variance with the response of the proposer of the motion and Senator Roche.  I welcome this broad shift in the new coalition&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>Rubbish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;that allows such discussion and differences when dealing with motions of this kind.  I have never heard in this House, two such differing speeches as those made by the Minister and Senator Cassidy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>Strength and diversity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>After reading Senator Cassidy's motion I feared it was part of the xenophobia we have become used to and, having listened to his speech, my fears were confirmed.  Senator Cassidy referred to the British Tory Party and his great ally, in this argument, was Mr. Peter Brooke, the former Secretary of State for Northern Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>We are partners in Europe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an alliance which I hope will prevail.  Senator Cassidy will have to do better than to use the British Tory Party as his chief ally in his pursuit of purity in Ireland.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask that Senator Ross be allowed make his contribution without continuous interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1540" />
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I remind Senator Roche that this is not a meeting of Wicklow County Council.</P>
      <P>An article in the <i>Independent</i> Magazine, 16 January 1993, says that when the Irish, who have very popular cable services, realise what the EC directive means, a row of almighty proportions is likely to break out.  This directive was agreed in March 1989 and came into effect in March 1991.  Four years later, Senators Cassidy and Roche wake up to the existence of this directive, express great shock and horror to the House and want something done about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>With respect, we are not speaking about the directive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Minister said they are far too late.  The time to bring this up was in 1989 when Senator Cassidy was in this House&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas Chathaoirleach An Leas Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to ask Senator Roche and Senator Cassidy to allow Senator Ross to make his contribution without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and when Senator Roche was in the other House.  Their concerns have emerged now because they have been reading the British House of Commons debates and I congratulate them on that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Untrue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, my concern is not caused by reading those debates but by&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to remind Senator Roche that that is not a point of order.  Senator Ross without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Where did the Senator learn about this?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Roche is new to this House and may not understand the order <Col N="1541" /> of this House or the fact that this House is extremely civilised.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask Senator Ross to address his remarks through the Chair.  I remind Senators that this is a serious debate and I ask for silence for Senator Ross.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister said that these channels are not freely available and that people have to go to some trouble and expense to obtain them.  The Minister made a pertinent point which the proposers of this motion should take into account, when he said:</P>
      <P>My information is that they do not fall unwanted into the living rooms of Ireland but require a conscious decision to obtain them.  Where the parents have acquired the necessary equipment to view the channel, I consider that they would have the primary responsibility for the protection of minors from viewing the programme.</P>
      <P>Everybody in this House want to protect vulnerable minors from pornography of the sort which Senator Cassidy described but we have to talk about this in a practical and not in a sanctimonious way.</P>
      <P>Under the EC regulations there is little we can do about the broadcasting of pornographic programmes by satellite into this country because they are legal under the rules and standards of the countries from which they are broadcast.  They may only be stopped in the country of origin. There are measures which can be taken in this country to restrict those broadcasts&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>Nobody wants to do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;by attempting to stop people advertising and by stopping the sale of decoders.  The transmissions come from Denmark and Holland and it is in those countries that the programmes have to be stopped.  They must be stopped at source.  The programmes cannot be banned from this country <Col N="1542" /> either technologically or legally and I ask the Senators to take that to heart when considering this motion.  It really is far too late in that sense.  We can &mdash; if Senators wish &mdash; put an enormous amount of pressure on the countries from which these particular broadcasts are transmitted.  We should not adopt the subjective view that Senators Cassidy and Roche took of censorship.  Senators must hear what is permissible and what is not. Senator Roche said we had morals and standards in Irish life which were acceptable&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the Senator's view?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;but he did not say what those morals and standards were.  Censorship is extremely dangerous because Fianna Fáil censorship is very different to Labour Party censorship and that is perfectly clear&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator knows nothing about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;from what we heard today from the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>Transmission is the issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I doubt whether I should get involved in this ball game between Senator Ross and Senator Cassidy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator's speech will be dissected with great interest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>I hear the voice o Senator O'Toole whose amendment is too clever by half.  It is framed to act like a blunderbuss to blow the motion away As a Democrat, I believe that people are entitled to put down motions which regardless of whether they are accepted are entitled to be debated and should not be mummified by clever amendment such as that of Senator O'Toole.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I learned all about it last week and was just putting it into practice I am a very quick learner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1543" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>When I was campaigning against the common market, as it then was, and colleagues were campaigning for it, I was never warned of problems of pornography coming from Europe.  I was told jobs and technology would come from Europe but nobody told me about dirty movies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Sex had not been invented then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>There was no sex before satellites.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>Nobody was warned about it.  One could say it is one of the prices we pay for the open market.  We have to be careful when we talk about censorship because the Irish have disgraced themselves more than most in relation to censorship.  I hope we never see a similar situation again.  The key issues here are transmissions and European broadcasting.  It is not about thought police going around to houses.</P>
      <P>Nobody in this House would grieve for the porn merchants &mdash; whether in Amsterdam or Dublin &mdash; who make substantial sums of money through &ldquo;movie making&rdquo; which essentially involves the degradation of women, children and men.  It is a big industry and one that should not be encouraged.  Most people would agree that the transmission of hard core pornography should be resisted.  It should be resisted by not allowing the satellite to be used to enrich the few who are producing and broadcasting pornography. There has to be some regulation; rights and freedoms carry responsibilities.  Who would argue that snuff movies which portray the killing of fellow human beings should be allowed under any kind of licence?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Movies with a hard core pornography content should not be broadcast in any civilised state or international community. What can we do?  As the Minister said there is very little one can do about the reception of these channels.  It has to be dealt with in the context of transmission in the broad European context. It would be as difficult to stop reception <Col N="1544" /> as it would be to stop a radiowave.  There is nothing one can do about it nor should there be, in my view.</P>
    <P>In relation to television and the powerful effect it can have, particularly on young people, some system of regulation, applied in a liberal way, is a necessary safeguard.  The only other method to control television viewing in homes is parental control.  Cork Multichannel, for example, transmits about 20 channels one of which, a German channel called Channel 18, transmits, not hardcore porn, but material unsuitable for young people.  One has to opt out to avoid reception of that channel.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Do you watch it?  Do you enjoy it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>It is unsuitable for those who are not used to such programmes.  I spent my fifteenth birthday in Venezuela when the Senator was probably being cosseted by his mother.</P>
      <P>If one does not want to receive this channel one must opt out.  Many people who avail of the channels are not aware of what is on offer; they realise there are sports channels, BBC1, BBC2, German channels and others but they are not aware of the programme content being transmitted.  I think that one should have to opt to receive that channel rather than opt out.  Parents may not realise that they have access to this channel or realise the content of the channel's programmes until perhaps they discover that when the children should have been safely tucked in bed they were instead watching an exciting movie involving four or five women and one or two men.  Then the parents contact the cable company and have the reception cut off.  I believe they should be obliged to opt in for reception of that channel rather than opt out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>That is fair enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the only change I would make there.  The Minister for Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht, Deputy Higgins, made it clear that we should not force him to proceed any quicker as he is <Col N="1545" /> in office for just 80 days.  He is conscious not only of the need for regulations but also the necessity to have a liberal regime both in broadcasting and in the arts and I support him on this matter.</P>
      <P>I support this motion, not because I believe the Government has a great role to play apart from controlling the transmission of hardcore porn, but as a protest against the porn merchants who believe there is a market in this country for their product.  I wish to be associated with that protest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>To delete all words after &ldquo;taken to&rdquo; and substitute the following:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;ensure that European education programmes be made available to Irish homes and schools via the satellite channels.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>One would get the impression, when listening to the proposer of the motion, that there was no sex in Ireland before satellite broadcasting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>There was in Cork.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I give Senator Magner and the Minister full marks for making speeches which opposed everything Senator Cassidy said, and I hope the proposer notices it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not be so facetious.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I will give the House an easy option; support the amendment and I will support the main motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>Support the motion then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I am utterly opposed to pornography.  It demeans the men and women who are forced to participate in it for money.  It is violence of the worst kind; it is worse than domestic violence or the violence of the battlefield.  It takes away human dignity and is bad in every way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1546" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>That is nonsense.  It is worse than killing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Toole, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not mind.  I am in favour of free speech, not censorship.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is saying pornography is worse than violence on the battlefield?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>It is obscene to say it is worse than the battlefield &mdash; people are killed on the battlefield.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Magner, you must allow Senator O'Toole to make his contribution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not want the Senators to be censored.  I leave that to others.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Toole should speak to the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Nobody wishes to encourage the transmission of pornography.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>Why vote against it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know how many people have a satellite dish.  I live in the country, unlike most people here who live in urban areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>Why vote against it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Roche, I am surprised at you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I am just pointing out his hypocrisy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I have set up my own satellite dish.  I have the receiver for this particular channel but I do not get the channel because, as the Minister has out lined, I would need a decoder and would have to sign up with the station in Denmark or in Amsterdam.  The children do <Col N="1547" /> not have access to the station and the Minister is correct in saying that, just as he is incorrect in saying that educational television is available on satellite to schools and houses throughout country.</P>
      <P>Educational television may be available to between 20 and 50 educational institutions that have enough money to buy the custom-made dish and special recorder required and also to pay the European authorities who transmit the programmes.  It is not widely available and it is misleading the Minister to advise him otherwise.  I have sought the relevant information on the matter and I can make it available.  Over the past two days I have had meetings with the Channel Four authorities in Dublin because they are concerned that Ireland is the only European country that does not have educational television available in primary schools.</P>
      <P>This motion is simply another diversion from real issues.  The real issue is that television is one of the most educative tools available to educators, parents or the community and it should be wisely used.</P>
      <P>I direct the attention of the House to a more important aspect of satellite television which I outlined in the House a week ago.  I put forward a proposal to the European Community that, in accordance with Article 126 of the Maastricht Treaty, a European educational broadcasting service should be established and be available to Ireland.  I make the point again this week as it is absolutely unfair that our children should be deprived of this service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister said that it was up to the national authorities of other European countries to make the necessary arrangements to broadcast their material by satellite. That is not what I am proposing. My proposal is that there should be a European broadcasting service in respect of educational television.  Already schools throughout Europe communicate with each other through the medium of satellite in European-funded programmes. Specialised equipment is made <Col N="1548" /> available to the schools so that they can exchange information and speak to each other using telephones, modems, computers, satellites and televisions.  That is the way forward.  That is what satellite television is about.</P>
    <P>I do not know how this pornographic channel is received.  No child can have access to it unless the parents make it available in the home.  That is why the motion, while it is not unimportant, is irrelevant to what is happening in Irish society today.  People in my area who want to receive foreign channels must have a satellite dish because they are not on a cable system as are urban residents.  I urge the Government to look at this fair and rational amendment to the motion which seeks to move this debate forward positively to assist Irish schoolchildren.</P>
    <P>I told the story recently in this House of an Irish educator, who is now Chief Education Officer in one of the border counties, who went to Zambia or another African country to set up educational broadcasting in the 1960s and 1970s. When he returned from having set it up in a developing country, he found there was no educational broadcasting service available in this country.  There has been a minor movement in that direction aimed at post-primary pupils, which is to be welcomed, but it is only a beginning.</P>
    <P>I have over the last ten years organised a number of conferences on educational television and the only people available with expertise in this matter were from ITV and the BBC in the North of Ireland. It is extraordinary that the only television programmes on the teaching of Irish available on this island are being produced, transmitted and made available by the BBC in Belfast.  That is surely a reflection on Irish society.  The people who came to Ireland recently to discuss making Channel Four television available for Irish primary schools, met with an official of the Department of Education who said he would be worried in case the content of these British programmes were not culturally neutral and might therefore damage our poor impressionable Irish minds.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1549" /> I find it extraordinary that the proposer of this moton will go to such lengths about something which is not creating a problem.  He is publicising a channel which most people do not know how to find and which is not advertised in Irish newspapers.  Last night I switched through all 40 television channels.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has two minutes left.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but this is interesting technical information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>We will give you a hand. Vote against pornography.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Most of the channels have been scrambled.  I am one of those who refuse to pay extra money for a decorder.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMagner" hpid="Mr. Magner Mr. Magner">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Magner</NameTxt>
      <P>Where would you find the time?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a 24-hour service. There is no freely available access to this channel.  Senator Cassidy may have misled the House which I am sure was not his intention.  He viewed this channel in a place where it was available by arrangement.  I do not know how much time Senator Cassidy has spent watching this channel which I have not seen myself. I do not know how available it is in the midlands.  I ask him to support the amendment and to do something positive for the next generation of Irish people rather than worry about something which is largely unavailable.  He should put his energies into positive and progressive action on behalf of the people of Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>Put the amendment down as an addendum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment being seconded?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, I was told I could not second it immediately but I am very happy to second it now.  When I was listening to some of the contributions the <Col N="1550" /> words of James Joyce in <i>A Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man</i> came into my mind &mdash; I am not quite sure why &mdash; that: &ldquo;Rody Kickham was a decent fellow but Nasty Roche was a stink.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I have rarely heard such pious humbug. The Minister made the principal point which I would have made that one must make a conscious act of choice in order to get this material.  It requires a satellite dish and a decoder.  In those areas where this material can be received it is scrambled. I asked some of the Members concerned, and I will spare their blushes by not naming them, which of them had seen this material and apparently only one of them had.  He complained that it reduced the revenue in the entertainment business so at least we know that this debate is about vulgar market economics and has nothing to do with&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>Humbug.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I could quote the conversation which took place in the anteroom.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>Humbug, absolute humbug.  We are against pornography.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I was struck by the absolute lack of conviction of Senator Cassidy who read his speech from beginning to end in a voice which suggested utter boredom. If he wants to kill this thing dead he should apply to star in one of those movies himself.  There is a danger here with regard to censorship which I oppose. I was watching this debate in my office; I could not bear to sit in the Chamber and listen to it.  I think it is outrageous and ridiculous of Senator Roche to say I was in dereliction of my duties because I was not in the Chamber.  It is a tradition in this House not to refer to the absence of Members.  I was working in my office and listening to Senators reading scripts on something about which they felt so intensely passionate that if there had been a meter reading vocal pitch it would have registered dead level because the voices were monotones.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1551" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I must ask the Senator to address himself to the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I am addressing myself to the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, in proposing an amendment is it in order for the Senator to refer to both the amendment and the main motion?  That has been a long tradition of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I was interested and amused that the parliamentary debates of the House of Commons were referred to and Senator Ross did an excellent job in exposing the nonsense behind them.  I am amazed that anybody in this country would take a headline from England in matters of civil liberty.  Who are they fooling, what do they know about the situation?  Have they heard of Clause 28, a noxious Thatcherite attempt at thought control, where the presentation of a positive image of alternative sexuality is a criminal offence?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you in favour of pornography?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes I am.  Do you know what pornography means?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Norris, without further interruptions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>He had such difficulty making his own speech that he is trying to cobble one together by interrupting other people's.  As I have said on a number of previous occasions, the word pornography comes from two Greek stems <i>porne</i> and <i>graphe</i>&mdash; the writings of prostitutes.  That is all it means.  The Senator is talking about obscenity, I presume?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I was talking about the obscenity of violence.  I am surprised the Senator is in favour of its transmission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1552" />
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very dangerous to attempt to censor people's options.  The one person on the Government side who claimed to have seen some of this material indicated that it consisted of various, not particularly polymorphous perverse, forms of human sexual intercourse.  This is a form of relaxation which adults should have the option to avail of.  The only reason people watch it is because it is a sexual stimulus and it facilitates the act of masturbation which is the safest form of safe sex available.  If people want to consume this material in the privacy of their own homes then I could not care less.  Unlike some of the other Members I have not scanned the airwaves looking for this material and with my 20 year old television set I very much doubt if I could receive it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is lucky not to receive it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>When I did come into the Chamber I detected a very curious pong and it was the whiff of nauseating self-congratulation from some of the Government side.  We hear about countries such as Holland, Denmark and the Scandinavian countries and think we are so much better.  We have a higher rate of abortion than Holland, a higher rate of infectious venereal disease and practically the highest rate of AIDS transmission about which we still cannot tell the truth.  We condemn Holland and Denmark &mdash; Protestant countries, you could not blame them, it is invincible ignorance I have no doubt &mdash; as dreadful moral cesspits.  They have a far healthier attitude towards sexuality than many of the people whose conversations I have heard in the Dáil Bar but I would not breach confidentiality by repeating.  We ought to have done with this kind of hypocrisy we heard this evening.  There seems to be a whiff of it in the air.  Is it because we are coming into Holy Week? I understand that Wicklow County Council recently attempted to ban the book <i>Forbidden Fruit</i> by Annie Murphy. There is a creeping mentality of censorship <Col N="1553" /> about and I am afraid we are liable to make fools of ourselves.</P>
      <P>The Minister in a detailed, balanced and wise speech &mdash; if he will not be damaged by praise from people such as I &mdash; indicated a very usefully neutral moral line.  Although he was on the side of what I would consider real morality, he did not adopt the pious morality of some of the other people; he also indicated the technical difficulties in trying to prevent not only the transmission of this material, but its reception as well.</P>
      <P>There was a time when I wondered if some people in this country were aware of the world outside Ireland.  We have expanded our horizons and we believe there is a place called Europe and we are a member of it.  There are countries outside the European Community that are not covered by this kind of directive. I am old enough to remember Radio Caroline, where they broke all the broadcast regulations by broadcasting from a boat.  If people want to broadcast pornography, there are many ways around it and they cannot be stopped by this kind of motion.</P>
      <P>The Minister quoted article 22 of the directive, &ldquo;to ensure that broadcasts do not contain any incitement to hatred on grounds of race, sex, religion or nationality&rdquo;. I hope it will also include &ldquo;sexual orientation&rdquo;.  I was horrified to see a headline in a Galway paper deliberately inciting hatred over the participation of homosexual groups in the St. Patrick's Day parade.  I am referring it to the Director of Public Prosecutions to find out if the incitement to hatred legislation has teeth.  This paper was sent to me by a heterosexual married woman.  These are the real issues, in my opinion.</P>
      <P>Somebody mentioned &ldquo;snuff&rdquo; movies; of course they are an abomination.  It is tragic that anyone would want to watch this type of material.  I do not know whether people are killed in these films, and I hope they are not, but we should deal with these films at the source.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I could not care less about explicit <Col N="1554" /> sexual material.  We are all sexual beings and the sooner we wake up to it the better.  There was talk about the United Kingdom and the measures they are introducing &mdash; what a laugh.  They legally sold to the Gulf states electronic instruments designed to torture human beings. Retired members of MI5 have been training the Khmer Rouge and have collaborated with the Indonesians in the genocide in East Timor.  With their friends, the Americans, they were involved in war crimes during the Gulf conflict and the same British tabloid newspapers from which the Senator got his information gloried in the sinking of the <i>General Belgrano</i>, and the deaths of innocent young men who were pressed ganged onto the ship.  That is a real obscenity, not a couple of people having intercourse on television.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before I call Senator Mooney, I join in giving a warm welcome to the Minister, Deputy Higgins, to the House and wish him luck in his office.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I echo your sentiments in welcoming the Minister.  I am delighted he is here.  I found his speech very interesting.  I wonder if Senator Norris, who has left the Chamber, is watching on television&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should not refer to the absence of a Member.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I find it incredible in the aftermath of the horrific killing of Jamie Bolger in Liverpool that there has been a wide ranging debate in the British media and in the British Parliament &mdash; I make no apologies for referring to our larger neighbour &mdash; about the direction British and European society is taking.  We are all a part of this &ldquo;Europeanisation&rdquo;.  I find it extraordinary that we should listen to Senator Norris, a man who has a particular sexual orientation and must be <Col N="1555" /> prejudiced by that sexual orientation, a man who has stated publicly he is homosexual and proud of it, so I am not insulting him; I could not care less about his sexual orientation, but when he comes into this House and expounds on sexual matters&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I remind the Senator that he should not refer to the personal life of a Member.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I must in the context of this motion; we are all influenced by our attitudes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask Senator Mooney to speak to the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel I am justified in rebutting much of what Senator Norris has said and he is joined by the general secretary of an educational body who is supposed to be protecting the interests of young people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Toole is not here to defend himself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry he is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Senator to speak to the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not mention his name.</P>
      <P>This is a timely motion and I applaud Senator Cassidy for bringing it before the House.  I also compliment the Minister on his speech, and perhaps I should repeat what he said: &ldquo;I share the Senator's distaste of and distress at the transmission of pornographic material on satellite television channels.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have a copy of today's <i>Daily Telegraph</i> and I am grateful to the journalist, Nicola Tyrer, for outlining a litany of horrors.  I am not talking about Red Hot Television, I am talking about the existing satellite channels that are available <Col N="1556" /> without a coding card.  I fear for the future of terrestrial television transmission. By the next century, we will be enveloped by satellite transmission. Indeed, Miss Tyrer refers to this in her article and says that, in the past week, and I quote:</P>
    <P>I have watched people being slit open by circular saws, a woman's eye pierced by a harpoon, a red hot poker being plunged into a woman's body, a close up of a man's neck being broken complete with crunching sound effect, a man having his head crushed so violently his eye bursts from it socket.</P>
    <P>These, she says, were highlights of her television week, and she was not viewing Red Hot Television.</P>
    <P>I get angry when I hear the liberal intelligentia acting as apologists for what they call the free and liberal society. There are constraints in these societies and in every democracy.  The Minister said one must seek a balance between hard-won freedoms of expression and the common good.  I will always come down on the side of the latter when it comes to pornography, because children will be affected.</P>
    <P>In this House it was said that satellite television has small audiences only and that it was not of major concern.  Sky Television has 2.2 million subscribers and more than 250,000 of them are Irish. Although Sky channels are available by subscription only and the films shown are available in video shops, Sky denies that Sky Movies Plus concentrates on violence. However, it is interesting to note that Sky Movies stopped submitting their films to the British censor four years ago because the cuts being called for by the UK censor, Mr. Ferman, were unacceptable. Mr. Ferman, who, incidentally, has initiated the first study in 20 years of what young offenders watch on television, has been told by a psychiatrist who works with convicted killers that these young people often have obsessive video viewing habits, watching films all through <Col N="1557" /> the night and sleeping in daylight hours. Apparently, the Kung Fu series is a great favourite.</P>
    <P>It is interesting that Mr. Curran, an exprisoner who served a life sentence for murder, is so convinced there is a connection between screen violence and behaviour that he recently appeared on Central Television to warn broadcasters that they were playing with fire.  He says that prisoners had access to any films they wished to watch.  Interestingly enough, they did not watch Red Hot Dutch or films showing sexual violence or gratuitous sex that Senator Norris and others talked about.  It was the nightmare films like the Freddy series that proved popular with prisoners.  These films are freely available to children to buy or rent in video shops without their ever watching satellite television.</P>
    <P>Mr. Ferman, the UK censor said:</P>
    <P>What we are watching is the beginning of the media society which is what life will be in the 21st century.  Films will be beamed in at all hours because they will be coming from parts of the world operating on different time zones.  They may well include video nasties.  We won't be able to regulate what comes from other continents.  We will have to begin to think how we are going to raise our children and grandchildren so that they can survive a world like that.</P>
    <P>Miss Tyrer says that her week's viewing left her &ldquo;shocked at the horrifying images we deem entertainment for adults, let alone the unsupervised, unloved children who undoubtedly are also seeing them&rdquo;. She is shocked, too, at the duplicity of our so-called moral guardians, a duplicity that mirrors the Janus-like personality of Mr. Murdoch who owns Sky Movies, a man who refers to himself as a born again Christian.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps he is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is somewhat spurious <Col N="1558" /> of Senator Norris to refer to the illegal activity of Radio Caroline.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the Senator to refrain from mentioning people who cannot defend themselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>A Senator on the other side of the House made a comparison between Radio Caroline and pornography. I hardly think the musical activities of Radio Caroline which I, too, enjoyed could be in any way equated with screen pornography.</P>
      <P>Mr. Joao de Deus Pinheiro, the EC Commissioner for audio-visual policy said that the measures outlined by the United Kingdom Government in relation to the proposal to ban the Red Hot Dutch channel were compatible with EC law and that Brussels would not be raising any objections.  I understand that Red Hot Television, which was originally called Red Hot Dutch, is thought to be transmitted via satellite from Denmark, and is received by subscribers using decoders sold under licence from a Dutch-registered channel.  To date the Commission has been unable to confirm where the broadcast is established, or which member state has jurisdiction over the channel, but Mr. de Deus Pinheiro said that member states are obliged to take action against broadcasts which, and I quote, &ldquo;might impair the physical, mental or moral development of minors, in particular those that involve pornography or gratuitous violence&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>In asking the House to support this motion I have to say that I am very disappointed with those who have supported the amendment and who have tried to separate an issue on educational television from a very serious debate on pornographic material being transmitted via satellite.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to share my time with Senator Henry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1559" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and wish him well in his office. I find myself in broad agreement with much the Minister has told the House this evening.  I will not refer to Senator Roche and Senator Magner because they are not here other than to say that I agree with some of the remarks that were made earlier.  It is dangerous for the State to get involved in areas of personal morality where civil liberties might be infringed. However, having said that, I accept that society has a right to regulate how in its broadest terms it conducts itself; we have to accept certain limitations on our freedom for the good of society.</P>
      <P>There is public disquiet about this matter.  On a local radio station at home there was a debate on it several weeks ago and it became apparent that some people are confused as to the difference between satellite television, cable television and video recordings &mdash; they have jumbled them all together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>That is obvious.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>We have a law regulating the licensing of outlets and so on, namely, the Video Recordings Act, 1989 and there is an adequate degree of regulation provided by that legislation to deal with video nasties.  We must also consider the area of television.</P>
      <P>I also find it offensive to suggest that the people of Denmark, Holland or other European countries are in some way not as civilised or as good as the people of Ireland.  I have seen no evidence on my travels in Europe that the people in any of these countries are less civilised or less good than people in Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The difficulty in defining pornography has been apparent during this debate. What is pornography?  Senator Cassidy's definition of pornography, my definition of pornography and the definition offered by Senator Norris, whom I am not <Col N="1560" /> allowed to refer to because he is absent, are vastly different definitions of pornography.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Maybe his absence is deliberate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>The definition of pornography and the extent to which the State can regulate it are very subjective matters.  At one time <i>Lady Chatterly's Lover</i> was regarded as pornography and there was a famous court case which established that objectively it was not pornography.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Stick to the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Obscenity is precisely the point I am coming to.  We need to draw certain distinctions here.  It is obscene to see the crumpled body of a child on a street in Warrington; it is obscene to see people starving in the Third World; and it is obscene to see what is happening in Bosnia.  We are subjected to such obscenity on prime time television during news bulletins and nobody can tell me that has no effect on young impressionable minds.  Let us get our perspective in order.  Of course, there are distasteful things: it is obscene to talk about &ldquo;snuff&rdquo; movies and so on.  Yet, where does one draw the line?  That is difficult.  Let us put into perspective our definitions of obscenity and pornography.</P>
      <P>I have more confidence in our young people than some of the Members of this House, as I said previously when the Seanad were discussing the availability of condomns.  There seems to be a presumption abroad that young people either do not understand or are not aware of these matters.  For goodness sake, let us live in the real world.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>The violent society is the real world.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>We are the people who created the violent society in which these <Col N="1561" /> young people are forced to live.  We are the people responsible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>We are trying to stop it here tonight.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Has TV no role?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>TV is a persuasive medium and it is obviously something we need to be concerned about but I have difficulty in supporting the motion.  There is a simple solution to these problems.  As a previous speaker said, one has to make a conscious decision to allow these things into their home.  What about parental responsibility; is the State always to be in <i>loco parentis</i>?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>In this instance, yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it appropriate that parents may, at their will, leave their home to go to the public house and come home polluted while their children watch these matters on television?  There is a simple solution: press the button and turn the television off.  The parents are in the pub and we are going to decide for them.</P>
      <P>Senator Cassidy had no knowledge whether I was going to support this motion.  I submit it is possible to support both the motion and the amendment.  I do not see the relationship between the two other than to say that last week's motion and its amendment may be related to the fact that we have an amendment to this motion this evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>The motion was put down three weeks ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment was not. If it is true that we cannot prevent transmission of this kind, and I accept that this is probably the case under European law, there are individual responsibilities involved.  That is not to say the State should not examine these matters closely.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1562" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>As a woman I am against pornography because most of it is directed against women and children. The main problem is the way in which it links violence and sex.  I am very anxious to know how much research has been done by those who put down the motion. Erotica should not be confused with pornography. I would like the results of the research into this motion to be produced before we make a definite decision.</P>
      <P>Concern has been expressed for minors but most pornography is bought and watched by middle aged males.  Children have very little interest in pornography. The worrying thing about pornography is the expression of violence in association with sex which naturally none of us wants to see.  The suggestion has been made that middle aged male parents will go out to the pub, leaving their children at home where these channels are being beamed in.  As Senator Dardis said, it is possible to turn off the television.  Technology has gone even further.  It is now possible to buy equipment which when linked to the television allows certain channels to be made non-operational so that only suitable channels can be watched in the absence of a parent or guardian.</P>
      <P>I admit to having bourgeois habits and when our family eats dinner in the kitchen we often have the television on in the background with the sound turned down.  Sometimes the conversation in the kitchen coincides with something interesting on the television and we can turn up the sound.  Last Sunday night at 9 o'clock in a programme which was supposed to be about male sterility there was a shocking scene which this House would have found extremely objectionable, and that was on a channel which is beamed into everyone's home.</P>
      <P>Since I have come into this House we have discussed sex on several occasions and every time it has been in association with violence.  Tonight it has been in association with sin.  We should make a determined effort to get away from associating sex with violence and sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1563" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I must ask the Senator to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>Naturally I would not want pornography on Irish television but let us assess what pornography is and also look very carefully, as people in Cork have done, at the possibility of having educational channels on Dublin television.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryKelly" hpid="Mr. Kelly Mr. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the motion.  I am disappointed that there is an amendment to it and that the amendment changes the motion radically.  It has been an excellent addendum rather than an amendment.  I wholeheartedly support any move towards broadening the education field. It worries me to have to choose between the amendment and the motion.  The motion is very serious.  Until Senator Henry's contribution I thought I was in a little boys' club to judge from the flippant and nasty irrelevant remarks that were flying across the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>On both sides.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryKelly" hpid="Ms Kelly Ms Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Ms Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Statements were made such as &ldquo;this motion was absolutely irrelevant to Irish society today&rdquo; by one speaker on the opposite side; another comment was &ldquo;not creating a problem in Ireland today&rdquo;.  I wonder if they are living in the same country as I, where day after day we see in our papers accounts of rape trials, attacks on women and so on.  Why is there this outburst of violence against women all of a sudden?  It must be prompted in some small part by what people, as Senator Henry said, particularly middle aged men, are watching on television.  I am not worried about pornography in the privacy of one's own home where it can be controlled.  My main worry is that this pornography is shown regularly on large screens in public houses, usually after closing time.  I found myself in such a public house in a rural part of County Limerick.  I was very embarrassed as one of the few women there at the time.  I found the comments <Col N="1564" /> being passed on women in general degrading.  I could not see how any man, after watching that programme, could have respect for women.  The Minister said:</P>
      <P>I would prefer to see a world where pornography, and I include gratuitously explicit violence as well as sexual pornography, was not made, was not transmitted and where there was no demand.  I believe that such material degrades makers, participants and viewers.</P>
      <P>The average pornographic movie shows women as totally mindless and exploited. There is an element of sado-masochism in pornography.  The image portrayed of the women in the movies is that they actually enjoy the violence inflicted on them.</P>
      <P>The women who take part in these movies are drugged and do not know what is going on.  The impression given to the viewer is that all women behave like that, that all women like violence connected with sex.  What is also very worrying is that many of the makers of pornographic films are now resorting to younger and younger women to the extent where child abuse as distinct from sexual activity is now featured.</P>
      <P>I recognise that it is very hard to define the difference between erotica and pornography, but if you see pornography you will recognise it.  Pornography can be identified by its attitude to women.  There is no respect shown to the woman involved in pornography.  It does not have to be described because instinctively you know that this lack of respect of women is part of the culture of pornography.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I was saddened to find that one of the prominent speakers in the Chamber did not condemn hard core pornography. One speaker agreed with pornography but later reversed this view and agreed that he did not approve of hard core pornography.  I was disappointed by the attitude from the opposite side of the <Col N="1565" /> House in not seeing this as a serious problem that is affecting our society.  I do not want to see and I do not want my daughters to see, these films.  If there is some way we can ensure that these films are not shown on large screens in public places, if there is some way we can express our abhorrence of this kind of pornography, without infringing on civil liberties, I would agree with it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  The debate has been quite interesting and there are a few points I would like to make.  We do not want too much censorship, we do not want pornography but, at the same time we do not want to limit the freedoms we enjoy. I welcome the Minister's approach to this matter.  Censorship must be handled very carefully.  The State has a bad history in the whole area of censorship; not alone has it banned books and films but at certain stages university students were not allowed to express views against the Establishment.  We do not want to go back to that stage.  A more liberal regime in the whole area of censorship is welcome but it has to be qualified with common sense and sensitivity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have censorship laws; for example, some years ago we passed the Video Recordings Act.  The dilemma is that some of the material coming in would not be allowed in video form because it would contravene the Video Recordings Act, 1989.  Our laws do not allow these videos to come in but, on the other hand, they can come in over the airwaves.  Censorship should not limit freedom but it should be applied with common sense and sensitivity.  Channels featuring explicit violence and depicting women in a degrading and dehumanising way are unacceptable.  It is not right that women are portrayed at the receiving end of the most brutal and sadistic treatment.  We cannot accept, no matter what levels of freedom we aspire to, that this should be the case because we are living in what we believe is a civilised society.  Society must <Col N="1566" /> set its standards in this area and we must try to introduce controls to meet those standards as far as possible.</P>
    <P>I would like to refer to one matter which has been highlighted, that is taking responsibility for the viewing habits of young people.  The primary responsibility lies with parents.  The State cannot do the parents' job and we must not take over their role.  Perhaps we should advise parents that they have a responsibility in that matter but we cannot, through our laws, take over their responsibility.  Parents should be aware of what their children are viewing and control it.  To limit the freedom of individuals generally, because parents are not doing their job, is hardly the way to go about it.</P>
    <P>Many of the films are uninhibited in their depiction of violence.  They are also realistic and there is no doubt they have an effect on impressionable young people and, sometimes, on mature people.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry" hpid="Dr. Henry Dr. Henry">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
      <P>Middle-aged men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanNeville" hpid="Mr. Neville Mr. Neville">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Neville</NameTxt>
      <P>They can lead to crime against innocent people.  They can create a tolerance level whereby violence becomes acceptable so you are naturally going to have more violence.  We need certain controls but it is difficult to get the mix right.  We should not limit freedom and we must ensure that the primary responsibility for the viewing habits of young people lies with parents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senator Lydon wishes to come in at this stage, he has about four minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>I was listening here to the champions of pornography who make out that what they are trying to remedy are the inhibitions on our instincts because of prudish traditions from which they are trying to release us.  They are trying, they claim, to enable us to be more vital and feeling, to be ourselves in the sexual realm; yet, what pornography achieves is the opposite.  In it, the images and words <Col N="1567" /> usurp the natural functions of instinct and instead of natural loving feelings moving towards meeting another human being, we have an intense mental concoction of often brutal imagery, as in the films on these satellite channels where rape and other gross acts of sadism are frequent. The effect of these mental brutalities is to disregard the person as being one of the characters.  We can see in girlie magazines the titillating way in which the girl is discussed; the photographic exploitation of her as an object destroys her as a person of equality&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I do not mind us going back to the Middle Ages but I ask Senator Lydon not to read from a script.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>Somebody mentioned D. H. Lawrence&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Is Senator Lydon reading his speech?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask you to resume your seat for a moment, Senator Ross.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonLydon" hpid="Mr. Lydon Mr. Lydon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lydon</NameTxt>
      <P>D.H. Lawrence said:</P>
      <P>Even I would censor genuine pornography rigorously.  You can recognise it by the insult it offers in a variable dissention of the human spirit.  Pornography is the attempt to insult sex, to do dirt on it, the insult to a vital human relationship, ugly and cheap. They make the human nudity ugly and degraded and they make the sexual act trivial, cheap and nasty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is an increasing body of evidence that shows, without a shadow of doubt, that pornography has a terrible effect on society and on human beings.  I do not want to go into a long debate at this stage but it is accepted that pornogrphy has this effect.  It is up to the Minister responsible to take action.  I guarantee that if there was a war and some channel was <Col N="1568" /> beaming propaganda in from outside, it could be blocked.  We have to take this action.</P>
    <P>There is no doubt in my mind that pornography dehumanises persons, particularly women who are generally the object of violence and sex.  We have only to watch the effects of it on British society as Senator Mooney mentioned.  If we allow it in here the same thing will happen.  We must take a stand and stop these films being beamed in.  I do not know how to do it but I know it can be done.  If there was a will to do it it would be done.  I ask the Minister to take action in the matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted I proposed the motion because many genuine fears and concerns have been expressed in the House.  This problem is something that can be tackled in the new broadcasting legislation.  I have every confidence the Minister will take on board the serious views expressed in relation to what is going on.  Since we started this debate I checked to see if my facts were correct in relation to the signal and its operation.  I want to place on the record that in order to watch Sky television in the midlands, and in all rural Ireland, viewers must have a card for the News, Films, Gold and Sport channels.  I ask the Minister to take these facts on board because many Senators seem to be confused about a satellite dish receiver and cable television. Under the cable system a card is required to receive all channels.</P>
      <P>In Ireland there are now 500,000 subscribers to the cable or satellite system.  I am a reasonably liberal person who has been involved in another side of this industry but I must say that this easy accessibility to pornography is bad for Ireland and for Irish society.  No parent will be able to monitor a television channel 24 hours a day if the card cannot be removed from the receiver.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The biggest growth in satellite television is in sport and many families are paying for the sports channel to promote <Col N="1569" /> in their children an inteest in sport.  We should encourage all our young people to get involved in sport and in this respect having a satellite dish is a great asset.</P>
    <P>The problem regarding transmission to rural Ireland has only arisen in the past five months.  The problem was highlighted in the UK Parliament, and I see an advantage in a second EC member state dealing with the same problem.  We could support the UK in its fight.  The fact that the UK has a strong voice in the European Parliament, and that two nations will be fighting for this one objective should strengthen our case.</P>
    <P>Regarding the issue of open broadcasting, of course I am in favour of it. Anyone who takes my views out of context would be distorting the discussion. They would seek to trivialise it by suggesting that Members on this side of the House do not have an open mind.  We would not have been the largest party in Ireland for the past 70 years if we had been narrow-minded.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>Nobody said the Senator had an open mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Nobody accused him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>It is open but it is very small.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I know there are many loud speakers on the far side.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>So are you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I admire Senator O'Toole but it was irresponsible for the general secretary of one of the largest education unions to have said that this discussion was largely irrelevant to Irish society.</P>
      <P>I thank the Minister and all who took part in this debate.  I hope our views will be considered when the broadcasting legislation is being prepared.  In the meantime, the transmission of these programmes must be stopped immediately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Mooney has referred to violence, apart from sexual violence, on television. <Col N="1570" /> This is appalling and appears to be unending.  Most of these films seem to have been made in Hollywood and California where they have the advantage of extra hours of light and sunshine. Years ago only family films were made with stars like Tyrone Power and Alan Ladd.  Speaking as a former film projectionist, I can say that those films passed the test of time and are still popular today.  Violence and sex are short term entertainment.</P>
    <P>On the subject of entertainment, I was delighted to hear the Minister mention the word.  Many Ministers before him put legislation through this House and had matters on the Adjournment but not once did I hear them mention the word entertainment.  If the service does not entertain you will not have any customers.</P>
    <P>The Minister is anxious to bring back the film board, a move I support.  The Irish film industry has a great ambassador for our tourism industry.  We have expertise in this areas and we should learn from what the film industry did for Australia. I know the Minister has a certain expertise in this field and I look forward to developments in this industry.  When he consults the film producers and film makers, they should be urged to make films which the whole family can enjoy. They are the people to will make the money if their films pass the test of time. However, if they produce films with violence as entertainment &mdash; and few people can identify with that &mdash; that would be a retrograde step and the industry will not survive.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the Minister's first visit to the House.  I know many Senators welcomed him.  As Cathaoirleach, I would like to express a very warm welcome to him.  He spent many happy years in this House and we are pleased, honoured and proud that he is now a Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1571" /> Question put: &ldquo;That the words proposed <Col N="1572" /> to be deleted stand.&rdquo;</P>
    <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 27; Níl, 15.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bohan, Eddie.<br />Byrne, Seán.<br />Cashin, Bill.<br />Cassidy, Donie.<br />Crowley, Brian.<br />Daly, Brendan.<br />Fahey, Frank.<br />Farrell, Willie.<br />Finneran, Michael.<br />Fitzgerald, Tom.<br />Hillery, Brian.<br />Kelleher, Billy.<br />Kelly, Mary.<br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kiely, Dan.<br />Lanigan, Mick.<br />Lydon, Don.<br />McGennis, Marian.<br />McGowan, Paddy.<br />Magner, Pat.<br />Maloney, Sean.<br />Mooney, Paschal.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />Ormonde, Ann.<br />Roche, Dick.<br />Wall, Jack.<br />Wright, G.V.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Burke, Paddy.<br />Cosgrave, Liam.<br />Cregan, Denis (Dino).<br />Dardis, John.<br />Farrelly, John V.<br />Henry, Mary.<br />McDonagh, Jarlath.<br /></entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Manning, Maurice.<br />Naughten, Liam.<br />Neville, Daniel.<br />Norris, David.<br />O'Toole, Joe.<br />Reynolds, Gerry.<br />Ross, Shane P.N.<br />Taylor-Quinn, Madeleine.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators Mullooly and Magner; Níl, Senators O'Toole and Norris.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <P>Question, &ldquo;That the motion be agreed to&rdquo; put and declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Mr. Mullooly Mr. Mullooly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mullooly</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to sit at 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 8 April.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. - EC" RHead="Programmes and Funding">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - EC Programmes and Funding.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister for Enterprise and Employment to the House on his first official visit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>With the agreement of the House, I propose to share my time with Senator Ormonde.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed? Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and I wish him well in his office.  I am aware of the Minister's talents and abilities.  He was Minister for Labour at one time and he made a major contribution to the development of labour legislation.  I wish him success in his new office and I look forward to a positive response from him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A recent report on information policy by independent communication experts in the European Community criticised the way European Community institutions presented themselves to the public.  The report stated that too often citizens viewed European Community <Col N="1573" /> institutions as abstract bodies which imposed decisions.  It was critical of the lack of transparency in Community affairs and it suggested that a number of changes, including the setting up of regional information points, should be introduced so as to break down the barriers between the Community and its citizens.</P>
    <P>It is important to provide information about the Social Fund, especially in relation to assistance for training, education and employment opportunities. Recently, a number of schemes were designed to help people return to the workplace and to find new employment opportunities.  Co-operation between European Community institutions and member states must be developed so that more courses can be put in place.</P>
    <P>I believe a short debate on this issue is necessary so that the Minister can explain how the schemes will be organised and how the people will benefit from them. It is essential that the Department of Enterprise and Employment organise these schemes in conjunction with the Department of Health and the Department of Education.  It would be a worthwhile exercise if the personnel involved in these schemes examined how they can be made more accessible to people, how maximum funds can be obtained from the EC and how the money can be used effectively.</P>
    <P>At present, approximately 40 schemes are in place which deal with new occupational skills.  These include HORIZON, COMETT, ERASMUS, TEMPUS, and PETRA.  I believe that co-ordination is necessary to ensure the EC funding give young people and those who wish to return to work the best possible opportunities.  I hope the Minister will indicate how EC funding can be used to best advantage so as to benefit the unemployed and those who wish to be retrained for the workplace.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde" hpid="Miss Ormonde Miss Ormonde">
      <NameTxt>Miss Ormonde</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister <Col N="1574" /> to the House and I wish him success in his new portfolio.</P>
      <P>As a guidance counsellor I am very concerned about the best way we can help our young people by way of the various EC schemes.  I refer to schemes such as ERASMUS, HORIZON, PETRA and COMETT.  I am anxious for the Minister to think seriously about how we can facilitate our young people in the implementation of these schemes. PETRA is a scheme which is vocationally oriented and which enables our young people to go to Europe on work experience. ERASMUS caters for third level students by giving them opportunities to work in another country in an educational context.</P>
      <P>I would like to think that we could harmonise our qualifications with those of Europe.  However, we do not know enough about these schemes.  I would like to see a system, organised by FÁS or by schools, whereby we could advise our young people of the opportunities available through EC schemes.  Perhaps guidance counsellors could liaise with each other by way of computer systems which are becoming user-friendly so that we could help our young people to participate in European programmes. Money is being made available in that area; I hope it is spent properly.</P>
      <P>From my experience of dealing with FÁS, I know money has not been spent well.  I hope now that we are rethinking the whole area we will evaluate the success of schemes and how best to implement them.  For example, the HORIZON programme is for young people going abroad for work experience during summer time.  In some schools it is not being availed of because the schools do not know about it.  Only schools aware of the scheme get the opportunity to use it to send students away during the summer months for work experience.  I hope the Minister will take these points into account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1575" />
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Minister for Enterprise and Employment (Mr. R. Quinn) Ruairí Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Enterprise and Employment (Mr. R. Quinn)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am pleased to be in the Seanad.  I started my career as a political representative in 1976 in this Chamber and I have very fond memories of the Seanad, particularly of the quality of contributions.  I appreciate the contribution made here during the course of the Unfair Dismissals Bill.  I also confirm to the House my intention to introduce in the Seanad the Bill to give effect to the Culliton proposals.</P>
      <P>I welcome the timely raising of this matter on the Adjournment.  As Senators will be aware the Government is in the process of finalising the submission for the national plan for the next tranche of structural funding from the EC.  I share the views expressed by both Senators that not all of the money that was available has been drawn down which is different from what I have been told in my brief here, that there is no evidence of underspending. The money has been drawn down but not all of it has been spent. That is the point Senator Daly made.  I suspect that is partly because in the past the Department of Finance was anxious to ensure that nobody but Merrion Street would now where the money was buried in Brussels.  Quite frankly, that was to the detriment of local initiative and local community involvement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now there has been an increase in funds following the completion of the Single European Act, the Commission has changed its former attitude to dealing directly with local regions throughout the Community.  There is an opportunity now to obtain funding for local projects from Brussels.  I have direct experience of this in my own constituency.  The Community Workshop in Ringsend was able to attract EC funding by providing matching funds here that did not have to receive departmental sanction and which in no way undermined or interfered with the receipts anticipated by the former Department of Labour, the former Department of Industry and Commerce or the Department of Finance.  This is <Col N="1576" /> particularly true in relation to the various programmes the Senators mentioned, such as NOW, EUROFORM, HORIZON, and especially ERASMUS and I will return to Senators on that matter in due course.</P>
    <P>As part of our submission to Brussels on the national plan for the Cohesion and Structural Funds, it would be extremely useful to ensure maximum publicity about those programmes.  If qualifying or potentially qualifying bodies such as schools and community groups could contribute some money and if the nation give official confirmation that it is a Community contribution, that would release additional funding which might not otherwise be available.</P>
    <P>The purpose of this plan for funding is to increase the degree of integration in the European Community.  I fully support that and I know it has the support of this House.  I will take the suggestion raised by the two Senators, communicate it to the relevant people and to the Commission. There will soon be a new spokesperson for the Commission in Dublin following the return of Mr. Terry Stewart to Brussels and it might be an opportune time for that message to be conveyed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matters. - Castlebar" RHead="Hospital Dialysis Services">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. - Castlebar Hospital Dialysis Services.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chathaoirligh, I thank you for letting my motion be heard this evening.  I welcome the Minister to the House and congratulate him on his promotion. I wish him well in his term of office.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have no doubt the Minister is well aware of the need for a kidney dialysis unit in Castlebar for the county of Mayo. Mayo is a county of more than 2,000 square miles and has a population of 110,000.  It is dreadful that to date our county general hospital has no kidney dialysis unit.  There are 13 patients in Mayo who receive kidney dialysis treatment. Some come from remote parts of the county and the Minister may be aware <Col N="1577" /> that most people have to travel to County Galway for treatment.  Such travel is very tiring for patients undergoing lengthy dialysis treatment.  County Mayo is so vast that for many to travel out of the county alone would necessitate a journey longer than from Wexford to Dublin.</P>
    <P>I thank the Garda Síochána for their tremendous fund raising events, which raised in excess of £57,000 towards a kidney dialysis unit in Castlebar.  I also thank the Castlebar Rotary Club and various other Mayo clubs who have raised a total of £150,000 towards the cause.  The Minister knows there is great community involvement in the effort to obtain this unit.</P>
    <P>In the near future the Minister will be travelling to Mayo to turn the sod for the new general hospital in Castlebar.  We will then be able to see at first hand the dearth of hospital facilities in Mayo.  The organisations that have raised funds over a long number of years are only too willing to donate that money so the kidney dialysis unit can begin its services in the near future.  It will cost in the region of £150,000 annually to run the unit.</P>
    <P>I call on the Minister, the Western Health Board and other agencies involved to make a special case and to provide Castlebar with this much needed facility.  There may be patients from other counties in addition to the 13 in Mayo, who could avail of the unit.</P>
    <P>I draw the Minister's attention to another pressing need in relation to leukaemia and cancer treatment.  The vast majority of people outside Dublin, especially those in the west of Ireland have to travel all the way to Dublin for leukaemia treatment, chemotherapy or other cancer treatments.  I call on the Minister and also perhaps the Minister for Transport Energy and Communications to provide such people with free public transport.  I came across a very sad case in the last week&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You have moved away from the notion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1578" />
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;where a young couple on social welfare had not the money to travel to Dublin with a young child for a leukaemia operation and the Health Board would not allow the child to be taken to Dublin by ambulance.  I ask the Minister to address that issue.  I would like those who have gone through much trauma over many years to have that facility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHowlin" hpid="Minister for Health (Mr. Howlin) Brendan Howlin">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Health (Mr. Howlin)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Burke for his kind comments and good wishes which I greatly appreciate.  I was proceded by a colleague&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Two colleagues.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHowlin" hpid="Mr. Howlin Mr. Howlin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Howlin</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;two colleagues who began their careers in this House &mdash; the Minister for Arts, Culture and the Gaeltacht, Deputy M. Higgins and the Minister for Enterprise and Employment, Deputy R. Quinn.  I also began my career in this House and it is good to come back.  I commend the standard of debate that has been a hallmark of this House.</P>
      <P>I am glad the Senator has given me the opportunity to speak about a kidney dialysis unit for Castlebar General Hospital.  It is an important issue particularly for the people of County Mayo and the west.  As Senator Burke said, kidney dialysis services for the Western Health Board area are provided at a special unit in Merlin Park Regional Hospital in Galway.  At present approximately 42 patients are attending Merlin Park for dialysis on a weekly basis, 24 of whom are from County Galway, 12 from County Mayo &mdash; the Senator says the number is 13 &mdash; and six from County Roscommon.  Patients attend the renal dialysis unit for treatment two or three times a week.  I appreciate and accept that this involves a lot of travel for some patients and a great deal of discomfort in many cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My Department was informed that the Mayo Kidney Dialysis Trust, through <Col N="1579" /> voluntary fund raising efforts, had raised approximately £150,000 to help the Western Health Board set up a satellite dialysis unit at Castlebar General Hospital to facilitate in particular patients from County Mayo.  The Western Health Board is responsible for the delivery of health services in the region and the board has informed my Department that it would require an additional £245,000 per annum to staff and run such a satellite unit.  My Department has many applications for additional revenue to support a range of proposals for desirable service developments throughout the country.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1580" /> While no specific funds have been provided in the 1993 Estimates in respect of the provision of dialysis services at Castlebar General Hospital, my Department will be discussing this matter with the Western Health Board in the context of the board's 1993 service plans.  I assure the Senator and the House of my interest in this matter and I hope the service can be provided as soon as resources allow.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.35 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 8 April 1993.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>