<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="13" Month="Jul" Year="1949" Vol="36" No="18" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 13 Iúil 1949" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 13 July 1949" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1481">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1481" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Bás an Dochtúra" RHead="Dubhghlas de hlde">
    <Title>Bás an Dochtúra Dubhghlas de hlde.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Micheál Ó hAodha Micheál Ó hAodha">
      <NameTxt>Micheál Ó hAodha</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá scéala báis Dhubhghlas de hÍde, an Craoibhín Aoibhinn, Ath-Uachtarán Chonradh na Gaeilge agus Ath-Uachtarán na hÉireann againn inniu.  Cuid den Oireachtas seo badh ea é mar Uachtarán. Bhí sé ina bhall den Tigh seo dhá uair.  Deineadh é a chomhthoghadh d'aon ghuth aon uair amháin sa bhliain 1925 agus d'ainminigh an Taoiseach é ina dhiaidh sin nuair a cuireadh an Seanad ar bun athuair sa bhliain 1938.  Nuair a bhí sé ina Sheanadóir rinneadh rogha dhe mar Uachtarán na hÉireann agus ceapadh ina Uachtarán é d'aon ghuth gan toghchán.  Ba mhór an onóir d'aon duine é sin agus taispeánann san go léir gur dhuine é a raibh meas air agus grá dhó thar aoinne eile in Éirinn. Bhí sé sin tuillte aige ámh, mar an uair ba laige agus b'ísle meanmna mhuintir na hÉireann tar éis bháis Pharnell tháining Dubhghlas de hÍde chun tine na náisiúntachta a lasadh athuair.  Ní le polaitíocht ná le troid a mheas sé san a dhéanamh ach le hobair náisiúnta a thabhairt do gach duine.  Bhí níos mó ná taobh amháin leis an obair sin athbheochaint na Gaeilge, agus ba é an dáltha céanna aige féin é.  Óráidí bríomhar, fuinniúil, éifeachtach ab ea é.  Caint bhreá bhlasta a bhí aige san Gaeilge agus i mBéarla agus ba dhuine é d'fhéadfadh sa chomhrá nó ar an ardán daoine a mhealladh chuige.  Dhein sé scéalta agus amhráin a bhailiú agus thug sé le tuiscint go raibh i bhfad níos mó <Col N="1482" /> taobh thiar don Ghaeilge ná an chaint amháin; thug sé le tuiscint go raibh stair, saol agus aigne na tuaithe ann agus a lan aoibhnis agus taithnimh le baint as an obair.  Theagasc sé dhúinn conas aoibhneas agus taitneamh a bhaint as fóghlaim na Gaeilge.  Gaiscíoch gan eagla dob ea é, ar nós Dhiarmada Uí Dhuibhne nár staon riamh i gcath ná í gcruadh-chomhrac in am an ghátair, ach duine séimh, caoin, lách, fíor-uasal ab ea é nár thug masla ná asachán riamh d'aoinne.</P>
      <P>Bhí rún daingean ag an gCraoibhín gan aon bhaint a bheith aige le polaitíocht.  Sheas sé leis an rún san, ach an saothar a dhein sé agus an sprid a mhúscail sé, chuaigh a anál i bhfad amach thar teorainn na Gaeilge agus thar teorainn na litríochta, agus tá cuid de thoradh an tsaothair sin againn anso inniu.  Táimse deimhin, nuair a déanfar fíor-stair na linne seo a thaighde agus a scríobhadh, go mbeidh ainm an Chraoibhín á chomhaireamh ar mhór-ainmneacha na hÉireann.  Is buan a chlú agus a cháil. Mar a dúras, bhí a lán buaidh ag an gCraoibhín.  Bhíos féin ar feadh tamaill mhaith ag obair ina theannta i gColáiste na hOllscoile anseo ach níorbh fholáir leabhar mór, toirtiúil, chun tuairisc oiriúnach, shásúil a thabhairt ar a shaol.  Dhein sé sárobair ar son na hÉireann agus ní raibh fala ná fíoch riamh ina chroí ná in a chaint.  Guímíd solas na bhFlaitheas agus radharc na Tríonóide dá anam glégeal.</P>
      <P>Ba í filíocht na Gaeilge an ní ba ghile lena chroí, agus gheobhfaí a rá mar gheall air an gCraoibhín an focal adúradh fad ó i dtaobh file Gaeilge: &ldquo;Ní bás do rug é&mdash;ach dul ar aoibhneas uainn.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Iarraim ort a Chathaoirligh, thar ceann an tSeanaid, comhbhrón an tSeanaid a chur in iúl dá ghaolta.</P>
      <P>
        <i>D'éirigh na Seanadóirí in a suidheacháin.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mícheál Ó hAodha Mícheál Ó hAodha">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál Ó hAodha</NameTxt>
      <P>Mar atá sé ansan.  It is intended to take the business as on the Order Paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Local Authorities (Works) Bill," RHead="1949&mdash;Committee Stage">
    <Title>Local Authorities (Works) Bill, 1949&mdash;Committee Stage.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1483" /> Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (5), line 20, after the word &ldquo;deposited&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;by consent of the owner.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Members of the Seanad and the Parliamentary Secretary will agree that the success of this Bill and the works to be carried out under it will largely depend on the co-operation of the farmers, the county councils and their staffs and the public in general.  To get that co-operation from the farmer in particular I put it to the Parliamentary Secretary that there must be consultation and you must first avoid, so far as possible, entering on a farmer's land without giving him due notification and, secondly, when you do enter on his land you must give every guarantee that as little damage as possible will be done during the carrying out of the works.</P>
      <P>Sub-section (5) provides:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Where any substance or thing is removed under this section from a watercourse, it may be deposited on land adjacent to the watercourse or the local authority may remove it, use it or dispose of it otherwise as they think fit.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My amendment seeks to provide that such depositing of material removed from a watercourse should be carried out only with the consent of the owner. In the case of drainage schemes throughout the country, we find that whether the work is done by machinery or otherwise the deposit is usually left on the brink of the river which has been cleaned, and in a very short time what has been removed from the river finds its way back again and the last position is much worse than the first. If the material taken from a watercourse is to be deposited on a man's land, I suggest that it should be done only with his consent and in a manner which meets his wishes.  If that is done, the scheme will receive more general co-operation from the farmer <Col N="1484" /> and will be a greater success.  The materials which may be removed include large trees or anything stopping the flow of water, and it would be unfair to give to the men engaged on this work authority to deposit such materials on a man's land in such a manner as not to conform with his wishes and probably to cause an obstruction.  It is to overcome these difficulties that I have put down this amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to be convinced that that is the purpose of the Senator in putting down the amendment. He is concerned about the farmer not having obstructions&mdash;trees, the roots of trees, tree stumps or such things&mdash;placed on his land.  If that is all the trouble there is, nothing would please the farmer better than to have deposited on his land oak stumps out of the river and let him take them away.  I agree with the Senator when he says that it is important to get the co-operation of everybody in this work. Suppose there is a decision to clean a drain.  It is good for the people at the head of the stream that the drain should be cleaned, but when they come down to my farm they find that I intend to be, not an obstruction in the river, but an obstruction on the bank, because I decide that I will not give my consent to the material taken out being deposited on my land.  What happens to the people upstream?  They will continue to be flooded.</P>
      <P>I do not know what experience Senator Hawkins has, but part of my farm is subject to a drainage rate, or at least is under a drainage scheme, and, if a contractor takes on the clean-of the river he notifies me that the river is to be cleaned and that if I want to save the few cocks of hay along the river bank, I had better do it within three or four days.  If it is not done within that time, the sand, grit and clay from the bed of the river will be deposited on the grass.  I do not raise any objection.  I get out like a sensible person and clear the hay away and leave what is taken out of the stream to be turned up on the bank. and later on I scatter it across the field and I find it rather productive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1485" /> It seems to me that if you give the power to one individual to say whether he will allow the material taken out of the bed of the stream to be deposited on his bank, that one individual could hold up a drainage scheme in which 40 or 50 persons were concerned.  I should like to know how Senator Hawkins would get over that obstacle. Would he not in fact be creating an obstruction?  On the other hand, I believe that courtesy ought to be shown to the farmer and his land should not be entered regardless of his rights and without saying anything to him.  Little courtesies pay and that ought to be the policy of the local authority in carrying out these works.  That can be secured not by legislation but by the spirit in which the work is approached and carried out.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government (Mr. Corish) Brendan Corish">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government (Mr. Corish)</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Hawkins said that he expected the works undertaken under this Bill would be carried out with the local authority and the different landowners working in harmony and co-operation.  He is absolutely right.  It is our expectation that that will be the case and we have no reason to believe that schemes will be carried out in anything but a spirit of harmony and co-operation.  If he examines the amendment, I do not think he will press it, because there would be certain restrictions on the local authority in cases of this kind, and I think the insertion of such an amendment might operate adversely against the landowner.  In the Arterial Drainage Act, 1945, which contemplated far more extensive works, Section 9 (f) is practically the same section as that embodied in this Bill, and it says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;For the purpose of the due carrying out of the scheme to do all or any of the following things, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
      <P> (i)  Take from any land all sods or other material required for the said purpose,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(ii)  deposit on any land all spoil or other material produced <Col N="1486" /> in the course of such carrying out, and</P>
    <P>(iii)  utilise for the said purpose all or any spoil, gravel, stone, rock or other matter removed in the course of such carrying out.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There was no such safeguard, as Senator Hawkins would describe it, in the Arterial Drainage Act as this, and I do not believe that the insertion of such an amendment is necessary.  The landowner has the right to appeal to the district justice if he thinks the local authority are going to inflict any damage on him or his land.  If, after the 14 days and after consultation with the local authority, he still thinks the in any way or infringe upon his rights, he has absolute power to appeal to the district justice.  The district justice may lay down certain conditions as to, if you like, the deposit of any things that may be taken from a river and as to whether they might or might not be deposited on the side of the banks.  In that, I think, he has an adequate safeguard.  The effect of the amendment would absolutely restrain the local authority from even putting gravel or sand or clay on the bank of the river even, say, for four or five hours if the particular landowner did not give his consent.</P>
    <P>Say, for instance, that the landowner did give his consent to the local authority to the deposit on the bank of all the things that were taken from a river.  You might then have a position whereby very objectionable things might be taken out of the stream and the local authority would be within their rights to deposit those things on the banks and the farmers would have no method of appeal against such an action.  During the 14 days, if the landowner has any doubt as to what might be done, he can, by discussion with the local authority, make suitable arrangements.  I should like to remind the Senator that if it was proposed&mdash;as local authorities are enabled to do under this Bill&mdash;that local authorities should build embankments, surely it would be ludicrous if the owner did not give his consent to the depositing of <Col N="1487" /> materials on the bank.  It would be ludicrous if you had a position whereby the local authority were forced to cart the deposit off by way of boat or barge to some other place and that they then had to bring back different material for the purpose of raising the bank and so making an embankment.</P>
    <P>The members of the local authorities are truly representative of all sections of the community.  I might say they are more especially representative of farmers and landowners.  They, as reasonable men, will make sure that schemes under this particular Bill will be implemented without in any way upsetting any farmer or landowner in this particular respect.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Parliamentary Secretary has met Senator Hawkins' point of view in this matter.  For instance, a case of this kind might arise.  A landowner knows that a certain job of work has to be done on his land.  He admits that it is desirable.  He knows the specifications of the work.  But will he know where the substance removed is going to be put on his land, or must he trust to the goodwill of the authorities in this matter?  It is quite possible, but, I know, not probable, that a landowner might even be victimised in this matter. He might give his consent to the removal of a certain obstruction and find that out of dislike or for some other motive the matter might be deposited in an entirely inconvenient place so far as he is concerned.  Is there any clause in the Bill which ensures that the landowner will know in advance where this material will be placed when he undertakes to accept the proposed alterations?  In other words, is the landowner safeguarded from having material deposited in an extremely inconvenient part of his land or not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be deposited by the side of the stream.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>But is there any clause in the Bill to that effect? It might be put on his front door step. I think some safeguard should be provided so that the landowner will know what is going to be done in regard <Col N="1488" /> to the substance before he agrees to the right of entry.  Would the Parliamentary Secretary give some assurance on that point?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>It is inconceivable that people engaged in a drainage scheme will go to the expense and labour of carrying material, which is lifted from the bed of a stream, some distance from the river.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It is far-fetched.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Their objective would be to deposit it on the banks of the stream.  It may turn out that that will involve inconvenience or loss to the farmer in certain instances but Section 5 of the Bill definitely provides for compensation in such cases.  Therefore, to the extent that the farmer may suffer loss or injury in any way in respect of his property or land, there is ample provision for a claim for compensation. Further, as the Parliamentary Secretary has said, if one person, through a sense of &ldquo;cussedness&rdquo; or otherwise, is capable of holding up a whole drainage scheme by preventing the deposit on his property of material which was lifted alongside his land from the bed of the stream, then the whole proceedings could be rendered absolutely farcical.  From a purely commonsense point of view I would suggest to Senator Hawkins that people should be required to give reasonable facilities in a matter of this kind, seeing that, above all, if they suffer damage or injury in any way they have the power to recover compensation afterwards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Parliamentary Secretary make some provision so that the landowner will know where this material will be deposited when the proposition is put before him?  In that case, the 14 days would be a safeguard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Every landowner will know that.  Since it is lifted from the bed of the stream he will try to put it in the nearest place and as quickly as he can.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>That might be the front door.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1489" />
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>If he is inconvenienced in that respect he has the right to claim compensation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusOFarrell" hpid="Mr. S. O'Farrell Mr. S. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>The very section which it is proposed to amend&mdash; Section 2, sub-section (5) &mdash;says that whatever is removed from the river may be put on the land adjacent to the river.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>Or the local authority may remove it, use it or otherwise dispose of it as they think fit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusOFarrell" hpid="Mr. S. O'Farrell Mr. S. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>He will put it where it is handiest to put it&mdash;and that is the bank of the river.  The Parliamentary Secretary made the point I had in mind.  If it were necessary to get permission from the landowner to deposit anything on his land, even on the river bank, temporarily&mdash;even for half an hour&mdash;it would mean that every shovel-full of clay or sand removed from the river in the area of that man's land would have to be carried in a bucket, perhaps, to somewhere else.  I do not think any landowner would be so unreasonable as to hold the scheme up and nobody who wants to facilitate other people in draining the land would object in regard to the question of the depositing of the material.  Although the amendment is well-intentioned and meant to safeguard the farmer it would, if inserted in the Bill, make it possible for any contrary person to hold up the whole drainage scheme which would affect perhaps a dozen people who may live nearby.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="Mr. Goulding Mr. Goulding">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Goulding</NameTxt>
      <P>If the sub-section were so worded as to change the word &ldquo;may&rdquo; in line 21 and insert instead the word &ldquo;must&rdquo;, I submit that that would compel the local authority, if the owner of the land objected, to remove the material.  It is quite possible that material could be taken from the bed of a river which would be of no advantage to the owner of the land.  Senator Baxter pointed out that this material could be spread on the land afterwards by the owner but sand or gravel would be useless and, in fact, a deposit of sand or gravel on the land might prove a real injury to the land.  On the other <Col N="1490" /> hand, if the local authority were compelled to remove it at some time, in agreement with the owner that would overcome the difficulty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Parliamentary Secretary give us an undertaking that a landowner will know where this material is to be deposited and have time, within the 14 days, to object against that in advance: in other words, when the proposition is put before him, will he know that the substance is going to be put in a special place when removed from the bed of a river?  Would the Parliamentary Secretary undertake to improve that somehow?  Otherwise, a man is assenting to an incomplete proposition. He knows the substance has been taken out of the river, but does not know where it may be put down.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusOFarrell" hpid="Mr. S. O'Farrell Mr. S. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>On the land adjacent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>That may be his front door.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>He has a way out; he can claim compensation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Baxter has pointed out that material which would be taken from the bed of the river has manurial value.  That is quite true. There are two rivers on my land and in one case a certain amount of blasting will have to take place and there will be large rocks.  Despite the fact that I can claim compensation, it is most unjust that the local authority may be able to put huge boulders on what is at present a rather good three-cornered meadow and leave them there for all time; and that my redress is to go to the District Court and there have to prove that so much damage has taken place as a result of the boulders being left there.  That is entirely different from depositing on the bank of the river material that may be washed down, such as gravel or sand.  Very often that can be spread easily and the land adjacent would benefit, but big boulders or rocks are another matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JeremiahRyan" hpid="Colonel Ryan Colonel Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very hard to deal with this point.  Senator Hawkins <Col N="1491" /> ought to understand that if the amendment were inserted it would make the schemes unworkable, as one man could hold up a scheme.  This Bill has been brought in in a hurried manner, to a great extent, to relieve unemployment. If we put clauses in the Bill allowing people to appeal against the work being done, we will put the whole thing off.</P>
      <P>In cleaning a stream, the stuff is deposited on the bank&mdash;that is the sum total of the scheme.  That has been done by the Turf Board and under every drainage scheme at the moment. There is a fair safeguard for compensation afterwards if damage is done. There is neither sense nor meaning in upsetting this, as it would upset the whole scheme and hold up the giving of employment.  No terrible injury will be done.  Senator Hawkins knows very well that there is an odd disgruntled farmer here and there who will not agree to anything; no matter what the scheme is he will try to stop it, as he does not want a bucket of stuff thrown on the river bank.  Every member of the county council knows that if you have to go to every owner to get his consent on a document in writing there are some who will battle with you, with the county engineer and the county manager, and who will want so much damages before you start at all. Let the Bill be put through and the scheme put to work as quickly as possible. We cannot do a lot of damage in one year, and more damage is being done by holding this up.  After six months it will be found that there are very few claims for compensation. There may be a blunder here and there because of a few cartfuls of stuff thrown on the bank, but the farmer will not go any further about it.  He has his remedy in Section 5 within a fortnight of the work being done.  No one is fairer than the members of the county council and they will be able to help him in the matter.  I appeal to Senator Hawkins to withdraw the amendment.  If I thought that serious damage would be done I would support him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>The debate has dealt mainly with the possibility of two cases <Col N="1492" />&mdash;an unreasonable landlord or an unreasonable county council.  Much though I regret it, I think where in legislation you have to decide between the two, you will have to let the local authority have preference over the unreasonable individual.  I do not think that, as a matter of practical politics, you could insert the absolute right of the owner of the land to veto the scheme&mdash;which the words of the amendment would undoubtedly bring about in the case of an unreasonable person. At the same time, I am not too happy about the wording of this paragraph. There is a tendency on the part of the draftsman nowadays&mdash;very marked over the last ten or 12 years&mdash;to try and so draft legislation as to make it almost certain that the individual trying to protect his reasonable rights will find when he goes to court that he has not got a leg to stand on.  It is perfectly right to provide that the stuff be deposited on land adjacent to the watercourse and I do not think it would be reasonable to give the owner the right to refuse his consent, but I am not convinced that it is reasonable to provide in an Act that the local authority may dispose of it otherwise as they think fit&mdash;which technically means that they could bring it to Dublin and dump it in here, and be within the law.  That, of course, would be an absurd case; but it seems to me that, through the whole of this Bill, there is something lacking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It should be possible for an owner to go to court and prove he has been unreasonably dealt with.  When dealing with contracts between landlord and tenant you find it very common to provide for &ldquo;consent, which shall not be unreasonably withheld&rdquo;.  I do not know if that would be feasible in a section of this kind but that is the idea I have in mind.  The Parliamentary Secretary says there is a right of appeal.  With very great respect to him, while that may be technically correct, I do not think that it is really correct.  It seems to me that the section would rule you out immediately. All that would be necessary would be for the local authority to say: &ldquo;We have power to put the stuff anywhere we think fit; that is where we thought <Col N="1493" /> fit and that is the end of it&rdquo; It would be possible to go to court if there were gross abuse, but I do not think the amendment would achieve that.  In a later section, the question of appeal arises.  To say you could go to court is correct, but when you know that the effective answer of the local authority is provided in this section, there is no possible way out and nothing to prove that they are acting unreasonably.  I think an effort should be made to see if it is not possible to provide somewhere in the Bill that the court might stop certain works if satisfied they were not being carried on in a reasonable manner.  Personally, I do not think that would happen in more than one case out of 1,000.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HelenaConcannon" hpid="Mrs. Concannon Mrs. Concannon">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Concannon</NameTxt>
      <P>One matter that should be considered is that if the position arises under Section 3 of the Bill where a local authority is not able to undertake the works, the Minister can give directions to another local authority to do them.  The question arises then as to which of the local authorities will have the powers and duties conferred under this particular section.  That is a matter which should be cleared up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. G. Bennett Mr. G. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to make reference to a matter dealt with by Senator Douglas, and that is in regard to the provision for dumping on banks.  I think that the Minister ought to make some provision at some stage by which farmers and river owners might have some appeal in cases where they are unreasonably interfered with.  I do not envisage that there is a likelihood of this happening, but there is always the possibility of a wrong being done by somebody even in a malicious way.  It could happen that somebody might maliciously dump the rubbish from a river, which is being cleared, on to the bank of a farmer's land and do irreparable damage to a place which was used for watering cattle.  I think the Minister ought to give some consideration to this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Another point that I wish to raise, though I do not think it is one that will happen very often, is that it is not a matter of what comes out of a river <Col N="1494" /> but of what is put into the banks. Some years ago I had a case in which the river was being drained near to my farm.  It was later established that the people who did it had no right to be there at all, but that does not matter at the moment.  The point was that my predecessors had built up a bank in a manner that nobody could afford to do to-day, with solid stones. When they blasted the river they blew the bank to blazes.  I did not make any objection at all, because I am not a law-seeker.  When, however, they blew up the river the stones were dislodged. Those stones would have been very useful to me, but because it was easier they placed the stones on the opposite bank, which was lower.  The farmer who owned that other bank subsequently sold them for a considerable amount of money.  I am only mentioning that because a similar thing could happen to some other landowner who could not afford to have it happen.  There should be some place to which farmers could appeal in cases like that.  The fact that there is no such provision in any other measure is no reason why we should not have provision in this one to give the farmers some redress in cases of wrongful damage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. J.T. O'Farrell Mr. J.T. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.T. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, may I draw attention to the fact that every Senator is free to move amendments to this Bill, and it is rather wasting time discussing what the Minister should have brought in when in fact the House had an opportunity to table amendments to that effect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan2" hpid="Mr. Brennan Mr. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel that there is a general feeling on all sides that some amendment is necessary.  I do not think anybody would suggest that unreasonableness on the part of any individual should get any encouragement but there is every possibility that landowners might suffer some damage by reason of the Bill.  Therefore I do not see why the Parliamentary Secretary would not between this and the Report Stage consider the acceptance of an amendment providing for the appeal in cases where the consent of the owner <Col N="1495" /> is not unreasonably withheld.  Such an amendment would meet everybody.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>May I point out that the words &ldquo;unreasonably withheld&rdquo; would have to be interpreted by the court and the delay would be just as great as ever.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelColgan" hpid="Mr. Colgan Mr. Colgan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colgan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are all reasonable when we get what we want but we are unreasonable when we do not get what we want.  We hear a lot of talk about democracy and the rights of the individual, but in the Bill as I understand it it is proposed to go into a man's land and dump on it whatever comes out of the river.  I suggest that what comes out of the river does really matter.  It is not always mud that comes out but possibly old petrol tins and lots of other dirt which could be dumped on a man's land.  Under the Bill this rubbish can be deposited anywhere.</P>
      <P>It is all very well to talk about people further up the river but the man further down will probable have all the river deposits dumped on his land.  I do not think there is anything unreasonable in asking that before a man's land is destroyed by what is taken out of the river, he should be consulted.  I think that this is all that the amendment is asking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>If he does not agree on consultation what are you going to do?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelColgan" hpid="Mr. Colgan Mr. Colgan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Colgan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are assuming that he will agree and if a man does not agree the Department have other ways of bringing compulsion on him if he is unreasonable.  We can all be reasonable when things are in our favour.  The amendment only asks that a man should be consulted.  As the Bill stands the Department has the right to go in and clear up a river without let or leave from the individual concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanRuane" hpid="Mr. Ruane Mr. Ruane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ruane</NameTxt>
      <P>In my view acceptance of this amendment is going to be a serious impediment to the main functions of this Bill which is mainly designed to benefit a large number of people.  If it benefits a large number <Col N="1496" /> of people and an individual here and there suffers, you cannot help that. I think it is unreasonable to have this phrase inserted in Section 2.  When the Shannon hydro-electric scheme was being extended throughout the country and transformers had to be erected on people's land, I know people who regarded that as a serious obstruction and if they could only have been put there by consent they would never have been put there.  If you accept this you will have applications for compensation, and it is doubtful if the Bill will ever function.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I believe the law as it stands at present is that if a river passing through a farmer's land does damage to a neighbour, the farmer is compelled to have the land cleared at his own expense, but now people are objecting to the Government clearing land and clearing an obstruction which is flooding land.  I cannot understand the objection because anybody who knows the country knows perfectly well that a lot of rivers need to be cleared and they are causing a terrible lot of obstruction.  They are creating a lot of flooding even in summer and at harvesting time, and washing away crops.  The Government are going to do the work at their own expense and I do not see where the objection comes in.  Senator Stanford says that he is greatly concerned about where the refuse will be put by the Board of Works.  If that farmer did the clearance work himself to the satisfaction of the Board of Works and put the refuse wherever he likes it would be a solution for Senator Stanford, and he would not need to be concerned about what is going to happen to the deposits.  I think that the Bill, as drafted, should be accepted without any amendments.  I cannot see that there is any fault to find with it as it exists at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>May I point out that, in view of what Senator Bennett has said about the value of the material taken from the river, there is a doubt as to whether the word &ldquo;owner&rdquo; refers to the ownership of the land or the ownership of the river.  It will be a source of argument for the legal profession.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1497" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnJosephMeighan" hpid="Mr. Meighan Mr. Meighan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meighan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has raised an important point with regard to draftsmanship.  I think the Government officials are inclined to safeguard their own interests and it has been the same for the past 14 or 15 years.  I know personally of a case where the Board of Works divided some bogs, and to divide and drain them it was necessary to take water through my own land.  I was presented with a paper to sign to the effect that they would be accountable for damage to the land or trespass.  I said I had no objection to their going through my land on going on with the scheme.  I was informed by the man in charge that there was no more about it as, if I did not sign, no money would be expended.  The neighbours were looking for the work and £200 or £300 was involved, and although it was not benefiting me to a great extent I signed. What happened?  The bog up higher burst, and not alone water came, but all the sediment came and filled my drain and the water percolated from it. I do not think that is fair.  That is the only case I know, but it is a case where the Government should at least be reasonable.  I have seen a lot of drainage schemes and the usual procedure was to bank the stuff taken from the river on the banks of the river.  I have not heard any complaints in this regard and, as a matter of fact, a lot of people looked on the stuff as having value as manure and spread it themselves over their land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think, as the Parliamentary Secretary said, the county council members are sympathetic to the landowners and I cannot fancy a local body approving of something wrong being done to a local ratepayer or landowner.  I cannot conceive any local body giving sanction to taking stuff from a river and lodging it in front of the hall door, as Senator Stanford suggested.  I would emphasise, however, that the Government should not be inclined to tie up and safeguard their own interests so much.  After all, it makes the people suspicious.  I have no hesitation in saying that if I were presented with a document to-morrow similar to the one I got before I would hesitate before <Col N="1498" /> signing it, because what happened was very unfair and was never remedied.</P>
    <P>I cannot speak too strongly in favour of this drainage scheme because from my personal experience over the last 15 or 20 years it is needed all over the West of Ireland, where there are small farms of five, ten, 15 or 20 acres with a valuation from £2 to £10.  It is not unusual, with the exception of this year&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not dealing with the Bill as a whole but with the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnJosephMeighan" hpid="Mr. Meighan Mr. Meighan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meighan</NameTxt>
      <P>The composition of the local bodies will be a safeguard.  I would like to ask the Parliamentary Secretary to give us an assurance that the Government officials will take a reasonable view and that nothing unreasonable will be done.  If that assurance is given I will be satisfied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Although this amendment may appear innocent, I agree with Senator Brennan that it is destructive of the whole object of the Bill.  Quite naturally, if you make the possibility of moving in on a river subject to the consent of the owner, if the consent is withheld, the scheme is withheld.  While my own personal view would be that the rights of the owner should be protected as fully as possible against the executive power, I do think that this amendment does, partially at least, destroy the effect of the Bill.  I think that Senator Brennan's suggestion of meeting the difficulty the other way, that is, that the consent of the owner should be got with the proviso that it must not be unreasonably withheld a good one.  I am prepared to oppose the amendment as it stands for the reason that it is destructive of the object of the Bill which I consider to be a very worthy object.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask, for the third time, for a definite statement from the Parliamentary Secretary with regard to the point raised?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has asked three times and perhaps, if he will give the Parliamentary Secretary an opportunity, he may reply.  The Senator can put the question again if <Col N="1499" /> the Parliamentary Secretary does not reply to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly I shall give him an opportunity, if he understands what the question is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to bring Senators' minds back to Senator Baxter's statement and to remove the doubt to which he seemed to give expression as to the motives which prompted the putting down of this amendment.  I have said on several occasions in the past that each and every member of this House has a right, if not an obligation imposed upon him, to examine every Bill to see if he can suggest any way in which it can be amended or approved.  I have on this occasion exercised that right to put forward what I think would be an improvement. We have had many statements about this amendment and the main case made is that the county councils are composed, in the main, of very reasonable people, almost entirely of the farming community, and that those employed by them, the county engineers and so on, also come from the farming community and therefore must be very reasonable men.  If this amendment of mine is accepted, however, all the farmers suddenly become the most unreasonable of people ever placed on God's earth and no one of them will consent to the carrying out of the engineer's proposals.  We cannot have it both ways.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JeremiahRyan" hpid="Colonel Ryan Colonel Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>One farmer in 20 might hold up a complete scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I hold that the farmers in general are most reasonable, but if you attempt to do something which they do not fully understand, something which has not been explained to them, and if their co-operation is not sought through the proper channels, then they can become most unreasonable and will go to the greatest extremes to assert their rights.  It has been suggested that acceptance of the amendment would involve, as Senator Baxter said, in the case of a scheme started upstream, a refusal by those downstream to give consent.  It would <Col N="1500" /> involve no such thing.  This amendment has nothing whatever to do with the carrying out of a scheme, except in so far as the engineer in charge, on behalf of the county council, tries to get from the owner of each holding through which the scheme passes, consent to the depositing on his land in a particular way of the material raised from the watercourse&mdash;if at all possible in a way that will meet his wishes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>If he does not consent, what happens?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Bennett has pointed out what can happen and what did happen in one case.  He also pointed out that there may be a watering place in a particular field through which a river passes.  It may be low-lying, and, in the opinion of some of the people carrying out the works, may be a very proper place for depositing material taken from the bed of the river, which may have the effect of depriving that farmer of what is the most essential service he had on his land.  It was to avoid occurrences of this kind that I put down the amendment.</P>
      <P>The main case made by the Parliamentary Secretary was that a similar provision was not inserted in the main Drainage Act, but that is no reason why sympathetic consideration should not be given to this amendment.  If an Act was passed on another occasion which contained no provision of this kind, surely it is no argument for refusing to accept this amendment.  The fact that something was not done in 1897 is no reason why it should not be done in 1949.  Senator Ryan made an appeal that the Bill should not be delayed, but should be allowed to pass as speedily as possible.  The acceptance of this amendment would not alone enable the Bill to pass more speedily but would ensure that the works would meet with general approval.  If, however, as it seems, the Parliamentary Secretary is not prepared to accept the amendment, I appeal to him to have it conveyed to the local authorities and to those who will be responsible for carrying out these works that they should, so far as possible, meet the wishes of the farmer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1501" />
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>Senators have given many examples as to what may happen in relation to the points at which materials from the bed of a river might be deposited.  I think it is unreasonable to expect any Parliamentary draftsman to include in a Bill of this kind or any other Bill provision for all the different cases instanced here.  I appreciate the point of view of Senator Hawkins when he wishes to provide every safeguard for the landowner in this matter, and I should like to say that the Minister certainly will communicate with the local authorities and advise them that they should consult the landowners in relation to the deposit of any materials taken from a river bed.  I suggest that if it were embodied in this sub-section that consent must be given by the owner on every occasion, you would not have a local authority in the whole country who would undertake any scheme of works which they are enabled to do under this Bill.</P>
      <P>I will endeavour to answer Senator Stanford.  He raised a particular question as to what safeguard the landowner had as to the deposit of material on his land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I was a little more precise.  Will the landowner know in advance where the material is going to be deposited after the job is done, so that he can object if he wishes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think we should embody in legislation any provision of that kind, but I suggest that any landowner on whose land a local authority proposes to engage in certain works may, after he has received 14 days' notice, consult or confer with the officials of the local authority as to where the material will be deposited.  If he is not satisfied, if he does not get any sort of reasonable undertaking from the local authority official, he may go to the district justice and prevent the local authority from entering at all on his land for the purpose of doing any such works as are provided for in the Bill.  If he feels that he has been damaged, so far as the deposit of materials is concerned, he still has the right to claim compensation, and, in determining <Col N="1502" /> what compensation might be paid, the district justice may take into account the cost of the removal of any materials which may be deposited in any place to which the landowner objects.</P>
      <P>This is a Bill, as I said on Second Reading, which is merely an enabling Bill.  It will be worked entirely by the local authorities and again we must assume, if we can go no further, that the members of the local authorities are reasonable men.  I do not think anybody would suggest that those on local authorities are the type of people who would, as was suggested by one Senator, do anything in a malicious way against a particular person.  In that connection, I might also be entitled to say that, in a case where a river runs through the lands of ten landowners, one of these landowners could refuse consent because he was contrary or because he was politically opposed to the majority of the local authority.  He has merely to say: &ldquo;I will not give my consent&rdquo;, and nine other landowners cannot secure the benefits which it is proposed to give them under the Bill.  Let the House be assured that there is no intention on the part of the Minister, or, I am sure, on the part of local authorities, to infringe the rights of any individual or damage any landowner.  I submit that, especially so far as Sections 4 and 5 are concerned, there is adequate provision for an appeal to the district justice and adequate means by which any person so aggrieved can claim compensation.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Sections 2 and 3 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (6), to add after the word &ldquo;works&rdquo; where it occurs secondly in line 35, the words &ldquo;for which a certificate of urgency has been issued by the county manager or county engineer, and&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This matter was raised, I think, on the Second Stage also.  While ample provision is made in relation to general works carried out&mdash;sub-section (2) provides <Col N="1503" /> that before entering on the land under this section for a purpose other than the execution of urgent works, certain steps have to be taken by the local authority&mdash;I should like the Parliamentary Secretary to tell us exactly what works are really deemed to be &ldquo;urgent works.&rdquo;  Sub-section (6) reads:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(6)  In this section the expression &lsquo;urgent works&rsquo; means works the immediate execution of which is, in the opinion of the local authority executing the works, necessary to prevent serious injury to any person, land or permanent construction.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The local authority is the body to decide as between ordinary works and works of urgency.  But the local authority empowered to carry out the majority of works under this Bill will be the county council.  The county councils, as far as I am aware, meet once a month.  The point was made on the Second Reading by the Parliamentary Secretary that where there is a case of flooding it has to be urgently attended to&mdash;or, perhaps the breakdown of a bridge&mdash;and that that comes under the heading of &ldquo;urgent works&rdquo;. Nevertheless, before that work can be carried out, there must be&mdash;if I am interpreting this section correctly&mdash;a meeting of the county council, the authority carrying out the works, to decide that the work in question is urgent work and that, therefore, it will not be necessary to conform to the regulations in regard to the giving of the usual 14 days' notice.  If it is work of urgency, surely you cannot allow the state of affairs to exist&mdash;as was pointed out by the Parliamentary Secretary in making a case for this section on the last occasion&mdash;whereby a meeting of the county council must be called in order to deem that this work is urgent and can, therefore, be gone ahead with.</P>
    <P>My amendment asks that in such cases a certificate of urgency be issued by the county manager or the county engineer.  The first point is that the issue of such a certificate is a guarantee that, in the county engineer's opinion&mdash;the person who will be responsible for the carrying out of the work&mdash;the work is urgent and that, <Col N="1504" /> therefore, the giving of the usual 14 days' notice must set aside.  On the other hand, you will be placing the county engineer, whose function it will be to carry out the urgent works, in the position that he will not have the authority given by this House or the other House or by the local body.  It is a matter which I think should get careful consideration.  If we do not alter this section there is no reason why any works should be carried out or why the county council&mdash;the body carrying out the works&mdash;should go to the trouble, and probably the expense, of giving the usual notice prescribed. All they need to do is to deem that the work is urgent.  I am sure that those of you who are familiar with the working of a county council will agree with me when I say that the procedure is that a meeting of the county council is called and certain schemes are put forward.  Each county council will deem that the scheme put forward for its particular area is the most urgent scheme and that it must get priority over the others.  Details of those are sent to the Department and, when sanctioned, come back.</P>
    <P>A meeting of the county council is then called.  The county surveyor is the person responsible for the implementation of the schemes.  In his opinion every scheme will be one of urgency.  Therefore, he will have set aside the provisions made here in regard to the giving of notice and in relation to giving an opportunity to the farmer, as I submitted on the other motion, to come before the court so that if he has a serious objection to the scheme being carried out he will be able to have the case tried in court. Therefore, I would ask the Parliamentary Secretary to accept this amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it necessary to accept this amendment under the law as it stands because, as far as the direction of the carrying out of urgent work is concerned, the county manager will determine what are urgent works.  It would be very difficult, on the lines that Senator Hawkins went on, to say actually what would be described as &ldquo;urgent works.&rdquo;  It would mean a list of any particular <Col N="1505" /> works that anybody thinks might be urgent.  But I think sub-section (6) of Section 4 goes as far as any sub-section could go to define &ldquo;urgent works&rdquo;.  I would refer the Senator to that particular sub-section, which reads as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(6)  In this section the expression &lsquo;urgent works&rsquo; means works the immediate execution of which is, in the opinion of the local authority executing the works, necessary to prevent serious injury to any person, land or permanent construction.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I think that is fairly well defined.  If it is the opinion of the local authority that it is necessary to carry out works to prevent serious injury to any person, land or permanent construction then these works should be carried out.  I do not think that, in matters such as this, we should embody in legislation any long procedure or any procedure which will merely cause delay.  The House will appreciate that the type of urgent work that would spring to one's mind would be where an embankment would be broken down and, as a result, there would be danger of land being flooded entirely if the county council, or its officials in this case, did not act promptly and do something to repair it.  Another example is a case which came to my notice recently and which, as a matter of fact, happened in my own town.  About 50 houses were flooded as high as the first floor.  It would be futile to attempt to do anything to alleviate flooding in that particular area if any elaborate procedure had to be gone through. The Water Supply Act, as far as the signing of any certificates or the giving of any certificates is concerned, does not require any such certificate to be given.  I appreciate &mdash; as Senator Hawkins has said, I think, on the last amendment&mdash;that if a certain thing was done in 1897 it is no reason why we should do it now.  I hope he will excuse me if I read sub-section 10 of Section 17 of the Water Supply Act.  The sub-section is as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;In this section, the expression &lsquo;urgent repairs&rsquo; means repairs the immediate carrying out of which is necessary to prevent a stoppage or <Col N="1506" /> diminution of the relevant supply of water or to prevent serious injury to persons or property.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I think that the county manager and the officials will best be able to determine what are urgent works under this particular Bill.  If it merely means getting in touch with the county manager in whatever part of the county or functional area the local authority may be, and describing the particular damage which is being done or which might be done if certain action were not taken, and getting his O.K. on it and having the work carried out immediately, I think that that is the fastest procedure and the only procedure which could be adopted in cases where repairs are necessary.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not too happy about the wording in this case. Although I take, in the main, the point of view of the Parliamentary Secretary that there should not be any delays, I am not convinced that the section as it stands is the best way of doing it. If you go back to sub-section (2), you find the reason for the definition of urgent works.  It is provided that the normal procedure will be that the local authority shall either obtain the consent of the occupier or shall give 14 days' notice within which the owner or occupier may appeal.  That is perfectly satisfactory and about as fair as it could be provided.  But you may have something so urgent that damage could be done during those 14 days and it is for that purpose, it seems to me, that sub-section (6) has been introduced.  It provides:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(6) In this section the expression &lsquo;urgent works&rsquo; means works the immediate execution of which is, in the opinion of the local authority executing the works, necessary to prevent serious injury to any person, land or permanent construction.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Parliamentary Secretary read from an Act of 1943, but I think he will find that it did not have that proviso. It provided that urgent works were those that were necessary and did not say &ldquo;in the opinion of the local authority&rdquo;.  This sub-section (6) does not prove they are necessary; it <Col N="1507" /> only proves they are necessary in the opinion of the local authority.  You could not appeal against that if you have a certificate.  If you have no certificate, the owner could go to court and say these were not urgent works and then it would be a matter for the local authority to produce some form of proof that, in their opinion, they were urgent.  I think that could be the opinion of the local authority six months after&mdash;though I am not quite sure; there is nothing to the contrary here&mdash;there was a dispute about damage.</P>
    <P>Again, we are only dealing with the case where the owner objects.  If he is not a complete fool and if the works are genuinely urgent, he should be the last person to object.  If he really believes they are not urgent, his remedy is to go to the District Court immediately and get them to step in, not under this Act but under the ordinary law.  I suggest that, between this and the Report Stage, the Parliamentary Secretary might go into that.  If he wants to prevent that procedure, he should provide for some certificate.  I do not know whether the two persons in the amendment&mdash;the manager or the county engineer&mdash;are the best, but from a practical point of view, when it comes to court, it would be better to have a certificate.  It is extremely vague as it stands.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Having heard the Parliamentary Secretary, we have at least clarified one point, that is, that the county manager is the local authority in this case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>As the law stands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>That just borrows another question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>It is bad law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>What is going to happen when the bad law is amended?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Make it good law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>We come back to the position I have put before the House, that the meeting of the county council must be held.  Far from being anxious <Col N="1508" /> to hold this up, I am anxious to expedite it.  Even with this bad law, it is giving the local authority power to put forward a scheme and have the work carried out, but before entry is made into land there should be some certificate given by the county manager or county engineer.  I would appeal to the Parliamentary Secretary, with Senator Douglas, to have the matter further examined between this and the Report Stage, and I am prepared to withdraw the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 3:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (2), line 57, to delete all the words after the word &ldquo;ending&rdquo; and substitute therefor the words &ldquo;two years after the completion of such works.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This is by far the most important and most serious amendment we are asked to consider to-day.  The Bill provides for certain works being carried out, for which the necessary finance will be provided from central funds, I understand. County councils will be obliged to undertake the carrying out of the works and to make good the amounts in respect of engineering staff and also meet compensation claims.  The compensation under this Bill, in the opinion of many people who have given it close consideration and examination, will be considerable.  The possibilities of large sums being demanded for compensation can be easily seen.  The provision made for claiming compensation under Section 5 (2) is that the claim must be made within either two years from the beginning of the scheme or one year after it has been completed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A drainage scheme can have many serious effects, which may not come to light for a considerable time after the work has been carried out.  A period of one year is too short, in fairness to a number of people, to give an opportunity of assessing the real damage. If a drainage scheme were begun early this year, with the weather we are having at present and which looks like <Col N="1509" /> continuing over a long period, and the period expired in 12 months, you could not say that that was a justifiable term in which to assess the damage.  It is reasonable to ask for an extension of time for those persons whose property has been damaged.  I would go even further than two years, but the amendment asks only for that.  I am sure it is not necessary to make any further case for it, as the majority of members of this House are farmers and know what a drainage scheme means and what the results may be in certain cases.  Therefore, I shall say no more but ask the Parliamentary Secretary to accept the amendment as being a reasonable one.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very unfortunate that this whole scheme is being approached from the point of view of how much damage will be done as a result of it.  That is unfortunate, but it seems to be the frame of mind in which Senator Hawkins finds himself this evening.  I am sure there will be general agreement that a great deal of good can be done by local authorities utilising the powers conferred on them in the Bill.  That is my view and I hope that it is also the view of Senator Hawkins.  I believe that most county councils will utilise these powers to the full and that those county councils who do not do so will be very foolish indeed.  So I think it is wrong to approach the Bill from the angle that you are going to do damage and that you must make provision for the damage that you are going to do because you are going to do good. That sounds contradictory, but nevertheless that is the conclusion that one must arrive at after listening to Senator Hawkins moving his amendment. As I see this problem of drainage, and speaking as a member of a local authority, my view about it is that the local authorities and the engineers to local authorities will look on every work executed, and for which they are responsible, from the point of view of whether or not there is going to be damage and claims for compensation as a result of these works being carried out.  I am quite certain that the engineers to the local authorities, instead of acting in a foolhardy fashion <Col N="1510" /> and rushing in to do works, are going to be very careful indeed and it is going to be very difficult to get them to do work that ought to be carried out if they have to look on the fact that there will be claims for compensation and that they will have to bear responsibility for having done something that was not wise.</P>
      <P>I say that if some of the schemes that have been carried out in the last ten or 15 years had been viewed from that angle they would not have been done.  I am speaking from personal experience.  A scheme was carried out in my own county by the Board of Works and they started at the head and let the water away down and flooded much greater areas than were flooded before the start of the scheme. That happened under other people's direction and the local authority had to pay compensation.  If the local engineers had been responsible for that scheme that would not have been done and I suggest, therefore, that Senator Hawkins is not sound in his approach in this discussion.  I think it is probable that our engineers everywhere will be over-cautious and instead of running in to carry out schemes where there are bound to be claims for compensation we will find it difficult to urge them to go into those areas lest the execution of the works will mean claims for compensation against the local authority.</P>
      <P>I know that, speaking at the moment, it is not a time when we are in a position to judge what damage may be done as a result of the schemes that may have been carried out if this Bill had been in operation for the last three months, but who knows what is going to happen in the next eight or nine months.  Senator Hawkins is very optimistic in regard to the weather but very pessimistic about the other things. I think as the Bill stands the farmer will be given a fair deal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A further point which I do not think has occurred to the Parliamentary Secretary and which I wish to mention is that I have seen drainage work carried out in our county.  It was in connection with the Erne and cost about £120,000.  The local authority has had to take that over from the Board of <Col N="1511" /> Works.  There has been a great deal of silting up since the original work and there is maintenance which we have to carry on and which is going to be a considerable drain on our resources. It is conceivable that after carrying out certain drainage works you are going to have other residue carried down and deposited and flooding will result.  I suggest to Senator Hawkins that the attitude of local authorities should be to use the powers of this Bill to the full, and we should approach the matter in the light that the local authorities, county councillors and engineers will use these powers in such a way as to get the best good and by doing the least possible damage.  If you are going to make such provision for compensation you are likely to create the position in which our people will be looking to see what damage they can claim as a result of the work being carried out.  I do not think that that is a good spirit to inculcate and develop.  It is too much like making a fellow prove that he is idle so that he can claim from the unemployment fund.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Iarraim ar an Rúnaí Pairliminte glacadh leis an leasú seo.  Is dócha, ar mo nós féin, gur chuir caint an tSeanadóra Baxter ionadh air.  Is cosúil go bhfuil an oiread sin droch-mheasa ag an Seanadóir Baxter ar an Seanadóir Hawkins nach féidir leis a chreidiúint go bhféadfadh focal fírinne a theacht as béal an tSeanadóra Hawkins ar chor ar bith. Ní hé an Seanadóir Hawkins adúirt go mba cheart go mbeadh cúiteamh nó compensation le fáil ag daoine; ní eisean a cheap é sin, beag ná mór.  Tá sé ráite ag an Aire agus ag an Rialtas atá freagarthach as an mBille in alt 5 gur dócha go mbeidh ocáidí ann go mbeidh cúiteamh dhá éileamh ag daoine agus admhaíonn an Rialtas atá freagarthach gur cheart go mbeadh bliain i gcásanna áirithe agus dhá bhliain i gcásanna eile ag na daoine leis an éileamh a chur isteach.  Tá sé sin sásúil chomh fada is a théann sé, ach tá muide ag iarraidh ar an Rúnaí Pairliminte dul níos fuide ná sin.  Sin é an méid.  Nílimid ag leathnú an scóip le haghaidh cúitimh, beag ná mór, <Col N="1512" /> ná nílimid ag súil go mbeidh gá le cúiteamh nuair a bheas an scéim ag dul ar aghaidh.  Tá súil againn nach mbeidh; tá súil againn go gceapfar na scéimeanna chomh cúramach agus chomh maith sin go raghaidh siad ar aghaidh ón gcéad lá, ach más gá do dhuine éileamh ar chúiteamh a chur isteach is dóigh liom gur cheart go mbeadh dá bhliain de thréimhse aige chun é sin a dhéanamh.  Níor chuimhnigh an Rúnaí Pairliminte ná an tAire go mbeidh bliain ann, b'fhéidir, mar an bhliain seo.  Ní argóint an-láidir é sin, ach is baol nach bhfeicfear toradh na scéime maidir leis an dochar a dhéanfas sí taobh istigh de bhliain amháin. B'fhéidir gur fada go bhfeicfimid bliain mar í seo, ach do réir na dtuairisc eile atá againn ba cheart dhá bhliain a bheith ann chun éilimh a chur isteach. Ní dóigh liom gur iarratas mí-réasúnta é sin.  Admhaíonn an Rúnaí Pairliminte gur cheart bliain a bheith ann i gcásanna áirithe agus dhá bhliain i gcásanna eile agus tá muide ag iarraidh air a theacht píosa den bhealach linn agus dhá bhliain a chur isteach i áit bliana amháin.  Ní gá dhom a rá leis an Rúnaí Pairliminte go bhfuil súil againn agus dóchas againn go ndéanfar maitheas de thoradh an Bille.  Teastaíonn uainn go raghaidh an obair ar aghaidh chomh maith, chomh tairbheach, chomh fóntach agus chomh sásúil agus is féidir, is cuma céard adeir an Seanadóir Baxter nó duine ar bith eile in a aghaidh sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>On this amendment I have a completely different point of view to Senator Hawkins.  I do not favour a long period of time during which claims can be made, either from the point of view of the individual or of the local authority, the people who have to pay the compensation. I am of the opinion definitely that one year from the finish of the works, which is the shortest time if I read the section correctly, is ample. If there are disputes about the claim it can be altered or amended afterwards, but it seems to me that few things are more unsatisfactory than to try to ascertain compensation for damages a long time after the event has occurred.  If common sense were exercised the claim should be put <Col N="1513" /> in at the earliest possible date after the damage.  I do not think it is good from the point of view of justice or equity to lengthen that period nor frankly do I think it helps in this case the individual who wants to claim. He weakens his case, proof is more difficult after long delay.  A claim should be put in as quickly as possible. I should like to see the practice observed when work of this kind is being done that the local authority should be obliged&mdash;I do not say that it should be put in the Bill&mdash;to notify the person concerned that if he has claims they should be sent in within a year.  He should be made aware of that fact, but apart from that there is ample time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Hawkins started off on the promotion of this amendment on the basis that compensation claims will be many.  We have certain information from the local authorities in the schemes they have submitted and the indications are that in a very small percentage of the schemes submitted will there be any compensation whatever.  The sub-section originally read that the claim should be made within 18 months from the date of the commencement of the works.  That was amended to provide, as the section reads now, that a claim could be made two years after the commencement of the works or one year after the completion of such works, whichever is the later period, and I would suggest to Senators that in most cases the period during which a person can make a claim will be 20 months.  This is not an arterial drainage Bill nor is it proposed to do works which will cause any substantial damage whatsoever. While it may be unfair to say this in view of the fact that Senators have not examined the schemes which we have in the Department, I should like to state that most of the schemes provide for a period of, say, three or four months so, in effect, the period for making claims in the vast majority of cases will be 20 months.  I would like to refer to the Arterial Drainage Act under which it was intended to do works of drainage which would be very much larger than those intended under this Bill.  Claims for compensation <Col N="1514" /> under that Act in sub-section (2) of Section 15&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;shall be made in writing to the commissioners within one year after the interference to which the claim relates is begun.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I think that this section, as amended in the Dáil, provides ample time during which to make a claim.  It will give in effect approximately 20 months to any person who feels he has been damaged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to Senator Baxter's opening remarks on this amendment, I would like to point out that it was not I who raised the question of compensation at all.  I did not encourage people to line up to make applications for compensation any more than I am responsible for the line-up at the labour exchanges to which Senator Baxter referred.  Provision for compensation claims to be sent in was made in the Bill by the Minister himself and therefore the person who drafted the Bill, the Minister, thought it reasonable that that provision should be made.  We accept that. We agree that that is just and proper just as we agree that a number of people will benefit from the Bill.  In saying this I am sure that I speak for the other members on this side of the House: we would like to see this Bill doing all the good the Minister and the Parliamentary Secretary expect it to do.  There was no reason from the remarks I made on this amendment for Senator Baxter to come to any conclusion other than that we wish the Bill every success.  It was because of that I went to the trouble of putting some amendments down which, I hoped, would help to create a better feeling between persons involved in the scheme. The Minister has accepted the principle of compensation and provided for it and it is now a question of what is a reasonable length of time to estimate in justice the damage done to such persons as a result of improvement to other persons' property.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Remember that it is because of an improvement to other people's property the damage is done.  If we appreciate that a certain amount of good will be done to the national advantage&mdash;<Col N="1515" /> because we must assume that when we are providing money for the scheme from the national purse&mdash;it is only reasonable that people, whose property or position has been much worsened as a result of an improvement to other people's property or position, should be amply rewarded.  In deciding that reward we should give as long a term as possible in justice so that we can come to a conclusion regarding the amount of damage done.  With the work this Bill does, the clearing of watercourses, it will take a considerable time to estimate the damage. There must be changes of weather. You may have a fine summer as we have at present, a bad winter or other circumstances that should be taken into consideration in estimating what damage has been done to a man's property.  What I am asking in the amendment is to extend that time from one year from the completion of the works to two years.  The Parliamentary Secretary has drawn attention to <Col N="1516" /> the Arterial Drainage Act where a time is specified from the commencement of the work, but I put it to the Parliamentary Secretary that no other provision could have been made because, certainly, it would be most unreasonable to provide that claims could not be made until after the completion of schemes which it might take six, seven, ten or 20 years to complete. There is a difference between arterial drainage and the work this Bill proposes to do.  I ask the Parliamentary Secretary to accept this amendment as being reasonable.</P>
    <P>Question put.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the amendment is carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely only one or two Senators said &ldquo;Tá,&rdquo; while several said &ldquo;Níl.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite a number of Senators said &ldquo;Tá.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The Committee divided: Tá, 15; Níl, 29.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Brennan, Joseph.<br />Campbell, Seán P.<br />Clarkin, Andrew S.<br />Colgan, Michael.<br />Concannon, Helena.<br />Fitzsimons, Patrick.<br />Hawkins, Frederick.<br />Hearne, Michael.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Honan, Thomas V.<br />Loughman, Frank.<br />O Buachalla, Liam.<br />O'Dwyer, Martin.<br />Nic Phiarais, Maighréad M.<br />Quinn, Martin.<br />Quirke, William.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Baxter, Patrick F.<br />Bennett, George C.<br />Bigger, Joseph W.<br />Burke, Denis.<br />Burke, Robert M.<br />Butler, Eleanor G.<br />Butler, John.<br />Counihan, John J.<br />Crosbie, James.<br />Douglas, James G.<br />Fearon, William R.<br />Finan, John.<br />Hayes, Michael.<br />Ireland, Denis L.<br />Lavery, Cecil P.L.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">McCartan, Patrick.<br />Meighan, John J.<br />O'Brien, George.<br />O'Connell, Thomas J.<br />O'Farrell, John T.<br />O'Farrell, Séamus.<br />Orpen, Edward R.R.<br />Ruane, Seán T.<br />Ryan, Jeremiah.<br />Stanford, William B.<br />Summerfield, Frederick M.<br />Sweetman, Edmund T.<br />Tunney, James.<br />Woulfe, Patrick.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Tellers:&mdash;Tá: Senators Hawkins and Loughman; Níl: Senators Baxter and Ruane.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared negatived.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 5 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like information as to whether, in the case of works carried out by the county council in respect of which the county <Col N="1517" /> council is responsible for the payment of compensation, the county council will also be responsible for the maintenance of these works when executed.  If not, the money expended will, after a period of years, be more or less wasted and the works will fall into disrepair. If that is so, will not the county council also be responsible for any damage which may be incurred by reason of stock being drowned in the rivers or drains?  Will the county council not be responsible for any compensation over any period of years once the works have been carried out and once they are responsible for their maintenance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  The county council is not liable for maintenance after they have executed works.  I should like to stress again that this is an enabling Bill and they may do it by themselves, if they like.  The Bill does not impose any obligation on local authorities in respect of the maintenance of any works they do, but they still have the power to do them again, if they want to.  I agree that it is desirable, but they may treat it as maintenance or as a new scheme for the protection of their own property or other property when they consider that it is in the public interest to do so.  With regard to the Senator's last point, I cannot imagine how anybody could blame a county council for the death of a cow after the two years' period laid down in the Act.  I could not reply to that point, because I cannot imagine how any works carried out two years before could be held to be responsible for the death of a cow or a sheep.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Would a civil action not lie, if anything of the kind occurred?</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 6 and 7 and Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
      <P>Report Stage ordered for Thursday, July 14th.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Land Reclamation Bill," RHead="1949&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Land Reclamation Bill, 1949&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: That the Bill be now read a Second Time.</P>
    <Col N="1518" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon) James M. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon)</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I should make it clear at once that this Bill, in itself, is really an enabling Bill.  Its main effect relates to the conferring of powers on the Land Commission to charge holdings where the proprietor desires that method of repayment to be employed. The second substantial effect is contained in Section 5, which gives the Minister for Agriculture power to enter on a common watercourse where it is necessary to do so in order to render field drainage work which he has done on behalf of a farmer effective.  The necessity for that power arises from the existence in widely separated instances of cantankerous individuals. It is not unknown that where a drain carries the water from several holdings that the farmer who lives at the highest point of that drain keeps his fields drained in good repair, but finds that his exertions are largely negatived by an eccentric or cantankerous neighbour who refuses to keep the main drain open.  Under the law as it at present stands it is probably true to say that the first farmer has a remedy at common law by suing his neighbour for improperly obstructing the channel through which the drainage should pass, but a cantankerous neighbour is usually not unfamiliar with the process of law and he is, therefore, able to hold things up for a considerable time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When you have in contemplation a scheme of the dimensions which I propose to outline to the Seanad in a moment, it becomes necessary to arm oneself with powers to clear the drain by statutory authority&mdash;always understood that it is the duty of any Minister or any public servant of the people to have recourse to such powers only in the last extremity.  It would be right that I should tell the Seanad now that it would be my purpose to secure the consent in every case of a farmer on to whose land it became necessary to enter for clearing a drain and that it would be my endeavour to get that consent by every conceivable means of persuasion before I had recourse to the powers which I seek in Section 5.  However, I am quite certain that the existence of the powers sought under Section 5 will make it very much <Col N="1519" /> easier to secure the necessary accommodation by persuasion than it would be if the rare cantakerous neighbour knew those powers did not exist.  I, therefore, hope to hold them <i>in terrorem</i> and to be able to report in 1967 that it has never been necessary to use them.  I do not want the Seanad to be under an illusion, though.  I am not seeking the powers under any guarantee not to use them.  Should the necessity arise to use them I would not hesitate to use them for the benefit of the cantakerous party's neighbours and for the benefit of the cantakerous party himself, had he the wisdom to discern it.</P>
    <P>Section 6 was inserted in an effort to meet views expressed by the Opposition in Dáil Éireann.  I did not think it was necessary and I do not think it is necessary for the purpose of the Bill, but I believe it to be sound Parliamentary practice that where the Opposition in the Dáil or in the Seanad expresses a strong view and if, without disrupting the whole structure of a Bill which is submitted to Parliament, one can incorporate their request&mdash;even if it appears unnecessary to the Government&mdash;one ought to do so.  That is my justification for recommending Section 6 to the Seanad.  It was done to meet a view strongly expressed by the Opposition which, on careful examination, I felt could be met without interfering with the general scheme and I accordingly met it.</P>
    <P>Section 7 is the usual section providing for powers to make regulations and Sections 8 and 9 are in common form.  I believe and hope that Senators were furnished with a copy of this pamphlet&mdash;<i>The Land Rehabilitation Project</i>&mdash;when the Bill was being circulated. The Seanad will probably wish to know the origin of this project, the purposes which it is hoped the project will serve and the methods by which it is hoped to carry it out.  The Government of which I am a member has accepted as the basis of their entire policy the view that the economic future of our people is ultimately founded on the land and that, while there is room for and urgent need of diverse occupations for our people <Col N="1520" /> within the four shores of this country, ultimately the prosperity of all sections of the community depends on whether the land and those who live upon it and get their living from it are prosperous or not.</P>
    <P>Recalling the history of how our people came to own the land, it is not difficult to sympathise with the circumstances which left us to-day with a great acreage of land the productive capacity of which was far lower than it ought to be, with the consequential result that hard work put into the land by those who lived upon it only too frequently gave the man who did the work a wretchedly inadequate reward.</P>
    <P>The further west one goes in Ireland the more bitterly true that proposition evidently becomes.  I was brought up in the County Mayo, in the second most congested area in Ireland, and all my life I have watched neighbours living out of ten or 20 acres, all raising good families on those tiny holdings, holdings where men from richer parts of Ireland would die of starvation if they were transplanted to them on the morrow.  But it is not only the land of those small holdings one has to think of, because the land war was fought in Tipperary just as much as it was in Mayo.  One of its results, which still remains with us, is that so much had to be spent in the effort to get the land for our own people that too little was done to make that land what it ought to be.  And on top of the effort that our people were called upon to make was superimposed the old tradition that one should be circumspect about improving one's land, lest the rent be raised.  Memories die slowly in rural Ireland and the grandfathers of most of the men who own the land of Ireland to-day knew that if they dared to improve their land the only consequence would be that the increased increment of their labour would be sequestered for the landlord. It was that vivid memory which provided me instanter with the appropriate reply to an inquirer who asked me, on the first occasion that I mentioned this project, whether if it were carried through successfully it would result in an increase of the valuation on the farmer's holding.  It <Col N="1521" /> gave one a certain thrill to know the answer by instinct before one had time to work it out by reason, and my reply was: &ldquo;Over my dead body&rdquo;.  Anyone who remembers how we came by the land would, I think, echo that sentiment.  It is a useful thing to remember.</P>
    <P>I was gratified to discover that the instinct which inspired me to make that answer found an echoing answer from the Valuation of Ireland Act, 1852, Section 14 of which states:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;No hereditament or tenement shall be liable to be rated in respect of any increase in the value thereof arising from any drainage, reclamation or embankment from the sea or any lake or river...&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I do not base the undertaking that I give to the farmers of Ireland in 1949 on the Statute of 1852, but I reassure them that the purpose of Section 14 of the Valuation of Ireland Act of 1852 will be served just as scrupulously in 1949 by virtue of the Government's undertaking as it was observed in 1852 by virtue of the Valuation Act of that year.</P>
    <P>The reluctance of our people to improve the land, lest the rent be increased, had a further exacerbation by events which&mdash;I wish to avoid even the slightest breath of controversy here to-day&mdash;transpired subsequently. The fear that to improve land would excite the covetousness of bad neighbours undoubtedly played its part in deterring our people from doing all that might have been done to keep the land in good heart.  A variety of causes combined to produce, over an area which we tentatively reckon to be about 4,000,000 acres of arable or potentially arable land, a situation the abatement of which calls for a capital equipment and investment quite hopelessly beyond the individual capacity of the farmers who own the land.</P>
    <P>In Ireland, there is universal agreement on the proposition that to own land is a natural right not to be abridged, not to be doubted, not to be qualified.  The ownership of land may carry duties and obligations, but it is an unqualified right.  One, therefore, found oneself confronted with a <Col N="1522" /> dilemma.  There were 4,000,000 acres of land, the private property of individuals, and on the produce of that land depended very largely the prosperity of the whole community, but no effort that the individuals who owned it could be expected to make would really extract from it what it should be made produce, as they had not the capital equipment or resources to bring it up to that level of fertility which would yield an adequate return for hard work.  Only too often, in democratic communities, faced with a dilemma of that kind, the tendency to vacillate and do nothing prevailed.  There are so many arguments for and so many arguments against that the time is spent in arguing and the standard of living of the people continues to decline.</P>
    <P>The Government of which I am a member determined that vacillations of that kind would serve no useful purpose: that if their thesis is correct that the standard of living of our people ultimately depends on the land and that if one-third of our agricultural land was now left in virtual dereliction, the one certainty was that that land must be brought in as quickly as possible and that philosophical perambulations as to whether public funds should be, with propriety, laid out on private property or not are a barren topic of discussion. We accordingly, resolved to put the work in hand to complete it and to trust that our people are what those who went before us believed them to be, the best people and the only people in the world qualified to work the land of Ireland.</P>
    <P>It is true this project is founded on one hypothesis and if that hypothesis is false, every penny spent on this project is thrown away.  The hypothesis is that the farmers of this country, who own the land, live on it and get their living from it, are the best people in the world to get the best return from it and that put in the position that the work they do upon it will be fairly rewarded, they will work it to the best possible advantage and that the community who put them in a position to get from the land an adequate return for the labour they put into it, are making a good investment when <Col N="1523" /> they invest their money and their savings in the land of Ireland.</P>
    <P>The source of this money is simple to discern.  The inconvertibility of sterling created the situation in which we had not ready access to dollars. Under the Marshall Plan we became entitled to borrow from the United States of America annual sums of dollars, and the scheme provided that we were lent the dollars and we purchased the commodities which we required in the United States.  On the arrival of these commodities in Ireland the individual <i>entrepreneur</i> paid for them in sterling and the sterling was deposited in the Central Bank under the control of the Minister for Finance to construct a fund out of which the debt due to the United States could be repaid as soon as convertibility would enable us to convert the sterling which we held in the Central Bank into dollars for transfer to the United States.  The Marshall plan provided in itself a period of five years after the loan was contracted in which neither interest nor principal were to be repaid. Nevertheless, prudence demanded that when the loan was not payable on demand it would be necessary to have the wherewithal to pay the loan when payment would fall due.  The problem then was how these moneys could be housed for safe keeping until they would be needed for the payment of the debt.  Two courses were open. One, to invest them in what was commonly called trustee securities, and the other to invest them in better securities.  There will be financiers who hold the view that the consolidated stock of the British Government is a better investment than the land of Ireland.  It is a legitimate view, but it is not the view of the Government of Ireland.</P>
    <P>Having carefully surveyed the various securities into which these moneys might be most safely put for safe keeping, the Government readily accepted the view that if you searched the world you could not find a safer place for the savings of the Irish people than the land of Ireland and the people living on it, and it is accordingly the <Col N="1524" /> Government's intention to put the money for safe keeping right into the land of Ireland and the people who live on it, confident that when the time for repayment comes, it will be found to be far safer there than it would have been in any consolidated stock of the British or any other Government in Europe.</P>
    <P>So the finance was found.  Ministers of Finance seldom hear their praises sung, but in all conscience I feel the obligation on myself to say and to reiterate here and elsewhere that but for the financial genius and extraordinary vision of the man whom this country is fortunate enough to have as Minister for Finance this project could never have seen the light of day.  Inevitably, much of the kudos that will be got from this measure will accrue to the Minister for Agriculture, and may I reassure Senators I shall collect all the kudos available, but it is right that the Seanad should know, as the Dáil now knows, that all the good&mdash;and I think it will be great good&mdash;that will come from this project is in a very large measure due to a Minister whose name will be very little associated with it but, in fact, without whose work it could never have been even contemplated.  So much, then, for how the finance is to be found and the history that lies behind it.</P>
    <P>Let me sketch in very short detail the work that is to be done and then I will wait such queries as Senators may address to me so that I may answer them to the limit of my capacity at the conclusion of the debate.</P>
    <P>The project falls into two divisions. The first contemplates that, after consultation with the appropriate officers of our Department, the farmer will undertake to carry out the work scheduled to be done by himself in consideration of receiving a grant estimated to reach two-thirds of the cost of the work to be done.  I cannot too strongly emphasise and re-emphasise that this project has nothing to do with employment schemes, relief schemes or such activities of any kind.  The aim is to get the work done under this project by the most economical method and the most efficient method and by <Col N="1525" /> the employment of that equipment which will enable those who work upon it to receive not the minimum agricultural wage obtaining in the area but a reward appropriate to the work done with the most modern machinery and with resultant increased volume of production for the people who do the work, to justify a corresponding reward. I think we can reasonably hope that a very great deal of labour will be provided.</P>
    <P>In fact, I might say a word of warning to Senators that, in so far as our progress may fall behind what I hope for, I believe it will fall behind for the want of available labour.  I am able to tell Senators that, although no prognostications have been made of recalling exiles we have already been able to welcome, not unemployed labourers on the unemployment rolls of Great Britain, but highly skilled operatives who have come home and who are coming home to earn that which they had in the relatively recent past to go abroad to earn.  What is gratifying is that they are coming home to earn the same reward for the same kind of work but this time with the satisfying addition of the knowledge that the work they are doing is for the benefit of their own neighbours and not of a foreign employer.  We will draw as the necessity arises upon the skilled labour force of our people in Great Britain.</P>
    <P>We have no desire to stretch out the completion of this project by an hour. Our aim is to complete all the work that requires to be done in the shortest possible time so that every acre of land requiring rehabilitation may be put to work at the earliest possible moment. We will draw therefore upon the skilled labour force in Great Britain, I hope in growing numbers, not only to do the job that needs doing but to train young men here at home to do the job themselves as well.  In our day, therefore, we may see the realisation of a dream that many of us have had when work upon the land will not be looked upon as suitable only for hewers of wood and drawers of water and when the workers who work upon the land will be equipped with equipment corresponding to that which has been put in the hands of industrial workers so that <Col N="1526" /> when they are so equipped their reward will be more commensurate with the work they do than it has been heretofore and will bear comparison with industrial rates of wages on a more rational basis than it has done heretofore. I mention that at this stage because, although under one part of the scheme it is anticipated that farmers will do the work themselves in consideration of a grant, I would like Senators to realise that it is intended in many cases that farmers will employ just the sort of equipment I have been describing and give contracts to neighbours' sons who, just as they kept tractors and ploughs to serve their neighbours, will now add to that equipment appropriate drainage machines wherewith to work for their neighbours on contract not only to create new field drainage systems but to maintain hereafter the standards we hope to establish.  If Senators would care to look at this, I am proud to claim, somewhat unusual Department pamphlet&mdash;because I direct the attention of Senators to what for the want of a better word I elect to describe as &ldquo;buttons and bows&rdquo; which adorn it&mdash;they will see that a case is envisaged where a farmer elects to do the work himself and becomes entitled to a grant of £140 consequent upon doing the work outlined on page 1.  Do Senators realise and believe that every applicant under this scheme to date&mdash; and we have had 3,543 covering 66,736 acres&mdash;has received a map of his holding with a complete diagram of all the works required to be carried out drawn in consultation and agreement with the farmer, just as it appears on page 2.</P>
    <P>We have envisaged the possibility that half-way through he might run out of funds and we are prepared to consider an application for what I think my learned friend, the Attorney-General, might describe as a <i>quantum meruit</i> with the qualification that under this scheme the <i>quantum meruit</i> must function as a whole were it to be left for ever in no better title than <i>quantum meruit.</i></P>
    <P>As Senators will observe, it would be conceivable that part of the works envisaged in that part of the plan shaded red could be carried out and, <Col N="1527" /> were work stopped, serve no useful purpose at all.  On the other hand, suppose the farmer had dug the main drain and supplementary drains to that main drain and had not yet reached the additional minor drains which would flow into the channel marked C-D, it would, in our opinion, be proper to pay an instalment of the grant due, referrable to the work done, because if the farmer never did anything more, that bit of work would be value for money.</P>
    <P>On the other hand, supposing the farmer did part of the drainage, and left undone some small part, so that none of the rest of the work would function at all, in these circumstances we would refuse and the work would be nugatory if we did.  There is an additional matter relating to the grant to which I wish to direct the particular attention of Senators.  If the nine acres envisaged in this example required neither lime nor phosphates, the entire grant would be payable in cash.  But supposing it emerged that the land reclaimed, consisting of nine acres, is deficient in lime and deficient in phosphate, we will pay the grant of £140 in kind up to the point of 2 tons of ground lime and 6 cwts. of ground phosphate as required.  That quantity of fertiliser spread upon the land will be charged at the rate of £5 per acre.</P>
    <P>Therefore, if all of the nine acres required that treatment the farmer would receive £95 in cash, two tons of ground lime and six cwt. of ground phosphate in respect of each acre, not delivered at his holding but spread by machinery on the land.  As far as we envisage here&mdash;and I direct Senators' attention to this&mdash;where land may require phosphate and no lime, or where it may require lime but no phosphate, corresponding provision is made for the payment of the grant partly in kind and partly in cash.  In every case it is our intention not to leave a holding until we can say that every acre which it is considered required reclamation and is capable of being laid down has been effectively laid down and will hereafter give an adequate <Col N="1528" /> return for the work a farmer or his family may do on it.</P>
    <P>We have had, however, to envisage another situation.  In the old days this kind of legislation was provided for under the Encumbered Estates Act. These were the days when, if a landowner grew poor and sold out, someone else came in and said: &ldquo;I will put in a poor farmer.&rdquo;  I use the adjective literally, because that became a popular pastime.  God grant it never will again.  Accordingly this Government determined that provision should be made for the farmer who is poor, one who is prepared to work but cannot find the money to meet his part of the cost to rehabilitate the land. We propose that where a farmer for one reason or another is unable to undertake the work himself, the Department of Agriculture will undertake to do it for him, and if there is agreement with him that it is necessary to do that, we will do it and charge him two-fifths approximately of the cost, subject to the overriding maximum of £12 per statute acre.  That £12 can, if the farmer so desires, be charged on his holding on precisely the same terms as land purchase annuities are charged in the first instance.</P>
    <P>Some of the more conservative watchdogs of our people's welfare were slightly scandalised at the proposal that a charge of this kind should have a lifetime of 60 years, but anybody who has lived amongst the small tenant purchasers, as we used to call them, knows how profoundly sensitive they are in regard to their land annuities. They have always been vigilant lest by some misguided step they would render themselves liable to a permanent charge.  They have always watched with vigilant care to see that the figure on the Receivable Order was altered by no mortal hand except to end it finally.  They were wise in that and, with the respect due to so wise an apprehension, I insisted that any farmer in Ireland, who desired to have 60 years to pay back the reclamation annuity, should be allowed the full 60 years to do so.  If the Seanad passes this Bill in its present form it will be permissible, but at the tenant's option and initiative, to consolidate <Col N="1529" /> the amount, in which case the terms of repayment will be greatly shortened.</P>
    <P>I want the Seanad to understand clearly that unless a purchaser asks for that to be done, the annuity will be charged on precisely the same terms as the original purchase annuity, and will extend for 60 years from the date on which the charge is made.  I know how conservative financiers will be aggrieved at this appalling heresy, but those of us who glory in having been born in Connacht, know that there is bred in that part of the island values more enduring than economics, one of which is a firm, unbreakable, resolution that security of tenure shall not be breached.  I know that there are logical answers to those who are purblind against the creation of a charge extending over 60 years, but I glory that the sovereign Parliament of a free people can from time to time and within reasonable limits say to economists and financiers: &ldquo;We don't give two hoots.  This is the way we want it and this is the way we will have it.&rdquo; I think I correctly interpret the minds of our people in saying to all the valued advisers whose prudence and circumspection we appreciate and acknowledge that, just for once, this is the way we want it and this is the way we are going to have it, and those who do not like it that way will just have to lump it.  We do not often break loose and assert our sovereignty, but just once in a century we mean to do just that very thing.  I take it that my duty is to lay this matter before the Seanad in the same detail as that in which I laid it before the Dáil, or perhaps I should have told the Seanad to read the Official Reports of the Dáil?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>You certainly should not do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I conceive it to be my duty to approach the Seanad in exactly the same spirit.  I sometimes find myself in doubt because if I do tell the Seanad scrupulously everything I have to tell I am told I am too blooming long-winded and asked, for God's sake, to shut up, and if I do not tell the Seanad everything the Seanad is entitled to know I am told that I am being disrespectful to the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1530" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>Has there been agreement that we should sit after 6 o'clock?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I was about to ascertain that.  I take it that it is the wish of the House that the Minister should continue?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that we continue for another five minutes to allow the Minister to conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Or longer, if necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>My only point is that the custom has been to adjourn at 6 o'clock, subject to prior arrangement being made.  There is no objection, for the sake of objecting, on this side to allow the Minister to continue, if he anticipates that he will finish within a reasonable period&mdash;ten or even 15 minutes.  I merely wanted to ascertain what exactly the position was.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The project deals with arable land or land deemed to be capable of being made arable.  Of that, the Minister must be the ultimate judge.  There is no other way in which that can be readily determined, and I must only ask the Oireachtas to accept the view that the Minister for Agriculture for the time being, sustained by his experts, will judge of that fully.</P>
      <P>There is provision in Part II to equip young men in the country to become contractors on terms broadly providing that, if they desire to acquire machinery for hire or for the performance of contract work, they can have it, if they are prepared to put up one-third of the price themselves.  A loan will be arranged for the second one-third and a grant will be provided in respect of the remaining one-third. In regard to grass seeds, it is hoped in time to acquire a supply of indigenous varieties which will be propagated at home and made available to those whose land has been reclaimed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I direct the attention of the Seanad to the fact that the £12 which is the over-riding maximum will involve the annuitant in a payment of £4 6s. 8d. over the area outlined in the example set out in the pamphlet of which Senators <Col N="1531" /> have a copy, and that means approximately 4/10 in every half-gale per statute acre.  We believe that the conversion of non-arable land into arable land must be worth 9/8 per year to any farmer in Ireland or anywhere else in the world.  That is what this project is designed to do.  That is what is available to any farmer who wishes to avail of it, and I hope and believe that very many will.</P>
    <P>Lastly, it has been suggested that this project should be expanded to provide for putting out fertilisers on the land of every individual in the country who wants to put out fertiliser and whose land stands in need of it, whether the land comes within the broader scope of the rehabilitation project or not.  That is a view I cannot accept, because I believe the resolution of the difficulty of a person who desires to put fertiliser on his land is to be found in the provision of adequate credit and not in the provision of a grant.  Unless the theory sponsored by the Department of Agriculture that the application of hard work, fertilisers and good seed will produce profit for the man who employs them on the land of Ireland from the land of Ireland is true, then all we contemplate doing in this project is waste and folly.  We propose that the land will be put into a position which will maintain it as a source of income for the man who works upon it and will enable it to be kept in good heart, if properly worked.</P>
    <P>Those who want fertilisers are assured by all the knowledge in the possession of the Department of Agriculture that, given the markets we now have, the application of fertiliser, hard work and good husbandry, the land of Ireland will produce not only good wages but good profit for the farmer who employs them.  I cannot see why any man's neighbour should be asked to make another man a free gift of the means to make a profit, while the man who is to have the profit sits on his sash and does sweet Fanny Adams. I will never ask Oireachtas Éireann to make that kind of provision.  Credit, advice and access to supply&mdash;yes; but a free gift of the substance of profit is no part of the community's duty, <Col N="1532" /> and I do not believe that the farmers who live on the land and get their living from the land in Ireland will ever ask that of their neighbours.  If they should ever change their minds about that, they will want another spokesman, because I will never ask it for them.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Sitting suspended at 6.10 p.m. and resumed at 7.15 p.m.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Fifth Report of the" RHead="Committee of Selection">
    <Title>Fifth Report of the Committee of Selection.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee of Selection has nominated the following Senators to the Special Committee to which the Fisheries (Statute Law Revision) Bill, 1949, has been referred:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Senators James Crosbie, Seán Goulding, Frederick Hawkins, Thomas V. Honan, Frank Loughman, Patrick MacCartan, James J. McCrea, Séamus O'Farrell, William B. Stanford, Edmund T. Sweetman and Patrick Woulfe.</P>
      <P>Ordered: That the Report do lie upon the Table.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Land Reclamation Bill," RHead="1949&mdash;Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Land Reclamation Bill, 1949&mdash;Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Is dóigh liom go raibh áthas orainn go léir go raibh am té ann nuair do chríochnaigh an tAire an oráid&mdash;nó níl fhios agam an ceart dom a rá gur óráid a thug sé uaidh mar, chun na fírinne a rá, cheap mé go raibh sé níos cosúla le seanamóir ná le óráid.  Do réir dheallraimh, ceapann an tAire go raibh sé riachtanach an oiread sin ama a chaitheamh ag míniú na ceiste.  O mo thaobh sa dhe, agus is maith liom giota cainté chomh maith le aon duine eile, d'fhéadfadh sé an méid a bhí le rá aige a rá laistigh d'am i bhfad níos lú ná mar a thóg sé.  Ní hé díreach fad na hóráide an lucht a bheadh agam le fáil air ach a laghad eolais den chineál atá riachtanach ar ócáid mar seo a thug sé dúinn. Shílfeá ar an Aire gur rud nua ar fad é an rud seo faoi dhréineáil agus faoi mhíntírú na talún.  Ní rud nua é. Is fada muid ag smaoineadh agus is fada muid ag fiosrú agus is fada muid <Col N="1533" /> ag pleanáil le go dtabharfaí scéimeanna chun cinn a chuirfeadh rath ar thalamh na tíre seo.  Deirtear nach bhfuil mórán ar an saol atá nua agus is féidir liom a rá nár dhúirt an tAire inniu morán a bhí nua chomh fada is bhaineas le cuspóirí agus prionsabail dréineála agus míntírú na talún. Caithfidh go bhfuil a fhios aige féin chomh minic is a pléadh na ceisteanna sin na blianta roimh an gcogadh. Caithfidh go bhfuil eolas aige faoin gcoimisiún talmhaíochta a bhí ar bun díreach roimh an gcogadh agus caithfidh go bhfuil a fhios aige gurb ceist í seo a pléadh go mion agus a cíoradh go mion.  Phléigh siad gach gné de dhréineáil agus míntírú na talún ach amháin nár chaith siad mórán ama ar scéimeanna cosúil le scéimeanna dréineála airtéirí.  Caithfidh go bhfuil a fhios ag an Aire an méid ama a chaith an Coimisiún Dréineála ag plé na ceiste céanna. Dá ndéarfadh an tAire linn inniu, dá moladh an tAire dhúinn inniu, breathnú ar an gCoimisiún Dréineála agus ar an tuarascáil a foilsíodh sa bhliain 1940 agus breathnú ar chuid de na caibidil agus ar chuid de na haltanna&mdash;go háirithe alt 154 agus cúpla alt eile a leanas an t-alt sin&mdash;agus iad a léamh, agus an scéal d'fhágaint mar sin is é mo thuairim gur obair níos fearr a bheadh déanta aige ná mar rinne sé.</P>
      <P>Phléadar an scéal, ní amháin ó thaobh geilleagair ach ó thaobh na sóisialachta.  Mhíniódar an buntáiste a bheadh ann dá ndéantaí an dréineáil ar fud na tíre.  Ní rud nua an cheist seo faoi dhréineáil.  Ní dúirt an tAire inniu oiread is focal amháin a chur len ár gcuid eolais i dtaobh deacrachtaí na hoibre nó i dtaobh tairbhe na hoibre atá beartaithe.</P>
      <P>Má tá daoine ann adéarfadh gur fhoghlaim siad a lán uaidh, caithfidh nach raibh mórán spéise a bhí acu san abhar sin na blianta atá caite.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Is maith liom go bhfuil an lá tagtha gur féidir dúinn rud éigin a dhéanamh leis na scéimeanna a bhí dá gceapadh againn le fada, a chur i ngníomh.  Tá mé cinnte, marach an cogadh atá thart tosaí, agus marach na deacrachtaí a tháinig chun cinn de bharr an chogaidh sin, nach mbeimis ag fanacht <Col N="1534" /> go dtí inniu le haghaidh scéimeanna mar atá beartaithe.  Ba cheart cothrom na Féinne a thabhairt in áit a bhfuil cothrom na Féinne tuillte.  Is fíor a rá go ndearnadh cuid mhaith&mdash;d'ainneoin nár shásaigh sé muid&mdash;le blianta ar mhaithe le cúrsaí dréineála.</P>
    <P>Is trua liom nach é an scéim mhór náisiúnta dréineála airtéirí atámuid a dul a chur i ngníomh i láthair na huaire.</P>
    <P>Tá súil agam go n-éireoidh leis an scéim agus guím go n-éireoidh léi.  Ach ní thógfaidh an tAire, ná aon duine eile, orm má abraim go bhfuil mé in aimhreas nach bhfuilimid ag tabhairt faoin obair ar an mbealach is fearr. Mhinígh an Coimisiún Dréineála chomh riachtanach agus tá sé go dtosóimis ar na scéimeanna móra náisiúnta agus go n-oibreodh muid ó bhéala na n-abhann isteach.  Tugaimid faoi deara an chabhair a fuair an tAire, i gcúrsaí féara na tíre, ó Mr. Holmes&mdash;a chuir ar ár leas sinn agus a mhol dúinn tosaí sna hinbhir agus oibriú uathu isteach.</P>
    <P>Níl aon rud ráite ag an Aire inniu faoi céard is dóigh leis a tharlós nuair a tosnófar ar na mionscéimeanna míntireachain.  Níor thug sé aon mheastachán dúinn, ná níor innis sé faoin méid atá déanta ag na hinnealltóirí.  Níor mhínigh sé dhúinn go bhfuil sé sásta ina intinn nach bhfuil dochar ag teacht de bharr na hoibre.  Cinnte, is féidir cuid mhaith a dhéanamh ar an gcuid istigh den tír; ach, ón eolas atá agamsa, bheadh muinín agam as an gCoimisiún Dréineála agus as an bhfiosrú a rinne Mr. Holmes, go bhfuil contabhairt ann cuid mhaith de thairbhe na scéime a chur ar neamhní de bharr faillí a dhéanamh sna scéimeanna móra dréineála.</P>
    <P>Meabhraíonn sin dom an chaint a rinne an tAire i dtaobh an fheabha is atá súil aige a theacht ar chúrsaí feilméarachta agus ar chúrsaí táirgeachta nó cúrsaí soláthair.  Tá mé a cheapadh go bhfuil an tAire ag dul amú go mór má cheapann sé go mbraitheann feabhas talmhaíochta agus ardú táirgthe sa tír seo ar scéimeanna dréineála, bídis beag nó bídis mór. Dá mba agamsa a bheadh, níl a fhios agam nach é adéarfainn gur ar an oideachas teicniciúl agus an oideachas <Col N="1535" /> ceardúil a bhraithinn.  Más mian leis an Aire rath a bheith ar thionscail na talmhaíochta ar an mbealach ba mhaith linn go léir, téadh sé i gcomhairle maidin amáireach leis an Aire Oideachais agus an Aire Airgeadais agus cuireadh sé ina luí orthu chomh riachtanach agus atá sé go ngéillfear do na hiarratais atá curtha isteach go mion agus go minic ar scoileanna teicniciúla agus ceardscoileanna, ar mhúinteoirí tuaitheolaíochta, ar mhúinteoirí siúinéireachta, ar mhúinteoirí miotalóireachta agus ar mhúinteoirí tís, gan trácht ar mhúinteoirí eile.</P>
    <P>Tá an obair seo go maith inti féin, agus creidim fein, agus creidim go diongmhálta é, agus ní inniu ná inné a tháinig an tuairim dom, go mbeidh faillí san obair seo go léir nó go n-ardaímíd caighdeán oideachais cheardúil, theicniciúil ar bhfeilméaraí.</P>
    <P>Níl aon éadóchas orm i dtaobh na ndaoine sin.  Ní hionann an scéal inniu agus an scéal mar bhí.  Is cuimhin liom nuair nár thairbhe nó nar chiallmhar labhairt le feilméara i dtaobh oideachais.  Tá a fhios agam anois go bhfuil fir&mdash;agus ní hiad na daoine óga amháin, ach daoine nach féidir daoine óga a thabhairt orthu&mdash;agus fonn mór orthu teacht ag lorg eolais i dtaobh feilméarachta teicniciúla. Is féidir liom é seo a rá mar dhearbhadh: is mó áit tríd an tír a dtéim féin ag tabhairt léachtaí ar ábhair a bhaineas le tionscail talmhaíochta agus tionscail tuaithe agus an moladh is mó is féidir a thabhairt ná go mba deacair dom dul isteach sna scoileanna le a mbíonn de dhaoine bailithe istigh romham. Tá dúil mhór ag na fir anois san oideachas.  Bíodh an scéim seo ann, agus bíódh an oiread toradh air agus is mhaith linn, ach ná bíodh dul amú orainn&mdash;ní eíreoidh linn go ró-mhaith mura dtugaimid aghaidh ar an bpointe boise ar oideachas na ndaoine a bheas ag obair faoin tuaith.</P>
    <P>Is trua liom nár cheap an tAire&mdash;go haírithe anseo sa tSeanad, an áit a mbeimis ag súil le eolas níos doimhne na mar is gnáthach linn a fháil go minic, go haírithe le gairid&mdash;roinnt figiúirí a thabhairt dúinn maidir <Col N="1536" /> leis an mbeartas atá aige i leith an Bhille.</P>
    <P>Ba mhaith liom dá bhfeadfadh sé a insint dúinn go réasúnta, cruinn nó coibhneasach, cé mhéid acra atá súil aige a dréineálfar faoin scéim.  Ba mhaith liom dá n-insíodh sé dhúinn céard é an meán-chostas an t-acra.  Bhí caint anseo cheana faoi naoi n-acra agus £140 agus £27 a bhaint de mar gheall ar seo nó ar siúd, ach is é an rud ba mhaith liomsa, an rud ba mhaith linn ar fad, go simplódh an tAire an scéal agus go n-inseodh sé dhúinn cé mhéad acra ar dóigh leis go mbeidh éileamh ar chabhair uaidh lena dhréineáil.  Céard é an meán-chostas an t-acra a bheas ann?  Beidh £36 curtha in áirithe le haghaidh na hoibre; beidh £12 le chur suas ag an bhfeilméara féin; seasfaidh an Stát £24 eile nó dhá dtrian eile.  An dóigh leis an Aire, ón eolas atá aige ar scéimeanna den tsórt seo a tríáladh cheana, go mbeidh sé i ndon an obair a dhéanamh ar an airgead sin?  Nuair a bheas áireamh déanta aige ar a gcostas, ba mhaith liom go dtabharfadh sé léargas dúinn ar an bhfeabhas a cuirfear ar an talamh.  Mar shompla, an t-eolas ar mhaith liom leide dhe a fháil uaidh cé mhéad beithíoch sa mbreis a iomprós gach acra de thoradh an fheabhais?  Cé mhéad céad meáchain cruithneachtan, arbhair, fataí nó rútaí a gheofas muid de thoradh na scéime.  Níl mé ag iarraidh ceangal a chur ar an Aire go n-inseodh sé go dtí an céad meáchain é, ach ba mhaith linn go n-inseodh sé dhúinn céard is dóigh leis a bheas againn de thoradh na hoibre ar fad.  Bfhéidir nach miste má mheabhraím don Aire gur mhaith liom go mbeadh leide eolais nó léargas le fáil ar na ceisteanna sin.  Tiúrfadh sé faoi deara sa tuarascáil a fuair sé ar chúrsaí féir is dréineála sa tír tar éis ar cuireadh d'fheabhas ar an talamh in aice na Bearbha gur ar éigin a bhain na feilméaraí aon leas as an talamh a feabhsaíodh dá bharr.  Admhaítear gur feabhsaíodh an talamh, ach is cosúil nár mheas na feilméaraí gur bhfiú dóibh airgead a chaitheamh leis an talamh sin le súil go bhfaighidís breis torthaí dá bharr.  D'fhéadfainn féin míniú a thabhairt air b'fhéidir, ach nuair a léigh mé é chuir sé íonadh <Col N="1537" /> orm.  Tá muinín agam as na feilméaraí, nuair a níonn siad rud tá údar acu leis. Is minic a d'fiafraigh mé d'fheilméara tuige nár chuir sé leasú ar a chuid talún agus d'fhreagair sé &ldquo;ní íocfadh sé mé.&rdquo;  Is minic d'fiafraigh mé d'fheilméara tuige nár chuir sé síol ina chuid talún &ldquo;ní íocfadh sé mé.&rdquo; Is minic a d'fiafraigh mé d'fheilméara tuige nach ndéanfadh sé dréineáil ar a chuid talún &ldquo;ní íocfadh sé mé.&rdquo;  Níl ann ach bealach an fheilméara le rá go bhfuil an &ldquo;law of diminishing returns&rdquo; i bhfeidhm chomh fada is bhaineas lena chuid talún.  An bhfuil scéimeanna ceaptha amach&mdash;ní scéimeanna gairide ach scéimeanna fada&mdash; scéimeanna go bhfuil a dtéarmaí sáthach fada go mbeidh a fhios ag an bhfeilméara go mbeidh ioncam de thoradh an airgid agus an tsaothair má thugann sé faoin talamh a shaothrú tar éis a feabhsuithe faoin scéim seo?  Ní leor a rá go bhfuil scéim againn gur cinnte don tráchtáil idir sinn féin agus Sasana go ceann trí nó cheithre bliana.  Dúirt mé anseo sa tSeanad seachtain nó coicís ó shoin nach duine mé a mba gheal leis go dtarlódh aon rud do chúrsaí tráchtála nó geilleagair Shasana, ach ba cheart dúinn cuimhneamh orainn féin agus níl mé sasta go mbeidh cúrsaí tráchtála Shasana chomh híontach sna blianta atá romhainn agus a cheapas daoine áirithe.  Bfhéidir go bhfuil mé éadóchasach faoin scéal, bhféidir go bhfuil níos mó ná éadóchas ann.  Ar chaoi ar bith, níl an deis agam meastachán a dhéanamh ar cheist mar sin a bhíos ag an Aire, agus ba mhaith liom go dtiúrfadh an tAire léargas dúinn ar an gcuma is dóigh leis a bheas ar an margadh sin na blianta atá rómhainn, ionas go mbeimid i ndon a shocrú an bhfuilmid ar an mbealach ceart ag tabhairt faoin scéal seo ar chor ar bith.</P>
    <P>Ba mhaith liom fios a bheith agam ar an meán-chostas an t-acra faoin scéim agus dá réir sin cé mhéad breise a cuirfear ar thorthúlacht agus táirgiúlacht na talún de bharr na scéime go léir.  Thaitnigh sé liom nuair a mheabhraigh sé dhúinn, cuma cén feabhas a chuirfear ar an talamh, nach mbeidh aon ardú dá ghearradh ar na feilméaraí maidir le rátaí. Dúirt sé nach ndeanfaí ardú rátaí <Col N="1538" /> ach os cionn a choirp.  Deir an tAire rudaí agus dearmadann sé arís iad. Níl a fhios agam nár dhúirt sé cheana nach ndeanfaí rud áirithe ach os cionn a choirp agus rinneadh an rud ina dhiaidh sin.  Athraíonn an tAire a intinn. Tá cead ag daoine a n-intinn d'athrú anois agus arís, ach ní thaitníonn liom chomh minic agus a athráios. an tAire a intinn os comhair na tíre. Ar chaoi ar bith, beidh sé cláraithe ar imeachtaí an tSeanaid nach ngearrfar ardú rátaí ar na feilméaraí agus nach méadófar luacháil na bhfeilm de bharr na scéime, má thuigim i gceart é agus taitníonn sé sin liom.</P>
    <P>Tá an oiread le rá faoin rud seo ar fad gur doiligh na pointí a mheasaim a bheith fíor-thábhachthach a phiocadh amach, ach má mheabhraím ceann eile don Aire agus don tSeanad beidh mé sásta.</P>
    <P>Tiocfaidh, do réir mar thuigimse, an t-airgead le haghaidh na scéimeanna seo as iasachtaí na Stát Aontaithe. Is iasachtaí atá muid le fáil ó na Stáit Aontaithe agus sílim nach bhféadfadh an Seanad cuimhneamh ar sin sáthach minic nó cuimhneamh air sáthach dian.  Ní deontais atá muid a fháil ó na Stait Aontaithe ach iasacht dolaeirí agus tá muid ag dul na dolaeirí sin a úsáid, cuid mhaith acu, le haghaidh scéimeanna dréineála mar atá i gceist sa mBille agus scéimeanna míntíriú. Céard atá muid ag dul a dhéanamh ar ball leis an mbreis tairgiúlachta a gheobhas muid de bharr an Bhille seo?  Cá bhfuil an margadh ina gcóir siúd do réir an léargais atá againn faoi lathair?</P>
    <P>Tá an tAire féin ceanúil ar mhargadh Shasana.  Go deimhin, níl móran de rogha aige ina lán cásanna.  An bhreis tairgiúlachta mar sin a bheas ann de bharr na hoibre seo, rachaidh sé isteach ar mhargadh Shasana.  An bhreis a bheas ann cuirfear ar fáil é de bharr dolaeirí atá muid le fáil ar iasacht ó na Stáit Aontaithe. Nach ionann sin agus a rá go mbeimid ag úsáid na ndolaeirí a gheobhas muid ó Mheiriceá le cuidiú le Sasana? Bhfuil aon mhargadh déanta againn le Sasana go bhfaighimid na dolaeirí a bheas riachtanach ar ball le Meiriceá a íoc ar ais?  Labhair an tAire ar an <Col N="1539" /> scéal.  Níl mé a rá go raibh sé ag iarraidh dallamullóg a chur orainn ach níor mhínigh sé an scéal go hiomlán dúinn. Tá muid ag fáil na hiasachta sin ó Mheiriceá agus ba mhaith liom a fhiafraí anois cén áit a ngeobha muid na dolaeirí nuair a thiosfas lá na reicneála le dolaeirí Mheiriceá a íoc ar ais.  Ní haon chabhair don tSeanad a rá go bhfuil airgead á chur isteach i gciste faoi leith sa mBanc Ceannais.</P>
    <P>Ní haon chabhair a rá gurb é an bealach is fearr a d'fhéadfadh muintir na hÉireann airgead a chaitheamh é a chaitheamh ar thalamh na hÉirinn, go háirithe ós rud é go mbeidh orainn ar ball na fiacha sin a íoc ar ais arís leis na Stáit Aontaithe.  Cén áit a bhfaighimid na dolaeirí?  Má breathnaíonn an tAire ar chúrsaí tráchtála le blianta fada, tiúrfaidh sé faoi deara go bhfuil fuílleach na tráchtála idir sinne agus na Stáit Aontaithe go láidir inár gcoinnibh.  An dóigh leis an difríocht a bheas ann go bhfaighimid é as an tionscail cuartaíochta, an tourist trade? Gheobhaimid roinnt as, ach an bhfaighimid an oiread agus a chuirfeas ar ár gcumas na Stáit Aontaithe a íoc ar ais san aon airgead amháin a theastaíos uathu, dolaeirí, nó an bhfeictear dó go mbeidh ar ár gcumas toradh déantóireachta a chur amach go dtí tiortha eile agus go bhfaighimid dá bharr sin dolaeirí a chuirfeas ar ár gcumas na fiacha seo a íoc ar ais?</P>
    <P>I ndeireadh cúise, an bhfuil an oiread sin dóchais ag an Aire go mbeidh an oiréad sin feabhais tagtha ar chúrsaí tráchtála Shasana taobh istigh de trí nó cheithre bliana go mbeidh, ní amháin dolaeirí aici lena bealach féin a íoc ach go mbeidh siad sásta an punt a dhéanamh inaistrithe ar dolaeirí ionas go mbeimid ábalta an riar a bheas uainn d'fháil agus na fiacha a bheas orainn a íoc ar ais?  Tá daoine sa tír ag caint air sin.  Labhair le duine ar bith faoi agus dearfaidh sé leat: &ldquo;Tá a fhios agam céard a tharlós.  Nuair a thiocfas an lá, ní bheidh tada le híoc.  Nuair thiocfas an lá, maithfear na fiacha dhúinn nó caithfear na fiacha a mhaitheamh dhúinn.&rdquo;  B'fhéidir sin.  Má tá aon tuiscint mar sin ann, agus ní chreidim go bhfuil, ba cheart go mbeadh a <Col N="1540" /> fhios againn é, ach muna bhfuil, má tá muid ar an aigne go bhfuil dualgas morálta orainn na fiacha seo a íoc ar ais, idir prionsiopal agus ús, ansin caithfimid anois, an t-am atá ann, ár n-aigne a dhéanamh suas ar cén chaoi ar féidir dúinn an táirgaíocht a fheabhsú sa tslí go mbeidh dolaeirí le fáil againn.  Caithfimid ár n-aigne a dhéanamh suas faoi cén chaoi a bhfaighimid na dolaeirí sin, bíodh siad sin le fáil de bharr socruithe trádála le tíortha seachas Sasana nó de bharr socruithe a dhéanfeas muid le Sasana de bharr na cabhrach atá muid a thabhairt di faoi láthair.</P>
    <P>Ba mhaith liom go n-inseodh an tAire dhúinn céard díreach is dóigh leis i dtaobh an scéil sin go léir.  Ní hé go dteastaíonn uaim go n-abródh sé linn go mba mhaith leis go mbeadh an scéal mar seo nó go mbeadh an scéal mar siúd.  Tá comhairleoirí aige, agus tá i mease ár seirbhíseach ardfhir atá chomh heolasach agus chomh cliste le haon tseirbhísigh sa domhan.  Tá taidhleoirí againn thar sáile agus támaid ag fáil eolais ar chúrsaí tráchtála agus ar chúrsaí airgeadais an domhan.  Tá figiúirí agus tuairiscí sa Roinn Airgeadais, sa Roinn Tráchtála, sa Roinn Talmhaíochta agus uile an oiread agus ba cheart go mbeadh ar chumas an Aire meastachán réasúnta cruinn do thabhairt dúinn i dtaobh na ceiste seo atá mé tar éis a lua.  Tá má ar aon-intinn le duine adúirt gurb é ár ndualgas an t-ualach a éadroimiú ar dhaoine an oiread agus is féidir, ach ba mhaith liom tuairim níos fearr a bheith agam ná már atá ar cé mhéad saothair, ar cén deis saothruithe sa mbreis a bheas ag duine de thoradh na scéimeanna seo a cuirfear ar bun faoin mBille.</P>
    <P>Mar shampla, an Vóta a thug an tAire isteach an lá cheana sa Dáil &mdash;dá mbeadh cead agam tagairt a dhéanamh dhó&mdash;ní thaitníonn an chosúlacht atá air liom.  Do réir mar fheicim féin an meastachán sin, caithfeúr trí ceathrúna den mhilliún punt ar oifigigh, ar chostas taistil agus ar mheaisíní.  Feicim go bhfuil £50,000 curtha síos le haghaidh fógraíochta.  Níl aon locht agam air, ach feicim ansin nach mbeidh ach impeall le ceathrú cuid an Vóta <Col N="1541" /> ag dul do na feilméaraí i riocht deontas. Tá súil agam nach sampla an meastachán sin ar chaitheamh an airgid ar an scéim fré chéile.  Tá súil agam go mbeidh i bhfad níos mó den airgead seo ag dul do na feilméaraí iad féin ná mar is dóigh liom do réir an Vóta seo atá os comhair na Dála faoi láthair&mdash;trí ceathrúna ag dul ar ghléasra, costas taistil agus mar sin de agus timpeall le ceathrú cuid ag dul do na feilméaraí.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Séamus Ó Díolún Séamus Ó Díolún">
      <NameTxt>Séamus Ó Díolún</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl sé sin macánta.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Ná habair nach bhfuil sé macánta.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Séamus Ó Díolún Séamus Ó Díolún">
      <NameTxt>Séamus Ó Díolún</NameTxt>
      <P>Deirim é.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Dá n-abródh an tAire go bhfuil dul amú orm, bheinn níos sásta.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Séamus Ó Díolún Séamus Ó Díolún">
      <NameTxt>Séamus Ó Díolún</NameTxt>
      <P>Nach bhfuil &ldquo;Grants towards purchase of machinery and equipment&rdquo; sa meastachán?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá tuarastail, páigh agus liúntais de £210,000 le teacht amach as an £1,000,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Séamus Ó Díolún Séamus Ó Díolún">
      <NameTxt>Séamus Ó Díolún</NameTxt>
      <P>Cad mar gheall ar &ldquo;lime and fertilisers?&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Go maith, ach fan go bhfeicimíd an scór.  Tá costas taistil £20,000 agus meaisíní, gléasraí agus eile £200,000.  Sin suas agus anuas le £500,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Séamus Ó Díolún Séamus Ó Díolún">
      <NameTxt>Séamus Ó Díolún</NameTxt>
      <P>Nach do na foilméaraí na meaisíní agus na gléasraí?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá £180,000 i gcóir aoil agus leasú agus tá £260,000 mar dheontais do na foilméaraí.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Séamus Ó Díolún Séamus Ó Díolún">
      <NameTxt>Séamus Ó Díolún</NameTxt>
      <P>Cé dhó an &ldquo;lime agus fertilisers?&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá mé lántsásta leis, ach tá me ag breathnú ar an Vóta ina iomlán.  Tá £50,000 ceaptha i gcóir fógraíochta, agus mar sin de; oifigí, stóras, cíos agus eíle, £15,000; agus mionchostais éagsúla £10,000.  Tá mise a rá go bhfeicthear dom nach bhfuil sa mhéid atá ag dul do na feilméaraí ar a gcuid oibre ach cuid an-bheag den £1,000,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1542" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Séamus Ó Díolún Séamus Ó Díolún">
      <NameTxt>Séamus Ó Díolún</NameTxt>
      <P>Mar dheontas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Cinnte, agus tá súil agam go mbeidh i bhfad níos mó le votáil mar gheall ar oideachas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Séamus Ó Díolún Séamus Ó Díolún">
      <NameTxt>Séamus Ó Díolún</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;Advertising and publicity&rdquo;&mdash;nach oideachas é sin?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Na fógraí a bheas sna paipéirí&mdash;ní hé sin an sórt oideachas atá i gceist agam.  Oideachas teicniúil atá im aigne.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Séamus Ó Díolún Séamus Ó Díolún">
      <NameTxt>Séamus Ó Díolún</NameTxt>
      <P>Agus tá £50,000 á vótáil le haghaidh oideachaís den tsórt sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>I gcomórtas leis an scéal atá le réiteach againn, ní fiú trumpa gan teanga an méid sin le haghaidh oideachais den tsórt sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Séamus Ó Díolún Séamus Ó Díolún">
      <NameTxt>Séamus Ó Díolún</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;Films and publicity&rdquo;&mdash;nach oideachas iad-san?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Cinnte, agus taitníonn siad liom, ach, ina dhiaidh sin, más dóigh leis an Aire gur figiúirí ar fiú trácht orthu i gcúrsaí oideachais an £50,000 atá luaite anseo, is ar éigin is fiú a bheith ag caint air.  Deirimse nach bhfuil mé cinnte go bhfuil an scéal go hiomlán agam.  D'fhéadfadh dul amú a bheith orm.  Tá a fhios agam nach bhfuil an cheist go hiomlán anseo, ach bheadh súil agam go mbeadh i bhfad níos mó, go mbeadh &ldquo;proportion&rdquo; níos airde ag dul do na feilméaraí ná mar is dóigh a bheas dá réir sin.</P>
      <P>Maidir leis na meaisíní, níl aon aimhreas ach go bhfuil an tAire anláidir ar na meaisíní.  Thaitnigh liom ar shlí rud adúirt an tAire trathnóna nuair a bhí sé ag caint agus nuair dúirt sé:</P>
      <P>This is the way we want it and this is the way we are going to have it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Nuair a bhí sé ag cur síos ar lucht géilleagair agus prionsabail geilleagair agus uile, d'fhuagair sé rud a d'fhuagair mé féin níos mó ná aon uair amháin sa tSeanad, go bhfuil rudaí níos airde ar an saol ná geilleagair.  D'fhéadfadh, áfach, an tAire a bheith ag dul amú ina thuairim mar gheall ar na meaisíní. Níor mhiste liom dá bhfágfaí na meaisíní i leataoibh, nó roinnt acu, agus go gcaithfí níos mó airgid ar <Col N="1543" /> obair láimhe.  B'fhéidir go dtiocfadh daoine ar ais go dtí an tír seo.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Séamus Ó Díolún Séamus Ó Díolún">
      <NameTxt>Séamus Ó Díolún</NameTxt>
      <P>Nach bhfuil siad ag teacht ar ais?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Is maith liom go bhfuil agus taitníonn liom go mór an sásamh a thugas sé don Aire go bhfuil siad ag teacht ar ais, mar cheann eile de na tuairimí&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Séamus Ó Díolún Séamus Ó Díolún">
      <NameTxt>Séamus Ó Díolún</NameTxt>
      <P>Tabharfaidh mé ainmneacha don tSeanadóir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní gá dhuit.  Ní fada uainn an lá nuair a bhí tuairim eile ag an Aire, go mba leas na hÉireann daoine dul amach, ach tá an beart sin slacaithe anois agus cuireann sé an-ríméad ar an Aire go bhfuil na daoine seo ag filleadh ar an tír.  Ba mhaith liom a lámh a craitheadh go mór ar an athrú aigne sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Séamus Ó Díolún Séamus Ó Díolún">
      <NameTxt>Séamus Ó Díolún</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl aon athrú aigne ann.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Is minic sna blianta atá caite an Rialtas a bhí ann roimhe seo go ndúradar go mba mhaith leo rudaí a dhéanamh nach bhféadfaí iad a chosaint do réir bun-phrionsabal an gheilleagair agus cé mhéad uair a rinneadh gáire agus magadh fúthú? Ní hé, mar adúirt, an teicniúlacht, an éifeacht ó thaobh geilleagair ach an leas náisiúnta, an leas sóisialach an rud is airde.  Is maith liom go bhfuil an tuairim sin ag an Aire agus beimid ag súil le rudaí níos fearr as seo amach ná mar bhí súil againn leo go dtí seo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Chuir mé spéis an-mhór sa bpíosa cainte a rinne an tAire faoi Alt 5 agus an míniú a thug sé dúinn ar an dóigh a bhreathnós sé ar obair na gcigirí agus ar an mbealach a dhéanfas na cigirí a gcuid oibre.  Bhí na cigirí faoi dhrochmheas ag an Aire uair amháin, ach tá sé anois ag iarraidh ar na coistí contae talmhaíochta níos mó cigirí a cheapadh. Athraíonn an tAire a intinn faoin a lán rudaí agus is maith liom go bhfuil a intinn athraithe i dtaobh ceist seo na cigireachta.  Ní bhaineann na cigirí feidhm as an dlí ach an uair a mbeadh gá leis.  Nach mar sin a bhí an scéal i gcónaí?  Nach mar sin a bhí an scéal faoin Rialtas a bhí ann roimhe seo?  Cuirfear an dlí i bhfeidhm go <Col N="1544" /> láidir ar na daoine ar cheart an dlí a chur orthu.  Bhfuil a fhios ag aon duine aon ócáid ar baineadh feidhm mí-cheart ag an Rialtas a bhí ann roimhe as coras na cigireachta?  Nach bhfuil a fhios ag aon duine go mba é polosaí na gcigirí gan chur isteach ar daoine ach a laghad agus a bfhéidir? Taitníonn liom go mór an dearcadh nua seo a bheith ag an Aire i dtaobh cigirí agus riachtanas cigirí.</P>
    <P>Ar aon chuma, ní shílim gur gá dom tada eile a rá faoin scéal.  Chomh fada agus a théas an prionsabal, is é sin, feabhas a chur ar an talamh agus cuidiú le feilméaraí níos fearr ná mar rinneadh go dtí seo, chomh fada agus a théann sé, cuspóir don tsórt seo a bhaint amach, is maith agus is rí-mhaith liom an Bille seo. Tá súil againn go mbeidh an toradh air a bhfuil súil againn ar fad leis. Is duine mise a chreideas, mar chreideas an mhuintir atá anseo liom, má theastaíonn uainn caighdeán maireachtála na ndaoine sa tír seo a ardú, ní ardóimid é ach de bharr breis táirgiúlachta.  Caithfimid a bheith cinnte, má cuirtear é sin ar bun, nach de bharr fiacha a chur orainn é nach mbeimid i ndon a íoc.  Rinne mé tagairt don treo a bhfuil na dolaeirí ag gluaiseacht agus ba mhaith liom go bpléifí an scéal sin, agus má tá míniú air, seachas an míniú atá agam, ba mhaith liom é a chloisint.  Is maith liom an beartas agus tá súil agam, má bhíonn gá dhúinn cur síos ar an gceist arís, go mbeidh an chosúlacht uirthi í bheith ag dul chun cinn chomh sásúil agus ba mhaith linn ar fad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ó Buachalla may feel that the part which he had to play was to speak as slightingly as he could of the measure before the House.  It is not a very big part for any man and particularly a responsible member of this House.  I suppose, as through the course of history, men have stood in the shadow of great events without having been in the least conscious of the fact.  Perhaps Senator Ó Buachalla stood in that place to-night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Senator Ó Buachalla Senator Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Senator Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Do I understand, Sir, that Senator Baxter said <Col N="1545" /> I spoke slightingly of the measure before us?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what you understood from him, Senator.  The Chair cannot go into that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>This measure, in my judgment, and, I believe, in the judgment of many farmers from Connaught, is going to be written down as one of the biggest events in the history of this State since its establishment and the fact that the Minister who initiated this measure takes a pride in his work is, I think, justifiable. A great deal of Ireland's history, sad, tragic, and noble, has been woven around the activities of our people on the soil.  I can recall a day when, 50 years ago, I was a very small boy, my father came to the school and, taking me by the hand, fetched me to a political meeting in the village about a mile from my home.  There, at the meeting, he lifted me up so that I might see the speaker, who on that day in the remote village of Bawnboy in the County of Cavan was John Dillon.  He was there raising his voice, addressing a crowd of people from the parish and from the adjoining parish who had collected to hear him in protest against the eviction of a small Protestant farmer.  The eviction had taken place and the man's Catholic neighbours had rallied around and built him a small home on the roadside adjoining his farm.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Many events, great and small, have taken place in this country since then. I would hardly have dreamed on that day that Irishmen in their own Parliament would have the son of John Dillon enunciating for them a new planned policy for progressive agriculture based on the land which John Dillon and his colleagues of those days defended so heroically so that the men who lived on that land might hand it down to their sons so that by right and title they might call it their own.  I think that everybody in this House and those who know anything of the remote or the more recent history of their country should be glad and proud to be able to make a contribution to this policy and have every right to take justifiable pride with the <Col N="1546" /> Minister that these days when we can do these things are with us.  I have said a great deal of our history has been bound up with the land.  The Minister when he came to office was, in my judgment, confronted with very considerable difficulties.  Not only was he faced with depleted flocks and herds but the land of the country was impoverished and in a very run-down condition.  Poverty of the soil means poverty for the people on and working on it.  It means poverty for the workers employed thereon which in turn means poverty for the villages, towns and traders.  Low farm income means low purchasing capacity for the farming community and the vicious circle goes on impoverishing the country as a whole.  You cannot have a high spending capacity on the part of the farmers where you have land poor and impoverished.</P>
    <P>That was how the Minister found it when he took over office.  He expressed the opinion that there was no great encouragement in the past for the people to put their energy and savings into the land, but I think he was perhaps rather kind in not pointing to the fact how over a period of years the policy of impoverishment of the soil has gone on.  For a number of years the earnings from the land in this country were so low that farmers were unable to meet current charges much less be in the position of putting back into the soil anything to restore its fertility.  The Minister found, with other things, a decrepit machine, and, looking across the country to see what they could do, he and his colleagues came to the conclusion that unless the land is strong and vigorous the people of the country must suffer.  He has planned this scheme, and I think the attitude which this House on all sides should adopt towards it should be to make it wider and better if that is possible, and to extend the maximum of support to the Minister to encourage him in the good work.  If we have any contributions to make to the scheme or any suggestions whatever, I am sure they will be received by the Minister and valued by him and they will help him in his task.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1547" /> As far as this Bill is concerned it cannot be said to be anything more than an enabling measure.  We have no great experience of the work which the Minister has set himself, and we have got to learn.  There are, no doubt technicians and young men of considerable ability in the Department, but there is very little experience of this work, while the attitude heretofore has been to reject much of the advice offered in regard to the necessity for a scientific approach to our land problems. Now, we have something new. I agree with the Minister when he says that the courage and the imagination of the Minister for Finance is something which must be commended.  However optimistic or aggressive a Minister may be, without the active and sympathetic consideration of the Minister for Finance he could not hope to succeed.</P>
    <P>The scheme, as I see it in the initial stages, is going to apply to eight counties, to which another county is soon to be added and the possibilities will only unfold themselves as the work proceeds.  I feel, however, that it would be very unfortunate to have any definite views formed now as to what exactly can be done.  We have got a great deal to discover about the nature of the soil.  Scientists all over the world are only beginning to learn about things which are there, but which were known to the ancients.  A great deal of information is only tapped in that way by those working on the land.  There is, for instance, a decline in production, there is bad farming, waste, and eroded soils in many continents, all the fruit of lack of knowledge as well as recklessness in farming.</P>
    <P>To a certain extent we have neglected the soil.  It is this soil the Minister is attempting to reconstruct, and as the first step in his plan he has a scheme of drainage.  I do not know if people in Connaught have the idea that, in the main, the problem is one which applies to poorer land.  I think we would be astonished at the extent to which this part of the scheme will be operated on some of our best land. It is true that in poor counties in the <Col N="1548" /> West and also in Cavan drainage is essential, as acid soil makes the proper cultivation of grass crops practically impossible.  A great deal of such land will benefit, but many Senators may not be aware that large areas of Meath and Westmeath, where we have the best land in Europe, will come in under this scheme and benefit by it.</P>
    <P>The problem of wet soil requires drainage.  I have certain views with regard to the method of approach to the problem that I have not had an opportunity of expressing but that I want to discuss now, because I think that such approach may be of considerable importance.  It is true that if soil is very wet and heavy or of a retentive nature full development is only possible after proper drainage. The question is: what is proper drainage?  That requires close study at the beginning, and it would be advisable that that aspect should be attended to before we go too far.</P>
    <P>Under the Minister's plans there is to be made available powerful machinery for drainage.  That is essential. The capital expenditure involved there is beyond the capacity of many farmers unless enterprising contractors or people who own much land are prepared to invest in the enterprise.  I have recently seen some planned drainage carried out in another area, and I suggest to the Minister and to his technical advisers that it would be well worth while investigating the possibility of that plan.  I saw a farm containing over 700 acres consisting of stiff heavy clay, similar to a good deal of the soil that has to be dealt with, and the work of sub-soiling machines there has been astonishing.  The gentleman who owns the farm who carried out the work is probably the most advanced agriculturist in the 32 Counties.  The machine was a 50 horse-power caterpillar tractor and it operated on 60 or 80 acres at first.  The scientific effects were remarkable.  The work was carried out in the autumn and, according to the owner, the results were equivalent to the application of at least two cwts. of sulphate of ammonia per acre. Apparently after subsoiling a nitrofication process took place which was astonishing.</P>
    <P>Drainage of the soil is something <Col N="1549" /> about which farmers have to be rather careful.  The British have had some strange experiences, as they discovered in some areas that they had taken the water out of the soil all too quickly. Later this had serious results in a water shortage.  Before such work is done, I suggest that it is well worthy of investigation, as I am convinced that we have a great deal to learn about it. It is better that we should learn early. There must be trial and error.  It is important, accordingly, that we should make our discoveries as early as possible.</P>
    <P>The plan for the application of phosphate of lime on these soils is something that is absolutely essential. Drainage alone will not re-establish a healthy condition in the soil.  We have to see that this soil condition is corrected.  I suggest to the Minister that when dealing with the land, whether in Connaught or Leinster, not only are drainage, liming and phosphates essential, but there is something which is of equal importance, the sowing of proper seeds.  When the Minister's technicians go on a farm to study the conditions there with regard to what is to be done I believe that in a great many instances it will be fruitful for these technicians to advise the farmers to plough their pastures and re-seed them.  I believe we will get the quickest and best results in that way. I do not know the position at the moment.  I know there are certain prejudices against the policy of reseeding&mdash;or, at least, there were certain prejudices in that respect among certain people in this part of the country.  I have had opportunities of discussing this problem with many people up and down the country.  I am convinced that there is a very considerable lack of information&mdash;even amongst our technicians&mdash;on this score.  I want to suggest that there are ways and means and places where information, which is absolutely reliable and incontrovertible, can be had on this subject.  When we attempt to measure the results of proper cultivation of our grass lands against the kind of thing that has been going on we can visualise what the consequences would be for the nation as a whole if, <Col N="1550" /> in conjunction with the Minister's policy of draining and of fertilising the soil, we attempted a proper scheme of cultivation and sowing of proper seeds.  Any measurements we have so far down here indicate that while we get about 10 cwts. of dry matter per acre it is possible to get 30 cwts.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Senator is looking at Part III.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I am looking at it at the moment.  I realise that, and I shall discuss it as the Minister has raised the matter.  What I want to stress in regard to this matter is that I do not think that we are to wait until a sufficient supply of the kind of seeds which the Minister is going to propagate will be available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree, but look at the last census.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that, but I think it would be a mistake if the emphasis is going to be on the question of developing indigenous strains and if the other aspect of the plan is to be left in abeyance until we are producing what we regard as the most suitable grasses.  I hope the Minister will see that his officers will very vigorously propagate that doctrine throughout the whole country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is, however, an aspect of this problem to which I do not think sufficient attention has been given.  The Minister has to get all the land of the country into proper condition and proper heart.  The increase in our exports is going to be determined by the extent to which we are able to increase production and it is going to be determined also by the speed with which we can reach our maximum production. If it is going to take us a considerable number of years before maximum production can be reached, then our whole economy is going to suffer.  I think that the position in regard to agriculture is going to become increasingly difficult.  There is no question that it is not going to be difficult to prevent a break in prices. If agricultural prices break here our whole economy is going to suffer and, it could be, badly shattered.  But if there is to be a struggle and a battle <Col N="1551" /> amongst farming communities in different countries to keep a hold on the market, those who have raised their production to the maximum, those who are able to produce most economically and those who are able to put the best goods on the market at the lowest price will be able to hold on.  It is the farmer who is able to increase the starch production on his acre from 1,000 units to 3,000 units who is going to be best able to carry his rates, rent, labour costs and to give to the consumer the kind of product the consumer wants and at the price the consumer wants it at.  That is not going to be such a simple problem on many farms.</P>
    <P>It is a great mistake to imagine that because a farm may be dry the farm land is good.  That is an aspect of this whole problem of the rehabilitation of our soil to which I think further attention must be given.  The Minister is making provision here for the development of hill farming, and that, I think, will cover very great areas in the country where rehabilitation is necessary. I do not know exactly what the Minister has in mind with regard to hill farming.  A good deal of information is available from what has been done in Wales and elsewhere in regard to this matter.  I think that we can very greatly improve the carrying capacity and the productive capacity of the hills of this country by the acceptance of a technique which is known elsewhere.  However, there is land on the plains which is not any richer than many of these hill farms we are going to deal with.  It is a very peculiar problem.  It is a problem about which a great many of our people know very little.  It is not a problem of which any of our Cavan farmers have any experience whatever. I think it is confined to certain areas in the country, but it is a difficult problem for the farmers in those areas, and I think that the Minister and his officials will have to sit down and put their thinking caps on them to consider what is to be done for these people, because an increase in their productive capacity is as urgent and important for the nation as a <Col N="1552" /> whole as the improvement of the hill farm or the wet fields in my county.</P>
    <P>I can recall going a number of years ago to two farms in County Wexford. It was an absolutely new experience for me.  I visited one of these farms some time in the month of February. A farmer was ploughing in one of the fields.  As I was going down to the farmer on business a terrific shower came on.  I had provided against the rain.  The farmer just stopped his horses in the field and, with a sack on his shoulders, he stood until the storm blew over.  That was for some 20 minutes or more.  When I got to the field he was ploughing he waited for about five or seven minutes before he started his horses again.  On my way over to him I noticed water rushing down just where the last score had been ploughed.  That went on for six or seven minutes.  Then it was dry.  The farmer started his horses again and there was not a sign of rain.  Had I had the same experience in one of my own fields I might take my horses away because I would not be able to put them back on it for a month.  However, in the case of this County Wexford farmer the open, porous character of the soil was such that anything could rush through it.  That means that its fertility was being washed away.  It was a very poor farm&mdash;the farmer's conditions indicated that and, as a matter of fact, that was why I was there.  That is a real problem.  No man could grow rich or have a decent standard of living on a farm with soil such as that.  Enough is not known about that problem.  Somehow people get the idea that people who live on such soils are silent.  They make a terrific effort to live.  They work from dawn till dark.  They must live by the fruits of their labours.  They are always toiling and yet a great many of them are in debt.</P>
    <P>I can recall another farm which I visited in the same county. The cattle were lying in the fields &mdash;it was a warm day in July&mdash; and I never saw poorer cattle in my life.  They were just obviously subsisting until the harvest crops were gathered and they were put in and fed for the winter.  There was not a sign of grass on the field.  I inquired when <Col N="1553" /> it was cultivated and was told that three of four years ago it was under cultivation, that it had been set out with a grass crop but there was not a vestige of cultivation on it.  We have soils like that which present a special problem, they are of a type of which nothing is known in a number of counties. If these people are to have a decent standard of life and make a reasonable contribution to the country's total production, they must get help of a kind that they never have been given in the past and that requires study of a problem which has not been revealed up to the present.</P>
    <P>The Minister is making a major contribution to the further development of our resources.  What he is attempting is both courageous and imaginative.  It would be a mistake for any of us to think we know everything about the land and about nature.  The more intimate you try to become with the ways of nature and the reactions of the soil to the different activities of man, the more you realise how little you know about it and how careful you have to be in speaking dogmatically or planning what we ought to do.  I suggest that this measure is, in the main, an enabling one.  We should all wish it well, accepting it for what it is and realising that we are going to do something new.  Many things may not turn out as we would wish, but they are being attempted in the right spirit and with the right motive.  If each in his own way will try to make a decent contribution, both in advice and in effort, the country will get much out of this measure, and progress will be as marked, as in the case of the struggle of men of another generation, of whom I spoke at the beginning of my remarks.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I must congratulate the Minister on his excellent Bill, which is calculated to rehabilitate the soil of the country.  He has said several times since he became Minister that the whole wealth of Ireland is derived from the soil.  In a general way that is probably true but, at the same time, the urban dweller must not allow too much importance to be attached to the primary producer.  The Minister has had the benefit&mdash;a questionable <Col N="1554" /> benefit, perhaps&mdash;of studying the science of Political Economy in University College, Dublin, and is no doubt familiar with the earlier school of economy, the Physiocrats, who maintained that the only true source of production of the national wealth is in the landowners and farmers.  I do not suggest, however, that the Minister is liable to fall into the physiocratic heresy.  Having struck that blow on behalf of the non-agricultural section of the population, I will admit that the farmers are, from the production point of view, the most important section, especially in regard to exports.  As the Minister has emphasised frequently, so truly, every percentage increase in production will mean a greater percentage increase in exports.  From the point of view of the balance of payments and the financial repercussions, increased exports are greatly to be desired.</P>
      <P>It always gives me great pleasure to find that, in 1949&mdash;when so much water has flowed under bridges, and, I am sorry to say, in Europe so much blood &mdash;the principles of agriculture which were held by the first distinguished Minister for Agriculture in this country have been completely vindicated by the course of events.  It gives me great pleasure to congratulate the Minister on carrying on the policy of that first Minister, who was assailed on all sides by people less wise and less prescient than he and who called him in derision the &ldquo;Minister for Grass.&rdquo;  That is one of the terms which, born in derision, live to be lauded.  I am not sure that the Minister would like to be titled by any other name than that of the &ldquo;Minister for Grass.&rdquo;  It is true, in a vivid sense, that all flesh is grass, all human and animal life, all exports, all means of subsistence, ultimately come from grass.  It has been stated by Senator Baxter that all production is bound up with drainage. That is why this Bill is particularly welcome. It is directed towards the drainage of the land and will bring about, we all hope, a serious contribution to general productivity, to the standard of living, to the volume of agricultural production and to exports.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I cannot sufficiently express my agreement with what the Minister said <Col N="1555" /> regarding the distinction to be drawn between State help and self help.  Part of my education has been derived from Sir Horace Plunkett and Father Finlay, who emphasised the great necessity for self help and the necessity to draw a line between these two things.  Most of my lessons I learned from these two preceptors.</P>
    <P>The investment which is being made in drainage in this Bill is a truly productive investment from the national point of view.  Perhaps I am too broadminded in seeing round a problem and have not the single-minded enthusiasm for a cause which makes a really great Minister.  Seeing too much round the problem leads to inefficiency, but I cannot help feeling, from the point of view of investments, that liquidity when one has to repay the debt is not entirely undesirable.  Whatever the Minister may say, from the point of view of liquidity, this is not perhaps quite as good an investment as the despised and derided consolidated stocks referred to earlier in the debate.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator prefer the consolidated stock?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not express any preference at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I did, however.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I said that I saw sufficiently around the subject to say that perhaps there was something to be said for the liquidity of consolidated stock and something to be said for drainage for dryness.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>And solidity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>The real point is that I do agree with the Minister of course that it is an excellent investment. I am very glad to see that Marshall Aid, these funds which are being piled up, should be put to such an admirably productive purpose, and it is only fair for us to say that the State as a whole is under great debt to the United States of America, not only for the provision of Marshall Aid, but for the readiness of the administrators to consent to the investment of the accumulated funds for this wholly admirable purpose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would ask the Minister to recall <Col N="1556" /> that in the course of his speech he referred to the necessity for improving the land and the people on the land.  I suggest that in addition to drainage, the provision of seed and the other measures we have discussed this evening, there are other directions in which there might be an admirable investment, increased agricultural education and increased agricultural expertise.  I hope that the same funds which are being utilised to build up the land will be utilised to build up the men on the land and I hope to see a great extension of agricultural education and agricultural research during the next few years.  I hope if that programme is carried through that my own college, which is associated with the Albert College at Glasnevin which has borne the burden and heat of the day when there was not so much support or so much money for it, will not be entirely neglected in the course of this educational development.</P>
    <P>This brings me to the point that the Minister invited questions and I might as well ask them.  With regard to repayment through annuities, the Minister suggested that conservative and hide-bound financiers might object to a 60-year annuity.  I do not plead guilty to any of these titles, and even if I did, I do not see anything wrong with a 60-year annuity.  The only reason I referred to annuities was to give the Minister an opportunity of clearing up the considerable amount of confusion which exists in the public mind regarding the position of the annuities since the Land Act of 1933. If the Minister looked at paragraph 517 of the Banking Report he would see a question asked by the Banking Commission which has never been answered by any Minister of this or the last Government, a question which affects the welfare of every farmer in this country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>May I inquire, if the Senator will excuse me, in Heaven's name how am I regarded as the responsible Minister to answer a question regarding Land Commission procedure which has remained unanswered for 11 years?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>The only answer I can give&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1557" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not the Minister for Lands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;if the Minister for Agriculture disclaims responsibility&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>For the Land Commission? Undoubtedly I do, most emphatically.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>Without pursuing it in the form of a question perhaps, Sir, I may address you and the Seanad in the indicative mood again to state my own reaction to the Minister's speech which does not call for a reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If it has the remotest connection with the Bill before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been, together with a great many people, puzzled by the whole question of land purchase annuities and I did feel that in the Minister's speech the mystery had been solved because the Minister stated this evening that these new annuities in repayment of land reclamation advances were to run for 60 years, on the same terms, I think he said, and concommitant in every way with, the land purchase annuities. It occurred to me that here is the answer to the question which has been unanswered for years; if the two annuities are alike in every way then we have an answer to the question the Banking Commission asked and nobody answered, that is that the annuities are to run for 60 years.  I think he has said so and therefore I am not asking the Minister for any reply other than his own.  I would draw the attention of the Seanad to this interesting revelation: for the first time a Minister has stated that the land purchase annuities halved by the Act of 1933 will terminate in 60 years and not, as the Banking Commission feared, now that the sinking fund provisions seem to have been dropped, remain as a permanent charge on the land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to compliment the Minister on his striking departure, if I may say his characteristic departure, in producing this picturesque presentation of the <Col N="1558" /> question.  It would be a good thing if other Ministers, notably the Minister for Finance, would take a leaf out of his book in presenting their cases particularly at Budget time.  I do not intervene as a rule in matters which are peculiarly agricultural, but I suggest that this is not so peculiarly agricultural as the average matter relating to farmers which comes before us.  I would rather regard it as a business proposition.  If, as Senator O'Brien indicated, we are forced to admit, and do admit, that the economy of the country is based on the land and if our present position is based on a position which I will call X and if under this Bill before us X is going to become X plus, then obviously we are going to increase the capital assets of the country on which all of us live. I just have had the advantage of travelling through the Continent and you do not need to be very observant to note the complete utilisation of the soil there.  France has been through a devastating war and I challenge anyone who has had the experience I have had in the past few weeks of travelling hundreds of miles through France to see an inch, literally an inch, of waste ground.  We are going to utilise the sterling moneys which are going to be deposited against the dollars we are spending now for this project.  On the face of it, I, personally, am inclined to welcome this proposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The expert farmers in this House will, perhaps, in the course of the debate reveal criticisms which I am not capable of revealing.  I do not profess to have a knowledge of farming matters, but if criticisms are put forward the Minister will no doubt do his best to dispose of them.  We are really being asked to finance an enterprise, a project which envisages faith, not in the present but in the future, and that faith is going to presuppose the continuance of our ability to dispose of our exportable agricultural produce. I suggest, because of the present hazy condition of world currency, the hazy condition particularly of sterling itself, that in the development of this ambitious scheme which is now before the House more consideration should really be given than has been given up to now to the provision of an alternative <Col N="1559" /> market for the produce we are going to export.  The Minister undoubtedly has this in mind, but we must remember that we are going to be repaid in 60 years' time in sterling, presumably, unless we change our currency in the meantime, against the dollars we are spending now, and for that reason we must look into the position which will be created if we continue to pile up sterling assets of doubtful exchange value later on.  I agree with Senator O'Brien when he says how much we are indebted to the United States for Marshall Aid.  Marshall Aid is one thing that is going to help Europe and we, even though we are on the outskirts, are in Europe.  In itself Marshall Aid is an investment, and it is also an insurance policy, and we have to take the view that whatever we get to-day must in God's good time be repaid.</P>
    <P>I do not intend going into the details of the scheme as has been done by farmer Senators but I welcome the provision in the Bill for up-to-date machinery, which is going to do more than develop our farms.  As I see it, it will benefit not only the farmers themselves but it will give an incentive to mechanically-minded young men to stay on the land and that is going to go a long way to stopping emigration and will enable these young men to stay where they can be of best service to the nation.  If the machinery of the Bill is going to result in the creation of squads of expert technicians, that is going to lead to benefits which even the Minister himself could not estimate. In addition to the benefit which it is going to be to the agricultural community it is a good business proposition. It is a measure that is a credit to the Minister and I trust that his highest hopes in the matter will be fully realised by results.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JeremiahRyan" hpid="Colonel Ryan Colonel Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill, which I think is a revolutionary step in regard to Irish agriculture.  It is my experience that the small farmer with ten, 15 or 25 acres was always in a difficult position, dragging the devil by the tail, and his small family were forced to emigrate except the one son who was to get the farm.  He, in turn, started off on the farm with very little <Col N="1560" /> to carry on and was soon in as difficult a position as his father who had passed it on to him.  It was the sons of these farmers who provided the bulk of the emigrants and the names on the list of registered unemployed.  I believe that, apart from the scientific aspects, the measure is going to benefit those farmers.  It will further provide employment for the sons of these farmers on the bigger farms throughout the country and on drainage works.  For that reason I am convinced that it will go a long way to stop emigration and to help to solve the unemployment problem in the rural communities.  It would also encourage us to become machine-minded in farm operations.</P>
      <P>There are many views on restoration of fertility to the soil but I think that what is now badly needed is manuring and seeding and this can now be properly done under the provisions of this measure.  I think we can safely leave the matter in the hands of our Minister and I am sure that if the scientists and the officials of his Department are not doing their work and giving the scheme every chance of success he will soon get others to do it. I hope that the measure will be passed through with the greatest possible speed and that we will be given the chance of using it to the maximum advantage. It certainly is a better investment than anything to be found elsewhere, to put the money into our land. I am not one who favours compulsion but if there are recalcitrant and bad farmers who will not take advantage of the scheme then compulsion must be used especially since we are investing the money of the people.  I believe this to be the safest investment and in restoring the land it will teach our farmers to be self reliant.  While the small farmers of whom I have spoken would reap an advantage the bigger farmers will also find a great advantage in the Bill.  They will be able to avail of the provisions because they will have the money to carry on.  I think we can safely leave the matter to the Minister and his technicians and if they do not make a job of it then we will have the opportunity of criticising them next year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Captain Orpen Captain Orpen">
      <NameTxt>Captain Orpen</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill <Col N="1561" /> and I think the Minister for Agriculture in introducing it has shown that great vision in regard to the land which many of us have been waiting on for a long time.  As I see it this Bill might be called and styled &ldquo;good husbandry on a national scale&rdquo;.  In a way we are using some of the nation's assets and ploughing them back into the land.  We all admit that quite a large part of the nation's assets has, either directly or indirectly, been derived from agriculture and the opportunity is now being taken to put them back into the land.</P>
      <P>When we come to look at this Bill in detail, we see that there are three classes of land that, in the main, can avail of its provisions.  They include wet land, which needs field drainage, land that requires reclamation in some form, presumably, land covered with scrub, or stones, while a third category on which, unfortunately, very little was said, concerns hill land and hill grazing. I want to say a few words, in relation to the first category, on field drainage.  People are inclined to think that much of the land of this country is quite satisfactory, and that field drainage will not improve it very much. That is a mistake.  In a country where there is a high rainfall the object is to make the best use of that rainfall and, as it were to pass it through the land, so that the excess is not held in the soil, but is removed as soon as possible.  Naturally we do not want to consider the microscopic quantity of water that is held in the soil and that stays there under normal circumstances. We have another type of soil which suffers from lack of drainage, because of its nature percolation is difficult.  There is some such land in Northern counties like Monaghan and Cavan where the soil is capable of improvement, probably by more drainage. Another category is found to a large extent in the Midlands, where you have not only to have it broken but to have underground field drainage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What I am hoping from this Bill is a study of soil problems as they appear on the farm.  It is very easy for engineers to lay down a scheme of drainage, but the tendency in many cases to-day is that for safety the engineer lays down an over-elaborate scheme. <Col N="1562" /> You can observe land that obviously requires drainage, and you are apt to think that all that has to be done is to remove water off it.  What should really be done in many cases is to see if a cure could be found at the source of the trouble.  If that could be cured the work could be done cheaper than by trying to drain a large area.  I do not say that there is a specific source of trouble in every case, but very often there is.  I have seen numerous examples of elaborate drainage schemes that were laid down, where ultimately the source when discovered could have been dealt with by one drain.  However, it is easy to be wise after the event.  I hope the experts will study carefully the knowledge that people gained in the past in regard to such matters.</P>
    <P>As to the problem of hill drainage, I am sorry the Minister is not here, because I want to quote him on that subject.  When speaking in the Dáil last month, col. 173 of the Dáil Debates, he rather hinted that we knew very little about hill land or its problems. He said: &ldquo;The improvement of hill drainage is quite unbroken territory in this country and has never been done before.&rdquo;  Very little has been done, but it was only in recent years that a complete solution became possible for the renovation of hill pastures.  That was not possible until the advent of heavy implements and powerful tractors. Anybody interested in the subject should, I suggest, go to Wales to see what has been done there under the scheme of farm hill experiments where, after 15 years of pioneering work, the ordinary hill farmer there is carrying out high level reclamation on his own account and at his own expense, with the help of the hill subsidy and also the hill-sheep subsidy.  As the Minister stated, we know very little about the way to tackle that job.  I suggest that the Minister or his officials should visit one or two farms which, in a small way, have been for 25 years renovating hill land, and have partially succeeded and in parts failed.  As everybody knows, more can be learned from failure than from success.  Success often hides various steps that lead to it.  while failure often gives a clue on what not to do.  It has been suggested <Col N="1563" /> by some people that in this Bill the Minister should have utilised these funds for improving better land than that referred to in Section 1, and that by so doing he would have more rapidly increased production.  That is quite true.  He would have, but that is not the object of this Bill.  I think the primary object of the Bill is to restore to the nation land which has gone out of cultivation and which could not by any possible stretch of the imagination have been rehabilitated out of the profits of the farmers themselves working on these farms.  The Minister has confined himself to difficult land, and, by difficult land, I mean land which is technically difficult and costly to rehabilitate, and it is just for the reason that it is difficult and costly that the farmer owning such land would have little chance of making sufficient profits out of the good part of his holding to restore and renovate the bad.  In the old days before 1850, this land was in full use.  A plentiful supply of unpaid family labour allowed the farmer to do things 100 years ago that it is difficult to do to-day.  However, it is to be hoped that, with the help given in this Bill, assisted by modern equipment, farmers and contractors will be able to rehabilitate and bring back into production this land which 100 years ago gave crops and fed men and beasts.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusOFarrell" hpid="Mr. S. O'Farrell Mr. S. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>A city man should be as interested in this Bill as any farmer.  There are times when we criticise the farmers and times when we poke fun at them, but there is never an occasion when we can ignore the farmer, or when we can even pretend that we can get on without the farmer's help.  We can live&mdash;there is no use in saying these things at any great length&mdash;if we are driven to it without any section of the industrial community, but we can never live without the food producer.  As a city man, therefore, I think that anything that can be done to improve the land is a benefit to the community generally.  I know from travelling around the country, and I have travelled a considerable amount in the last few years, there is a tremendous amount of land <Col N="1564" /> in need of rehabilitation and I know also that it has got into a state of neglect because it was not in one generation or in two that the neglect occurred but has been spread over a considerable period.</P>
      <P>If the Minister were here, I would question him on the use of the words &ldquo;free grant.&rdquo;  I see no free grant for the farmers in this.  Even though he has showered leaflets on us in explanation of the Bill, I still do not regard it as a free grant.  If a farmer is paid a contribution towards the cost of doing necessary improvements on his land in order that the community might be assured in the future of sufficient foodstuffs for their own use and for export, he is merely being paid a wage for work done.  If a labourer is employed in building a house in which he himself may subsequently live, his wages are not called a free grant.  I have no objection to the farmer getting all the Government proposes to give him now, but I do not think it will be a free grant.  The farmer has to pay back his share of it, but, if I were a farmer I would object to that.  Somebody who does not take the trouble to examine the Bill or to look into its details, will say that the farmers are getting millions out of this Government. The farmers may be getting millions out of this Government or any other Government, but they will not get anything from any Government, unless they give something in return or, at least, the prospect of something in return.</P>
      <P>There is one question which has not been made clear to me by either the Bill or the explanatory leaflet.  I am not sure whether we have been discussing the Land Reclamation Bill or the land rehabilitation project leaflet.  The two things are not identical.  Section 2 sub-section (1) of the Bill says that the Minister may, at the request of the occupier of land, carry out works.  Nowhere in the Bill, except by inference, is it made clear that the farmer or occupier may himself carry out the work.  I assume it could be done, because the explanatory leaflet specifically states: &ldquo;If you are not able to do it or to have it done, the Department will do it.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1565" /> It is quite clear from both the leaflet and the Bill that before the work is done by the Department or by a contractor, the Government will give an estimate of the cost and will also state what proportion of the money is to be given to the occupier for his share of the work, but I wonder how the Estimate will be made up.  It will not cost exactly the same amount of money to drain every field or every acre.  It will be more costly in one place than another and I am wondering what the wage content of the estimate will be. In some places, much more labour will be required to do the work even of removing fences and other works specified in the Bill, and how much of the labour will be paid labour?  If the Department supplies the workers, what rate of wages do they contemplate paying and putting into the estimate? That, I think, is a relevant question. If they pay the agricultural rate of wage, they probably will not get sufficient workers to carry out the scheme. If they pay more than the current agricultural rate, they will probably attract men from the farms, and will create another problem.  I merely mention these things, because, if we see in advance that things are likely to occur which may be troublesome, it is better face them now than to have to face them later on.  I do not suppose there are many farmers who have sufficient sons of their own to carry out any reasonably big reclamation scheme, even on their own farms.  Most of the sons of farmers, with the exception of one, or perhaps two in some cases, have left the country and gone to seek employment elsewhere.  Therefore, even a farmer who undertakes to do the work himself will have to rely on hired labour, and I do not know whether a farmer will get the necessary labour to do the work for the price the Department may estimate when calculating what grant or allowance they will make for it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill, as the Minister pointed out, is to provide ways and means for the reclamation of land, which may be carried out under three headings.  My point in intervening in the debate is to ask <Col N="1566" /> one or two questions in relation to the carrying out of the scheme.  The first arrangement is that the work may be carried out by the owner on the basis of a grant of a certain amount being made; the second, that the work may be carried out by the Department on the basis of an arrangement made with the owner of the land so improved to pay at the rate of £12 per acre on completion of the work; and the third that the Department may carry out the work, the cost being spread over 60 years and repayable by an annuity of £4 8s. 11d.  To take the first part, if a farmer undertakes to carry out the work under this scheme he is entitled to get two-thirds of the estimated cost. The estimated cost may come to a considerable amount if the farmer undertakes large-scale drainage.  I would put it to the Minister that it is expecting too much of the ordinary farmer to think that he will be in a position to pay for the labour involved up to the completion of this work, without any assistance, and I submit that provision should be made whereby part payments would be made as the work progresses.</P>
      <P>Again, where the owner of land enters into a contract with the Department to carry out the drainage and to repay a sum of £12 an acre, if the farmer undertakes large-scale developments it is too much to expect that he will be in a position to pay&mdash;take, for instance, 20 acres at £12 per acre&mdash;and there should be an arrangement whereby payment would be made in instalments as the work progresses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is not the first Government scheme which has been introduced for land reclamation.  We have had in the past number of years many such schemes &mdash; the farm improvements scheme, the farm buildings scheme, the lime distribution scheme, the fertilisers subsidy scheme and many other schemes on which almost £1,000,000 was paid annually to our farmers.  I have great doubts but that, by a more liberal extension of the farm improvements scheme, we might possibly make better progress than we will make under this particular scheme.  I should like to have from the Minister information as to whether it is proposed to <Col N="1567" /> carry on, side by side with this special scheme, the various other schemes that are already in operation.  This scheme, to begin with, will only apply in eight counties.  If we are going to deprive the remainder of the country from availing of the farm improvements scheme, the farm buildings scheme, the lime subsidy scheme and the various other schemes until such time as it is possible to spread this scheme all over the country we shall be placing all those other counties at a severe disadvantage.</P>
    <P>Another point that has been recommended by the Drainage Report and again by the persons appointed to carry out our land survey is the carrying out of all drainage in consultation with the main Drainage Board.  It has been pointed out by both people that it is essential to have this consultation as otherwise serious damage could be done.  Another point is that where a farmer carries out this scheme he has to pay £12 per acre and yet it is quite possible that in the carrying out of this scheme not alone will his land benefit but the land of his neighbour may also benefit.  No provision is made so that the payments demanded will correspond with the distribution of benefits.</P>
    <P>Some Senators have said that this is a step in the right direction and that it will put back into cultivation lands which have gone to waste over a number of years.  When one travels up and down the country one sees sometimes so much scrubland that one would wish not alone for a Bill of this kind but sometimes even for compulsory powers so that some of the land now lying waste could be brought back to cultivation. If we examine the problem we will find that it goes back to the time when our people went out of tillage. As the tillage acreage declined acre by acre so, too, did our population decline.  While it may be suggested that the policy we put before the people as a Party was a tillage policy that does not mean that we were against the proper cultivation of grasslands. I hold that you cannot have proper grass lands if you have not tillage. One thing that is important, and more important now from the Minister's point of view having regard to <Col N="1568" /> the many statements which were made in the past, is that he should make it quite clear that it is in the interests of the country as a whole and particularly of the farmers that we should have a proper rotation of crops. Otherwise, the £4,000,000 or the £40,000,000&mdash;whether it is to be paid in dollars or in sterling&mdash;will be of no use. To do that we must have education. The draining of the land and making it fertile is not sufficient if our farmers do not know how to utilise that land to the best advantage.  In the near future we shall be in a position to compete with people who are highly mechanised as far as their agriculture is concerned, who have high technical advice and who have developed much further than we have developed in that direction.  Then we shall find that we shall have losses and that we shall not be in a position even to repay the money we have put into this project. With that education also must go an encouragement to our farmers to do what any shrewd businessman will do.</P>
    <P>A businessman will always put his money into his business to expand it. He will not be reluctant to borrow money from the bank for the expansion of his business in general.  However, the farmer, in many cases I am afraid, is too fond of putting the money in the bank and of not putting anything back into the land which he has taken out of it.  In our improved agricultural education we must bear that point in mind.  We must make a very serious attempt to impress on our farmers the importance of putting a good share of the profits which they take out of the land back into the land again.  I think I said before that their present attitude is due to many causes. It is due to the lack of credit facilities for our farmers.  It is due also to a system that has grown up whereby there must be a dowry for each of the daughters if they are to be married out of the home and, further, it is due to the fact that the farmer feels more secure when he has the money in the bank and ready at his hand for occasions of this kind.  These are the reasons why he is so reluctant to put some of his money back into the land.</P>
    <P>The Minister held out very little hope of doing what I think is the first <Col N="1569" /> essential in this problem, namely, assisting those who have good land, land that does not require drainage but which, over a number of years&mdash;and probably during the emergency period &mdash;has supplied the food for this nation. That land has now gone out of fertility. It needs lime and fertilisers generally.  There is no provision in this Bill to meet cases of that kind.</P>
    <P>If the Minister were present now I would urge him to encourage our farmers to go in for a more generous use of fertilisers.  We have the position, as I pointed out on the Finance Bill, that the Department of Agriculture is giving very bad example and a very bad lead in this direction.  During the emergency years vouchers were issued to those who grew wheat.  The position at the present time is that the 1945 vouchers have not yet been recognised or provision made whereby the people would get the amount of fertiliser credit which these vouchers would entitle them to.  In reply to a question in the Dáil recently the Minister said that it would probably be the end of July before the 1945 wheat-growing vouchers would be provided for and that it might take two or three years before the 1946 and the 1947 vouchers would be reached.  If we are going to spend £4,000,000 or £40,000,000 on this scheme of reclamation of what we consider not first-class land, should we not give our first attention to the land that is there ready to increase production?  The Minister's argument was that he had no staff and that it would necessitate the recruiting of it. Surely the Minister, in his enthusiasm to put over this scheme, is not going to baulk at the mere taking on of even a small temporary staff to deal with this important matter?  I know the amount is small and that the amount of fertilisers which a farmer may purchase on these documents would be insignificant.  However, it would be the example, the encouragement and direction that would be given, by getting quickly and directly from the Department such a document, where the farmer may say that he is going to get a quarter ton on the voucher and will make it a ton, that will have a psychological effect which may be of <Col N="1570" /> more benefit than the mere giving of the voucher itself.</P>
    <P>I hope this scheme will be a success and I welcome it.  It will mean a lot to the country as a whole.  We are taking a big risk here, as the moneys for this must come from taxation, or be borrowed and paid back.  Therefore, we must make every endeavour to see that the scheme will be a success. The Minister paid tribute to two Ministers for having the moneys made available so readily, and he said he was very grateful.  Does that suggest that if there were any other Government in power or any other Ministers the same moneys would not be made available from the same source?</P>
    <P>I would like the Minister to look into the points I have raised, so that those who would be prepared to undertake works under this scheme might be given better opportunities and facilities to do so.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanRuane" hpid="Mr. Ruane Mr. Ruane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ruane</NameTxt>
      <P>When speaking last week on the Second Stage of the Local Authorities Bill, I referred to it as a type of legislation which this country needs very much.  I regard the present Bill as a continuance of that good work and I compliment the Minister and all those concerned with the drafting on the excellent manner in which they have prepared this Bill.  It appears to me, in studying it, with the explanatory pamphlet, that no aspect of the situation has been neglected or omitted.  The Bill is a short one, and, with the pamphlet, easy to follow, and when the people for whom it is intended become familiar with its provisions the schemes outlined should be easy to operate.  Designed, as I take it to be, to put into production the vast areas now impoverished, compelling inducements are offered to the owners of those lands to avail of the provisions of the Bill.  Those who are able to carry out the work themselves are being remunerated on a very generous basis, those who have not the necessary labour may have it done for them by payment of a very reasonable figure per acre, and those who have not the necessary capital may have the work done and repayment made over an extended period.  I do not know what else could be done to make that <Col N="1571" /> particular feature of the Bill more acceptable to the people for whom it is intended.</P>
      <P>One feature of the measure that appeals to me very strongly is the provision it makes for equipping the people with machinery.  In the rural areas, our young people have a special aptitude for operating and looking after machinery.  Through this Bill, they may become owners of valuable plant and thereby, looking after their own property, prolong its use and get a far more lucrative return by doing less slavish labour than if they had to do on ordinary drainage by manual labour.  Considering that the Government is prepared to advance one-third of the cost of plant recommended by its advisors, and to facilitate a loan for another third, these two inducements should make it possible for any group of young men interested in this work to put together the necessary third and thereby provide themselves with the plant, from which they could undertake contract work in their areas and, by doing so, go a long way towards easing the shortage of manual labour.</P>
      <P>I take it that one of the fundamental objects of the Bill is to increase production. There are both good and bad farmers, as occurs in every other section of the community, and you had farmers who, during the emergency, in carrying out tillage regulations through intense cropping took the last ounce out of their land; with very poor fertilisers or lack of fertilisers these lands are in an impoverished condition at the present time.  I take it that, hand in hand with the work of reclamation, land of that type will receive attention, as it should not be left over until the greater work is done.</P>
      <P>The scheme outlined here is a very ambitious one and those concerned with its drafting deserve the gratitude of the people.  However, the success of the measure depends on the manner in which the people concerned co-operate with the generous provisions of the Bill.  I am quite satisfied, from the information the Minister gave us in introducing the Bill, that the people will co-operate and that, as a result, the objects the Bill sets out to achieve will be brought nearer to us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1572" />
    <Speaker pid="MartinODwyer" hpid="Mr. O'Dwyer Mr. O'Dwyer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dwyer</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, would like to welcome the Bill, as it has great promise of benefits to the country in general.  Even outside the actual benefit of the reclamation of land, the expenditure of such a large amount of money will change the whole economy of rural districts.  The expenditure of £3,000,000 or £4,000,000 would be as welcome in rural districts as a good downpour of rain at present. Undoubtedly, field drainage is urgently needed in the country.  Anybody who travels through the country can see an unlimited amount of land wanting drainage.  Land is going for nothing and that would show it even if we had not figures.  In my own part of the country where land is better than the general we see land which was good before going back rapidly year by year into swamp.  If we examine it we find that a perfect drainage system was put in over 100 years ago which was since neglected.  The reason was that in those days there was a supply of cheap labour and since then it was not possible for farmers with the prices prevailing to do it again.  With pre-war prices anybody will understand that it would not be possible to pay labour to dig up land and do the necessary drainage.  The farmer had not the capital and, if he had itself, it would not give him an economic return.  No field drainage has been done for the last 70 years except in exceptional places.  This grant makes it possible practically for the first time to carry out on a large scale that necessary drainage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are some points to which I would like to draw the Minister's attention.  We would all like to see this project a success and would be glad to help it in any way by our suggestions.  A great reason for the swampy condition of a lot of the land is the condition of the watercourses, the rivers and streams that go by it. I know of several cases where it would be quite useless to drain a farm if the adjoining river were not deepened or widened or the watercourse cleared, and not alone the adjoining river, but you would want to go further.  You would want to put the arterial drainage project into operation as soon as possible in order to make a complete <Col N="1573" /> success of this project.  Unless the streams, rivers and main arteries are cleared and put in good condition this project will not be completely successful and I would ask the Minister to use his influence with the Government to have the Arterial Drainage Act put into operation as soon as possible if only to help this present project.</P>
    <P>This question of field drainage is not altogether as simple as people think. Reading it, it struck me that the Minister, perhaps, did not realise how terribly technical it is.  He mentioned that where a farmer applied for a grant a supervisor would come down and they would talk it over.  The supervisor would go back and send the farmer a map of the holding showing the things that would be done and that seemed to settle that, but I am afraid that it will be much more difficult than that.  I have often seen very good farmers trying to drain their land who, when they had spent the money, found that it was not working.  It is a matter on which technical advice is required.  The sum of money involved is very large and as well as the farmer and the supervisor it would be necessary to have technical advice before the money was expended.  It would be well if engineers were appointed to supervise the whole thing.  As I have said, no drainage worth while has been done in the country for nearly 100 years.  Field drainage has gone completely out of fashion, but in other countries in Europe field drainage and other kinds of drainage is an everyday necessity and engineers devote their time to that.  In Ireland, however, the whole study of engineers is away from the land.  When even farmers' sons go to school to be engineers their mind is diverted from the land into industrial projects or anything else.  I think that engineering help should be sought in those countries where drainage is an everyday necessity.  I think it would be a good idea if the Minister were to bring over engineers as were brought over for the Shannon scheme, experts in those matters who would help the Irish engineers.  Thirty, 40 or 50 million pounds is a very large sum of money and it would be worth while to take no chances because we all know that vast sums of money ever and <Col N="1574" /> always were lost on the drainage of rivers.  We have all seen cases where vast sums of money were spent with no result whatsoever, so the Minister would be very wise to take no chances on those things because even field drainage is a matter that requires expert knowledge.</P>
    <P>The Minister has mentioned mole ploughs.  I would be very slow to use a mole plough.  It is only an occasional time that it does a lasting job and it would be quite possible that drainage could be done with a mole plough that would last for only two years.  I would not be in favour of it where so much money is being spent. It would be better to make the drains as permanent as possible.  The drains which were made 100 years ago lasted for 50 years.</P>
    <P>I think also that if drainage were carried out in a whole district with a large number of farmers working together it would enable the Minister to provide better engineering facilities than if the works were carried out one by one.</P>
    <P>The Minister also mentioned valuation and I was glad to hear him say that there would be no increase in land valuation as a result of the drainage. At present there can be no increase in land valuation because the British valuation is in force still but there is talk of a revised valuation for land, and when the time comes there is a danger that the valuation would be increased.  The Minister should look into that matter.  The land might be valued at so much now but in 20 years' time when the revaluation comes along it might be different altogether.  It might be well if the Minister put in a clause to the effect that in any future revaluation of the land it should be taken on its present basis of undrained land.</P>
    <P>I think that is all I have to say except to repeat that I welcome the Bill and that I am sure everybody will give all the help they possibly can to make it a success.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>Nobody will accuse me of great originality when I say that agriculture is the basis of our prosperity and for this reason I presume to say just a few words.  Of course we <Col N="1575" /> have heard all aspects of this Bill tonight from the farmers.  The only thing I want to say is to commend the general policy that underlies the Bill. I welcome the Government policy of renewing and extending the machine which produces wealth.  In other words, they are nourishing the goose that lays the golden egg.  That is not an original saying but it is none the less true.  There is too much tendency nowadays in other countries, as well as in our own, to spend time eating the golden eggs all the time without doing anything to nourish the goose. In fact even to-day you will find people not only eating the eggs but even sucking the blood from the goose.</P>
      <P>My only comment, therefore, is that I recognise in this Bill a wish on the part of the Government to help the machine, to build up and to nourish it in such a way that it will be able to produce more and more wealth for the country.  I hope that this policy will be observed in other spheres of our national life.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrancisLoughman" hpid="Mr. Loughman Mr. Loughman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Loughman</NameTxt>
      <P>Apart from dealing with the Bill as it is, I would like to deal with a few side issues.  In the past very many valuable things have been discovered when the soil of Ireland has been turned and, when this measure is available, soil will be turned which has not been broken for centuries.  In the course of that work valuable finds may be made in this country.  We all know that many of the treasures in the Museum and in other places were discovered accidentally, and what I want the Minister to do is to ensure that when ground is being broken and when these works are being carried out he will consult with the local societies interested in these matters with a view to preventing such treasures being destroyed through ignorance or carelessness.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have an instance in mind where drainage work was being done and there was a collection of gold coins of James II, and within half an hour it was not possible for any person interested in them to get one of the coins. <Col N="1576" /> They were scattered all over the place and I believe not one of them remains in the possession of anybody with a knowledge of their value to-day.  I would impress upon the Minister to insist and to see that nothing is left undone to ensure that nothing of that kind is lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the Senator would wish me to be careful of the mounds as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrancisLoughman" hpid="Mr. Loughman Mr. Loughman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Loughman</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been down in some of the buildings, prehistoric ruins, which have been discovered under these mounds.</P>
      <P>There is one other point I wish to make.  I value the names of places and many of the fields in the country are known by historic names at the present time.  I can see that with this Bill in operation many of these field boundaries will disappear and many of the names that are associated with the fields will be lost and with that loss many historic associations will be severed.  I would suggest that when work is being done on farms involving the removal of these boundaries the names should be placed on the fields.  I have one instance in mind.  I happen to know of a field close to a very ancient abbey in this country.  It is divided by the road from the actual abbey and probably the field was a portion of the abbey or the abbey graveyard. It was known as Cuan na Foucha which, I understand, means the harbour of the ghosts and, of course, as I said, that field is probably the graveyard or portion of the old abbey.  It has a historic association and I think that in any work that is being done association of that kind should not be lost sight of.</P>
      <P>The farmers will deal with the other aspects of the Bill and I only wish now that the objects for which the Bill has been drafted will be achieved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnJosephMeighan" hpid="Mr. Meighan Mr. Meighan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Meighan</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move the adjournment of the debate.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 10 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Thursday, July 14th.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>