<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="24" Month="May" Year="1978" Vol="89" No="3" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 24 Bealtaine 1978" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 24 May 1978" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="217">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="217" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 2, 1 and 3 in that order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of the Order of Business, could the Leader tell us will we be sitting tomorrow?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The position is that if we conclude the Landlord and Tenant (Ground Rents) (No. 2) Bill by the time we rise this evening we will not be sitting tomorrow.  Otherwise, we would have to sit tomorrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>The indications are that the Landlord and Tenant (Ground Rents) (No. 2) Bill will hardly see out the rest of the day on top of the motion on the State-sponsored bodies.  Therefore, I take it that we will not be sitting tomorrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Not if we have concluded Nos. 1 and 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to register a protest at this, a Chathaoirleach, because we have been sitting only one day per week.  There is the feeling amongst many Members that the Seanad is not being utilised to its full potential.  We were all very pleased when the debate on the White Paper on the economy was arranged, an important debate on a very important subject, but all that will have been undone if this debate is allowed now to be postponed indefinitely.  There are many Members who are seriously disappointed that this debate is now apparently being shelved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I support that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="218" />
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I share the Senator's regret that we are not sitting tomorrow. The position is that the Minister concerned simply cannot be here tomorrow and I think it is important that he should be here for the debate on the White Paper.  It was intended to sit tomorrow to finish it.  As he cannot be here, it is better to adjourn it until next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that in the absence of the Minister the debate would be pointless but&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Eoin Ryan to reply and conclude on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>With respect, a Chathaoirleach, we are discussing procedures or non-procedures for tomorrow.  I just want to make the comment that I understand the pressures on Ministers and that it is not always possible for them to be here, but, having introduced the debate, it is disappointing that something has arisen which has greater priority for the Minister than giving time to one of the Houses of Parliament.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>What I think would be acceptable, and I suggest the House might agree to it, is to continue the debate on the White Paper, sit tomorrow if necessary, with the reservation that the Minister be allowed half-an-hour next week to conclude but that everybody who wanted to speak on it could speak either this evening or tomorrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>There would not be a lot of point in that suggestion because when the Minister was opening the debate he indicated to us that he was, if you like, throwing in the ball and was anxious to hear our views.  It would be better, from our point of view, that the Minister would be here to hear us.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Message" RHead="from Dáil">
    <Title>Message from Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>
      </P>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has passed the following Resolution in which the concurrence of Seanad Éireann is desired:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="219" /> (1)  That it is expedient that a Joint Committee (which shall be called the Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies) consisting of seven members of the Dáil and four members of the Seanad (none of whom shall be a member of the Government or a Minister of State) be appointed to examine the Reports and Accounts and overall operational results of State-sponsored bodies engaged in trading or commercial activities referred to in Schedule A hereto and the trading and/or commercial aspects of the Reports and Accounts and overall operational results of the State-sponsored body referred to in Schedule B hereto and to report thereon to both Houses of the Oireachtas and make recommendations where appropriate.</P>
    <P>(2)  That, after consultation with the Joint Committee, the Minister for the Public Service with the agreement of the Minister for Finance may include from time to time the names of further State-sponsored bodies engaged in trading or commercial activities in the Schedules and, with the consent of the Joint Committee and the Minister for Finance, may delete from the Schedules the names of any bodies which he considers no longer to be State-sponsored bodies engaged in trading or commercial activities.</P>
    <P>(3) That, if so requested by a State-sponsored body, the Joint Committee shall refrain from publishing confidential information regarding the body's activities and plans.</P>
    <P>(4) That the Joint Committee shall have power to send for persons, papers and records and, subject to the consent of the Minister for the Public Service, to engage the services of persons with specialist or technical knowledge to assist it for the purpose of particular enquiries.</P>
    <P>(5) That the Joint Committee, previous to the commencement of business, shall elect one of its members to be Chairman, who shall have only one vote.</P>
    <P>(6) That all questions in the Joint <Col N="220" /> Committee shall be determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting and in the event of there being an equality of votes the question shall be decided in the negative.</P>
    <P>(7) That the Joint Committee shall have power to print and publish from time to time minutes of evidence taken before it together with such related documents as it thinks fit.</P>
    <P>(8) That every report which the Joint Committee proposes to make under this Order shall on adoption by the Joint Committee be laid before both Houses of the Oireachtas forthwith whereupon the Joint Committee shall be empowered to print and publish such report together with such related documents as it thinks fit.</P>
    <P>(9) That four members of the Committee shall form a Quorum of whom at least one shall be a member of Dáil Éireann and at least one shall be a member of Seanad Éireann.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Schedule A</i>
    </P>
    <P>Aer Lingus, Teoranta</P>
    <P>Aerlínte Éireann, Teoranta</P>
    <P>Aer Rianta, Teoranta</P>
    <P>The Agricultural Credit Corporation, Limited</P>
    <P>Arramara Teoranta</P>
    <P>Bord na Móna</P>
    <P>British &amp; Irish Steam Packet Company Limited</P>
    <P>Ceimicí, Teoranta</P>
    <P>Comhlucht Siúicre Éireann, Teoranta</P>
    <P>Córas Iompair Éireann</P>
    <P>Electricity Supply Board</P>
    <P>Fóir Teoranta</P>
    <P>Industrial Credit Company, Limited</P>
    <P>The Irish Gas Board</P>
    <P>Irish Life Assurance Company Limited</P>
    <P>The Irish National Stud Company, Limited</P>
    <P>Irish Shipping Limited</P>
    <P>Irish Steel Holdings Limited</P>
    <P>Min Fhéir (1959) Teoranta</P>
    <P>National Building Agency Limited</P>
    <P>Nítrigin Éireann Teoranta</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="221" /> Óstlanna Iompair Éireann Teoranta</P>
    <P>Pigs and Bacon Commission</P>
    <P>Radio Telefís Éireann</P>
    <P>Voluntary Health Insurance Board.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Schedule B</i>
    </P>
    <P>Gaeltarra Éireann.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Committee on" RHead="State-Sponsored Bodies: Motion">
    <Title>Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>(1) That Seanad Éireann concurs with Dáil Éireann in its Resolution communicated to Seanad Éireann on 17 May 1978, that it is expedient that a Joint Committee (which shall be called the Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies) consisting of seven members of the Dáil and four members of the Seanad (none of whom shall be a member of the Government or a Minister of State) be appointed to examine the Reports and Accounts and overall operational results of State-sponsored bodies engaged in trading or commercial activities referred to in Schedule A hereto and the trading and/or commercial aspects of the Reports and Accounts and overall operational results of the State-sponsored body referred to in Schedule B hereto and to report thereon to both Houses of the Oireachtas and make recommendations where appropriate.</P>
      <P>(2) That, after consultation with the Joint Committee, the Minister for the Public Service with the agreement of the Minister for Finance may include from time to time the names of further State-sponsored bodies engaged in trading or commercial activities in the Schedules and, with the consent of the Joint Committee and the Minister for Finance, may delete from the Schedules the names of any bodies which he considers no longer to be State-sponsored bodies engaged in trading or commercial activities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(3) That, if so requested by a State-sponsored body, the Joint Committee shall refrain from publishing confidential information regarding the body's <Col N="222" /> activities and plans.</P>
    <P>(4) That the Joint Committee shall have power to send for persons, papers and records and, subject to the consent of the Minister for the Public Service, to engage the services of persons with specialist or technical knowledge to assist it for the purpose of particular enquiries.</P>
    <P>(5) That the Joint Committee, previous to the commencement of business, shall elect one of its members to be Chairman, who shall have only one vote.</P>
    <P>(6) That all questions in the Joint Committee shall be determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting and in the event of there being an equality of votes the question shall be decided in the negative.</P>
    <P>(7) That the Joint Committee shall have power to print and publish from time to time minutes of evidence taken before it together with such related documents as it thinks fit.</P>
    <P>(8) That every report which the Joint Committee proposes to make under this Order shall on adoption by the Joint Committee be laid before both Houses of the Oireachtas forthwith whereupon the Joint Committee shall be empowered to print and publish such report together with such related documents as it thinks fit.</P>
    <P>(9) That four members of the Committee shall form a Quorum of whom at least one shall be a member of Dáil Éireann and at least one shall be a member of Seanad Éireann.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Schedule A</i>
    </P>
    <P>Aer Lingus, Teoranta</P>
    <P>Aer Rianta, Teoranta</P>
    <P>Aerlínte Éireann, Teoranta</P>
    <P>The Agricultural Credit Corporation, Limited</P>
    <P>Arramara Teoranta</P>
    <P>Bord na Móna</P>
    <P>British &amp; Irish Steam Packet Company Limited</P>
    <P>Ceimicí, Teoranta</P>
    <P>Comhlucht Siúicre Éireann, Teoranta</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="223" /> Córas Iompair Éireann</P>
    <P>Electricity Supply Board</P>
    <P>Fóir Teoranta</P>
    <P>Industrial Credit Company, Limited</P>
    <P>The Irish Gas Board</P>
    <P>Irish Life Assurance Company, Limited</P>
    <P>The Irish National Stud Company, Limited</P>
    <P>Irish Shipping Limited</P>
    <P>Irish Steel Holdings Limited</P>
    <P>Min Fhéir (1959) Teoranta</P>
    <P>National Building Agency Limited</P>
    <P>Nírigin Éireann Teoranta</P>
    <P>Óstlanna Iompair Éireann Teoranta</P>
    <P>Pigs and Bacon Commission</P>
    <P>Radio Telefís Éireann</P>
    <P>Voluntary Health Insurance Board.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Schedule B</i>
    </P>
    <P>Gaeltarra Éireann.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>You have not concluded the discussion on Item No. 2?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister going to speak on the motion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PearseWyse" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. Wyse) Pearse Wyse">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. Wyse)</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to state that I am deputising for the Minister for the Public Service here this afternoon.  This motion proposes to reactivate the Joint Oireachtas Committee on State-sponsored bodies who were established following the passing of motions in the Dáil and Seanad in late 1976.  That Committee met only twice before they lapsed automatically on the dissolution of the 20th Dáil.  Both of these meetings were taken up with procedural matters and the Committee had little opportunity of getting down to the practical task of looking at the State-sponsored bodies under their mandate. This fact has weighed heavily in the Government's decision to re-establish the Committee without making any major alterations in their terms of reference. It is proposed that the new Committee <Col N="224" /> will, like their predecessor, deal only with those bodies which are engaged in trading or commercial activities.</P>
      <P>I will detail later what the changes are; they are generally of a procedural or technical nature.  The Government are aware that a case can be made for a Committee with a wider area of concern and, perhaps, more detailed terms of reference.  Nevertheless, they believe that the proper approach is to allow the Committee to function for the present with these substantially unchanged terms of reference; any changes which experience may suggest as desirable can be made by the Oireachtas in the light of that experience.</P>
      <P>Commercial organisations founded or acquired by the State are a feature of most modern States.  There are, however, two important distinctions between our situation in that regard and that in other countries.  First, State involvement in those enterprises does not, in our case, arise from any ideological preconception and is not generally, therefore, a matter of dispute between political parties. Secondly, our State-sponsored bodies, although small by comparison with some of their counterparts in larger EEC countries, constitute, in the aggregate, a significant sector of our economy.</P>
      <P>It is significant that the bodies listed in the Schedule to this motion provide some 60,000 jobs and include some of the nation's largest employers.  This fact alone makes their wellbeing the concern of every Member of this House.  Their importance does not, however, stop there.  As a group, these bodies employ a large share of the nation's capital and the range of economic activities in which they engage affects almost every area of national life.</P>
      <P>Given the importance of these bodies to our economy and the degree to which their investment and strategic decisions could affect the quality of our lives for many years ahead, it is, all will agree, proper that they should now come into closer relationship with the Oireachtas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The reasons why State-sponsored bodies are established are many and varied.  Although in organisational form these bodies have many similarities with <Col N="225" /> private sector companies, there are real and fundamental differences.  Complex economic and social issues were involved in their creation.  The balance sheet may rule in private enterprise; it is only one of the yardsticks by which State-sponsored bodies should be judged.  Yet, if we were to assume too readily that the normal commercial criteria should not apply, the danger could arise that social need could be advanced as the justification for any and every loss.  We all know that there are social costs.  Ideally, these costs should, as far as possible, be separately identified leaving the true commercial area of the business to be judged by the standards of the market place.  The Committee may have a worth-while contribution to make in clarifying this difficult issue.</P>
    <P>I wish to make it clear that the establishment of such a Committee involves no suggestion that these bodies are failing in their responsibilities.  A number of chief executives have already indicated that they see the Committee's role as a positive one which will enable the Oireachtas and the public to appreciate the difficulties they encounter and the challenges they face.  The work of the Committee will, I know, be particularly demanding and their success will depend on the ability of their members to come to grips with salient&mdash;and probably highly technical&mdash;data.  I am conscious that the demands on Deputies and Senators are already very great.  If the members of this Committee are not to be overloaded and are to get to the core of the issues, it is vital that the Committee should have available to them a good back-up service to sift through and analyse relevant data. In addition to a secretariat, which need not, I think, be large, I will be prepared to make provision for the engagement of technical expertise, preferably on a limited term basis for particular investigations.</P>
    <P>I pointed out earlier that certain changes had been made from the terms of the motion previously passed by both Houses.  The first of these incorporates the title &ldquo;the Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies&rdquo; in the motion.  This change formally recognises a title which <Col N="226" /> has already gained currency.  The second substitutes the term &ldquo;Minister of State&rdquo; for &ldquo;Parliamentary Secretary&rdquo;.  This change is a consequence of the establishment of the office of Minister of State and the abolition of that of Parliamentary Secretary by the Ministers and Secretaries (Amendment) (No. 2) Act, 1977.</P>
    <P>The changes in paragraphs 5 and 6 are in line with those adopted for other Joint Committees pending the revision of the Standing Orders of the House and relate to the election of a Chairman of the Committee and to the resolution of questions in the Committee by vote.</P>
    <P>Under the terms of reference of the motion establishing the former Committee they had power to publish evidence only in conjunction with a report.  The Government felt that this in effect put a restriction on the Committee in so far as a long time might elapse between the giving of evidence and the ultimate publication of the report.  To rectify this position the Committee's powers are suitably extended in paragraphs 7 and 8 of the motion to permit them to publish evidence or material as soon after each meeting as they deem fit.  In doing so, however, it is subject to the qualification that the Committee may not publish material if a State-sponsored body so requests on the grounds that publication of confidential information would be injurious to its business or commercial interests.</P>
    <P>The final change is that the Dairy Disposal Company Limited has been removed from Schedule A of the bodies to be examined as it is in the process of winding up its affairs and its commercial involvement is now practically negligible.</P>
    <P>There have been, over the years, frequent suggestions that State-sponsored bodies should be accountable to Parliament. The Committee proposed in this motion can be seen as a response to this view.  It can also be viewed as a means whereby the Oireachtas which created those bodies can now look at the range of bodies as a group or individually and make suggestions as to their future development.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>We in the Fine Gael Party welcome this motion and the reactivation <Col N="227" /> of this Committee.  Parliamentary involvement or oversight of the work of semi-State companies is something that has been looked for on and off for upwards of 20 years.  It only came to pass towards the end of the last Dáil.  The Committee set up then had not really begun to operate other than to establish their procedures and begin to look at their staffing requirements.  Accordingly, we look forward to a deeper involvement by that Committee in the implementation of their terms during the life of this Oireachtas.</P>
      <P>It is common case on all sides of the House that this involvement by the Oireachtas, in accordance with the terms of reference, in the affairs of State-sponsored bodies is a good thing because these bodies are spending public money.  The constitutional theory is that that expenditure is by the authority of Parliament and if that authority is to be properly exercised it should be the subject of review or oversight by a body representing parliament.</P>
      <P>This Committee will be analogous to but not similar to the Public Accounts Committee of the other House in so far as the same detailed scrutiny will not be carried out.  Because of a certain commercial element in the operation of many of the State-sponsored bodies it might not be suitable for that type of detailed scrutiny.  Nevertheless there is an analogy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would not like to think that this new Committee will operate in the same way as the Public Accounts Committee which at this stage has lost much of its reality and constitutional position by reason of the fact that it is operating so far removed in time from the expenditure it is examining.  It is very important for the maintenance of the powers of Parliament that the review of spending and the retention by Parliament of power over accountability of the finances passed by it should not become diminished.  Many people are worried that Parliament no longer really counts.  Because of the party system Parliament has become, in many cases, a rubber stamp for the will of the Executive.  Indeed, if the chief person in the Executive is a person of <Col N="228" /> very strong character Parliament, in effect, can become the rubber stamp for the will of one man.  This is not democracy as we know it.  Anything that seeks to reassert the sovereignty of Parliament is desirable.</P>
    <P>I see this motion and this Committee in that light.  It has a very important role to play.  It will be important that they will be enabled to play this role effectively by having a full secretariat, having all the technical assistance they may need, bearing in mind that they will be overseeing the activities of a large number of bodies discharging widely differing roles.  If it is to do that effectively in time it will need to have lots of secretarial and expert assistance.  I hope that will be made available.</P>
    <P>In so far as it is Parliament overseeing the Executive, in the sense that semi-State bodies are linked through the appropriate Ministers to the Executive, the principle of the chairman of the Committee coming from the Opposition is a good one.  It will prevent any dangers of a conflict of interests.  I am not saying that a chairman from the other side would not be independent and impartial but it is important, in this sort of scene, that he would be seen to be.  That could not be achieved if the chairman is from the ranks of the Government benches. The chairman should be a member of the Opposition.  Regretfully that principle was not applied during the life of the last Committee but, as that Committee barely got into being before Parliament was dissolved, no great precedent has been established.</P>
    <P>I have noticed that the present Minister for Finance, when in Opposition, speaking on the debate to set up this Committee originally was of the opinion that I am now expressing, that the chairman should come from the ranks of the Opposition.  I would urge that on the Minister of State as a desirable principle when the nature of the Committee is to, if you like, oversee the activities of the Executive albeit at a greater remove than the Public Accounts Committee.  That principle should be established from the beginning of this present Committee, from the beginning of this Parliament.</P>
    <P>I welcome the changes being made in <Col N="229" /> the term of reference, especially the one which permits interim publications of the work of the Committee.  Under the terms originally drafted nothing could be published until the final report.  As the Minister says, it may be desirable in the meantime, pending publication of the final report, to publish various pieces of material coming to the attention of the committee.  I welcome that.  It gives extra status and power to the committee.</P>
    <P>The other terms of reference have had to be drawn somewhat sketchily because this is a new committee embarking in a new area.  They will have to approach their job in a pragmatic way, developing their role as it goes along and seeing their terms of reference in operation before they can come back to the Oireachtas and ask for an extension of their powers or a clearer definition of their role.  Initially the terms of reference are about right and I would not seek to try to expand these or define in advance any principles of procedure.  These will have to evolve as the committee operate. I have no doubt that will be the spirit of the committee, to operate with cooperation as the main feature of their relationship with the semi-State bodies; there will not be any suggestion of Big Brother looking for mistakes.  On the contrary, it will be an operation of mutual help rather than a teacher/pupil or parent/child relationship.  I do not think anyone in the Oireachtas would want that, nor would they want to operate in any way that would lead people in the semi-State bodies to see this committee as inhibiting their activities.</P>
    <P>As the Minister pointed out, the role of these semi-State bodies is a mixture of social and commercial.  This will require sensitivity of approach on the part of the committee.  Politicians will be aware of both considerations, will be able to weigh their values in the operations of the various semi-State bodies, take them into account and give proper weight to each.  As the Minister said, State involvement is not a matter of any ideological preconception and is not a matter of dispute between the parties.  It has not been up to now though, as I noted in the debate on the White Paper, the present economic strategy of the Government <Col N="230" /> excludes State enterprise completely.  I suppose that is a matter of tactics rather than of ideology.</P>
    <P>I welcome the setting up of the committee. I hope it will be able to get to work very speedily with a fully staffed secretariat and with an Opposition chairman.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAMartin" hpid="Dr. Martin Dr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>I join Senator Cooney in welcoming the measure and indeed in applauding all its recommendations.  It is obviously a matter of great importance that there be some sort of a body, paternal or fraternal, operating in terms of the Oireachtas and the semi-State bodies.  If it operates in terms of the brief of a watchdog function all the better still. There are just two points I want to make with regard to the measure itself.  First, we see that in paragraph (1) of the motion and I quote:</P>
      <P>It is expedient that a Joint Committee (which shall be called the Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies) consisting of seven members of the Dáil and four members of the Seanad (none of whom shall be a member of the Government or a Minister of State) be appointed to examine the Reports and Accounts and overall operational results...</P>
      <P>It is an unhappy number that has been ascribed to the Seanad, that is, four members.  It seems to have been arrived at without any serious consideration of the composition of this House.  The only <i>rationale</i> on which one could justify four would be to recognise that there are four different groups within the Seanad. There are the Government, the Labour Party, the Fine Gael Party and the Independent Senators.  If the number four has any <i>rationale</i> that is really what it should reflect.  I understand that that is not really what is at the back of the minds of the framers of the motion at all, that they propose there will to be two from the Government and two from the Opposition parties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Last year when this measure came forward there was general agreement right up to the last minute that an Independent Senator, Senator West, would be a member but, at the last <Col N="231" /> minute, the Government and the Opposition failed to reach agreement on this matter.  It looks as if the motion at present will go forward as constituting a committee which merely includes representatives of the three main parties.</P>
    <P>The purpose of the entire motion&mdash;and I have read out some of its purposes&mdash;is that a committee be appointed:</P>
    <P>...to examine the Reports and Accounts and overall operational results of State-sponsored bodies engaged in trading or commercial activities referred to in Schedule A hereto and the trading and/or commercial aspects of the Reports and Accounts and overall operational results of the State-sponsored body referred to in Schedule B hereto and to report thereon to both Houses of the Oireachtas and make recommendations where appropriate.</P>
    <P>If we see that as the overall brief of the committee I cannot think of any role for which an Independent Senator would be better fitted.  If they are to report on these and examine them critically and constructively there is just the possibility that either a Government or an Opposition Senator might have reason to soft pedal or go easy on something that might be marginally irregular because there is no party in the House at present that has not been in power and that has not had dealings with these semi-State bodies.  In other words, there is at least an occult reason why, in certain circumstances, both Government and Opposition might wink at an irregularity or might at least take a benign or congenial view of something that might be regarded a little more stringently by a purely Independent Member.</P>
    <P>The more I think about this the more incensed I become at the notion of setting up a body of this type, of giving a watching brief of this kind to a committee consisting solely of party members under party Whips and responsible to party discipline.  It is understandable in the Dáil but there is in the Seanad a body of people who are here specifically because they are supposed to be Independent and to see that they are excluded <Col N="232" /> from what should be an impartial and independent inquiry into the operation of these bodies, to see such a committee set-up and to exclude the one independent voice which exists, in either part of Parliament, seems to me to be nothing short of a mockery of the whole process of Independent representative in the Seanad.</P>
    <P>I want to make that first point with all the force available to me, that unless there is an Independent Member amongst those four this committee seems to me to be disabled from the start; it starts out with limited credibility.</P>
    <P>I should like to have it explained to the public why an Independent Senator is not allowed representation.  I should like to see the Minister's face while he is explaining it to the House.  I should also like to know why the figure four?  Why not five?  That would make it possible to have Government majority representation, one from each of the Opposition Parties and an Independent Senator.  It would be no skin off anybody's heel.  The committee seem to be deliberately, perversely framed in order to exclude an independent voice.</P>
    <P>I think I have made my case with sufficient force.  I have repeated myself because that is one of the few ways one can lend weight to a point of this importance on a motion of this kind.  I hope my colleagues on the Independent benches will not hesitate to put forward their version of this complaint when the time comes.  There is only one other aspect of the motion I find profoundly relevant, that is, this whole point put forward in the Devlin Report that the heads of State-sponsored bodies should be limited in the salaries they are granted.  This cheeseparing limitation is disastrous.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The remuneration of the heads of State-sponsored bodies does not arise on this motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAMartin" hpid="Dr. Martin Dr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>I should hate to even question the ruling of the Cathaoirleach, but am I correct in recalling that the matter was admitted in the debate in the Dáil?  It seems to have been allowed <Col N="233" /> there, whether it was allowed irregularly there or not&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="An Cathoirleach An Cathoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The business of the other House does not arise here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAMartin" hpid="Dr. Martin Dr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not arise here.  On the matter of the remuneration of the heads of the semi-State bodies, having stated I am of the opinion that they should not be held under such restraint, I will abide by your judgement and pass on to the general import of the motion.  In doing that, let me say just once again before I sit down how very, very seriously I take the policy, if it is a policy and if it is implemented, of excluding an independent voice from this very important committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of the Labour group in the Seanad, I welcome the re-establishment of this Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies.  The only deep regret the Labour group have is that it took so long to re-establish this committee.  The original committee had two meetings only, had barely established their own working methods when they were dissolved at the time of the general election.  It is a reflection on the slow procedures of the two Houses that it has taken from last May until this May to re-establish the committee.  We cannot afford this kind of tardiness and this dilatory approach.  It undermines a lot of what was said in the other House and what will be said today in this House about the important role of such a committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If the committee are that important, then I suggest they should have been re-established when the Dáil and Seanad sittings recommended after the general election.  This point is worth making for future reference.  This is the second of these innovatory specialist committees which evolved recently in the Oireachtas.  First, we had the Joint Committee on the Secondary Legislation of the European Communities and then this Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies.  After a great deal of pressure the EEC committee got re-established last December.  That, in itself, was far too long.  There was far too long a lag between May and December which effectively <Col N="234" /> meant the committee began to meet in January to cope with the various draft directives and regulations which had issued from Brussels the previous May.  Similarly, the Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies should have been re-established at the beginning of November at the latest, and should by now be issuing their first reports.</P>
    <P>Time has been lost.  Indeed, the services of staff have been lost because I understand the clerk who was appointed to that committee has sat in his office waiting for the re-establishment of the committee and, in effect, his time has been wasted and public moneys have been wasted waiting for the committee to be re-established.</P>
    <P>Since we now have these specialist committees, and since by the nature of them they are Joint Committees of both Houses, they will dissolve when we have a general election, it is not too soon to make a firm political commitment that they will be re-established as soon as both Houses come back into business themselves.  The Joint Committee have a statutory basis so there is no question but that they would be re-established.  A firm all-party commitment about the importance of this committee should ensure that they, too, would be very quickly re-established.</P>
    <P>I should like to support Senator Martin.  He is right in saying there should be Independent representation from this House on the Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies.  The Seanad has that kind of personal expertise and commitment to offer.  It is recognised on all sides of the House that the Independent Members of the Seanad put in very conscientious time, do their work and do their homework, and have made very substantial contributions in the areas of operation of our State-sponsored bodies. What he said also struck a cord with me personally as a former Independent member.</P>
    <P>It is an insult to the contribution they make at the moment, and can make, if there is not an Independent Member on the Joint Committee.  There are two ways of doing it, as Senator Martin said. Either one of the four Senators should be an Independent Senator, or else the matter <Col N="235" /> should be returned for consideration of enlarging the size of the Joint Committee. From my own personal experience on the Joint Committee on the Secondary Legislation of the European Communities, a committee of 11 is small to ensure a good working quorum for consideration of the work of the committee. The experience of the Joint Committee has been that, even with a committee of 26, it is sometimes difficult to get more than seven or eight to participate in a full Joint Committee session, or in a session of one of the sub-committees.  A committee of 11 makes it difficult, I presume, to form sub-committees and this, in itself, will slow up the approach to their workload of the Joint Committee on State-sponsored Bodies.  If they cannot form a number of sub-committees, they will have to consider their entire workload in full committee and, since their terms of reference, as has been mentioned, are to examine the reports and accounts and the overall operational results of the very significant number of State-sponsored bodies listed in Schedule A, and Gaeltarra Éireann listed in Schedule B, this is a very formidable workload.</P>
    <P>There is a danger that the Joint Committee might get bogged down in examining one or two bodies&mdash;in examining CIE and RTE, for example&mdash;and a whole session might go by without the committee performing a very important preliminary task, that is, to have an overview of the present operation of the State-sponsored bodies.  I should like to see the committee in a position to give both Houses of the Oireachtas a genuine sense of how chief executives and staff running the State-sponsored bodies view the statutory procedures under which they were set up.  Do the legislation and the terms of reference they were given stand up to the experience of many years in operation, or are there substantial improvements which could be made in that regard?  Are they able to put forward the kind of plans and proposals they want to?  This kind of general overview of all the State-sponsored bodies listed in Schedules A and B should be completed within a period of a maximum of two years in order to allow the committee, in <Col N="236" /> a normal span, to have further time to look in more depth at certain of the State-sponsored bodies which could be singled out.</P>
    <P>If this task is to be placed on the shoulders of 11 people, therefore preventing the development of a structure of sub-committees, there will be very considerable problems in ensuring that this important overview of each of the bodies is completed within a two-year span.</P>
    <P>Another vital matter in establishing a committee of this nature is the permanent staffing of the secretariat of the committee.  As I understand it, the clerk appointed to the old committee remained the expectant awaiting clerk of this committee about to be re-established, but I have not heard any other firm commitment as to the back-up permanent staffing this committee will have.  I would welcome a very specific indication on this from the Minister.  Presumably the previous committee had an opportunity in their preliminary meetings to assess the minimum staff which would enable them to accomplish their task and, again, comparisons with the work of the Joint Committee on the Secondary Legislation of the European Communities are worth while.</P>
    <P>It is worth recalling that the Joint EEC Committee&mdash;to give their short title&mdash;had two years of considerable teething problems in relation to getting a firm commitment for adequate permanent staff on the secretariat.  This committee had to wait for a long time to be established.  An equivalent committee were established in Britain in 1949 and have been operating since.  We as a Parliament are very late indeed in establishing such a committee, given the immense economic significance of the State-sponsored bodies in our economic life.  Given how long it took, first of all, to establish the committee at all and, secondly, how much delay there has been before their re-establishment by this motion in the Dáil and Seanad, it is vital that the committee should start with the adequate complement of staff.  I would have thought the minimum the committee should have would be their clerk and at least two other permanent <Col N="237" /> staff of senior standing, and they should also have secretarial assistance.</P>
    <P>Apart from that, I am glad to see that the terms of reference ensure what looks like a commitment by the Minister for the Public Service to enable the Joint Committee to engage the services of persons with specialist or technical knowledge to assist them for the purpose of particular inquiries.  This is absolutely essential if the Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies are to approach their task with adequate expertise and back-up knowledge.  It will be difficult for these 11 members to assess the accounts of State-sponsored bodies without very significant technical and specialist expertise available to them.  The accounts of State-sponsored bodies, no more than the accounts of other companies, do not reveal very much, and they require very specialist assessment in order to get a true account of the performance and of the actual record of the State-sponsored body.  It will be essential for the Joint Committee to use the power there in order to perform their scrutinising task on behalf of both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>I also welcome the new paragraph (7) of the motion:</P>
    <P>That the Joint Committee shall have powers to print and publish from time to time minutes of evidence taken before it together with such related documents as it thinks fit.</P>
    <P>If the committee taken evidence from chief executives and senior members of State-sponsored bodies, and from other sectors of the economy affected, other experts, and publish this evidence, they will perform a very important service for Members of both Houses who can then be better informed about the role, the priorities and the problems of State-sponsored bodies, the difficulty at times in combining the emphasis on a necessity to be a trading corporation and, at the same time, to fulfil a valuable social function, the conflict at times which must face senior executives in CIE, for example, between remaining if possible reasonably within economic bounds and, at the same time, ensuring that they provide a social service and, in the interests <Col N="238" /> of economising, do not pare down dramatically on the provision of a social service.</P>
    <P>I am glad to learn that a number of chief executives have expressed a welcome for the establishment of this parliamentary committee.  They are right to do so.  They deserve to have a dialogue with a parliamentary committee to ensure that their pre-occupations are considered adequately by an expert committee of Parliament, with expertise available to them, with continuity of membership, so that there can be a substantial learning process by all members of the committee.  Publication on a fairly consistent basis, of evidence taken by this Joint Committee would be of very significant benefit to both Houses and to the public generally, because there has not been sufficient general accountability or general feedback from the managers of our State-sponsored bodies, those who run them.</P>
    <P>The various debates on the Estimates for Departments, or debates in either House when a Minister comes in looking for a further sum of millions for a State-sponsored body, have not been very constructive.  They were random and discursive because Members were not equipped with adequate knowledge to assess the performance of the State-sponsored body.</P>
    <P>The amount of employment given by State-sponsored bodies and the fact that they are about to embark on worker participation are matters members of the Joint Committee should be in a position to assess; also, the successful implementation of a commitment to industrial democracy, to worker participation, which hopefully will become a much more substantial feature in our industrial relations, the progress of a State-sponsored body and the matter I mentioned, the possibility that, in a number of instances, the original Act which may date from the twenties or the thirties may no longer be a sufficiently flexible framework for a State-sponsored body. There will be an opportunity for a parliamentary committee to consider the possibility of broadening or up-dating the statutory terms of reference of that State-sponsored body.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="239" /> As well I would hope the fact that there is a parliamentary committee would have, in itself, a chain reaction in the State-sponsored bodies, that they will themselves standardise to some extent the way in which they present their accounts and try to ensure full understanding and disclosure in those accounts, that they will seek to bring out reports and assessments for the members of the State-sponsored bodies committee and that these will be made available generally to Members of both Houses.</P>
    <P>Again, the experience of the Joint Committee on the Secondary Legislation of the European Communities has been that there is an important role for these committees in meeting interested groups and even interested individuals in the community, either inviting written submissions or going further and having oral hearings with these interested groups, with both sides of industry, with other affected sectors.  This is an active role for the committee as a Joint Committee of the two Houses and enables Parliament to be better briefed, to be closer to the sectors affected, by giving them an opportunity of putting their views to a representative committee of Parliament.</P>
    <P>Unless this committee are established rapidly and given adequate back-up services to enable them to get into gear very fast there is a danger that the Oireachtas will appear to be becoming more and more irrelevant to the complexity of modern Government and administration. The plenary debates on the floor of the Houses will not stand up to critical scrutiny because it will be far too much a case of one Deputy after another, or one Senator after another, getting up and talking in very general terms, mentioning a few individual grievances from personal knowledge, or from knowledge of one or two constituents, or whatever it may be.  There will be a failure to realise that the complex nature of the operations and activities of State-sponsored bodies cannot be commented upon without adequate scrutiny, the assistance of experts and, indeed, an opportunity to hear and receive written and oral submissions from the senior <Col N="240" /> managements of these bodies, and an opportunity to hear and receive written and oral submissions from affected groups in society.</P>
    <P>I welcome the establishment of this committee and I reiterate my support for what Senator Martin said.  Membership of the committee from the Seanad should include an Independent Senator because of the commitment, expertise and independence of those Members. There is a value in that membership of the Joint Committee and it is an insult to Independent Members and a denigration of the different kinds of contribution the Seanad can make to a Joint Committee to deny them representation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelMulcahy" hpid="Mr. Mulcahy Mr. Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Fáiltím go mór roímh an rún seo.  Ceapaim go bhfuilimid ag cur ar bun eagras nua a thabharfaidh taca do na comhlachtaí éagsúla Stáit san am atá le teacht.</P>
      <P>I welcome this motion and I should like to make a few comments on different aspects of it.  I must admit to having a certain sympathy with the views of the Independent Senators.  There seems to be a certain way of setting up these committees.  Perhaps we will have to learn whether or not that is the best way to go about it.  I would point out to Senator Martin, and the Independent Senators, that the reports coming from this committee will be discussed in both Houses.  Members will have access to the data and the discursive debates Senator Robinson referred to may be a little more focussed as a result of the existence of these reports.  I am appalled at the workload ahead of the committee. As Chairman of one of the subcommittees of the Joint EEC Committee which Senator Robinson referred to, I realise the difficulties in trying to manage one of these committees.  At the moment in the Joint EEC Committee we are trying to manage with one meeting per month of the sub-committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This whole approach will develop by trial and error but it is an extremely important move in that now we are bringing into existence a new organisation in the sense that there will exist a Joint Committee supported by staff who are not part of the service but are part of the <Col N="241" /> House staff, in the same way the Joint EEC Committee is supported.  I do not think I should take up the time of the House speculating about what might happen as this committee get under way but I am appalled at the workload. Members of the committee will have to learn how to analyse the operating accounts and the operations of the various State bodies in order to come to a conclusion about whether they are being run properly and perhaps make some observations as to how they might be improved.</P>
    <P>In this regard, I am pleased to note in the Minister's introductory statement that some chief executives of these bodies have welcomed this move as a means of getting some of their ideas across which might have been bottled up in the past within the civil service system and the ministerial system.  I am referring here to the rather slow developments in the evolution of the recommendations of the review body on the civil service, in Devlin 1, in relation to the aireacht idea and in relation to other appointments which were to be made.  The existence of this Joint Committee might help to accelerate public service reform as well as looking at the operations of semi-State bodies.  I hope the work of the Joint Committee will not be seen as negative, that they will not be there just to ask questions in an awkward way in the sense of an over-emphasis on control.  I hope they will play a positive role in the development of these bodies and that the hopes of the chief executives of the semi-State bodies will be realised in that regard.  When the media have to report discursive debates in this House they may be a bit more patient when they realised the data required to make any really focussed analysis of situations, particularly in relation to large-scale capital expenditure.  The reports of the committee will be current, rather than waiting and analysing on a <i>post hoc</i> basis events which took place anything up to a year-and-a-half beforehand and are not really going to &ldquo;grab&rdquo; anybody.</P>
    <P>I see an appalling workload ahead of the committee.  They will have to learn how to handle it and they may have to develop new procedures.  Members of the <Col N="242" /> committee will have to give time to the workload, which cannot be left entirely to the back-up service.  I welcome the fact that the committee seem to be empowered to draw on specialised technical services&mdash;I assume, on consultants to make specialised reports&mdash;and that these reports will be commissioned by a committee of the Oireachtas.  This is not unusual, but not frequent.  It will certainly change the way things have been done between these Houses and the public service.  I welcome the motion and look forward with interest to the way the committee evolve.  There may be some question as to whether they will be able to do this job at all.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MylesStaunton" hpid="Mr. Staunton Mr. Staunton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Staunton</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity of addressing myself to the motion setting up the Joint Committee on State-Sponsored Bodies.  I believe there is a consensus within the Oireachtas regarding the proposed formation of this committee.  Indeed, the committee now being reactivated is, to a significant extent, similar to that which was introduced by the Coalition Government in late 1976.</P>
      <P>Since approximately 1927 when some semi-State bodies were established, there has been a growing disquiet that despite the extent to which the trappings of power may exist within the Oireachtas, much real power lies outside these Houses.  As we have seen the growth of the semi-State system has been very successful. We have seen this vast increase in the extent of the scope of such semi-State bodies, in the proportion of the gross national product, in the output of this country and in the budget of this country held by the semi-States.  The significance of this is shown in that in the bodies to which we are addressing ourselves, those engaged in the commercial and trading sector, we are talking about total assets exceeding £1,000 million and turnover of over £500 million and an employment of about 60,000 people.  With this vast growth in the semi-State sector there has been public disquiet about what has seemed to have been a lack of public accountability of a suitable type.  For that reason I welcome the formation of this committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The motion before the House <Col N="243" /> presented by the Government concerns itself with what it describes as two Schedules, Schedule A and Schedule B. Schedule A lists those semi-State companies which in broad terms of reference could be said to be in a trading and commercial situation as opposed to the activities of the other semi-State bodies. Whilst I welcome the inclusion of the trading and commercial semi-State bodies in the list, we should address ourselves to the issue in principle and ask ourselves why the other large number of semi-State bodies are excluded from the Motion.  There should be agreement within this House that the Oireachtas should have as its objective Parliamentary control of all of these semi-State companies without exception. If we look to the debate that took place on this issue in November 1976 in the Dáil it is interesting to note the comment at that time of the present Minister for Finance, Deputy Colley, column 1419, Volume 293 when he urged the Minister at that time to have a look at this issue. At that time the Bill now introduced was substantially the same and was confined to the trading and commercial companies. The point was made by the Minister at the time that it was confined to the commercial and trading companies as merely the first step because of the practicalities of organising control of all such semi-State bodies both regarding the resources of this House and the resources of Members.  It is interesting to note that Mr. Colley in his speech urged the Minister to have another look at this question.  He went on to say that when one thinks about it one is entitled to ask questions.  Why should a body like Coras Trachtála or the IDA or other similar bodies not be answerable to the Houses of the Oireachtas in respect of certain major aspects of policy?  I quote:</P>
    <P>If we take the IDA, it is true that the general policy followed is subject of discussion and debate in this House but, on the other hand, the methods used by the IDA to achieve its aims are not open to question in this House.  There are good reasons in some cases why it should not be open to full scale public discussion at least <Col N="244" /> until the facts are established.  What I am saying is true of many other bodies also.  I would question the wisdom of excluding from the terms of reference of this committee all State-sponsored bodies which are not engaged in commercial or trading activities. It may well be that the range of work involved is such that it would require another committee or even two other committees to do it.  I am not dealing with the practicalities of that at the moment but rather with the principle involved.</P>
    <P>I would presume that there is consistency in the Minister's thinking and his involvement in the present Government. If that is so, then the Government, while introducing this motion confining the control of the semi-State bodies to those in what is defined as the commercial or trading sector, will take the view that parliamentary control of all of the semi-State bodies is necessary and desirable and that this is merely the first step.  Presumably, having looked at the workings of this first step, the Government would continue to think logically and would extend the ambit of this committee or a further committee to take control of the wider range of semi-State bodies we are concerned with.</P>
    <P>I would welcome reference by the Minister to this issue which I have raised and to the speech made by the Minister for the Public Service, Deputy Colley, two years ago.  I would like to hear what the Government's objectives are in this regard, long-term though they may be at this stage.  When we look past the range of the trading and commercial activities there are other sectors such as AnCO, Bord na gCapall, Bord na gCon, Bord Fáilte, Bord Iascaigh Mhara, Córas Tráchtála Teoranta, the Agricultural Institute, the Industrial Development Authority, the Kilkenny Design Centre and SFADCo in the Shannon region.</P>
    <P>Consideration of this distinction, the desirability of control of all such companies for parliamentary reasons, brings me to mention in detail the rather odd inclusion in this motion of what is described as Schedule B.  Contained within that Schedule B is Gaeltarra Éireann.  Apparently under the motion which we are asked to accept the trading <Col N="245" /> and commercial aspects of the reports and accounts and the overall operational results of the State-sponsored body referred to in Schedule B are to be examined.</P>
    <P>I take exception to the inclusion of Gaeltarra Éireann within this motion because it is entirely inconsistent and smacks of a witch-hunt.  The reason I object to it is that it is stated in the Minister's speech that Gaeltarra Éireann is in a somewhat different category. Whilst it is a promotional body it is also involved in equity participation.  This by definition is commercial activity and for this reason it should be included within this motion.  The inconsistency arises for two or three different reasons.  There are other bodies which are semi-State bodies which are in the practically identical situation in that whilst they are primarily promotional bodies they also hold equity.  For example, the Industrial Development Authority is largely promotional but again it is empowered by the Minister to hold equity in companies and does hold equity with private companies in a number of cases around this country.  In addition to that Bord Fáilte, the promotional body for tourism, is in the position of holding equity in certain situations with local authorities and in other situations around this country.  Yet we have the anomaly in the resolution introduced here today, and indeed, it is the single significant difference between the resolution introduced and the resolution of the previous Government in late 1976, in that Gaeltarra is included in this one and was not in the prior one.  We have to ask ourselves why Gaeltarra Éireann is included for such accountability when its sisters in the semi-State sector in an identical position are not.</P>
    <P>There is a further inconsistency.  It is stated by the Minister in his speech in the Dáil that Gaeltarra Éireann is included because of the fact that it is in a commercial and trading situation in addition to its promotional activity.  We need to define the type of commercial and trading activity in which it is involved to follow this through.  Whilst previously Gaeltarra Éireann was in a strong trading and commercial position <Col N="246" /> in that it owned its own companies and was involved as a company in trading, that side of Gaeltarra is a lesser section than it was some years ago.  Whilst it holds equity in other situations that equity is held with private companies in industries which are run in the private sector.  If it is the Minister's desire that this committee should look at Gaeltarra's equity participation with private industry, and having regard to the terms of reference here which refer to examining the reports and accounts and the overall operational results, we are dealing with an area which will demand confidentiality beyond the point of merely a right of such trading activities by any committee of this Oireachtas.  It is entirely inconsistent. If at this stage the Minister can have second thoughts it is desirable that he should do so.  On the broadest principle I hope that the Government will be consistent in re-echoing the remarks of the Minister for the Public Service and have as their ultimate objective the inclusion of all the semi-State companies within the accountability of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>I also subscribe to the views of some of my fellow Senators who spoke about the involvement of members on this committee and the workload which it will involve.  There is no doubt that this is a major job which is going to be carried out by both Members of the Dáil and Members of Seanad Éireann.  The run-up to this is not satisfactory because in many Dáil and Seanad Committees the participation and attendance have not been as good as they might have been.  I do not say this in criticism of individual members of such committees but rather because of the enormous burden they bear, more particularly the Members of the Dáil who are responding to the general public to a different extent from Members of Seanad Éireann.  The constraints where constituency work and work delegations and committees are concerned lead to an extremely difficult job particularly for Deputies on any committee such as this.  Sadly under the system which we operate they run the risk of losing votes from their constituents to those who choose not to exercise this type of parliamentary work for which they were fundamentally <Col N="247" /> elected.</P>
    <P>The Government will have to face up to providing adequate support for Members of the Oireachtas.  We have been saying this for a number of years and we are saying it in an apolitical sense.  Unless there is back-up and support for Members of the Oireachtas it would be absolutely impossible for Members to give of their best to committees such as this or to perform as effectively as they should in the national interest. A great many Members have the will to act fully in the national interest on committees such as this but until such time as they get the support and the back-up they cannot begin to do so. There is a huge anomaly here in that we have office conditions which are entirely unacceptable.  There is a lack of secretarial assistance for constituency work.  We have a situation where we have small rooms in which five or six Members of the Oireachtas are working together.  There are larger rooms in which ten, 12 or 14 are working together without secretarial assistance.  Yet we have this huge anomaly that this is the premier body here, the legislative body, the overseer, the controller to which all other bodies are subordinate.</P>
    <P>We talk about public accountability but again we come back to this point that we have all the trappings of power here but real power can rest elsewhere.  If there is to be effective Oireachtas control of these huge semi-State bodies with assets amounting to hundreds of millions of pounds the Members will have to be spoon-fed by Government so that they can perform adequately.  This committee will not perform as usefully as it might. We cannot begin to look at the semi-State bodies in the non-trading sector until such time as the operations of this House and the support of the Members of it are considered.</P>
    <P>For other reasons it is desirable that this committee be established.  In the enthusiasm generated because of a certain aspect of the national life of our economy it may seem in a certain year that it is desirable that a semi-State body should be established but conditions change very rapidly.  The first semi-State body was established in 1927.  We are <Col N="248" /> now 50 years past that point.  Originally there might be a consensus within the Oireachtas.  The Government might make a decision and articles of association are drawn up for a semi-State body to become involved in the national interest in a particular sector of our economy but times changed and possibly ten or 15 years later some of these bodies may not be necessary and coordination and the possible moving of personnel in semi-State bodies might be desirable in the national interest.  There is the danger, and there have been examples of it, that bodies established and set in motion without adequate public accountability can sometimes take a loose interpretation of the articles of association under which they were originally set up.  In this type of situation one can see semi-State bodies getting involved in areas of activity which were not envisaged by the Government of the day, which were not a charter given to it by the Oireachtas and which ultimately are undesirable in the national interest.  For that reason a committee such as this monitoring what is happening is extremely useful.</P>
    <P>There is also the issue of conflict with private enterprise.  Clearly we have a mixed economy here which has worked very well in the interests of this country but the danger in a mixed economy is that matters can spill over.  One can get unnecessary conflict between the public sector and the private sector.  Unnecessary conflict between the public and the private sector is very undesirable.  If we want to foster a spirit of private enterprise here it is important to avoid encroachments on the private area by the State sector because this can act as a huge disincentive in the most general terms apart from the specifics of the case in question.</P>
    <P>There is a danger in this area where semi-State bodies are concerned.  We should continue along the lines on which there has been general agreement. Within the State sector there is considerable scope for activity in economic and in many other areas.  This scope for the State rests with those sections of our economy in which the options have not been taken up by private enterprise but I <Col N="249" /> resent encroachments by the public sector where it is thought that the private sector is doing an adequate job in the national interest.  That type of activity is not desirable.</P>
    <P>Paragraph 3 of the motion states that if so requested by semi-State bodies the committee should refrain from publishing confidential information.  I am in complete agreement that confidential information should be withheld when it is thought that it should be but I cannot, in a democratic system, go along with the nation that the ultimate decision of definition about what is supposed to be confidential should rest with the semi-State body in question.  If we run into a position where the committee, for their own good reasons, see nothing wrong with the disclosure of certain information relating to semi-State bodies the mere definition of this as being confidential by the semi-State body could block such publication.  It is possible that the semi-State body in their wisdom might be right but it seems to me that the committee are the ultimate authority and should have the ultimate power of what constitutes confidentiality.</P>
    <P>One final point is the issue of historical accounting.  One of the weaknesses in the EEC Committee of the Oireachtas is that much of the work we were doing was historical.  We were looking at secondary legislation, much of which was passed a considerable time before it came near us and some of which was concerned with olive oil in southern European States and many such matters which were not relevant to this country.  We were anxious that we should, as a committee, be kept informed of what was happening and of proposed legislation so that if we had a view and could influence events we could warn the Government of the day of our views on a particular issue.</P>
    <P>There is a similar danger in the setting up of this committee that we should guard against.  We are not going to have effective Oireachtas control of the semi-State bodies if we get involved to too great an extent in historical accounting. Reading the motion before us we are going to examine the reports and the accounts and the overall operational results.  In talking about reports or accounts <Col N="250" /> or overall operational results we are talking about the formal reports and accounts and such like information of such bodies.  The accounts of many of these bodies will likely end on December 31.  Some are fairly efficient in getting out their accounts, some are not.  If some of these accounts are coming out in July or August of the following year&mdash;say, seven or eight months after December 31&mdash;some possibly later than that, the earliest stage at which this committee could examine such accounts is after the Summer Recess in October.  We then have a likely position in which the reports and accounts of many of these companies will not be looked at until perhaps the October after the December of the year which had concluded, namely, about nine or ten months after the start of the operations for the year in question.  We are being optimistic in some cases in expecting debate at that time because, having regard to the large number of companies with which we are concerned, debate could run considerably later than that.</P>
    <P>The committee should in the first instance have discussions with the semi-State bodies in question regarding dates of publication of accounts.  If there is to be dynamism in this committee, if it is going to respond on behalf of the general public here, if there is going to be enlightened debate, if it is possible to be helpful in so far as operations of certain companies are concerned, it is desirable that these discussions should take place at as early a stage as possible.  The danger is that, having regard to some bodies where accounts have been published very late, we may get into historical accounting to the extent that we are back to the trappings being there rather than power, and we will have a situation where the operations of some of these companies will be examined perhaps two or three years later than is desirable.  This would be most undesirable and I hope this committee will, in a friendly sense and at an early stage, talk about this question of accounting procedures and publication of accounts. The relevant year is the year 1978 and the publication of accounts for the year will end for most of these companies at the end of December next year.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="251" /> Finally, I know that this will provide useful dialogue and be of as much assistance to the chief executives and the boards and the various workers in the semi-State bodies as it will be to the Oireachtas.  We are not on a witch hunt. They provide an excellent service to this country.  I would imagine that the question of public accountability and the sensitivity where the public are concerned, which could be explained very well to these companies by Members of the Oireachtas, might in turn be very useful to them in that there is going to be two-way dialogue here.  I would hope that when this committee gets involved in dialogue with these various semi-State bodies the normal format will be for dialogue to take place at some time during the debate in each company with the chief executive of each semi-State body. It needs this kind of significance.  I hope that part of the dialogue will be between the committee and the chief executive of the organisation in question.</P>
    <P>With the major reservations about the inclusion of Gaeltarra Éireann which is entirely inconsistent, having regard to the position in Bord Fáilte and the Industrial Development Authority&mdash;there is no reason for it or if there is, other companies should be in there with it and working on the principle that the Government is moving towards a situation of control of all semi-State bodies especially having regard to Mr. Colley's speech in the Dáil in 1976&mdash;I welcome this motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GemmaHussey" hpid="Mrs. Hussey Mrs. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be very brief in welcoming the setting up of this committee which seems both a necessary and suitable function for the Oireachtas.  It does call into question the whole way that we conduct our affairs.  The provision and the use of the facilities in running this parliament strikes me as being more suited to an age before modern communications and before the complexities of parliamentary life reached what they are now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are umpteen committees meeting on Wednesdays in every corner of the House and across the road in other houses.  All these committees are <Col N="252" /> concentrated into a couple of days in the middle of the week and people are trying to be in two places at the same time, if not three or four places at the same time. It would be better to have no committee than a committee which only half functions.</P>
    <P>From the experience that I have on various committees, so far, I am not satisfied that they are functioning fully.  I am not blaming the people who are on those committees.  We seem to be stuck in a system that we all deplore but nobody seems to be actually tackling what way we are going to solve it.  Obviously Senators and presumably Dáil Deputies who wish to sit on these committees will be sure before they elect to do so that they will have the interest and the time to give to the committee.  If the officials of the semi-State bodies are going to take time off from their own very pressing business which is the running of these bodies to come and present themselves before this committee, the least they can expect is that they will have a well attended, well organised, well informed body of public representatives to talk to.  It has not been my experience that that has been the case on various committees that I have sat on so far.</P>
    <P>There is a sepulchral silence about this place on a Monday and a Friday.  I am from Dublin and I understand that difference but the fact remains that Leinster House and the house across the road and everywhere else has echoing halls on a Monday and a Friday. Everybody is gone away and there is complete silence, and it is not so good either on a Thursday afternoon.  There is something the matter with the way the thing is being run.  Other countries have managed to design systems so that their public representatives do not have to be all things to all men all the time.  It is mentioned quite a lot, and I submit that it is about time something was done before we go on setting up very valuable committees like this.  Study should be carried out of all the different committees which are in existence which have members who are Deputies and Senators.  There should be a time-table of where they are all meeting, what the attendance rate is and why it is so bad.  I <Col N="253" /> should be at a meeting now but obviously I cannot be in two places at the same time.  I doubt the efficiency or the effectiveness of setting up committees like this which are going to cost the taxpayers even more money than they are already paying if they cannot be organised in a modern efficient manner. Senator Mulcahy says that by trial and error these things will work out.  There has been enough trial and error, and it is about time we stopped hoping for accidents to make things right.</P>
    <P>There is a very important point which I would like to speak on.  I was sorry that the last speaker did not mention it.  It is the representation of Independents on this committee.  It is extremely important that there should be an Independent on the Committee.  The Independent Senators fill a place in this House which is written down in the Constitution of Ireland.  We have a very specific place in this House and therefore any joint committee of Dáil and Senate which leaves us out is not a representative committee. We are presuming that there will be a place for Independents on this committee. Anything else would be unthinkable. It would be flying in the face of the intention of the person who wrote that Constitution in the first place.  I am very glad that there was a ruling earlier which makes it quite clear that this House certainly has no wish to enter into any debate on, or, indeed, does not condone, the recent disgraceful situation where the salary of a chief executive was dragged through the public.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to raise five aspects of the whole project.  I call it a project because it has been decided to set up this committee after practically half-a-century of experience of State-sponsored bodies being accepted by the public as beyond accountability to Government Departments.  This was an unacceptable situation and I suppose it is better late than never that this committee has been set up.  The first point is in regard to terms of reference.  The motion refers to the committee examining the reports and accounts and overall operational results of State-sponsored bodies.  I wonder whether the investigation <Col N="254" /> of policy matters is invested in these terms of reference.</P>
      <P>Paragraph (3) reads: &ldquo;... if so requested by a State-sponsored body, the Joint Committee shall refrain from publishing confidential information&rdquo;. This is giving far too much power to State-sponsored bodies.  It would appear that they can make a request at the beginning of any investigation and that that request must be acceded to.  I would prefer if it had been written in that such a request could be discussed first of all and that a decision as to whether it would be accepted or not would be entirely at the discretion of the committee. As it stands, this committee will have no option but to accede to a request to refrain from publishing.</P>
      <P>We are all aware of the workload of Members of both Houses and I think it is no harm to give an example of the committee's functions in regard to the State-sponsored bodies listed which are shown in Schedule A.  We know that from time to time hell lets loose in regard to certain State-sponsored bodies. CIE comes under the hammer of public criticism from time to time as Aer Lingus did recently, and the ESB more times than not, and so on.  If this happens when the committee is in existence I can see its members being obliged to give a considerable amount of time to examining a particular body; certainly in the case of CIE which runs into heavy annual deficits.  The pressure on this committee will be tremendous from time to time, particularly when public criticism is vociferous.  In that event I cannot see how the committee will be able to cope with the other two dozen or more bodies which are listed in Schedule A.  This means that these bodies may not be subjected to regular examination and perusal that was envisaged in the setting up of the committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I cannot understand why the number to serve on the committee has been restricted to seven Deputies and four Senators, a total of 11 out of a total House membership of more than 200.  In other words, only 5 per cent of the total membership of both Houses will be involved <Col N="255" /> in this very important work.  I cannot understand why the work of these bodies, which covers various matters such as transport, industry, tourism and agriculture, was not given for examination to a larger number of Deputies and Senators.  The number could be at least doubled.  The subjects for examination could then be divided amongst that membership of two dozen, or even more, from both Houses, which would give the committee a far greater opportunity to discuss and investigate all these matters. It would be quite easy to divide, say, the Joint Committee into three separate subcommittees each responsible for transport or for industry or for agriculture.  In that way the public would get far greater service out of the proposed committee than it is going to.  I certainly do not see the committee being able to perform the task which has been entrusted to it.</P>
    <P>The back-up service has already been mentioned and I am afraid to say that, even in the Minister's opening address, there are certain indications that this back-up service will not be adequate.  In his speech the Minister said: &ldquo;In addition to a Secretariat, which need not, I think, be large, I will be prepared to make provision for the engagement of technical expertise, preferably on a limited-term basis for particular investigations&rdquo;. How big is large?  The seven public representatives engaged on this committee are not going to have time for much more than putting down headings on points which come into their minds in regard to the State-sponsored bodies.  It would be necessary to have sufficient research staff, even investigatory staff, to do the back-up work for the public representatives so that the committee can really function.  If we do not give the committee sufficient and adequate back-up staff, we are going to kill it dead at a very early stage of its existence, and that is something we do not want to happen.</P>
    <P>Our experience of the Public Accounts Committee shows that they are dealing too late with events and the actual expenditure of money to be really effective and to be able to do more than make vague recommendations.  From that experience we see certain dangers <Col N="256" /> which we should avoid.  If we do not give the committee the necessary back-up staff, increase its membership, and give it adequate terms of reference, such as being able to examine policy matters of State-sponsored bodies and make decisions in regard to publishing documentary information, we will not achieve what we all hope will be achieved in regard to this Joint Committee.</P>
    <P>In conclusion I should like to pay a tribute to the chief executive and officers of all semi-State bodies.  They are much maligned from time to time.  They take a very heavy public responsibility on themselves which is increasing from year to year.  I am glad that they see in the formation of this committee an opportunity for them to let the public, through this committee, appreciate the difficulties under which they work.  I have listed my reservations in regard to the committee and hope that the committee will function very soon.  It is disappointing to find that the committee which was set up in late 1976 met only twice up to June of 1977 and that they did no more than consider procedural matters.  I hope that this new committee will act quicker than that.  Indeed, I cannot understand why it has taken from last June to the present time to re-establish this committee. Again, I am afraid, it indicates a lack of confidence in the ability of any committee comprised of such a small number to perform its function.</P>
    <P>I request the Minister to get this committee working as soon as possible and to have them come back with recommendations. I have no doubt that they will have positive recommendations in regard to extending their research and investigatory staff, and the Minister should act on their recommendation as quickly as possible in order to achieve their overall purpose.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ValentineJago" hpid="Mr. Jago Mr. Jago">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jago</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this committee and I also welcome the terms of reference as I have been rather worried about some of the expressed views on Oireachtas control.  I do not believe the committee are going to set up Oireachtas control.  There is Oireachtas accountability.  Oireachtas control will <Col N="257" /> really mean creating another body over the body that is already controlling the particular semi-State body.  The Board creates that.  Therefore, the work that we are envisaging is that the committee will examine the accounts and a person experienced in accounts can then see the questions to be asked.</P>
      <P>From that you have accountability in the same way as you would have accountability in a public company where the shareholders would be told of the service the company is giving.  Therefore you can have people on the committee who have experience and are used to examining accounts and do so quickly.  On the other hand you can have people who are not very used to examining accounts. Two things would be important.  One is a back-up service to analyse the accounts for the members of the committee whereby they can formulate the inquiries they want to make.  The other thing is that those who are appointed to the committee must be regular attenders to keep the continuity there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I support the plea made by Senators Martin and Hussey that membership of the Joint Committee should include one of the Independent Senators.  After all, four of the five Independent Senators are present, active and it is not too presumptuous to suggest that they are not below average intelligence or level of information. In that connection I thought it was a bit condescending of Senator Mulcahy to suggest that we could be fobbed off by simply saying, &ldquo;Well, you are going to get the reports of the committee&rdquo;. That is wilfully beside the point.  The point has been made by other Senators and I am not going to labour it except to thank Senator Robinson, speaking from the Labour Front Bench, for her support for Independent representation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Like other Senators, I welcome the Bill but I take Senator Markey's point that perhaps it was shortsighted to keep the level of membership at such a low number as 11 given the enormous number of State-sponsored bodies on the Schedule.  I am very glad to welcome the setting up of this Joint Committee if for no other reason than that it will serve to <Col N="258" /> inform the public of the work of the State-sponsored bodies and so deflect some of the frequently vicious flak aimed at public servants in the State-sponsored sector.  This is particularly so with regard to CIE, where the social services offered by the national transport system are frequently ignored in a mean and deliberate denigration of its services.</P>
    <P>With Senator Markey I also take this occasion to pay tribute to the great work done by the State-sponsored bodies, which is almost co-terminous with the history of this State.  I am glad to see that according to the Minister's statement there is no question of a witch hunt or that the committee have primarily an inquisitorial function.  I thought that Senator Staunton seemed to suggest that this is the way he saw the Joint Committee working, especially in his reference to Gaeltarra Eireann being included. Therefore, I am glad to see in the Minister's statement the reference to the fact that the chief executives have already indicated that they see the committee's role as a positive one which will enable the Oireachtas and the public to appreciate the difficulties they encounter and the challenges they face, which is a very important clause.  Not only has the Oireachtas the right and the duty to oversee the work of the State-sponsored bodies but the institution of this committee will supply the Oireachtas with the opportunity for encouraging these State-sponsored bodies in their work and to see how farther they can extend and cooperate one with the other in the crucial economic period in which we are now living.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Pace</i> Senator Staunton, it is preempting the issue to say that you start with the first principle that the public sector must not encroach on the private sector.  The Joint Committee must not vitiate its own work by closing the options at the beginning.  I think all the options should be open.  Finally, it is very sensible on the whole to envisage, in paragraphs 7 and 8, the committee publishing interim reports.  This will have the effect, <i>inter alia</i>, of keeping public interest alive and well informed.  I do hope, however, that the final report of the committee will not be over-delayed.</P>
    <Col N="259" />
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not intend to speak on this motion, but the more I listened to some of the fine contributions that were made, the more I reflected on the sorry state of many of the joint committees that we have.  Reference has already been made to the amount of work which the Joint EEC Committee had to deal with.  Indeed, it occurs to me that a couple of weeks ago we had the first meeting of the Seanad committee on statutory instruments and I understand from the Clerk of that committee that the last committee on statutory instruments considered instruments up to 1976.  If one were to bridge the lacuna that exists now, one would have to consider 1,000 statutory instruments.  If the new committee on statutory instruments is to function at all, it is going to have to ignore a lot of the statutory instruments that have already come into effect. Between the Joint EEC Committee and all other committees that sit in relation to the work of these Houses there seems to be a great lack.</P>
      <P>I welcome the motion both in the sense that this committee should be a watchdog, as it were, and also in the sense that chief executives of semi-State bodies can use this committee as a way of expressing their problems or the hopes they have for their enterprises.  It is important that this committee be sufficiently staffed with back-up services and people.  The number of seven from the Dáil and four from the Seanad is grossly inadequate to deal with the amount of work which is envisaged for the committee.  One has only to glance down the list in Schedules A and B to realise the enormous area of enterprise that is covered.  I support the remarks made by Senator Martin and other Senators.  It is proper that Independent Senators, or at least one Independent Senator, should be on this committee. How they will be selected I do not know. There are Independent Senators on both sides of the House and presumably they will meet and discuss it amongst themselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is sad that when we speak of the composition of the Seanad we too often think of the party composition.  The only <Col N="260" /> time the real composition of the Seanad seems to be relevant is at the time of elections.  We forget that in the Seanad we have five specialist groups represented.  Then we have the University Senators, not forgetting the soccer team.  It would be a very good idea to enlarge the committee considerably, certainly double their strength, and to have the work subdivided among them.  The Seanad representatives on the committee should not be just from party groups but from the five vocational panels and from the Independents.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PearseWyse" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. Wyse) Pearse Wyse">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. Wyse)</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senators were making their contributions it came to me forcibly that we are talking about setting up a structure and then monitoring it until it reaches perfection.  The Senators had this very much in mind in their contributions.  It is very important that we should monitor the proceedings and progress of this committee.  I agree with the Senator who said that the workload is going to be a very important aspect.  As one who worked on many Oireachtas committees, he is aware of the fact that too often in the middle of our business the bell rings for a division, and so on.  These interruptions mean that you cannot specialise or give your fullest attention to the work on hand.  This matter will need serious consideration.  I am glad that so many Senators made contributions today.  Again, we are talking about a structure, monitoring it, and seeing how we can bring about perfection in its workings.</P>
      <P>Senator Cooney suggested that the chairman should be from the Opposition. This was not provided for in the motion before the previous Seanad.  As I said in introducing the motion, the Government decided to try out the original scheme and we were not anxious to make any very elaborate changes in the original scheme.  Therefore, the matter of the chairmanship, like other matters, can be reviewed when the committee have obtained some experience of their operations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Martin referred to the number of Senators to serve on the committee. On the number of four Members of the <Col N="261" /> Seanad &mdash; I think he asked was that provided for.  It was provided for in the original motion.  We are making no significant changes in the original terms. As regards his point that an Independent Senator should be included, this is a matter for the Committee of Selection.  I do not wish to stray into the committee's province but I am sure the committee will bear in mind the Senator's remarks. There was a strong case made today for the inclusion of an Independent Senator on the committee.  However, I am not going to influence the committee in anything I say here today.  It is a matter for themselves and I have no doubt that this matter will be seriously considered by them.</P>
    <P>Senators mentioned the staffing of the committee which, of course, is very important. The Minister for the Public Service will meet all reasonable requests of the committee for staff.  It is for the committee to decide in the first instance what staff they need.  At this stage I believe that the administrative section need not be large but it is important that technical expertise be available to the committee. This will be needed and I have no doubt that the Minister concerned will ensure that these services are available to the committee.  That is very important as too often, committees fail to function effectively unless they have sufficient staff and the necessary back-up services to help them.</P>
    <P>Senator Staunton questioned the provision whereby State-sponsored bodies have the right ultimately to decide what information is confidential.  I think a number of Senators touched on this matter today.  I agree that this provision could be abused by a State-sponsored body, but at this stage it would be wrong to assume that such would occur.  If it should occur, the committee would no doubt report it to the Oireachtas.  If that happened, the Government would take the necessary steps to bring in amendments in that respect.  If such an abuse arises, I think there is provision for the Minister to act, if he is satisfied that this is happening.  The Members of the Oireachtas can bring abuses to the notice of the Government and the Government can bring in an amendment to prevent any further abuse.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="262" /> The inclusion of Gaeltarra Éireann for its commercial activities has been questioned by Senator Staunton.  The reason for the inclusion of Gaeltarra Éireann is that they were included in the motion for the previous committee when the then Minister for the Public Service accepted an amendment to have them included.  I am afraid that the Senator was under some misapprehension when he suggested that Gaeltarra Éireann were not included in the previous Schedule.  What may be confusing him is that he is looking at the original motion rather than the amended motion.</P>
    <P>Senator Staunton also asked why non-commercial State-sponsored bodies are not included.  The answer is twofold. First, the Government have decided to give the original idea of the committee a trial and the non-commercial bodies were not originally included.  Second, as the Senator said, the committee as now proposed will have a greater workload and we must see how they function before we extend this mandate.  It is very important that we know exactly how the work of the committee is going so that amendments or suggestions are recommended.</P>
    <P>I said at the outset that we are talking about a very important structure which will need all possible consideration and advice as it works.  For that reason, I want to thank Senators for their contributions. This is the first big step forward in parliamentary procedure. This has been agreed by all Members. Both sides of the House agree that this is something good, something that has been talked about for a long time.  It is now in operation and I hope it will prove to be of benefit.  I will certainly convey what has been said here today to the Minister and further consideration will be given to all aspects of the contributions. I thank Senators for their contributions.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Landlord and Tenant (Ground Rents)" RHead="(No. 2) Bill, 1977: Second Stage">
    <Title>Landlord and Tenant (Ground Rents) (No. 2) Bill, 1977: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Col N="263" />
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Mr. D. Andrews) David Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Mr. D. Andrews)</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senators are by now aware, this is the second instalment in a trilogy of measures to give effect to the Government's proposals in the area of landlord and tenant law.  The first of these measures &mdash; the Landlord and Tenant (Ground Rents) Act, 1978, to which I will refer for convenience as the No. 1 Act&mdash;became law on 16 May 1978.  Its effect is that, as and from that date, no new ground rents on dwellinghouses may be created.</P>
      <P>The objects of the present Bill are:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a) to provide a new purchase system under which ground rent lessees and tenants, including lessees under local authorities, may buy out the fee simple of the dwellinghouses they occupy, paying purely nominal fees in respect of the legal costs involved;</P>
      <P>(b)  to extend to new classes of lessees and yearly tenants the right to acquire the fee simple; and</P>
      <P>(c)  to abolish a landlord's right of re-entry for non-payment of ground rent.</P>
      <P>The third instalment of this legislation will be initiated as soon as possible after proceedings in the present Bill have been concluded and will deal in the main with changes in the law relating to occupational tenancies, on the basis of recommendations that have been made by the Landlord and Tenant Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Before dealing with the details of the Bill which is now before the House, I would like to refer to some general issues.  First, I would refer to the Government's undertaking, as expressed in the Fianna Fáil election manifesto, in relation to ground rents.  The actual undertaking was set out in one sentence at paragraph 9 of our manifesto, under the heading &ldquo;Local Government&rdquo;, and read: &ldquo;Fianna Fáil will provide a scheme which will lead to the abolition of existing residential ground rents&rdquo;.  I am aware from the debate that took place on the No. 1 Act when it was before the Dáil in November and <Col N="264" /> December last that there are those who would like to misconstrue the undertaking in the manifesto.  They would like that undertaking construed as if it were a promise to abolish ground rents directly, leaving landlords either with no compensation or to be compensated by the State.  In the other House the Minister went into great detail to set the record straight on that subject.  I do not propose to go into the same detail here, but I should like to emphasise that the record is there for all to see.  If we wanted to promise the abolition of ground rents directly that is precisely what we would have said and, indeed, that is what we did say and do in relation to rates and car tax, for instance.</P>
    <P>Apart from the political aspect &mdash; what was promised in the manifesto &mdash; it is important also to point out that nothing that has been said in the other House or outside it can reasonably be taken as indicating that the Minister or the Government favoured abolition in that sense &mdash; that is, abolition without compensation. On the contrary, I think it fair to say that the present Minister for Justice went to considerable pains when in opposition to make his position quite clear.  He is on record as having referred to his discussions with the residents' associations on this very subject.  He said that they had never suggested that the ground landlord's interest should be taken over without compensation. Neither did he ever suggest that the State should be responsible for compensation.</P>
    <P>As I have indicated, an essential feature of this Bill is the way it proposes to deal with the long-standing problem of legal costs.  If we can solve the problem of legal costs then, I would suggest, we have solved the problem of ground rents.  If we enable tenants to get the fee simple at a fixed nominal charge for the legal work, then we have a scheme which will lead to the abolition of ground rents and that is precisely what we have in this Bill.</P>
    <P>The State's contribution towards the costs of acquisition as proposed in this Bill is the kernel of the whole scheme. That contribution amounts virtually to <Col N="265" /> undertaking the whole task.  The fees to be charged will be nominal and are the minimum which could be charged so as to avoid purely frivolous applications under the scheme.</P>
    <P>What this Bill does, therefore, is to provide the means to make ground rents a thing of the past so far as ordinary dwellinghouses are concerned.  It provides strong encouragement for ground rent tenants to exercise their rights.  I feel it will succeed in this for the following reasons.  I think that most people paying ground rents are genuinely interested in becoming full owners &mdash; that is to say, owners of the fee simple &mdash; of their dwellings if they can do so without too much inconvenience and without incurring an unknown but substantial burden of legal costs.  If they are not, then the campaign against ground rents cannot have been representative of the feelings of ordinary householders. The terms of this Bill will offer the strongest possible encouragement to them to become full owners for the very simple reason that it offers what the Minister for Justice has already referred to elsewhere as the bargain of a lifetime. I also think that the vast majority of tenants will move quickly and will not put the matter on the long finger because this bargain will be available only for the coming five years or so.</P>
    <P>This five-year limit was strongly contested when the Bill was being debated in Dáil Éireann, and a 25-year period was sought instead.  The opposition to a five-year limit is, I believe, mistaken.  That limit is not designed to reduce the State's financial commitment to the scheme.  On the contrary, the time limit may well increase that commitment because it will encourage all tenants to avail themselves of the scheme.  There are good practical reasons why tenants from time to time may wish to acquire the fee simple &mdash; that is, of course, apart from the general desire to be the full owner.  It may be a question of needing freedom from certain covenants.  It may be a question of raising a loan when the lease has less than 50 years to run.  But to wait until these forces operate in the case of all ground leases would not, to my mind, be consistent with a scheme aimed consciously <Col N="266" /> at the abolition of the ground rent system.  The limitation of the State's contribution to applications that are made within the period of five years is designed to introduce the concept of terminating the system, as far as dwellinghouses are concerned.  I think it will work that way too.  What is more, I genuinely believe that, if we were to make the scheme open-ended or have it available for 25 years, that would tend to destroy its potential efficacy.</P>
    <P>I should now like to comment briefly on the various provisions of the Bill and in so doing, to indicate where the Bill differs from the proposals of the previous Government contained in the Bill which lapsed with the dissolution of the last Dáil.  Part II of the Bill deals with the classes of tenant who will be entitled to acquire the fee simple in their properties. Senators will have seen from the Explanatory Memorandum circulated in connection with the Bill that this Part, together with section 26 in Part IV, is intended to be a fully comprehensive statement of the classes which are to have this right as well as of the law relating to the determination of a purchase price.  It consolidates the provisions in this area which are at present contained in the Landlord and Tenant (Reversionary Leases) Act, 1958, the Landlord and Tenant (Ground Rents) Act, 1967 and the Landlord and Tenant (Amendment) Act, 1971.  In addition, it provides for new classes of leases and tenancies which are to attract the right to acquire the fee simple in future and it clarifies the law as to the method of determining the maximum purchase price.</P>
    <P>It is in this part of the Bill that we must face up to the problem of trying to determine what is a ground rent.  Most Senators will be aware by now that there is no statutory definition of a ground rent.  Indeed, this matter was discussed in detail during the passage of the No. 1 Act through this House.  The essential thing about such a rent in the ordinary way is that it arises in a landlord and tenant relationship where the tenant owns the &ldquo;bricks and mortar&rdquo; interest in the property and, for that reason, the ground rent will tend to be a small rent in relation to the value of the entire <Col N="267" /> property.  At the other end of the scale there is, of course, the concept of occupational rent, which is a rent payable when the landlord owns that &ldquo;bricks and mortar&rdquo; interest.  This may appear simple enough at both extremes of the scale.  Unfortunately difficulties do arise in determining whether a rent falls within one class or another in the middle, or grey areas.</P>
    <P>The Landlord and Tenant Acts have since 1931 sought to distinguish between those two types of rents and to provide for the rights of the parties involved as appropriate to each type.  The Acts did this initially by developing the concepts of a building lease and a proprietary lease as the types of leases which were taken to reserve a ground rent as distinct from an occupational rent.  The problem was, however, that as time went by these concepts were found to be inadequate to describe all the types of lease which were found to reserve ground rents.  As a result, in the 1958, 1967 and 1971 Acts new types of leases and tenancies had to be added to the concepts already established in 1931.  The result is, to say the least, a somewhat complex body of law.</P>
    <P>The provisions in Part II of the Bill provide, in turn, for the addition of new classes of leases and tenancies which have been identified as ground rent leases and tenancies.  However, the former practice of adding to the 1931 Act concepts of building lease and proprietary lease is now being abandoned. Instead the Bill sets out all the conditions with which any lease or tenancy must comply if it is to attract the right to acquire the fee simple.  This is of course a very welcome simplification of the law.  I hasten to add that, as far as the substance of Part II of the Bill is concerned, it represents no change as against the provisions which were included in the Bill introduced by the Minister's predecessor except for one extension which was done by way of an amendment during the Dáil proceedings. There is, however, one important change of presentation.</P>
    <P>In the previous Bill, which was, of course, a general landlord and tenant Bill as opposed to a ground rents Bill, <Col N="268" /> there was no single comprehensive statement of the classes of leases and tenancies which would attract the right to purchase the fee simple.  Instead, there was a list of conditions to apply to leases which would attract the right to obtain a renewal of the lease on termination, that is a reversionary lease, as well as a list of conditions applicable to yearly tenants who would have the right to acquire the fee simple.  By way of a cross-reference, the lessees who were to have the right to a reversionary lease were also given the right to acquire the fee simple.</P>
    <P>I think it is perhaps fortunate that this Bill, limited as it is to ground rents, could not adopt the same approach and that a new one had to be found.  To my mind, there is a considerable advantage in doing things the way we have them in the present Bill.  For most people the acquisition of the fee simple will be a matter entirely separate from other landlord and tenant rights, particularly in the context of a State-aided scheme.  Very many people who have no great knowledge of the law will find it necessary to check their leases against the provisions of this Bill.  For that reason it seems to me to be useful that there should be one comprehensive statement of the conditions which must be complied with, and that this should be as simple and readable as it is possible to make it.  Indeed the Bill has been welcomed by residents' organisations in this regard.</P>
    <P>At this stage I do not propose to go into detail as to the classes which are to have these rights.  Such a discussion would be more appropriate for the Committee Stage of the Bill and in that regard, the explanatory memorandum which sets out the categories to be newly entitled under the Bill may be of some assistance.  I should like to say, however, that the general intention behind this Part of the Bill is that all known classes of ground rent tenant should be given the right to acquire the fee simple.</P>
    <P>When I say &ldquo;all known classes&rdquo; I do not want to give the impression that there is anything arbitrary about proposals to extend the right of purchase to new categories of leases or yearly tenancies.  Such proposals have in the past been made only after the fullest <Col N="269" /> consideration and following thorough investigation. In recent years this investigation has been done by the Landlord and Tenant Commission and the proposals in this Part are based on their recommendations.  This is only as it should be, since a decision to move a tenancy from one category to another is not only a technically complex matter but one which affects important property rights.</P>
    <P>I should now like to comment on Part III to which I have already referred as containing the kernel of this Bill, that is, the State's contribution to the purchase scheme.  It is, I think, generally agreed that the main reason why people did not avail themselves to a greater extent of their right to purchase the fee simple under the 1967 Act was the legal costs of doing so.  I think it fair to say that this is acknowledged in the approach which the Minister's predecessor had adopted in the Bill which lapsed.  The proposals in that Bill to introduce a system of transfer by way of a vesting certificate to be issued by a State authority was intended to deal with the problem of costs.</P>
    <P>There are, however, important differences between the approach adopted in this Bill and what we might call Senator Cooney's Bill.  The most important difference &mdash; and one which is an essential feature of the scheme &mdash; is that we are in this Bill telling the tenant precisely how much it will cost him to get his fee simple.  For a transfer by consent the fee will be £5 and no more.  When we were debating the previous Bill we had no idea whatsoever what the intention was with regard to the costs of acquisition.  At no stage was the actual fee to be charged mentioned and this was, indeed, to have been left over for determination in the context of regulations to be made after the Bill had passed.  However, Senator Cooney, as Minister for Justice, did indicate that he did not expect that the fee would be less than £25.  This uncertainty was, to my mind, a serious defect in the Bill that lapsed.</P>
    <P>While the detailed provisions of section 23 in relation to fees will appropriately be discussed on Committee Stage, there is one aspect I should like to mention now.  In the Dáil a comparison <Col N="270" /> was made between the £12 arbitration fee to be charged in this Bill, or £17 in a successful case which leads to the issue of a vesting certificate, and a fee of £2 payable for arbitration under the 1967 Act pursuant to the Circuit Court Fees Order.  The Minister dealt fully with this and indicated how unreal this comparison was but I should like to say, as emphatically as I can, that any comparison of this kind is utterly wrong and misleading.  The true comparison with the fees to be charged under this Bill for arbitration &mdash; which will represent the tenant's only costs of getting the vesting certificate &mdash; can be summarised under five headings of costs for which the tenant is liable under the 1967 Act.  These could include all of the following:</P>
    <P>(1)  the fee of £2 mentioned already which merely covers the application to the county registrar,</P>
    <P>(2)  the tenant's own legal costs, if any, of the arbitration,</P>
    <P>(3)  the immediate landlord's and any superior landlord's costs of the arbitration,</P>
    <P>(4)  the county registrar's costs of the arbitration, if any, and</P>
    <P>(5)  in a successful case, that is where the award specifies that the fee simple is to be conveyed to the tenant, the costs of the conveyance.</P>
    <P>As the Minister pointed out, these costs&mdash;which are all payable by the tenant&mdash;could amount to hundreds of pounds.  The fee of £2 would be only a tiny proportion of them.</P>
    <P>There is another important difference between the scheme now proposed and that of the previous Bill.  It is not merely a procedural point that the task of converting leasehold titles into fee simples is being given in the Bill to the Land Registry rather than to county registrars as was proposed in the previous Bill. Serious doubts had been voiced as to whether a procedure based on county registrars would work.  The view of the Government is that it could not have worked well.  Many problems could have arisen if this job had been given to 26 different offices around the country. This is particularly true since the staff of these offices could not be augmented by the recruitment of suitably qualified <Col N="271" /> persons.  Of course, this has added significance when we are introducing a scheme which will be widely availed of, as I expect it will.  In this context, it would be well to bear in mind that the potential response is of the order of 250,000 applications.  On the other hand, what we are proposing in this Bill must be, from an objective point of view, more efficient and less expensive in real terms.  The Minister has made all the necessary arrangements to ensure that the Land Registry will be properly equipped to carry out the tasks to be imposed upon it under this legislation and I am fully convinced that there is no other institution of the State which could do it as well.</P>
    <P>One further advantage accrues from operating the purchase scheme through the Land Registry.  That is that it will enable close liaison to be maintained with the Registry of Deeds so that purchasers who wish to register their new fee simple titles there &mdash; and purchasers will be given every encouragement to register either in the Land Registry or in the Registry of Deeds &mdash; can be enabled to do so with minimum trouble and expense.  I would like to make it clear that purchasers who do not register will still have a perfectly good title that is not only statutorily guaranteed but that is also already a matter of official record in the register of vesting certificates that will be kept in the Land Registry.  Registration is nevertheless most desirable and indeed close consideration has been given to the question of providing for compulsory registration of the vesting certificates in those cases &mdash; the great majority &mdash; where registration is optional.  The Government's view, however, is that it would be wrong in principle to introduce compulsion here, that is apart from the areas in which compulsory registration already applies, and that the furthest we should go is to give purchasers under the scheme the maximum encouragement and facility to register.</P>
    <P>Some Senators will undoubtedly be aware that there have for some time been arrears of work in the registry and may ask if the addition of new responsibilities will not exacerbate that position. <Col N="272" /> While I realise that the ordinary work of the Land Registry is not directly relevant to the Bill, I think I should explain briefly how it is proposed to deal with the overall situation so that the scheme will be workable, without adversely affecting the ordinary work of the registry.  What has been arranged is that there would be a special addition of staff designed specifically to handle the ground rents work.  In addition, other substantial staff increases in the registry have been authorised to enable the arrears of ordinary work to be disposed of in a reasonably short time.  In fact, I understand that there are already encouraging signs that these measures are having a beneficial effect.</P>
    <P>There remain two important aspects of this Bill &mdash; which were not in the lapsed Bill &mdash; upon which I should like to comment.  The first is the fact that it extends the right to purchase the fee simple to ground rent tenants of local authorities.  The second is the proposal it contains to abolish a landlord's right of re-entry for non-payment of ground rent.</P>
    <P>One of the main criticisms of the Bill which lapsed was that it distinguished unfairly between ground rent tenants in the private sector and those in the public sector.  There were references to making second-class citizens of people who had purchased or who were purchasing their own homes from local authorities by way of leases.  Under the present Bill local authority lessees will, for the first time, have the right to acquire the fee simple.  The procedure will be by way of vesting orders to be made under the Housing Act, rather than by way of the Land Registry procedure under the Bill. The fee payable by the tenant will be £5.</P>
    <P>The remaining point I should like to deal with is the question of the abolition of the landlord's right of re-entry for non-payment of ground rent.  Senators will be aware that leases normally contain a condition that in the event of the rent being in arrears for a specified period, the lessor may re-enter on the lands.  In addition, section 52 of the Landlord and Tenant Law Amendment Act, Ireland, 1860, Deasy's Act, gives the landlord a right to take an action for ejectment where the tenant allows the <Col N="273" /> rent to run into one year's arrears, even if the time for re-entry provided in the lease has not expired.</P>
    <P>One of the criticisms made of the present law is that it gives landlords a security for their rent which is out of all proportion to the size and nature of their interest in the property concerned.  There may have been an argument in favour of the extensive power which this enables landlords to wield when they had a real responsibility for good estate management in the interests of all the tenants. This is no longer so.  The protection of the amenities is now a function of planning legislation.  It follows that the landlord should no longer have a right to re-enter but should be in the same position as any other creditor.  He should have only a right to sue for the debt owed him.  Section 27 of the Bill abolishes the right of re-entry for non-payment of ground rent in the case of a dwellinghouse but leaves unaffected the landlord's right to sue for arrears of rent as a civil debt.</P>
    <P>As Senators are, no doubt, aware this Bill was before the Dáil from early in February until last week.  The lengthy debates in that House were most useful in as much as they resulted in quite a number of amendments.  Some of these were of a drafting nature, others covered points of substance and we can, as necessary, explore them on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>During the passage of the No. 1 Act through this House, the question was raised of instruments which could create a rent charge, as an alternative to the creation of a ground rent, as well as other possible means of evading the prohibition on the creation of future ground rents on dwellinghouses.  This matter clearly is relevant to Part II of the present Bill and it has been examined in that context.  As a result of that examination we are satisfied that the scope of the Bill in respect of ground rents is as wide as the scope of the landlord and tenant relationship itself.  We are indeed satisfied, and satisfied on the basis of the examination to date of this area by the Landlord and Tenant Commission, that this Bill &mdash; and <i>ipso facto</i> the Act prohibiting the creation of ground <Col N="274" /> rents &mdash; does extend to every known form of landlord and tenant arrangement creating a ground rent.</P>
    <P>If new kinds of conveyancing arrangements are devised to evade that prohibition and are brought into use, these arrangements will come under examination and if necessary new legislation can be promoted to deal with them. However, that legislation would not necessarily fall within the code of landlord and tenant law.  Apart from that consideration I feel it necessary to say that concern about the possibility of sophisticated evasions is academic rather than practical.  What that concern postulates is that conveyancing lawyers will sit down and devote themselves to devising means of circumventing the clear intention of an Act of the Oireachtas.  I cannot see why that should happen; I cannot see what is to be gained.  As regards devices like rent charges, in particular, anyone who sought to circumvent the No. 1 Act might be treading on very thin ice.  If his or her new arrangement turned out to be, after all, a lease he or she would have advised his client, as vendor or lessor, very much to that client's disadvantage. The purchaser, instead of paying a disguised ground rent, would have &mdash; under the No. 1 Act &mdash; the right to buy in the fee simple at the lessor's expense.  Finally, uncertainty about the status of any such new arrangement would mean, in practice, that the intending purchaser could not raise loan finance for his purchase, and this would be a deterrent even from a vendor's point of view. Lending institutions are most unlikely to lend money on a security that is at risk of being found to be a nullity.</P>
    <P>I should like on behalf of the Minister for Justice, to take this opportunity of expressing the gratitude of the Government to the members of the Landlord and Tenant Commission and their Chairman, Judge Conroy.  I have already mentioned the part that the Commission have played in regard to the question of determining what classes of lease or tenancy should attract the right to acquire the fee simple.  The work of the commission will also be of the greatest significance in regard to the <Col N="275" /> further Landlord and Tenant Bill which will be required, dealing in the main with occupational tenancies.  The members of the commission are all busy men whose time is devoted voluntarily to the important tasks which have been allotted to them.</P>
    <P>I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to commence by echoing the tribute which the Minister of State has paid to Judge Conroy and the members of the Landlord and Tenant Commission. There is no doubt that they are owed a big debt for all the work they have done in this complex but important legal and economic sphere.  Having said that I fear that my first expression will not be as harmonious because it is to complain at the absence once more of the Minister for Justice.  I make this complaint not by way of reflection on the person of the Minister of State who is present and for whom I have a high personal regard. This is the second Bill exclusively the province of a Minister for Justice and the promoting Minister has not come to the Upper House of the Oireachtas to present it.  Senators will have noted from the script that was handed out that the ostensible reason is that the Minister for Justice was taking Questions in the other House.  When this debate started it was 4.30 p.m. and Questions had finished one hour previously.  The excuse now is a patently hollow and insincere one.  It is regrettable that an excuse so patently insincere and hollow should have been included in the script that was circulated to Members of this House.  It is nothing short of an insult that the House be offered an excuse that is patently untrue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, with respect to Senator Cooney's allegations I should like to make it clear that I did not articulate the first sentence of the script.  I did not do so on the basis that it was no longer relevant.  I am here on behalf of the Minister for Justice.  He has asked me to come here and I do so in my own right on his behalf.  I must say I cannot see what the Senator sees so ill about that.  The Minister has asked me to do it for him and I am doing it for him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="276" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course the Minister was asked as Minister of State. Otherwise he would not be here.  I acknowledge that he did not read out the part of the script that contained the excuse, but nevertheless this is the excuse that is being given; that is the reality of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>At that time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>But when the time had passed making that excuse irrelevant, one would have expected the Minister to be here when the reason for which he was excused no longer applied. However, that is by the way.  I have made my protest.  It is no personal reflection on the Minister of State, but it is a matter of regret that the promoting Minister is not here for this Bill.</P>
      <P>All of us were awaiting this Bill originally with expectation and no less in curiosity to see what was going to be provided, because expectation and curiosity had been aroused that this Bill was going to have some principle that would be radical, that was going to fulfil the spirit of the manifesto.  We were looking forward to radical changes in the whole concept of ground rents in the relationship of landlord and tenant.  We were looking forward to something that was going to change the existing ground rent compulsory acquisition scene.  But what we got, I am afraid, was nothing radical, nothing new, because if this Bill is one to lead to the abolition of existing ground rents, so was the 1967 Act and so was the Bill that fell on the dissolution of the last Dáil.  There is no difference in principle between any of those three Bills.  It was with a great sense of anticlimax that one eventually saw the Bill that was produced.  For some time before the last election there had been a vociferous and persistent lobby demand &mdash; and it is interesting to note that lobby groups do not ask any more, they demand &mdash; radical changes in relation to ground rents and their acquisition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I can speak from experience because I had personal contact with the main lobby group in that area, the Association of <Col N="277" /> Combined Residents' Associations.  It might be interesting for Senators to know what were precisely their demands. They demanded that ground rents be ended.  When it was pointed out to them that ground rents were a property right and could not be confiscated under the Constitution, they said: cannot you have an amendment to the Constitution to enable this to be done?  When it was pointed out to them that there were difficulties in having a referendum on a matter such as that and that there would have to be compensation, they were against compensation, some of them, on the grounds that these rents were immoral of their very nature and the owners of them were not entitled to compensation.  Some of them would not hear of compensation; they insisted on cessation without compensation. It was also put to me at some of these meetings that not merely should the ground landlord not get compensation but that certain ground landlords should be ordered to pay compensation to the ground tenants in many cases where it could be shown that the rent paid by the ground tenant over a number of years would have exceeded what some independent party would regard as having been the value of the property when first leased.  That was the scene and the nature of the demand for radical, revolutionary change.  These people had to be told that what they were seeking was constitutionally, practically and legally impossible, constitutionally impossible because to interfere with one property right would end all property rights.  It was not on as a matter of practice because I felt and still feel that there are greater demands on the Exchequer resources than in some way subsidising the purchase of ground rents.  But that was the demand and the case being made.</P>
    <P>I am aware that these people saw the present Minister, when he was in Opposition, and members of his party.  I do not know what he said to them, but obviously he did not go on the same lines as I had gone.  I am led to believe from various clues, tips of icebergs here and there, that the impression was given to these people that something radical would be given to them.  The Minister, <Col N="278" /> when in Opposition, was speaking in the Dáil in 1975 and it is reported in Dáil Official Report, column 1123 of 9 December 1975:</P>
    <P>It is part of the Fianna Fáil package in relation to the ordinary householder that not only should he be relieved of the burden of rates but also of ground rents.</P>
    <P>That was a clear signal to these people, and to the rest of us, that this was the message he was giving to this lobby group; they were going to be relieved of their ground rents.  It was used in the same sentence as the question of rates. When the manifesto came out and promised the abolition of rates and promised a scheme to lead to the abolition of ground rents the people who had seen the two things linked so publicly by the Fianna Fáil Party assumed that abolition meant the same thing in regard to each subject.  Of course, the small print was there, and the small print is what the clever salesman always relies on.  The small print was &ldquo;lead to the abolition of ground rents&rdquo;.  Nevertheless it had the effect of satisfying the lobby. The Minister deserves, from one politician to another, congratulations on his political opportunism and sleight of hand in managing to convince these people that they were getting what they were demanding.  Of course what they are getting is nothing different from what was already a principle of the law both in the 1967 Act and what was promised in the Bill which fell with the dissolution of the last Dáil.</P>
    <P>It is a matter of amazement to me that the people concerned still have not realised the stroke that was pulled on them.  I find it difficult to understand the reason.  I can only reckon it is for one of two reasons.  One is that they are so incredibly obtuse that they do not realise that what they have been offered here is exactly the same as what they had been objecting to all along.  It is difficult to believe that any group could be that obtuse. Their present silence is due possibly to the fact that the Minister belongs to the party to which he belongs.  However, we now know what was intended by the Minister.  It was an anti-climax when there was an expectation that radical <Col N="279" /> changes were going to be introduced. What we have here, in effect, is the same principle dressed up in somewhat different clothing.  The mechanics are different but the principle remains exactly the same.  I have no objection at all to that because it repeats the principle of the Bill which I was introducing during the course of the last Dáil.</P>
    <P>I shall make a couple of comments on some of the changes proposed in the clothing on the principle.  The Minister is allowing his bargain price, as he describes it, to be available for five years.  In the Dáil I understand he was very definite that it would be only five years and that if people did not avail of it within five years they were back then to buy out under the 1967 Act.  I notice in the course of the Minister's speech today two significant little words, and one must pay attention to the small print, as I have demonstrated, where he says that the bargain will be available only for the coming five years or so.  I would be interested, if the Minister would let us know exactly how long &ldquo;or so&rdquo; means. It is a serious change from the principle set out in the other House.  I do not think it is a good thing to put any limitation at all on this so-called bargain.  It should be available without limitation of time and people should be entitled to avail of the bargain when it suits their own situation or circumstances.  Fees might not arise until after the five years.  If a person is quite content to continue paying his ground rent for a longer period than five years from the passage of the Bill, that is entirely a matter for himself.  The Minister in the other House&mdash;he does not repeat it here&mdash;said that he was not forcing people to buy out the ground rents.  But this raises the question when are people being forced or compelled, and if there is a financial sanction being placed on somebody for failing to do something, then there is an element of force.  The Minister, I think, is compelling people to act or move within the five years when it might not be suited to them.  It is wrong, having introduced the idea of this bargain, that it should have to be availed of within a limited time. That smacks of the Christmas sales that shops run and seems to me to be an <Col N="280" /> altogether inappropriate principle to introduce into legislation.</P>
    <P>The other change in relation to the mechanics is that the vesting order will be made by the Registrar of Titles and not by the county registrar.  This raises the question of the capacity of the Land Registry to deal with a potential avalanche of applications.  The Minister spoke of potential response of the order of 250,000 applications.  If they all have to come within five years, there is going to be literally an avalanche of paper into the Land Registry, 250,000 vesting orders descending on the Land Registry, 1,000 a week and, for an office already stretched, this seems slightly incredible. The Minister in his speech has said that he has made all the necessary arrangements to ensure that the Land Registry will be properly equipped.  I would be anxious to hear precisely what these arrangements are.  I would like to know the number of extra heads of staff, their position, and what procedural changes are being introduced in the Registry to ensure that the whole mechanism of that body does not become clogged with this avalanche of papers that has to be dealt with within the next five years&mdash;one thousand a week if they are spread over the five years; it they all come within the first year or thereabouts, it will be an appalling position altogether.  The Minister said also that other substantial staff increases in the Registry have been authorised.  I would like to know precisely how many extra people are going to be involved and at what level.</P>
    <P>When replying I would ask the Minister to deal with something that puzzled me in his speech when he was speaking of the question of the registration of the vesting orders, I would like him to link that with the requirements of section 22 (3) which provides that:</P>
    <P>(3)  The vesting certificates shall be deemed to be a conveyance of sale ... and to be an instrument in the prescribed form ... for the purpose of registration under the Registration of Title Act.</P>
    <P>I understood that a document of that type does not vest the legal estate until such time as it is registered in the Land Registry, that it merely gives an equity <Col N="281" /> but that the legal estate does not accrue until registration, that is, registration vests the legal estate, not the signing of the instrument and, presumably, not the making of the vesting order.  I would be interested to have the Minister's views on that aspect of the proposed arrangement when he is replying.</P>
    <P>The last thing I want to say is related to something which the Minister mentioned towards the end of his speech when he referred to the passage of the No. 1 Act through the House and various points made, when it was indicated that there were loopholes in the Bill.  I take the point that the drawing of these matters to his attention is somehow resented.  One gets this impression when reference is made to the possibility of sophisticated evasions as being academic rather than practical.  It is the duty of an Opposition to parse a Bill as closely as it can.  If in that parsing potential loopholes are revealed it is a matter for the Minister to show that the parsing is not correct or that the loopholes can be blocked.  I do not think that is merely an academic exercise because we are passing legislation that will be of practical benefit in the lives of citizens. Lawyers will have to deal with it and advise their clients on it in their day-to-day activities.  We have to be in a position to see exactly what is in it.</P>
    <P>This is a Bill which is being passed to meet widespread but not a universal demand for a change in the law.  There would be a substantial number of citizens who are ground landlords, who are perfectly entitled to be the owners of ground rents and who would not be enamoured of the changes which are being proposed here.  If those citizens want to examine the new legislation with a view to evading it that is their perfect entitlement. I do not think they should be able to evade it, because it is our job here to try to pass legislation so that they cannot.  But they are perfectly within their rights to engage lawyers to try to evade it for them if the legislation is not drawn tightly enough.  That is the entitlement of any citizen.  Our efforts to try and tighten up the Bill are not merely efforts at academic games but have a real practical end, that is, to <Col N="282" /> render the Bill, before it leaves here, tight so that it cannot subsequently be evaded by people who <i>bona fide</i>, and correctly if they so wish, are entitled to look to it. The last Bill was just finished in this House when I received a letter from I think the building industry itself raising two points with regard to the previous Bill: (1) the unsatisfactory position of people with contracts for leases or executory leases at the time of the passage of the Bill.  That is a matter we raised here at some length but which was not taken up by the Minister.  The other point raised by the builders' federation was in regard to the question of a person holding land on lease after the passing of the Act but without planning permission at the time of the passing of Act.  It is significant that these people made precisely the same points that we made here and indicated the reason the Bill was faulty in that regard.  These are not points of academic titillation but are matters of practical law.</P>
    <P>This Bill is an anti-climax when one considers the atmosphere, the demands, the winks, nods, half promises and the hints that were being made in regard to those demands before the election.  I do not quibble with the Bill at all because its principle is exactly the same as that in the Bill which fell.  I recognise the child; he is exactly the same child.  It would be wrong of me to complain because his clothing is somewhat different.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>The same father; an unusual situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>The only difference between the two children is that one tells lies.  This Bill, which enables householders to buy out their ground rents, is an excellent measure and must be welcomed, certainly as a matter of principle.  As everybody knows for a number of years certainly the whole question of ground rents has been a cause of considerable public disquiet and all political parties have been anxious to do what they could to remedy the situation. Any change that one tries to bring about in the area of landlord and tenant law is difficult because it is an area of law that is extremely complex.  Indeed there are a great number of areas in our <Col N="283" /> landlord and tenant law that require updating and change.  One hopes that the final Bill in the trilogy of Bills referred to by the Minister of State will be brought before the Houses of the Oireachtas as quickly as possible.  As Senator Cooney has already said the last Dáil, before it was dissolved, had before it a Bill which was a major and comprehensive one in the landlord and tenant area.  This Bill now before us is very largely based on the provisions of the old Bill.  Its principle is precisely the same.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Just on a general point I disagree very much with the idea of bringing in a trilogy of Bills.  In an area like landlord and tenant which is, of its nature, so complex it creates big problems for the future to bring in three separate measures in an attempt to reform the existing legislation when one could bring all the legislation together and bring in a substantial and comprehensive document so that, firstly, so far as legislators are concerned, they be given the opportunity to consider the reforms, not in isolation&mdash;as we have had to do up to now&mdash;but rather in the context of the entire landlord and tenant legal area.  In addition, I noted with some amusement the Minister's remark in his opening address that the purpose of having separate Bills, and particularly the purpose of having a separate Bill for this particular reforming measure, was to enable tenants to read the Bill and understand it themselves.  I ask Senators to look at the Bill and if anybody who has not got a legal background can explain it to me I will get him an excellent job in a solicitor's office.  It is a highly complex, technical Bill.  To expect any layman to be able to read that Bill, as it stands and understand in detail its purpose or whether he will qualify under its provisions is the greatest load of hogwash I have ever heard.  To start with the Bill refers back to existing legislation and, of its very nature, definitions of &ldquo;ground rents&rdquo; of &ldquo;leases&rdquo; or whatever are incomprehensible to a lay person.  I cannot accept that as being a valid reason for introducing three separate Bills where, in my belief, one would have done. Anybody who has a problem in landlord and tenant law of any significance is left <Col N="284" /> in the situation at present where not only to find a solution to his problem or find what exactly is his position in law, but even for definitions, he must go through a number of our enactments.</P>
    <P>It is an area that badly requires complete updating.  I would hope that at some time in the future the Minister for Justice might find the opportunity of having a study group set up, something like the Landlord and Tenant Commission, but a working group set up, to codify all our landlord and tenant legislation.  It is a big job but one that will be worth while and that will prove to be of use not only to legislators and law students but to everybody who has any concern or interest in the area.</P>
    <P>One can think of a lot of areas in which our laws could do with codification. I do not know whether it is our history coming from common law into the type of system we have now, but we seem to have a tendency in Ireland, and certainly in the United Kingdom also for this patchwork legislation.  It is a bad practice and something which we should try to avoid.  The trilogy of Bills now referred to, although none of us has any major argument with the content of any of them&mdash;it is silly not to bring them all together when they could be.</P>
    <P>I might add, in relation to something Senator Cooney said about the defects in Bill No. 1, that even since that Bill was passed a couple of weeks ago I am aware of certain problems that have already arisen under it in relation to people being unable to get bridging finance from their bank and unable to get definite loan sanction from building societies because a building society's concern is the length of time it will take to get in a fee simple.  Oddly enough, in this Bill&mdash;and I propose to examine it very carefully&mdash;I can see a solution to one of the problems that we raised.  The disadvantage we have had is that when we dealt with Bill No. 1 we had no idea what was coming.  There is another Bill yet to come which although it does not directly impinge on the principle of this Bill will, because of its being a landlord and tenant Bill, have consequences, connections and alliances between various of its provisions.  It is a great pity that an <Col N="285" /> opportunity that existed to bring them all together was not taken.</P>
    <P>In so far as the principle of this Bill is concerned, as Senator Cooney has already said, it differs in no degree whatever from the principle of the Bill that died with the last Dáil and, for that matter, to a very large extent is similar to the provisions of the 1967 Act.  I am interested that the opening statement made by the Minister of State contained in the very first paragraphs the defence or the attack against the Opposition that was to be expected.  It is an indication of the weak ground that the Minister recognises he stands on.  His colleague, the Minister for Justice, took the same stand in the Dáil.  It is clear that the Minister for Justice and the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs are both very concerned at people's reaction to this Bill.  There are certainly differences, there are differences that are not substantial in any sense.  There is one difference which can be regarded as an extension which was not in the old Bill. That was the proposal to include local authority lessees under the provisions of this Bill.  I welcome that.  The old Bill was not passed and no one knows to what extent it might have altered before it was passed.  But the fact is that the then Fianna Fáil Party, now Government, knew exactly what was in the old Bill. They knew exactly what ACRA were looking for, they knew that ACRA were dissatisfied with the principle in the old Bill.</P>
    <P>Whilst I accept that the Fianna Fáil manifesto was vague and innocuous, as it was in certain convenient areas&mdash;and it said that Fianna Fáil would introduce a scheme that would lead to the abolition of ground rents&mdash;Fianna Fáil canvassers did not knock on doors and say: we are going to introduce a scheme that will lead to the abolition of ground rents. They said: we are going to abolish ground rents.  Not only did Fianna Fáil canvassers say it but, in newspaper advertisements sponsored by Fianna Fáil and paid for by Fianna Fáil during the course of the General Election, even in my own constituency, a rural one, Fianna Fáil were quite prepared to state the bald facts if returned to office and a list of promises, many of which have not <Col N="286" /> yet been fulfilled, many of which I doubt will ever be fulfilled.  These can be catalogued in time.  Amongst that list appear the bald statement: will abolish ground rents.</P>
    <P>This Bill does not abolish ground rents.  It does nothing more in substance or in principle than the Bill that Senator Cooney introduced as Minister for Justice in the Lower House before the last Dáil was dissolved.  The description Deputy John Kelly has given this Government, as the fraud squad, can be aptly applied to this situation.  This is like the Fisheries thing.  It is like a whole series&mdash;unemployment and so on.  Virtually every one of the substantive promises Fianna Fáil made have been left unhonoured.  But, in this instance, Fianna Fáil have the incredible gall to stand up and defend their position when they know in their hearts and souls what was said at door to door canvassing, what was said in newspaper advertisements and what was intended.  I accept now that the present Minister for Justice knew that he could not introduce such a scheme, but that was not to say that he could not mislead people into believing that he could introduce such a scheme.  I must say that that type of approach, whilst it has worked very well for Fianna Fáil on this occasion, is likely to kick back against them on future occasions because people will be very slow to accept what they hear in election campaign promises from a political party that acted like that in the past.</P>
    <P>Of course the position is that this election manifesto promise&mdash;just taking the manifesto promise itself, that Fianna Fáil would introduce a scheme that would lead to the abolition of ground rents&mdash;apart from the misleading aspect of that or the way it was construed&mdash;I wonder very much whether or not this scheme will lead to the abolition of ground rents.</P>
    <P>The figure given by the Minister is that there are approximately 250,000 potential applicants under this scheme. If they are to apply over the next five years it would mean that there would have to be an average of 1,000 applications per week.  Only time will tell whether that will actually happen, but I am prepared to wager with anybody <Col N="287" /> who wants to take me up on it that there will not be 250,000 applications.  I am also prepared to wager that in 20 years' time, unless some different and very radical legislation is introduced, solicitors and lay people will still be dealing with ground rents problems.  The only way this scheme could be said to lead to the abolition of ground rents would be if it were made compulsory for people to apply.  Of course it is not and it should not.  That is the only way it could be said fairly about this scheme that it fulfils the Fianna Fáil promise.  Enough said about the political promise aspect of it.  We have become used to it already and obviously we will have to galvanise ourselves before the next two or three years have passed.</P>
    <P>Whether the Land Registry or the local county registrar's office is the appropriate office to deal with these applications is a moot point.  From my own experience I would think the local county registrars' offices are operating efficiently at the moment.  They probably have not got the same workload as the Land Registry.  I would prefer to see applications going through the county registrars' offices unless there was a definite commitment to increase the staff in the Land Registry.  The Minister has given that commitment not only in relation to operations under this Bill but also generally speaking.  I welcome that commitment but if there are to be thousands of applications as are envisaged it would be necessary to increase the staff of the Land Registry very substantially indeed. It is most desirable that the staff in the Land Registry should be increased very substantially if only to clear up the arrears of work at the moment.</P>
    <P>In the other House the Minister for Justice referred to the third leg of the trilogy we are to see.  This is in relation to the problem arising at the moment over business leases where one applies for a reversionary lease of a 21-year period and the Circuit Court does not have the power to include provision for rent reviews.  The Minister for Justice said he would have this before the House in a very short time.  That was last February and I should like to ask whether we are likely to see it before the <Col N="288" /> summer recess.  This is causing very serious problems not only for business people but also for judges who recognise a market rent for a business premises as being, for example, £50 a week at the moment, but they have not got the power to allow for a rent review in five or seven years' time.  In order to compensate the landlord they tend to add something extra to the initial market rent.  This is highly unsatisfactory and is causing hardship for business lessees and difficulties for judges and uncertainty in the whole area.  It should be changed.</P>
    <P>It was interested to note the remarks in the Minister's speech about the concern we expressed on this side of the House over the possible creation of future legal instruments to get around the provisions of the No. 1 Act as it now is.  It strikes me that this business about rent charges does not apply at all in a landlord and tenant context but only in a conveyancing context.  I accept that this Bill seems to apply to every conceivable landlord and tenant situation but the point made in the debate on the No. 1 Bill was not that a landlord and tenant situation was not being covered, but that it was a simple conveyancing situation which could allow for a recurring sum to be paid on an annual or bi-annual basis. I will look at it again but quite honestly I cannot see the sense in that.</P>
    <P>The final point I want to raise is in relation to remarks in the Minister's address regarding registration.  I see that registration is most desirable but the Government have decided not to make it compulsory.  I wonder whether the ramifications of this have been fully thought out.  Certainly as matters stand in law, you have a transfer deed, or a vesting order as it will be in this case, signed, stamped or whatever, you have priority, but you have not got priority over somebody who registers before you.  If for one reason or another people did not take steps to have it registered, they could put themselves in a very dangerous position.  Not from any political point of view, but from the point of view of trying to ensure we are not enacting any bad or loose law, I suggest that should be looked at again.  I suspect <Col N="289" /> it is recommended&mdash;and will be recommended again&mdash;to tenants to register their new vesting orders to save costs. Perhaps this is a hidden cost which will be involved.</P>
    <P>Perhaps the Minister would explain this.  If somebody decides to take up the invitation by the Land Registry to have his vesting order registered, will the tenant have to pay any extra cost for having that done?  One way or the other, if the cost is regarded as too high, I would recommend that the Government should sponsor it or subsidise it.  A statement in the debate on the Second Stage of a legal Bill that registration is regarded as desirable but will not be made compulsory is not pleasing to somebody who is involved in the law at any level.  I am sure the Minister would not agree with this as a general proposition unless there is a very sound reason behind it.  I would ask that it be looked at again.  Could the Minister now tell me whether there will be an additional cost on a tenant who chooses to take the sensible course and actually register his vesting order?</P>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill can be contrasted with the other Bill recently passed by both Houses.  That very desirable and, indeed, historic Act put an end to an aspect of the feudal system of land tenure to which there was widespread and well-founded objection. The No. 1 Act has freed the rising generation of house buyers from an institution which, whatever its validity eight centuries ago, had in our own time become an easy legal method for raising pin money.  The No. 1 Act has delivered the correct moral judgment on the system, which is why great interest was displayed in the Government's proposals to abolish existing residential ground rent.  The present Bill purports to discharge a promise given in the election and printed in the national press advertisements providing for the abolition of existing ground rents.  Enough has been said on this matter.  I do not want to take up the time of the House with a fruitless exercise in further semantics about what &ldquo;abolition&rdquo; and &ldquo;providing for the abolition&rdquo; can be interpreted to mean.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Substantially this Bill before us is the <Col N="290" /> 1967 Landlord and Tenant (Ground Rents) Act with admittedly some welcome changes.  Where the 1967 Act laid down that the householder wishing to buy out his ground rent would have to pay both his own and the landlord's costs for the legal fee involved in the transaction, this Bill reduces the legal fee to be paid by the householder to a possible maximum £17.  For the first time, therefore, the householder can compute with fair accuracy what his total outgoings will be in purchasing freehold.  That certainly is to be welcomed.  This Bill continues the compensation clause of the 1967 Act whereby the person purchasing freehold has to pay an amount of compensation to the landlord reckoned according to the yield to redemption on the stock exchange in the latest 15 year national loan.</P>
    <P>Many householders might be unaware that, under the most recent national loan raised since the budget, the multiple to be paid by a person buying out a freehold has risen to 8.34 times the annual ground rent.  If, as is possible, a further national loan is raised at a further reduced interest rate, then this multiple will increase again.  Under the interest rate prevailing in 1967, the multiplier is 13.2 times the annual ground rent.  It is not surprising that many tenants are still dissatisfied with aspects of this Bill.  In fact, it was against the background of the compensation allowed in the 1967 Act that the final ACRA campaign was launched which has been successfully completed to the extent that it contributed very substantially to Fianna Fáil's victory, especially in the Dublin area.</P>
    <P>The only relief householders are to get will come entirely from State funds.  This brings me to the five year limiting clause on the reduced legal fees provided for in this Bill.  Does the minister hope to use the five year limitation as a stick with which to drive householders to avail of the buying out procedure established under the Bill?  Householders were advised in the past that it was not in their economic interest to buy out under the 1967 Act.  Neither is it in their economic interest to buy out under this Bill.  But how can the Minister justify <Col N="291" /> withdrawing the State funding after five years from the householder when this Bill continues the full compensation afforded to landlords for the life of the present Bill?  Is it because five years is the putative life of this Government and a promise of renewal of aid is deemed likely to hold votes on this issue through the following general election?  Putting it brutally, are the lessees to be fooled in one election and insulted in the next?  If the reduced legal fees are honestly intended, then an amendment asking for the deletion of any reference to five years will be accepted so that the Minister's &ldquo;Sale of the Century&rdquo; can continue for the life of the Act.</P>
    <P>It has been said that to abolish ground rents without compensation would be unconstitutional.  In this connection my own sympathies are with those who say the compensation should be on the other foot.  Indeed, Senators will recall reading in their history books that, when Mr. de Valera was introducing the agreement which, in effect, ended the economic war&mdash;a very favourable agreement from the Irish point of view&mdash;his viewpoint was that, if justice were really to be done, the lump sum payable to the British Exchequer should in fact be payable the other way around.  This is analogous to the situation here.  I would not personally be terribly worried about the question of constitutionality, about no compensation being unconstitutional. Nor am I worried about the larger question raised which is that people say, &ldquo;Look, if we move too harshly against ground landlords, we are challenging the rights of property itself.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I am quite willing to support any campaign to abolish, not the rights of property, but the rights of property which are not allied to responsibility.  I remember enough of my indoctrination in Thomism to remember that St. Thomas said that: &ldquo;No man has a right to call anything his property unless he mixes his labour with it.&rdquo;  At any rate, on the view that to abolish ground rents without compensation would be unconstitutional, if we admit that it relates to property, it can hardly be contended that ground rents are property in that sense. Regarding ground rents as I do as a <Col N="292" /> species of robbery, I do not think it can be wrong to abolish them outright but, accepting ground rents as a form of property for the purposes of argument, we must remember that the Constitution speaks of the principles of social justice and gives the right to the State to delimit by law the exercise of the right to private property in order to reconcile their exercise with the exigencies of the common good.</P>
    <P>Ground rent of all the forms of property or alleged property in this State is surely the best candidate ever for the application by the State of this common good limitation on the absolute right of property.  We must remember that such an application would be securing the property rights of householders who have paid more than once for the ground space on which their house stands.  In my own case, I must say it is not the actual money being paid in ground rent, which now with inflation forms such a tiny portion of anyone's total outgoings on property, it is not the actual payment of what is now a negligible sum that is annoying, but rather the fact that ground rent is paid, more and more, not to needy individuals or improvident widows who inherited some property, but to great blocks of anonymous landlords.  I have long resented subsidising my own ground landlord to attend race meetings and to buy mink coats for his wife.</P>
    <P>The proposal which ACRA put up for a tribunal which would operate under the criteria suggested by that organisation seems as fair a system as could be devised to seperate wrong from right on this issue, as well as avoiding the constitutional difficulty which seems to scare the Government and even certain members of the Opposition.  At any rate, if the spirit of this Bill is really to abolish ground rent, rather than simply encourage lessees to buy out their ground rent, the Bill should be so amended as to give a much greater incentive and to remove every possible obstacle from the lessee.  It will not be the job of the arbitrator, in this instance the Registrar of Titles, to arbitrate as between two equal parties who have corresponding equal right and equal obligations.  The onus is <Col N="293" /> very much on the Government to make sure that the lessee gets every favourable interpretation of the Bill.  That is why I would see that certain amendments are necessary if the Bill is indeed to lead to an abolition of ground rents and not simply to be another ineffective measure to encourage the lessee to purchase his freehold.</P>
    <P>Having said that, I welcome one or two provisions of the Bill, in particular the new rights of the council tenants to acquire their freehold which gives them an entirely new right to their property&mdash;that is most laudable as is section 27 (1) which no longer gives the lessor a right to re-enter and take possession of the premises where rent is in arrears. That is long overdue.</P>
    <P>Finally, on the whole, I welcome the Bill, noting that it comes about a century after perhaps the greatest social agitation in this country against landlord injustice. There was in the thirties a followup to the agitation of the rural tenants in the resolution of the annuity dispute.  I like to think of what we are now doing as the final solution to the question of abolishing the rights of property in the 19th century sense of property without obligation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Mr. D. Andrews) David Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Mr. D. Andrews)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am most grateful to the various Senators who have contributed to the debate on the Second Stage of this very radical and far-reaching legislation.  It is the purpose of the Opposition to examine what they consider to be the defects in the Bill but it is quite clear from the tenor and composition of the contributions&mdash;and indeed excellent contributions they were too&mdash;that there is very little controversy about this legislation in the House. Senator Molony said that when he examines the Bill in greater depth he will put down amendments to improve the Bill and make it more watertight, according as he sees it.  I would like to assure Senator Molony and other Senators that amendments will be considered and examined and if they are neccessary they will be accepted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Bill has been given considerable thought.  As I say, the function of the <Col N="294" /> Opposition is to knock certain aspects of it, but one thing they did not knock was the principle enshrined in the Bill.  This brings me on to Senator Cooney's contribution. In Senator Cooney and Senator Molony we are dealing with two men who are solicitors in their own right, who have practices based on their own reputations.  They know the highways and by-ways of landlord and tenant law probably better than most of us and consequently their contributions are welcome.</P>
    <P>On the question of there being no difference in principle between the No. 2 Bill and the 1967 Act, the three main differences are differences in principle.  The State is putting money into this scheme. Local authority tenants should not be seen as second-class citizens.  They are equal citizens under the Constitution with all other citizens and that equality must be seen to be enshrined in our legislation.</P>
    <P>I am surprised that Senator Murphy, with his historian's view of contemporary history, did not refer to the fact that the right of re-entry of the landlord is being abolished, which is a significant social achievement and, indeed, an achievement which has not been referred to by those who wish to criticise the Bill. There we have a number of radical features straight away.  The State is now intervening on behalf of the tenant. Local authority tenants are being included, and the right of re-entry in the event of non-payment of ground rent by the tenant to the landlord is now being abolished.  These are significant departures from existing law and bring up to date the Fianna Fáil concept of social justice based on its natural application.</P>
    <P>Senator Cooney suggested that the Minister had hinted in some way that he will introduce a scheme which will abolish ground rents in the sense of giving no compensation.  Senator Cooney seemed to go into the realms of fantasy and speculation.  He based many of his arguments on what the Minister might have said at meetings with ACRA and other tenant organisations in the corridors of power or in the Fianna Fáil Party rooms.  I was present at quite a number of the meetings with the then <Col N="295" /> Opposition spokesman on Justice, Deputy Collins, and I should like to assure Senator Cooney and any other Senator who might have doubts in that regard that in no way did we misrepresent the situation to these tenants' organisations.  As far as the constituent of compensation or no compensation is concerned, we put them in the picture as to where they stood.  We were not dishonest or irresponsible in that respect. We in no way tried to infer or suggest that we would do away with the landlords's rights which as a citizen he has under the Constitution.</P>
    <P>We pointed out to the tenants' organisations and others who attended numerous meetings when we were in Opposition that landlords had certain rights and that while we could do certain things in relation to ground rents, we could not strip the landlords of their ground rents overnight and not compensate them.  We found this to be unconstitutional and improper in justice.  We are living in a democracy and, if you are looking for something, you have to pay for it.  The sensible approach as projected by Deputy Collins when he was spokesman on Justice to these organisations and other individuals was the approach taken by the then Minister for Justice, Senator Cooney.  We saw the relevance of what he said then, and in no way were we irresponsible in that regard.  While Senator Cooney may be wearing his constitutional purity on his sleeve, I should like to say we were also open in our actions and our attitude to that aspect.</P>
    <P>Senator Cooney suggested that the Minister hinted in some way that he would introduce a scheme which would abolish ground rents with no compensation or payment by the State.  This, of course, is not so.  In his contribution in the Dáil on this legislation the Minister repudiated this totally.  More than that, the residents' associations came out publicly and said they never expected such a scheme, a scheme without compensation. As I pointed out, I was present at these meetings on numerous occasions when we were in Opposition and at no time was an undertaking given as <Col N="296" /> suggested in Senator Cooney's allegations.</P>
    <P>Senator Cooney made all the usual political insinuations which are difficult to take from a man of his accepted standards and high intelligence.  He started off by saying that the Bill was essentially the same type in principle as his Bill.  He then entered into the arena of speculation which is totally unrelated to reasonable argument and logic.</P>
    <P>On the five year limit on the purchase scheme I have to admit that I welcome the view expressed by Senator Molony in this respect.  If he puts down an amendment on the five year limit that may induce us to have another look at it. Senator Cooney referred to a 25 year limit and Deputy O'Keeffe in the Dáil suggested a 25 year limit.  It would be no harm if the Senator put down such an amendment.  I can certainly see the logic of the argument.  It is understandable.  It is important, however, that the Bill should not be open-ended and that is the reason why this five year limit was placed on it.  The termination of the ground rents system must come sooner rather than later.  I do not think the Minister is contemplating an extension of the five year period in the future.  I think Senators would agree that this would postpone action.  On the suggestion that there might be 250,000 possible applications for vesting orders in five years, I do not think 1,000 people a week will rush to the Land Registry with their applications.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>Those were the figures given by the Minister for Justice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not in any way refuting the figures, but I am talking about the practicalities.  The possibility of 1,000 a week is rather remote.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>If it has to be done within five years it is a practical proposition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>Unfortunately life just does not work out that way, and one can be sure that quite a number of people would not accept the Minister's bargain of a lifetime.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="297" />
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>In other words it will not lead to the abolition of ground rents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>Whose fault is that?  It is not my function to give Senator Molony instructions on how he should read it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDeBrun" hpid="Acting Chairman (Séamus de Brún) Acting Chairman (Séamus de Brún)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Séamus de Brún)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister must be allowed to continue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not my function to tell Senator Molony how to run his legal practice.  I am quite satisfied that he has the highest competence.  I am sure that if he was concerned that his clients know about the five-year limit that he should circularise all his clients. It might do him some good and it might do his clients some good.  Indeed, he might be accused of advertising, and that is the danger there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>We would all like to do that but would be afraid of the consequences.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>In an investigation I completed in the Land Registry there were 250,000 applications in five years. That is the responsibility of the&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>How many extra staff?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the five-year limit is because we believe that if it is open-ended it would only encourage people to postpone action. What we sought to make clear is that the time-limit is part of a package which is designed to terminate the ground leasehold system as it applies to dwellings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There was also a suggestion by one of the Senators that there is an element of force or compulsion being introduced by the five-year limitation.  There is no such thing.  This Bill was introduced as an improvement on the existing legal structures in relation to ground rents.  There is no suggestion of force or compulsion, and it is being done as the State sees it in the best interests of those people for whom the legislation is being introduced. We feel that five years is a reasonable limitation.  Senator Cooney referred to <Col N="298" /> the words &ldquo;five-year limit or so&rdquo;.  He wanted the words &ldquo;or so&rdquo; explained.  I assume that in the last couple of months of the five-year period, certain applications will come in and then pour over for another five or six months.  That is really what five years or so means.</P>
    <P>Senator Molony and Senator Cooney mentioned the question of land registry staff.  I understand that the Minister for Justice dealt with this argument in the Dáil.  He pointed out that additional staff are being recruited to do the work arising under the Bill and that separate accommodation is being arranged.  I have had dealings with the Land Registry in my representative capacity over the years.  I am sure the Senators and particularly the practitioner Senators would agree with me that in no way can we criticise the staff for the length of time it takes to deal with certain matters there. It is a criticism of the lack of personnel there to assist the existing staff.  The staff there are excellent and superb people and are most accommodating and cooperative in every respect.  That has certainly been my experience and I know it to have been the experience of other people who have dealt with the staff of the Land Registry.  They are a fine group of public servants in every respect.</P>
    <P>I understand that the officials here have checked on the position in the Registry about its arrears.  There has been a very encouraging improvement in the position over the last few months particularly in respect of first registrations or examiners' cases which constitute the work area and is closely related to the proposed ground rents work.  This trend is expected to continue and as a result arrears should be down to manageable proportions by the end of the year.  The average delay will be down to two or three months, assuming that no violent increase in the flow of applications occurs.</P>
    <P>In respect of the last interjection by Senator Cooney in respect of numbers of staff, there were some 50 extra posts recently sanctioned to deal with the general situation.  I understand that they are in the course of being filled.  I do not want to mislead the Senate.  I am saying that the 50 extra posts recently sanctioned <Col N="299" /> are to deal with the general situation. In advance of the operation of this scheme eight to ten posts have been sanctioned and are being filled for ground rent work alone.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Where will they operate?  In the main registry?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I assume so, until alternative accommodation is found for them.  To return to the question that in some way the opening speech suggests that the Minister for Justice resented the suggestion that people might escape from the effects of this ground rent law by virtue of their superior legal knowledge and they might find some way of circumventing the terms of the Act itself when it becomes law, there is no question of resentment.  That is a figment of Senator Cooney's imagination. He is reading something into it which does not exist.  The Minister in his speech quite clearly makes a statement of fact, no more and no less.  It is a matter of interpretation. If Senator Cooney and myself read the same book we can come up with different criticisms of it.  So I assume that if we read the same speech we would put different interpretations on it. My interpretation of the Minister's very reasonable speech is that it is unresentful. It is a logical statement in relation to what it states.</P>
      <P>Senator Molony asks why there should be three separate Bills.  The Minister is very strongly of the opinion that ground rents are a separate issue.  In this he is fully supported by the tenants' associations.  Senator Cooney seems to be a little bit resentful.  This is my interpretation of what he said of the tenants' associations.  Maybe the tenants' associations did not support Senator Cooney in the last general election. I do not say that in a personal way. I am very sorry to see Senator Cooney losing his seat in the lower House.  I have a personal regard for him and I think he had a very difficult task as Minister for Justice, but that is by the way and not related to the present Bill.  The Minister for Justice is very strongly of the opinion that the ground rents are a separate issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>What was the last Bill <Col N="300" /> about?  Bill No. 1 was ground rents too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you suggesting that the two of them should be incorporated?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be far more sensible if they were all dealt with together.  We have a 1967 Ground Rents Act as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I think you will agree that taken separately the two are quite understandable and comprehensive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>For a lawyer I am surprised to hear you say that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Molony again suggested that if the previous Bill had lasted it might in time have been extended to cover local authority lessees. Again I must come back to Senator Cooney's remarks on the No. 1 Bill. Senator Cooney said here on Committee Stage of the No. 1 Bill that he was personally opposed to letting local authority lessees have the relevant rights.  He also said it in the context of the last Bill.  I say we want local authority tenants in.  Senator Cooney in this Bill and the last Bill did not want them in in any circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Clearly you are outnumbered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>According to Senator Cooney the local authority tenants are second class citizens. Senator Cooney is trying to categorise and interject an element of class distinction into this, and it is a very bad principle.</P>
      <P>Senator Molony makes the point, and I agree with him, that the citizen, the man in the street, reading the Bill could not off the record understand it.  I accept that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the Minister for Justice's argument for actually having a separate Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, no.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>The argument the <Col N="301" /> Minister for Justice gave for having a separate Bill was so that the layman could understand it.  I think it is a very stupid move.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree with you that it was the only argument.  It was one of a series of arguments in relation to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>It was the only one he gave.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not true either.  You can quote me on the Committee Stage.  The arguments I put forward were quite clear and they certainly did not highlight that aspect.  It is difficult for the man in the street to digest the offering on this particular legal plate and comprehend it on one or two readings.  It would probably need a number of readings in addition to the assistance of a competent legal advisor.</P>
      <P>Senator Molony then gave us an insight into Fianna Fáil canvassers during the last general election by saying that people knocked on the door saying that Fianna Fáil would abolish ground rents. I led a lot of canvassers in my own constituency and, unless Senator Molony has some inside information that he is not telling us about, Fianna Fáil canvassers were very responsible in relation to the ground rent campaign and they quite clearly stated what was in the manifesto. They were carrying around this bible with them.  If anybody asked them what they had to say about anything the leader of the canvassing group would produce this excellent document and refer to it and read it out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps it needed interpretation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>You were not around at the time, Senator Murphy, with great respect, or I probably would have sought your interpretation at the time.  But it did not need interpretation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>How about the newspapers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDeBrun" hpid="Acting Chairman (Séamus de Brún) Acting Chairman (Séamus de Brún)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Séamus de Brún)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister of State is to continue <Col N="302" /> without interruption, please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>Now I refer to the fraud squad.  Deputy Kelly referred to the present Government and the manifesto. Perhaps Senator Molony can help me on that one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>The fraud squad.  I am sure Deputy Kelly should know something about frauds and squads.  He was the Chief Whip, after all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>So were you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I was referring to the qualifications, Senator.  He was a Chief Whip of the Coalition Government and he was also Attorney General in the Coalition Government so he should know a little about these things.  I am not reflecting on Deputy Kelly's personal integrity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>He will have to wait for his opinion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I never sought his opinion.  In regard to the argument of the Land Registry versus county registrars, the staff of the Land Registry includes officers who are engaged full time in the scrutiny of titles and who require a knowledge of conveyancing work and all its complexities.  The qualifications required for arbitration under Part III of this Bill are more abundantly available in the Land Registry than in any other Department of State or office of the public service.  In fact it may be contrasted with county registrars' offices in this regard.  In such offices it is simply not possible to recruit qualified staff to carry out the arbitration functions where the county registrar could not deal with all cases.  The Circuit Court offices are staffed by general service civil servants.  There is no way in which higher staff would need qualifications to be recruited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a matter which I should put right on the record.  It is in relation to the accommodation of newly recruited staff dealing with ground rents.  The accommodation is going to be separate.  I misled <Col N="303" /> the House on that.  I thought they would be working in the same office.  I understand that that is not so.</P>
    <P>Senator Molony mentions the third Bill.  I cannot tell Senator Molony what is in the third Bill.  I do not know.  The Minister for Justice, whilst aware of the definite outlines, has not finalised it.  It is hoped that the Bill will be introduced before the end of this Seanad session.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister is not coming up here maybe he could do that one concurrently in the other House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be a very complex piece of law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>All the more reason we should deal with it early.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel that law should be dealt with in the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what I am saying. It could be introduced in the Dáil while Deputy Andrews is up here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to Senator Molony's remark, the Minister is very much aware of the problems arising out of the Supreme Court decision in relation to the rent on the 21 year renewal leases where no rent reviews are possible.  This gives an urgency to the proposed Bill and the possibility of amending the law in this respect.  The cost of registration of the vesting certificate of the Registry of Deeds will be £4.  The cost of first registration of a house valued £20 in the Land Registry will be £5.50.  The cost of transfer from the leasehold register to the freehold register of a house with a ground rent of £10 will be £2.90.  The cost of registering a fee simple of a house valued £20 on registered land will be £5.60.  A map would be required only in the second example, that is the first registration in the Land Registry, and that would have to be paid for by the applicant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator John Murphy in his very strong and ultra-nationalistic speech made a very strong attack on landlords. I would like to remind Senator Murphy that landlords have their rights too.  In all <Col N="304" /> circumstances they have to be treated like other citizens before the law.  Whilst it is all very well to become emotional about it, we are bound by the Constitution which was given to us by the people. We have to apply it to all citizens.  I understand that Senator Murphy has a very strong national sense of history.  It is an approach to history which is peculiarly his and he is entitled to it.  I do not make any criticism of it.  But one must see his contribution in that light.</P>
    <P>In relation to Senator Murphy's question about the eight and a half years' purchase, the most recent appropriate Government loan on which to base a current example for the purpose of the Bill is the 11½ per cent development loan 1997 to 1999 issued in February 1978. The price at which this is currently available, 15 May 1977, offers a yield of 12.4 per cent and the maximum purchase price of a £10 ground rent would accordingly be £75 or seven and three-quarter years' purchase.</P>
    <P>There is nothing more I have to add.  I am grateful to the Senators.  We have done our best to produce a Bill which has no defects but if they feel that any aspect of the Bill might be loose, for the sake of improving legislation as they might see it, we would welcome an examination of any amendments they might consider necessary.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it be in order for me to ask a very brief question of the Minister?  The Minister mentioned that the abolition of the landlord's right of reentry was a very serious step.  I would like the Minister to tell the House the last occasion on which the landlord's right of re-entry was ordered by a court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not answer that offhand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidMolony" hpid="Mr. Molony Mr. Molony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Molony</NameTxt>
      <P>It will do on Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Mr. D. Andrews Mr. D. Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Andrews</NameTxt>
      <P>I can see what the Senator is getting at.  The Senator is not so much concerned about when it happened but as to the principle involved.  I will certainly make every effort to have the information available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="305" /> Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage ordered for Thursday, 1 June 1978.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Business suspended at 6.25 p.m. and resumed at 7 p.m.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="White Paper on National Development:" RHead="Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>White Paper on National Development: Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann takes note of the Government's White Paper on National Development, 1977-1980.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash; (Senator E. Ryan.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardConroy" hpid="Professor Conroy Professor Conroy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Conroy</NameTxt>
      <P>We have reached the point of discussing social issues in relation to the National Development Plan.  The Senator who was speaking before me was emphasising one particular aspect of social issues, the absence of it from the plan, and was commenting that there are a lot of things that both sides of the House would like to do, that if we have not the necessary economic situation it is not possible to provide all the social services which we would like.  Nonetheless, in the White Paper we do have references to education, health and social welfare services generally.  There is one aspect which comes in the national plan, in particular, to the priority which we have or should have&mdash;that the question of employment and the opportunities and prospects for our school leavers.  Section 7 of the plan points out that the Department of Education estimate that the number of pupils in national schools will increase by almost 5 per cent from 536,066 in 1976-1977 to 563,000 in 1981-1982. That is over half a million in primary schools.  At secondary level there is reference to a total of 310,000, allowing for a 10 per cent increase.  Then we come to the third-level education and there is a figure of 45,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a major point here about the developments and the progress which we had in the sixties, a point which I think is overlooked to a very considerable extent. We did have increasing employment and prosperity in the sixties.  We did have many improvements.  One of <Col N="306" /> the factors which was of crucial importance in relation to employment, and which tends to be overlooked, is that we had a vast increase in the number of children who had the chance to go to secondary school, to get a secondary education, shall we say, so as not to get confused between the various types of secondary education.  This had an immediate direct effect in that you now had children who had an opportunity to get education which preceding generations did not have.  This in itself had a direct effect.</P>
    <P>It also had two other effects.  One of these is one which can only be postulated, but it is probably true that having had a secondary education, having stayed that few years longer in the country, the children and people concerned were, perhaps, less likely to leave. Certainly it had the important social implication that one did not have the tragic horrific scenes of young Irish children of 14 and 15 arriving in places like London and Liverpool with literally no jobs and literally no education, which I think was one of the most appalling tragedies and disgraces of previous years.  With the increase in secondary education, one also had a considerable increase in the level of education of the population.  This has already been of very significant importance in relation to the type of modern industries which we have and were able to succeed in attracting during the sixties. It is extremely important for industrialists who are concerned with establishing industry to know that we have a population which has a certain level of education.  This situation had double effect. One, the children had the secondary education, they were occupied by it, they had better opportunities.  Two, the mere fact that they were educated to secondary level made it more attractive for industries with a higher technological basis to come to this country.</P>
    <P>One of the aspects which we must emphasise in the late seventies and eighties is the third-level sector.  I say third-level sector because we must include all elements and, in particular, emphasise the technical and the technological aspects.  We had had for far too long a post-colonial hang-up on <Col N="307" /> the idea that third-level education of the right sort is a baccalaureate in arts. Indeed, it was tragic until recently to hear quite eminent people in certain of our colleges and higher institutions talking about a university as though the key of the university was its arts faculty.  I do not deny that it is a very important part, but that was a Victorian British concept. The top-class universities tended to have a far more specific professional basis to them.  In the post-war years we have had remarkable developments in technological universities.  I must say one of the most advanced, impressive and excellent that I have visited was in Hanover, which consists of a medical school, technological engineering and related professional training trend of excellent standard which we could well copy.</P>
    <P>Therefore, I would suggest that an important part of our planning over the coming few years should be an emphasis on third-level education with a technical and technological bias.  Not only do I think that this would be very important directly to the people involved who would have this opportunity, but, quite frankly, it is essential for us if we are to continue to attract the sort of industries with potential, computer-based industries and so on, which we need if we are going to maintain any sort of competitive edge.  Let us face it, there is no way in which we can compete solely on the basis of low incomes.  We have to compete on the basis of having technology, having the modern equipment, of using it to the fullest extent.  To do that we must have people who are able to manage, work and operate in such circumstances.</P>
    <P>There is another social issue, and one which I would regard as the most important of all, and that is specifically the question of employment.  Basically, this is what we should have as our absolute priority over the coming few years.  This is basically what our national development should be over this few years.  I think we have to be very careful to make sure that we keep this in the forefront of our minds.  I am afraid that there is a definite danger and very good arguments will be put forward.  Unfortunately, and one must say this, one got this impression <Col N="308" /> from one of the Senators speaking at the previous debate, that questions of financial orthodoxy, very good arguments of financial orthodoxy, will be allowed to take precedence.  I am not saying that financial orthodoxy is not very important or that financial probity is not very important.  Of course we must take cognisance of it, but it is not or should not be our first priority to consider balancing our national budget, to consider the degree of our national debt, to consider the degree to which our trade balances or imbalances are developing. Obviously we must take it into account. It may well be that, from time to time, very severe financial measures will be necessary in order to maintain employment, but let us not in any sense put the cart before the horse.  The financial measures should take second place to the employment measures.  That is what must come first.</P>
    <P>The suggestion of financial precedence is also coming to us from the EEC.  I think the EEC Commission have recently made some comments in this direction.  We have to be very firm about this in our relationship with the EEC, make it very clear to the EEC that our primary problem is that of employment and employment opportunities for our school leavers.  It is not a question of the precise financial balances which we may happen to have or may not have.</P>
    <P>I am very sorry to have to do this, but one must take some degree of difference with Senator Whitaker.  May I preface that by emphasising my great admiration for the tremendous work which Senator Whitaker has done.  There is no doubt that, as far as I am concerned, at any rate, he is very much the prophet of the fifties &mdash; the man who paved the way and put forward the plans for our previous development.  I am sure that it is not really his intention, but I am afraid that what is tending to come across through the media is an emphasis on finance and the idea of employment is getting slightly lost.  This could be a very dangerous and, if I may be permitted to say so, a pernicious emphasis.</P>
    <P>Senator Whitaker referred approvingly to Dr. Kieran Kennedy and I should like to refer to the book which Dr. Kennedy <Col N="309" /> and Brendan Dowling have written. I am referring, to <i>Economic Growth in Ireland: The Experience Since 1947.</i> Chapter 111, page 48 reads:</P>
    <P>If the amount of public discussion on a subject were taken as an index of its importance, then the state of the balance of payments and the behaviour of prices would seem to be of overwhelming importance in the post-war Irish enonomy.  Maintenance of the external and internal value of the currency are, of course, legitimate areas of concern in economic policy. But the priority accorded, particularly in the 1950s, to the preservation of external balance seemed disproportionately greater than concern for output and employment.</P>
    <P>That was the financial orthodoxy of that time, this tremendous concern with that particular aspect of financial matters. Now I fear we are turning towards a matter that Senator Whitaker mentioned, and he is absolutely correct to mention it, that is, the question of the inordinate volume of public indebtedness. Senator Whitaker suggested that this might rise to a figure of about £500 million by 1980 and, of course, I would not dream of attempting to contradict his figures.  At the same time, we really have to remember that in the White Paper, first of all, we do take cognizance of these financial features and on page 84, in relation to public expenditure priorities, it is stated that in formulating policy changes to moderate the growth of public expenditure the Government will give first priority to expenditure directed at enlarging employment and maintaining existing employment in the directly productive sectors of the economy.</P>
    <P>I am sure that Senator Whitaker is aware of this, but I must point out that that is really what we are doing.</P>
    <P>I should also like to refer to some facts and figures about our financial situation, and I am taking these from the 1978 edition of the <i>OECD Observer</i> which is the 14th year of it.  Our total official reserves, as of the date quoted here, which was 31 December 1977, in millions of US dollars were 2,372.  To put that in perspective, this considerably <Col N="310" /> exceeded the figure of Denmark which was 1,670, and was virtually equal to Australia, a much wealthier country than we are, standing at 2,383.  Admittedly it does not compare with countries like Switzerland, the United States and so on, but it is still a very satisfactory position.  On the other hand if we take our private consumption expenditure <i>per capita</i>&mdash; again, there is a slight suggestion here that in some sense or other we were spending too much or something or other of this nature &mdash; the total amount as at current prices in US dollars was 1,580, which was lower than a very poor country such as Greece, which was lower than Italy, which was scarcely above that of Portugal.</P>
    <P>We on this side of the House would disagree very much with people on the far side of the House in regard to capital formation.  We consider that capital is one of the things that we urgently require. Measures taken by the previous administration, unfortunately, had a most pernicious effect in that direction, and it is essential that we have capital. But one must point out that our gross fixed capital formation taken as a percentage of gross domestic product at current prices came to 24.5, which was considerably above that of Italy at 20.3, or Greece at 21.5 or Denmark at 21.5. Admittedly it is far below certain countries such as Japan and so on. Nonetheless it is still a relatively high and good rate of fixed capital formation. So let us not over-emphasise our financial poverty or indebtedness.</P>
    <P>Senator Whitaker referred to the Central Bank, and he is perfectly correct and proper to make a reference to it. Can we cast our minds back just a little bit to the time when we were having the advances of the sixties and there was one hiccough during the period of that advance, a hiccough in 1966?  Again, I quote from the authors whom Senator Whitaker has referred to, Dr. Kennedy and Brendan Dowling.  On page 233 they point out that:</P>
    <P>The only serious set-back to the expansion of total output occurred in 1965-66.</P>
    <P>On the following page they go on to say:</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="311" /> Action to check demand was initiated about the middle of 1965.  In May 1965 the Central Bank advised that the rate of credit expansion should be decelerated and that priority should be given to loans for productive purposes,...</P>
    <P>The following paragraph reads:</P>
    <P>In retrospect, it appears doubtful whether a cut back in public investment was necessary.</P>
    <P>We have to be terribly careful that we do not again start to listen to well intentioned statements but statements which, no matter how much praise they happen to get in financial circles in London, New York, Zurich or in financial circles anywhere else, or what halos we may put around ourselves in relation to our extremely satisfactory financial standing in world circles, what matters and what should come first, within reasonably prudent financial limits, is employment. That is what must come first.</P>
    <P>In regard to planning in general, with great respect to him, I must say I found Senator Whitaker's speech rather extraordinary, and vague and even confused in certain aspects of it.  I quote from Volume 89, column 185 of the Official Report:</P>
    <P>Let me first make it clear, however, should that conceivably be necessary, that I am not against planning in the sense of a comprehensive and coherent programme of development. Indeed, I have been complaining for years about the absence of a plan and I warmly welcome the early restoration of planning by the present Government.  The question of what Department should be in charge of planning has now been resolved and I have no more to say about that.  A much deeper question remains to trouble us all &mdash; whether we have the kind of society in which planning is relevant.</P>
    <P>I find that an extraordinary statement. When I was last speaking on this subject I quoted the excellent book which Senator Whitaker wrote as a relatively young man on credit creation.  That <Col N="312" /> book was written a long time ago, but perhaps one can come back to the seventies and quote from a speech of Dr. Whitaker's which was printed in the journal of the Institute of Public Administration of Ireland, Vol. 25, No. 3 of 1977.  The second paragraph on page 288 reads:</P>
    <P>Plan A Supreme Policy Document</P>
    <P>First, let me indicate what I think a plan should be in a democratically-governed country.  It should be a complete and internally-consistent statement by Government of the policies and actions to be followed in order to achieve specified objectives of an economic and social character.  It is, in my view, the supreme policy document of the Government in power. For that reason, the basic plan should appear very early &mdash; within the first year &mdash; of the term of office of any Government, its life should coincide with the normal four to five year life of a Government, and the degree to which the plan's objectives are achieved should be the foremost measure of the success or failure of a Government's economic and social policy.</P>
    <P>I am afraid I agree wholly with that statement.  I find it a little hard to relate it to his speech here the last time we were debating the subject.  He goes on to say:</P>
    <P>It is, I believe, indispensable to good management &mdash; and therefore, to good Government &mdash; and it can, through its combination of realism, dealism,&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>To my astonishment last week, Senator Whitaker was criticising idealism.  We need a lot more in this country, not a lot less.</P>
    <P>&mdash;&mdash;equity and purpose, be a strong community&mdash;binding force and a generator of the confidence and cooperation needed to achieve difficult goals.  Our experience shows that the psychological factor can, at times, be the most powerful factor of production.</P>
    <P>That is something for all of us to bear in mind.  The psychological factor is very important and it is not necessarily <Col N="313" /> helped by the sort of speech that we had last week.</P>
    <P>Senator Whitaker's own study on economic development, which was correctly lauded by Kennedy and Dowling, lauded for a number of different aspects, goes on to say, and I quote from page 254:</P>
    <P>And the overwhelming achievement of <i>Economic Development</i> was in dissipating the prevailing pessimism, even before recovery from the economic depression had begun.</P>
    <P>What an optimistic attitude prevailed at that time in the midst of so much pessimism. I would be very, very sorry if the prophet of the fifties were to become the Cassandra of the seventies.</P>
    <P>There was one further point, and it epitomised the very grave serious divergence between financial theory and the realities of life, and this was the reference to Santa Claus.  I suppose most of us smiled and I suppose that most of us could afford to smile at the reference to Santa Claus not calling.  If you are really out of work, if your father really is unemployed, if you have given preference to all these excellent financial plans and references to national development, have given them priority, and the effect is that the father of a family is out of work, the children do not see Santa Claus very often in most circumstances.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>I am disappointed that the Minister himself is not here to listen to the debate.  I might add that under normal conditions and if we were discussing agriculture we would be extremely delighted to be talking to the Minister of State.  As far as this debate is concerned the relevant Minister should be here, and I was given to believe that he would be here after 7 o'clock.  Considering his opening remarks about the importance of this White Paper I find it inconceivable that he is not here to listen to it.  There is not much point in having a debate on this topic if the man primarily concerned with it is not here to listen to it as he said he would welcome all views and details of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like to preface my remarks by referring to Senator Conroy's contribution. <Col N="314" /> I thought for most of the time that Senator Conroy was not speaking on the White Paper but on Senator Whitaker.  It led me to believe that he would like to say out straight that he did not particularly like what Senator Whitaker said, but would not like to say a thing like that out straight.  He is right and he is wrong at the same time.  The very sensible argument made by Senator Whitaker was what we were pursuing when in Government.  It must be fairly difficult for the present Government to swallow what Senator Whitaker has been saying.  I agree that it is a fine thing to have open discussion, and we welcome that from all sides.  I certainly thought that we had a very pronounced and dedicated debate on Senator Whitaker, and it is a pity he was not in the House to hear this type of contribution.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardConroy" hpid="Professor Conroy Professor Conroy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Conroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I informed Senator Whitaker, before the House met, that I would be expressing this criticism and I would make that clear to the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulConnaughton" hpid="Mr. Connaughton Mr. Connaughton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connaughton</NameTxt>
      <P>We make the point for and against, primarily against, but not in public.  Just before the last general election, Mr. Colley, when interviewed on television on more than one occasion, gave the example that the economy at that time was like an aeroplane on its way down the runway, that it was taxiing along, and what was vital and necessary at that stage was a huge injection of capital to ensure that it got smoothly off the ground.  It got the injection of capital.  It got £831 million to be exact, more than the economy got at any other time in our history.  I suggest that the aeroplane never took off.  I suggest that if we are not careful it will do worse than that, it will soon grind to a halt and with it, to use the parallel, an awful lot of money that this country does not actually own.  We had to borrow that £831 million and we have to pay it back.  It will have to be paid back by every citizen in one way or another.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We borrowed that money, we were told, to do a number of things.  We borrowed it to provide badly needed extra employment, to increase productivity and to reduce inflation.  Inflation is certainly reducing but I should like to make <Col N="315" /> it clear that it is reducing everywhere else as well, particularly in Great Britain with whom our economy is reasonably well linked.  There is no credit due to anybody for that.  I believe that the way the present position is, it might be as low as we are going to see it for this year.  In fact, some economists are on the point of saying that we might have a slightly increased inflation rate at the end of this year.  All economists are not happy with the amount of money we borrowed.  The Green Paper when published will be more to the point than the White Paper is and it will give us a better idea of where we are going.</P>
    <P>This £831 million did not cure all our ills.  We all know the benefits of the budget: we did not have to pay our car tax but we paid double insurance a few months later.  We have had more than 130 price increases &mdash; I believe it is near to 150 now &mdash; and that is not generally known.  Those increases come at a time when we were supposed to be levelling out.  We had several price increases about which the Government were not in a position to do anything.  However, worse was still to come.  During the 60s and into the 70s at least one of the boasts we had was that we were providing employment for all our people. In the last couple of months the dirtiest word in my opinion in the English language, &ldquo;emigration&rdquo;, has crept in. Unfortunately for everybody it appears from the short, medium or long-term plans of the Government that a certain number of our people will have to emigrate.  Nobody can put a figure on it at present or say whether it is 10,000 or 15,000 but it is a considerable number of people.  It is a trend I would not like to be part of at any time.</P>
    <P>Another important question in direct relation to the White Paper is: how many people are out of work here at present?  Are more out of work now than at this time last year?  Have we a different method of calculating the live register?  I was led to believe by the then Opposition last year that we had 170,000 people out of work.  I have been told that at present it is officially 112,000 but we certainly did not create that number of jobs.  I am of the opinion that <Col N="316" /> the number of jobs created in the last six or eight months would be about enough to counteract the redundancies plus no more than a few thosand.  That was for an investment of £831 million.</P>
    <P>Senator Brennan in his contribution last week said he is not an economist &mdash; I am not an economist; I was not trained in that business &mdash; and he directed his views to the ordinary people and said that all one has to do is to ask them about the economy to see the beam on their faces.  He must be like the ostrich in the sand; he only saw the people he wanted to see.  While a certain section of our community benefited greatly by the Government our boys and girls who left school last year cannot be too happy, and the boys and girls who are about to leave this summer will be less happy.  No matter what Government are in power the question of employment is a very difficult one for them.  It is something that should not be made into a political football. Any young person reading the Fianna Fáil manifesto last year would be led to believe that his problems were over but on reading the White Paper one can see that the problems are still there. In my opinion they are getting worse.</P>
    <P>Another important factor in the White Paper is our rate of growth, predicted to be 7 per cent.  Most economists and commentators now suggest that that will be about 5½ per cent.  That is a big and important difference as far as the benefits of the budget are concerned.</P>
    <P>Dr. Whitaker mentioned the changing realities since the manifesto.  I contend that the realities were there all the time and the primary objective of whatever Government was in power was to get our own people back to work here.  If the next document being prepared on the subject by the Government is not more specific than the White Paper we will have despair all round.</P>
    <P>I noticed in the White Paper that agriculture comes in for very little comment. It is important if we are to do what we would all like to, that the agricultural sector must be given a chance to contribute more.  At this stage there are too many acres of land lying unproductive. Several million pounds should be <Col N="317" /> pumped into structural arrangements of farms.  Land drainage, which we hope is on the way, is an important scheme.  We hope that processing agricultural products will create more sustainable long-term jobs.  I hope the Green Paper will dwell on and give a clear commitment to this.</P>
    <P>On a number of other issues relating to the White Paper and promises made one could not but be upset about the industrial unrest here in the last five or six months.  One must ask the question: where does the fault lie?  For any period of five or six months in the history of the previous Government, the incidence of strikes and closures would not have been as great.  Where does the fault lie?  I am not blaming the Government but somebody must be at fault.  If we are to pull our weight in Europe on an industrial arm we must do something about our industrial relations.  What happened about the proposed industrial development consortium of which we heard so much?  Certain commentators suggested at the time that it was going to do lots of things but I have been told that it met only three times since it was inaugurated&mdash;I am not sure if that is the correct figure&mdash;but if that is anything like the correct figure it is close to inactivity. What happened the Export Credit Finance Corporation?  We have not heard a lot from it.  Is the Employment Action Committee on which we pinned such great hopes doing enough?  If there is to be a future for our young people whatever is necessary for this committee by way of finance and legislation should be given to it.</P>
    <P>I am not at all impressed by the results to-date, and I am perturbed about the number on the live register. The number of people employed between this time last year and now is very small.  I shudder to think what will happen when the school doors close in one month's time and all our students come on the employment market.  The National Manpower offices around the country will have their busiest season ever.  I hope the Minister for Economic Planning and Development, Deputy O'Donoghue, will be as good as his word.  It is not a political matter at this <Col N="318" /> stage, and that is why I find it difficult to understand why he is not here to listen to a debate which he termed to be important.</P>
    <P>We are a small nation with a huge national debt.  At a time when our economy was improving we poured our money into a situation that led to a certain type of individual getting richer and a greater number of people coming out worse.  I hope that when we get the Green Paper more positive action will be taken and that we receive from the Government the type of promises we were led to believe they could deliver only 10 months ago.  I will be the first to congratulate any Government that will get our young people back to work, no matter who they are, but I am afraid from the way they are shaping that it will not be the present Government.  Our national debt will be so high and the repayments so large that those who will be around next budget day will get a greater shock than they got last budget day when so many goodies were given out.  If we got our people back to work by those incentives that would be all-right, but the point I am making is that we spent over £800 million in a number of specific directions but we have not got a return for it yet.  Economists are saying that we are not likely to.  If that is the case and if we have over-borrowed the Seán Citizen of Ireland will have to pay. When budget time comes around there will be a fair amount of fleecing.  The majority of our people will be of the opinion that Senator Whitaker's philosophy will certainly be the best one.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CLambert" hpid="Mr. Lambert Mr. Lambert">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lambert</NameTxt>
      <P>Whilst one might agree with Senator Whitaker that this first White Paper on National Development is a mirror of the election manifesto those of us in the private sector were glad to see that the election promises and policies were confirmed in a document which clarifies the Government's purpose in establishing the framework by which longer-term plans and activities can be motivated.  The next step which we appreciated was the identification of the incentives for Irish industry granted under the budget, and there can be no doubt that the private sector is responding as is evidenced in the <Col N="319" /> buoyancy within our economy at the moment.  It does, however, take time to adapt to the new and more encouraging circumstances, to recast internal budgets and current corporate plans and to plan the implementation of revised policies in accordance with the more favourable opportunities which are being made available.  Furthermore, I must remind the House that for the first 55 years of our national independence, the private sector has had to operate in an environment that has been fraught with misunderstanding and a lack of appreciation by most politicians of the practical problems which have confronted private enterprise and, in particular, Irish manufacturing industries under continuously changing circumstances.</P>
      <P>In my short sojourn in the House I have listened to many disparaging references to the private sector which I consider unfair and lacking sensitivity towards the practicalities of operating under a competitive enterprise system. In my opinion, the basic reason for many negative comments is that we are an agricultural community and that the inherent attitudes of the majority of those who have entered politics over the years from all over the country have quite naturally been influenced by a rural background in one form or another.  This empathy, together with the superb lobbying and expertise of the farming confraternity in managing the news media, account for a certain bias against those operating in other economic activities.  I am the first to admit that Irish business and Irish industry as a total entity has not been able to communicate adequately over the years the important part which it has played, and must play, in our national development, and this deficiency is even more obvious to me since I entered the periphery of politics.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is a fact that communication is improving and that both Governments have listened more alertly to the voice of industry in recent years, as evidenced in the fact that, in the past year or so, no one can dispute that a full realisation has emerged of the necessity to generate <Col N="320" /> wealth through production and processing of goods before it can be spent, and at long last there is a growing awareness of the need to initiate a more encouraging environment in which the manufacturing sector can develop and expand its output.</P>
    <P>Looking back 30 years to the post-War period, or the post-Emergency period as we call it, I can recall my own experience of working in a traditional industry of national significance which has survived despite the problems which bedevilled the Irish private sector.</P>
    <P>Before the War we were exporting all over the world.  However, this initiative was disrupted during the Emergency period, and in 1947 when the possibility of resuming exports emerged, the Irish Government refused us permission to use whatever ingredients were available for any of our products to be exported, ordaining that the home market must be supplied first.  This policy was obviously a result of the large post-War credits owing to our agricultural community.  Our neutrality probably accentuated the isolationist policy which dominated the 1930's.  At any rate, the economic necessity to export was not foreseen at that time and we all lived in a fool's paradise.</P>
    <P>Incidentally, the various Irish distillers suffered from similar Government restrictions, and this accounts for exports of Scotch whisky getting off to a much faster start than Irish whiskey in America after the War.  However, even more frustrating was the fact that from 1948 to 1956 the private sector was price controlled and then profit controlled during the period of rapid inflation, which meant that by 1956 Irish industry was still trying to operate within an unbalanced price structure and to a profit standard set by the Government years before.</P>
    <P>I bring these historical facts to the notice of the House in order to recall how Government controls at that time stifled growth, precluding us from making enough profits to provide for replacement of machinery at inflated prices, never mind planning for modernisation or expansion.  Throughout the depressing fifties political bias was still strongly orientated towards agriculture, to such an extent that many private businesses <Col N="321" /> failed during that period and many of our best brains had to emigrate through lack of opportunities.  By 1957 we had had eight years in Limbo compared with British industries, whose automation and growth bounded ahead during those years due to the type of incentives to modernise and expand which now are being introduced here.  Not until 1958, when Seán Lemass saw the light and gave Irish industry a lead in the first economic expansion programme, were we able to restart almost from scratch again from that period.  The prospect of Ireland joining the European Common Market and the discussions and debates which took place on that possibility during the 1960s marked the beginning of a greater awareness within the Department of Industry and Commerce of the important part which Irish industry must play.  In fact, the present Taoiseach, when Minister for Industry and Commerce, was foremost in encouraging overall greater efficiency through the CIO and gave solid support to the Buy Irish campaigns which were then run on very limited budgets, when I was president of the old NAIDA during the 1964-65 period.  His appeal for practical patriotism evoked satisfactory responses in the short-term.</P>
    <P>I hope we shall receive and review some statistical facts on the success or otherwise of the current &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo; campaign in the forthcoming Green Paper.  However, despite the growing support from various Ministers for Industry and Commerce, my assessment of the past situation was confirmed recently in a paper read at the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society which indicated that successive Government attempts at planning since 1958 has been doomed to failure, both due to lack of political commitment and a lack of necessary policies.</P>
    <P>Mr. Katsiauoni's paper goes into detail on the targets set in various plans which were not adequately worked out, that as a result of the lack of clarity, the provision of information by which firms like ours could make long-term plans was negated and that during that period there were many casualities in the industrial sector because most targets <Col N="322" /> were established by purely mechanical estimate to fit in with the overall target. Contrary to its canvassed status as the main agent of economic growth, the industrial sector tended to be relegated to a subsidiary position with little attention paid as to how it was to be developed.</P>
    <P>Another major setback for private enterprise took place in the supplementary budget of 1970 when the Government decided to raise company tax from 50 per cent to 58 per cent, a decision which included a retrospective element of corporation profits tax which for many firms meant an effective tax levy in 1971 of over 70 per cent.  This put a severe strain on those who were involved in capital investment and once again resulted in Irish companies having less funds available to plough back for their re-equipment programmes at a time when dangerous inflationary policies and pressures and large increases in costs were eroding profit margins and firms were feeling the effects of the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Agreement as imports from Britain increased rapidly.</P>
    <P>Subsequently many of our food industries were hit by the flour crisis.  The Russian great grain robbery in 1973, which took its toll before the oil crisis, caused a world-wide recession and we are all familiar with the dramatic effects on both public and private enterprise since that period.  Although once again Industry and Commerce lent a sympathetic ear, the lack of any national planning during those years, for whatever reason, kept private enterprise in a perilous position.  The two periods of Coalition Government in 1955-57 and 1973-77 have great similarity in that the Fianna Fáil Party, when in Opposition, seemed to have had more time to examine the practical economic factors affecting the nation's growth and more time to plan alternative ways out of our difficulties and out of our recession.  This is a valid reason to be optimistic about the immediate future because it has resulted in the setting up of a separate Department for Economic Planning and Development on a permanent basis so that the exigencies of being in office will not overtake the practical aspects which need ongoing attention.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="323" /> I am more acquainted with the time-consuming commitments of Ministers under our democratic system of parliament since I joined the Seanad.  I am, therefore, confident that with the introduction of planning units into each Government Department charged with the implementation of plans set out in the forthcoming Green and White Papers hopefully over the years the private sector should be able to look forward to a period of stable support and encouragement from all Government Departments undiverted by <i>ad hoc</i> political expediency.</P>
    <P>Now, we have the Minister's word that the White Paper we are discussing today is the start of a new statutorily based planning process in Ireland.  He has promised consultations with social departments and other relevant groups, and I hope that the women of Ireland, represented by Senator Hussey, will be included in these discussions, so that whatever the aspirations of sectional groups there must be greater public understanding of the underlying reasons for Government policy in the context of what the country can afford and the priorities for creating jobs.</P>
    <P>Furthermore, in reviewing the pattern of the past 50 years, I must emphasise that while one cannot expect miracles overnight, the recent change in the political stance is the most encouraging prospect for the private sector which it has ever encountered.  Some of the incentives will not become effective for a period of time, and the effect of the additional public expenditure will also take time to infiltrate the whole economy.  As Irish industry takes up the challenge proferred, Government and Opposition, in fact all Members of the Oireachtas, must understand that its response must be carefully planned, organised and directed to ensure the longer-term benefits to the national economy. Therefore, we need the realistic understanding and support of all sections of the community.  Certainly, private enterprise welcomes the inference last weekend by the leader of Fine Gael, that they would give support to progressive Government policies and will not just <Col N="324" /> oppose them for the sake of political gain.</P>
    <P>In the face of critical attacks on the private sector in the past, the voice of Irish industry has been most tolerant in its assessment of the failures of some State bodies to perform adequately.  The telecommunications and Aer Lingus disputes provide the most recent examples, and one must observe that the frustrated private sector was obliged, as usual, to refrain from too outspoken comment on such disputes at the critical times so that negotiations could proceed in a calm atmosphere.</P>
    <P>Subsequently, there is seldom any statistical assessment of the damage caused by such public sector disputes.  If company chairmen happen to refer to such adverse effects one year later in company reports, such serious set-backs are well forgotten and overtaken by other events.  Journalists and politicians tend to regard such comments in retrospect as lame excuses.</P>
    <P>I have listened in recent months to deserved praise being heaped upon the State enterprises which have had a successful record, when increases in public expenditure are being appropriated.  But let us also remember in the future the number of successes in the private sector, companies like Waterford Glass, Smurfits and Cement Roadstone, which give a great deal of employment, a great deal of added value, and have earned prestige across the world for the image of Ireland.</P>
    <P>Aside from Irish industry, let us not forget the distributive sector, where private enterprises have saved this country from absorption into the British economy.  For instance, the Irish grocery trade is amongst the most progressive sectors of our economy and foremost in co-operating, promoting and selling Irish products.  Therefore, I appeal for a more balanced attitude this year towards what the Minister for Finance has already described as our mixed economy which is neither a private enterprise nor a socialistic State.  The private sector is very conscious that agriculture must always play the major role in our economic affairs.  But a mixed economy <Col N="325" /> such as ours could indeed be the envy of many countries if only our national planning can develop the correct balance between the public, private and farming interests.  Then, in my opinion, we have enormous potential for our future growth, for job creation and social prosperity.</P>
    <P>I intended ending there but I had sympathy for Senator Martin who earlier today highlighted the frustrations of the independent Senators in connection with the Joint Committee on State-sponsored bodies.  I share with him some of the frustration that when a backbencher like myself has the opportunity to speak it is almost always to an empty House obviously because the Press gallery is manned by one person.  Such is politics.  But I consider it a tragedy that the parliamentary procedure gives priority to those who are alert to the media, to their availability, rather than to the seriousness of the public debate.  I have noticed that the Senators who bleat most about the under-utilisation of the Seanad&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Harte) Acting Chairman (Mr. Harte)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Harte)</NameTxt>
      <P>May I just draw the attention of the Senator to the fact that a lot of his remarks are not related to the discussion on the White Paper?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CLambert" hpid="Mr. Lambert Mr. Lambert">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lambert</NameTxt>
      <P>One must admit that I am talking to practically an empty House on the Opposition.  It is a pity that the Senators who bleat about the under-utilisation of the Seanad are not here to hear my remarks.  It is an unhappy situation for the private sector.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ValentineJago" hpid="Mr. Jago Mr. Jago">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jago</NameTxt>
      <P>As has been said already, the White Paper is basically an extension of the Fianna Fáil manifesto.  I cannot go along with the suggestion that this should have been discussed before being published because, when all is said and done, the manifesto was discussed, it was commented upon, it was criticised; this went on for many weeks before the general election and the present Government were returned in no uncertain manner to implement it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Why was this plan produced?  We were going through a period of inflation <Col N="326" /> which was caused mainly by outside elements. Our country, during that time, made no attempt through planning or otherwise to counter that action.  The worker found prices increasing rapidly and his purchasing power dropping equally rapidly through inflation.  It was every man for himself because there was no leadership or guidance available to him.  What he had to do was put in for large wage increases and he had to get them.  He now found that, having got his wage increases, he was taxed more and, with this reduction in his take-home pay, then he put in for more wage increases and so a spiral began.  The employer found himself in a position that he was faced with a trade recession.  He had ever increasing wages, increasing costs generally, and with no plans or forecasts to guide him all he could do was play safe.  He cut back, stopped investment and by so doing created redundancy with added unemployment.  The Government, at that time, faced with more unemployment and higher bills, had to meet this cost by heavy borrowing. There was no census of population, no way of seeing what the extent of the likely unemployment was going to be.  Some people had an idea of how many school-leavers there were going to be in the years ahead &mdash; there were many comments on it &mdash; and the serious situation that was likely to obtain in this country if no action was taken to counter it; it could have meant even revolution.</P>
    <P>I want to stress that this situation is still with us.  It can be very serious if we are not successful in conquering it.  As some Senators may have heard, in Italy they blame the Red Brigade as being caused by a problem similar to this.</P>
    <P>Therefore, in that context this plan was born and obviously its basic aim is to get jobs.  Firstly the trend has been created, where year by year people just put in to get higher wages every time inflation caused prices to increase.  One of the first things to do was to break the spiral.  Therefore, in this plan there were reduction in car tax, rates off private dwellings, £1 off the stamp for people earning under £50 per week, and increased personal allowances in income tax.  All of these concessions were given to prove that the only way to keep up <Col N="327" /> one's standard of living was not necessarily to get an increase in one's basic wage.  In this plan it was recommended that a wage increase of 5 per cent would give a real increase in actual terms to the workers.  It was essential to prove to workers that there are other ways of improving their standard of living and that it was essential to have wage restraints if we were going to create jobs.  As you all know the result was wage restraint but not down to the 5 per cent.  I would have been happier if it was 5 per cent.  Wage restraint must continue for the future because, if we do not get jobs, then what it means is that people who have increased their earnings to improve their individual situations will have to pay for the people who are unemployed, and they will get less money in the end because the money will have to come by way of taxation.</P>
    <P>The aim of this plan was to create jobs.  Therefore the plan was to create jobs quickly in the public sector.  This has already been done to a certain extent and is carrying on.  Then, in the private sector incentives were given to industry to increase their output.  Senators are already aware of those incentives; I will not go through them in detail.  There were also incentives to the farming community to increase their output.  Senators are also aware of those and therefore I will not go into detail.</P>
    <P>What happened?  One of the first difficulties was &mdash; as already referred to here &mdash; the industrial relations situation which this Government, to a certain extent, inherited.  We had Ferenka &mdash; 1,400 extra on the unemployment register.  We have had the telephone strike, an upset in communications.  We have had the Aer Lingus strike, another upset in communications, and we have unofficial strikes everywhere.  In this area there is something wrong.  If this is not corrected no plan to get jobs can be successful.  As Senators are all aware this Government took immediate action.  I understand that the commission which the Minister for Labour has formed is now sitting, and I sincerely hope and trust &mdash; as I imagine does everybody here&mdash;that a solution to this situation will eventually emerge.</P>
    <P>Despite all this what has been the <Col N="328" /> result?  Jobs have been created in the public service.  Jobs have been created in the building trade.  I do not know the up-to-date figures of the jobs creation.  No doubt the Minister when summing up will tell us.  Last week a conservative body like the CII reported a 10 per cent increase in output in the private sector; 5 per cent increase in productivity for 1978 for the 100,000 jobs.  It must be remembered in this case that in the private sector, at the time this plan came into operation, in most cases they were under capacity.  It must be remembered also that in the private sector they have to watch productivity to remain competitive. Therefore one has to wait until the under-capacity is taken up before one can reach the stage where one gets increased jobs.  Therefore the jobs to come in the private sector will come now probably at a greater rate than they have up to now.</P>
    <P>What else have we seen?  The live register is continually mentioned to us as an indication of how jobs are being gained but the live register is not a true indication of what jobs are gained because people who are not registered at all have got jobs and the indications are that there are quite a number.  Despite that, on 12 May the live register number was down 8,000 on the same week of the year before.  Also in April of this year as compared to April last year, our import excess in the balance of payments was down by £12.9 million.  In the four months period to April this year compared with the same period last year our import excess was down £63.8 million. These are figures which show the growth in the country.  It has been mentioned by various economists that our growth must retard next year.  Economists base their forecasts on figures.  But if we base it on human beings, I see a different picture. There is nothing whatever to prevent our farmers continuing to increase their production.  If our farmers increase their production then we must get more jobs, irrespective of what any economist says.  Our meat processing industry, now that some of the difficulties have been removed, can create jobs.  If we honestly deal with all the problems which prevent competitiveness in the private sector, if we can get together and find out what is <Col N="329" /> wrong with our industrial relations position &mdash; is it our personnel officers; is it the trade unions; is it the Labour Court set up, or what is wrong&mdash;get that right and make our private sector competitive, there is nothing to prevent us expanding and creating more jobs; even if we ask the housewife to consider seriously the Buy Irish Campaign.  On the figure for this month if we had a switch of 4½ per cent, we will correct our balance of payments.</P>
    <P>I welcomed this plan when it was produced because during periods without a plan we were like a ship without a rudder or a chart.  We have a plan, we are working to it, we are showing that our economy is better now than it has been for goodness knows when. We have great hope, we have the people to work.  What we have to do is give them the work to do.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>When the economic history of late 20th century Ireland comes to be written this White Paper will be a crucially important source document because of the light it will throw on the bankruptcy of the socio-economic philosophy it enshrines. Long before it is considered by the historians, however, it will constitute damning evidence in the trial of the private enterprise system in Ireland, a trial which has already begun and is being conducted before the jury of the youth of this country.  The White Paper may be considered as the third volume in what to date is an economic trilogy. Volume I was the pre-election manifesto, volume 2, an even livelier work, full of stirring fictions and entitled the Budget 1978, and the most important volume to date now lies before us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I propose to address myself at some length to this debate on the White Paper so that my detailed comments will be recorded in the Official Report of the House.  By way of preface I reiterate what many of my fellow Senators have said in their case, that they are no economists; I am no economist but perhaps this is just as well, because that distinguished body of conventional wisdom has greeted the strategic economic and social choices that face <Col N="330" /> this society with a thunderous silence. Confronted with a demographic explosion that offers us the boundless opportunity of building a vibrant and dynamic nation state, liberated from the national and economic delusions of my own generation and of my own peers, faced with a spectacle of renewed emigration and even of social disintegration, confronted with what is at once a unique peril and a unique opportunity, our economists, by and large, have regrettably opted for micro-economic papers on microscopic subjects and have offered no large vision to our people.  At any rate I have studied this White Paper with a care and attention sharpened by a recognition of my own limitations in what is for me unfamiliar territory.  But I soon found out that it required no particular expertise to penetrate the flimsy patchwork of orthodoxy in pursuit of disaster that goes by the name of the White Paper on National Development.</P>
    <P>The central exercise I carried out is related exclusively to the most important theme of the paper and which I think the Government would admit, namely, the creation of employment.  The exercise I carried out hinges on three fundamental questions: first, how many jobs does this document state the Government will create, given the thousands of school leavers and undergraduates &mdash; some of them now passing through my hands &mdash; who are marching out into &ldquo;their country now&rdquo;, bravely summoned to confidence by the clarion call of the Fianna Fáil manifesto.  Secondly, to whom do the Government give the responsibility of creating these vital jobs?  Thirdly, how well have these trustees discharged their stewardship in the past?</P>
    <P>So, to the first question, the number of jobs.  There was in 1975 a very broad measure of agreement on this.  Professor Brendan Walsh then projected that our society would have to create some 30,000 jobs each year and every year for ten years.  Recently he has revised these massive figures downwards.  It now seems that we need fewer jobs, a mathematical point that must give us pause since the main demographic projections of Professor Walsh on birth, <Col N="331" /> marriage and death have not altered.  On investigation I find that in 1978 Professor Walsh thinks we need fewer jobs because of what he calls a longer retention rate, which is a euphemism to describe parents keeping their children at home longer and subsidising their idleness.  One is not impressed with this kind of sophistry or statistical repositioning of the stark truth of Brendan Walsh's 1975 projections.  Any study of the population and school-leaving trends confirms the 30,000 jobs per annum figure.  Incidentally, Professor Walsh calls in that grim old abductor, emigration, which may once again kidnap the unwanted children of the nation for whom jobs cannot be found.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Harte) Acting Chairman (Mr. Harte)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Harte)</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I please ask the Senator not to attack somebody who cannot defend himself here?  It is not really relevant to the debate, as I see it anyway, so perhaps the Senator could stick to the motion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>With respect, we are discussing the economy as a whole. Professor Brendan Walsh has been cited several times by Senators on this debate. I am referring to&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the tone of the remarks the Chair objects to.  It is not the practice to attack somebody outside.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>With respect, I would like to be informed of the difference between a wrong tone and a right tone.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The person to whom the Senator has been referring cannot defend himself here.  All I am asking is that the Senator adhere to the White Paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>With respect, is it not a debate on the economy as a whole?  Why should I be halted when no other Senator was halted?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not halting the Senator on the question of the White Paper but on his remarks in regard to somebody who is not present in the House and is not in a position to defend <Col N="332" /> himself.  If the Senator were attacking another Senator or a Minister, that would be different as the attack could be answered here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>With respect, I am not attacking.  I am commenting on the well publicised statements of one of our leading economists in a debate on the economy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>We have to keep in our minds what is before the House. What is before the House is the Government's White Paper on National Development, 1977-1980.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>With respect, Senator Lambert has just finished a long review of the background to the handicaps of the private sector over the last 50 years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I also found it necessary to take Senator Lambert to task on a remark.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>That was clearly an irrelevance at the end of his contribution. However, I do not want to argue with the Chair.  I am mystified by its comments.</P>
      <P>Deputy Máire Geoghegan-Quinn, the Minister of State at the Department of Industry, Commerce and Energy, who is not present but who is well able to defend herself, hints in an <i>Irish Times</i> report of 6 April 1978 that our people should look forward to emigrating to Western Europe.  She and the Government must be left in no doubt that they are not going to get off the hook in that way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Let us suppose that we need, not 30,000 new jobs per annum but something less than that figure.  What has this White Paper to say?  Its simple message boils down to three figures.  In a jargon language, which prefers negative statements to positive assertions, we are told that unemployment will be reduced by 20,000 in 1978, by 25,000 in 1979 and by 30,000 in 1980.  Or, putting it positively, the Government will have created 75,000 jobs by the end of 1980.  In regard to the present year do Senators or anyone <Col N="333" /> know whether 20,000 new jobs will have been created by the time this lovely summer fades through autumn into a winter of discontent?  The Government knowing that the live register will tell the tale now informs us that these 20,000 new jobs will not be reflected on the live register.</P>
    <P>This sleight of hand erodes a vital cornerstone of faith in the White Paper. Whether the first year's target is reached will be like the existence of God &mdash; beyond literal proof.  We are told then not to look to the live register &mdash; Senator Jago has told us this also &mdash; but rather to trust the Government and to sense the burgeoning feeling of confidence in the economy.  Indeed if business optimism, that intangible sex appeal of the money market, is our only guide then the people who inhabit the house the bankers built can be happy with their Government.  Perhaps these are the select people Senator Brennan had in mind when he told us last week to ask the man in the street &mdash; perhaps it was the man in Grafton Street &mdash; for his views on the economy.  We may or may not have 20,000 new jobs by the end of the year.  It is becoming increasingly impossible to discern what is the criterion by which we will know that the promises in the manifesto and in the White Paper have been fulfilled.  If we are not to look to the live register what are the definite criteria by which we will know whether Fianna Fáil have delivered or not?</P>
    <P>Well, we may or we may not have 20,000 jobs by the end of the year but we certainly have a jump in bank profits &mdash; as I pointed out here two weeks ago in the debate on youth unemployment. The Bank of Ireland profit is up 26 per cent and the AIB an incredible 44.9 per cent up on last year.  Meanwhile the beef ranchers have expanded their income by 34 per cent while the budget, in an extra burst of generousity to this hard-pressed group, brought in a number of extra subsidies and remissions of taxation under the pretext of giving them the same crack of the whip as the industrial worker.  However, while the industrial workers have sent up production by 14 per cent the beef barons have settled for a derisory 3 per cent increase in output. <Col N="334" /> These are good times indeed for the bankers, the beef barons and the lucky people whose business and taxation is their own business, not accountable to the nation.  It certainly seems to be &ldquo;their country now.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Having considered my first question on the number of jobs to be created, we move on to my second question: to whom has the Government entrusted the awesome responsibility of delivering 75,000 new jobs in the next three years? Why, to none other than the bankers, the beef barons and the bright boys. With what surging confidence can the teachers and youth leaders across the land face their classrooms and tell the children of the nation who it is that will bring them to the promised land?  Who but these Moses of finance, these Goliaths of cattle production, these Solomons of double-entry bookkeeping and scandalous land speculations at the public expense; in short these.  Old Testament figures of the Irish private sector, with their fundamentalist beliefs in hard work for everybody else, perpetual poverty for a fifth of the population and perpetual frugality for the working class. How they must have applauded the conservative utterances here last week of that austere grey eminence of the public purse Senator Whitaker.  Observe, by the way, that contrary to the impression given by the media, Senator Whitaker does identify himself with the Government's socio-economic philosophy.  He may have some differences with them on fiscal policy or on bookkeeping, but even these differences are disappearing according as Government Ministers come to emphasise the need for cuts in present public expenditure and in future borrowing. The rapprochement in the lovers' tiff between the Senator and the Government was evident here last week&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>We have reached the agreed time for adjournment.  Would the Senator like to move the adjournment of the debate?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it be possible for me to finish a section of my speech?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The order was <Col N="335" /> agreed today that the House would adjourn&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>At what time then is it likely that the debate on the White Paper will be resumed next week?  This will be particularly important for me since I will have to resume the debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>There are only two items, as far as I know, likely to be on the Order Paper next Wednesday.  One is <Col N="336" /> the White Paper and the other is the Agricultural Rates Bill.  I cannot say which will be taken first.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee Stage of the Landlord and Tenant Bill (No. 2) was fixed already this week for next&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>For Thursday.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.35 p.m. until 2.30 p.m.  Wednesday, 31 May 1978.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>